<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/</course_url>
    <course_title>Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>Literature </list>
      <list>History </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Conrad. The Secret Agent.</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_conrad/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>himself seem less culpable; Ossipon, chasing girls for their money etc)  
 
stevies extreme 
   selflessness appears half as a beacon to which to aspire, and half like a mental 
   deficiency. 
 
 
 
question What is the flaw in Winnie Verloc's character? 
  
Like a character 
   in a Greek drama, Winnie is a tragic figure  
not because she has committed a crime but 
      because of an inherent flaw:  
 
her deep and "philosophical reserve"  
that allows her to distance herself  
from the appalling events around her.   
In this sense she is the reader's 
   representative in the novel,  
ignoring the truth  
until she becomes entangled in the problem itself by not reacting.
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MK sends letter requesting retribution (horses fa ttene d, money to Herse for injury and property 
loss, etc) He receives nothing and bands a group with the help of Herse and attacks the castle.  
The band follows the escaped Tronka to a c onvent (run by his relative) and continued to 
Wittenberg where he posts a manifesto detailing the wrongs against him. 
 
In response, Martin Luther writes a public letter to MK requesting him to cease actions against peopl
e and the state. MK travels to Leipzig and read s Luthers placard and decides to visit him. 
They discuss the matter and Luther offers a peaceable solution: wouldnt it be better for MK to fatten the horses himself? 
 
Junker is released from prison. Knacker of Dr es
 den enters to decide MKs fate. MK agrees. 
Chancellor wants payoff. Public opin ion changes after the incident. 
 
MK and Negalschmidt are enemies. MK visits home a nd remains watched under house arrest. 
Negalschmidt writes and offers to liberate MK if MK agrees to re-join the band. The letter is 
intercepted and brought to Baron von Wenk, the Elector and President. They pass letter back to 
MK. He agrees to the proposal (for freedom) and is arrested. He confesses and is sentenced to 
the gallows. 
 
MK is taken to Berlin. Runs into Chancellor and El e ctor. Elector requests vial on MKs neck. MK 
refuses because he was treated badly in Dresden. The Elector asks council to pardon MK to no 
avail.  
 
 
Elector finds a woman to impersonate the gypsy. She is a real gy psy (MKs dead wife.) MK is 
offered Communion by Luther. The state grant s MKs wishes and his horses are fattened and 
restored. On the gallows, MK eats the gypsys pr ophecy. The Elector collapses and MK is killed. 
 
  
 
question how did Mr. Verloc and Winnie meet? 
 
Mr Verloc was a lodger in the house kept by Winnie's mot
 her, who now lives with them above the 
shop. She is dependent upon her daughter.  
 
Winnie also looks after her brother Stev ie who is blond, "delicate" and 
   unworldly.  
 
question which incident from the past illustrates how Stevies character? 
 
when working in an office two other boys persuaded him to set off 
   "fierce rockets" in the corridor by te lling him that the compa ny was unjust and oppressive. 
 
stevie cannot be trusted to work, and 
   how he can be exploited: 
 
pre-shadows the role Stevie plays in the novel.. 
 
 
 
question why does the professor carry the bomb? 
 
so that he can commit a kamikaze explosion at any moment.  
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Conrad, The Secret Agent  (1907)  
 
18571924, English novelist, b. Russia (now Ukraine),  
originally named Jsef Teodor Konrad Walecz Korzeniowski.  
 
Born of Polish parents, he is considered one of  the greatest noveli sts and prose stylists in 
English literature.  
 
Heart of Darkness (1902) 
 
distinctive, opulent prose style 
 
Conrads novels combine realism and high drama.  
 
Their settings include nautical backgrounds as well as high society, and international politics.  
 
Conrad was a skilled creator of atmosphere an
 d character; the impact of various 
situations was augmented by his use of sym bolism. He portrayed acutely the conflict 
between non-west ern cultures and mode rn civilization.  
 
His characters exhibit the possibilities for is ol ation and moral deterioration in modern life. 
  
The Secret Agent
 was inspired by an anarchist attempt made on the Greenwich Observatory in 
1894.  
 
The 'Author's Note' states "This bo ok i s that story, reduced to 
   manageable proportions, its whole course suggested and centred around the absurd 
   cruelty of the Greenwich Park explosion."  
 
Conrad, lived in London at that time,  
he would have read the newspaper accounts of the incident,  
which were brief and at first mysterious,  
like the articles in the novel.   
However they did establish that t he victim was M
 artin Bourdin,  
a man linked to anarchism,  
 
he was badly mutilated, and had probably stumbled as he carried a bomb.  
 It later emerged that Bourdin was brother- in-law to a known anarchist, Samuels.  
 
These details provided the skeleton for Conrad's tale. 
 
Plot synopsis
 
 
MK attempts to cross out of Brandenburg to sell his h orses. He is stopped at the gate near 
Tronka castle and is asked to produce a pass. He holds no pass and in lieu he offers his two 
black horses. He rides off to Dresden to settle the matter and leaves Herse (servant) to keep the 
horses in his stead. 
 
MK begins lawsuit. Suit is thrown out b/c Tronka is related to the Elector. Another suit is filed and 
that is shelve
d (more nepotism.) MK decides to se ll his house. Lisbeth (wife) offers to settle the 
court matter herself b/c she had a relationship with official before her marriage to MK. She returns 
(in rough shape) and quickly dies.) 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Sir Ethelred sheds more light on the incident, stating that the bomber "has destroyed 
   himself by accident", and muses on whether the man was a deaf mute.  
 
 
 
Structure  
 
   Conrad's novel is intricately con structed  
to affect the reader:  
 
question does he give us all the info we need?  
it leaps in time and setting and drops out bits of information  
so as to manipulate a reader's understanding.   
These features lead to  a dense, obtuse novel  
in which it is hard to gain an overview,  
and thus the themes of lack of social awareness  
and insufficient communication ...  
("he [Verloc] did not really know what to say to Stevie" etc.) ... 
are reflected in the book's form. 
 the impression of 'compartments' of partial understanding  
is promulgated: 
     via the structure,  
we are aware of insufficient underst an
 ding of each secluded character 
     because we ourselves are only privy to one dimension. 
 
 
question    What is the importance  of Stevie in The Secret Agent?  
    Winnie's "delicate brother", blond and "in a fra il way
 , good looking, too, except for the vacant 
   droop of his lower lip" is inveigled into anarchistic activities and becomes a "heap of rags, 
   scorched and bloodstained". The reader's reco g nition of his death unf olds over the course 
   several chapters, and consequences of it continue until the suicide of Winnie, after which 
   his sacrifice is made even more poignant  by being forgotten a nd in vain, an "unpenetrable 
   mystery". The fate of Stevie is central to t he plot of the novel: he i s a manipulated altruist, an 
   unwilling catalyst, and a victim of hypocrisy.   
The sacrifice of Stevie symbolizes the  d
 estruction of our liking for humanity.  
 
   Stevie is a figure that contributes to the novel's satire of anarchism ,  
in that he displays 
     more revolutionary altruism than any of the professionals,  
yet has no capability as a terrorist.   
 question how to compare stevie to the other characters? 
 
hes selfless.  how are the others self
 -involved? 
 Stevie's "innocent but pitiless rage" is thus a danger to himself, and 
   by contrast to the peripheral characters' self-inte
 restedness (the Professor, making bombs 
   to boost his sense of power; the Assist ant Co mmissioner, backstabbing Heat to make 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>This gives the 
   Professor a sense of power, especially since he feels it means he could outwit the police 
   since if they tried to arrest him he c oul d detonate the bomb thus killing himself and anyone 
   close by him.  
 
 
 
Atmosphere and setting: location, light, style  
 
   The novel is very clearly set in London (t he city Con rad depicted as the actual Heart of 
   Darkness in the last lines of that novel).  
 
Conrad succinctly places the action in  a  restrictive and unenlightened city: 
 
   "The shop was small, and so was the house. It was one of those grimy brick houses which 
   existed in large quantities before t he e ra of reconstruction dawned upon London." 
 
Conrad depicts a dingy, vast and uniform capital.  
 
Brett Street: impersonality of the metropolis 
 
Conrad's creation of atmosphere is very economical; accuracy and lack of extravagance. 
 
Light is used throughout 
   as a form of 'pathetic fallacy' since it regul arly mat ches the feelings  of the protagonists. 
 
question find some passages that describe light and atmosphere 
  
London, the centre of "the Empire on which the sun never sets" is ironically dark and    shadowy.  
 
The gloom gives a sense of danger, of obscu
 rity, of confusion and amorality . 
 
 
question what clues suggest it was stevie? 
 
Heats visit to the hospital to 
   view the remains of the victim of the bomb is d escribed: the body he inspects is "a heap of 
   rags, scorched and bloodstained, half co n cealing what might have been an accumulation 
   of raw material for a cannibal feast".   
 
question: how does this relate to heart of darkness
? 
 
the Chief Inspector is told that the man 
   seen heading towards the scene of the expl osi on just before the bomb went off was "a 
   fair-haired fellow". This is the first of four majo r clues in this chapter that point to the idea 
   that it was not Verloc who died. 
 
the Chief Inspector 
   salvages from the remains a small, triangular label attached to a velvet collar, which later 
   turns out to be a sure sign of the identity of the corpse.  
 
 
question was it a suicide bombing? 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Said. &#8220;The Essential Terrorist.&#8221;
Lentricchia and McAuliffe.&#8220;Groundzeroland.&#8221;
Scanlan. Plotting Terror. Introduction.&#160;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_said/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>1950s one could see state socialism as state tm 
 
1968 specters of intl tm resurface with student revolutions 
 
 
convergence of: aeroterrorism 
   leisure flight 
   media 
 first global terrorist broadcast is when?  1972 olympics 
 
by mid-70s, RAF playing right to tv 
 
 
at the end of Scanlans intro, she consid ers 
 radical chic...  what is that?  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lentricchia and McAuliffe, Crimes of Art and Terror  
 
question: do lentricchia and mcauliffe perceive a  curious knot bw artists and terrorists? 
 
2/ they call it an incestuous relationship 
5/* epigram:  from Mao II
 
question: so what shared desire do artists and terrorists have, accd to l? 
 
2/ to transgress the given order 
 
8/* jump the gap between word and thing 
 defeat the representationa l characte r of literature 
 question: they mention one artwork-- performan ce
  art-- that enacts this jumping the  
   gap.  what is it? 
 
chris burden, shoot  (1971)  
 
question: how is this unmediated cultural/historical moment different to the  
   aesthetic/poetic object of aristotles imagination? 
 
 
now lets look at a passage on p. 10 more material here about Stockhausen, about shared 
desi
re of artists and terrorists 
 
10/* read citation 
 
 
question: how far back can we trace this transgressive desire? 
 
3/ from 11 sept all the way back to romanticism 
 
question: L + M maintain that most americans didnt grieve for victims of 11 sept.   
   do you agree? 
 
L + M see 9.11 as a rupture, a defamilia rization-- not as an em otional event 
 
L + M take an unsentimental approach to art 
 
**Essentially, L + M see an equivalence betwe en terror and performance art. 
 
14/ Atta = author 
 pit of WTC marks the original art of the suicide pilots 
 
 I have a problem with this 
 
Im also wondering about an assertion at the end of this chapter: 
 they say curators and collectors choose bits of refuse and turn them 
  into artifacts. 
 
Said, The Essential Terrorist  
 
question: who was said?  whats his relationship to chomsky? 
 
what is the political context to which he refers? 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>153/* [top two graphs] 
 establishment of israel; disenfranchisement of palestinians 
 
question: how does this relate to european history? 
 
explain orientalism :  european subject established in opposition to oriental other 
   * * * heart of darkness
 question: how does this kind of binary opposition  
   play itself out in saids analysis of terrorism? 
 
152/* read bottom paragraph 
 
 
 
Scanlan, Plotting Terror  
 seeks affinities bw literary and terrorist plots 
 
identifies remnants of a romantic belief in the power of 
 the marginalized 
  to transform history 
 
sees tm as both:  actual killing 
    and a fictional construct 
 
5/* defines tm 
 a symbolic act designed to influence political behavior  
  by extranormal means, entailing the use or threat of violence 
 
question: whats the diff bw calling someone a terrorist 
   and calling them a revolutionary? 
 
Scanlans general inquiry:  the writers ability to understand 
      and influence politics 
 
     rel. bw language and violence 
 
     the nature of power 
           the impetus to resist 
 
question: who are the three cla ssi
 c authors she begins with? 
 
  dostoevsky, james, conrad 
 
11/ overview of 20th c. terrorism in Eu rope  question:  what are flashpoints? 
 1933 tm considered outmoded as a revolutionary method 
 
 political activists thought  that sustai
 ned strikes  
  were more effective than sporadic violence  
1945 postwar regimes were democratic enough that social change 
  could be effected thru legitimate means 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>DeLillo. Mao II.</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_delillo/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>language. I've always seen myself in sentences. I begin to recognize myself, word by 
word, as I work through a sentence. The language of my books has shaped me as a 
man. There's a moral force in a sentence when it comes out right. It speaks the writer's 
will to live.  
 question:  how is bill like/unlike a terroris t?  charlie and george both see alignment: 
 
 
97/ [Charlie]: "You have a twisted sense of the writer's place in society. You think the writer 
belon 
gs at the far margins, doing dangerous things. 
 
130/ [George Haddad:] "And isn't it the novelis t, Bill, above all people, above all writers, who 
understands this rage, who knows in his soul what the terrorist thinks and feels? Through history it's the novelist who has felt affinity  for the violent man who lives in the dark. 
Where are your sympathies? With the colonial police, the occupier, the rich landlord, the corrupt government, the militaristic st ate? Or with the terrorist?"  
 on a related note, george asks: 
 
157/ [Haddad:] "Is history possible? Is anyone serious? Who do we take seriously? Only the 
lethal believer, the person 
who kills and dies for faith. Ever ything else is absorbed. The 
artist is absorbed, the madman in the street is absorbed and processed and incorporated. Give him a dollar, put him in a TV commer cial. Only the terrorist stands outside. The 
culture hasn't figured out how to assimilate him."  
 question:  does bill think he s aligned 
 with terrorist?   no. 
 
bill sees himself at odds with terrorists 
 
156-57/ [Bill:] "For some time now I've had the fee ling that no velists and terrorists are playing a 
zero-sum game."  
"Interesting. How so?"  
"What terrorists gain, novelists los e. The degree to which they influence mass 
consciousness is the extent of our declin e as shapers of sensibility and thought. The 
danger they represent equals our own failure to be dangerous."  
"And the more clearly we see terror, t he less impact we feel from art."  
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>individual vs. crowd (history vs. media)  
 
link to bill:  masterpieces of art about death drive 
 
34/ They show the fence from a distance , b odies piling up behind it, smothered, 
sometimes only fingers moving, and it is like a fresco in an old dark church, a 
crowded twisted vision of a rush to death as only a master of the age could paint 
it.  
 
Question:  how do artists and terroris ts  relate (sim/diff) to history? 
 
41/ [Bill]: "There's a curious knot that binds novelists and terrorists . In the West we 
become famous effigies as our books lo se the power to shape and influence.... 
Years ago I used to think it was possible fo r a novelist to alter the inner life of the 
culture. Now bomb-makers and gunmen have taken that territory. They make 
raids on human consciousness. What wr iters used to do before we were all 
incorporated." 
 
Question:  do we need/want art anymore? 
 
72/ [Scott]: "The novel used to feed our search  for meani ng. Quoting Bill. It was the 
great secular transcendence. The Latin mass of language, character, occasional 
new truth. But our desperation has led us toward something larger and darker. 
So we turn to the news, which provides  an unremitting mood of catastrophe. This 
is where we find emotional experience not available elsewhere. We don't need the novel. Quoting Bill. We don't even ne ed catastrophes, necessarily. We only 
need the reports and predictions and warnings."  
 
What does Abu Rashid say about the rel. of terror to history at the 
 end of the novel? 
 235/ [Abu Rashid's unnamed interpreter:] "Terror makes the new future possible. All 
men one m 
an. Men live in history as never before. He is saying we make and 
change history minute by minute. History is not the book or the human memory. 
We do history in the morning and change it after lunch."  
 
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Don DeLillo, Mao II (1991 ) 
 
what photos mark off the different sections? 
 --football riot 
 --khomeini demo 
 
historical moment of rushdie affair, khomeinis funeral, islamic fundamentalism, tiananmen 
 
what is plot? 
 
What, for you, are key passages in first half? 
 
question:  who are the main characters?  
 --bill, brita, karen, scott, charlie, j-c julien, george haddad, abu rashid 
 
bill:  what do we know about him as a writer?  
 
20/ modern classic author 
 
28/ writing is physical, material, human 
 
 [Bill Gray looking at] ...what he'd written during the day, the scant drip, the ooze of 
spe
ckled matter, the blood sneeze, the daily pale secretion, the bits of human tissue 
sticking to the page. 
 
45-46/  "When I was a kid I used to announce ballgames  to myself. I sat in a room and made up 
the games and described the play-by-play. [] And I've been trying to write toward that 
kind of innocence ever since. The pure gam e of making up. You sit there suspended in a 
perfect clarity of invention. There's no separation between you an d the players and the 
room and the field. Everything is seamless and transparent. And it's completely 
spontaneous. It's the lost game of self, without doubt or fear."  
 48/ bills identity is constituted through literature: 
 
[Bill]: "Every sentence has a truth waiting at the end of it and the writer learns to know it whe
n he finally gets there. On one level this truth is the swing of the sentence, the beat 
and poise, but down deeper it's the integrity of the writer as he matches with the 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>question: why the subplot of the mass wedding? 
 
 
 
How is terror mentioned in story?  
 
27/ [Brita]: "I feel as if I'm being taken to see s ome terrorist chief at hi s secret retreat in the 
mountains." 
 
40-41/ [Brita on the traveling life]: "...there is no moment on certain days when I'm not thinking 
terror."  
 
140/ [Scott remem bers Bill saying:] "Stories have no point if they don't absorb our terror."  
  
 
how is photography thematized?
 
 
question:  what is delillos point about photography? 
 
 --warhols mao II  20-21/ ptg indifferent to viewer      62/ scott gives karen reproduction 
 
 140/ [Scott realizes that Bill had his picture taken in order to disappear more 
compl
etely and irrevocably.]  
 
 
 
 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_introduction/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>[introduction] 
 
this is a course about history (terro r) and culture (art/lit) 
 --how do they intersect? 
 
lets consider a statement made by avant-garde composer karlheinz stockhausen on 16 sept 
2001 --WTC attack was greatest work of art t hat is po
 ssible in the whole cosmos. 
--drew parallels with his work as a composer:    
you have ppl so concentrated on one performance, and then 5000 ppl are disp
atched into eternity, in a single moment I couldnt do that.  in comparison 
with that, were nothing as composers.  
--accd to stockhausen, a similar impulse  
exists behind the act of terror and the work of art:  
 
 what happned spiritually [on 9.11], this jump out of secu
 rity, out of the self-
evident this sometimes also happens in art or it is worthless. 
 
lets explore the interconnection bw art and terrorism. 
 
Romantics tended to associate art and violence. 
Romanticism .  [what is?  when?] 
 reaction to an emergent industrial society 
 romantics associated art with the idea of 
  a terrifying awakening that would undo the wests 
   ec. and pol. order 
 
writers and artists seek to shoc k, to tran sgress the everyday. 
 
wordsworth yearned for extraordinary incident to prod us out of savage torpor. 
 
The anarchist and terrorist mvts that 
  developed during the same period 
    were similiarly motivated. 
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>These mvts countered industrial society 
 ... wanted to induce shock to bring about 
  new state of affairs  
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Kleist. Michael Kohlhaas.</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_kleist/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Heinrich von Kleist (1777-1811)  
 
german dramatic poet 
 Kleist served (179299) in the Prussian army and led an unhappy life that 
ended in suicide.  
 
Among his passionate tragedies is Penthesilea (1808), The Prince of Homburg, 
(1821, tr. 1956), a historical tragedy.  
 
Kleist's terse, dynamic style and his sense of co
 nflict : between reason and feeling, divine law 
and human law : are also evident in his novellas.  
 
Best known of these is Michael Kohlhaas (1808-10, tr. 1967). 
 
 
 
Enlightenment and Reformation  
 
both pretty revolutionary, yet neither kant nor  luther e ndorsed public resistance to authority 
 
 luther:  95 theses did, however, help ignit the peasant war of 1524 
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Wittkowski. &#8220;Is Kleist&#8217;s Michael Kohlhaas a Terrorist?&#8221;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_wittkowiski/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>question: Is Michael Kohlhaas a terrorist? 
 
Wolfgang Wittkowski says this: 
 
471/ mk commits acts of terrorism 
  but he willingly accepts decapitation  
    in the enlightened Rechtsstaat  of brandenburg 
 
 but of course, there are other elements of t he story that interrupt this legal disquisi tion 
 
 what are they? mysticism 
 
 
This novel is a study of the use and abuse of the law 
 how the law is used to political advantage 
 
question lets reconstruct the plot  
 
 
question how is mk described? 
 
  opening graph:  both honorable and terrible 
 
question whats romantic about him? 
    
   outraged, tortured, half-mad in other words, close to god 
 question how is martin luther described? 
 
  hes a referee 
 
question how does mls regard for mk change? 
 
   first ml leads public defamation of rebel 
    then, after their meeting he grants mk the 
     holy communion 
      that he had once denied him 
 
 
while alive, lisbeth wanted MK  to forgive; he res
 ists. 
 
as gypsy, she gives him a weapon to save his life and finish his destroyer 
 -- but he can choose this freely 
 
MK becomes deadly avenger of justice violated</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Fo. The Accidental Death of an Anarchist.
Wieviorka. &#8220;The Italian Phenomenon of Leftist Extremist Terrorism.&#8221;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_fo/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>censorship. 
  
  A group of fascists kidnaps, tortures and rapes 
                           Franca Rame. Through this beastly act, they seek 
                           to punish Franca and Dario for their political 
                           activism, in particular Franca's work in the 
                           prisons since 1970. Outcries of indignation and 
                           support throughout Italy. 
 
 
1977-78 In November opens at a 
                           production of "Female parts", a piece mixing the 
                           grotesque, comic and dramatic to illustrate the 
                           situation of women today. Alone on the stage is 
                           Franca Rame, who for the first time puts her 
                           name besides Fo's on the author by-line. The 
                           performance is staged more than 3000 times. 
 
         1979 Fo writes "La tragedia di Aldo Moro", on the 
                           kidnapping and assassination of the Italian 
                           Christian Democratic Party leader at the hands of 
                           the Red Brigades. The play, which has never 
                           been performed, is built on Sophocles' 
                           Philoctetes. 
 
questions 
 
what do you make of the prosthetic limbs? 
 
57/ is the bomb real or a copy?  what difference doe s it make? 
 
67/ why mention watergate? 
 
71/ maniac calls police children of hitler.  RAF also called same. 
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>three fascists were convicted of the Milan bombings.  
One of them, Giannettini turned out to be a paid informer for the Italian police. 
 
Dario Fo, working in Milan with the Capannone of Via Colletta,  
 wrote the play in 1970 and it toured Italy playing to 
  audiences totaling more than a million.  
 
It caused a sensation itself, creating a storm of controversy in the press, 
 bomb threats to the theatres, etc.  
 
It has subsequently been translated into a number of languages and has been 
produced throughout Europe and in the United States. 
 
The play, while dealing with weighty political issues,  
 is nevertheless an extremely funny one rooted in Italian 
  traditions of farce and of commedia del'arte.  
 
Its probing of issues of fascism, totalitari anism and the threats of a 
 police state transcend the par ticula rs of the events  
  which inspired it.  
 
Fo has penetrating insights into the nature of powe r in contem porary society and in this play 
 he exposes some of its contradictions.  
 
Key dates in Fos career: 
 
1970-71 La Comune produces a play about the Italian and Palestinian 
                           resistance. 
 
                        Following the terrorist attack on the Banca 
                           Nazio nale dell'Agricoltura in Milan, Dario writes 
                           and produces "Accidental Death of an Anarchist", about                            the strage di Stato [a massacre thought to be 
                           organized by organs of the state]. 
 
1973-74 The theatre collective is subjected to various acts 
                           of repression by the police as well as to efforts at 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Dario Fo, The Accidental Death of an Anarchist
 
1997 Nobel Laureate in Literature  
 
Accidental Death of an Anarchist 
was a reaction to the arrest of anarchist railway man Giuseppi Pinelli.  
 
On December 12, 1969 a bomb went off in the Agricultural Bank in Milan  
 killing 17 people and wounding 100.  
 
Immediately after the bombing fascists of the Italian Social Movement (MSI)  
 distributed leaflets denouncing the 'red terror'  
  and police in Milan went into action,  
   sweeping up a number of socialist, communist and anarchist activists.  
 
One of these was Pinelli,  
 well known as a pacifist opposed to individual acts of violence.  
 
After four days of interrogation in police headquarters  
 Pinelli 'fell' out of a fourth floor and died.  
 
Police claimed that the death was an 'accident'.  
These events sent a shock wave throughout Italy. There were demonstrations, articles in the 
 
press, inquires, etc.  
 In 1971, the policemen in charge of the investigation,  
 Calabresi, was charged with manslaughter.  
 
Calabresi, in turn, launched a lawsuit against Lotta Continua,  
 the newspaper that had exposed many 
 of the inconstancies 
  in the police version of events.   
These came to an end in May on 1972 when Calabresi was assassinated in front 
 of his house by 'unknown assailants.'  
 
Ten years later in Catanzaro,  
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>D&#252;rrenmatt. The Assignment.
Crockett. Understanding Friedrich D&#252;rrenmatt: The Assignment.</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_durrenmatt/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The Assignment  disrupts conventions of terrorist lit 
 
most of the books weve read follow 19th-c. realism 
 --govt officials, press, and terrorists all collaborate to construct terrorism accd to popular 
fiction 
 --terrorist is portrayed as the other, the outsider 
 
how do we see this in the good terrorist ? 
 --mad bombers, motivated by traumatic childhoods and personal failures  
traditionally, there is little attempt to convey the details of the histo
 rical causes the motivate 
militancy 
 
FD wants to show inadequacy of realism 
 --he also suggests that terrorists are hal f-creation s of the unstable state (taussig) 
  --they are represented in a way that legitimates the states own violence 
 
Terror and Taboo  (Zulaika and Douglass) 
 terrorism denotes the terrorism discourse 
 that is created and sustained by wester n govts, the media, and te
 rrorist experts 
 
this discourse pays enormous attention to bombings by revolutionary groups 
 while slighting the much larger incidence  
  of domestic violence or urban violence (in US). 
 
disproportionate emphasis on the dangers of tm 
 discourages citizens of the democracies from criticizing 
  their govts stockpiling of nuclear/bio weapons, 
   w h i c h ,  
    the discourse tells us, 
     are to be feared mainly bc 
      the terrorists might get hold of them! 
 
FD wants to expose the myths of tm, wants to sh ow the complex reality that underlies 
 the familiar stories. 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>f. deciphers passage, then starts to identify with srensen 
 
77/ f is helpless as a spider 
 she comes to represent a certain kind of art-- 
  documentary realism 
   -- but the premises of rm begin to explode for her 
    the day she films tinas burial 
 50/ f is helplessly drawn to tinas coat 
 
when tina writes in her journal I am being watched, FD (and the character D) 
 articulate the relation of observation to identity 
 
what was fs orignal goal as a documentarist: 
 f. wanted to create a total portrait of our planet (5) 
 
but fs faith in representation is shak en b y her reading of tinas journal. 
 all the detail crushes out individuality by its ruthless observation (11) 
 
this terroristic ruthless observation ends by dest roying the identity it seeks to establish. 
 question: FD sees a danger in realistic art and in the commonsense, consensus notion of reality.  why? 
 
35/ one example of this film crew and police are aligned with each other. 
 both are organs of surveillance 
 
FD, better than a political analyst, 
 shows the emotional and intellectual costs of 20th c. life 
  when even tm cant be counted on to correspond 
   to our conceptions of it. 
 
Otto v Lamberts insight that Auschwitz was not  the work of terrorst but of sta
 te employees 
(58) is well supported in this novel. 
 
Terrorists serve the need to believe that 
 there are centers of resistance against a well-established order 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>german version has second subtitle:  novelle in 24 stzen (philosophical propositions, Iliad ) 
 subversive suggestion:  the classical (western) literature is
  terroristic. 
 question lets read the epigraph 
 
this evokes the radical insecurity in our world 
 -- we move into a future at once unknowable and deeply determined 
 --human being reduced to a spider (short-lived pest) 
 
question what kind of god can we have now? 
 
19-20/ read passage (also part of 21) 
 
 
Soren Kierkegaard (1813-55)  
 
reacts to Hegel, precursor to existentialists 
belief in the necessity for each individual of makin
 g a fully conscious, responsible choice 
among the alternatives that life offers 
 
central question:  how do I relate to God as an existing subject? 
 
The starting point of Fear and Trembling  is the story of Abraham and Isaac.  
 
Abraham prepared to sacrifice Isaac in obedience to a higher duty 
 --this contravenes t he laws of ethics.  
 
Kierkegaard asks:  can we imagine a situation  
 in which ethics can be suspended by a higher authorityi.e., by God 
  when God himself must be 
   considered the essence of everything ethical?  
 
This problem 
 which Kierkegaard calls the teleological su spension of the ethical 
  led him to the conclusion that faith is essentially paradoxical. 
 
Like Either/Or , Fear and Trembling  was an attack on the prevailing Hegelian philosophy,  which 
employed grandiose historical perspectives  
  in which the individual was sucked up  
   as tracelessly as a grain of dust.  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Friedrich Drrenmatt, The Assignment  (1986) 
 
swiss dramatist and novelist 
 
begins like thriller:  funeral of euro woman found dead near al-hakim ruin but plot is bizarre-- diverges from traditional form to frus
 trate reader 
who are culprits?  does anyone get justice?  
plot: 
after funeral of tina von lamber t, he
 r husband, a psychiatrist 
 engages the filmmaker F to find murderer 
F goes to unnamed location in N. africa 
 where she interviews officials and films the murder site 
also catches on camera the execution of an innocent man 
 condemned for the crime 
officials (secret service) persuade her to  track down real murderer 
 by impersonating tina.  another woman plays Fs part. 
a danish journalist tips F. off to the notion that tina is still alive 
 -- real victim was another journalist, jytta srensen 
f. gets picked up by vietnam vet who mans an observatory 
  that is intended to surveill count ry s war with neighboring country 
who is veteran?  who is beast?  real murderers of the two danes. 
 
who is D?  based on FD.  hes a logician, has a telescope (15)  (D 
 conjectures that all art is self-portrait (26)) 
 
historical moment of novel:  arms race (MAD), cold war of mid-80s 
 
lecture notes are from margaret scanlan, plotting terror
 shot thru with irony:  military i ndustrial 
 complex creates tautology 
 wars a re faught to fuel industry 
 
multinationals supercede national identity.  it s just co mputers pitted against each other. 
 novel of the posthuman, postnational condition 
  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>how does he do this? 
 
fragmentation of identity 
 thru this fragmentation FD shows a longing for order that 
  asserts itself in  
   --totalitarian politics 
   --fundamentalist religion 
   --documentary realism 
  all these disciplines depend on observation 
 
how to distinguish bw victims and practitioners of terror? 
 
FD doesnt give us conventional story of sinister islamic terrorists. 
 who are the actual killers?  the two americans, polypheme and achilles 
 
FD situates novella with regard to Islami c fundam entalism, but then contravenes our 
expectations: 
 
58/ if anything, otto v. lambert is on side of militants 
 
in this novel, tm is impossible to locate 
 --it is dispersed through state and society  
again, how to distinguish bw victims and practitioners of terror? 
 
nothing is what it seems 
 --srensen, not tina, is the first victim 
 --tina returns from dead (73) 
 --hard to decide whether brain-damaged vet is victim or terrorizer 
 --few names of ppl or places 
 --reader cant master the story 
 
question what do you think the subtitle means? 
 
we desire discipline and control, we want to be observed. 
 
consider this passage (89)  freedom was t he trap into
  which she was expected to flee 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>yet as the novel demonstrates, 
   the very notion of a center is illusory 
 
The new physical terror of computerized bombing 
 and the old one of rape (Iliad) 
  correspond to a condition in which 
   contemporary human beings live and move, 
    their identity fragmented by 
     new philosophical conceptions of memory 
      and the self 
    as well as by new technologies 
     that violate privacy. 
 
surveillance-- intended to reduce nuclear wa r and tm-- are oppressive but desired. 
 
question what is ironic end of novel? 
 
f. is saved from achilles bc a camera cr ew rises up from desert to film her 
 at this juncture f. sees how endangered she wa
 s (124-25/ she walked and walkedshe was 
being portrayed) 
 
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lessing. The Good Terrorist.
Scanlan. &#8220;Doris Lessing&#8217;s The Good Terrorist.&#8221;
Corrado. &#8220;The Evolution of the Irish Republican Army.&#8221;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_lessing/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>She is attuned to the accents of the commune - posh tones slipping out when least appropriate. 
(Alice suspects that at least one accent  was modelled on Coronation Street.)  
 
tensions in the novel: 
 
1.  Individual idealism  is nicely balanced against the behaviour of the group;  
 
2.  English communism  against manipulation from outside;  
 3.  the impulse to revolution against the dangers of amateurism
.  
 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>corrado on IRA  
  
ideologically, terrorists from the fascist right to the radical left operate across europe  
terrorists both nationalist/ethnic and ideological 
 
def of political terrorism: 
 
explicitly political tactic 
 employed by self-appted individuals 
  who belong to clandestine groups 
   who want to destabilize a political regime 
    by provoking the govt to retaliate 
     thereby encouraging a repressive response 
      and sowing dissension in the ranks 
       of those in power 
 
 
mode:  to generate fear and confusion among noncomatants 
 
undermine confidence in govts political and miliatry forces 
 
what are favorable conditions for tm? 
 
sympathy or at least tolerance  
 
highly visible social group that sees itself as oppressed in political 
 and/or economic terms 
 
need concrete symbol of repression-- 
 historical acts that involve govt violence 
  against a group 
    
 
they need historical precedents, need to show c ontinui
 ty with past, need to show need for drastic 
and violent action 
 
 
question what is sinn fein? 
 
 
 
Doris Lessing, The Good Terrorist
 
1919, British novelist, b. Kermanshah, Persia (now Iran).  
 
She was brought up on a farm in Southern Rhod e sia (now Zimbabwe) and in 1949 went to 
England, where her first novel, The Gr ass Is Singing (1950), was published.  
 
one of the major writers of the mid-20th c ent. and an in fluential figure among feminists,  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Jasper is grudgingly proud of the way she know s ho w to confront officials, to wheedle the 
connection of water and electricity, to eliminate squalor  
 
-- though predictably some of their new comrad es ma ke snide remarks about Alice's bourgeois 
domesticity, saying she cares more for curtains than issues.  
 
No one, however refused the delicious soup she con cocts so economically and can expand to 
unthinkable quantities when a party congress is called. 
 
According to an established pattern Jasper lets Ali ce look after him (though he never allows any 
physical closeness)  
...and then complains that other people exploit her.  
 
The fact that they have been living off Alices mother  
for the past four years is ignored, a matter of expedie ncy for which they are far from 
grateful.  
 
When Alice sees no alternative to stealing money fro m her father, Jasper is enraged to discover 
that she holds any back for emergencies. 
 Still, Alice cannot imagine life without Jasper and she sees herself as a committed revolutionary.   
When she isnt so busy nesting, she liked to be on the battlefront: picketing, bein
 g bound over 
and, best of all, spray-painting slogans.  
 
She is aware that the latest aim of the C.C.U.  (Communist Centre Union) is to help the I.R.A., but 
is increasingly concerned about activities in the squat next door  - what is buried in their 
garden and why there is a whiff of slick K.G.B.  professionalism amidst their bungling 
English zeal.  
 
She is barely conscious of her deeper alarm ab out the plan s hatching under her won roof: the 
dabbling with explosives, the ill-formed objectives , the disregard of consequences. 
 
Doris Lessing has superbly portrayed the tensions and ironies of a certain kind of militant left-
wing living today, drawing her characters with eloquent subtlety.  
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lessing writes on a wide variety of themes:  
 
Rhodesia, women, communism, and animals.  
 
Distinguished for its energy and intelligence, her wo rk is principally concerned with the  
lives of women 
 
--their psychology, politics, work,  
--relationship to men and to their children,  
--and their change of vision as they age.  
 
In her later books she has mainly focused on effort s by individuals to resist societys 
pressures toward marginalization and acculturation.    
 
Throughout Lessings work run currents of r ealism an d fantasy, each of which dominate 
in some novels and mingle in others.  
 
Her fiction includes a series of five novels collectively entitled The Children of Violence, 
whi
ch concern a semiautobiographical character named Martha Quest (1952-69).  
 
One of her most influential works, The Gol den Notebook (1962), a study of the struggles 
of a woman writer, is considered a classic of feminist fiction.   
 
The Good Terrorist (1985) 
The Sweetest Dream (2001), a semiautobiographical tale of the 1960s.  
 
To dramatize the plight of unknown novelis ts, Le ssing wrote two novels, The Diary of a 
Good Neighbour (1983) and If the Old Could (1 984), under the pseudonym of Jane Somers; they 
were ignored by critics until Les sing revealed their true authorship. 
  
The Council, to discourage squatters,  
have sent in workmen to make the place uninhabitable, but  
that will hardly stop Alice.  
 
She is a veteran of some fourteen years experience in squats and communes and here is a 
hou 
se which, judging by the smell coming from upstairs, can use her talents.  
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Fleming. &#8220;Propaganda by Deed: Terrorism and Anarchist Theory in Late Nineteenth-Century Europe.&#8221;
Bakunin. God and State.
Kropotkin. &#8220;The Spirit of Revolt&#8221;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_fleming/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>question what is the alternative to the state? 
 
The alternative, Bakunin suggested,  
 was a decentralized federation of communes  
   that guaranteed relative autonomy  
    and control  
     over the means of production  
      at the local level.  
 
The State and Anarchism  (1873) 
 
Bakunin directed a similar critique  
 against scientific elites,  
  the social sciences,  
   and the scientific pretensions of Marxism. 
 
                                                                   Bakunin also stressed  
 that the destruction of the old order  
   was a prerequisite for socialism 
 
and thus he strongly opposed Hegelian  
 and liberal reformist notions of progress  
 
question did you note any contradictions in his ideas? 
 
His theory of revolution was contradictory, however  sometimes leaning on the notion of 
spontaneous action    and at other times  
   emphasizing the need  
    for conspiracy and careful direction.  
 The latter, in any event,  
 better characterized his actions  
  during the First International.  
 
Ultimately, Bakunins apocalyptic views   and associations with nihilists  
  such as Sergei Nechayev  
   (accused of murdering a fellow conspirator)  
 
contributed to a gradual loss of credibility  
 and to his eventual expulsion from the First Intl. 
                                                                     Although Bakunins split with Marx  
 fragmented the revolutionary movement in Western Europe, he had 
      a lasting effect on the anarchist movements     in Russia, Italy, Switzerland, and Spain.  
 
Throughout his career,  
he founded actual and sometimes imaginary  
revolutionary networks,  
   whose varying degrees of political realism     
 
often perplexed his followers.  
 
Among his more effective organizations was the 
 International Alliance of Social Democracy,  
   which he conceived     as a forward-thinking movement  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>within the First International 
 
the alliance advocated the defin itive abol ition of classes  
   and the political, economic, and social      
 
equalization of the sexes. 
 
 
Kropotkin, Peter  (184 2-1921)   
 Russian nobleman, and main proponent of anarchocommunism.  
 
He was a geographer who carried out explorations of Siberia, Finland, and Manchuria before 
devoting hi
s life to political activities. 
 Modern Science and Anarchism
 (1903) 
 
question did you pick up on his interest in darwin? 
 
Kropotkin believed that Darwins theory of evolution,  pr op erly applied,                                                  
  showed that human beings  
   are social creatures who flourish best  
    in small communities 
   cemented together by mutual aid  
     and voluntary associations  
The centralized state 
 with its apparatus of coercion 
  represents a backward step, or obstacle to the     
 
implementation of this ideal. 
                                                       
Reading question: 
 
What is the flaw in Winnie Verlocs character?                
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Moderates [like Karl Kautsky and Eduard Berstein]  
 advocated working for socialism  
  within the democratic political process  
  (a model increasingly known as social democracy).  
 
Others, such as Lenin, advocated violent revolution.  
 
question how would bakunin and kropotkin align with this? 
 
The Bolshevik Revolution of 1917  
 and the end of World War I  
  marked the definitive split between moderates 
and revolutionaries. 
                                                                      
Post 1945:   West, welfare state 
  East, state socialism                                                               
                                                                                                                             
 Noncommunist socialist parties  
 remain prominent in many countries in Europe  
  and the rest of the world.  
 
Most now pursue agendas  
 associated with increasing social welfare  
  rather than fundamental economic transformations.  
 
 
 
Bakunin, Mikhail   (1814 -1876) 
 
question what do you know about him? 
 
A Russian anarchist and revolutionary   who developed an influential critique of the state  
  and vied with Karl Marx  
   for control  
    of the First International (1864-1876).  
 
question what was bakunins problem with marx? 
 Bakunin saw authoritarian tendencies  
 in Marxs socialism  
  and especially opposed Marxs emphasis  
   on the need for  
    a centralized proletarian regime.  
 
question what were bakunins problems with the state? 
 
For Bakunin, the state in any form 
 became a mechanism of mystified power,    controlled by an elite.  
 
In this respect it mirrored religion-- 
 indeed Bakunin saw the two  
  as parallel historical developments.  
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Anarchy and anarchism   
 
What is anarchy? 
Anarchy is the absence of centralized authority or government. 
                                                                      
The term was first formulated negatively  
 by early modern political theorists  
  such as Thomas Hobbes [question:  who is hobbes?] 
   who regarded it  
    as a condition of chaos, terror, and  
      violence.  
 
In the nineteenth century, however,  
 it came to be seen  
  as an alternative to state coercion  
   and economic exploitation. 
                                                                     Historically, anarchism is based  
 on the assertion that  
  people are capable of harmony  
   but are deformed and oppressed  
    by political and economic institutions.  
 
Its most active early promoter was 
             Pierre-Joseph Proudhon (1809-1865),  
  whose influential What is Property? (1840)  
    argued that property is theft 
                                                                      and proposed that  
  small associations of free producers  
    replace capitalism and the state.  
 
question how is proudhons understanding of property tied to Marxs (surplus 
v
alue...)? 
 
In the next generation,  
 the more radical Mikhail Bakunin  
  proposed the complete replacement  
   of private property  
     by collectivism.  
 
Anarchism gradually lost ground to socialism  
 and particularly communism  
  during the late 19th and 20th centuries.  
 
Revolutionary anarchism 
 peaked in the West  
  with a wave of assassinations around 1900.  
 
Anarcho-syndicalism,  
 which drew on Proudhons ideas  
  and advocated the devolution of power  
   to workers councils,  
    played an important role  
in the short-lived Spanish republic  
       of the 1930s.  
 Contemporary anarchism  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>plays a role in opposition to globalization  
   and neoliberalism on the world stage. 
 
 
Socialism   
 
question what is socialism? 
 A form of social organization  
 that prioritizes the common ownership of property    and the collective control  
   of economic production.  
 
Socialism emerged from a diverse array  
 of social experiments and doctrines  
  developed in the 1820s.  
 
These reflected both excitement  
 about the possibilities  
  of a rational, ordered, industrial society  
  
 and growing concern  
  about the actual effects 
   of industrialization  
    under the conditions  
     of private accumulation  
      and market capitalism.  
 
question what are the ill e ffects of industrialization? 
 During its first decades,  
 socialism was pursued primarily by small,  
  utopian communities. 
                                        
The transformation of socialism into a polit ical do
 ctrine occurred in the 1850s-70s 
especially as Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels   
 
developed their own account of socialism  
as the outcome of a revolutionary class  
struggle between workers and  
capitalists.  
 By the late nineteenth century,  
 socialism had developed  
  into a political doctrine  
   associated with  
     --newly formed trade unions  
     --mass political parties  
 
(e.g., the Social Democratic Party in Germany and the
  Labour Party in Britain).  
 
These groups supported diverse views of socialism,  
 from the incremental and ameliorative goals of many trade unionists to 
the radical, revolutionary agendas  
   of Marx, Engels, and the anarchists.  
 
These divisions became increasingly pronounced over time.  
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>B&#246;ll. The Lost Honor of Katharina Blum.
Corrado. &#8220;The History of the German Student Movement and the Birth of the Baader-Meinhof Group.&#8221;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_boll/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>of news for a large portion of the German populat ion. What is the relationship between the News  
and the public sphere? 
 
2. What are the forms of violence that Bll addresses in this work? 
 
3. How does the notion of the public sphere help us to  understand what Bll is trying to say about 
violence?  
 
3. Those who control truthits construction as we ll a s its certificationin a society are in a 
position of power. Address the relationship between the News  and the truth (for instance, 
compare Katharinas facts to the polices facts to the Newss  facts). 
 
useful links: 
 
http://www.baader-meinhof.com/terminology/terms/springer.html 
 
http://www.boell.org/welcome.asp 
 
http://www.baader-meinhof.com/who/terrorists/bmgang/meinhofulrike.html 
 
 
notes from corrado reading on baader-meinhof group  
 
Burschenschaften wanted to redeem German nation by direct act of will 
--reaction against Napoleonic incursion 
--romantic, idealist 
--distant goals, outside of time and space, sublime spectacle 
 
post war:  consolidation of frg democracy and demise of major conditions for tm 
 
1983:  27 members of green party elected to parliament 
 
radicalization of student mvt:  
 
formation of SDS german soct student alliance 
1950s on:  baby boom, student population booms  
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>But Blls mind, topical events were the keys to reality.  
 
He cited the example of Japanese fishermen expos ed to the radi ation of American atomic testing 
in the Pacific.   
The event was topical 
 the men were not agents of history or of change 
  but even so, the reality  of the event wa
 s such  
   that it introduced into everyones mind      a  new con
 sciousness that air itself can be a form of death.  
 
So Bll is partly trying to explain the co nsciou sness that governs postwar life  
 (why do we think this way and not that?).  
 
To help him achieve this end,  
 he introduces into his narratives individu als who them selves have made no history,  
  but who carry in their own stories the keys to the overarching structures and  
   forms of power governing life.  
 
Katharina Blum is one such character. 
 Social violence dominated the west in the 60s and 70s.  
 
In Germany, student protests broke out in 1968,  
 there were running protests over the Vietnam War  
  and the deployment of nuclear missiles on German soil,  
 
and at the Munich Olympics in 1972  
 terrorists shot and killed Israeli athletes.  
 
Small hostile violent groups, such as t he Baade
 r-Meinhof Group or Red Army Faction, 
 ravaged German life.  
 
In 1971 two members of that group were killed,  
 and in 1972 the US army barracks in Heidelberg were bombed,  
  as was the Springer publishing house in Hamburg.  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Heinrich Bll 
 
http://www.boell.org/welcome.asp 
 
German writer, winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1972.  
Bll portrayed Germany after World War II  
with a deep moral vision  
and attacked the materialistic values of the post-war society.  
 
Bll's unorthodox Catholic belief often mark ed the spiritual conte nt of his stories.  
 "Art is always a good hiding-place, not for dynamite, but for intellectual explosives and social time bombs. Wh
y would there otherwise have been the various Indices? And 
precisely in their despised and often even despicable beauty and lack of transparency lies the best hiding-place for the barb that brings about the sudden jerk or the sudden 
recognition."  (from Nobel Lecture , 1973)  
 
 
Bll was drafted into the compulsory work prog ram. "... my unconqu
 erable (and still unconquered) 
aversion to the Nazis was not revolt," Bll later wrote, " they revolted me, repelled me on every 
level of my existence: conscious and instinctive, aesthetic and political." (from What's to Become 
of the Boy?, 1981)  
 
During World War II Bll served six years as a privat e  and corporal in the army on both the Soviet 
and Western fronts.   
He was wounded four times, and at the end of the wa
 r he was interned in a prisoner-of-war camp 
in France.   
In his early novels Bll depicted the despair of soldiers' lives... 
the oppressive cruelties he witnessed in his youth an
 d in military service.  
 
From the "worm's-eye" view of World War II hi s scop e widened gradually on the reality of modern 
German society. 
 
Billiards at Half Past Nine  (1959) took place in a single day (September 6, 1958).  
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>It depicted a prominent family of Cologne architects,  
who have been successively involved with the building of an abbey  
at the beginning of the 20th-century, its destruction during World War II,  
and its rebuilding after 1945.  
 
In the course of the day Bll reveals  
the crucial incidents in the past of the family,  
from the Wilhelminian empire through Weimar and Hitler  
to the prosperous West Germany of 1958.  
 In 1968 Bll worked as a teacher at the University of Fran
 kfurt and later at other universities (in 
Prag 1969 and in Israel 1970).  
 
Bll was politically active and in 1972 he participated in SPD's election campaign.  
 
The Lost Honour of Katharina Blum  (197 4) 
 The protagonist, Katharina Blum, is a decent young housekeeper.  
 
question: what is the basic plot? 
 
She falls in love with a young man, who is wanted by the police.  Katharina helps him to escape, and is interrogated by
  the police as if she had participated in 
terrorist acts.  She is persecuted in the sensation-seeking press, and especially an unscrupulous reporter 
named T
tges, who is responsible for ruining her reputation.  
Finally she is driven to the act of murdering him.  
When the reporter says, "How about us hav ing a ba ng for a start?" she shoots him.  
 
Bll himself had experienced harassment  
by the media and his house was searched by police  
when he announced that terrorist Ulrike Meinhof should be given a fair trial.  
 
Volker Schlndorff and Margarethe von Trotta adapted the book into screen in 1975.  
 
Safety Net  (1 979) was inspired by the press coverage of the Baader-Meinhof terrorist group. 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>The entire Baader-Meinhof affair was exploited by rig ht wing media  
 which used stories on the affair    as a means to bring down the German government.  
 
Bll intervened on behalf of Ulrike Meinhof in 1972  
 because he believed that the press,  
  which had been accusatory, had deprived her and her group of a fair trial.  
 
Bll was then himself criticized, subject to police searches,  
 accused of creating a climate for violence,  
  and cast as a threat to the internal security of the nation.  
 
Bll sued for defamation and eventually won his case in Constitutional Court in 1981. 
 
The Lost Honor of Katharina Blum  appears in the mi
 dst of this period, in 1974.  
 The story is a polemical parody of the structures a
 nd mentalities of life.  
 Bll uses the story to criticize several forms of violence in modern society;  
 physical violence is actually the least among them.  
 
The story of KB
  is well known. 
 
Katharina Blum sleeps with a suspected terrorist,  
 and is subsequently charged by the police with murder.  
 
Lets look closely at what he is saying  
 about the systematic dangers t hat exi st in postwar society. 
 question: what is the public sphere?  how does media participate? 
 
Consider for discussion: 
 1. The newspaper Ne
 ws in this story ( Die Zeitung  in the German version) is actually Bild-Zeitung , 
a tabloid published by the Axel Springer (discuss ed in class). It was and still is the major source 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>tension bw students and faculty (who have control over curriculum, sovereignty).  professors act 
out authoritarian personality. 
 
418/ general structure of univ. system facilitates move to student violence 
 
Frankfurt school theorists (Habermas, Marcuse) assert: 
 
419/ univ system had to be altered so that st u dents could undergo the radicalizing experience 
that would allow them to contribute to changi ng w. german society in a nonviolent manner 
 
once violence erupted, habermas spoke out against students:  violence would bring about 
rep
ression that would hinder the unfolding of radical revolution in frg. 
 rudi dutschke maintained that frg needed to be denazified. 
 
triggers for RAF: vietnam 
   release of comrades from prison 
 
meinhofs goal: to demonstrate the vulnerab ility of the p
 olice by showing that armed 
confrontation is feasible-- that  it is possible to carry out actions where we can win. (422) 
 
424/ timeline of 1977  
question what psychological parallels are there between 
  napoleonic victories, failed liberalism of 19. centu
 ry, shame of NS time? 
 answer: all attributed to parental failure 
 
question: habermas sees RAFs confusion of sym
 bol and reality as pathological. 
  what does he mean?  do you agree?  ra sch, a forensic psychiatrist, 
  has disagreed. 
 
429/  RAF only offered the oppressed a dist ant symbolic identification in 
  return for their revolutionary sacrifices. 
 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>In his essays  
Bll saw his role as a writer to act as the social conscience of his age.  
 
He ridiculed contemporary jargon,  
defended individual freedom and self-determination,  
and warned about the dangers of escalating nuclear armament  
and the creeping powers of the state security system.  
 
Often returning to his Catholic faith... 
Bll examined the godlessness of the times ... 
but viewed critically the church itself.  
 
 
Ulrike Meinhof 
http://www.baader-meinhof.com/who/terrorists/bmgang/meinhofulrike.html  
  
Heinrich Bll, Lost Hono
 r of Katharina Blum  
 
We turn this week to a novel published in the mid-1970s.  
 
Although fiction, its story rings true in that it rev eals some of the ba sic stru ctures of daily life and 
interaction in a highly industrialized society near the end of the 20th c.   
Due to its treatment of the theme of violence following the outbreak of severe violent acts in the 
we
st in the 1960s and 1970s, KB is often overused as a document of the period, and it is often 
read for its surface features alone.   Yet Bll had much more in mind than a literal reading of the text as a direct reflection of an actual 
event.  
 
Bll distinguishes between the topical and the real.  
 
Real events, he argued in 1953, were events i dentifie
 d as having had significant impact upon 
our lives (an example would be WWII).   
Topical events, by contrast, were more ordinary  (in th
 at they were forgotten and therefore 
seemingly inconsequential).  
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Elsaesser. &#8220;Antigone Agonistes.&#8221;
Baumann. &#8220;How Everything Started.&#8221;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_baumann/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>272/* german govt officials still bound by military codes of Nazi past 
 
 
where did the young generation of the 70s see the co ntinuity bw the nazi times and postwar 
germany? 
 
Essentially they equated fascism with capitalism 
 
 
Performativity of RAF 
Elsaesser, too, sees something theatrical in the RAF 
 --he mentions that the RAF wanted to unmask  the hypocrisy of postwar Germany 
 --he compares them to Hamlet and to Antigone  
Elsaesser compares the RAF to several modern art movements.  What are they? 
 --happenings 
 --fluxus 
 --graffiti 
 --situationism 
 --avantgarde film:  battleship potemkin 
 
Also the RAFs actions were so emphatically urban  
285/* they were urban guerillas... they were part of a tendency to see space as a political 
cat
egory 
 
the RAF played upon the inhospitability of modern cities 
 
the RAF erupted into the urban fabric 
 
but Elsaesser makes an important distinction that lent ricchia, for example, does not: 
 
287/* sees street not as metaphor for the stage 
  but as synecdoche for urban space 
 
a figure of speech by which a part is put for the w hole (as  fifty sail for fifty ships), the whole for a 
part (as society for high society), the species for the genus (as cutthroat for assassin), the 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Michael Baumann, How it all began  
 
In intro, it says that the main issue is violence: 
 Should the state have a monopoly on its use? 
 
Can you imagine a moment in history when such a monopoly worked against democracy? 
 
Boell and Sartre endorsed publication of this book 
 -- some have gone so far to say that suppression of book 
  is tantamount to violence.  Do you agree?  What is real violence? 
 
Go over main points in chronology, pp 12-18 
 
What kind of youth did MB have?  What are main elements of his formation? 
 --worker, rebel, commune, drugs, read bakunin 
 
With whom does he identify?  (blacks,  jews... thru music, thru exclusion) 
 
Lets lay out a few points of MBs argument from the rest of the book: 
 
31/ some ppl, when pushed to the limit, can only free the mselves by irrational, aggressive 
actions 
 
33/ privileges individual action 
 every slave... that is how the individual te rror of the ol d anarchists can be explained 
 heres the crux in which german militants found themselves: 
41/ before i get transported to auschwitz, id rather shoot first 
 
one thing that only is expressed later in the book is th
 at MB identifies with third world struggle 
46/ a little manifesto:  struggle doesnt happen in metropolis anymore 55/ refers to fanon 
 
militants trained in jordan 
 
60/ mention of bombing of synagogue in berlin (shalom and napalm) 
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>genus for the species (as a creature for a man), or the name of the material for the thing 
made (as boards for stage) 
 
 RAF signals shift in political culture... 
  From elite politics of stage/parliament/agora   thea ter 
   To street politics of event/e ntertainment culture  media  
 
Elsaesser sees a love/hate relationship bw RAF and US.  What is it? 
 --against US imperialism 
 --idolizes US youth/counterculture... macho gangster 
 
the RAF became the german equivalent of pop art 
 
is Elsaessers question, that RAF violence was essentially symbolic just rhetorical? 
 RAF seemed to attack the space of the spectacl e, bu
 t it already operated within this space 
 Lets read a really dense passage together and th ink 
 about whether artist could be substituted 
for terrorist:  295/ whole last graph  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>mb criticizes RAF as too intellectual-- the only shoot out of abstraction (78) 
 
 
Thomas Elsaesser, Antigone Agonistes  
 
what is the Antigone story (Sophocles)? 
 
Whats Elsaessers project at hand her e ?  Whats the main concern? 
 267/ tv show deathgame brought RAF mythology to rest 
 it did what neither police state did... 
  nor what the films of the 70s managed to do 
 
What is the hot autumn of 1977? 
 
267-68/ timeline 
 
These events brought postwar Germany to crisis... 
 They revealed how fragile the cargo of democracy was, 
  How quickly it could devolve into violence... 
   Both state and mass violence. 
 Who are main protagonists of Deathgame
? 
 269/ Hans-Martin Schleyer and Helmut Schmidt, then a hostage 
 
How is this different to M+J
?   vT doesnt show side of victim 
 How are audiences in 70s different from those in 90s and today? 
 
270/ 70s viewers sympathized with RAF, were
  skeptical of press and state 
 Read passage on 271.  Elsaesser says th is isnt a cyn
 ical stance.  Why not? 
 Schmidt and his advisors draw a parallel bw 1977 and Stalingrad. 
 Why is this a problem? 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Richter. 18. Oktober 1977.
Grimonprez. Dial History.</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21g-061-advanced-topics-plotting-terror-in-european-culture-spring-2004/resources/mit21g_061s04_06104notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>To help him achieve this end,  
 he introduces into his narratives individu als who them selves have made no history,  
  but who carry in their own stories the keys to the overarching structures and  
   forms of power governing life.  
 
Katharina Blum is one such character. 
 
Social violence dominated the west in the 60s and 70s.  
 
In Germany, student protests broke out in 1968,  
 there were running protests over the Vietnam War  
  and the deployment of nuclear missiles on German soil,  
 
and at the Munich Olympics in 1972  
 terrorists shot and killed Israeli athletes.  
 
Small hostile violent groups, such as t he Baade r-Meinhof Group or Red Army Faction, 
 ravaged German life.  
 
In 1971 two members of that group were killed,  
 and in 1972 the US army barracks in Heidelberg were bombed,  
  as was the Springer publishing house in Hamburg.   
The entire Baader-Meinhof affair was exploited by rig
 ht wing media  
 which used stories on the affair  
  as a means to bring down the German government.  
 
Bll intervened on behalf of Ulrike Meinhof in 1972  
 because he believed that the press,  
  which had been accusatory, had deprived her and her group of a fair trial.  
 
Bll was then himself criticized, subject to police searches,  
 accused of creating a climate for violence,  
  and cast as a threat to the internal security of the nation.  
 
Bll sued for defamation and eventually won his case in Constitutional Court in 1981. 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Heinrich Bll, Lost Hono r of Katharina Blum  
 
We turn this week to a novel published in the mid-1970s.  
 
Although fiction, its story rings true in that it rev eals some of the ba sic stru ctures of daily life and 
interaction in a highly industrialized society near the end of the 20th c.   
Due to its treatment of the theme of violence following the outbreak of severe violent acts in the 
we
st in the 1960s and 1970s, KB is often overused as a document of the period, and it is often 
read for its surface features alone.   
Yet Bll had much more in mind than a literal reading of the text as a direct reflection of an actual 
event.  
 
Bll distinguishes between the topical and the real.  
 
Real events, he argued in 1953, were events i dentifie
 d as having had significant impact upon 
our lives (an example would be WWII).   
Topical events, by contrast, were more ordinary  (in th
 at they were forgotten and therefore 
seemingly inconsequential).  
 
But Blls mind, topical events were the keys to reality.  
 
He cited the example of Japanese fishermen expos ed to the radi ation of American atomic testing 
in the Pacific.   
The event was topical 
 the men were not agents of history or of change 
  but even so, the reality  of the event wa
 s such  
   that it introduced into everyones mind  
    a  new con sciousness that air itself can be a form of death.  
 So Bll is partly trying to explain the co nsciou
 sness that governs postwar life  
 (why do we think this way and not that?).   
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Springer Press  
 
11 April 1968 - Thousands of protestors riot at the Berlin head quarters of the Springer Press after 
SDS and APO leader Rudi Dutschke is shot by an extremist. 
  
 
The bane of leftist Germans, the Springer newspapers were outrageously conservative. Owned 
by Lord Axel Springer , the Springer Press controlled almost half of the newspaper circulation in 
West Germany.  
Springer was an avowed anti-communist. During a ti me whe
 n others corporations were leaving 
West Berlin in droves (fearful of the tenuous politic al situation that barely k ept the city out of East 
German hands), Axel Springer chose to put the headquarters for his publishing empire in Berlin. 
Springer built a 20-story monstrosity mere yards away from the Berlin Wall (a block away from 
Checkpoint Charlie), and put a huge reader-board on the side facing East Berlin. The board would flash the news of the free world to the "ens laved Germans" on the other side of the wall. 
The sheer size of the building was intended as a constant reminder to East Germans of the superiority of the Capitalist system. 
 
The Baader-Meinhof Gang
 bombed the Springer building in Hamburg in May of 1970 , injuring 17 
workers. 
 http://www.boell.org/welcome.asp 
 
German writer, winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1972. Bll portrayed Germany after 
Wo
rld War II with a deep moral vision and attacked the materialistic values of the post-war 
society. Bll's unorthodox Catholic belief often ma rked the spiritual content of his stories.  
 "Art is always a good hiding-place, not for dynamite, but for intellectual explosives and social time bombs. Wh
y would there otherwise have been the various Indices? And 
precisely in their despised and often even despicable beauty and lack of transparency lies the best hiding-place for the barb that brings about the sudden jerk or the sudden 
recognition."  (from Nobel Lecture , 1973)  
 
Heinrich Bll was born in Cologne. His father wa
 s a cabinetmaker and sculptor, whose ancestors 
had fled from England to escape the persecution of  Roman Catholics. Bll started to write poetry 
and short stories in his youth. He was one of the fe w boys in his school who did not join the Hitler 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>sixty other characters are depicted. Boll parodied fa shionable documentary novels, but also used 
the dead language of real documents of Nazi bureaucr acy. The narrator tries to reconstruct the 
life of Leni, the simultaneously saintly and sensuous heroine. "The female protagonist in the first 
section is a woman of forty-eight, German: she is five foot six inches tall, weights 133 pounds (in 
indoor clothing), i.e., only twelve to fourt een ounces below standard weight; her eyes are 
iridescent dark blue and black, her slightly greying hair, very thick and blonde, hangs loosely to her shoulders, sheathing her head like a helmet." Leni has survived a difficult childhood, a bad 
marriage, a forbidden love affair with a Soviet prisoner-of-war, the bombing of Cologne, and postwar series of losses. In the end his friends, social 'discards', organize a 'Help Leni 
Committee' to bail her out of bankruptcy and prevent her eviction.  
 
In 1968 Bll worked as a teacher at the University of Fran
 kfurt and later at other universities (in 
Prag 1969 and in Israel 1970).  
 
Bll was politically active and in 1972 he participated in SPD's election campaign.  
 
The Lost Honour of Katharina Blum  (197 4) 
 
The protagonist, Katharina Blum, is a decent young housekeeper.  
 
She falls in love with a young man, who is wanted by the police.  
Katharina helps him to escape, and is interrogated by  the police as if she had participated in 
terrorist acts.  
She is persecuted in the sensation-seeking press, and especially an unscrupulous reporter 
named T
tges, who is responsible for ruining her reputation.  
Finally she is driven to the act of murdering him.  When the reporter says, "How about us hav ing a ba
 ng for a start?" she shoots him.  
 Bll himself had experienced harassment by the media and hi
 s house was searched by police 
when he announced that terrorist Ulrike Meinhof should be given a fair trial.   
Volker Schlndorff and Margarethe von Trotta adapted the book into screen in 1975.  
 
Safety Net  (1
 979) was inspired by the press coverage of the Baader-Meinhof terrorist group. 
 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21G.061 Advanced Topics: Plotting Terror in European Culture
Spring 2004
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>In his essays Bll saw his role as a writer to act as the social conscience of his age. He ridiculed 
contemporary jargon, defended individual freedom  and self-determination, warned about the 
dangers of escalating nuclear armament and the cr eeping powers of the state security system.  
 
Often returning to his Catholic faith Bll examined the godlessness of the times but viewed 
critically the church itself.  
 
Bll died in Bonn on July 16, 1985. After his death,  cri tics lamented the lack of a successor 
capable of carrying on his public missions as moral authority and a spokesman for intellectual freedom. 
 
http://www.baader-meinhof.com/who/terrorists/bmgang/meinhofulrike.html 
 
Ulrike Meinhof's parents both died early, leaving Ul rike
  and her sister Weinke in the care of 
Renate Riemack, a friend of their mother's. Riemack was a devoted socialist, and a profound 
influence on Meinhof. 
 
Meinhof married Klaus Rainer Rhl , publisher of the left-wing student newspaper, konkret . After a 
few years Meinhof became konkret's  editor. Rhl and Meinhof have twin girls, Bettina and 
Regine , on 21 September, 1962. 
 
Meinhof drifted away from Rhl, and towards the radical fringe of the student movement. She left 
her hu
sband in the late sixties. On 14 May, 1970 , she participated in the freeing of Andreas 
Baader , giving birth to the so-called "Baader-Meinhof Gang."  Though partially named after her, 
Meinhof was not, as is often assumed, the co-lea der of the gang (Baader, along with his girlfriend 
Gudrun Ensslin , led the group, with Meinhof, Jan-Carl Raspe , and others comprising a second 
tier of leadership). She spent the next two years on the run, robbing banks and bombing 
buildings, before being captured on 15 June, 1972 . 
 
While in prison over the next four years, Me inhof g rew increasingly depressed as the other gang 
members ostracize her. She hung herself in her cell on 9 May, 1976  (though some have 
questioned this official explanation and instead suspect that she was murdered by the state).  
 
Ulrike Meinhof  
 
Member 
Baader-Meinhof Gang 
 
Born 
7 October 1934 
 
First Active  
May 1970 
 
Current Status  
Committed suicide in prison 9 May 1976  
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Youth movement. However, his elder brother, Al ois, joined the movement to keep his fathers 
business afloat. Bll graduated from a high school in 1937. In his certificate Bll had two errors: 
his birth date was incorrect and his choice of career - "book trade" wa s altered by the school 
principal.  
 
Bll was drafted into the compulsory work prog ram. "... my unconqu erable (and still unconquered) 
aversion to the Nazis was not revolt," Bll later wrote, " they revolted me, repelled me on every 
level of my existence: conscious and instinctive, aesthetic and political." (from What's to Become 
of the Boy?, 1981) During World War II Bll served six year s as a private and corporal in the army 
on both the Soviet and Western fronts. He was wounded four times, and at the end of the war he 
was interned in a prisoner-of-war camp in France.  
 
After returning to Cologne, Bll studied at the uni versity and worke d then for a short time in the 
family workshop and later at the city's Bureau of Vital Statistics. Bll's first stories appeared in 
1947. Some of his early works were published in English in The Mad Dog (1997). The title story 
depicts two friends, a a priest and a murderer, who meet at the end of the war but find that they 
are separated by their own horri fic experiences and spiritual emptiness. Bll's first novel, The 
Train was on Time , appeared in 1949. From 1951 he was a full-time writer.  
 
In his early novels Bll depicted the despair of soldi ers' lives, the oppressive cruelties he 
witnessed in his youth and in military service. From the "worm's-eye" vi ew of World War II his 
scope widened gradually on the r eality of modern German society. 
 
In a 1952 essay, Bll accepted the label "rubble literature" as a designation of literary trend which 
focu
sed on the war, coming home, and reconstruction. Bll wanted to find a realism that would 
correspond "to the laconic nature of the genera tion which has 'come home,' a generation that 
knows there is no home for them on this earth." 
 
Billiards at Half Past Nine  (1959) took place in a single day (September 6, 1958). It depicted a 
prominent family of Cologne architects, who have been successively involved with the building of 
an abbey at the beginning of the 20th-century, its destruction during World War II, and its 
rebuilding after 1945. In the course of the day B ll reveals the crucial incidents in the past of the 
family, from the Wilhelminian empire through Weim ar and Hitler to the prosperous West Germany 
of 1958.  
 
In 1971 appeared G roup Portrait With a Lady , which was again formally innovative: it was 
composed from interviews and documents about Leni  Pfeiffer, through whom the lives of some 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The Lost Honor of Katharina Blum  appears in the midst of this period, in 1974.  
 
The story is a polemical parody of the structures a nd mentalities of life.  
 Bll uses the story to criticize several forms of violence in modern society;  
 physical violence is actually the least among them.  
 
The story of KB
  is well known. 
 
Katharina Blum sleeps with a suspected terrorist,  
 and is subsequently charged by the police with murder.  
 
Lets look closely at what he is saying  
 about the systematic dangers t hat exi st in postwar society. 
 question: what is the public sphere?  how does media participate? 
 
Consider for discussion: 
 1. The newspaper Ne
 ws in this story ( Die Zeitung  in the German version) is actually Bild-Zeitung , 
a tabloid published by the Axel Springer (discuss ed in class). It was and still is the major source 
of news for a large portion of the German populat ion. What is the relationship between the News  
and the public sphere? 
 
2. What are the forms of violence that Bll addresses in this work? 
 
3. How does the notion of the public sphere help us to  understand what Bll is trying to say about 
violence?   
3. Those who control truthits construction as we ll a
 s its certificationin a society are in a 
position of power. Address the relationship between the News  and the truth (for instance, 
compare Katharinas facts to the polices facts to the Newss  facts). 
  
http://www.baader-meinhof.com/terminology/terms/springer.html 
 
 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
