<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/</course_url>
    <course_title>American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, and Future</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Public Administration </list>
      <list>Political Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Indochina War. 1950&#8211;1975</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_vietnamwar/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21&#8211;22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
toward Hanoi explains this alliance. Perhaps the
 
"proxy" assumption became valid after 1975 but US
 behavior made it true--it was a self-fulfilling
 prophecy.
 
-- Ho Chi Minh sought to get the US into the Pacific war
 
in 1941 and later asked the US to make Vietnam a US
 protectorate like the Philippines. This showed Ho's
 willingness to cooperate with the US.
 
-- The power of nationalism trumps ideology in modern
 
times. This ensured that a united Communist Vietnam
 would be nobody's proxy.
 
C. Regarding Containment Version #2, Domino theory:
 
Hawks note that:
 
-- Domino effects have clearly been observed elsewhere in
 
world history, e.g., in Southern Africa in the 1970s,
 Central America in the 1980s, and Eastern Europe in
 1989. This establishes the plausibility of domino
 effects in Southeast Asia.
 
-- Cambodia and Laos fell to Communism in 1975.  So
 
dominos did topple in Southeast Asia.
 
-- More Southeast Asian states might have fallen had the
 
US not given them a 10-year breathing space to get
 their act together. Hanoi revealed its aggressiveness
 by invading Cambodia in 1979; had its other SE Asian
 targets been weaker it might have moved further.
 
Doves note that:
 
-- Deduction flunks the cadre version and the conquest
 
version of the domino theory. The intense inter-ethnic
 hatreds of Southeast Asia made the operation of
 Vietnamese cadre in other countries impossible; and
 Vietnam lacked the military power to win a regional war
 of aggression against its major neighbors.
 
-- Not many dominos fell after 1975.  The big prizes-
Thailand, Malaysia, Burma, Singapore, Indonesia, the
 Philippines, Australia, and Japan--all stood firm.
 
-- Cambodia provoked Vietnam's 1979 invasion so this
 
episode says little about Vietnamese aggressiveness.
 
D. Regarding Containment Version #2, Strategic Region
 
assumption: Events don't test this proposition. It could
 be tested by a simple inventory of the assets of the
 region. 
E. Regarding the Credibility theory:
 
Hawks note:
 
-- The 1975 US defeat was followed by an upsurge of Soviet
 
activity in the Third World during 1975-1980--in
 Angola, Afghanistan, and Ethiopia.
 
-- Several thugs around the world, including Saddam
 
Hussein and Osama bin Laden, later cited the 1975 US
 pullout from Vietnam as evidence that the US would not
 strongly resist their schemes.
 
Doves argue that:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
a. Subversion version: "A communist-controlled Vietnam
 
will send agents across borders to subvert
 
neighbors."
 
b. Invasion version: "A communist-controlled Vietnam
 
will send armies across borders to conquer
 neighbors."
 
c. Inspiration version: "A communist victory in Vietnam
 
will inspire revolutions elsewhere in Southeast Asia,
 by showing that they can succeed and that the US will
 let them succeed."
 
d. Intimidation version: "A communist victory in Vietnam
 
will position Vietnam to intimidate other Southeast
 Asian states into submission and alliance with
 Vietnam."
 
3. Strategic region assumption, 1950-1965.
 
a. Southeast Asian bases matter; their transfer tips the
 
global balance of power.
 
b. The West depends on Southeast Asian raw materials.
 Vietnam had no industrial power or other assets of
 
strategic value. But if assumptions B2 and B3 (the Domino
 theory and the Strategic Region assumption) are true,
 Vietnam nevertheless is a power-asset, as the outcome in
 Vietnam would decide who owned other strategically
 important places.
 All three assumptions--proxy, domino, and strategic
 
region--had to hold to tie the outcome in Vietnam to
 
Containment. One or two are not enough.
 
C. Credibility: "Defeat in Vietnam will destroy the
 
credibility of US threats and promises elsewhere, e.g., the
 
US threat to defend Europe from Soviet attack."
 1. Feared effects of lost credibility:
 
a. Others will disbelieve US threats and promises,
 
hence:
 i.	 NATO or other US alliances may disintegrate
 because US allies will doubt US assurances,
 inclining them to cut a deal with the Soviets.
 
ii.	 The USSR may doubt US resolve in Europe or
 
elsewhere. As a result it may challenge the US
 at more points; and it may underestimate US
 resolve and over-commit, causing a US-Soviet
 war.
 
iii. Nuclear proliferation will increase as Germany,
 
Japan and other states come to mistrust US
 security guarantees and seek their own means of
 security.
 
b. Dominoes will fall via intimidation (see III B 2d,
 
above).
 
c. Revolutions will be inspired (see III B 2c above).
 
2. Credibility arguments passed through three phases:
 
a. Version #1 ("The Soviets are testing us in Vietnam"),
 
1945-1965.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
D. The Soviet Union and China begin feuding, 1958-59. 	Their
 
rupture becomes severe by 1964 and verges on war by 1969. 
Can US efforts to avert Chinese expansion in Southeast Asia
 still serve Containment?
 
E. 1961-1962: more US military advisers go to Vietnam. 	They
 
total over 9,000 by late 1962.
 
F. 1963: France and many in South Vietnam favor resolving the
 
civil war in South Vietnam by agreement to unify and
 neutralize Vietnam in the cold war. The JFK administration
 rejects this option, and ousts South Vietnamese leaders
 Diem and Nhu who favor it. (They are killed.)
 
G. Early 1965: Vietcong victory in the South is imminent. 	The
 
US intervenes massively to avert it. Thus large direct US
 involvement begins. The US starts bombing in February 1965
 (Operation "Rolling Thunder") and sends large ground forces
 in July 1965. US forces in Vietnam peak at 543,000 troops
 in 1969.
 
H. January 1968: the Communist Tet offensive. 	The US smashes
 
the offensive and badly weakens the Vietcong but the US
 public misreads the Tet offensive as a sign of US failure.
 
I. 1969: the US begins to withdraw and launches
 
"Vietnamization"--it turns the war over to the South
 Vietnamese.
 
J. 1970: the US widens the war into Cambodia and Laos in an
 
effort to deny sanctuaries to the Vietcong.
 
K. 1973: a peace is agreed. 	The agreement allows North
 
Vietnamese forces to remain in the South. Later in 1973,
 wrongly thinking the war is over, the US Congress forbids
 US bombing throughout Indochina.
 
L. 1973-75: both Vietnamese sides break the peace. 	The US
 
then stands aside as communist forces seize the South and
 unify Vietnam under Hanoi's rule, April 1975.
 
M. Total killed in the Indochina War during 1960-1975:
 
2,544,000. US dead: 56,000.
 
III.	 FACTUAL AND THEORETICAL BELIEFS THAT MOTIVATED U.S.
 
INVOLVEMENT
 
A. Containment, Version #1: "The US must stop communism in
 
Vietnam to save France and NATO." (1945-48)
 1. "France's colonies make it stronger, hence a stronger
 
NATO ally."
 
2. "We must placate France on Indochina to gain its
 
cooperation in NATO."
 
B. Containment, Version #2: "The US must stop communism in
 
Vietnam to contain Soviet (or Chinese) expansion. A
 communist victory in Vietnam will tilt the global balance
 of power toward the Soviet Union (or China)."
 1. Proxy assumption, 1949-75: Ho Chi Minh is Moscow's
 
puppet; or is Beijing's puppet, while Beijing is
 Moscow's puppet. 
2.	 Domino theory, in 4 versions, 1953-1965.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
-- Version #2 of the Credibility theory is false because: 
a. The US had no obligation to defend South Vietnam
 
under the SEATO treaty since that treaty was aimed
 
at international aggression and the war in South
 Vietnam was mainly civil.
 
b. The South Vietnamese voided any US obligation to
 
defend them by their political corruption and
 military incompetence.
 
-- Versions #1-#3 of the Credibility theory are falsified
 
by history:
 a. After 1975 NATO remained strong and nuclear
 
proliferation didn't happen.
 
b. There was no upsurge of Soviet activity worldwide
 
during 1975-1980--merely a relocation of activity
 away from Europe, the Mideast, and Southeast Asia
 and toward Africa and South Asia. And research by
 Ted Hopf shows that the Soviets didn't infer much
 from the US defeat.
 
c. The Vietnam war itself drained American willpower-
see e.g., the "Vietnam syndrome"--an alleged postwar
 US gunshyness. This syndrome, if real, was caused
 by US involvement in Indochina. So fighting in
 Vietnam did more harm than good for US credibility.
 
F. Domestic Backlash:
 
1. Version #1 ("Electoral backlash") is not tested by
 
events, but could be tested by looking at poll data.
 
2. Version #2 ("Nightmare of recrimination") seems
 
falsified by history. When the war ended it quickly
 vanished from the consciousness of an American public
 more interested in Star Trek, disco, and platform shoes.
 
G. Philanthropy:
 
1. There was a bloodbath in Cambodia--two million were
 
murdered by the communist Khmer Rouge--and millions fled
 South Vietnam in boats. But in Vietnam no bloodbath
 happened--some 40,000 people died in work camps but
 there was no mass killing. Doves argue that if the US
 had left Indochina before 1970 there would have been no
 war in Cambodia, hence no bloodbath there either. But
 hawks answer that without US intervention Communism
 would have spread still more widely in Southeast Asia,
 and that Communist governments are prone to commit
 bloodbaths.
 
2. The Vietcong were unpopular after 1975 but probably had
 
significant popularity in South Vietnam in the 1950s and
 1960s. President Eisenhower once stated that the
 Communists would have won a free election in 1956.
 
3. After 1975 the North Vietnamese took over the South,
 
suppressing all local institutions. No self-
determination for Southerners.
 
H. Was victory possible? 	Doves note that the US lost, but
 
hawks claim that victory was in America's grasp in 1968. 
The Viet Cong were decimated in the 1968 Tet offensive.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
b. Version #2 ("We have promised to defend South
 
Vietnam"), 1961-75.
 
c. Version #3 ("We have paid costs, hence our reputation
 
is engaged"), 1969-75.
 
3. Prescriptions: John McNaughton ("We must suffer but
 
needn't win") vs. Henry Kissinger ("We must win because
 
we suffered"). 
D.	 Domestic Backlash.
 
1. Electoral backlash version ("We'll be tossed out of
 
office if we lose"), 1949-53, 1965-69.
 
2. Weimar analogy version ("American society will witness a
 
nightmare of recrimination if we lose"), 1969-75.
 
E.	 Philanthropy.
 1. Bloodbath theory ("Hanoi will slaughter Vietnamese non
communists"), 1969-75.
 
2. Vietcong unpopularity assumption ("The VC are unpopular,
 
hence their victory would be an undemocratic outcome"),
 
1964-75.
 
3. North Vietnamese aggression postulate ("This is a war of
 
aggression by North Vietnam against the South; hence a
 Northern victory would deny the South its right of self-
determination"), 1964-75.
 
F.	 "We can win," 1961-64--optimism about the military outcome.
 
IV. THE ANTI-WAR MOVEMENT: DID IT FAIL? IF SO, WHY?
 
V. 	EVALUATING ARGUMENTS FOR THE VIETNAM WAR
 
To evaluate the US war policy, ask: What should we see in the
 historical record if the hawks were right? If the doves were
 right? Then ask: are the predictions of each viewpoint
 congruent or incongruent with the evidence?
 A. Regarding Containment Version #1: 
Doves note that Vietnam was a millstone, not an asset, for
 
France; and France needed US cooperation in NATO far more
 than the US needed France. The US could have compelled
 France's cooperation without appeasing it on Indochina.
 
B. Regarding Containment Version #2, Proxy theory:
 
Hawks note that:
 
-- Hanoi became a loyal Soviet ally, 1979-1991.  Vietnam
 
gave the Soviets a large naval base at Cam Ranh Bay.
 
-- The Soviet Union and China gave the Vietnamese
 
Communist movement large aid.
 
-- Ho Chi Minh was trained in Moscow as a Comintern agent
 
in the 1920s.
 
Hawks say these empirical observations signal a master-
servant relationship between the USSR and the Vietnamese
 communists.
 
Doves note that:
 
-- Hanoi was hostile toward China during 1975-91 and aloof
 
toward the Soviet Union during 1975-79. Hanoi did ally
 with the USSR after 1979, but US and Chinese hostility</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 
THE VIETNAM WAR, 1945-1975
 The Vietnam War was the most hotly debated war in US history. 
Friendships and families were torn by the quarrel.
 The key rationale for the war: US national security. Hawks
 
claimed that defending South Vietnam from communism would serve
 
US national security by serving the larger US policy of
 Containment of the USSR. Doves were unpersuaded. Did the war in
 fact serve Containment? Historians still disagree on this issue. 
You be the judge.
 
I. EVALUATING POLICY: METHOD
 
Address some or all of these questions:
 
A. Were the theoretical beliefs that led policymakers to
 
support the policy true or false? In short: judge the
 covering laws.
 1. As measured against realities as known with 20/20
 
hindsight.
 
2. As measured against only realities that could have been
 
known at the time.
 
&gt; And if the covering laws are valid, are conditions needed
 
for their operation present in this case?
 
B. Were the factual beliefs that led policymakers to support
 
the policy true or false?
 
C. Were the results of the policy:
 
1. Desired or undesired by policymakers?
 2. Good or bad? (As measured against your own standard of
 
good/bad).
 
D. Did govt decision making follow rules of science--were
 
arguments assessed against logic and evidence? Or was it
 arbitrary?
 
II. U.S. DECISIONS IN VIETNAM/INDOCHINA, 1945-75
 
A. 1941-46: Japan takes Vietnam from France, 1941. 	The US
 
then takes Vietnam from Japan, 1945. The US then fatefully
 decides to allow France to re-take Vietnam. Soon a
 communist-led Vietnamese rebellion against French rule
 begins.
 
B. 1950: the US starts aiding France in a big way against the
 
rebels.
 
C. 1954-56: France decides to give independence to Vietnam. 
The US then decides to let the northern half of Vietnam
 fall to communism but to try to create a non-communist
 Southern state. Toward this goal: (a) The US blocks
 elections in the South because it fears the communist Ho
 Chi Minh will win. (b) A communist-led rebellion begins in
 South Vietnam. (c) In 1956 342 US military advisers are
 dispatched to aid the Southern army against the communist
 rebels (known as the Vietcong, or "VC").</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Theories of U.S. Foreign Policy</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_intrnatnlpolit/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3&#8211;5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
of ideas --&gt; public enlightenment --&gt; wise policies. 
Which is true? Is the public ignorant or enlightened?
 Assigned reading: Cohen.
 
3. Academic irresponsibility, the cult of irrelevance
 
prevalent in academe --&gt; public is ignorant. American
 academe as cause of public ignorance.
 
4. The absent calamity: Unlike most nations, Americans have
 
never suffered epic death and destruction that stemmed
 from their own foreign policy blunders. This fosters
 blithe U.S. indifference toward studying world politics. 
Blunders result.
 Assigned reading: Cohen.
 
5. A manipulated or incompetent press.
 
i.	 U.S. government domination of the press --&gt; tough
 questions aren't asked, key facts omitted --&gt; public
 is ignorant. Official dominion of press coverage as
 cause of public ignorance.
 Assigned readings: Just &amp; Rosenstiel.
 
ii.	 Foreign dictators' can intimidate the press --&gt;
 
dictators decide how the press covers them.
 Assigned reading: Jordan, "News We Kept To
 Ourselves."
 
iii. The U.S press has deteriorated in recent years with
 
the rise of "infotainment" culture in mainstream
 media, propagandistic cable TV news, and talk radio. 
Plus the rise of the internet has eroded the revenue
 base of the mainstream news media, so its
 newsgathering has shrunk. A weak press makes an
 ignorant public.
 Assigned reading: none.
 
6. US "liberal tradition" --&gt; US exports democracy (note
 
clash with hypothesis II A1).
 Key theorist: Louis Hartz. Assigned reading: none.
 
7. Racism --&gt; US policies (from Hiroshima to Vietnam).
 
Assigned reading: Hersh.
 
C. Lobbies, interests groups: foreign lobbies--the British
 
lobby 1914-17 and 1938-41, the China lobby of the 1940s-50s,
 and the Taiwan, Israel (or Likud), Cuban, Polish, Armenian,
 Georgian, and Greek lobbies of today--drive US foreign
 policy.
 Assigned readings: Newhouse, Massing, Guttman.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
Another variant: "Politicians out of power act to mess up
 
incumbent presidents' foreign policies, as Nixon subverted
 Johnson's Vietnam peace effort in October 1968."
 
I. Organization theory.
 
1. "Organizations seek size, wealth, autonomy, and
 
conservation of their 'essence' (i.e., no change in their
 mission)." Example: the Soviet military in the 1950s
 preserved its tank-army essence while leaving the USSR
 unprotected.
 Key theorist: Morton Halperin.
 Assigned reading: none.
 
2. "Organizations follow standard operating procedures." 
Example: Soviet missile installations in Cuba in 1962
 were identical in shape to other Soviet installations,
 hence were easily detected by U.S. spy planes.
 Key theorist: Graham Allison.
 Assigned reading: none.
 
3. "Organizations cannot self-evaluate." 	An example: the
 
"intelligence to please" syndrome--intelligence agencies
 don't evaluate, they kiss up to power, some argue.
 Key theorist: Aaron Wildavsky.
 Assigned reading: Kristof, "Save our Spooks."
 
J. Psychological theories. 
1. "Attribution theory"--states tend to attribute their own
 
behavior to their circumstances, while attributing
 others' behavior to their innate character. (Hence
 states see their own nasty conduct as excused by
 necessity, while others' nasty conduct is unprovoked and
 unjustified.)
 
2. A related syndrome: states tend to ascribe others' good
 
behavior to their own efforts to make the other behave
 well; and to blame others' bad conduct on the other's
 innate character. Hence they underestimate their own
 role in causing others' hostility; hence they exaggerate
 the immutability of that hostility.
 
3. Belief perseverance--states are slow to absorb new facts
 
and realities that clash with their elite's existing
 beliefs.
 
4. States tend to exaggerate the shared character of
 
information, hence they are often unaware when others'
 perceptions diverge from their own.
 
5. States tend to exaggerate the centralized, disciplined,
 
and coordinated character of others' behavior.
 Key theorist for hypotheses J1-J5: Robert Jervis.
 Assigned reading: none.
 
6. "Groupthink"--internal dissent and policy evaluation are
 
suppressed to maintain small-group cohesion.
 Key theorist: Irving Janis. Assigned reading: none.
 
7. Identity theory, ingroup-outgroup theory: "Humans are
 
groupish. They readily sort themselves into competing
 groups. Hence nationalism is powerful, and demagogues
 have the advantage in public discourse."</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
Key theorists: Kenneth Waltz, Stephen Walt.
 
Assigned reading: Walt, Origins of Alliances.
 
2. "Birds of a Feather Fly Together" (vs. "Birds of a
 
Feather Fly Apart"): "Common ideology --&gt; alliance" vs.
 "Common ideology --&gt; conflict for leadership of the
 brotherhood." Some argue that both U.S. and Soviet
 leaders put false faith in "Birds of a feather fly
 together" during the Cold War. The G.W. Bush
 administration made the opposite error in 2003 regarding
 Saddam Hussein and Osama Bin Laden, wrongly dismissing
 the importance of their clashing ideologies.
 Assigned reading: Walt, Origins of Alliances.
 
C. Nationalism. 	"Nationalism makes imperialism very difficult;
 
and nationalism is omnipresent and omnipotent; hence the age
 of empire is over." How to test this theory? Let's think
 of natural experiments.
 Key theorists: Carleton Hayes, Louis Snyder.
 Assigned reading: none.
 
D. Collective goods: the "tragedy of the commons" and the "free
 
rider" problem. "Collective goods (a.k.a. positive
 externalities) are under-provided; collective bads (a.k.a.
 negative externalities) are over-provided." Implication: we
 tend to trash the environment. The tragedy of the commons
 gives us an incentive to pollute, and impedes cooperation to
 clean up pollution.
 Key theorists: Garret Hardin, Mancur Olson.
 Assigned reading: none.
 
E. Marxist theories:
 
1. Rosa Luxemburg: "Capitalist states seek empires to serve
 
as markets for excess production, &amp; thus cure
 depression." Explains U.S. entry into WWI?
 
2. Harry Magdoff: "Capitalist states intervene abroad to
 
protect their multinational corporations." Explains the
 1954 CIA-sponsored coup in Guatemala?
 
Assigned readings: none.
 
F. Peaceful democracies: "Democracies seldom fight each other;
 
hence a world of democracies would be peaceful."
 Key theorists: Immanuel Kant, Michael Doyle.
 Assigned reading: none.
 And a related idea ...
 
G. Wimpy democracies: "Selfish democratic publics won't pay to
 
maintain adequate armed forces; liberal societies have no
 stomach for war's injuries to individual rights."
 Key author: Jean Francois Revel.
 Assigned reading: none.
 
H. Democracies led astray by election-year antics. 	"During
 
political campaigns U.S. politicians pander to U.S. voters
 by framing dangerous foreign policy positions that they
 cannot abandon once in office. The country is thereby led
 into folly."
 Assigned reading: Michael Beschloss, "Foreign Policy's Big
 Moment."</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>THEORIES OF INTERNATIONAL POLITICS
 
AND THEORIES OF U.S. FOREIGN POLICY
 
I. 14 GENERAL THEORIES OR FAMILIES OF THEORIES RELEVANT TO US
 
FOREIGN POLICY
 
A. Offense-defense theory. This theory has two variants:
 
1. Threat variant: 	"Security is the prime goal of states. 
When states are insecure they become more aggressive as
 
they try to gain more defensible borders, to acquire
 resources that enhance their power, to cut their
 neighbors down to size, and to install more friendly
 regimes in neighboring states. The search for security
 causes wars, empires, interventions, and arms races."
 Corollary: "War is more likely when conquest is easy,
 
less likely when conquest is hard."
 Two sub-variants: (a) "States fear conquest and
 
aggress to avert it." (b) "States fear violence against
 their citizens and aggress to avert it."
 Phenomena explained: why the US has been less
 
imperialist than other powers, and has started fewer big
 wars than other powers (compare, e.g., to Germany).
 Prescription: the US can keep peace in Europe, East
 
Asia (Korea), elsewhere by guaranteeing the safety of
 states in these regions.
 How could this theory be tested??
 
2. Opportunity variant: The more easily states can conquer,
 
the more aggressive they become. "States seize what
 their power allows; empires grow and contract as the
 metropole's power rises and falls."
 
A related idea: the "security dilemma." "The means states
 use to increase their security decrease the security of
 others."
 Key theorist: Robert Jervis.
 Assigned reading: Van Evera, "Offense-Defense Theory"
 
B. Theories of Alliances.
 
1. "Balance of Threat": "States align against the most
 
threatening state (i.e., the most powerful, aggressive,
 nearby state) in the neighborhood." Vs. "Bandwagoning":
 "States align with threatening states--intimidation wins
 friends." Some argue that this theory explains why the
 U.S. had far more allies than the Soviet Union during the
 Cold War (1947-89). The Soviets were more aggressive than
 the U.S., and were closer to more states, so they were
 more threatening to others, hence they scared others into
 America's arms.
 Prescriptions: believers in bandwagoning will favor
 
hawkish policies and bullying/belligerent tactics;
 believers in balancing will prefer dovish policies and
 policies of reassurance.
 How can these hypotheses be tested?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
Key theorists: Sherif and Sherif.
 
Assigned readings: none.
 
K. "Spiral Model" vs. "Deterrence."
 
1. Spiral model: "Wars arise when states punish others
 
expecting compliance; but punishment only provokes
 retaliation, sparking a conflict-spiral."
 
2. Deterrence: "Wars arise when states appease aggressors;
 
this leads the aggressor to expect further appeasement,
 and to ignore warnings when appeasement ends."
 Key theorist: Robert Jervis.
 Assigned readings: Jervis, Daniel Gilbert, and SVE
 handout.
 
L. Gender theories: "Men are more aggressive than women;
 
foreign policies made by men reflect male attributes."
 Key author: Joshua Goldstein
 Assigned reading: none.
 
M. Credibility theory ("deterrence theory"--Thomas Schelling):
 
"The credibility of commitments is interconnected; the
 abandonment of one commitment destroys the credibility of
 others."
 Key authors: Thomas Schelling, Daryl Press.
 Assigned reading: none.
 
N. Domino theory: "An aggressor's conquest of one state eases
 
its conquest of nearby states."
 Key author: Jerome Slater. Assigned reading: none.
 
II. THEORIES/THEORY FAMILIES SPECIFIC TO AMERICAN FOREIGN POLICY
 
(&amp; DERIVED EXPLANATIONS)
 
Theories specific to United States foreign policy:
 
A. Elite Culture: the role of:
 
1. Prep school/big business culture in foreign policy
 
making--Princeton grads run US foreign policy --&gt; USFP
 favors US business, is cool toward democracy overseas
 (note clash with hypothesis II B6).
 Assigned readings: Isaacson and Thomas, Hersh.
 
2. The national security establishment and the role of
 
military worldviews. Some argue that professional
 militaries are prone to exaggerate the hostility of other
 states and the effectiveness of using force when they
 communicate to civilians. Some claim that the U.S.
 military does this. Others counter that the U.S.
 military has often been more dovish than U.S. civilian
 leaders since about 1980.
 Assigned reading: none.
 
3. Elite ignorance of world affairs, 1900-1970. 	The USA as
 
innocent abroad.
 Assigned reading: Cohen, "Great Caesar's Ghost."
 
B. Public Opinion, Popular Culture, Ideology:
 
1. Policy overselling --&gt; policies develop lives of their
 
own.
 Key theorist: Theodore Lowi. Assigned reading: none.
 
2. Public ignorance --&gt; policy blunders vs. Free marketplace</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_introduction/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>&gt; 	Industrial power was concentrated in the a few places: 
North America, Europe, and Japan. See especially the 
world maps drawn to GOP size and Oye table 4-1. 
D. 	Did American foreign and military policy make power
political sense? 
1. 	 Did Germany and its allies have any hope of defeating 
the US and its allies in 1914 and 1939? If not, should 
the U.S. have been able to deter German expansion in 
1914 and 1939? 
&gt; U.S. mobilization strategy: frugal prudence or 
strategic blunder? 
2. 	 Did U.S. efforts against Germany in 1917 and 1941 and 
the Soviet Union in the Cold War avert real dangers? 
Specifically, if these states had conquered all of 
industrial Eurasia (that is, Western Europe, Russia and 
Japan) would they then have had enough power to conquer 
the U.S.? See maps and table 4-1. 
3. 	 Did U.S. Cold War interventions in the Third World 
(Vietnam, Korea, Guatemala, Chile, Iran, Congo) make 
sense? See maps and table 4-1. 
E. 	Will China's further rise threaten U.S. security? Will the 
spread of WMDs to non-state actors threaten U.S. security? 
If so, how should the U.S. respond? 
&gt; Should the US move to contain China and/or impede its 
rise? Is this necessary? Could it succeed? 
&gt; 	Is a rising power always a danger to be stopped? 
Britain did not stop Prussia in 1870 and paid. Britain 
did not stop the U.S. in 1861-65 and profited. 
&gt; 	 Does the U.S. face other more serious threats (for 
example WMD terror and climate change)? Should it 
cooperate with China (and Russia) to defeat these 
threats? 
&gt; 	 Compare four threats: China, Russia, WMD terror, &amp; 
climate change. Which is greatest? 
IV. 	 THE EVOLUTION OF U.S. POLITICS &amp; SOCIETY 
A. 	Ignorance: American knowledge of the world was low, then 
rose, now falls. 
&gt; Americans now learn less about the world from the press 
than 40 years ago. Schools teach less international 
history. 
&gt; 	Unlike Europeans and Asians, Americans have never suffered 
the full horrors of war in their homeland. Are they naive 
about it? 
B. 	U.S. foreign policy was once run by aristocrats. This is no 
longer true. But who now dominates? DC thinktanks &amp; 
lobbies are increasingly important. Who controls them?? 
C. 	The changing U.S. economy: 
&gt; Fears of depression abated after 1941--until we forgot 
Keynes after 1980, creating a new risk of depressions. 
&gt; 	Economic inequality diminished sharply in the U.S. during 
1941-1980, has expanded sharply since 1980. 
D. 	U.S. white racism &amp; antisemitism greatly diminished after 
-1940. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>AMERICAN FOREIGN POLICY: INTRODUCTION 
I. COURSE QUESTIONS REQUIREMENTS AND READINGS 
A. 	Questions addressed in 17.40 include: 
1. 	What explains past and present U.S. policies? 
2. 	Were the premises behind u.s. policies valid or false? 
Were their results good or bad? Were these results 
desired or undesired by policy makers? We will evaluate 
u.s. policies. 
a. 	Were the policy's effects on the USA and U.S. 
interests good or bad? Consider four U.S. interests: 
&gt; National security interests: preserving U.S. 
sovereignty and avoiding war. Did past or present 
wars, interventions, doctrines and policies make the 
U.S. more or less secure in these terms? 
&gt; Economic interests. Did U.S. policies advance 
these? 
&gt; 	Other interests: environment, public health, e.g., 
protecting against new pandemics. Do U.S. policies 
protect these? 
&gt; 	Philanthropic interests--promoting human rights or 
otherwise "doing the right thing" by others. What 
code of ethics should guide foreign policy? Have 
U.S. policies measured up to it? 
b. The policy's effects on other peoples and states. 
3. 	What should now be done? Regarding, e.g., al Qaeda, 
ISIS/Iraq/Syria, the spread of weapons of mass 
destruction (WMD) , the North Korean and Iranian nuclear 
programs, China's rise, national ballistic missile 
defense, trade policy, climate change, Ukraine/Russia, 
Afghanistan/Pakistan. 
4. Predictions: what will be done? 
We will focus on question #2, evaluation, especially of 
national security policy. 
B. 	Class requirements and readings. 
&gt; 	Discussion sections ("recitation sections") are required 
and important. Please attend and please participate! We 
need your help to make sections work! 
&gt; 	In sections you will present to the National Security 
Council and participate in debates. 
&gt; 	Four papers: two -2-pagers and two -8-pagers. A draft of 
an -8 pager must be submitted in advance to your TA. 
&gt; Two IS-minute quizzes. 
&gt; One final. 
&gt; Readings. 
C. 	Syllabus organization. We progress in this order: (1) 
national security overview; (2) general theories; (3) grand 
strategies; (4) historical cases and policy problems 
(national security policy, foreign economic policy, and 
terror); (5) implications for current policy. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>rather, the stronger method is the one that suits the data 
available. This varies by topic. 
&gt; 	In U.S. history departments the study of international and 
military history has been sidelined and replaced by social 
history (e.g., race, class and gender issues). These are 
very important but so is international history! Its 
demise is harming our ability to study U.S. foreign 
policy. 
III. 	 THE GLOBAL DISTRIBUTION OF POWER, l789-PRESENT. See the maps 
of the world scaled to GDP by Edwin Reischauer, in three 
versions (plain, Germania, and Sovietania); the 2005 map; 
tables 6, 17, 18, 30, 31, 35, and chart 2 from Paul Kennedy, 
Rise and Fall of the Great Powers; and Table 4-1 from 
Kenneth Oye, ed., Eagle in a New World. 
A. 	U.S. national security turns on (1) the global distribution 
of power, and (2) the intentions of other states and actors. 
Can others harm you? Will they try? 
B. 	Four questions about the nature of international power: 
1. 	Before 1945, what was national power made of? 
Strategists then argued that industrial power = military 
power = power. They believed that other elements of 
power--population, military bases, control of critical 
raw materials like oil--also mattered but were secondary 
to industrial power. Industrial power, measured in GDP, 
was seen as the key index of power. 
2. 	What is national power made of today? Is industrial 
power still key? Or do weapons of mass destruction (WMD) 
change everything? Can actors with little industrial 
power acquire WMD? If they do, are they powerful despite 
their lack of industrial power? 
&gt; North Korea, an impoverished state, has build nuclear 
devices. 
&gt; 	Some worry that stateless terrorists might buy or steal 
or be given weapons of mass destruction, or the 
materials to make them. 
Do these possibilities make obsolete the use of 
industrial power as our key measure of national power? 
3. 	Offensive vs. defensive power: which dominates? 
&gt; 	 Was defense or offense easier among states before 
nuclear weapons arrived (1945)? By how much? What 
implications follow? 
&gt; 	Have nuclear weapons changed the offense/defense 
equation? If so, how? Some argue that nuclear weapons 
make conquest impossible among major powers. Are they 
right? 
4. 	Related: is destruction easier or harder than defense 
against destruction? 
C. 	The evolution of U.S. and global power, 1789-present. 
&gt; U.S. industrial power grew vastly during 1789-1938. See 
tables 6, 17, 18. 
&gt; 	U.S. standing military power grew much less, 1789-1942, 
due to America's mobilization strategy. See tables 19, 
31, 35. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>D. 	Class missions, expectations. 
&gt; 	Broad course missions: students will learn how to ask 
questions, devise and frame explanations and arguments, 
and marshall and present evidence. 
&gt; 	We focus on developing your communication skills. Past 
MIT alumni reported that they needed more communication 
and leadership skills to realize their goals in life. We 
are here to help with that. 
&gt; 	Absolutely no background knowledge of U.S. foreign 
policy/diplomatic history is assumed for this course. 
Feel free to consult 17.40 staff about non-17.40 stuff like 
planning your career. We will offer what wisdom we can. 
II. WHAT IS POLITICAL SCIENCE? 
A. 	Experimentation vs. observation. Both methods can work 
well. 
B. 	Large-n (statistical) studies vs. case studies. Both 
methods work. The nature of the data decides which method 
is stronger. 
&gt; Natural experiments--situations in history that resemble 
controlled experiments--are especially strong tools of 
investigation. 
C. 	To test theories: (1) Infer predictions from the theory 
stating what we expect to observe in the world if the theory 
is valid, and what we should observe if it is false. (2) 
Assess the degree of congruence between our predictions and 
our observations. Congruent = theory is corroborated; 
incongruent = theory is infirmed. 
D. 	Accidents, chaos theory, and history: 
&gt; Does politics have regularities--laws of motion--like 
those of the natural world? 
&gt; 	If accidents, personalities, and serendipity shape 
history, how can general theories explain the past? Annie 
Oakley could have killed Germany's Kaiser Wilhelm in 
-1889. If so, could she have saved us from the 20th 
century? (Maybe!) 
E. 	Why has political science achieved less than the natural 
sciences? 
F. 	Controversies in social science about how to do it. 
&gt; 	Social scientists debate the best way to test theories. 
Some claim that large-n methods and/or controlled 
experiments are inherently stronger than case methods. 
Others argue that no method is inherently stronger; 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The U.S. &#8220;War on Terror,&#8221; 9/11/01&#8211;present</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_waronterror/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>THE WAR ON TERROR, 2001-PRESENT
 
I. 	THE THREAT OF WMD TERROR: KEY QUESTIONS
 
A.	 How great is the threat of WMD terror attacks, or other mass-
killing terrorist attacks (e.g., attacks on chemical plants or
 
nuclear plants)? How can this threat be measured? Experts
 disagree! Some say the threat is minor (John Mueller, Ian
 Lustick), others believe it is immense and immanent (Graham
 Allison). How can we tell who is right?
 
B.	 How should this threat be addressed? What strategy is best?
 
II. AL QAEDA IN CONTEXT
 Before 1993 terror experts believed that terrorist groups had
 
limited aims--Brian Jenkins said terrorists wanted "a lot of people
 watching not a lot of people dead"--and they were too incompetent to
 conduct large-scale mass-casualty attacks.
 The 1993 al-Qaeda attack on the World Trade Center and the
 
1994/95 Aum Shinrikyo attacks in Tokyo showed that some terrorists
 aspire to immense killing.
 The 2001 World Trade Center attack by al-Qaeda showed that some
 
terror groups are capable of large-scale well-coordinated global
 attacks, hence of killing on a grand scale in the US.
 Its past statements and actions indicate that al-Qaeda seeks to
 
wreak large mayhem in the U.S. The late al-Qaeda leader Osama Bin
 Laden (1988-2011) proclaimed that "to kill Americans ... civilian
 and military--is an individual duty for every Muslim who can do it
 in any country in which it is possible."
1 His former press
 
spokesman, Suleiman Abu Ghaith, claimed a right for al-Qaeda to kill
 four million Americans, including two million children.2 His
 
operatives sought to acquire nuclear weapons during the 1990s.
 
III. ORIGINS OF AL-QAEDA: WAR CAUSES TERROR / FAILED STATES CAUSE
 
TERROR
 
A. War causes terror (an argument by Stephanie Kaplan):
 Osama Bin Laden formed al-Qaeda in Pakistan in 1988 by combining
 
Arabs who had volunteered to aid the Afghan side in the Soviet-
Afghan war (1979-89). Specifically, al-Qaeda combined Egyptian
 followers of Egyptian Islamist ideas (Hassan al-Banna and Sayyid
 Qutb) with Saudi followers of Wahhabism, a hateful and xenophobic
 Saudi Islamic sect.
 Al-Qaeda has since been fed by the Afghan civil war (1989-1996),
 
the India-Pakistani conflict, the Arab-Israeli conflict, the
 Russian war in Chechnya, the 2003 US invasion of Iraq, the 2011 US
 invasion of Libya, the Syrian civil war of 2011ff, and the Somali
 civil war of ~1980sff. Al-Qaeda feeds on war!
 
B. Failed states cause terror
 
1
 In 1998, quoted in Anonymous, Through Our Enemies' Eyes:
 
Osama bin Laden, Radical Islam, and the Future of America
 (Washington, D.C.: Brassey's, 2002): 59.
2 Graham Allison, Nuclear Terrorism: The Ultimate
 
Preventable Catastrophe (New York: Times Books, 2004): 12.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
increased markedly among Muslims, Christians, Jews and Buddhists
 
over the past 15 years. (See Daniel Benjamin and Steven Simon,
 The Age of Sacred Terror [2002.])
 
B. Weapons of mass destruction (WMD) technology and knowledge are
 
spreading relentlessly.
 1. Weapons of mass destruction are growing more accessible to
 
terrorists as technology advances and technical knowledge
 disperses.
 a. The price of making WMD falls steadily as technology
 
advances until it becomes affordable by terrorists.
 
b. The internet has a worrying downside. 	It enables groups
 
with only rudimentary research skills to quickly learn how
 to assemble and use WMD.
 
2. Nuclear proliferation, e.g., to Pakistan in the 1990s and
 
North Korea today, creates more opportunities for bad actors
 to buy or steal nuclear weapons or materials.
 
C. The spread of bioweapons and the resulting risk of bioterror pose
 
a growing danger. (Discussed in our previous class on national
 security policy.)
 Some, including myself, were lulled about the bioterror danger
 
before 9/11/01 because the United States and most other major
 powers were uninterested in developing bioweapons. (The U.S.
 abandoned its offensive bioweapons program in 1969). We inferred
 from this that bioweapons weren't very useful and so wouldn't be
 developed or used. But while bioweapons may be unuseful to
 states, they are very useful to terrorists who seek vast
 
destruction instead of finite military objectives. The
 
appearance of skilled terrorist groups that aspire to mass
 murder, like al-Qaeda, means that a new class of potential
 bioweapons users has appeared. These weapons now have customers!
 Many were also lulled by the world's success in surviving the
 
nuclear revolution. They assumed that nuclear, chemical, and
 biological weapons were all of a piece--all were "weapons of mass
 destruction"--and that measures that worked with one (arms
 control, deterrence) would work with all three. But, as noted
 last week, bioweapons are far to control by agreement than
 nuclear weapons and their use is harder to deter. This is
 because bioweapons are more likely to be obtained by nondeterrable terrorists and arms control to halt their spread is
 far harder.
 (See writing by MIT grad Greg Koblentz on these issues.)
 
IX. GOOD ANSWERS ARE HARD TO FIND!
 One answer: Isolationism toward the world and Stalinism with a
 
democratic face at home in the U.S. Tight surveillance of all human
 activity by a vastly increased state security apparatus. A grim
 specter.
 Another answer: end scientific progress. Abolish MIT.
 Anybody got better ones?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
&gt; U.S. support for corrupt authoritarian Arab regimes in Egypt,
 
Saudi Arabia, and elsewhere.
 
&gt; U.S. economic sanctions on Iraq after 1991, which it alleged (I
 
think wrongly) had killed many innocents.
 
&gt; U.S. troops stationed in Saudi Arabia and Kuwait after 1991.  This
 
was declared a sacrilege by al-Qaeda.
 
&gt; US backing for Israel.  Al-Qaeda seeks to destroy Israel, and
 
complains against all US aid to Israel. Other Arabs grudgingly
 
accept Israel but oppose its continuing occupation/control of
 Palestinian lands. The U.S. has given large aid to Israel (~$3
 billion per year) while Israel has exported settlers (now
 numbering over 600,000) into the conquered Arab territories. U.S.
 aid to Israel is essentially unconditional, so these Arabs see the
 U.S. as backing Israeli colonization of Arab lands. This warms
 them to al-Qaeda's anti-Israel stance.
 
V. AL-QAEDA ATTACKS, US RESPONSES; AL-QAEDA TODAY
 
A. Al-Qaeda's major attacks on western targets: the 1993 bombing of
 
the World Trade Center, killing 6 people; a failed 1994 attempt
 to destroy 11 airliners over the Pacific ocean; the August 1998
 bombing of the U.S. embassies in Kenya and Tanzania, killing 212
 Africans and 12 Americans; a failed January 1, 2000 attack on the
 Los Angeles airport and hotels in Jordan; the October 2000
 bombing of the USS Cole in Yemen, killing 43 US military
 personnel; the 2001 attack on the World Trade Center, Pentagon
 and (probably) Congress, killing 2996 people; a 2002 attack in
 Bali Indonesia, killing 202 people; the 2004 train bombing in
 Madrid that killed 191 people; the 2005 attack in London that
 killed 52 people; and the 2015 attack on the staff of Charlie
 Hebdo in Paris. Al-Qaeda has also attacked many Muslim targets
 in the Middle East and North Africa, killing thousands.
 
B. US responses: the U.S. struck back at al-Qaeda's Afghan bases
 
with cruise missiles in August 1998, and ousted the Afghan
 Taliban regime that protected it in October 2001. The US mounted
 large-scale drone attacks against al-Qaeda leadership in Pakistan
 starting in 2009, decimating the AQ leadership. US special
 forces killed Osama bin Laden in May 2011.
 
C. Al-Qaeda today.
 
1. The al-Qaeda central command in Pakistan, now led by Ayman al-
Zawahiri, has been badly weakened by US drone strikes and US
 efforts to isolate it from its worldwide friends. However,
 al-Qaeda franchises have sprung up in Yemen, Somalia, Iraq,
 Syria, Libya, Mali, Nigeria, and the Sinai. Of these groups
 only the Yemen franchise ("Al Qaeda in the Arab Peninsula," or
 AQAP) now aspires to strike the US, but this could change.
 
2. An al-Qaeda spinoff, ISIS (or ISIL), seized large territories
 
in Iraq and Syria in 2014 and murdered many there. It is now
 much reduced and its state will soon be destroyed, but it will
 likely survive as a dangerous underground force.
 
4. The Afghan Taliban, a past al-Qaeda ally, remains strong in
 
Afghanistan. Three jihadi groups--the Pakistani Taliban,
 Jaish-e-Muhammed and Lashkar-e-Toiba--remain active in
 Pakistan.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
5. The al-Qaeda narrative remains widely believed in the Muslim
 
world.
 
VI. PRINCIPLES OF COUNTER-TERROR
 
Counter-terror is a war of intelligence, and a war of ideas, not a
 
war of firepower.
 Terrorists that can be found can be neutralized; finding them is
 
the hard part.
 Terrorists are sustained by popular support. They can be
 
defeated only when their narrative is defeated; probably not before.
 
VII. U.S. COUNTER-Al-QAEDA STRATEGY: A WAR ON TOO FEW FRONTS?
 
A. Consider 12 possible missions that a counter-terror strategy
 
might include. Both the Bush 43 and Obama administrations, but
 especially Bush 43, were criticized for focusing unduly on the
 first mission while neglecting others.
 1. The military/intelligence offensive. Go abroad and roll up
 
al-Qaeda's organization and sanctuaries, using intelligence
 and military force. Two approaches are debated:
 a. Use US forces to destroy and replace regimes that give
 
sanctuary to al-Qaeda, and to strengthen regimes that are
 willing to suppress al-Qaeda that inhabits their territory. 
Example: the US destroyed and replaced the Taliban regime
 in Afghanistan in 2001, then worked to build up an anti-
Taliban Afghan government.
 
b. Attack al-Qaeda organizations directly, using drones, local
 
allies, and US special forces, without replacing the
 regimes of the states they inhabit. Examples: Obama waged
 an intense drone (Predator/Reaper) war against al-Qaeda and
 Taliban militants in Pakistan. In Somalia, Yemen and Syria
 the U.S. has moved against al-Qaeda affiliates with drones
 and through proxies, while working around weak or
 uncooperative local regimes. Few U.S. troops were put on
 the ground to do this.
 Both Bush 43 and Obama focused on the offensive. This
 
offensive had some successes (destroying the Taliban regime in
 Afghanistan in 2001 and the Islamic State's proto-state in
 20015-17) but also failures (the escape of al-Qaeda's
 leadership from Tora Bora in Afghanistan in late 2001, the
 Taliban resurgence after 2006, the survival of al-Qaeda
 franchises in Yemen, Mali, Libya and elsewhere, and the rise
 of ISIS).
 The Trump administration has continued this emphasis on
 
offense.
 
2. The defensive. U.S. borders remain quite open. U.S. nuclear
 
reactors and chemical plants remain inviting targets for
 terrorists. U.S. ports remain open to devastating attack. 
U.S. biodefenses have been strengthened but the U.S. remains
 vulnerable to bioterror. U.S. insurance laws governing terror
 give businesses little incentive to harden their
 infrastructure against terror.
 
3. Lock down loose nuclear weapons, materials, and scientists.
 
Bush 41, Bill Clinton, and Bush 43 all moved to lock down</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2
 Failed states (states that cannot control their territory) have
 
multiplied in number in recent decades.
 Al Qaeda infests failed states: Afghanistan in the 1990s; Yemen;
 
Somalia; Iraq; Syria; Libya; Mali; Nigeria; Chechnya; and Pakistan
 
(a semi-failed state).
 
IV. AL-QAEDA IDEOLOGY AND OBJECTIVES
 
A. Al-Qaeda ideology
 Al-Qaeda seeks to restore the Muslim world to the purity of the
 
seventh century. Toward this it seeks to remove corrupt secular Arab
 rulers (e.g., Mubarak and Sisi in Egypt, Saddam Hussein in Iraq,
 Bashar al-Assad in Syria, the Hashemite monarchy in Jordan, and the
 Saudi monarchy); to eliminate western influence that it believes
 sustains these corrupt rulers; and to liberate "Muslim lands" now
 under non-Muslim rule. These "Muslim lands" include any places that
 were once governed by Muslim rulers (Spain, southern France, Israel,
 Greece, the Balkans) or by rulers that paid tribute to Muslim Caliphs
 (Russia).
 After the Soviet ouster from Afghanistan Bin Laden's prime target
 
became the United States--the "far enemy." He believed this "far
 enemy" sustained the "near enemy" (the corrupt Arab regimes), so the
 far enemy had to be beaten to defeat the near enemies.
 Al-Qaeda thinking follows the "jihadi" or "harabi" worldview
 
propounded by Hassan al-Banna and Sayyid Qutb, drawing on ibn
 Taymiyya. It is reinforced by Saudi Arabia's export of its xenophobic
 version of Islam--Wahhabism--throughout the Mideast since 1962. It
 contorts Muslim scripture and tradition to allow the spreading of
 Islam by force and the killing of non-combatants. (Both are forbidden
 by mainstream Muslim traditions.)
 
B. The al-Qaeda historical narrative
 Al-Qaeda's narrative is compelling but essentially false. It
 
claims that the last century has seen vast unprovoked one-way violence
 by the U.S. and other western states against Muslims, who themselves
 were peaceful. In fact Muslims and non-Muslims have both committed
 great crimes against the other. Islamic Sudan slaughtered two million
 non-Muslim South Sudanese (1983-2006), Sudan supports the murderous
 Lord's Resistance Army in Uganda, Islamic Indonesia murdered 200,000
 Christian East Timorese (1975-2000) and 400,000-500,000 of its Chinese
 minority (1965), and Islamic Turkey murdered ~1,000,000 Christian
 Armenians in 1895 and 1915. Muslims have also killed many Muslims,
 including: Saddam Hussein's mass killings of Kurds, Shias, and others
 (totalling perhaps 400,000-500,000 Iraqis killed), Hafez Assad's 1982
 slaughter at Hama and Bashar Assad's more recent slaughter of Syrian
 civilians, the vast crimes of the Islamists in Algeria since 1992, and
 the Iran-Iraq war. Muslim extremists make a weak case when they
 demand vengeance against others for committing deeds they tolerate
 among themselves.
 The Qur'an says: "Believers, if an evil-doer brings you a piece of
 
news, inquire first into its truth, lest you should wrong others
 
unwittingly and then regret your action." (Qur'an, 49:6). Perhaps
 this is the basis for a dialogue to narrow differences about history.
 
C. Al-Qaeda complained of four specific US policies before/after the
 
9/11/01 attack:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
loose nuclear and biological materials and scientists in
 
Russia and elsewhere, but slowly. Most are now secured but
 not all.
 
4. Wage a war of ideas.  To defeat al-Qaeda the U.S. must change
 
the terms of debate in the Muslim world. The key tool: Public
 diplomacy, or "counter-narrative" efforts.
 U.S. public diplomacy efforts have been half-hearted. Al
 
Hurra TV and Radio Sawa, the main public diplomacy broadcast
 projects, are ineffective. The Voice of America Arab language
 service was closed. (!)
 
5. End inflammatory conflicts that feed al-Qaeda.  Al-Qaeda feeds
 
on war, especially wars involving Muslims. Perhaps the US
 should work to end such conflicts. They include: the Israel-
Palestinian conflict, the India-Pakistan conflict, and the
 Afghan and Syrian civil wars.
 To end the Israel-Palestinian conflict: some suggest the
 
U.S. should frame its own final-status peace plan and coerce
 both sides toward it with carrots and sticks.
 Regarding Kashmir and Iraq: same idea? Frame a final
 
status agreement and use carrots and sticks to push both sides
 toward it.
 
6. Save or resuscitate failed states? or develop a strategy to
 
intervene against terrorists in such states?  This issue was
 
much-debated regarding Afghanistan. Should the U.S. try to
 resuscitate the Afghan state? Or ignore the Afghan state, and
 intervene directly against the Taliban if it grows too strong
 or behaves too badly.
 
Additional possible missions:
 7. Spread democracy, destroy authoritarian rule in the Muslim
 
world.
 
8. End poverty, bring prosperity to the Muslim world, ROW.
 9. Get the US out of the Middle East--pull US troops from the
 
Mideast region? (Robert Pape recommends.) And/or reduce or
 cut US ties with Israel?
 
10. Deny financing to terrorists by counter-finance activity. 
Deny terrorist organizations other means of sustenance,
 whatever they might be,
 
11. Deny terrorists communication space.
 12. Negotiation/deterrence/appeasement?? Make terrorists become
 
more benign??
 
What research is needed on these or other missions?
 
B. Is policy innovation required to address the WMD terror threat? 
Some argue that the U.S. should put relatively less resources
 into traditional military functions--army, navy, air force--and
 more resources into counterterror functions, including public
 diplomacy, diplomacy to lock down loose nukes and bioweapons
 around the world, and nation building/saving failed states.
 
VIII. THE LONG RUN: TWO SCARY TRENDS RAISE RISKS OF WMD TERROR
 
A. Violent religious fundamentalism is rising in many religious
 
communities. This raises the danger that more al-Qaedas could
 someday be born.
 Millennarian fundamentalism is especially dangerous and has</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The 1962 Cuban Missile Crisis; Other Cold War Crises.</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_cubnmisilecris/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19&#8211;20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
C. The US sent nuclear-armed intermediate-range ballistic
 
missiles (IRBMs) to Britain, Italy and Turkey, 1957-1962.
 
II. THE SOVIETS SEND MISSILES TO CUBA, MAY-OCTOBER 1962: WHY? 
AND WHY DID THEY DO IT SECRETLY?
 
The Soviets sent the missiles to Cuba ...
 
A. To acquire enough nuclear strength to escape the shadow of US
 
nuclear superiority?
 
B. To deter the US from a feared invasion of Cuba?
 C. To acquire enough nuclear strength to force the US to settle
 
the Berlin crisis in the Soviets' favor?
 
D. To humiliate US President John F. Kennedy (JFK)?
 Historians and Soviet crisis participants interviewed later
 favor explanations #1 and #2, with focus on #2. A few favor #3. 
In 1962 JFK's policymakers favored explanation #4.
 Note: the Soviet deployment included 60 nuclear warheads for
 
medium and intermediate-range MRBM and IRBM missiles; 36 IRBMs;
 and 98 tactical nuclear weapons plus short-range Luna (Frog)
 missiles and Ilyushin 28 Beagle bombers to deliver them. The
 Lunas and Beagles were ideal for nuking a US invasion force.
 
III. THE US RESPONSE
 
A. JFK warns Soviet Premier Nikita Khrushchev to deploy no
 
missiles in Cuba, Sept. 4 and Sept. 13, 1962.
 
B. The Soviet missiles are discovered, Oct. 16. 	JFK decides
 
they must go. Why?
 1. Fears for US credibility, NATO unity: "If we cave NATO
 
will collapse!"
 
2. Fears that the missiles would give the Soviets an
 
unacceptable military advantage? No: JFK expressed little
 concern about the military consequences of the Soviet
 missile deployment.
 
3. US domestic politics? 	Did JFK fear attacks from the right
 
if he caved? The White House tapes don't reveal such
 concerns; and non-elected officials were more hawkish than
 JFK, suggesting that electoral political concerns weren't
 driving hawkish thinking. But JFK did privately express
 fear of impeachment or defeat in the 1964 election if the
 missiles stayed in Cuba. "Kenneth Keating will be the
 next president." 
C. The ExComm considers three options, Oct. 16-Oct. 22:
 
1. Quiet diplomacy. 	Threaten Khrushchev privately while
 
making no public military moves.
 
2. Blockade ("quarantine") Cuba. 	Exclude only missiles and
 
warheads for now, to freeze the military status quo. 
Maybe extend the blockade to cover oil and other items
 later, if necessary, to strangle Cuba.
 
3. A surprise US conventional air strike against the Soviet
 
missiles, followed immediately by a US military invasion
 of Cuba.
 
Early in the crisis JFK and most of his advisors favored
 option #3, Surprise Attack and Invasion. But JFK eventually</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
2. US anti-submarine operations were more aggressive than JFK
 
knew. Indeed, they were more aggressive and dangerous
 
than the US Navy itself knew. On Oct. 27 the Navy forced
 to the surface a Soviet submarine that, unbeknownst to the
 Navy, carried a nuclear torpedo and was commanded by a
 Soviet officer that feared he was under attack and briefly
 considered firing his nuclear torpedo.
 
3. A US U2 strayed over Siberia during the crisis. 	The
 
Soviets could have thought this a precursor to a US first
 strike. The Soviets scrambled fighters to shoot it down;
 the US scrambled nuclear-armed fighters in response.
 
4. US test intercontinental ballistic missiles (ICBMs) were
 
armed with nuclear warheads during the crisis; and a
 scheduled test from this test-field was still conducted.
 
5. A US intelligence ship remained close to Cuba early in the
 
crisis--an inviting target.
 
6. A pre-planned retaliatory strike was nearly conducted
 
after the Oct. 27 U2 shootdown--another near-oversight.
 
C. False warning problems. 	The US jury-rigged south-directed
 
warning system had a hidden common-mode failure: it would see
 a Cape Canaveral launch as a Cuban launch.
 
D. Would JFK have pushed matters to war? 	If forced to decide on
 
Day 1, yes. Later, only in extremis. We now know he made a
 plan (the Cordier plan) to agree publicly to withdraw the US
 IRBMs from Turkey if this was necessary to resolve the
 crisis. But JFK did formulate his last offer/threat as an
 ultimatum with a deadline--a risky act.
 
E. What if someone else had been President? 	JFK was markedly
 
more dovish than other US policymakers. Had he not been
 President history probably would have been different and more
 exciting. The military favored war. Acheson favored war.
 
VII. LATER HISTORICAL REVELATIONS: REVISIONS TO RFK'S ACCOUNT
 
-- The Cordier plan.  JFK had a hidden plan to pursue a public
 
Jupiter trade.
 
-- The Soviets had nukes in Cuba, including tactical nukes,
 
commanded by officers with predelegated authority to use
 these weapons at the outset of the crisis. Khrushchev
 withdrew this authority during the crisis but there is no
 guarantee these weapons would have gone unused in event of
 war.
 
-- The US seriously intended to oust Castro.  It was probably
 
provoked the Soviet missile deployment. It also provoked
 Castro to seek nuclear war if Cuba was invaded.
 
-- A soviet sub commander considered launching a nuclear weapon
 
at a US destroyer.
 
VIII. PERSISTING MYSTERIES OF THE CRISIS
 
-- Why the rush by the US?  	 The US was in a great rush to
 
resolve the crisis, pressing matters at a desperate pace on
 October 27, when Kennedy told the Soviets that the US would</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
-- The bomb-vs.-quarantine debate early in the crisis.
 
-- A later debate over whether to trade US Jupiters to get
 
Soviet missiles out of Cuba.
 
VII. 	HOW DANGEROUS WAS THE CUBAN MISSILE CRISIS?
 
JFK estimated the risk of war at between 1 in 3 and 1 in 2.
 A. How accurate were perceptions on both sides? Not very!
 
1. JFK didn't expect a USSR missile deployment to Cuba. 
That's why he warned publicly against it--he thought his
 bluff wouldn't be called.
 
2. US policymakers didn't see a chief USSR motive for
 
deployment (defend Cuba from invasion). Hence nearly
 overlooked the no-invasion pledge as a solution to the
 crisis.
 
3. Khrushchev didn't expect the US to detect his missile
 
deployment.
 
4. US leaders wrongly assumed Khrushchev ordered the Oct. 27
 
U2 shootdown.
 
5. US leaders underestimated Soviet and Cuban military
 
capabilities in Cuba.
 a. The US thought the Soviets had 8,000-10,000 troops in
 
Cuba. In fact the Soviets had 43,000 troops. Cuba had
 another 270,000 well-trained troops. The US planned to
 invade with only 140,000 troops. This war won't end
 well for the USA!
 
b. More interestingly, the US was unaware that the Soviets
 
had 98 tactical warheads and means to deliver them in
 
Cuba. Wow!
 
6. US leaders were unaware:
 
&gt; 	That the four Soviet Foxtrot submarines near Cuba each
 
carried one nuclear-armed torpedo; and were perhaps
 
authorized to use it in event they were attacked.
 
&gt;	 That the commanders of these subs were unaware of the
 
US scheme to signal their subs with practice depth
 charge explosions. Hence the US used the depth
 charges.
 
7. Castro was unaware of US nuclear superiority. 	Also,
 
Castro thought that the US was bent on invading Cuba. And
 ... he urged the Soviet Union to answer a US invasion, if
 
it occurred, with nuclear strikes on the US!
 
8. JFK was unaware of symmetry of Soviet and US missile
 
deployments. JFK: "It's just as if we suddenly began to
 
put a major number of MRBMs in Turkey. Now that'd be
 goddam dangerous, I would think." McGeorge Bundy and
 Alexis Johnson then explain "Well, we did, Mr. President."
 
9. On October 28 Khrushchev thought JFK intended to announce
 
the start of war at 5:00 p.m. that day. Not so.
 
B. How tight was central control on military operations? 	Not
 
very!
 1. The Oct. 27 Soviet shootdown of the US U2 was unauthorized
 
by Moscow.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 
THE CUBAN MISSILE CRISIS, OCTOBER 16-28 1962
 
I. 	BACKGROUND
 
The Cuban Missile Crisis of October 1962 brought the world close
 
to nuclear war. Some of President John F. Kennedy's (JFK's)
 advisers recommended that the US launch a surprise air attack on
 Cuban and invade Cuba. This would have led to direct combat
 between US forces and Soviet forces. Both sides were armed with
 tactical nuclear weapons. Other advisers counselled Kennedy to
 launch preventive general nuclear war against the USSR. During
 the crisis Cuban dictator Fidel Castro urged the Soviet leaders
 to launch nuclear war against the US if the US invaded Cuba. 
The world held its breath! What caused this crisis? How close
 did we come to war? Why did the crisis end peacefully?
 A. The US had nuclear superiority over the USSR in 1962. 
Specifically, the US had a clear second-strike countervalue
 capability (the capacity to inflict unacceptable damage on
 Soviet society after absorbing an all-out Soviet surprise
 counterforce attack) and perhaps also had a first-strike
 
counterforce capability (the capacity to strike first with
 enough force to leave the Soviets unable to inflict
 
unacceptable damage in retaliation). The Soviets had a total
 of 42 nuclear-armed ICBMs, of which 36 could be launched on
 15 minute warning; of these, 26 were deployed in hardened
 silos.
1 How many could survive US attack and fly to the
 
US???
 &gt; During 1955-1960 US Air Force leaders argued that the US
 
faced a "bomber gap," and then a "missile gap," in which
 the Soviets had or were getting a first-strike capability
 over the US. US photo-reconnaissance satellites verified
 the reverse--that the US had nuclear superiority--in 1960. 
US knowledge of its superiority was revealed to the public
 and the Soviets in a press briefing by Roswell Gilpatrick
 on October 21, 1961. Until then Soviet leaders probably
 thought the US (1) believed Soviet forces were vastly
 larger than they were; and (2) didn't know where Soviet
 forces were, hence couldn't target them. The Gilpatrick
 briefing likely came as a great shock to Soviet leaders.
 
B. The US plotted Castro's downfall, 1959-1962. 	US actions: a
 
"covert" invasion of Cuba at the Bay of Pigs, 1961; Operation
 Mongoose and its planned Cuban uprising, 1961ff; and the
 Phibriglex exercise, 1962, to liberate a Caribbean island
 from the dictator "Ortsac." US overthrow efforts were inept
 but serious in intent. They convinced Castro that a US
 invasion was inevitable.
 
1
 Michael Dobbs, One Minute to Midnight (Vintage, 2007):
 
190.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
use force unless matters were resolved in a day or two. What
 
drove JFK's sense of urgency?
 Would a longer US blockade of Cuba have succeeded in
 persuading the Soviets to remove their missiles from Cuba?
 
-- What US response would have occurred had the Soviets not
 
accepted Kennedy's terms on Oct. 28? (Would Kennedy have
 implemented the Cordier plan? Gone to war?)
 
-- What were Soviet and American plans for war if the war
 
erupted?
 
IX. WHAT CAUSED THE CRISIS? WHY WAS WAR AVOIDED?
 
A. Causes: US belligerence toward Cuba? 	US nuclear superiority? 
Soviet recklessness? Lack of clear "rules of the game"? US
 domestic politics?
 &gt; Re: US belligerence toward Cuba: perhaps the US could have
 
avoided the crisis by leaving Castro's regime alone.
 
&gt; Re: US superiority: there are some capabilities one does
 
not want to have.
 
&gt; Re: US domestic politics:
 
&gt; Soviet missiles in Cuba did not give the USSR a first-
strike capability; and added little to Soviet second-
strike capability.
 
&gt; The Soviets could and did greatly expand their second-
strike capability during the next 12 months by deploying
 ICBMs in the USSR. So any second-strike benefit to the
 USSR would be brief; and any harm to the US would be
 delayed only a year.
 
&gt; JFK said he warned the Soviets against deploying any
 
missiles in Cuba on Sept. 4 and 13 because the Soviets
 had told him they wouldn't deploy any. He would have set
 a higher ceiling had he thought the Soviets were
 deploying.
 
&gt; Implication: the crisis was caused by JFK's public
 
warnings of Sept. 4 and 13, and the domestic political
 risk these warnings created for JFK. The real military
 stakes were trivial.
 &gt; Further implication: did nuclear war almost happen to
 
save JFK's political skin?
 
B. Did JFK and Khrushchev bring the world close to nuclear war
 
over trivial issues?
 &gt; Soviet missiles in Cuba were not militarily very important. 
The Soviets achieved a second-strike countervalue
 capability using forces based in the USSR about 18 months
 after the missile crisis (in spring 1964). Was Khrushchev
 wise to take huge risks just to try to advance this event
 by a few months? Was JFK wise to risk war in response?
 
&gt; US missiles in Turkey were not militarily important.  	 Yet
 
both JFK and Khrushchev were sticky about them.
 
C. Why war was avoided: Lack of Soviet military options? 	JFK's
 
hidden concessions?
 
D. The effects of US nuclear superiority were starkly different
 
in the early 1950s (the Soviets stood down in response) and</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
chose option #2, Quarantine.
 
US officials didn't come up with the Quarantine idea until
 Oct. 19, three days into the crisis. Governments think
 slowly!
 
D. JFK's counter-fait accompli: the Quarantine announcement of
 
Oct. 22.
 
IV. 	SCARY EVENTS AT SEA
 
The Soviets deployed four Foxtrot-class submarines near Cuba
 during the crisis. Unknown to the US, each sub carried one
 nuclear-armed torpedo. Each was perhaps authorized to use it in
 event they were attacked.
 The US devised a system to signal these subs to surface by
 
exploding practice depth-charges near the sub, and transmitted
 this scheme to Moscow during the crisis. Moscow never forwarded
 this news to the submarine commanders. Hence they interpreted
 depth-charge explosions not as signals but as an attack meant to
 sink them. One sub commander considered nuking a US destroyer
 
in response.
2
 
V. THE SETTLEMENT
 
A. Khrushchev sent JFK a letter on Friday Oct. 26 offering to
 
remove Soviet missiles from Cuba in exchange for a US no-
invasion pledge regarding Cuba. The next day he sent a
 second letter adding a demand: the US must also remove its
 missiles from Turkey. Oh dear!
 
B. JFK's Oct. 27 answer: He ignored the second letter and
 
publicly accepted Khrushchev's first offer--a Soviet
 withdrawal of its missiles from Cuba in exchange for a US
 pledge not to invade Cuba. He spiced this acceptance with a
 private ultimatum (24 hours to agree or the US would attack
 the missiles) and sweetened it with a secret concession
 (withdrawal of US missiles from Turkey within six months). 
Khrushchev quickly accepted Kennedy's offer on Oct. 28.
 Question: Was the spice in Kennedy's letter smart? The
 
sweetener?
 
VI. HINGES OF THE CRISIS
 
A. US officials feared war at three points:
 
-- On October 16-18--at the start of the crisis--when US
 
officials considered launching war.
 
-- On October 24, when the U.S. thought Soviet ships were
 
approaching the line of US ships blockading Cuba.
 
-- On October 27, when Khrushchev seemed to stiffen his
 
terms, a Soviet missile shot down a US U-2 over Cuba, and
 Castro's forces began firing on US low-level recon planes.
 
B. Two hawk vs. dove disputes occurred in the US government:
 
2
 Svetlana V. Savranskaya, "New Sources on the Role of
 
Soviet Submarines in the Cuban Missile Crisis," Journal of
 Strategic Studies, 28:2: 233-59 at 234-35, 249-51.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
the early 1960s (the Soviets secretly moved missiles to Cuba,
 
nearly provoked war).
 &gt; Competing explanations:
 
-- Khrushchev was more of a risk-taker than Stalin.
 -- Khrushchev had an aggressive option--moving missiles to
 
Cuba--that Stalin didn't have. What if Stalin had had
 such an option?
 
&gt; Implication: military superiority can be good or bad.
 
X. CRISIS HISTORY WRITING: Perhaps the historical record
 
understates the prevalence and effectiveness of conciliation as a
 tool of statecraft. Leaders tout their threats and conceal their
 concessions, as JFK did. Hence history features successful acts of
 belligerence while successful conciliations are downplayed. See
 Smith, "Peace Presidents," assigned.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>U.S. National Security Policy, 1945&#8211;present</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_natonlsecurity/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15&#8211;16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
Which nuclear capabilities would be intolerable for the US in
 
the hands of which other states? Specifically:
 1. Which capabilities must the U.S. prevent other states from
 
gaining?
 &gt; A "latent" bomb--the capacity to build a bomb in a few
 
months or years? (Example: Iran today, which has a latent
 bomb 1 year from completion.)
 
&gt; One or a few bombs that are unprotected from attack, and
 
could therefore be eliminated by a US first strike; and/or
 that lack a delivery system required to detonate them in
 the US or another foreign country? (Example: North Korea
 today; the USSR 1949-50).
 
&gt; A secure nuclear force that could survive a US first
 
strike and inflict unacceptable damage against the US in
 retaliation? (Example: the USSR 1965-89.)
 
&gt; A force that could destroy U.S. forces in a first strike?
 
2. Which states must be prevented from gaining these
 
capabilities?
 &gt; Britain/France? Israel? India? China? Russia?
 &gt; "Rogue states" that aggress against neighbors, oppose US
 
foreign policy, seek weapons of mass destruction (WMD),
 e.g., North Korea or Iran? Quasi-rogues like Pakistan? 
Saddam's Iraq before 2003?
 
Some analysts say the key issue is: "Is the regime
 deterrable?" Meaning, are they (1) Prone to misperceive
 others' reactions to their actions? (2) Sensitive to costs? 
(3) Do they value conquest as highly as their own survival? 
If so, big trouble!
 
3. How to prevent unacceptable actors from gaining unacceptable
 
capabilities?
 
IV. THE NUCLEAR REVOLUTION AND AMERICAN SECURITY
 
Three questions: (1) What have been the effects of the nuclear
 revolution on world politics and U.S. interests? (2) What
 strategy should the U.S. adopt for the use of its nuclear
 forces, especially toward other current and future nuclear
 powers? (3) How should the US address the danger of nuclear
 proliferation?
 A. The evolution of the U.S. nuclear arsenal (see last page).
 B. The effects of the nuclear revolution: good or bad?
 
offensive or defensive? Nuclear weapons have four cascading
 effects:
 1.	 Hydrogen bombs are more powerful by six (yes, six)
 
orders of magnitude compared to the TNT explosives used
 in World War II. Atomic bombs = x 1,000 increase on
 TNT; hydrogen bombs = x 1,000 increase on atomic bombs.
 
2.	 Due to '1'--the destructiveness of nuclear weapons--the
 
"cost exchange ratio" vastly favors defenders (better
 termed "retaliators") over attackers seeking to disarm
 them. Nuclear weapons pack tremendous explosive power
 in small, cheap, light devices that are easy to hide,
 protect, and deliver. Hence destroying them is very</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
hard, protecting and delivering them very easy. 
3.	 Due to '2'--the cost-exchange ratio--a relationship of
 
MAD ("Mutual Assured Destruction") tends to develop
 
between major powers. Both can destroy the other's
 society even after absorbing an all-out counterforce
 attack by the other.
 &gt; The U.S.-Soviet relationship reached deep MAD in the
 
mid-1960s.
 
&gt; The US-China and US-Russia relationships may not be at
 
MAD today. This is because those states have made
 little effort to create secure arsenals. If they
 tried, they could do it.
 
&gt; The US-North Korea relationship is not at MAD.  	 A US
 
nuclear strike could very likely take out North
 Korea's nuclear force, precluding NK retaliation.
 
4.	 "Defense-dominance." Some argue that MAD strengthens
 
defender-states and weakens aggressor-states. Are they
 right?
 
C. Alternate nuclear doctrines: Countervalue vs. Counterforce
 
strategies. Nuclear weapons present states with two basic
 nuclear doctrines toward other nuclear states: counterforce
 and countervalue.
 &gt;&gt; Countervalue: the enemy society is targeted. Political
 aims are achieved by threatening to punish the adversary
 by destroying its population and industry.
 
&gt;&gt; Counterforce: the enemy nuclear forces are targeted. 
Political aims are achieved by threatening to disarm the
 adversary--to remove its capacity to inflict punishment
 on oneself.
 Counterforce forces include forces that could
 
preempt the others' nuclear force (e.g., accurate
 intercontinental missiles) and defenses that could
 destroy the other's retaliating weapons (e.g., national
 ballistic missile defenses).
 
Since forces can be used first or second, we have a crude
 universe of four possible nuclear capabilities:
 1.	 First-strike countervalue capability: the capacity to
 
launch a first strike that inflicts unacceptable damage
 on the adversary's society.
 This capability is very easy to build, for reasons
 
noted above in Section IV B1-2, but is quite useless.
 
2.	 Second-strike countervalue capability: the capacity to
 
absorb an all-out counterforce first strike and inflict
 unacceptable damage on the adversary's society in
 retaliation.
 This capability is easy to build, for reasons noted
 
above in Section IV B1-3.
 
3.	 First-strike counterforce: the capacity to launch a
 
first strike that removes the adversary's capacity to
 inflict unacceptable damage on oneself in retaliation.
 This capability is very hard or impossible to build,
 
for reasons noted above in Section IV B1-3.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>U.S. NATIONAL SECURITY &amp; NUCLEAR POLICY, 1945-PRESENT
 
I.	 HOW SHOULD THE UNITED STATES SET MILITARY REQUIREMENTS?
 
By answering five questions in sequence: (1) What are U.S.
 
national interests? (2) What threats to these interests can we
 discern? (3) What strategies would best address these threats? 
(4) What missions must the US military and/or other government
 agencies perform to support these strategies? (5) What forces
 or other assets are required to perform these missions? (A
 framework by Steven E. Miller.)
 
II. FOUR KEY NATIONAL SECURITY POLICY ISSUES TODAY
 
What strategy should the U.S. adopt to address the WMD terror
 
threat (al-Qaeda or ISIS with an a-bomb)? What capabilities
 does this strategy require? What changes are required to
 create these capabilities? For example: shift resources from
 the Army, Navy and Air Force to intelligence (CIA and FBI)? 
To nation building? To "public diplomacy" (shaping foreign
 opinion)? To locking down loose nukes around the world?
 
How should the U.S. address nuclear proliferation? By
 
preventive war? By applying economic sanctions? By giving
 security guarantees or economic bribes to potential
 proliferators? Pursue world disarmament? (On disarmament see
 assigned article by Carla Robbins, "Thinking the
 Unthinkable.")
 &gt; When should the U.S. wage preventive war against emerging
 
nuclear powers? Against which states? What forces does
 this require? The 2002 U.S. National Security Strategy
 framed a doctrine of preventive war (see Lieber and Lieber,
 assigned earlier). Is this a good strategy?
 
How should the US respond to China's rise? By pursuing
 
containment? Cooperation?
 
Should the U.S. try to maintain a strategic nuclear first-
strike counterforce capability against China and Russia? 
Toward this, should the U.S. develop a national missile
 defense (NMD) system?
 
How should the U.S. address the possibility that emerging
 
technologies will spread WMD-scope destructive powers to nondeterrable non-state actors (e.g., terrorists or psychopaths)?
 &gt; What effects would follow if the Silex laser-enrichment
 
process succeeds?
 
&gt; ... or the power to make ultra-lethal new bioweapons
 
proliferates?
 
Can we survive a world of "a nuke in every garage," or "a
 bioweapons lab in every garage"? What can be done to avert
 it? See readings assigned for this week by Martin Rees, Henry
 Kelly, Antonio Regalado and William Broad.
 
III. SPECIFIC QUESTIONS ON WMD POLICY</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
leave of their senses? Inquiring minds want to know.
 
VII. SOVIET MILITARY DOCTRINE, 1947-1989: OFFENSE AND PREEMPTION. 
(PRETTY CRAZY! WHY ADOPTED?)
 
VIII. THE U.S. DEFENSE DEBATE, 1947-1989
 
A. America's prime problem: defending Western Europe from
 
Soviet conquest.
 
B. The "how to defend Europe" debate, 1947-1989: 7 contending
 
strategies:
 
1.	 Strategic nuclear countervalue: threaten to punish
 
Soviets by blasting their cities if they invade Western
 Europe.
 
2.	 Strategic nuclear counterforce: threaten to disarm &amp;
 
conquer Soviets if they invade. (Adopted by Eisenhower,
 1953-61, under doctrine of "Massive Retaliation".)
 
3.	 Theater nuclear denial: threaten to incinerate invading
 
Soviet armies. (Adopted briefly in late 1950s.)
 
4.	 Conventional denial: thwart invading Soviet armies with
 
conventional forces. (Preferred by US, 1960s-1970s, but
 vetoed by Germany.)
 
5.	 Conventional offense: seize Soviet territory if they
 
invade.
 
6.	 German nuclear deterrent: let Germans threaten to blast
 
Soviet cities. (Eisenhower favored, JFK opposed.)
 
7.	 Tripwire strategy: spring-load a European war to make it
 
uncontrollable. US goal: Conventional war ---&gt; theater
 nuclear war ---&gt; general thermonuclear war. (Actual
 US/NATO declaratory strategy, 1967-1989.)
 
C. The Third World intervention debate (The "how to contain"
 
debate recast).
 
IX. NONPROLIFERATION/COUNTERPROLIFERATION: NINE STRATEGIES
 
A. Technology denial. 	Make it hard for the proliferator to
 
acquire needed technology for nuke-making.
 
B. Economic sanctions: threaten or impose them.
 C. Bribery: bribe the potential proliferator to eschew nukes. 
(See Robert Reardon's research on this.)
 
D. Sabotage: Stuxnet their equipment, kill their scientists.
 E. Create legal framework to assign civil liability for lost
 
nukes to the states that lose them. This threatens
 potential proliferators with vast lawsuits if they ever lose
 control of a nuke. This will make their business community
 question whether going nuke is a good idea.
 
F. Give security guarantees to potential proliferators (as the
 
US has given guarantees to Taiwan, South Korea, Germany,
 Japan, and others).
 
G. Conventional preventive war.
 
1. Focused only on destroying proliferators nuclear
 
infrastructure, e.g., Israel's Osiraq raid.
 
2. Focused on regime change in the proliferator state.
 
H. Nuclear preventive war.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
4.	 Second-strike counterforce capability: the capacity to
 
absorb an all-out counterforce first strike and mount a
 counterforce counterattack that leaves the attacker's
 forces unable to inflict unacceptable further damage on
 one's own society.
 This capability is even harder to build than a
 
first-strike counterforce capability.
 
These four capabilities can be displayed in a 2x2 table:
 Striking what?
 Values (cities) Forces 
+))))))))))))))))0))))))))))))))))), 
*#1 First *#3 First * 
* Strike * Strike *
 First * Countervalue * Counterforce *
 Striking * Capability * Capability *
 When? 	 /))))))))))))))))3)))))))))))))))))1 *
#2 Second *#4 Second *
 Second * Strike * Strike * 
*	 Countervalue * Counterforce * 
*	 Capability * Capability * 
.))))))))))))))))2)))))))))))))))))-
Cold War-era debates over US nuclear doctrine focused
 
on whether the US should be content with capability #2 (a
 
second strike countervalue capability, or SSCVC) against the
 Soviet Union (SU), or should also strive for #3 (a first
 strike counterforce capability, or FSCFC). Advocates of
 pursuing an FSCFC said that it was achievable, and would
 deter the SU more than it provoked the SU. Opponents of
 pursuing an FSCFC said it was unachievable; and is
 inherently offensive, hence would provoke the SU to worse
 behavior.
 Current debates over US nuclear doctrine focus on
 
whether the US should be content with a second strike
 countervalue capability against China and Russia, or should
 also work to maintain a first strike counterforce
 capability.
 Debates over US foreign policy also focus on whether
 
the US should allow Iran, North Korea, and other states to
 gain capability #1, a first strike countervalue capability.
 A fifth capability can also be distinguished: a "latent
 
bomb," meaning, the capability to make a bomb in the near
 future. Debates also focus on whether the U.S. should allow
 this latent capability in bad hands.
 
D. COUNTERVALUE vs. COUNTERFORCE STRATEGIC NUCLEAR WEAPONS:
 
WHAT'S THE DIFFERENCE?
 
&gt; Second-strike countervalue nuclear forces can survive a
 
surprise attack and retaliate against the attacker's cities
 or other "value" targets.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
probably impossible to devise.
 
C. Biological weapons can more easily be used anonymously.
 
D. Defenses are more feasible against bio attack than against
 
nuclear attack--but the attacker still has a large
 advantage.
 
E. Contagious bioweapons can spread unpredictably, harming the
 
user's friends/family/army/society. Hence their use can be
 irrational.
 
As a result of factors 'A' 'B' and 'C' some argue that
 bioweapons are weapons from hell as perhaps their use cannot be
 deterred and cannot be defeated, while their power will only
 grow. If so, we face big trouble ahead.
 In Kurt Vonnegut's 1963 novel Cat's Cradle a mad scientist
 
invents a new crystalline form of water, "ice nine," that
 solidifies at 90 degrees fahrenheit. Its release ends life on
 earth by freezing the oceans. Is the biotechnology revolution
 handing us a biotechnical ice nine--a vastly destructive
 technology for which we are socially, politically and morally
 unready? Will it doom us?
1
 In 2016 Director of National Intelligence Thomas Clapper
 
warned specifically that a powerful new gene-editing tool,
 CRISPR, might someday be used by bad actors to make ultra-
lethal ultra-contagious new pathogens. Hence, said Clapper,
 CRISPR poses a threat to US national security. See assigned
 reading by Antonio Regalado.
 Martin Rees, in Our Final Hour (assigned), argues more
 
generally that vast destructive powers are spreading to
 individual terrorists or psychopaths. The answer must be the
 end of human privacy, to ensure that no lunatic can secretly
 make a superkiller bug in his or her basement.
 What can we do to avert this threat? Can we slow or channel
 
the process of scientific discovery away from inventing these
 horrors? For example, should biologists agree to regulations
 that limit their research, to avoid inventing superkilling
 agents? Or must curiosity inexorably kill the cat (us)? Or
 does Rees overstate this danger?
 Is bioscience bringing this nightmare alive?
 
VI. A SECOND NUCLEAR REVOLUTION? WILL THE POWER TO MAKE NUCLEAR
 
WEAPONS SPREAD TO CRAZY STATES AND TERRORISTS?
 
General Electric and Hitachi have reportedly developed a new
 means to enrich uranium. Enriching uranium is the key step in
 making an atomic bomb. The GE/Hitachi Silex process allows
 enrichment in a small, low-cost facility. This will put atomic
 bombs in close reach of crazy states and terrorists. Is Rees's
 nightmare coming true? Have the people at GE and Hitachi taken
 
1
 Herman Kahn once likewise warned that if a $10 "Doomsday
 
Machine" is ever devised civilization is doomed because someone
 will eventually use such a cheap machine, regardless of
 countermeasures. Oh dear.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>--------------------------------8 
I. Threaten to hold at risk the potential proliferator's
 
nuclear forces by maintaining a first-strike counterforce
 
capability, in order to devalue the proliferator's potential
 nuclear force. "You will never have a meaningful, useable
 nuclear capability, as we will maintain the capacity to
 disarm you."
 
ADDENDUM #1: US Nuclear Weapons Inventory:
 
1945: 2
 
1946: 9 
1947: 13 
1948: 50 
1950: At least 292 
1953: 1500 
1959: 6000 
1991: 18000
 Sources for 1945-1950: David Alan Rosenberg, "U.S. Nuclear
 Stockpile, 1945 to 1950," Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, May
 1982, pp. 25-30. Sources for 1953-1959: Stephen Ambrose,
 Eisenhower, Vol. 2, p. 494. Source for 1991: Kurt Campbell,
 Ashton Carter, Steven Miller &amp; Charles Zraket, Soviet Nuclear
 Fission, p. 22.
 
ADDENDUM #2: Soviet Nuclear Weapons Inventory:
 First a-bomb: 1949; first fusion device (proto-H-bomb): 1953;
 
first H-bomb: 1955; 27,000 nuclear weapons in the Soviet
 inventory in 1991. Source for 1953 and 1955: John Holdren, "The
 Dynamics of the Nuclear Arms Race," in Avner Cohen and Steven
 Lee, Nuclear Weapons and the Future of Humanity: 45. Source for
 1991 inventory: Campbell, Carter, Miller &amp; Zraket, Soviet Nuclear
 Fission: 15.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
 An example of a pure second-strike countervalue weapon
 
in the 1960s-1980s era: the U.S. Polaris ballistic missile
 
submarine fleet. Polaris subs could hide from Soviet attack
 in the vast ocean and their missiles could strike Soviet
 cities, but these missiles lacked the accuracy to destroy
 Soviet hardened nuclear forces.
 
&gt; First-strike counterforce nuclear forces can be used to
 
destroy an opponent's nuclear forces in a first strike.
 An example of a pure first-strike counterforce weapon
 
is a highly accurate intercontinental ballistic missile
 (ICBM) based in a vulnerable soft silo. It could be used to
 launch a surprise attack on another state's ICBMs or command
 centers, but it could not survive an attack to retaliate
 against the attacker's cities.
 Other forces that contribute to a first-strike
 
counterforce capability include "killer" submarines designed
 to locate and sink other submarines, which can be used to
 destroy ballistic missile submarines (if the opponent has
 them); and area ballistic missile defenses (often called
 "national missile defense," or "NMD") deployed to protect
 cities. The role of NMD in a first strike would be to knock
 down warheads missed by the first strike that are
 retaliating against the attacker's cities. In this role NMD
 is the defensive half of a first strike system and thus is
 essentially offensive despite its defensive appearance.
 Many weapons have both second strike countervalue and
 
first strike counterforce characteristics--they contribute
 to both second-strike countervalue and first-strike
 counterforce capabilities.
 
E. THREE DANGERS THAT OTHER STATES' NUCLEAR FORCES COULD POSE
 
Why are other states' nuclear forces scary?
 1.	 A nuclear-armed state might use its weapons.
 2.	 A nuclear-armed state might be emboldened to adopt more
 
aggressive policies, believing that its nuclear weapons
 protected it from retaliation.
 
3.	 A nuclear-armed state might by incompetence or
 
inadvertence allow its nuclear weapons to be stolen,
 bought or transferred to bad actors, especially
 terrorists.
 
V. THE BIOLOGICAL WEAPONS REVOLUTION AND AMERICAN NATIONAL
 SECURITY
 
Bioweapons differ from nuclear weapons in five prime regards:
 A. Biological weapons are cheap to make and can be made or
 
purchased by non-state actors--that is, by terrorists.
 &gt; Moreover, bioweapons may grow much more lethal in the
 
future as new super-pathogens are engineered by scientists
 exploiting new genetic engineering techniques.
 
B. Biological weapons programs have no clear signature that
 
distinguishes them from peaceful biological research. As a
 result an arms control regime that bans bioweapons is</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>U.S. Foreign Economic Policy, 1945&#8211;present</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_usforineconpol/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
larger ways. So let's not follow them on their path of
 
folly.
 
-- Another problem: governments are inept at identifying
 
such industries even if they do exist.
 
D. Externalities arguments: "We should subsidize and protect
 
industries (e.g., high-technology industries) that produce
 spinoffs (e.g., high technologies) that benefit the rest of
 the economy." But can governments correctly identify these
 industries?
 
E. Coercing other governments to change policies.
 
1. Some advocate protection to coerce others to open their
 
markets. "We should restrict others' imports until they
 ease their restrictions on US imports."
 &gt; But will retaliation start a trade war, leaving all
 
worse off? In other words, can we tell whether
 retaliation will cause "deterrence" or a "spiral"?
 
2. Some advocate protection to coerce others into other
 
trade-related policy changes, e.g., to adopt U.S. labor
 standards, or environmental protection standards. But
 critics say: "These demands are just excuses to protect
 relatively inefficient U.S. industries from
 international competition."
 
3. Many advocate trade sanctions--limits on imports and
 
exports--to coerce others to align non-trade-related
 policies (e.g., security policies or human rights
 policies) with U.S. wishes.
 a. Unilateral economic sanctions never work, but
 
sanctions can be an effective tool of persuasion when
 pursued multilaterally. Threat of multilateral
 sanctions succeed as often as threat of force. See
 e.g., US-led sanctions against Iran, 2013-15.
 
b. "Smart" sanctions--actions aimed at the assets and
 
lifestyle of governing elites, such as freezing their
 foreign accounts--are often wiser than trade
 sanctions, because trade sanctions injure whole
 populations while smart sanctions target only the
 decision makers. But the banking community dislikes
 smart sanctions, so often trade sanctions are
 unwisely pursued instead.
 
F. National security: "Free trade injures national security."
 
1. "If our adversary gains more from trade than we do we
 
shouldn't trade with them, because they may convert
 their gains into weapons and subjugate us." This is the
 main reason why military adversaries seldom trade with
 each other, and a key argument against US trade with
 China.
 
2. "We must maintain critical war industries that feed our
 
military machine, hence we must protect them from
 foreign competition if they could not survive the
 competition of world markets in peacetime." 60 years
 ago some argued for protecting the U.S. steel industry
 on these grounds.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>U.S. FOREIGN ECONOMIC POLICY:
 
TRADE, INVESTMENT, AND AID ISSUES AND POLICIES
 
I. TRADE THEORY AND BACKGROUND
 
A. Classical Liberalism argues: more freedom of all kinds is
 
better. People and states have large common interests. 
These are best realized by fostering political, economic,
 and religious freedom. We should replace absolute monarchy
 with democracy; religious absolutism with freedom of
 religion; and economic controls with free markets and free
 trade.
 
B. Free Trade versus Mercantilism:
 
1. Free trade ("liberal") doctrine holds that a state's
 
prosperity is maximized by the unfettered exchange of
 
goods and services with other states. This is achieved
 by minimizing restrictions on trade.
 
2. Mercantile doctrine holds that a state's prosperity is
 
maximized by achieving a trade surplus--by exporting
 more than it imports. This is achieved by state
 
subsidies to exporting industries, and by state
 restrictions on imports, such as tariffs, import quotas,
 and import-impeding regulation of imported products. 
Motives: to accumulate specie (1700s); and/or to end
 recessions/limit unemployment (recent times).
 
C. The logic of free trade rests on David Ricardo's theory of
 
comparative advantage (1817): "Utopia is far more efficient
 
than Flatland at making cheese, and moderately more
 
efficient at making wine. Utopia and Flatland both prosper
 by trading Utopia's cheese for Flatland's wine, even though
 Utopia now imports wine from a country that makes it less
 efficiently that Utopia, because trade lets Utopians
 specialize in what they do best." A social science theory
 of great importance!
 
D. A short history of trade: Restrictions on trade have fallen
 
since the late 1700s, and especially since 1945, as
 "liberal" ideas won the day. The US led the movement to
 free trade during 1945-today.
 But the U.S. still restricts imports of some products,
 
especially those produced by fading U.S. "sunset"
 industries--agriculture and textiles/apparel. Agriculture
 and textiles are the "sunrise" industries for the world's
 poorest countries so these U.S. restrictions are a harsh
 blow to the world's poor.
 
E. 2-way vs. 1-way trade. 	Ricardo noted the benefits of 2-way
 
trade. Many in the U.S. today implicitly prefer 1-way
 (export-only) trade, which is a form of mercantilism.
 
F. Is a US trade deficit good or bad? 	Neo-mercantilists
 
believe it bad. Others argue that it represents a net
 transfer of wealth to America, hence is good. Americans</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
wind up with neat stuff--cars and electronics from Japan
 
and China--while Japan and China get only paper promises
 (your money). We get the benefits of trade without doing
 any work! What's wrong with that?
 
II. NINE PROTECTIONIST ARGUMENTS
 
A. "Save US jobs": "We must exclude imports to save jobs and
 
industries threatened by foreign competition!" This
 argument is advanced by industries too inefficient to
 compete on equal terms against foreign imports. But others
 argue:
 -- We can save jobs and industries by using monetary policy
 
(having the Federal Reserve Bank lower interest rates)
 or fiscal policy (moving to deficit spending) to
 regulate the business cycle and pep up the economy when
 it slows. This is how the US has prevented another
 depression since 1941 and moderated the Great Recession
 of 2007-present.
 
-- We can subsidize the retraining of workers in industries
 
that can't beat the foreign competition, instead of
 indirectly subsidizing the industries themselves through
 trade restrictions.
 
-- Other countries may retaliate by restricting their US
 
imports, causing a spiral of protectionism that closes
 down world trade and leaves all worse off. The collapse
 of world trade after Congress passed the Smoot-Hawley
 tariff (1930) illustrates.
 
When the U.S. has low unemployment we rarely hear the jobs
 argument. When unemployment is high we hear it more
 loudly.
 
B. Infant industry arguments (Adam Smith, Alexander Hamilton,
 
Friedrich List): "Infant industries merit protection while
 they develop the economies of scale and expertise they need
 to face international competition." Many economists accept
 this argument. But will the infant ever grow up and get
 off the dole? Some fear not.
 
C. Strategic trade argument--an expansion of the "infant
 
industry" argument. It holds: in industries in which firms
 (1) achieve large economies of scale, and (2) "learn by
 doing"--get more efficient as they gain experience--the top
 dog in the industry can dominate the world, destroy
 competitors, and earn monopoly profits.
 -- Implication: states should protect and subsidize such
 
industries.
 
--	 Problem: there are few such industries. Aircraft
 
manufacture may be an example, but there aren't many
 others, if any. This reflects the power of global-
scale market forces. Global markets are especially
 powerful since they are so vast. They are usually too
 strong to override by state policies. Let others
 (Japan) try--they'll be sorry. Their strategic trade
 restrictions damage us in small ways but damage them in</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
G. Economic stratification--"Free trade helps the rich but
 
punishes the poor."
 
1. Impoverishment of unskilled workers in the advanced
 
countries (i.e., the U.S.): "Free trade puts U.S.
 unskilled workers in direct competition with vast pools
 of unskilled workers in the Third World; this drives
 down wages for US unskilled workers; this widens the
 income gaps between U.S. classes." The Stolper-
Samuelson theorem frames this argument. In theory we
 might deal with this problem by subsidizing the wages of
 low-wage workers, or by otherwise compensating low-wage
 workers. But in practice this doesn't happen in the
 U.S. See assigned reading by Dani Rodrik.
 
2. Worldwide "races to the bottom" in social policy: "When
 
goods and services move freely, companies can more
 easily move to the country that gives it the best
 terms--i.e., low taxes, narrow labor rights, the right
 to pollute--and then export their products to their main
 markets. Companies can use this threat to move as a
 lever to compel governments everywhere to restrict labor
 rights and transfer tax burdens from businesses to
 others." A global "race to the bottom" results that
 widens the gulf between rich and poor in all societies.
 
H. Protecting other cultures--"Under free trade the U.S.
 
exports its noxious culture products to the world, enraging
 or corrupting other societies":
 1. Other countries (Canada, France, Islamic states) object
 
to U.S. insistence that they cannot restrict imports of
 U.S.-made TV, film and other entertainment. Their
 argument: "We want our culture, not yours. Your media
 products preach violence, hedonism, and greed. Many are
 pornographic. Such rotten values caused Rome to fall. 
Please keep MTV and such to yourselves. We don't want
 to swim in that sewer." Others answer: "If you don't
 want these products, don't buy them." And the answer
 comes back: "Market forces often cause bad results for
 society. You Americans won't allow free import of
 cocaine, despite the market for them. Why should we
 allow free import of poisons from Hollywood?"
 
2. Some argue that jamming MTV down the throat of
 
traditional cultures fuels angry religious
 fundamentalism around the world. "The U.S. should stop
 exporting its noxious entertainment products for its own
 good."
 
I. Rapid economic churning--the rise and fall of industries-
is harmful. It creates personal insecurity and disrupts
 valuable social institutions--communities (see Edmund Burke
 on their value), neighborhoods, and extended families. 
Outsourcing jobs destroys social fabric. Free trade should
 be limited when it fosters harmfully rapid "creative
 destruction" in the US.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
III. NON-ECONOMIC ARGUMENTS FOR FREE TRADE
 
A. "Free trade causes economic interdependence, which causes
 
peace, so let's promote free trade."
 
B. "Free trade causes prosperity, which causes democracy,
 
which causes many good things including peace, so let's
 
promote free trade."
 
IV. BOLSTERING FREE TRADE: METHODS
 
A. Reciprocity. Restrict imports from countries that restrict
 
U.S. imports.
 
B. Make regional free trade agreements, e.g., the 1993 North
 
American Free Trade Agreement, or "NAFTA", which
 established free trade between Canada, the US, and Mexico.
 
C. Make global free trade agreements, e.g., the General
 
Agreement on Tariff and Trade, or "GATT", established in
 1947, institutionalized and renamed the World Trade
 Organization, or "WTO", in 1995.
 
D. Spread some enlightenment! 	Educate publics on how much
 
they are losing by protecting their economy!
 
V. INVESTMENT ISSUES
 
A. Raising US national rates of savings and investment will
 
spur U.S. economic growth. And if so...
 
B. Should the US government protect multinational corporations
 
in their conflicts with Third World nationalist
 governments? Won't this encourage capital outflow in the
 form of foreign investment? For example, have efforts to
 punish Cuban abuses of U.S. corporations in Cuba (e.g., the
 1990s-era Helms-Burton law) serve U.S. interests?
 
C. Should the US fear foreign investment here? 	Is it scary or
 
good that foreigners own much of America?
 
VI. FOREIGN AID ISSUES
 
A. US foreign aid is small--only $23 billion (one twenty-third
 
the size of the US defense budget, ~1 percent of total US
 federal budget). This is chump change.
 
B. What can aid achieve?
 
1. Can rich states pull poor states from poverty by giving
 
aid? The evidence is mixed. The counter-argument: "aid
 distorts market forces."
 
2. Is aid an effective foreign policy tool? 	Yes. Bribery
by-"foreign aid" often works! Aid as baksheesh.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Current Issues and Crises; Assessment of Bush 43 and Obama Administration&#8217;s Foreign Policies; The Future of American Foreign Policy.</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_predictingfutr/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>25&#8211;26</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>PREDICTING THE FUTURE AND PRESCRIBING FOR THE FUTURE:
 
WHAT LOOMS AHEAD? WHAT POLICIES SHOULD THE U.S. ADOPT?
 
I. 	COURSE THEORIES: DID THEY PASS/FLUNK TESTS? WHAT DID THEY
 
EXPLAIN?
 
Which theories survived confrontation with the evidence, and
 which did not? How much history do they explain? What
 evaluative conclusions follow from our answers? (E.g., did
 the U.S. overlook valid theories? Place faith in false ones?)
 A.	 Offense-defense (security dilemma) theory: US foreign
 
policy as a test and a case to explain.
 1.	 Threat variant: the greater the security threat states
 
face, the more aggressive they become.
 
2.	 Opportunity variant: the more easily states can
 
conquer, the more aggressive they become.
 
Does U.S. activism correlate with America's sense of
 insecurity? Of opportunity? Was American policy driven
 by a search for security or a desire to exploit
 opportunity? Were America's adversaries driven by
 security concerns, or tempted by opportunity? Was the
 U.S. in fact insecure? Was it sufficiently aware of
 others' security concerns and their likely reaction to a
 U.S. threat?
 
B.	 Alliance theories:
 
1.	 Balance of threat theory: can it explain the Cold
 
War's structure? What policy implications follow?
 
2.	 Birds of a feather: did they fly together? How often
 
did the common U.S. expectation that birds of a
 feather would fly together prove accurate?
 
C.	 Spiral model vs. Deterrence: which model explains more? 
(Does either explain much?) Possible spirals: the US vs.
 3rd World; USSR vs. Western Europe. Possible deterrence
 failures: US vs. Iraq 1991.
 
D.	 Foreign Policy Elite theories: did elite
 
values/personalities matter?
 
E.	 Marxist theories: do they explain anything? U.S. entry
 
into WWI? Guatemala 1954?
 
II. EVALUATING US FOREIGN POLICIES
 
A.	 U.S. policies toward Europe, 1914-present.
 
1.	 Effects on Europe: did U.S. policies help or harm
 
Europe?
 
2.	 Effects on the U.S.: was involvement in Europe a
 
wasteful adventure or a wise investment?
 
B.	 U.S. policies toward the Third World, 1898-present.
 
1.	 Effects on Third World: was the U.S. an "evil empire"
 
or white knight?
 
2.	 Effects on the U.S.: was Third World involvement a
 
"bungle in the jungle" or a smart stratagem?
 
C.	 Overall quality of U.S. foreign policy making process: how</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
Iran, and a U.S. ground invasion and occupation
 
of Iran.
 
iv.	 At what cost could such wars be won? And could
 
the U.S. manage the occupations of N. Korea or
 Iran?
 
v.	 Is arms control an answer to nuclear
 
proliferation? Is U.S. nuclear restraint or
 disarmament an answer?
 
vi.	 How should the U.S. address the longer-term
 
danger posed by emerging destructive technologies
 (biotechnology, nanotechnology) as described by
 Martin Rees, Our Final Hour. We need answers to
 this question, as these technologies (e.g.,
 CRISPR) are upon us!!
 
B.
 How large is the WMD terror threat? How should it be
 
addressed?
 Specific related dangers:
 --
Al-Qaeda and ISIS, how to address them?
 
-- "Loose nukes": Russian loose nukes; poorly secured
 
nuclear material at research reactors. Al-Qaeda or
 other terrorists may get their WMD from Russia or
 research reactors. Let's finish securing this stuff!
 
-- Unstable Pakistan: Al-Qaeda uses Pakistan as a haven,
 
and the Afghan Taliban uses Pakistan as a base for its
 rampaging in Afghanistan. Some in the Pakistan
 military are religious extremists. And Pakistan has
 
~80-100 nuclear weapons. So terrorists might gain WMD
 there too. So let's stabilize it! But how??? Serious
 
thought is needed. Some analysts think Pakistan is the
 
most dangerous place in the world. But the U.S. has no
 plan to address it.
 
C.
 Peacemaking.
 
1.	 The Israel-Palestinian conflict. Could the U.S.
 
impose peace on Israel and the Palestinians?
 Many experts argue that the continuation of this
 
conflict harms American standing in the Islamic world
 
and strengthens al-Qaeda. Some say the US could
 produce peace if it twisted arms.
 
2.	 The India-Pakistan conflict. This conflict is
 
fuelling Islamic terrorism, radicalism in Pakistan,
 and Pakistani support for the Taliban insurgency in
 Afghanistan. Is it time for the U.S. to push for a
 peace settlement? Could the U.S. achieve one?
 
3.	 Consider a larger move to resolve things in South
 
Asia--a pair of grand bargains:
 a. Push for India-Pakistan peace.
 b. Organize the neutralization of Afghanistan.
 
4.	 Consider moves to resolve civil wars in Iraq, Syria,
 
Yemen, Libya, Ukraine; also South Sudan, Central
 African Republic, Congo. And to avert war in Burundi.
 
D.
 Saving the global commons, especially the environment.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>1
 The Great Law of the Iroquois Confederacy required that:
"In our every deliberation, we must consider the impact of our
 
decisions on the next seven generations."
  4 
Unchecked climate change could do great economic damage
 and displace scores or hundreds of millions of people. 
Can we solve this problem? 
See assigned articles by
 
Frank, Homer-Dixon, and Davenport. 
Climate change can probably be halted by phasing in a
 
steep global carbon tax. Such a tax would spark the
 creation of potent new clean energy technologies that are
 unimagined today. These green technologies would replace
 carbon-based energy by underbidding it in the market. 
This solution would cost rather little--far less than 1
 percent of gross world product per year. See assigned
 article by Joe Romm. Ominously, however, six imposing
 problems make it unlikely that we will halt climate
 change.
 (1) The individual pursuit of self-interest makes the
 
problem worse, not better. The environment is a "commons"
 or "collective good," so individuals are rewarded by
 taking actions that harm it--although the group as a whole
 is injured. Market forces therefore cannot solve this
 
problem.
 (2) Global warming pits a concentrated special
 
interest--the oil and coal industries--against the general
 global public interest, which is harmed by warming. 
Special interests almost always defeat the general
 interest because they are better organized. So Exxon
 Mobil, which opposes action against climate change, has
 more influence than the broad public.
 (3) Solutions to global warming require international
 
cooperation. The world's major states must jointly agree
 to implement a carbon tax. But governments are bad at
 cooperation, and bad at solving problems that require
 cooperation with others.
 (4) Delayed damage--the harm done by emitting
 
greenhouse gasses is delayed, and so is largely hidden
 while the damage is being done. The human race may
 unleash irreversible climatic calamity before the first
 signs of that calamity become clear.
 Solutions to this conundrum requires that the American
 
public know enough science to appreciate the potential
 dangers of dynamics that science has identified (like
 climate change) but are not yet manifest. But the U.S.
 public knows little science and does not listen to
 scientists. See assigned article by Cornelia Dean.
 (5) Western moral and religious traditions (unlike
 
others, e.g. the Iroquois
1) give short shrift to the
 
rights of future generations. Instead our ethics assume</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
closely does it match the rational-legal scientific ideal? 
Is American foreign policy made by strategic wizards or by
 blundering bureaucrats and ignoramus voters?
 
III. PREDICTING THE FUTURE / PRESCRIBING FOR THE FUTURE
 
A.	 How serious are geopolitical threats (that is, the threat
 
of too much power in the hands of bad-acting states)? 
Should the U.S. act to avert them?
 1.	 The rise of China. Should the U.S. try to hamper
 
China's growth? Break China up? Help China grow, on
 the theory that this will promote Chinese democracy? 
On what theoretical or moral assumptions does the
 issue rest?
 
2.	 The rise of other states: Russia? Should the U.S. try
 
to stop their rise?
 
3.	 The rise of nuclear proliferators. Should the U.S.
 
try to stop or even reverse WMD proliferation? If so,
 how?
 i.	 What threat would a nuclear Iran or more-nuclear
 
North Korea pose? What benefits would war to
 disarm them provide?
 a. Will N. Korea or Iran hand WMD to terrorists?
 b. Will N. Korea or Iran aggress against
 
neighbors, believing that their nuclear
 umbrellas protect them from countermeasures?
 
ii.	 What tactics are most likely to end the North
 
Korean and Iranian nuclear programs?
 a. Coercing them into dropping their nuclear
 
programs by economic sanctions?
 
b. Preventing them from exporting their nuclear
 
weapons by blockade?
 
c. Somehow overthrowing their regimes by economic
 
pressure and/or covert action?
 
d. Weaning them from their nuclear programs by
 
positive inducements--trade agreements or
 security guarantees?
 
e. Or is war necessary? Or might even war be
 
futile? Counterproductive?
 
Regarding Iran, the George W. Bush administration
 put all its chips on regime change. This didn't
 work, as Iran's regime survived. The Obama
 administration then used economic sanctions
 during 2010-15 to coerce Iran to cut a deal, and
 Iran to agree a deal in 2015. The Trump
 administration now seems to be moving to abrogate
 the deal. Good idea?
 
iii. Would an effort to remove Iranian or North Korean
 
WMD by force succeed? Would it deter or dissuade
 proliferation by other WMD-seekers? Or might it
 frighten these WMD seekers to seek WMD more
 actively?
 Consider both an airpower-only U.S. war on</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
that each generation must solve its own problems. Hence
 
we see little duty to sacrifice to preserve the world for
 future generations. Watch out grandchildren! We live for
 ourselves, not for you!
 (6) The threat posed by climate change has an anodyne
 
appearance that does not resonate with human threat
 responses. No blood or sharp teeth.
 Bottom line: global warming has a clear solution but
 
the human race is probably incapable of implementing that
 solution. Oh dear!
 
E.	 Human rights: what about doing the right thing? "Those
 
who really deserve praise are the people who, while human
 enough to enjoy power, nevertheless pay more attention to
 justice than they are compelled to do by their situation." 
(Thucydides, History of the Peloponnesian War, trans. Rex
 Warner [Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1972], p. 80.)
 
IV. WHAT GRAND STRATEGY SHOULD THE U.S. ADOPT?
 
Consider again the broad options we discussed in September:
 
Isolation
 
Neo-containment Type #1: the U.S. contains China's rise.
 Neo-containment Type #2: the U.S. limits the access of
 
some states (North Korea, Iran) to WMD.
 
Neo-rollback: the USA wages preventive war against rogue
 
states that pursue WMD.
 
Promoting peace:
 
&gt; Selective pacification, or "selective engagement": the
 
U.S. prevents interstate conflict/war in industrial
 
regions.
 
&gt; Global pacification/New World Order: the U.S. prevents
 
interstate conflict/war everywhere.
 
U.S. global empire: the U.S. seeks to shape other states'
 
domestic political and economic order.
 
Concert: the U.S. seeks to cooperate with other major
 
powers, including China, to avert WMD terror and to stem
 climate change.
 
You be the judge.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>World War I and World War II</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_worldwari/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9&#8211;12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Liberal ideas:
 
National self-determination ---&gt; peace.
 
Colonial rivalries ---&gt; war.
 Free trade and economic interdependence among states ---&gt;
 peace.
 Power-balancing and alliance making ---&gt; war.
 Open diplomacy ---&gt; peace. 
Democracy ---&gt; peace.
 
Other ideas:
 
Large armies and navies ---&gt; war.
 
Were these the real causes/lessons of WWI? Today people point
 to out-of-control militaries in Germany, Austria, &amp; Serbia;
 and to hypernationalism. Wilson overlooked this stuff.
 
IX. GENERAL IMPLICATIONS AND LESSONS OF WWI
 
A. Interdependence ---&gt; war? 	(Was the U.S. sucked into WWI by
 
interdependence?)
 
B. War ---&gt; wider war? 	(Does WWI show that wars have a
 
propensity to spread, and to engulf the U.S.?)
 
C. If a member of congress wanted to get the U.S. into a big
 
war, how would they do it? Would they push for small
 involvement, hoping that this would lead to larger
 involvement? See, e.g., proposals that the U.S. establish
 safe zones in Syria today. Some fear this would draw the
 U.S. into Syria's civil war, or into war with Iran or
 Russia.
 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>allow U.S. trade with the other, or halt trade with both.
 
B. Limited U.S. naval war against Germany. 	Convoy U.S.
 
shipping to Britain and France but otherwise leave Germany
 
alone. (Like the US-Iran "tanker war" of the 1980s.)
 
C. Use America's vast economic and military leverage during
 
1914-1917 to force the belligerents to make peace.
 
VI. EVALUATING U.S. ENTRY, 1917: A GOOD IDEA?
 
A. What threats were averted? 	(If Germany had won the war-
then what?)
 
B. What benefits did victory provide? 	(Hitler, Naziism, World
 
War II ... can you spot a problem here?)
 
VII. EXPLAINING U.S. ENTRY: CONTENDING THEORIES
 
A. Three economic explanations:
 
1. Neutral rights, commerce protection--"we must protect
 
our 2-way trade with Britain, to capture the
 efficiencies of the international division of labor."
 What kind of U.S. war does this explanation predict?
 
A limited U.S. war to protect U.S. commerce with
 Britain, with no land war on the continent against
 Germany? 
2. Neutral rights, business cycle variant (export
 
protection)--"we must protect our 1-way exports to
 Britain, to ease U.S. unemployment."
 What kind of U.S. war does this explanation predict? 
A limited U.S. war at sea to protect U.S. commerce with
 Britain? A strategy of prolonged stalemate rather than
 a push for decisive victory? 
3. "Merchants of Death"--protection of munitions makers-
"we must protect/expand our munitions exports to Britain
 to keep U.S. munitions makers and workers prosperous."
 Again, does this explanation predict U.S. pursuit of
 
decisive victory or prolonged stalemate?
 
B. National security/balance-of-power. 	The U.S. fought to
 
contain German military power.
 What does this explanation predict we should find in the
 U.S. archives? In U.S. public rhetoric justifying the war? 
What should be the prospects for German victory in early
 1917? Should the U.S. be seeking a compromise peace in
 1916?
 
C. U.S. mobilization strategy made the U.S. unable to prevent
 
the war and tempted Germany to cut U.S. trade with Britain
 before the U.S. could move forces to Europe.
 What does this explanation predict we should find Germans
 saying about the U.S. in the German archives?
 
D. U.S. misperceptions. 	Wilson didn't foresee a long war, the
 
German sub campaign, or the growth of U.S. dependence on
 exports to allies. 
E. Common U.S./allied democratic culture.
 F. British propaganda, manipulation of U.S. opinion.
 G. Wilson's enormous ego: "I shall lead the world to peace!"
 
VIII. IDEAS THAT GUIDED WILSON AT VERSAILLES: TRUE OR FALSE?
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>THE UNITED STATES AND WORLD WAR I
 
I. QUESTIONS ABOUT THE US AND WORLD WAR I
 
-- Why did the United States enter World War I?
 
-- Could the U.S. have prevented or stopped WWI?  Could it
 
have stayed out of the war? If so, how?
 Note: WWI did vast harm to the world, causing Lenin &amp;
 Stalin, and Hitler &amp; World War II. Ouch!
 
-- Effects of U.S. entry on the U.S.: good or bad?  Effects of
 
U.S. entry on the world: good or bad? Effects of allied
 victory: good or bad?
 
-- Were the ideas of the 1919 Versailles peace settlement wise
 
or foolish? Were they grounded on valid of false factual
 and theoretical assumptions?
 
-- Lessons: what can we learn from this episode?
 
II. BACKGROUND FACTS AND EVENTS, 1895-1914
 
A. The U.S. is not a factor in European politics in 1914.
 
1. The U.S. had vast economic strength but small military
 
forces in 1914.
 
2. The U.S. was not allied with any European power (or any
 
other power). What if the U.S. had forged defensive
 alliances with some European states before 1914?
 
B. The U.S. economy in 1914 was in a deep cyclical recession.
 C. Britain appeased the U.S., 1895-1914 --&gt; U.S.-British
 
amity. German belligerence toward U.S., 1898-1914 --&gt;
 chilly U.S.-German relations.
 
D. Britain had global naval supremacy in 1914. 	Germany and
 
the U.S. lagged in naval power, even in combination (GB =
 2,714,000 tons, US+Ger = 2,290,000 tons). Germany had
 Europe's strongest army.
 
E. International maritime "rules," 1914: quite pro-neutral,
 
pro-free trade:
 1. Neutral states can ship any goods other than war
 
materiel ("contraband of war") to belligerents, except
 through a blockade.
 
2. A blockade must be effective to be recognized (requiring
 
a "close" blockade). Neither Britain nor Germany could
 impose a close blockade on the other, so U.S. non-
contraband trade with both was allowed.
 
3. Contraband is narrowly defined as weapons and war
 
material.
 
4. Even belligerents' merchant ships cannot be sunk without
 
warning.
 
F. Woodrow Wilson: a huge ego. 	Much hubris. He thought he
 
knew the answer to the war problem, hoped to impose it on
 the world. The American people: innocents abroad.
 
III. CHRONOLOGY
 
A. World War I begins, August 1, 1914. Germany is the chief
 
instigator. The Triple Entente (Britain, France, and
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Russia) fights the Central Powers (Germany and Austria-
Hungary).
 
B. The U.S. adopts a strict neutrality policy, August 1914. 
It restricts U.S. loans to belligerents to inhibit them
 from buying U.S. weapons and war materiel and asserts a
 U.S. right to trade with both sides.
 
C. Britain conducts a propaganda campaign in the U.S.: "The
 
Western Hemisphere is the Kaiser's next target!" and "This
 is a war for democracy!"
 
D. The U.S. abandons its neutrality policy, late 1914. 	Key
 
decisions:
 -- Washington decides to permit large U.S. arms sales to
 
belligerents.
 
-- Washington accepts severe British restrictions on U.S.
 
trade with Germany--contrary to U.S. rights under
 international law (see above).
 
Net result: the U.S. arms and trades with Britain but not
 Germany.
 Contending explanations:
 -- Wilson is shortsighted.  He doesn't foresee that this
 
will provoke Germany to war-causing belligerence against
 the U.S.
 
-- Wilson is pro-ally for security reasons and/or cultural
 
reasons.
 
-- Economic forces--the U.S. needs export trade to mitigate
 
its recession.
 
E. Germany retaliates in fits and starts, 1915-1917. 	It sinks
 
the Lusitania, May 1915; starts unrestricted submarine
 warfare, January 1917; and pursues a German-Mexican
 alliance, as revealed in the Zimmermann telegram, early
 1917.
 
F. The U.S. decides for war, March 1917. 	But what kind of
 
war--a limited naval war or something bigger? Answer: a
 bigger war--a naval war plus a ground war.
 
G. U.S. war aims grow, 1917-1918, from "war without victors"
 
to total defeat of Germany.
 
H. Allies win the war, November 1918. 	Total cost to U.S.:
 
117,000 U.S. battle dead. Allies impose Versailles Treaty,
 1919. Key elements of Versailles:
 -- A League of Nations will keep peace and provide
 
security.
 
-- Germany loses its colonies, pays moderate reparations. 
But Germany is not occupied or partitioned. Was this a
 mistake?
 
-- The U.S. and Britain guarantee French security.
 
IV. 	COULD THE U.S. HAVE PREVENTED THE WAR?
 
Would a U.S. defensive alliance with France and/or Russia, or
 (even more implausibly) with Germany have prevented the war? 
Should the U.S. have pursued such alliances?
 
V. COULD THE U.S. HAVE AVOIDED THE WAR? ALTERNATE U.S.
 
POLICIES, 1914-1917
 
A. Full U.S. neutrality, 1914ff. Either compel both sides to
 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Other American Interventions:
1900&#8211;1934 (Panama, Cuba, Haiti, the Dominican Republic, Nicaragua, Mexico, Russia)
1945&#8211;1993 (Iran 1953, Guatemala 1954, Chile 1973, Angola 1975, Indonesia 1957, Guyana 1964, Congo 1960, the Wars of the Reagan Doctrine, Panama 1989, Persian Gulf 1991, Somalia 1992&#8211;93)
Non-Interventions:
(Mexico in 1930s; Bolivia in 1950s)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_americanintrvn/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23&#8211;24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
tear up society. Fighting continues to this day in Afghanistan
 
and Angola is a mine-ridden ruin, strewn with death and
 suffering. A million Angolans died in the war of 1975-1991.
 
B. Assistance to El Salvador's government, 1979-91. 	The U.S.
 
helped El Salvador's rightist oligarchs defeat the communist
 FMLN rebellion. 70,000 killed. Democracy has followed since. 
Also immense criminalization and gang violence, triggering
 refugee flows to the USA in 2013ff.
 
Summary: paramilitary interventions can effectively punish target
 regimes. But is this good? They also often escape US control,
 killing civilians and otherwise sowing wide unintended chaos and
 ruin.
 
VII.	 DIRECT INTERVENTIONS AGAINST INTERNATIONAL AGGRESSION, 1945PRESENT
 
A. Korea, 1950-present. 	The U.S. reversed North Korea's aggression
 
and deterred any renewed aggression.
 
B. The Persian Gulf War, 1990-1991. The US forced Iraq out of
 
Kuwait.
 
Possible moral: the US is good at this kind of intervention. US
 armed forces are well-designed for halting or reversing cross-
border aggression.
 
VIII. DID U.S. COLD WAR INTERVENTIONS SERVE CONTAINMENT? HOW CAN WE
 
TELL?
 
IX. CURRENT INTERVENTION ISSUES
 
A. Controlling the spread of weapons of mass destruction (WMD). 
This is now a paramount U.S. interest! Consider these
 
strategies:
 1. Denying technology to proliferators--can this still work by
 
itself? (No.)
 
2. Economic carrots and sticks: (a) threat of economic sanctions
 
and (b) bribery for good conduct. Are these measures strong
 enough alone to stem and reverse proliferation?
 
3. Provide security for potential proliferators. 	This worked
 
with Germany, Japan, Taiwan and South Korea. But what if the
 potential proliferators are nasty countries hostile to U.S.
 allies? E.g., Saddam's Iraq, Iran, North Korea.
 
4. Hold proliferators' nuclear forces at risk. 	The U.S. would
 
let proliferation happen but be prepared to undo it by
 (nuclear) preventive war. This threat will make
 proliferators behave. It requires a nuclear first- and
 second-strike capability. Can such capabilities be gained
 and sustained against such states? Many say it requires
 national ballistic missile defense. Is this true?
 
5. Counter-society deterrence. 	Threaten to annihilate societies
 
that use nukes recklessly. But will this work after they get
 a second strike capability? Will it prevent transfer of
 weapons to terrorists? And is it ethical to threaten to
 massacre civilians? Children?
 
6. Counter-elite deterrence.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
-- Nicaragua 1909, 1912.
 
2. Other security:
 
-- Russia 1918-1920, to support non-communists (an
 
intervention in Europe, not the 3rd world, but I toss it
 
in).
 
3. Economic:
 
-- Cuba 1906-1909, 1917--to protect U.S. investors.
 -- Panama 1903--to get a bargain price on canal rights.
 -- Mexico 1913--to protect U.S. investors.
 
4. Other:
 
-- Nicaragua 1927-32--to contain leftist Mexico.
 -- Mexico 1914--to promote democracy in Mexico.
 
The U.S. Marines fought nasty counter-insurgencies against
 locals who resented US occupation in Haiti 1915-34, the
 Dominican Republic 1916-24, and Nicaragua 1927-32, killing
 several thousand people.
 
C. Non-intervention: FDR's Good Neighbor Policy, 1934-45.
 
IV. COVERT OPERATIONS, 1945-PRESENT
 
A. Iran 1953: the CIA instigated a coup against the elected
 
Mossadeq regime. Britain sought a coup against Mossadeq to
 protect British oil companies from nationalization by the
 Mossadeq government. So Britain fed the U.S. false tales of
 communists penetration of Iran and of communist leanings by
 Mossadeq. These fables helped spur the U.S. to organize the
 1953 coup. The U.S. then installed a cruel pro-U.S. rightist
 dictatorship under the Shah Reza Pahlavi (1953-1979). In 1979
 the Shah's regime was overthrown by extremist Shiite mullahs who
 had been radicalized by the 1953 coup and the Shah's
 dictatorship. These mullahs then established their own cruel
 dictatorship (1979-present) and pursued a fiercely anti-American
 foreign policy.
 
B. Guatemala 1954: a CIA coup against the elected leftist Arbenz
 
regime. Impetus for the coup came from the United Fruit
 Company, which opposed Arbenz because he refused to grant UFCo
 sweetheart terms. The coup brought a brutal rightist
 dictatorship to power. Vast horrors followed. Guatemala saw
 periodic rebellions for the next four decades. The Guatemalan
 government suppressed these rebellions with immense violence
 (200,000 killed). Peace came only in 1996. Guatemala is now a
 democracy, but is ridden with murderous street gangs who
 terrorize widely.
 
C. Congo 1960: the U.S. (via the CIA) abetted the murder of Patrice
 
Lumumba, the most popular leader in the newly-independent Congo. 
The U.S. then supported the rise and rule of the deeply corrupt
 Joseph Mobutu, who brought ruin to Congo. A great civil war,
 still simmering, followed his downfall. Murdering Lumumba: good
 choice?
 
D. Chile 1970-1973: CIA operations overthrew the elected leftist
 
Allende regime. Impetus for the coup came from the CEOs of
 Pepsico, ITT, and Kenicott and Anaconda copper. Harsh
 dictatorship followed, 1973-1989, ~2000 Chileans murdered by</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>AMERICAN INTERVENTIONS IN THE DEVELOPING WORLD: AN OVERVIEW
 
I. CORE QUESTIONS
 
A. How large is the American "empire"? Where is it located?
 
B. What have been the effects of US interventions on the USA? 	Have
 
they improved or injured U.S. security? U.S. prosperity?
 
C. What have been the effects of US interventions on the target 
societies? Have they improved or injured target societies'
 human rights? Have they brought democracy? Civil peace?
 
D. What caused US interventions? 	Mainly security or economic
 
concerns?
 
E. When is U.S. intervention successful and when does it fail? 
What methods of intervention are effective and which are not?
 
F. Ethics of intervention: When does the U.S. have a right to
 
intervene in other societies' affairs? When does it have an
 obligation to intervene?
 
II. THE SPANISH-AMERICAN-FILIPINO WAR, 1898-1902
 
A. Background to war.
 
1. Recurrent recessions struck the U.S. in 1873-78, 1882-85 and
 
1893-97. Some refer to the 1873-1897 era as the "Long
 Depression." It was second in severity only to the Great
 Depression of 1929-41.
 
2. Americans believed two economic myths: that China had a large
 
market; and that one-way export of U.S. goods to this China
 market was possible, and would prevent further economic
 depressions.
 
3. Americans believed in 1898 that Europeans were about to
 
conquer and partition China; and that the U.S. needed
 military bases in East Asia if it wanted its slice of the
 China pie. The Philippines could supply such bases.
 
B. The costs of the U.S.-Filipino war: 5,000 Americans and 200,000
 
Filipinos killed. Some 70,000 US troops were deployed to the
 Philippines.
 
C. Were American perceptions accurate? 	In fact the China market
 
was minuscule, and one-way trade with China was impossible. The
 US Asian empire did not prevent future depressions. Moreover,
 US possession of the Philippines caused unforeseen US-Japan
 conflict, since US measures to defend the Philippines also
 threatened Japan--an example of the security dilemma at work. 
Oh dear.
 
III. US CARIBBEAN INTERVENTIONS, 1900-1934. 10 INTERVENTIONS IN 6
 
COUNTRIES
 
A. "Dollar Diplomacy" before World War I. 	Dollar diplomacy was
 
actually about U.S. national security (specifically, keeping
 European navies out of the Caribbean), not dollars.
 
B. Dominant U.S. motives:
 
1. Dollar Diplomacy/security:
 
-- Dominican Republic 1916-1924.
 -- Haiti 1915-1934.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
Pinochet. Democracy restored in 1989.
 
E. Other successful operations: Brazil 1964, Greece 1967. 	Failed
 
operations: Cuba 1961, Indonesia 1957, Eastern Europe and China
 
1950s, against Saddam's Iraqi regime 1991-2003.
 
&gt; Some of these coups, most notably Iran 1953, Guatemala 1954, and
 
Chile 1973, were done partly to help US and British multinational
 corporations. Moral: economic motives sometimes drive US foreign
 policy. It is not all about national security. Question: do
 ordinary Americans benefit when the US government helps US
 corporations operate overseas? Doesn't this promote job flight
 
from the US?
 
&gt; Possible moral: covert operations are effective against
 
democracies but useless against tyrannies. US operations against
 
Cuba, the USSR, China and Iraq all failed.
 
&gt; Question: what about assassination as a U.S. policy?  	 Ever a good
 
idea? E.g., against Saddam Hussein during 1991-2003? Or Hitler
 1933-45?
 
V.	 DIRECT MILITARY INTERVENTIONS IN OTHERS' INTERNAL AFFAIRS, 1945
PRESENT
 
A. Eight direct interventions, 1945-89.
 
1. Vietnam/Indochina 1961-1973.
 
2. Dominican Republic 1965.
 
3-4. Grenada 1983; Panama 1989.
 5-8. Germany, Japan, Italy, Austria, 1941-1945.  These
 
interventions had striking democratic and peace-causing
 results.
 
B. Twelve direct interventions, 1989-present.
 
1. Four 1990s interventions: Somalia 1992-93; Haiti 1994; Bosnia
 
1995; Kosovo 1999. Observers disagree on whether these were
 successes or failures. The Somali intervention probably
 saved ~20,000 lives and cost 42 U.S. lives. Haiti remains a
 mess. Kosovo is quiet but Bosnia remains a powder keg.
 
2. Two 2000s interventions: Iraq 2003-2011; Afghanistan 2001
present. U.S. losses in Iraq: 4,477 U.S. dead, 30,000
 wounded, many badly. In Afghanistan: 2200+ U.S. dead so far. 
These wars illustrate that counter-insurgency (COIN) is hard!
 Iraq is now widely deemed a blunder. No WMD was destroyed.
 
Al-Qaeda was boosted. ISIS was spawned. Two public
 misperceptions fueled the war: that Saddam was involved with
 the 9/11/01 attack, and Saddam had WMD. Both false.
 
3. Six interventions by drone, airpower: Yemen, Somalia,
 
Pakistan against al-Qaeda affiliates; Libya 2011; Iraq and
 Syria against ISIS today.
 
C. A Non-Intervention: Rwanda 1994. 800,000 were murdered.
 D. Intervention issues, regarding four main intervention missions:
 
democratization, regime change, pacifying societies in conflict,
 and defeating insurgencies.
 1. Re: democratization:
 
&gt; When does imposing democracy require long occupation?  	 Long
 
occupations were needed in Germany, Japan, Italy, Austria,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
1994 genocide in Rwanda; the horrors in Sudan (including Darfur)
 
since 1983; the current mass killings in Syria, Congo, South
 Sudan, Central African Republic, Burundi, Burma?
 General background questions that are relevant:
 -- Has the U.S. done good for others when it intervened overseas
 
in the past? If not will it do better in the future?
 
-- Is the U.S. state, or any state, good at performing
 
philanthropies--especially abroad? Will governments do more
 harm than good when they are not accountable to those
 affected by their actions, as when they intervene in others'
 affairs?
 
-- Are societies entitled to shape one another when they "know
 
better" than the other--or do societies have a right to
 commit their own crimes and blunders?
 
-- Does the U.S. have a duty to help others?  At what discount
 
do we value others' lives? How many Sudanese, or Afghans,
 are worth one American?
 
-- What instruments of intervention are legitimate?  Covert
 
action? Economic sanctions? Assassination?
 
E. Democracy: is democracy good for everyone? 	Can the US export it
 
successfully?
 
F. Defending America's cultural/historic kin: Israel, South Korea,
 
Philippines. Who do Americans owe, and what do Americans owe
 them?
 
G. Miscellaneous: drugs (Mexico today), migrants (Haiti 1994).
 
X. WHO FAVORS INTERVENTION TODAY?
 
The U.S. has intervened abroad repeatedly since the Cold War ended
 (1989) under both Democratic and Republican administrations. 
President George H.W. Bush intervened in Panama, Kuwait/Iraq, and
 Somalia. President Bill Clinton remained in Somalia, and
 intervened in Bosnia, Kosovo, and (indirectly) Haiti. President
 George W. Bush intervened in Afghanistan, Iraq and Somalia. 
President Obama expanded the intervention in Afghanistan,
 intervened in Libya and Syria, and re-intervened in Iraq. In the
 Trump administration interventionists Mike Pompeo and Tom Cotton
 are ascendant, but the less interventionist James Mattis remains
 powerful. Overall the orientation of the Trump administration
 toward intervention remains unclear.
 Neoconservative foreign policy thinkers are the strongest
 advocates of interventions today, especially in the Mideast. They
 hold large influence in Washington.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
c. Good communication with the occupied public. 	Explain
 
your actions, tell your side of the story.
 
d. Carrots as well as sticks. 	Offer economic incentives
 
(bribes) for cooperation with your program.
 
e. Take steps to ensure that the government you support
 
behaves in ways that cause it to be viewed as legitimate
 
by the public. It must deliver services competently and
 fairly. Bush 43 and Obama failed on this score in Iraq,
 tolerating abuse of Sunni populations by the dreadful
 Shiite Maliki regime. Hence ISIS grew strong in Sunni
 areas.
 
f. A clear-and-hold strategy is far better than a search
and-destroy strategy.
 
g. Get local forces to do the heavy lifting in COIN. 
Locals know the local language and culture and will be far
 better at intelligence collection.
 
h. Insurgencies are very hard to defeat if they have
 
sanctuaries in neighboring countries. Such sanctuaries
 must be shut down.
 
i. Don't let the insurgency start in the first place. 
Insurgencies are like peat fires--very hard to start, very
 hard to stop. The best COIN strategy is to prevent
 insurgency in the first place.
 
&gt; Can mass violence (e.g., killing everyone in rebellious
 
districts) defeat insurgency? History (e.g., the defeat of
 the Guatemalan insurgents in the 1980s) suggests yes if the
 violence is accurately directed at the most rebellious
 areas. But this is not a tool the U.S. can use. If used
 today in the Mideast it would further alienate the wider
 Muslim world and bolster al-Qaeda/ISIS.
 
&gt; Is torture useful in COIN?  Does successful COIN require the
 
use of torture or other violations of the laws of war?
 
Summary on direct intervention: US success often requires US
 occupation. But occupation often triggers insurgencies; and
 the US is bad at counter-insurgency.
 
VI.	 INTERVENTION BY PROXY: PARAMILITARY INTERVENTIONS AND
 
INTERVENTIONS BY ASSISTING REGIMES, 1945-PRESENT
 
A. Four Reagan Doctrine Wars, 1983-1991.
 
1. Nicaragua: the U.S. supported Contra rebels against the
 
Marxist Sandinista governments, 1983-90. 50,000 Nicaraguan
 deaths.
 
2. Angola: the U.S. supported UNITA rebels against the Marxist
 
MPLA government, 1975-91. 1,000,000 Angolan deaths.
 
3. Cambodia: the U.S. supported anti-Hun Sen forces, 1979-89. 
64,000 El Salvadoran deaths.
 
4. Afghanistan: the U.S. supported Afghan mujahideen against the
 
Soviet invaders, 1980-92. 1,000,000 Afghans killed.
 
Possible morals: (1) paramilitary campaigns can have military
 success. The US proxy armies did well in all four wars. (2)
 Paramilitary intervention makes a big mess because civil wars</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
a. Threaten to annihilate proliferators' elites if they use
 
or transfer nukes recklessly.
 
b. Establish the principle that all governments must pay
 
damages to anyone injured by their WMD. Face
 
proliferators with the risk of immense lawsuits if they
 lose control of their WMD to terrorists or others. Will
 possessing WMD then be so fashionable?
 
7. Regime change by subversion or economic strangulation
 
(including by blockade) or air strike.
 
8. Sabotage and/or disruption. 	Unleash destructive cyber-
attacks on the proliferator's installations (for example
 Stuxnet). Assassinate its nuclear scientists (as someone has
 killed some Iranian scientists).
 
9. Preventive war (either limited or total):
 
a. Conventional preventive war, e.g., Israel against Iraq in
 
1981, Syria in 2007. This was Bush 41 administration
 policy, as framed in the 2002 U.S. national security
 strategy. Possible candidates for future action include
 Iran, North Korea, Syria, and maybe more.
 
b. Nuclear preventive war--a more frightening idea.
 
10. Tolerate some proliferation; deter proliferators from
 
misusing their weapons.
 
Question: How can the U.S. justify denying WMD to others while
 maintaining thousands of nuclear weapons itself?
 
B. Interventions against terror networks, as in Afghanistan 2001
and ISIS today in Iraq/Syria/Libya. US options:
 1. Intimidate terror-harboring regimes into controlling their
 
own terrorists. Is that sufficient? Or ...
 
2. Oust terror-harboring regimes and replace them with regimes
 
that will police their terrorists (as the US did in
 Afghanistan in 2001).
 
3. Oust terror-provoking regimes (Assad in Syria, Maliki in
 
Iraq) and replace them with pluralist regimes.
 
4. Broker an end to civil wars that feed terrorist networks, as
 
in Syria and Iraq today.
 
5. Build up the militaries of states, (e.g., Afghanistan,
 
Somalia, Congo, Syria, Iraq) so they can police their own
 territory, eradicate terrorist havens. Is the U.S. good at
 doing this? (No.)
 
6. Intervene directly against terror networks in hostile or
 
failed states, bypassing the government. This was 2009 Biden
 Plan for Afghanistan; and is the 2014ff Obama approach to
 ISIS.
 
C. War prevention: If the U.S. doesn't prevent or halt distant wars
 
will they spread to involve the U.S.? Also, will terrorists
 feed on distant wars if the U.S. doesn't halt or prevent them
 (as al-Qaeda fed on the Afghan civil war)? But if the U.S.
 tries try to prevent wars, will it succeed? (Does it know how?) 
And if the U.S. doesn't will it get sucked into wars it could
 otherwise avoid? 
D. Human rights. 	Should the U.S. undertake humanitarian
 
interventions to stop gross human rights violations, e.g.: the</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
but not in Panama or Grenada.
 
&gt; When is democratization impossible, even with a long
 
occupation? Intense poverty and illiteracy usually
 
preclude democracy. Deep ethnic divisions also impede
 democracy. These conditions cannot be easily cured. Hence
 some argue that these problems preclude democracy in Haiti,
 Somalia, Bosnia, Iraq, Afghanistan, Syria, and perhaps
 Egypt.
 
2. Re: Regime change:
 
&gt; The most organized elements dominate politics after regime
 
changes, not the most popular elements.
 
&gt; The most organized elements are often the most extreme
 
elements.
 
&gt; Ergo: regime change often brings worse monsters to power
 
unless the US occupies the target state.
 
3. Re: preventing/dampening/ending civil war:
 
&gt; When do deep social divisions preclude civil peace?  Some
 
argue that deep ethnic divisions prime Iraq, Afghanistan,
 Somalia and Syria for civil war.
 
&gt; Does the US government know how to dampen or end civil
 
wars?
 
4. Re: defeating insurgencies:
 
&gt; The US military is very good at fighting the regular forces
 
of states, but bad at COIN. COIN is essentially police
 work, alien to the ethos of the U.S. military services, and
 requiring skills and assets, especially knowledge of local
 language and culture, that U.S. forces often lack.
 
&gt; When will U.S. intervention require U.S. counter-insurgency
 
(COIN), as in Vietnam 1965-73 and Iraq 2003-11? When and
 how can insurgency be avoided, as in Germany, Japan, Italy,
 and Austria after 1945, Grenada 1983, and Panama 1989? The
 U.S. is bad at COIN and needs to keep such interventions to
 a minimum.
 Some argue that the Iraq insurgency of 2003-2011 was
 
inevitable. Others say it was avoidable, and stemmed from
 U.S. blunders: entering Iraq with a fairly small invasion
 force, failing to provide security following the invasion,
 disbanding the Iraqi Army in spring 2003, and unduly broad
 de-Ba`athification of the state, which amounted to de-
Sunnification and so provoked the Sunnis.
 
&gt; COIN often degenerates into brutal operations against
 
civilians that include widespread torture and murder, as
 both insurgents and counterinsurgents compete to coerce
 cooperation from civilians.
 
&gt; Nine keys to success in COIN:
 
a. Good intelligence, as COIN is largely police work (as
 
noted above), not war.
 
b. Avoiding injury to innocents. 	This requires good
 
intelligence; and very restrictive rules of engagement for
 your troops ("shoot only when you are sure you will not
 harm civilians"). Your troops will chafe at strict rules
 of engagement but they are essential to victory.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Cold War Origins and Conduct; the Korean War</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_coldwarorigins/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13&#8211;14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>COLD WAR ORIGINS, &amp; U.S. INTERVENTION IN THE KOREAN WAR
 
I.	 HOW THE COLD WAR ERUPTED: EVENTS
 
A.	 Background: President Franklin Roosevelt (FDR) hoped to
 
continue collaborating with the Soviet Union after World War
 
II. FDR's plan for peace: The five major powers (U.S.,
 
Britain, France, the USSR and China) would cooperate to keep
 peace, as the European great powers did after 1815.
 
B.	 Conflict over Poland, 1944.
 
-- Soviet dictator Josef Stalin wanted a communist Poland under
 
Soviet control. So he created a communist Polish government
 to rival the non-communist Polish government in exile. This
 irked Western powers who first joined WWII to free Poland.
 
-- July 1944: the Soviets encouraged a Polish underground
 
rising against the Nazis. Then the Soviet army halted on
 Warsaw's outskirts and let the Nazis slaughter the
 underground. Stalin refused even to let the U.S. and
 Britain air-drop supplies to them until it was too late. 
Not nice!
 
C.	 Yalta summit, February 1945. Stalin agreed to reorganize the
 
Polish government on a more democratic basis and to hold "free
 and unfettered elections" in Poland. But FDR agreed to let
 Stalin decide how much to reorganize the government, and how
 elections would be run. By conceding control of details to
 Stalin FDR in effect conceded on substance. William Leahy, a
 top FDR aide, warned FDR that "this [agreement] is so elastic
 that the Russians can stretch it all the way from Yalta to
 Washington without ever technically breaking it." FDR replied:
 "I know it, Bill ... But it's the best I can do for Poland at
 this time." In short, Yalta was a vague agreement.
 Then FDR oversold the agreement to the U.S. public by
 
implying that Stalin conceded more than in fact he had.
 
D.	 Potsdam summit, July 1945. Stalin demanded territorial
 
concessions in Turkey, Japan, and part of Libya (then an
 Italian colony). Truman refused. Some Americans read Stalin's
 demands to signal darkly aggressive Soviet intentions.
 
E.	 Stalin's ominous Feb. 9, 1946 speech. Stalin called for a
 
rapid Soviet military buildup and spoke of the wartime alliance
 as a thing of the past. This alarmed westerners.
 
F.	 Iran, March 1946. Stalin failed to pull Soviet forces out of
 
Northern Iran until he was pressured.
 
G.	 Turkey 1946. Stalin sent Turkey an ultimatum demanding joint
 
control of the Dardanelles. Truman stood firm and sent the
 battleship Missouri to the Mediterranean.
 
H.	 Greece 1947. The West wrongly thought Stalin was instigating
 
the Communist revolution in Greece. In fact he wasn't. Greek
 communists got aid from Yugoslavia's communist Tito government
 but not from Stalin. 
I.	 The Berlin Crisis of 1948-1949: a scary confrontation that
 
stemmed from the struggle for Germany.
 
J.	 Europe in ruins. Hence Truman fears pro-Soviet communist</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>U.S. Interests and Grand Strategies</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-40-american-foreign-policy-past-present-and-future-fall-2017/resources/mit17_40f17_usintreststrat/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6&#8211;8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
Suleiman Abu Ghaith declared al-Qaeda's right to kill 4
 
million Americans including two million children.
 
B.	 Is the US succeeding against al-Qaeda? Does the US have a
 
winning strategy?
 Al-Qaeda has been weakened, especially by the U.S.
 
killing of Osama Bin Laden in May 2011 and the attrition
 of the al-Qaeda organization in Pakistan by drone strikes
 since 2009. But AQ affiliates have sprouted since 9/11/01
 in Iraq, Syria, Yemen, Somalia, Libya, the Sinai, Mali,
 and Nigeria. Al-Qaeda spinoff ISIL controls much of Iraq
 and Syria. AQ affiliates al-Nusra and Khorasan pose a
 current threat in Syria. 
The al-Qaeda narrative remains widely believed in the
 
Muslim world. Al-Qaeda &amp; affiliates &amp; similar groups
 (ISIL) will not be defeated until the al-Qaeda narrative
 is destroyed.
 
VI. FIVE PRIME U.S. INTERESTS TODAY: AVERTING A EURASIAN HEGEMON
 
(BUT THAT'S EASY); PREVENTING/DEFEATING CATASTROPHIC TERRORISM
 (SOME SAY THAT'S EASY TOO--IS IT?); CONTROLLING WMD SPREAD;
 PROTECTING GLOBAL COMMONS (ENVIRONMENT, PUBLIC HEALTH);
 PRESERVING WORLD ECONOMY.
 
Can these five interests be protected without broad
 cooperation with other major states? 
VII. SIX CONTENDING GRAND STRATEGIES TODAY
 
Two grand strategies focused on other great powers:
 
1. Isolation (Favored by: Ron &amp; Rand Paul, strong
 
libertarians).
 
2. Containment vs. China and/or Russia. "China and/or
 
Russia pose the greatest threat to U.S. national
 security. The U.S. should contain their expansion. 
Specifically, the U.S. should prevent Russia from
 creating a sphere of influence in the Caucasus or
 Ukraine; and should organize an encirclement of China,
 e.g., using India, Vietnam." (Favored by: John McCain;
 Steve Bannon (China only); implied by Obama pivot to
 Asia.)
 
Three grand strategies focused on countering WMD terror. "WMD
 
terror poses the greatest threat to U.S. national security. 
Addressing this threat by countering its two prime elements-WMD proliferation and terrorist networks that have global
 ambition and reach--should be America's top priority":
 
3. Containment vs. proliferators, state sponsors of
 
terror, and terrorist movements. Use sieges and
 
deterrence to counter proliferator states (e.g., North
 
Korea, Iran) and terrorist states and movements (e.g.,
 ISIS in Iraq and Syria, al-Qaeda central in Pakistan,
 the Taliban, AQAP in Yemen). "We must contain and
 weaken bad actors by sieges, harassment, and sabotage
 while deterring their aggression. They will eventually</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
the catastrophe is unavoidable.
 
Oh dear. :-(
 
Key readings: Frank, "Small Price"; Homer-Dixon, "Terror
 in Weather Forecast"; and Davenport, "Climate Change."
 
C.	 Managing emerging threats to public health:
 
a. Emerging natural diseases. 	The 1918 flu killed 675,000
 
Americans--more than World Wars I and II combined--and
 40-100 million people worldwide. AIDS has killed ~30
 million worldwide. The growing human intrusion into
 natural habitats increase the danger of that new mass-
killer diseases will emerge; and the advance of
 medicine promises new defenses against such diseases. 
Defeating such diseases requires international
 cooperation on public health. The danger they pose is
 an argument for preserving cooperation with other
 states. Key reading: Troedsson and Rychener,
 "Influenza Takes Flight."
 
b. Emerging antibiotic resistant pathogens--a scary
 
problem that requires international solutions.
 
D.	 Economic interests: 
1. Economic primacy: "We must remain the #1 economy." 
Questions:
 a. What matters more: relative or absolute prosperity?
 b. How can relative prosperity be maximized? 	By hard-
line (trade restrictions, subsidies to US
 industries, etc.) or soft-line foreign economic
 policies?
 
2. Other interests: preserving access to raw materials? 
Defending US overseas investments? Promoting free
 trade/fair trade?
 
E.	 Defending America's cultural/historic kin: Israelis,
 
Poles, Cubans, Georgians, S. Koreans, Africans.
 
F.	 Miscellaneous: controlling drugs, migrants.
 
V. A PRIMARY NATIONAL SECURITY INTEREST, POST 9/11/01: THWARTING
 
WMD TERROR AGAINST THE UNITED STATES. BUT DOES THE U.S. HAVE A
 COUNTER-TERROR STRATEGY?
 
How large is the terrorist threat? What should be US strategy
 vs. terror?
 A. The 9/11/01 attack convinced many people that the terrorist
 
threat was larger than previously believed.
 
-- On 9/11 al-Qaeda showed considerable skill--far more
 
than other terrorist groups.
 
-- Nuclear weapons and materials are less secure from
 
theft or purchase than they once were, due to
 Pakistan's acquisition of nuclear weapons and the
 collapse of the Soviet dictatorship in the USSR in
 1991.
 
-- The al-Qaeda attack dramatized al-Qaeda's vast
 
destructive ambitions. Terrorism experts once argued
 that terrorists only want large audiences, not large
 numbers of dead. But former al-Qaeda spokesman</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
17.40  American Foreign Policy: Past, Present, Future
Fall 2017
For information  about citing these  materials  or  our  Terms  of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
collapse or mellow." (Favored by: Obama, Biden.)
 
Barry Posen's strategy of restraint is a tempered
 version of strategies #2 and #3. Key reading on Posen:
 Dizikes, "Time to Rethink."
 
4. Rollback vs. proliferators, state sponsors of terror,
 
and terrorist movements. Move to conquer and/or
 
destroy proliferator states (e.g., North Korea, Iran)
 and terrorist states and movements (e.g., ISIS, al-
Qaeda central in Pakistan, the Afghan Taliban, AQAP in
 Yemen, Syria). "We must conquer and/or destroy bad
 actors. Specifically, we mst remove and replace the
 regimes of proliferator states and state sponsors of
 terror; and destroy terrorist movements by conquering
 and policing their stomping grounds." (Favored by: Tom
 Cotton, Lindsey Graham, William Kristol, Robert Kagan,
 Trump administration.)
 
5. A Concert of major powers vs. proliferators, state
 
sponsors of terror, terrorist networks, and climate
 
change. Forge cooperation with other major powers,
 including Russia and China, to defeat these threats. 
"It's 1815 again. Other major powers no longer
 threaten U.S. security because the nuclear revolution
 makes conquest among major powers impossible. But WMD
 terror now poses a serious threat from below. It
 threatens all powers and cannot be defeated without
 cooperation by most or all powers. Climate change also
 threatens all states and cannot be stemmed without
 common action. Hence a concert of cooperation by all
 powers against WMD terror and climate change is
 feasible and necessary." (Favored by: SVE, and Obama
 administration at times.) (Key readings: Van Evera,
 "American Foreign Policy for the New Era"; and Sanger
 and Baker, "Obama Reorients.")
 A Concert strategy has two variants: Concert-by
containment and Concert-by-rollback. The consensus
 that a Concert requires is easier to achieve on
 Concert-by-containment.
 
A hybrid strategy:
 
6. Countering WMD terror plus ending unfair trade deals
 
and ending illegal immigration. The Trump
 administration. See Kahl and Brands, "Trump's
 Strategic Train Wreck."</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
Chavez in Venezuela, Aristide in Haiti). For example,
 
neoconservatives in the 1990s and the Bush 43
 administration favored "regime change" of rogue regimes and
 other unfriendly regimes. Framing this strategy are
 Sanger, "Bush to Formalize," and Lieber and Lieber, "Bush
 National Security Strategy" (assigned).
 
5. Selective pacification, or "selective engagement": the USA
 
prevents interstate conflict/war in industrial regions
 (Europe, E. Asia, Persian Gulf). "War elsewhere hurts the
 USA, so let's prevent it."
 
6. Global pacification/New World Order: the USA prevents
 
interstate conflict/war everywhere. The US could do this:
 a. Unilaterally: the US acts as a global policeman; or
 b. Multilaterally: the US acts with allies or in a
 
collective security system.
 
7. U.S. global social engineering/global empire: the USA
 
undertakes to prevent civil war, and/or protect human
 rights, and/or spread democracy, and/or spread market
 economics around the world (or in part of the world, such
 as the Middle East). 
The rationale is mainly idealist/philanthropic, but can
 
include security: "civil wars tend to spread to entangle
 the US so lets stop them"; "democracies seldom fight other
 democracies, hence the US enjoys more peace in a democratic
 world, so lets impose democracy"; and "democracies produce
 fewer terrorists, so the US is more secure in a democratic
 world, so let's impose democracy."
 Examples: Bill Clinton's policy of "engagement and
 
enlargement" of the zone of democracy, 1993-2001; Bush 43's
 pro-democracy 2nd inaugural address, 2005; the imperial
 policy favored by some conservatives since 2001 (see
 assigned news articles on "American Imperialism, Embraced,"
 The New York Times Magazine, December 9, 2001; and Thomas
 E. Ricks, "Empire or Not? A Quiet Debate over U.S. Role,"
 Washington Post, August 21, 2001); US intervention in
 Somalia 1992-3; US/French/British overthrow of the Qadafy
 regime in Libya, 2011; and recent calls for the US to
 overthrow the Assad regime in Syria.
 Can the U.S. pull this off? Will the U.S. benefit by
 
doing it? Specifically: can democracy be exported by force
 to other societies? Does the US know how to do it? Is
 democracy good for everyone? Are market economics good for
 everyone? Is regime change always a good remedy for human
 rights abuse? For civil war?
 
Where is counter-terror in this scheme? It's not prominent.
 
IV. SECONDARY INTERESTS AND STRATEGIES TO PROTECT THEM, ALL
 
ERAS. BUT ARE THESE INTERESTS REALLY SECONDARY?
 
A.	 Human rights: should the U.S. act to protect them? E.g.,
 
should it have moved to stop genocide in Rwanda in 1994?
 In South Sudan and Darfur, 1982-2008? Brutality in Libya,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>UNITED STATES INTERESTS AND GRAND STRATEGIES
 
I. GRAND STRATEGIES MATTER. Some failed grand strategists:
 
Napoleon, Kaiser Wilhelm, Hitler, Neville Chamberlain. Ouch! 
Bad strategies bring bad outcomes! And Woodrow Wilson lacked a
 post-war strategy for taming Germany. Result: WWII. Ouch!
 
II. NATIONAL SECURITY GRAND STRATEGIES, COLD WAR ERA (1947-1989)
 
A. The "Whether to Contain" Debate: Isolation vs. Containment
 
vs. Rollback (1947-1964). The debate turned on four
 
questions:
 1. How cumulative are industrial resources? 	Can a
 
conqueror convert these resources into military power,
 then use them to take more?
 
Isolationists: "resources are not cumulative--empires
 
bleed their owners."
 
Rollbackers: "resources are very cumulative--empires
 
strengthen their owners."
 
2. How easy is conquest? 	Can the USA conquer the USSR? 
Vice versa?
 
Isolationists: "conquest is very hard"; Rollbackers:
 
"conquest is easy."
 
3. How aggressive is the USSR? 	(Is war with the USSR
 
inevitable?)
 
Isolationists: "The Soviets are moderately aggressive,
 
war is avoidable."
 
Total Rollbackers: "The Soviets are very aggressive,
 
war is inevitable."
 
4. Will offensive action against the USSR provoke it or
 
calm it down?
 
Containers: "offensive policies will provoke Soviet
 
retaliation and war." 
Partial Rollbackers: "offensive policies will scare
 
the Soviets into a stand-down."
 
Key reading, Gaddis, Strategies of Containment.
 Key debaters: Robert Taft for Isolation, George Kennan and
 Walter Lippmann for Containment, James Burnham and General
 Nathan Twining for Rollback.
 
B. The "How to Contain" Debate: Finite Containment vs. Global
 
Intervention (for example, in Vietnam, Guatemala, Chile,
 Nicaragua, El Salvador, Angola, etc.) (1965-1991). Four
 key questions underlay this debate:
 1. Size of Soviet threat to Third World: can the Soviets
 
seize it?
 a. By direct military intervention?
 b. By victory of local Marxist proxies? 	(Do birds of
 
reddish feathers fly together?)
 
2. How "cumulative" are Third World resources? 	Would a
 
Soviet empire in the 3rd World tilt the global balance
 of power toward the USSR?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
a. Value of 3rd world military bases?
 
b. Does US economy depend on 3rd world raw materials?
 c. Domino theory--is it true?
 d. Credibility theory--are commitments interdependent?
 e. Does the nuclear revolution make conventional-era
 
cumulativity arguments obsolete, by making conquest
 so hard that no Third World gains could position the
 USSR to conquer the USA?
 
&gt; An axiom relevant to debates #1 and #2: "A wise warrior
 
shoots with a rifle, not with a shotgun."
 
3. Can US interventions against the 3rd world left succeed?
 4. Would independent communist states threaten US security?
 Key debaters: George Kennan, Walter Lippmann, &amp; Hans
 Morgenthau for Finite Containment; NSC-68 (Dean Acheson)
 and Walter Rostow for Global Intervention.
 
III. NATIONAL SECURITY GRAND STRATEGIES, POST-COLD WAR ERA
 
(1991-9/11/2001)
 
Seven U.S. grand security strategies were proposed during
 1991-2001:
 1. Isolation: the USA comes home. The Soviet collapse in 1991
 
removed the only real threat to the U.S. Time to come home
 and celebrate!
 
2. Neo-containment/ Type #1: the USA contains the new
 
potential Eurasian hegemon (usually identified as China). 
The USA would contain the potential hegemon's imperial
 expansion, and might also try to hamper its economic
 growth.
 &gt; Tactical debates about executing strategy 2 (and 3 and
 4):
 a. Unilateral vs. multilateral strategy. 	The George W.
 
Bush ("Bush 43") administration (2001-2009) leaned
 unilateral, the Barack Obama administration (2009-17 was
 more multilateral, the Donald Trump administration is
 more unilateral.
 &gt; A relevant strategist: Tom Sawyer.  Sawyer's axiom:
 
it is better to persuade other boys to whitewash the
 fence than to whitewash it oneself.
 
b. Threats vs. inducements to win allies. 	Bush 43 relied
 
mainly on the big stick to win friends; Obama used both
 sticks and inducements; Trump threatens sticks.
 
3. Neo-containment Type #2: the USA contains the world's most
 
crazy or hostile states (North Korea, Iran) by limiting
 their control of special technologies (weapons of mass
 destruction, or "WMD") or oil resources, using active
 deterrence and coercion and by lowering US dependence on
 their products (oil).
 
4. Neo-rollback: the USA wages preventive war against rogue
 
states that pursue WMD such as Iraq 2003 (and perhaps North
 Korea or Iran today) and against otherwise unfriendly
 regimes (Taliban in Afghanistan 2001, Qadafy in Libya 2011,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
2011? Mass murder in Syria in 2011-present? The killing
 
of a million in Zimbabwe since 1990? The killing of
 millions in Congo, 1996-present? The ongoing expulsion of
 the Rohingya from Burma? See Kaufmann, Cooper, Kristof
 and Kinzer in your assigned readings.
 
B.	 Environmental interests: preventing climate change and
 
other environmental damage. Many fear that human-caused
 warming will reach catastrophic levels in a few years if
 unchecked. If so, oceans rise will destroy large coastal
 regions, including many great cities. Verdant regions
 will become deserts. Scores or hundreds of millions will
 be made homeless. Great economic damage will ensue. 
Conflicts may erupt as desperate groups fight for a place
 in this dark new world. (Oh dear! This interest doesn't
 sound secondary!)
 The climate change problem has feasible solutions--a
 
carbon tax would likely work well--but here are some
 reasons why we may be unable to solve it:
 1. It pits a concentrated interests (carbon fuel
 
industries) against a more dispersed general interest
 (everyone else). Concentrated interests usually win
 such fights.
 
2. Solutions require international cooperation among
 
states. Instead states will free-ride, letting others
 solve the problem while they shirk.
 &gt; Problems #1 and #2 are manifestations of Mancur
 
Olson's collective goods theory in action.
 
3. The climate science community is neither adept at using
 
nor fond of using public relations techniques to make
 its findings known to publics. But such techniques are
 necessary to reach global publics.
 
4. Western ethical and religious traditions do not
 
emphasize moral obligations to future generations
 (unlike, for example, the Iroquois Great Law, which
 requires that we consider the effects of our actions
 down to the seventh generation.)
 
5. The climate change danger has no analogies in human
 
history. Humans often think analogically; so, seeing
 no analogies to the danger, people dismiss it. (But
 offering useful analogies is Jared Diamond, Collapse, a
 valuable book).
 
6. The climate change danger does not have a primordial
 
signature such as screaming, big teeth, spattering
 blood, or fire. Humans over-respond to dangers with
 such primordial signatures, but under-respond to slow-
rising dangers that lack them, like climate change.
 
7. In the USA today, government money is almost never
 
spent to solve problems that are not yet causing pain. 
Unfortunately, the pain of climate change will be
 delayed until long after the actions that cause it,
 setting in fully only after the harm is done. If we
 wait to feel real pain before acting we may wait until</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
