<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/</course_url>
    <course_title>Argumentation and Communication</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Communication </list>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>Literature </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/lect_6</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/lect_6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Arguments andArguments and 
DebatesDebates
11.22511.225
Session 6Session 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Decide on Point HierarchyDecide on Point Hierarchy
DUSP Should Reduce 
the MCP 1 Class Si ze 
to a tota l of 60 4. Individual 
Classes are too big 
3. Advisors are 
hard to find 
1. Not enough funding 
for stud ents 2. Housing is scarce 5. Caliber of students is 
not high enough</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Map Your ArgumentMap Your Argument
CORE MESSAGE 
DUSP Should Reduce 
the MCP 1 Class Si ze 
to a tota l of 60 Individual Classes 
are too big 
Advisors are hard 
to find 
Not enough funding for 
students Housing  is scarce Caliber of students is not 
high</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Arguments/DebatesArguments/Debates
A chance to learnA chance to learn
A chance to match witsA chance to match wits
A chance to have an impact on the listenerA chance to have an impact on the listener
A dialogue out loudA dialogue out loud 
StatementsStatements
QuestionsQuestions
AnswersAnswersNew Ideas</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The Three Bases of an ArgumentsThe Three Bases of an Arguments
Based on credibilityBased on credibility
Based on logicBased on logic
Based on emotional draw
Based on emotional draw</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>The CritiqueThe Critique
IntroIntro 20 seconds20 seconds

Tell the Audience you are glad to review your colleague Tell the Audience you are glad to review your colleague ss 
work and that you will be briefwork and that you will be brief be respectful of differingbe respectful of differing
opinionsopinions
Highlight no more than 1 or 2 criticismsHighlight no more than 1 or 2 criticisms
BodyBody 2 minutes2 minutes could use a back up slide if you arecould use a back up slide if you are
fast and planning aheadfast and planning ahead
Deliver only 1 or 2 important criticismsDeliver only 1 or 2 important criticisms 
Provide at least 1 detail, if possibleProvide at least 1 detail, if possible 
Wrap upWrap up 30 seconds30 seconds 
Repeat main pointsRepeat main points
Connect back to your core messageConnect back to your core message</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>How do you Debate?How do you Debate?





Deliver your point of view and sit down?Deliver your point of view and sit down?
Deliver your point of view and stand firm?Deliver your point of view and stand firm?
Deliver your point of view and listen?Deliver your point of view and listen?
Deliver your point of view, listen andDeliver your point of view, listen and 
understand?understand?
Deliver your point of view, listen, understandDeliver your point of view, listen, understand 
andand ..nooooooooonooooooooo . Change?. Change?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>What is an Argument?What is an Argument?
Is it about:Is it about:
Winning?Winning?
Asserting your position?Asserting your position?
Convincing someone else?Convincing someone else?
Listening?Listening?
Speaking?Speaking?
Finding the truth of the matter?Finding the truth of the matter?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>The RebuttalThe Rebuttal --3 minutes3 minutes
Strategy AStrategy A if you have aif you have a 
strong responsestrong response
Acknowledge 1 of 3 criticalAcknowledge 1 of 3 critical 
points (10 seconds)points (10 seconds)
Say what problem withSay what problem with 
critical point (3 minutes)critical point (3 minutes)
Logical ProblemsLogical Problems
Credibility ProblemsCredibility Problems
Emotional ArgumentEmotional Argument 
ProblemsProblems
Back to Core MessageBack to Core MessageStrategy BStrategy B --if you have aif you have a 
weak responseweak response
Acknowledge one pointAcknowledge one point
Give an alternative viewGive an alternative view 
Bring audience back to yourBring audience back to your 
core message and say why itcore message and say why it 
is stronger.is stronger.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>PersuasionPersuasion
Connect your message to youConnect your message to you who you are andwho you are and 
why what you say matterswhy what you say matters
Narrative to make themes come aliveNarrative to make themes come alive
Address the specific concerns of your audienceAddress the specific concerns of your audience
Address counterpoints in your talkAddress counterpoints in your talk
Be seriousBe serious but donbut don t be afraid to smilet be afraid to smile</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Step 1 = Research, Perspectives,Step 1 = Research, Perspectives, 
MessageMessage 
Know your MaterialKnow your Material
Know who your audience isKnow who your audience is what do they know?what do they know?
Know who you areKnow who you are what is your bottom line?what is your bottom line?
Know your opponentKnow your opponent what is his/her bottom line?what is his/her bottom line?
Find your message as an individualFind your message as an individual
Find your message as a groupFind your message as a groupMessage Research Lens</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Debate ObstaclesDebate Obstacles
Fear of your oppositionFear of your opposition
Tenacity to one viewTenacity to one view
No clear, concise message
No clear, concise message


Lack of a willingness to consider another viewLack of a willingness to consider another view 
Do you consider change to be failure?Do you consider change to be failure?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Connect the PointsConnect the Points
DUSP Should Reduce 
the MCP 1 Class Si ze 
to a tota l of 60 4. Individual Classes 
are too big 
3. Advisors are 
hard to find 
1. Not enough funding 
for stud ents 2. Housing is scarce 5. Caliber of students is 
not high enough 
Faculty are 
constrained 
Research assi stant positions 
are hard to getPaying for school is not 
our only concern</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Revisit Your Core MessageRevisit Your Core Message
DUSP Should NOT decrease class sizeDUSP Should NOT decrease class size
DUSP needs the extra tuition fundsDUSP needs the extra tuition funds ----$300,000/yr!!$300,000/yr!!
DUSP needs a variety of views from around theDUSP needs a variety of views from around the 
worldworld
Larger numbers = more power at MITLarger numbers = more power at MIT
Larger numbers = more active researchLarger numbers = more active researchDUSP Should 
NOT Reduce 
Class Size</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Step 2 = Play with Your Message
Step 2 = Play with Your Message







Are there faults in the logic of your message?Are there faults in the logic of your message?
Are there faults in the evidence supporting yourAre there faults in the evidence supporting your 
message?message?
Are there gaps in information that need to be filled?Are there gaps in information that need to be filled?
Are you convinced by what you say?Are you convinced by what you say?
What are your assumptions?What are your assumptions?
What are your opponentWhat are your opponent s assumptions?s assumptions?
Are there other assumptions? Different starting places? Are there other assumptions? 
 Different starting places?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>List Counter PointsList Counter Points
DUSP Should Reduce 
the MCP 1 Class Si ze 
to a tota l of 60 4. Individual Classes 
are too big 
3. Advisors are 
hard to find 
1. Not enough funding 
for stud ents 2. Housing is scarce 5. Caliber of students is 
not high enough 
Counte r: more diversity, more 
experience, better discuss ions, 
more networking opportunities 
Counte r: Forces students 
to sell themselves better, to 
try harder to impress, to 
focus on who they really 
want to work with.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Step 3 = The StrategyStep 3 = The Strategy
The 12 minute presentationThe 12 minute presentation
IntroIntro quick intro/deliver core message 2 quick intro/deliver core message 2--min.min.
BodyBody deliver no more than 3 supportingdeliver no more than 3 supporting 
pointspoints 7 minutes7 minutes
Most important point firstMost important point first
Provide at least 1 or 2 details on one or two pointsProvide at least 1 or 2 details on one or two points 
ConclusionConclusion Repeat Core messageRepeat Core message --2 minutes2 minutes
Have no more than 7 slidesHave no more than 7 slides</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/guide_info_memos</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/guide_info_memos/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
Guidelines for Effective Informational Memos 
Writing clear, informative memos is a critical to your caree r whether you are a policy maker, engineer, architect, 
consultant, or activist.  Informative memos help lay the grou nd work for critical decisions that you and others will be 
making.  Informative memos are not d ecision memos; they do not recommend a course of action.  Instead, 
informative memos are directed to a decision maker and seek to:  
	highlight options, 
	compare alternatives, and  
 provide analyses. 
As such your ability to covey complex information simply is key.  Also important is your forethought about the 
concerns of the decision maker and d eciding how to address each concern. 
Of course no writing is unbiased and while you will likely have an opinion about the best course of action, save 
these strong opinions for later. Instead , challenge yourself to carefully lay out  each critical issue, idea or plan and 
analyze these using a carefully chosen structure (e.g., pros/cons, long term/short term).  Think of an informational 
memo as a document that sets the stage, frames the issues , and provides the detailed analysis that feeds into the 
larger decision.  When you what kno w your decision maker expects (audien ce) and you give her what she needs 
clearly and concisely (meeting expectations), you become part of the decision making team.    
Okay, so heres the strategy:  
1.  Include a Summary Paragraph:   
Similar to an action memo, here you need to summarize the contents of the memo.  However, your decision maker 
doesnt want an action plan.  She will create th at (or have you create it later).  Instead: 
	State the issue (1 sentence), 
	Summarize the analysis briefly (1-3 sentences), and 
	Outline the options (1-3 sentences). 
2.  Focus on the content of the memo: 
The body of the memo is where the analysis goes.  Here you want to explicitly tell the decision maker that she will need to make a decision about the issues that you will present one by one.  For each issue you need to: 
	Name and explain briefly each issue  most important issue goes first; 
	Provide the analysis at a level exp ected by the reader (dont include raw data, if she wants to focus on 
trends); 
	Discuss options; and 
	Use a sub heading to divide issues. 
3. Craft the Conclusion 
Informational memos have conclusions that state what the next steps are, but dont draw conclusions or recommend any specific action.  It is not about providing a distinct an swer to a question but providing a variety of well-analyzed 
options.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
4. Dont under estimate the power of tone in writing 
Get in the habit of thinking about who you are writing to and where the memo might end up (the press, a higher up, 
etc.) Everything you write these days and send electronically (even e-mail) sh ould be carefully crafted, edited and 
then scanned for problems.  Informative memos have a distinctively neutral tone.  They dont seek to sell an idea, 
although your choices about what to present and how will often persuade a decision maker.  In general tone should: 
 Be diplomatic; 
 Acknowledge problem areas; 
 Advance options without arguing with existing policies; and 
 Be tactful, not patronizing or insistent. 
Practicing more than one style of memo writing will help you fine tune and develop your individual style.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/lect_3</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/lect_3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting BriefingDissecting Briefing 
AssignmentsAssignments
Find out who is in your group:Find out who is in your group:
	Who has public housing experience?Who has public housing experience? What kind?What kind?
	Who isWho is  an architect/desan architect/des igner?igner?
	Who isWho is  a techie?a techie? This perThis per son should check to makeson should check to make 
sure presentation works in Gateway classroomsure presentation works in Gateway classroom 
hour before presentationshour before presentations
	Who knows how to pull up/use maps?Who knows how to pull up/use maps? 
	Who knows public policy?Who knows public policy? What kind?What kind?
	Who has worked for a Mayor?Who has worked for a Mayor?
	Who has time to visit theWho has time to visit the site(ssite(s ) with a digital) with a digital 
cameracamera (this may not be necessary but some(this may not be necessary but some 
groups did this last year)?groups did this last year)?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting BriefingDissecting Briefing 
AssignmentsAssignments
Divide up the Assignment:Divide up the Assignment:
Everyone needs a speaking part
Everyone needs a speaking part
Everyone needs aEveryone needs a task(stask(s ))
Divide up questionsDivide up questions what goeswhat goes 
where?where?
Volunteer for what you are goodVolunteer for what you are good 
at.at.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting Assignments
Dissecting Assignments
Who are you?Who are you? You have beenYou have been 
appointed by Thomasappointed by Thomas MeninoMenino ,, 
the Mayor of Boston, to the Taskthe Mayor of Boston, to the Task 
Force on the Future of PublicForce on the Future of Public 
HousingHousing</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting BriefingDissecting Briefing 
AssignmentsAssignments
	What Role is the Group Playing?
What Role is the Group Playing?
The Staff the Task Force on the
The Staff the Task Force on the 
Future of Public Housing.
Future of Public Housing. 
	Each group includes:Each group includes: 
z	zBoston Housing Authority,Boston Housing Authority, 
z	zBoston Redevelopment AuthorityBoston Redevelopment Authority
z	zDepartment of Neighborhood
Department of Neighborhood 
Development
Development
z	zSocial service staff from other agencies.Social service staff from other agencies.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting MemoDissecting Memo 
AssignmentsAssignments
	What do you write?
What do you write? 
	informational memo
informational memo 
	1,500 words1,500 words
	discusses anydiscusses any twotwoof these threeof these three 
ongoing concernsongoing concerns 
a few sentences about the third
a few sentences about the third 
issue if it links to other issues
issue if it links to other issues 
	dondont try to address all three issuest try to address all three issues 
in such a compact document.in such a compact document.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting MemoDissecting Memo 
AssignmentsAssignments
	HereHere s one strategys one strategy Dissect theDissect the 
Assignment:Assignment:
	Pick your first questionPick your first question 

z	zwork on one at a timework on one at a time you can makeyou can make 
connections between them later.connections between them later.
	Turn first subTurn first sub --question into a
question into a 
background sentence that beginsbackground sentence that begins 
As you pointed outAs you pointed out ....
	Spend no more than a paragraph (5Spend no more than a paragraph (5 
sentences) on background.sentences) on background.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting BriefingDissecting Briefing 
AssignmentsAssignments
	The Mayor has asked each group toThe Mayor has asked each group to
prepare a 20prepare a 20 --minute briefingminute briefing thatthat 
analyzesanalyzes the lessonsthe lessons of a singleof a single
redevelopment caseredevelopment case (see below) for:(see below) for:
	(a) The role of physical design in(a) The role of physical design in
redevelopment success; andredevelopment success; and 
	(b) The optimal role for planners in public(b) The optimal role for planners in public
housing redevelopment.housing redevelopment. 
	What is the best mix of physical and nonWhat is the best mix of physical and non -
physical planning interventions to ensurephysical planning interventions to ensure
effective redevelopment?effective redevelopment? 
	What kinds of planning policies can bestWhat kinds of planning policies can best
promote this mix?promote this mix?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting MemoDissecting Memo 
AssignmentsAssignments
Large Overarching Questions:
Large Overarching Questions: 
If you were in charge of developing aIf you were in charge of developing a 
proposal for a public housingproposal for a public housing 
redevelopment now, what priorities wouldredevelopment now, what priorities would 
you set for allocating funds to theseyou set for allocating funds to these 
different forms of intervention?different forms of intervention? 
	There are at least X priorities that need toThere are at least X priorities that need to 
be set for allocating funds.be set for allocating funds. 
z	zWere there important missed design
Were there important missed design 
opportunities?
opportunities?
z	zShould more of the money have been spent onShould more of the money have been spent on 
some other nonsome other non --design aspects of thedesign aspects of the 
redevelopment, such as social servicesredevelopment, such as social services</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting Assignments
Dissecting Assignments
Who is your audience?Who is your audience? 
zzMayorMayor
zzDeputy Chief of Staff for PolicyDeputy Chief of Staff for Policy</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting MemoDissecting Memo 
AssignmentsAssignments
	2. Redevelopment: Physic2. Redevelopment: Physic al Design vs. Socialal Design vs. Social
PolicyPolicy
	Each of the three redevelopment efforts discussedEach of the three redevelopment efforts discussed
in class entailed spending t ens of millions of dollars in class entailed spending t ens of millions of dollars 
on efforts to redesign the physical environment.on efforts to redesign the physical environment.
What aspects of this design intervention were mostWhat aspects of this design intervention were most
important? Were there important missed designimportant? Were there important missed design
opportunities? Should more of the money haveopportunities? Should more of the money have
been spent on some other nonbeen spent on some other non --design aspects ofdesign aspects of
the redevelopment, such as social services? Arethe redevelopment, such as social services? Are
physical designs and social policiesphysical designs and social policies alternativealternative 
ways to take action to im prove public housing, or ways to take action to im prove public housing, or
are they connected in some important ways? If youare they connected in some important ways? If you
were in charge of developing a proposal for a publicwere in charge of developing a proposal for a public
housing redevelopment now, what priorities wouldhousing redevelopment now, what priorities would
you set for allocating funds  to these different forms you set for allocating funds  to these different forms 
of intervention?of intervention?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting BriefingDissecting Briefing 
AssignmentsAssignments
	Who is the Audience?Who is the Audience?
	Two local philanthropists ,Two local philanthropists ,
	Editor ofEditor of The Boston GlobeThe Boston Globe newspaper,newspaper, 
	two respected real estate developers,two respected real estate developers, 
	a university professora university professor 
	the retired head of a local civil rightsthe retired head of a local civil rights 
organizationorganization
	heads of three nonprofit communityheads of three nonprofit community --basedbased 
development organizationsdevelopment organizations 
	Head, Boston Housing Authority andHead, Boston Housing Authority and 
	MayorMayor</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting MemoDissecting Memo 
AssignmentsAssignments
Large Overarching Questions:Large Overarching Questions:
Are physical designs and social policiesAre physical designs and social policies alternativealternative 
ways to take action to im prove public housing, or ways to take action to im prove public housing, or
are they connected in some important ways?are they connected in some important ways?
	PhysPhys ical desical des igns and social policies are/are notigns and social policies are/are not
alternativealternative ways to take action to improve publicways to take action to improve public
housing and are/are not connected.housing and are/are not connected. 
z	zWhat aspects of this design intervention were mostWhat aspects of this design intervention were most
important?important?
z	zWere there important missed design opportunities?Were there important missed design opportunities?
z	zShould more of the money have been spent on someShould more of the money have been spent on some
other nonother non --design aspects of the redevelopment, suchdesign aspects of the redevelopment, such
as social services?as social services?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Dissect Briefing Assignment
Dissect Briefing Assignment
	Set the Schedule for Individual and GroupSet the Schedule for Individual and Group
Pieces:Pieces: 
	1.1. Saturday am:Saturday am: FinisFinis hh Drafting your indivDrafting your indiv iidualdual 
section(ssection(s )) 
	2.2. Sunday am:Sunday am: Draft your slides on Sunday amDraft your slides on Sunday am
	3.3. Sunday pm:Sunday pm: Meet with group and merge slidesMeet with group and merge slides
(assume something will go wrong)(assume something will go wrong)
	4.4. Monday:Monday: Practice with Group (assume someonePractice with Group (assume someone
will not be ready)will not be ready) 
	5.5. Tuesday: Practice with Group (assume someoneTuesday: Practice with Group (assume someone
will be late)will be late)
	6.6. Wednesday:Wednesday: ArriveArrive hour early to test yourhour early to test your
presentation in the Gateway Classroompresentation in the Gateway Classroom
(Remember: Larry Vale(Remember: Larry Vale s presentation didns presentation didn t fullyt fully
work last week)work last week)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting BriefingDissecting Briefing 
AssignmentsAssignments
	Dissect the AssignmentDissect the Assignment
	Given uncertainties about the future ofGiven uncertainties about the future of 
funding for public housing redevelopmentfunding for public housing redevelopment 
as well as ongoing misperceptions aboutas well as ongoing misperceptions about 
the current state of public housing in thethe current state of public housing in the 
city, the Mayor wants to know:city, the Mayor wants to know:
	What housing authority planners shouldWhat housing authority planners should
do next?do next?
	What issues matter most when trying toWhat issues matter most when trying to 
assessassess successsuccess 
	Analyze several past effortsAnalyze several past efforts</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting MemoDissecting Memo 
AssignmentsAssignments
Create an overarchingCreate an overarching 
statementstatement 
Knit the two questions together
Knit the two questions together 
broad is okaybroad is okay 
Make the background work forMake the background work for 
both questions.both questions.
Narrow your statement
Narrow your statement</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Preparing Preparing 
Briefings/MemosBriefings/Memos
Cherie Cherie MiotMiot AbbanatAbbanat
Department of Urban Studies and Department of Urban Studies and 
PlanningPlanning</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting MemoDissecting Memo 
AssignmentsAssignments
	Focus on the last subFocus on the last sub --question it is:question it is:
zzfocusefocuse d
d 
zzoverarching
overarching 
z	zcould turn into the larger pointcould turn into the larger point 
	Sift through the subSift through the sub --questions to decidequestions to decide 
which of these subwhich of these sub --questions is:questions is:
z	zA key pointA key point 
z	zMost importantMost important
z	zTangentialTangential
	Find evidence and examples to support theFind evidence and examples to support the 
points that you will make.points that you will make.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting MemoDissecting Memo 
AssignmentsAssignments
Background:Background: Each of the threeEach of the three 
redevelopment efforts in Bostonredevelopment efforts in Boston 
(Franklin Field, Commonwealth(Franklin Field, Commonwealth 
and West Broadway) spent tensand West Broadway) spent tens 
of millions of dollars onof millions of dollars on 
redesigning the physicalredesigning the physical 
environment. Explainenvironment. Explain ....</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting BriefingDissecting Briefing 
AssignmentsAssignments
Some expectations:Some expectations:
	InterruptsInterrupts 
	Challenges to your claims
Challenges to your claims 
	Some might also argue (a bit) withSome might also argue (a bit) with 
each other.each other.
	In addition, you should prepare aIn addition, you should prepare a
briefing summarybriefing summary a report ina report in 
miniatureminiature ofof no more than 500no more than 500 
wordswords , to summarize your analysis, to summarize your analysis 
and recommendations.and recommendations.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting MemoDissecting Memo 
AssignmentsAssignments
Create a conclusion for theCreate a conclusion for the 
entire paper.entire paper.
DonDont forget about next steps att forget about next steps at 
the end of your memo, ifthe end of your memo, if 
appropriate.appropriate.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Dissecting BriefingDissecting Briefing 
AssignmentsAssignments
Get the Basics Down:
Get the Basics Down:
What software is group using?
What software is group using? 
Power Point? Web based?
Power Point? Web based?
	Who is the final editor in group?
Who is the final editor in group?
	Who is the moderator in group?
Who is the moderator in group?
	What format will use?What format will use? Linear orLinear or 
Hub/spokeHub/spoke
	Who is writing the 500 word briefingWho is writing the 500 word briefing 
document?document?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/writing_eff_esay</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/writing_eff_esay/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
 
 
Cherie Miot Abbanat, Lecturer 
Department of Urban Studies and Planning 
   
Guidelines for Writing Effective Essays 
 
Can you read and digest a series of articles assigned to you?  Next, can you extract th e essence out of each article 
and summarize it in no more than a few sentences?  Okay, you can read, you can summarize, but can you pull 
together the threads that connect each of the articles together and create a new idea?  Can you offer thoughts and 
insights on the ideas in these articles? We want to know. 
 
So, you have been given an essay to write.  We design essay questions in order to challenge you in many ways that 
we believe you will be challenged while you are at MIT a nd beyond MIT.  But, where do you begin and how do you 
know when youre done? 
 
Task 1:  Review and review again the essay question.   
Sometimes you develop the questions yourself  thesis ques tions.  Most of the time, however, you will be handed 
questions that were written by your professors and you will need to respond.  Examine the question.  Think about 
the question.   Brainstorm answers and otherwis e get into that creative space inside you.   
 
Some essay questions are really broad.  Broad questions ca n be helpful, but sometimes they can make you want to 
tear your hair out because you are not sure what the professor expects.  Try to think of these types of questions as an opportunity because they may signal that the door is wide open for you to pick and choose what you really want to 
say. Usually what broad questions really mean is that th e professor is not exactly clear  about what s/he wants in 
terms of an answer.  Or, it means that the case can be appr oached from a number of different angles.  Regardless, 
when a professor offers you a broad question, rejoice!  You have lots of room to create. 
 
Some essay questions are very specific.  Here the professor knows what s/he wants and s/he wants to know that you 
know what s/he wants.  Here you need to focus your attenti on on the articles.  You need to take good notes, work to 
distill the information.  Most of all, you need to figure out what is asked and how best to respond so that you all questions are addressed.  Once you figure out what type of question you have, I recommend that you focus on a few key elements:   
 
Task 2:  After you have reviewed the question ask yourself the following:   
 Do you understand the question that is being asked? 
 Do you know what topic you need to address?  
 Did you already summarize each of the articles in your own words?  If not, go do this. 
 Can you tell from your notes, which ideas are yours and wh ich ideas are the authors id eas?  If not, fix your 
notes  no plagiarism please! 
 Did you craft an outline for your essay question?  
 
Task 3:  Write a first, messy draft:  
 Dont try to control your first responses to the questio n too much, just write what comes to mind while you 
have the question in your mind. 
 What questions do you have for the authors of the articles you are responding to?   
 What inconsistencies do you find in the articles?  What problems do you see?  What holes can you identify?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
 
 
Cherie Miot Abbanat, Lecturer 
Department of Urban Studies and Planning 
   Read your essay out loud. 
 
Essay writing can be challenging, there is no doubt.  But, try to think of it as a way you can teach yourself about the 
issues and ideas that are important to you. Who knows, maybe one of these ideas will turn into your thesis!</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
 
 
Cherie Miot Abbanat, Lecturer 
Department of Urban Studies and Planning 
   Is your thesis clear?  Do you need to explain what you are trying to show?  What is your main message  what you really want to say about the topic you have been asked?  Draw a 
big circle around this idea. 
 What claims or assertions can you make that might support your main message?  If you dont have any, you need to check to see if your main message is robust enough. 
 What evidence and examples do you find that support your claims?  If you dont have any, time to do more 
writing and reviewing. 
 
Task 4: Focus on your introduction.  Once you have your fi rst draft written, it is time to edit  -- to scrutinize 
what the creator in you thinks is important.  
 Does your introduction provide some context or backgr ound for the issue and then relate your thesis or 
main message?  If not, why not? 
 Does the last sentence in your introduction draw the reader into the rest of the paper? 
 Does your introduction relate to the essay question?  If you have a specific essay question, your intro must relate directly to the question.  If you have a broad essay question, your response must touch on the issues 
discussed in the question, but usually cannot attend to all the details of the question. 
 
Task 5:  Focus on your supporting paragraphs. 
 Do you develop your main idea in your subsequent paragraphs using assertions and supporting evidence to make your point? If not, start finding evidence and examples to support your points. 
 Do you include lots of shoulds in your writing?  If so, this type of writing can point to assertions without 
evidence and examples to back up claims.  Sometimes  we think if we use strong language --The BRA 
should understand that low income housing is good for all of Boston  we dont need to support our 
statements.  Try to rewrite most of the shoulds out of the response.  Try replacing shoulds with 
coulds to see what happens.  Usually you have to offer more evidence and examples to shore up your 
ideas.   
 
Task 6:  Focus on your conclusion. 
 First, do you have a conclusion? 
 Does your conclusion restate your first paragraph?  If so, delete your conclusion and start again, this is freshman college writing. 
 Does your conclusion synthesize the many ideas discussed in the essay in order to offer your reader more 
insight on the problem?  If not, why not?  If not, what does your conclusion need in order to further the 
main idea that you are discussing?  I know this is hard, but try to push yourself!   
 Did you pull the strings of the analysis together for the reader? 
 Did you show how the chunks of analysis work together?  
 
If you have done all of these things, you are probably done writing and you need to turn to editing.  
 
Task 7:  Take time to edit.  
 Predict three questions your professor will want to ask you about your ideas.   Have these questions been 
answered? 
 Get a friend to read your essay. 
 Proofread.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/guide_dec_memos</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/guide_dec_memos/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
1. Put the main message first and summarize it for the reader in the first paragraph.  
2. Put the most important supporting point with effective heading next. 
3. Put the second most important supporting point next. 
4. Continue to include point afte r point with its effective heading. 
Then: 
A. Read them in sequence out loud to yourself. 
B. RE-Organize your headings to figure out if  there is a more effective way to order them. 
C. Ask yourself again  So What? 
Task 5: Write a first draft 
Now that you have your main message and your headi ngs in the right order, it is time to start 
writing. For this part, you need to consult Task 2  Generating Ideas.  What ideas did you write? 
Do you nee to write more? Less?  To begin wr iting in your categories try the following:   
Raw Text 
1. Pick an effective heading to work on  one th at has a clear message that relates to your main 
message or core idea.  This should be your fa vorite heading  the one you know the most about 
or the one you find most interesting. 
2. Begin to write on your heading section. You c ould free write, brainstorm ideas, or use any of 
the other ideas listed in task 2. The poi nt is to begin to get words on paper. 
Forming Paragraphs 
Once you have your ideas for your paragraphs, you need to organize them into paragraphs.  A 
paragraph is a unit that discusses a single issue or point.  If you wa nt to talk about a new issue, 
you need to have a form a new paragraph. 
Paragraphs have the foll owing characteristics: 
1. They are short 5 to 7 se ntences at most in memos. 
2. Paragraphs have a topic sentence that st ates the main issue that will be discussed. 
3. Paragraphs must be related to the effective heading which is directly related to the papers 
main message. 
4. Paragraphs can provide evidence a nd examples to support the main point. 
5. Paragraphs can have a short conclusion. 
6. Paragraphs use transitional words to connect sentences within the paragraph. 
7. Paragraphs link to the next paragraph or to the next section using a transitional sentence 
(more on this below).   
Cohesive Tissue 
It is not enough to talk about your  ideas in paragraph units.  Paragraphs need to connect to one 
another and to the section that follows.  To create connections we use transition words or 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
phrases. Words such as however or in additi on are general words that can be used.  Other 
words that speak directly to the subject matter tend to be better connectors. 
In addition, transitional sentences are used by writers to connect paragraphs together.  Sentences 
such as As we will see below, there are three major considerations that. 
Task 6: Edit for clarity, concis eness, accuracy, visual design, and 
tone. 
Once you are finished composing, you need to begin th e editing process.  It is best if you can ask 
a friend to read your work for you so that you can get a fresh pair of eyes to help you find 
mistakes.  Here are some general strategies.  
Read your memo out loud. 
Read you memo backwards one sentence at a time. 
Check for typos. 
Put your work aside for a few hours, a day in order to make sure it reads well. 
Check for effective word choice.
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>__________________________________________________________________________ 
___________________________________________________________________________ 
___________________________________________________________________________ 
______________________________________________________________________________ 
______________________________________________________________________________ 
Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
Task 1: Analyze your audience and purpose 
1. 	Purpose: 
Why am I writing this?  _______________________________________________ 
What do I want the reader to do?  ______________________________________ 
2. 	Audience: 
Who exactly is my reader? Do I have more than one reader? ________________ What is the readers role: decision make r?  Implementer?  Influencer? Other? 
What does the reader know about my subject? ____________________________ 
How will my reader react to my main message? Receptive? Indifferent? 
Resistant?__________________________________________________________________ 
Whats in it for the reader? Why shou ld the reader read this or agree with it?  
What issues could affect this communi cation?  Ethnic? Corporate? Language? 
3. Main Message: 
If the reader were in an elevator and th e doors were closing, what would I yell to 
that person to remember as my main message? 
Once you have your main message  ask the following questions: 
  So what? 
  Who cares?
Could I be wrong? 
Task 2: Generate ideas 
1. Brainstorming 
A. Brainstorming technique  write as many ideas as you can down without thinking or 
editing them. 
Or 
B. 	 Draw a circle in the middle of a piece of paper. 
Write your main message in the circle. 
Write your ideas on spokes that su rround and connect to the main message. 
Number your ideas in order of importance. 
2. Free writing technique   write for 5 minutes without stopping.  You are not allowed to take 
your pen off your paper or stop. If you dont know what to say, just keep writing I dont know 
what to say 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>------------------------------------ ----------------- ------------------ ----------------- --------------- 
----------------------------- --------------------------------------------------- 
----------------------------- --------------------------------------------------- 
Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
Guidelines for Decision Memos 
So, you have to write a decision memo and youre wondering what is a decision memo anyway? 
What do these Gateway people really want from me ?  What do I know about some dam in India?   
I know these assignments can be frustrating, especially when you feel you dont have enough 
time, but there is a purpose.  The public housing case was meant to introduce you to the fast pace 
of the class, but provide most  everything you need  predigeste d cases  so that you wouldnt 
have too many loose ends.  The Narmada case asks you to stretch a bit more.  We want to know 
if you can take a very open ende d case, with many players and many issues and find some way to 
make sense of the mess.  In other words, can you offer guidance to a lead ing international World 
Bank Council? 
Here is one strategy with 6 tasks that are explained in detail below: 
PLAN 
Task 1: Analyze your audien ce and define your purpose 
Task 2: Generate ideas 
Task 3: Group information under headlines 
Task 4: Sequence your ideas 
DRAFT 
Task 5: Write a first draft 
EDIT 
Task 6: Edit for clarity, concis eness, accuracy, visual design, and 
tone. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
3. Questioning  for 5 minutes write as many questions as you can about your subject with out 
stopping to consider whether they make sense. 
4. Dictation  Dictate your ideas into  a digital recorder. 
Task 3: Group information under headlines 
1. Memo categories that can double as headlines 
Summary Analysis Proposal 
Action Steps Rational Specifications 
Action Requested Analysis of data Summary 
Next steps   Implementation Plan Conclusion 
2. Creating Effective headings 
The purpose of headings is two-fold. First, headings guide the reader to the important 
information.  Second, the headings give the reader  a message about the content in that section.  
When finished, the reader should be able to get a full sense of the memo just by reading the title 
and the headings that you write.  If you still havent found your ma in message, turn your topics 
into statements and see if your main message surfaces.   
Category 	 Effective Heading 
Actors 	     Four Groups of Actors argued four different strategies in  
     t h e N a r m a d a C a s e 
Top Down Planning 	 Planning from the t op cannot be completely dismissed as a  
     mechanism for affecting change 
Transnational Factors   Transnational Acto rs are often not cons idered in planning a 
large-scale project  a mistake that can lead to. 
Task 4: Sequence your ideas 
It is not enough to just figure out the points you want to make  and your main message, you need 
to put them in an effective order.  To do this, take a look at the headi ngs you wrote for Task 3 
and number them in order of importance.  Once you do this, you need to study them to find out 
how read, one after to the other. In other wo rds, your headings, need to flow in the right 
direction when your read them. 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/oralpresentation</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/oralpresentation/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>0</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 8
Non Linear Structure -- Hub and 
Spoke ModelStructure
Image courtesy of  the US Department of Transportation &lt;ht tp://ostpxweb.dot.gov&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 18
What about Context?Content
16
14
12
10
8
1951 1953 1955 1957 1959New York
Massachusetts
Connecticut
Rhode Island
Traffic Deaths per 100,000 Person in Connecticut, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, and New York, 1951-1959
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 29
Lack of Graphical IntegrityContent
Image removed due to 
copyright restrictions.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 33
Content
Image removed due 
to copyright restrictions.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 6
Middle -- Choose a Framework
Cause/Effect
Problem/Solution
Categories or elements of the problem
Questions/Answers
Chronological  historical backgroundStructure</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 20
What about Size? Content
Image courtesy of the CIA &lt;http://www.cia.gov&gt;Windward passageNorth Atlantic 
ocean
Golfe de le Gonave
Caribbean SeaJeremie
JacmelMiragoaneSaint-MarcPort-de-Paix
Les CayesHincheCUBA
Dominican RepublicPORT-AU-PRINCEHispaniolaGonaivesCap-Haitienlie de la Tortue
lie de la Gonave
0
030
3060 km
60 ml
Figure by MIT OCW. Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 9
Content is Key!!Content
Image removed due to 
copyright restrictions.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 2
The Tasks.
DeliveryStructure Content</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 14
What does the Audience Expect?
Time (min) Temperature (C)
02 5
32 7
62 9
93 1
12 32
15 32Content</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 5
Begin with the End
What is the Purpose of the Presentation? 
What Problem are you working on?
Roadmap  what structure do you use?Structure</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 41
Did you prepare for questions?
Listen actively (nod, make eye contact)
Answer the question and move on 
Say you dont know, if you dont know
State that you will supply answers later, 
if necessaryDelivery</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 39
The Presentation Doesnt Live on 
the Screen
Say more than 
you show
Hand-out more 
than you say
Leave paper trailDelivery</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 1
Effective Oral Presentations
11.225
Fall 2006
Cherie Miot Abbanat
Department of Urban Studies and Planning</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 32
What can you do to help a child in China 
stay in school?Image removed due 
to copyright restrictions.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 19
Does Image Quality Matter?
Consider size 
Choose colors with care
Make data accessibleContent</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 13
What does the Audience Expect?
t (time)= 15, T (temperature)=32; t=0, 
T=25; t=6, T=29; t=3, T=27; t=12, 
T=32;t=9, T=31Content</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 16
What about Context?Content
325
300275
1955 1956Before Stricter Enforcement
After Stricter EnforcementNearly all the important questions are left unanswered by this display: 
Connecticut traffic deaths, Before (1955) 
and after (1956) stricter enforcement by the police against cars exceeding speed limit.
Graphics Must not Quote Data Out of Context
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 43
The Tasks.
DeliveryStructure Content</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 40
The Presentation Flows Through 
You
Weave a story 
Why is this 
interesting?
Include stories, examples, 
evidence?Delivery</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 12
Visual Arguments Need Evidence
Present evidence
Teach with evidence
Convince with 
evidence Content</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 21
What about Colors?Content
JAPAN SEAJAPAN
BASIN
YAMATO 
RIDGEMURORAN35003000500
20002000
TRENCH 
RISE
20001000
HOKKAIDO
VLADIVOSTOKMetres
Metres7000
6000
5000
4000
3000
2000
1000
500
200
7000600050004000300020001000500200Sea Level
Hypsometric / Teintes Hypsometriques
Area below sea level regions
 sous niveau de la merBathymetric Tints / Teintes Bathymeriques
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 27
Where Does the Reader want to Focus?Content
Image removed due 
to copyright restrictions.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>43</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 44
Sources
Purpose, Movement, Color: 
A Strategy for Effective Presentations
Tom Mucciolo and Rich Mucciolo, MediaNet, Inc., 
1994
The Quick and Easy Way to Effective Speaking
Dale Carnegie, Dale Carn egie Associates, Inc., 1962
The Visual Display of Quantitative Information
Edward R. Tufte, Graphics Press, 1983</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 25
Focus on the Overall Composition
What is the eye drawn to?
Where does the reader want to focus?
Less is More
Avoiding chart junkContent</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 23
What about Colors?Content
Figure by MIT  OCW .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 15
What does the Audience Expect?
Temperature (C) Time (min)
25 0
27 3
29 6
31 9
32 12
32 15Content</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 11
Content and Visual Aids 
Keep them simple
Average attention span
per slide is 8 seconds
Use examples and metaphor
The stretching of vorticity is a 
difficult physical concept, but 
comparing it to a skater's 
conservation of momentum 
helps to clarify what we meanContent</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 42
Can you finish strong?
Structure  pick one
Content is key! -- What was your primary 
message?
Delivery  -- Rehearse, rehearse, rehearseDelivery Content --&gt; Structure --&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 10
Content is Key.
Know your project 
Collect more information than you will 
use
Focus on graphs and charts
Anticipate problem areasContent</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 17
What about Context?Content
325
300
275
250
225
1951 1953 1955 1957 1959A few more data points add immensely to the account:
Connecticut Traffic Deaths, 
1951-1959
Figure by MIT OCW .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 26
What is the eye drawn to?Content
Image removed due 
to copyright restrictions.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 34
Prepare the Delivery
Focus and center 
yourself
Be excited about your subject
Be yourselfdont imitate others stylesDelivery</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 36
Rehearse non-verbal 
communicationDelivery
NON-VERBAL COMMUNIATION
SPEAKS LOUDLY
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 4
Structure the Presentation
Beginning
Middle 
EndState the Issue
Tell us why it is 
interesting
Choose a framework 
Analyze the parts of 
the issue
Show how the parts 
fit with the whole
Recap/Synthesis/ Next StepsStructure</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 30
Faulty ComparisonsContent
Image removed due 
to copyright restrictions.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 35
Did you rehearse?
Practice and time briefing at least 6 times
Get feedback 
Is your content clear?
Do you rock, squirm, gesture too much?
Is there room for improvements/adjustments?
What 3 questions will your audience ask 
you?Delivery</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 38
How do you connect with your 
audience?
A presentation is two-way
communication
Pay attention to audience reaction
Modify your talk as needed (are they listening or 
reading email?)
Look for nods, smiles and strange looks to determine if your message is being received.Delivery</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 22
What about Colors?Content
JAPAN  SEAVLADIVOSTOK
BASIN
YAMATO 
RIDGE
YAMTO 
BASINJAPAN
MURORAN
TRENCH 
RISEHOKKAIDO3000
35003500
2000200020001000500
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 24
Make Data AccessibleContent
10.0
8.0
13.0
9.0
11.0
14.06.0
4.0
12.0
7.0
5.08.04
6.95
7.58
8.81
8.33
9.967.24
4.26
10.84
4.82
5.6810.0
8.0
13.0
9.0
11.0
14.06.0
4.0
12.0
7.0
5.09.14
8.14
8.74
8.77
9.26
8.106.13
3.10
9.13
7.26
4.7410.0
8.0
13.0
9.0
11.0
14.06.0
4.0
12.0
7.0
5.07.46
6.77
12.74
7.11
7.81
8.846.08
5.39
8.15
6.42
5.738.0
8.0
8.0
8.0
8.0
8.08.0
19.0
8.0
8.0
8.06.58
5.76
7.71
8.84
8.47
7.045.25
12.50
5.56
7.91
6.89
10 20510
5 15 10 205 15
10 20510
5 15 10 205 15X Y X Y X Y X YI II III IV
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 28
What are Credible Visual 
Arguments?
The integrity of the graphic is key
Include careful comparisons
Document everythingContent</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 31
What are Emotional Arguments?
Have a single message
Appeal to our hearts
Stir us inside
Move us to action
Include evidence and examplesContent</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 3
Unmask your Audience
Race
Gender
Generation
Affiliation
Size
Attitude
Education
Economic status</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 7
End With Your Message
Highlight Major 
Points
Summarize Recommendations
Synthesize in light of problem/purpose
Outline next steps!Structure
Project Progress
Change Requests
Issues
Other InformationS
Y
N
T
H
E
S
I
Z
EStatus Report
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 37
How do you connect with the 
audience?
Use the terms that your audience knows
Use examples to explain new ideas
Engage the audience
Establish eye contact; look at people not the screen
Use friendly hand gestures
Speak to specific individuals if you know themDelivery</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/guide_pres</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/guide_pres/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
Task 2.  Focus on the parts of the briefing  Introduction, Analysis, Conclusion 
	Craft the Introduction  Here you introduce the issue(s) and tell a portion of the story.  This means that 
you get to present the first piece of th e whole picture, so present it well.  
o	Introduce team members -- Say who you are (a consulting group, a task force, etc.) 
o	Say who the audience is (homeowner s, residents, academics, etc.) 
o	State the purpose of the briefing  Describe the issue for the audience 
o	Outline the entire briefing for the audience 
	Focus the Content/Analysis - The body of the briefing, like a memo, is  where the analysis goes.  Here you 
want to show the decision maker the analysis that she will need to make her decision. 
o	Break down analysis into  chunks and assign each chunk to a team member (most important piece 
goes first) 
o	For each chunk, highlight its main points 
o	Show data, charts, graphs, photos as part of the analysis 
o	Decide -- does this individual piece have its own conclusion? Action steps? 
o	Make sure that one chunk doesnt out pace other chunks in terms of depth, analysis and visual 
effectiveness  remember youre a team. 
	Nail down your Conclusion  Synthe size, synthesize, synthesize -- Briefings have conclusions that 
synthesize the information for the listener and outline the next steps.  It can be about recommending a 
specific action or providing a variet y of well-analyzed options.  As th e wrap-up presenter, can you: 
o	Pull the strings of the analysis together for the listener? 
o	Show how the chunks of analysis work together (even though they were presented by different team members)? 
o	Tell your audience/decision makers what the next steps/next area of analysis, next study should 
be? 
Task 3.  Get Ready for Questions and Answers --  Everyone in the team must be ready for Q&amp;A.  So, everyone 
needs to focus. 
1.	Predict three most likely questions you will be asked and prepare answers 
2.	Create back up slides with further analysis and put them at the end of the slide show 
3.	Listen carefully to questioners 
4.	Be brief, be concise and be understanding 
5.	If you dont know, dont pretend to know 
6.	Dont meet a rude question with a rude answ er  be polite and diplomatic and move on 
7.	Respond with br ief examples 
8.	Pause briefly before you answer  this shows that you have considered the question  
9.	Decide who will field which types of questions</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
Guidelines for Effective Briefings 
Can you get up on your feet with only a weeks notice and speak on a topic you just learned something about? We 
want to know.  Can you digest the history, the context, the social engineering and mis-engineering, successes and 
failures and report on these to an audience?  We want to know. And, can you coordinate with a group, can you 
create a set of effective written and visual materials, can you be enthusiastic, fun and entertaining? We want to 
know. 
So, we designed these oral briefings to challenge you in many ways that we believe you will be challenged when you get out of MIT.  The real world doesnt provide endle ss time to research, prepare and present.  Many times you 
will be asked to speak on an issue when there is  very limited data, no time and scant resources. 
But, public briefings should be brief and too the point (read:  you wont have to be up there forever). We 
recommend that you focus on the key elemen ts (discussed below) of a briefing:   
 Pick a format  linear or hub/spoke. 
 Provide brief background/context on the issue.  
 Provide a clear structure for the briefing. 
 Provide analysis. 
 Provide a conclusion. 
As with informational memos, your ability to covey complex information simply is key.  Also important is your 
forethought about the concerns of the audience.  Challenge yourself to carefully lay out each critical issue, idea or 
plan and analyze these using a carefully chosen structure (e.g ., pros/cons, long term/short term, then/now).  Think of 
your briefing as way to frame issues and analyze those specif ic issues so that you can feed into a larger decision. 
When you know what your decision maker expects (audience) and you give her what she needs clearly and 
concisely (meeting expectations), you become part of the decision making team. 
Heres one strategy:   
Task 1.  Work as a Team  You will need to decide a few things as a group before you get underway.  The format 
is critical. Remember that there are two approaches  th e linear model and the hub and spoke model.  Both models 
share a priority:  Get the audience info rmed and back up what you say with well-designed visuals.  The difference 
between the two models is high vs. low control over the flow and sequence of information. 
It is likely that your team will have a variety of skill sets.  Some of you will be better a t:  creating slides, presenting, 
coordinating, or ordering take out. Whatever these strengths are, play to them and decide: 
 Who talks when? 
 Who is the techie? 
 Who changes whose slides when different members present? 
 Who is the best speaker (put first or last or use as the moderator (hub/spoke)? 
 Who has the most fear (needs the most encouragement and pr actice with team)?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/analyze_argument</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-225-argumentation-and-communication-fall-2006/resources/analyze_argument/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>How To Analyze an Argument 
 
 
 
Logic 
1.  What is the topic? 
2.  What is the main  claim  main message? 
3.  What are the assertions that support and further the main message? 
4.  Is there evidence to support the assertions? 
 
Ethos -- Credibility  Why should we listen to this author? 
5. Is the author well informed? How do you know? 
6. Does the piece offer different sides of the argument? (counter-
arguments? 
Does the author tell how s/he  is connected to the issue? 
 
Passion  Why should we care?  What is the significance? 
7. What is the tone like?  Engaging?  Defensive?  In other words, do you 
feel like you are talking to someone or do you feel like someone is talking at you? 
8. Does the author say how th e issues affect him/her? 
9. Does the author help you f eel connected to the issue?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
