<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/</course_url>
    <course_title>Calculus of Several Variables</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Mathematics </list>
      <list>Linear Algebra </list>
      <list>Differential Equations </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Forms on Rn</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_34/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;34</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lets gure out what the Hodge star operator does in R3 . Supp ose 
that 
 =dx  dy. 
Then  =  is a 1-form such that 
   =dx  dy  dz. 
It follows that  =dz. Similarly 
(dx  dz)= dy and  (dy  dz =dx). 
Let 
 = f1 dx + f2 dy + f3 dz. 
Putting all of this together, we see that 
d = d(f 1 dx + f2 dy + f3 dz) 
f3 f2 f3 f1 f2 f1 = y  z dx  x  z dy + x  y dz. 
Similarly 
d   = d  (f1 dx + f2 dy + f3 dz) 
= d(f 1 dy  dz  f2 dx  dz + f3 dx  dy) 
f3 f2 f1 =  z + y + x dx  dy  dz 
f1 f2 f3 = + + . x y x 
In other words, 
curl = d and div = d  . 
Note that this points to a way to unify the various versions of the 
fundamen tal theorem of calculus for surfaces and three folds (namely , 
the theor ems of Green, Stokes and Gauss). One can also use this 
notation to express Maxw ells equations quite ecien tly. But these are 
both other stories. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Denition 34.3. A basic k-form on Rn is a formal symb ol 
dxi1  dxi2  ...dxik , 
wher e 1  i1 &lt;i2 &lt; &lt;ik  n A gener al k-form on Rn is any  
expression of the form 
 = fi1i2...ik dxi1  dxi2  ... dxik , 
1i1&lt;i2&lt;&lt;ikn 
wher e fi1i2...ik are smooth functions. 
Note that there are  n ,k 
basic n-forms. 
Supp ose we start with a general 1-form in R3 , 
 = f1 dx + f2 dy + f3 dz. 
We can formally dene a 2-form d as follows: 
d = d(f1 dx + f2 dy + f3 dz) 
=df1  dx +df2  dy +df3  dz 
f1 f1 f1 = x dx + y dy + z dz  dx 
f2 f2 f2 + x dx + y dy + z dz  dy 
f3 f3 f3 + dx + dy + dz  dz x y z 
f2 f1 f3 f1 f3 f2 = x  y dx  dy + x  z dx  dz + y  z dy  dz. 
Note also that if 
 = f12 dx  dy + f13 dx  dz + f23 dy  dz, 
then we can formally dene a 3-form d as follows: 
d = d(f12 dx  dy + f13 dx  dz + f23 dy  dz, ) 
f12 f13 f23
= z  y + x dx  dy  dz.
The nal interesting formal operation on k-forms is:
Denition 34.4. Let  be a k-form on Rn . The Hodge star oper
ator assigns an (n  k)-form  to , which is dene d by the rule: 
()   =dx1  dx2  dxn. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>34. Forms on Rn 
Denition 34.1. A basic 1-form on Rn is a formal symb ol 
dx1,dx2,...,dxn. 
A gener al 1-form on Rn is any expression of the form 
 = f1 dx1 + f2 dx2 + + fn dxn, 
wher e f1,f2,...,fn are smooth functions. 
Note that there are n basic 1-forms. If f is a smooth function, we 
get a 1-form using the forma l rule, 
n f df = dxi. xii=1 
Denition 34.2. A basic 2-form on Rn is any formal symb ol 
dxi  dxj , 
wher e 1  i&lt;j  n.A gener al 2-form on Rn is any expression of 
the form 
 = fij dxi  dxj 
i&lt;j 
wher e f1,f2,...,fn are smooth functions. 
Note that there are  n = n(n  1) ,2 2 
basic 2-forms. 2-forms satisfy the following formal rule, 
dxi  dxj = dxj  dxi. 
Given two 1-forms, 
 = f1 dx1+f2 dx2++fn dxn and  = g1 dx1+g2 dx2++gn dxn,  
we can multiply , using linearit y and skew-comm utativi ty, to get a 2
form  
   = (figj  fj gi)dxi  dxj . 
i&lt;j 
Notice how, using skew-co mmutativit y, we can write everything in 
terms of basic 2-forms. Note also that skew-comm utativit y forces 
dxi  dxi =0. 
More generally: 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Parametrised curves</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Therefore 
(1  e 2)x 2 +2pex + y 2 = p 2 . 
There are three cases. The conic 
C = { (x,y)  R2 | (1  e 2)x 2 +2pex + y 2 = p 2 }, 
is an
  
 

ellipse if |e| &lt; 1 
parab ola if |e| =1 
hyperbola if |e| &gt; 1. 
2Lets supp ose that
|e|
&lt; 1. First divide through by 1  e, 
2pe 1 2 p2 
2 x
+
x +
y =
.
1  e
2 1  e2
 1  e
2 
If we complete the square, then we get
pe 2 1 2 p2 
x +1  e2 +1  e2 y = (1  e2)2 . 
Finally divide through by the RHS to get
2 2 x + pe 
1p 1
ee2 + 

1y 
p 
e2 =1. 
2 
This is the equation of an ellipse. The centre of the ellipse is at 
pe(1  e2 , 0). 
One can check that this means one of the focal points is at the origin. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>, 14. Parametrised Curves 
Denition 14.1. A parametrise d dierentiable curve in Rn is 
a dier entiable function r : I  Rn, wher e I is an open interval in R. 
Remark 14.2. Any open interval I is one of four dier ent forms: 
(a,b); (,b); (a, ); (, )= R, wher e a and b are real numb ers. 
Denition 14.3. The velocity vector at time t of a parametrise d 
dier entiable curve  is the derivative: r : I  Rn 
v(t)= r(t)= Dr(t). 
If v is dier entiable, then the acceleration vector at time t is the 
derivative of the velocity vector: 
a(t)= v(t)= r(t). 
Example 14.4. Let 
r : R  R3 
be given by 
r(t)=(a cos t,a sin t,bt). 
This traces out a helix. The velocity vector is 
v(t)=(a sin t,a cos t,b). 
The acceleration vector is 
a(t)=(a cos t, a sin t, 0). 
The speed, that is the magnitude of the velocity vector, 
v(t) =(a 2 + b2)1/2 , 
is constant. Nevertheless the acceleration vector is not zero, as we are 
travelling on a curve and not a straight line. 
Lets now attac k a very famous problem. Kepler formulated three 
laws of planetary motion, based on extensiv e observ ations of the recorded 
positions of the planets. The rst law states that planets move around 
in ellipses, where the sun is at one focal point of the ellipse; lets see 
how one can deriv e this law from Newtons universal law of gravity. 
Lets put the sun at the origin O of our coordinates. Lets supp ose 
that the plane t is at the point P = P (t) at time t. Then 
r(t): R  R3 , 
is a parametrised dieren tiable curve, where r(t)= OP . 
We will need a simple formula for the vector triple product in R3: 
(u  v)  w=(u w)v  (v w)u. 
One can check this formula using coordinates. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>On the other hand, 
dv d(v  c)a  c = dt  c = dt 
It follows that 
v  c = GMu+ d,
where dis a constan t vector. If we cross both sides with c, then the 
LHS is zero and so the RHS is zero. It follows that d also lies in the 
plane . Dene  to be the angle between dand u. Now 
c2 = c c 
=(r  v) c 
=(v  c) r 
=(GMu+ d) r 
= GMr + rd cos . 
Let c = c and d = d. Then 
2cr = GM + d cos  
p = ,1+ e cos  
where 
2c d p = and e = . GM GM 
Lets express these equations in Cartesian coordinates and not polar 
coordinates. We have 
x = r cos  
y = r sin . 
Therefore 
p = r + er cos , 
so that 
p = r + ex. 
Solving for r, 
r = p  ex. 
Squaring both sides we get 
r 2 =(p  ex)2 . 
That is 
x 2 + y 2 = p 2  2epx + e 2 x 2 . 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Theorem 14.5 (Newton). Supp ose that 
GM r, a =  r3 
for some constants G and M. 
Then r traces out either an ellipse, a parabola or a hyperbola. 
Proof. We have 
d(r  v)= dr v + dv 
dt dt  r  dt 
= v  v + r  a 
= 0+ 0= 0, 
since a and r are parallel by assumption. Hence 
r  v = c, 
a constan t vector. It follows that r and v lie in the plane  through 
the origin and orthogonal to c. 
We may write r = ru, where u is a unit vector. 
d(ru) dr duv = = u+ r. dtdt dt 
It follows that 
c = r  v 
dr du= ru dtu+ ru r dt 
du2 = r.u  dt 
So 
GM dua  c =  r2 u r 2 u dt 
du= GMu u dt 
du= GM  u u  dt  
dudu= GM (uu) dt  (u )u dt 
d(GMu) = . dt 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Cross product</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>vector. On the other hand, we know that w= v. In this case, 
v  w= v  (v) 
= v  v 
= v  v. 
To get from the second to the third line, we just switched the factors. 
But the only vector which is equal to its inverse is the zero vector. 
Lets try to compute the cross product using (3.4). If v =(v1,v2,v3) 
and w=(w1,w2,w3), then 
v  w=(v1 + v2j+ v3k)  (w1 + w2j+ w3k) 
= v1w1(  )+ v1w2(  j) + v1w3(  k) 
+ v2w1(j  )+ v2w2(j  j) + v2w3(j  k) 
+ v3w1(k )+ v3w2(k j) + v3w3(k k) 
=(v2w3  v3w2) +(v3w1  v1w3) k. j +(v1w2  v2w1)
Denition 3.6. A matrix A =(aij ) is a rectangular array of numb ers, 
wher e aij is in the i row and jth column. If A has m rows and n 
columns, then we say that A is a m  n matrix. 
Example 3.7.
A = 21 7= a11 a12 a13 ,02 4 a21 a22 a23 
is a 2  3 matrix. a23 = 4. 
Denition 3.8. If
ab A = cd 
is a 2  2 matrix, then the determinant of A is the scalar 
ab = ad  bc.
cd
If
 
abc
def


 A =
gh i
is a 3  3 matrix, then the determinant of A is the scalar 
abc f
df
d
 e
 e
def
 b
 = a
 + c
hi
g
i
g
h
.
gh i
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>As v, wand v  wform a right-handed triple, it follows that w, v 
and v  wform a left-hand ed triple. But then w, v and v  wform 
a right-handed triple. It follows that 
w = w. vv  
This is (1). 
To check (2), we check that 
(u  (v + w)) x =(u  v + u  w) x,   
for an arbitrary vector x. We rst attac k the LHS. By (3.12), we have 
(u  (v + w)) x =(x  u)(v + w)  
=(x  u) v +(x  u) w 
=(u  v) x +(u  w) x. 
We now attac k the RHS. 
(u  v + u  w) x =(u  v) x +(u  v) x.   
It follows that both sides are equal. This is (2). 
We could check (3) by a similar argumen t. Here is another way. 
(u + v)  w= w (u + v) 
v = w u  w 
= w + w. u  v  
This is (3). 
To prove (4), it suces to prove the rst equal ity, since the fact that 
the rst term is equal to the third term follows by a similar deriv ation. 
If  = 0, then both sides are the zero vector, and there is nothing to 
prove. So we may assume that  = 0. Note rst that the magnitude 
of both sides is the area of the parallelogram with sides v and w. 
If &gt; 0, then v and v point in the same direction. Similarly v  w
and (v  w) point in the same direction. As v, wand v  wfor a 
right-handed set, then so do v, wand (v  w). But then (v  w) is 
the cross product of v and w, that is, 
(v)  w= (v  w). 
If &lt; 0, then v and v point in the opposite direction. Similarly 
v  wand (v  w) point in the opposite direction. But then v, w
and (v  w) still form a right-handed set. This is (4).  
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3. Cross product
Denition 3.1. Let v and wbe two vectors in R3 . The cross product 
of v and w, denote d v  w, is the vector dene d as follows: 
	the length of v  wis the area of the parallelogram with sides v 
and w, that is, vw sin . 
 v  wis ortho gonal to both v and w. 
	the three vectors v, wand v  wform a right-hande d set of 
vectors. 
Remark 3.2. The cross product only makes sense in R3 . 
Example 3.3. We have 
  j  	 k  j = k, k = and  =j. 
By contrast 
j k, j =  and   k=   = k  	 j. 
Theorem 3.4. Let u, v and wbe three vectors in R3 and let  be a 
scalar. 
(1) v  w= w v. 
(2) u  (v + w)= u  v + u  w. 
(3) (u + v)  w= u  w+ v  w. 
(4) (v  w)=(v)  w= v  (w). 
Before we prove (3.4), lets draw some conclusions from these prop
erties. 
Remark 3.5. Note that (1) of (3.4) is what really distinguishes the 
cross product (the cross product is skew commutative). 
Consider computing the cross product of , and j. On the one hand, 
(  )  j= 0  j = 0. 
On the other hand, 
  (  j) =  k= j.
In other words, the order in which we compu te the cross product is 
importan t (the cross product is not associativ e). 
Note that if v and ware parallel, then the cross product is the zero 
vector. One can see this direc tly from the formula; the area of the 
parallelogram is zero and the only vector of zero length is the zero 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Example 3.11. The scalar triple product of , jand kis one. One 
way to see this is geometric ally; the parallelepip ed determine d by these 
three vectors is the unit cube, which has volume 1, and these vectors 
form a right-hande d set, so that the sign is positive. 
Another way to see this is to compute directly 
(  j) k= kk=1. 
Final ly one can use determinants, 
0 
0 10
(  j)
k=
01
 =1.
 
1 
Lemma 3.12. Let u, v and wbe three vectors in R3 . 
Then 
(u  v) w=(v  w) u =( w u) v.  
Proof. In fact all three numbers have the same absolute value, namely 
the volume of the parall elepip ed with sides u, v and w. On the other 
hand, if u, v, and wis a right-handed set, then so is v, wand u and 
vice-v ersa, so all three numbers have the same sign as well.  
Lemma 3.13. Let v and wbe two vectors in R3 . 
Then v = wif and only if v x = wx, for every vector x in R3 .  
Proof. One direction is clear; if v = w, then v x = wx for any vector  
x. 
So, supp ose that we know that v x = wx, for every vector x.  
Supp ose that v =(v1,v2,v3) and w=(w1,w2,w3). If we take x =, 
then we see that 
v1 = v  = w = w1. 
Similarly , if we take x =j and x = k, then we also get 
v2 = v j= wj= w2, 
and 
v3 = v k= wk= w3. 
But then v = was they have the same comp onents.  
Proof of (3.4) . We rst prove (1). Both sides have the same magni
tude, namel y the area of the parallelogram with sides v and w. Further 
both sides are orthogo nal to v and w, so the only thing to check is the 
change in sign. 
4 00</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Note that the cross product of v and wis the (formal) determinan t
jk
v1 v2 v3 
w1 w2 w3 .
Lets now turn to the proof of (3.4). 
Denition 3.9. Let u, v and wbe three vectors in R3 . The triple 
scalar product is (u  v) w. 
The triple scalar product is the signe d volume of the parall elepip ed 
formed using the three vectors, u, v and w. Indeed, the volume of the 
parallelepip ed is the area of the base times the heigh t. For the base, 
we take the parallelogram with sides u and v. The magnitude of u  v 
is the area of this parallelogram. The height of the parallelepip ed, up 
to sign, is the length of wtimes the cosine of the angle, lets call this 
, between u  v and w. The sign is positiv e, if u, v and wform a 
right-hande d set and negativ e if they form a left-hande d set. 
Lemma 3.10. If u =(u1,u2,u3), v =(v1,v2,v3) and w=(w1,w2,w3) 
are three vectors in R3, then 
u1 u2 u3 
v1 v2 v3 
w1 w2 w3 .
 (u  v) w=  
Proof. Wehavealready seen that 
 u  v = jk
u1 u2 u3 
v1 v2 v3 .
If one expands this determinan t and dots with w, this is the same as 
replacing the top row by (w1,w2,w3), 
(u  v) w=  w1 w2 w3 
u1 u2 u3 
v1 v2 v3 .
Finally , if we switc h the rst row and the second row, and then the
second row and the third row, the sign changes twice (whic h makes no
change at all):
(u  v) w=  u1 u2 u3 
v1 v2 v3 .
w1 w2 w3 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Maxima and minima: II</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_21/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>rst equation by the second: 
yx = , xy 
so that y2 = x2 . As x2 + y2 = 2 it follows that x2 = y2 = 1. So x = 1 
and y = 1. This gives four potential points (1, 1), (1, 1), (1, 1), 
(1, 1). Then the maxim um value of f is 1, and this occurs at the 
rst and the last point. The minimum value of f is 1, and this occurs 
at the second and the third point. 
One can also try to param etrise the boundary: 
r(t)= 
2(cos t, sin t). 
So we maximise the comp osition 
h: [0, 2]  R, 
where h(t) = 2cos t sin t. As I = [0, 2] is compact, h has a maxim um 
and minim um on I. When h(t)=0, we get 
cos 2 t  sin2 t =0. 
Note that the LHS is cos 2t, so we want 
cos2t =0. 
It follows that 2t = /2+2m, so that 
t = /4, 3/4, 5/4, and 7/4. 
These give the four points we had before. 
What is the closest point to the origin on the surface 
F = { (x,y,z)  R3 | x  0,y  0,z  0,xyz = p }? 
So we want to minimise the distance to the origin on F . The rst trick 
is to minimise the square of the distance. In other words, we are trying 
to minimise f(x,y,z)= x2 + y2 + z2 on the surface 
F = { (x,y,z)  R3 | x  0,y  0,z  0,xyz = p }. 
In words, given three numbers x , y  0 and z  0 whose product is 
p&gt; 0, what is the minim um value of x2 + y2 + z2? 
Now F is closed but it is not bounded, so it is not even clear that 
the minim um exists. 
Lets use the metho d of Lagrange multipliers. Let 
h: R4  R, 
be the function 
h(x,y,z,)= x 2 + y 2 + z 2  (xyz  p). 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21. Maxima and minima: II 
To see how to maximise and minimise a function on the boundary , 
lets conside a concrete example. 
Let 
K = { (x,y) | x 2 + y 2  2 }. 
Then K is compact. Let 
f : K  R, 
be the function f(x,y)= xy. Then f is continuous and so f achieves 
its maxim um and minim um. 
I. Lets rst consider the interior points. Then 
f(x,y)=(y,x), 
so that (0, 0) is the only critical point. The Hessian of f is 
01 Hf(x,y)= .10 
d1 = 0 and d2 = 1=0 so that (0 , 0) is a saddle point. 
It follows that the maxima and minima of f are on the boundary , 
that is, the set of points 
C = { (x,y) | x 2 + y 2 =2 }. 
II. Let g : R2  R be the function g(x,y)= x2 + y2 . Then the 
circle C is a level curve of g. The original proble m asks to maximise 
and minimise 
f(x,y)= xy subject to g(x,y)= x 2 + y 2 =2. 
One way to proceed is to use the second equation to eliminate a vari
able. The metho d of Lagrange multipliers does exactly the opposite. 
Instead of eliminating a variable we add one more variable, tradition
ally called . So now lets maximise and minimise 
h(x,y,)= f(x,y)  (g(x,y)  2) = xy  (x 2 + y 2  2). 
We nd the critical points of h(x,y,): 
y =2x 
x =2y 
2= x 2 + y 2 . 
First note that if x = 0 then y = 0 and x2 + y2 = 0 = 2, impossible. 
So x = 0. Similarly one can check that y = 0 and  = 0. Divide the 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>is a point where the sum of the squares is a minim um. 
Here is another such problem. Find the closest point to the origin 
which also belongs to the cone 
2 2 2 x + y = z, 
and to the plane 
x + y + z =3. 
As before, we minimise f(x,y,z)= x2 + y2 + z2 subject to g1(x,y,z)= 
x2 + y2  z2 = 0 and g2(x,y,z)= x + y + z = 3. Introduce a new 
function, with two new variables 1 and 2, 
h: R5  R, 
given by 
h(x,y,z,1,2)= f(x,y,z)  1g1(x,y,z)  2g2(x,y,z) 
= x 2 + y 2 + z 2  1(x 2 + y 2  z 2)  2(x + y + z  3). 
We nd the critical points of h: 
2x =21x + 2 
2y =21y + 2 
2z = 21z + 2 
2 2 2 z = x + y 
3= x + y + z. 
Supp ose we substrac t the rst equation from the second: 
y  x = 1(y  x). 
So either x = y or 1 = 1. Supp ose x = y. Then 1 = 1 and 2 = 0. In 
this case z = z, so that z = 0. But then x2 +y2 = 0 and so x = y = 0, 
which is not possible. 
It follows that x = y, in which case z = 
2x and 
(2 
2)x =3. 
So 
3 3(2 
2) x = = . 2 2 
2 
This gives us two critical points: 
3(2 
2) 3(2 
2) 3
2(2 
2)P1 =( , , )2 2 2 
3(2 + 
2) 3(2+ 
2) 3
2(2 
2)P2 =( , ). 2 2 ,  2 
Of the two, clearl y the rst is closest to the origin. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>To nish, we had better show that this point is the closest to the 
origin on the whole locus 
F = { (x,y,z)  R3 | x 2 + y 2 = z 2 ,x + y + z =3 }. 
Let 
K = { (x,y,z)  F | x 2 + y 2 + z 2  25 }. 
Then K is closed and bounded, whence compact. So f achieves its 
minim um somewhere on K, and so it must achieve its minim um at 
P = P1. Clearly outside f is at least 25 on F \ K, and so f is a 
minim um at P1 on the whole of F . 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>We look for the critical points of h: 
2x = yz 
2y = xz 
2z = xy 
p = xyz. 
Once again, it is not possible for any of the variables to be zero. 
Taking the product of the rst three equations, we get 
8(xyz)= 3(x 2 y 2 z 2). 
So, dividing by xyz and using the last equation, we get 
8= 3 p, 
that is 2  = . p1/3 
Taking the product of the rst two equations, and dividing by xy, we 
get 
4= 2 z 2 , 
so that 
1/3 z = p. 
So h(x,y,z,) has a critical point at 
2 (x,y,z,)=(p 1/3 ,p 1/3 ,p 1/3 , 1/3 ). p
We check that the point 
(x,y,z)=(p 1/3 ,p 1/3 ,p 1/3), 
is a minim um of x2 + y2 + z2 subject to the constrain t xyz = p. At this 
point the sum of the square s is 
3p 2/3 . 
1/3Supp ose that x 
3p . Then the sum of the squares is at least 
2/3 1/3 1/33p . Similarly if y 
3p or z 
3p . On the other hand, the 
set 
K = { (x,y,z)  R3 | x  [0, 
3p 1/3],y  [0, 
3p 1/3],z  [0, 
3p 1/3],xyz = p }, 
is closed and bounded, so that f achieves it minim um on this set, which 
we have already decided is at 
(x,y,z)=(p 1/3 ,p 1/3 ,p 1/3),
since f is larger on the boundary. Putting all of this togeth er, the point
(x,y,z)=(p 1/3 ,p 1/3 ,p 1/3),
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Functions</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>7. Functions 
Denition 7.1. A function f : A  B consists of: 
(1)	the set A, which is called the domain of f, 
(2)	the set B, which is called the range of f, 
(3)	a rule which assigns to every element a  A an element b  B, 
which we denote by f(a). 
It is easy to write down examples of functions: 
(1) Let A be the set of all people and let B = [0, ). Let f(x) be 
the heigh t of person x, to the nearest inch. 
(2)	f : R  R given by f(x)= x2 . 
(3)	f : R  [0, ) given by f(x)= x2 . 
(4)	f : [0, )  R given by f(x)= x2 . 
(5)	f : [0, )  [0, ) given by f(x)= x2 . 
(6)	f : R  {0, 1} given by 
0	if x is rational f(x)= 1	if x is irrational. 
(7)	f : N  {0, 1} given by 
0	if x is even f(x)= 1	if x is odd. 
Denition 7.2. If f : A  B and g : B  C are two functions, 
then we can comp ose f and g to get a new function g  f : A  C. 
If a  A, then (gf)(a)= g(f(a)). 
If f : R  R is the function f(x) = sin x and g : R  R is the 
function g(x)=2x, then gf : R  R is the function (gf)(x) = 
2sin x, whilst f  g : R  R 
is the function (f  g)(x) = sin2 
x. 
Denition 7.3. Let f : A  B be a function. 
We say that f is injective if whenever f(a1)= f(a2) for some pair 
a1, a2  A, then in fact a1 = a2. 
We say that f is surje ctive if for every b  B, we may nd an 
a  A such that f(a)= b. 
We say that f is a bijection if f is both injective and surje ctive. 
It is interesting to go through the examples above. The function in 
(1) is neither injectiv e or surjectiv e. Indeed there are lots of people who 
are ve foot nine, so just because there are two people with the same 
heigh t, does not mean they are the same person. So f is not injectiv e. 
On the other hand, there is no person who is a million inches high, so 
f is not surjectiv e either. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>If f : R  R is the function f(x)= x2, then the graph of f is the 
parab ola, y = x2 , 
{ (x,x 2) | x  R } R2 . 
Now supp ose that g : R2  R is the function 
g(x,y)= x 2 + y 2 . 
The graph of g is the set z = x2 + y2 , 
{ (x,y,x 2 + y 2) | (x,y)  R2 } R3 . 
One way to picture g is to slice it using level curves and level sets. 
If g : R2  R is any function, the level curve of g at heigh t c is the 
set 
{ (x,y)  R2 | g(x,y)= c } R2 . 
In the example when f(x,y)= x2 + y2, the level curves are concen tric 
circles of radius c, centred at the origin. If c = 0 the level curve is 
the origin and if c&lt; 0 the level curve is empt y. Note that graph has a 
minim um at the origin. 
If g : R3  R is any function, the level set of g at height c is the set 
{ (x,y,z)  R3 | g(x,y,z)= c } R3 . 
If g(x,y,z)= z  x2  y2 then the level sets are parallel parab oloids. 
It is interesting to try to visualise various functions. If we consider 
f(x,y)= x2 y2, then this is an upside down parab oloid, which has a 
maxim um at the origin. Note that the level curves are the same as the 
level curves for f(x,y)= x2 + y2 (for dieren t values of c, of course). 
Now consider the function f(x,y)= x2  y2 . If we consider xing 
y = b and varying x, then we get a parab ola z = x2  b2 . If we consider 
xing x = a and varying y, then we get an upside down parab ola, 
z = a2  y2 . In fact the origin is a saddle point, a point which is 
neither a maxim um nor a minim um. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The function in (2) is neither injective nor surjectiv e as well. f(1) = 
1= f(1), but 1 =1. There is no real number whose square is 1, so 
there is no real number a such that f(a)= 1. 
The function in (3) is not injectiv e but it is surjectiv e. f(1) = f(1), 
and 1 =1. But if b  0 then there is always a real number a  0 
such that f(a)= b (namely , the square root of b). 
The function in (4) is injectiv e but not surjectiv e. If f(a1)= f(a2), 
then a2 = a2
2. As both a1  0 and a2  0, this implies a1 = a2. On the 1 
other hand, there is still no number whose square is 1. 
The function in (5) is bijectiv e. It is injectiv e, as in (4) and it is 
surjectiv e as in (3). 
The function in (6) is not injectiv e but it is surjectiv e. f(0) = 0 = 
f(1), but 0 = 1. On the other hand, if  b {0, 1} then either b =0 or 
b = 1. But f(0)=0 and f(
2) = 1. 
The function in (7) is not injectiv e but it is surjectiv e. f(0) = f(2) = 
0, but 0 =2. On the other hand, if b {0, 1} then either b = 0 or 
b = 1. But f(0)=0 and f(1) = 1. 
(8) f : R3  R given by f(v)= v. 
(9) f : R3 {0}  R3 given by f(v)= v
v . 
(10) r : R  R3 given by f(t) = (cos t, sin t,t). 
x(11) f : R  (0, ) is given by f(x)= e. 
The funct ion in (8) is neither injectiv e nor surjectiv e. There are 
plenty of unit vectors and there are no vectors of negativ e length. 
The funct ion in (9) is neither injectiv e nor surjectiv e. There are 
plenty of vectors which point in the same direction and the image 
consists of vectors of unit length. 
The function in (10) is injectiv e but not surjectiv e. 
The function in (11) is bijectiv e. If f : A  B is a bijectiv e function, 
then f has an inverse function g : B  A. gf : A  A is the 
identity, it sends a to a. Similarly fg : B  B is the identity, it 
sends b to b. The inverse of the exponential function is the logarithm 
g : (0, )  R given by g(x) = ln x. 
Denition 7.4. If A and B are two sets, the product of A and B, 
denote d A  B is the set of ordered pairs 
A  B{ (a,b) | a  A,b  B }. 
The graph of a function f : A  B is the subset of the product 
{ (a,f(a) | a  A } A  B. 
The product R  R = R2 , R  R2 = R3, and so on. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Flux</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_31/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;31</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Find the ux of the vector eld given by 
  F (x,y,z)= y + zj+ xk, 
through S in the direction of n. 
First we need to parametrise S. We want a right handed triple of 
unit vectors 
(a, b,n) 
which are pairwise orthogonal, so that they are an orthonormal basis. 
Lets take 
221 a=( ,, ). 333
With this choice, it is clear that 
an=0, 
so that a is orthogonal to n, 
b = n a
  
jj
= 1/3 2/3 2/3 
2/32/3 1/3 
= 2/3 +1/3k. j +2/3
This gives us a parametrisation,
g : U  S  W, 
given by 
g(r,)= OP + r cos a+ r sin b 
= (1, 1, 2) + (2r/3cos , 2r/3cos ,r/3cos )+(2r/3sin ,r/3sin , 2r/3sin ) 
= (1+2r/3cos   2r/3sin , 1+2r/3cos  + r/3sin , 2+ r/3cos  +2r/3sin ), 
where 
U = (0, 2)  (0, 2), 
and W is the whole of R3 minus the bounda ry of the disk. 
Now 
g = cos a+ sin b and g = r sin a+ r cos b,r  
and so 
g g = (cos a+ sin b)  (r sin a+ r cos b)r  
= r(cos2  + sin2 )n = r
n. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>and W is the whole of R3 minus the three lines P0P1, P1P2 and P2P0. 
Now 
g g = and P0P2 = (2, 3, 3), P0P1 = (1, 1, 2) = 
s t 
and so
g g
= s  t jk
1 12
3
 2
 3
= 3 +k. j  
Clearly , n and g g have the same direc tion. s  t 
FdS= FdS  
S  SW 
= F(g(s,t)) g g ds dt s  t U 
1  1s 
= (2  s  3t, 1+2s +3t, 1+ s +2t) (3, 1, 1)dt ds 
0 0 1s 1 
= (6  3s  9t  1+2s +3t  1  s  2t)dt ds
0 0 1s 1 
= (4  2s  8t)dt ds
0 0 
1 
4t  2st  4t2 1s ds 0 =
0 
1 
= (4(1  s)  2s(1  s)  4(1  s)2)ds 
0 
1 
= (2s  2s 2)ds 
0 12s3 
2  3 = s
0 
1 = . 3 
Example 31.3. Let S be the disk of radius 2 centred around the point 
P = (1, 1, 2) and ortho gonal to the vector 
1 22 n=( , ). 3, 33
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>31. Flux
Let S  R3 be a smooth 2-manifold and let
g : U  S  W, 
be a dieomorphism. 
Denition 31.1. Let f : S  W  R and F: S  W  R3 be two 
functions, the rst a scalar function and the second a vector eld. We 
dene   g gf dS = f(g(s,t)) s  t  ds dt 
 SW  SW  
FdS= F(g(s,t)) g g ds dt.   s  t SW SW 
The second integral is called the ux of Facross S in the direction 
of 
g g 
n= s  t . 
g g 
s  t  
Note that  
FdS= (FS.
n)d  
SW SW 
Note also that one can dene the line integral of f and Fover the 
whole of S using partitions of unity. 
Example 31.2. Find the ux of the vector eld given by 
F(x,y,z)= yj + xk,  + z 
through the triangle S with vertic es 
P0 = (1, 2, 1) P1 = (2, 1, 1) and P2 = (3, 1, 2), 
in the direction of P0P1  P0P2 n= . 
P0P1  P0P2
First we parametrise S,
g : U  S  W, 
where 
g(s,t)= P0P1 + tOP0 + sP0P2 = (1+ s +2t, 2  s  3t, 1+2s +3t), 
and 
U = { (s,t)  R2 0 &lt;s&lt; 1, 0 &lt;t&lt; 1  s }, | 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Clearly this points in the direct ion of n. 
FdS= FdS  
S  SW  
= F(g(r,)) g g dr d r   U
 2  2
= (1+2r/3cos  + r/3sin , 2+ r/3cos  +2r/3sin , 
0 0 
1+2r/3cos   2r/3sin , )(r/3, 2r/3, 2r/3)dr d.  
Now when we expand the integrand, we will clearly get 
 +  cos  +  sin , 
where ,  and  are ane linear functions of r (that is, of the form 
mr + b). The integral of cos  and sin  over the range [0, 2] is zero. 
Computing, we get 
 = r(1/3 +4/3+2/3) = 7r/3, 
so that  is a linear function of r. Therefore the integral reduces to 
 2  2  227r 7r2 
dr d = d 3 60 0 0 0 2 14 = d 30 
28 = . 3 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Implicit functions</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Similarly 
F f x2 . x2 =  F 
x3 
So 
F f (1, 3) =  x1 (1, 3, 1) 9 ,x1 F (1, 3, 1) = 11x3 
and 
f F (1, 3, 1) 0 x2 
x2 (1, 3) =  F (1, 3, 1) = 11 =0. 
x3 
Denition 13.2. Let A  Rn be an open subset and let f : Rn  R 
be a function. 
The directional derivative of f in the direction of the unit vector 
uis 
Duf(P ) = lim f(P + hu)  f(P ) . 
h0 h
If u =ei then,
f
Dei f(P )= (P ),xi 
the usual partial deriv ative. 
Prop osition 13.3. If f is dier entiable at P then 
Duf(P )= Df(P ) u. 
Proof. Since A is open, we may nd &gt; 0 such that the param etrised 
line 
r :(,)  A, 
given by r(h)= f(P )+ huis entirely contained in A. Consider the 
comp osition of r and f, 
f  r : R  R. 
Then 
Duf(P )= d(f  r) (0)dh 
= D(r(0)) Dr(0) 
= Df(P )  u. 
Note that we can also write 
Duf(P )= f(P ) u. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>be the function 
F (x1,x2,y)= x 3
1x2  x2y 2 + y 5 +1. 
Let 
S = { (x1,x2,y)  R3 | F (x1,x2,y)=0 }. 
Then (1, 3, 1)  S. Lets compute the partial deriv atives of F , 
F 2(1, 3, 1) = 3x x1 1x2 =9
(1,3,1) 
F 3 2(131)=( )xy ,, 1x2 (131),,=0
F 
y (1, 3, 1) = (2x2y +5y 4) = 11.
(1,3,1) 
So 
DF (1, 3, 1) = (9, 0, 11). 
Now what is importan t is that the last entry is non-zero (so that the 
1  1 matrix (1) is invertible). It follows that we may nd open subsets 
(1, 3)  U  R2 and 1  V  R and a C1 function f : U  V such 
that 
F (x1,x2,f(x1,x2)) = 0. 
It is not possible to write down an explicit formula for f, but we can 
calculate the partial deriv atives of f. 
Dene a functio n 
G: U  R, 
by the rule 
G(x 1,x2)= F (x1,x2,f(x1,x2)) = 0. 
On the one hand, 
G G =0 and =0. x1 x2 
On the other hand, by the chain rule, 
G = F x1 + F x2 + F f 
x1 x1 x1 x2 x1 x3 x1 
Now 
x1 = 1 and x2 = 0. x1 x1 
So 
F f x1 . x1 =  F 
x3 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>13. Implicit functions 
Consider the curve y2 = x in the plane R2 , 
C = { (x,y)  R2 | y 2 = x }. 
This is not the graph of a functio n, and yet it is quite close to the graph 
of a function. 
Given any point on the graph, lets say the point (2, 4), we can always 
nd open intervals U containing 2 and V containing 4 and a smooth 
function f : U  V such that C  (U  V ) is the graph of f. 
Indeed, take U = (0, ), V = (0, ) and f(x)= x. In fact, 
we can do this for any point on the graph, apart from the origin. If 
it is above the x-axis, the function above works. If the point we are 
interested in is below the x-axis, replac e V by (0, ) and f(x)= x, 
by g(x)= x. 
How can we tell that the origin is a point where we cannot dene an 
implicit function? Well away from the origin, the tangen t line is not 
vertical but at the origin the tangen t line is vertical. In other words, if 
we consider 
F : R2  R, 
given by F (x,y)= y2  x, so that C is the set of points where F is 
zero, then 
DF (x,y)=(1, 2y). 
The locus where we run into trouble, is where 2y = 0. Somewhat 
amazingly this works in general: 
Theorem 13.1 (Implicit Function Theorem) . Let A  Rn+m be an 
open subset and let F : A  Rm be a C1-function. Supp ose that 
(a,b)  S = { (x,y)  A | F (x,y)= 0 }. 
Assume that   Fidet =0. yj 
Then we may nd open subsets a  U  Rn and b  V  Rm, wher e 
U  V  A and a function f : U  V such that S  (U  V ) is the 
graph of f, that is, 
F (x,y)= 0 if and only if y = f(x). 
wher e x  U and y  V . 
Lets look at an example. Let 
F : R3  R, 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Note that the directional deriv ative is largest when 
f(P ) u= , f(P ) 
so that the gradien t always points in the direction of maximal change 
(and in fact the magnitude of the gradien t, gives the maxim um change). 
Note also that the directional deriv ative is zero if u is orthogonal to 
the gradien t and that the directional deriv ative is smallest when 
u = f(P ) . f(P ) 
Prop osition 13.4. If f(P )=0 then the tangent hyperplane  to 
the hypersurfac e 
S = { Q  Rn | f(Q)  f(P )=0 }, 
is the set of all points Q which satisfy the equation 
f(P ) PQ =0. 
Remark 13.5. If f is C1, then f is the graph of some function, locally 
about P . 
Proof. By denition, the point Q belongs to the tangen t hyperplane if 
and only if there is a curve 
r :(,)  S, 
such that 
r(0) = P and PQ. r(0) = 
Now, since r(h)  S for all h  (,), we have F (r(h))=0. So 
dF (r(h))0 = (0)dh 
= F (r(0)) r(0) 
= F (P )  PQ.  
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Triple integrals</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_24/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>wher e : D  R and : D  R are continuous functions. 
Type 2: D = 23(W ) is an elementary region and 
W = { (x,y,z)  R2 | (y,z)  D,(y,z)  x  (y,z) }, 
wher e  : D  R and  : D  R are continuous functions. 
Type 3: D = 13(W ) is an elementary region and 
W = { (x,y,z)  R2 | (x,z)  D,(x,z)  y  (x,z) }, 
wher e  : D  R and  : D  R are continuous functions. 
Type 4: W is of type 1, 2 and 3. 
The solid pyramid is of type 4. 
Theorem 24.8. Let W  R3 be an elementary r egion and let f : W  
R be a continuous function. 
Then 
(1) If W is of type 1, then 
   (x,y )  
f(x,y,z)dx dy dz = f(x,y,z)dz dx dy. 
W 12(W ) (x,y ) 
(2) If W if of type 2, then 
   (y,z)  
f(x, y, z) dx dy dz = f(x, y, z) dx dy dz. 
W 23(W ) (y,z) 
(3) If W if of type 3, then 
   (x,z )  
f(x,y,z)dx dy dz = f(x,y,z)dy dx dz. 
W 13(W ) (x,z ) 
Lets gure out the volume of the solid ellipsoid: 
W = { (x,y,z)  R3 |  x
a 2 
+  y
b 2 
+  z
c 2 
 1 }. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>||   
 Prop osition 24.4. Let W  R2 be a bounde d subset and let f : W  
R and g : W  R be two integrable functions. Let  be a scalar. 
Then 
(1) f + g is integrable over W and    
f(x,y,z)+g(x,y,z)dx dy dz = f(x,y,z)dx dy dz+ g(x,y,z)dx dy dz. 
W W W 
(2) f is integrable over W and   
f(x,y,z)dx dy dz = f(x,y,z)dx dy dz. 
W W 
(3) If f(x,y,z)  g(x,y,z) for any (x,y,z)  W , then   
f(x,y,z)dx dy dz  g(x,y,z)dx dy dz. 
W W 
(4) fis integrable over W and 
| f(x,y,z)dx dy dz| |f(x,y,z)| dx dy dz. 
W W 
Prop osition 24.5. Let W = W1  W2  R3 be a bounde d subset and 
let f : W  R be a bounde d function. 
If f is integrable over W1 and over W2, then f is integrable over W 
and and W1  W2, and we have 
   
f(x,y,z)dx dy dz = f(x,y,z)dx dy dz+ f(x,y,z)dx dy dz 
W W1 W2 
 f(x,y,z)dx dy dz. 
W1W2 
Denition 24.6. Dene three maps 
ij : R3  R2 , 
by projection onto the ith and jth coordinate. 
In coordinates, we have 
12(x,y,z)=(x,y),23(x,y,z)=(y,z), and 13(x,y,z)=(x,z). 
For example, if we start with a solid pyramid and project onto the 
xy-plane, the image is a squar e, but it project onto the xz-plane, the 
image is a triangle. Similarly onto the yz-plane. 
Denition 24.7. A bounde d subset W  R3 is an elementary sub
set if it is one of four types: 
Type 1: D = 12(W ) is an elementary region and 
W = { (x,y,z)  R2 | (x,y) 
2 D,(x,y)  z  (x,y) },</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24. Triple integrals 
Denition 24.1. Let B =[a,b]  [c,d]  [e,f]  R3 be a box in space. 
A partition P of R is a triple of sequenc es: 
a = x0 &lt;x1 &lt; &lt;xn = b 
c = y0 &lt;y1 &lt; &lt;yn = d 
e = z0 &lt;z1 &lt; &lt;zn = f. 
The mesh of P is
m(P) = max{ xi  xi1,yi  yi1,zi  zi1 | 1  i  k }.
Now supp ose we are given a function
f : B  R
Pick
cijk  Bijk =[xi1,xi]  [yj1,yj ]  [zi,zi1]. 
Denition 24.2. The sum 
nn	n
S = f(cijk)(xi  xi1)(yj  yj1)(zi  zi1), 
i=1 j=1 k=1 
is called a Riemann sum . 
Denition 24.3. The function f : B  R is called integrable, with 
integral I, if for every &gt; 0, we may nd a &gt; 0 such that for every 
mesh P whose mesh size is less than , we have 
|I  S| &lt; , 
wher e S is any Riemann sum associate d to P. 
If W  R3 is a bounded subset and f : W  R is a bounded 
function, then pick a box B containing W and extend f by zero to a 
function f: B  R, 
f(x)=	x if x  W 
0 otherwise. 
If f is integrable, then we write	  
f(x,y,z)dx dy dz = f(x,y,z)dx dy dz. 
W	 B 
In particular  
vol(W )= dx dy dz. 
W 
There are two pairs of results, which are much the same as the results 
for double integrals: 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>This is an elemen tary region of type 4.  
vol(W )= dx dy dz 
W 
 a  bq
1(x ) cq
1(x
a )(y
b ) 
2 2 2 
a 
=  q q dz dy dx 
2 2 2 a b1(ax )c1(x
a )(y
b )
2  a  bq
1(x ) x 2  y 2  
a 
=  q 2c dy dx 
2 1  a  ba b1(x
a )
2  a  bq
1(x ) x 2  y 2  
a 
=2c  q 1  dy dx 
2 a  ba b1(x
a )
  q  
2c ab1(x
a )2  x 2 
=  qb2 2 dy dx 1  yb a b1(x )2 a 
a 
c  a  x 2  
= b2 1  dx b a a
a  x 2 
= bc dx 1  a a 3 a x= bc x  3a2 
 a3a= bc 2a  2 3a2
4
= abc. 3 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Stokes theorem</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_32/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;32</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>It follows that
 j k 
x y z 
u u u x y z 
v v v g g
= u  v 
(y,z)   (x,z) (x,y) = j+ k. (u,v) (u,v) (u,v) 
So, 
curl Fg g = F3 F2 (y,z)+ F3 F1 (x,z)+ F2 F1 (x,y) . uv y  z (u,v) x  z (u,v) x  y (u,v) 
On the other hand, if one looks at the proof of the second step of 
Greens theorem, we see that 
G2 G1 ,u  v 
is also equal to the RHS (in fact, what we calculated in the proof of 
Greens theorem was the third term of the RHS; by symmetry the other 
two terms have the same form). This is (1). 
For (2), lets paramet rise H2  U by x(u) =(u, 0) and S  W by 
s(u) = g(x(u)). Then 
Fds = Fds  
S SW b 
= F(s(u)) s(u)du 
a
 b
= F(g(x(u))) Dg(x(u))x(u)du 
a
 b
= G(x(u)) x(u)du 
a 
= G. ds 
H2U 
= G. ds, 
H2  
and this is (2).  
This completes step 2. 
Step 3: We again use partitions of unity. It is straigh tforw ard to 
cover the bounded set K by nitely many compact subsets K1,K2,...,Kk, 
such that given any smooth vector eld which is zero outside Ki, then 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>the conditions of step 2 hold. By using a partition of unity, we can nd 
smooth functions 1,2,...,k such that i is zero outside Ki and 
k
1= i. 
i=1 
Multiplying both sides of this equation by F, we have 
k
F= Fi, 
i=1 
where Fi = iFis a smooth vector eld, which is zero outside Ki. In 
this case 
 k 
curl FdS= curl Fi  dS  
Si=1 S 
k 
= Fi  ds 
i=1 M 
= Fds.   
M 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>and so the result reduces to Greens Theorem. This comp letes step 1. 
Step 2: We supp ose that there is a compact subset K  S and a 
parametrisation 
g : H2  U  S  W, 
which is compatible with the orien tation, such that 
(1) F(x)= 0 if x  S  K, and 
(2) K  S  W .
Dene a vector eld G: H2
 R2 by the rule 
G(u,v)= F(g(u,v))  Dg(u,v)(u,v)  U 
0 (u,v) /U. 
Note that 
x y z G1(u,v)= F1 + F2 + F3u u u 
x y z G2(u,v)= F1 + F2 + F3 . v v v 
Using step 1, it is enough to prove: 
Claim 32.4. 
(1) 
curl S 
H2 u  v du dv. F.d= G2 G1 
S 
(2) 
Fds = Gds. 
S H2 
Proof of (32.4) . Note that 
curl F
=
 j k 
   
x y z 
F1 F2 F3 
F3 F2 F3 F1 F2 F1  = y  z   x  z j+ x  y k. 
On the other hand, 
gx y z  =  + j+ k u u u u 
gx y z  =  + j+ k. v v v v 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>32. Stokes Theorem 
Denition 32.1. We say that a vector eld 
, F: A  Rm 
has comp act supp ort if there is a compact subset K  A such that 
F(x)= 0, 
for every x  A  K. 
If S  R3 is a smooth manifold (possibly with bounda ry) then we 
will call S a surfac e. An orientation is a continuous choice of unit 
normal vector. Not every surface can be oriented. Consider for example 
the Mobius band , which is obtained by taking a piece of paper and 
attac hing it to itself, except that we add a twist. 
Theorem 32.2 (Stok es Theorem). Let S  R3 be a smooth oriente d 
surfac e with boundary and let F: S  R3 be a smooth vector eld 
with compact support. 
Then   
curl FdS= Fds, 
S S 
wher e S is oriente d compatibly with the orientation on S. 
Example 32.3. Let S be a smooth 2-manifold that looks like a pair 
of pants. Choose the orientation of S such that the normal vector is 
pointing outwar ds. Ther e are three oriente d curves C1, C2 and C3 (the 
two legs and the waist). Supp ose that we are given a vector eld Bwith 
zero curvatur e. Then (32.2) says that   
Bds + Bds + Bds = curl BdS=0.   
C3 C1C2S 
Here C1and C2denote the curves C1 and C2 with the opposite orien
tation. In other words,
Bds = Bds + Bds.  
C3 C1 C2 
Proof of (32.2) . We prove this in three steps, in very much the same 
way as we proved Greens Theorem. 
Step 1: We supp ose that M = H2  R2  R3, where the plane is 
the xy-plane. In this case, we can take n= k, and this induces the 
standard orien tation of the boundary . Note that 
curl Fn= F2 F1 , x  y 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Inclusion-exclusion</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_23/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;23</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>To integrate f over D1, break D1 into three parts. 
  3  (x)  
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dy dx 
D1 3 (x) 
 1  
9x 
2 
= f(x,y)dy dx 
3 0 
 1  
9x 
2 
+ f(x,y)dy dx 
21 
1x
 3  
9x 
2 
+ f(x,y)dy dx. 
1 0 
One can do something similar for D2. 
Example 23.3. Supp ose we are given that 
  1  2y  
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dx dy. 
D 0 y 
What is the region D? 
It is the region bounde d by the two lines y = x and x =2y and 
between the two lines y =0 and y =1. 
Change order of integration: 
  1  x  2  1  
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dx dy+ f(x,y)dx dy. 
D 0 x/2 1 x/2 
Example 23.4. Calculate the volume of a solid ball of radius a. Let 
B = { (x,y,z)  R3 | x 2 + y 2 + z 2  a 2 }. 
We want the volume of B. Break into two pieces. Let 
B+ = { (x,y,z)  R3 | x 2 + y 2 + z 2  a 2 ,z  0 }. 
Let 
D = { (x,y)  R2 | x 2 + y 2  a 2 }. 
Then B+ is bounde d by the xy-plane and the graph of the function 
f : D  R, 
given by 
f(x,y)= a2  x2  y2 . 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>It follows that 
vol(B+)= a2  x2  y2 dy dx 
 aD 
ax 
2 2 
= a2 2 2 dy dx 
a x y
 
aa  

a2

xx2 
 
2  
2 2 y= 
a 
ax1  2  x2 
a2  x2 dy dx. 
2 2 a
Now lets make the substitution 
y dyt = so that dt = . 
a2  x2 
a2  x2 
  1  
2vol(B+)= a 
1  t2(a  x 2)dt dx 
a 1  1  
2 = a 
(a  x 2) 
1  t2 dt dx 
a 1 
Now lets make the substitution 
t = sin u so that dt = cos udu. 
 a 2 
vol(B+)= (a 2  x 2) 
 cos 2 u du dx 
2a  
a  = (a 2  x 2)2 dx 
a  2 x3 a 
= a 2 x  3 a 
3a= (a 3  3) 
2a3 
= . 3 
Ther efore, we get the expected answer 
4a3 
vol(B) = 2 vol(B+)= . 3 
Example 23.5. Now consider the example of a cone whose base radius 
is a and whos e height is b. Put the central axis along the x-axis and 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>23. Inclusion-Ex clusion 
Prop osition 23.1. Let D = D1  D2 be a bounde d region and let 
f : D  R be a function. 
If f is integrable over D1 and over D2, then f is integrable over D 
and and D1  D2, and we have 
    
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dx dy+ f(x,y)dx dy f(x,y)dx dy. 
D D1 D2 D1D2 
Example 23.2. Let 
D = { (x,y)  R2 | 1  x 2 + y 2  9 }. 
Then D is not an elementary region. Let 
D1 = { (x,y)  D | y  0 } and D2 = { (x,y)  D | y  0 }. 
Then D1 and D2 are both of type 1. 
If f is continuous, then f is integrable over D and D1  D2. In fact 
D1  D2 = L  R = { (x,y)  R2 | 3  x 1, 0  y  0 } 
{ (x,y)  R2 | 1  x  3, 0  y  0 }. 
Now L and R are elementary regions. We have 
  3  0  
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dy dx =0. 
R 1 0 
Ther efore, by symmetry, 
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dx dy =0 
L R 
and so 
   
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dx dy + f(x,y)dx dy. 
D D1 D2 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>0 the base in the yz-plane. In the xy-plane we get an equilater al triangle 
of height b and base 2a. If we view this as a region of type 1, we have 
x x (x)= a 1  and (x)= a 1  . b b 
We want to integrate the function 
f : D  R, 
given by  2x f(x,y)= a2 1  y2 . b 
So half of the volume of the cone is 
 b  a(1)  2  
  b 2 
)bb
x x x
 x2 a
2 1  b  y2 dy dx = a
1  b dx
2
a(1 0 
 ba2 2xx2 
= 2 0 1  b + b2 dx 
= a2 
2  
x  x2 
b + x3 
3b2 b 
0 
= 1 
6(a2b). 
Ther efore the volume is 
1 
3(a2b). 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Conservative vector fields revisited</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_29/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;29</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>29. Conser vative vector fields revisited
Let U  R2 be an open subset. Given a smooth function f : U  R 
we get a smooth vector eld by taking F= grad f. Given a smooth 
vector eld F: U  R2 we get a function by taking f = curl F. 
Supp ose that M  U is a smooth 2-manifold with boundary . If we 
start with F, then we have 
curl FdA = Fds. 
M M 
Supp ose we start with f, and let C be a smooth orien ted curve. Pick 
a parametrisation, 
x:[a,b]  U, 
such that x(a) = P and x(b)= Q. Then we have 
  b 
grad f ds = grad f(x(t)) x(t)dt   
C a
 b
d = f(x(t))dt dta 
= f(x(b))  f(x(a)) 
= f(Q)  f(P ). 
Denition 29.1. We say that X  Rn is star-shap ed with respect 
to P  X, if given any point Q  X then the point 
P + tPQ  X, 
for every t  [0, 1]. 
In other words, the line segmen t connecting P to Q belongs to X. 
Theorem 29.2. Let U  R2 be an open and star-shap ed let F: U  
R2 be a smooth vector eld. 
The following are equivalent: 
(1) curl F=0. 
(2) F= grad f. 
Proof. (2) implies (1) is easy. 
We check (1) implies (2). Supp ose that U is star-shap ed with respect 
to P =(x0,y0). Parametrise the line L from P to Q =(x,y) as follows 
P + tPQ =(x0 + t(x  x0),y0 + t(y  y0)) = Pt, for 0  t  1. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Dene 
f(x,y)= Fds 
L 1 
= xF1(Pt)+ yF2(Pt)dt. 
0 
Then 
 1f  = (xF 1(x0 + t(x  x0),y0 + t(y  y0)) + yF2(x0 + t(x  x0),y0 + t(y  y0))) dt x 0 x  1 F1 F2 = F1(Pt)+ tx (Pt)+ ty (Pt)dt. x x 0 
On the other hand, 
 F1 F2 
t (tF 1(x0 + t(x  x0),y0 + t(y  y0))) = F1(Pt)+txt F1(Pt)+ty y (Pt). 
Since curl F= 0, we have 
F1 F2 = ,y x 
and so  1f 
x = 
0 F1 
t (Pt) dt = F1(x, y). 
Similarly 
f = F2(x,y). y 
It follows that F= grad f.  
Denition 29.3. Let F: U  R2 be a vector eld. Dene another 
vector eld by the rule 
F : U  R2 wher e  F =(F2,F1). 
Theorem 29.4 (Divergence theorem in the plane) . Supp ose that M 
R2 is a smooth 2-manifold with boundary M. 
If F: U  R2 is a smooth vector eld, then 
div FdA = Fnds, 
M M 
wher e nis the unit normal vector of the smooth oriente d curve C = M 
which points out of M. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Proof. Note that 
curl(F) = div F, 
and 
F  ds =( F n)ds, 
and so the result follows from Greens theorem applied to F.  
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Arclength</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Note that there is an obvious way to get the unit tangen t vector. Take 
the deriv ative and divide by the speed. In fact 
dr(t) dr(s) ds = dt dsdt 
= T(s) ds,dt 
by the chain rule. So 
dr(t) 
T(s)= dt ,ds 
dt 
where the denominator is precisely the speed, so that the unit tangen t 
vector is the unit vector which points in the direction of the velocity. 
Example 15.11. Let r(t)=(a cos t,a sin t) be the standar d parametri
sation of the circle of radius a. Then 
s s = ta so that t = . a 
So   ss r(s)=(a cos ,a sin ), aa 
and   
T(s)=( sin s, cos s ). aa 
Denition 15.12. Let r : I  Rn be a C2 curve such that r(t) = 0 
for all t. 
The curvatur e (s) of r(s) is the magnitude of the vector 
dT(s) ,ds 
and the unit normal vector is the unit vector pointing in the direction 
of 
N(s)= dT(s) . ds 
In the example above, 
dT(s) 1  s  s  
=( cos ,  sin ),dsaa a 
which has length 1/a. So the larger the radius, the smaller the curva
ture (whic h is what one migh t expect). The unit normal vector is 
N(s)=( cos s,  sin s )= r(s). a a 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>, 15. Arclength
Denition 15.1. Let I be an open interval. A partition P of [a,b] 
I is a sequenc e of points 
a = t0 &lt;t1 &lt; &lt;tn = b, 
for some n  1. The mesh of P is 
m(P) = max
i {|ti+1  ti|| 0  i  n  1 }. 
Denition 15.2. Let r : I  Rn be a parametrise d dier entiable 
curve, and let P be a partition. We think of 
n1
l(P)= r(ti+1)  r(ti), 
i=0 
as being an approximation to the length of the curve r([a,b]). 
The curve r has length L if given any &gt; 0, there is a &gt; 0 such 
that for every partition P whose mesh size is less than , we have 
L  l(P) &lt; . 
There are interesting exam ples of curves that dont have a length. 
Start with interval [0, 1] in the plane. The length is 1. Now adjust 
this curve, by adding in a triangular hump in the middle, so that we 
get four line segmen ts of length 1/3. This is a curve of length 4/3. 
Now add a hump to each of the four line segmen ts of length 1/3. 
The length of the resulting curve is (4/3)2 . If we keep doing this, then 
we get more and more complicated curves, whose length at stage n is 
(4/3)n . This process converges to a very pointed curve whose length is 
innite (in fact this curve is a fractal). 
However: 
Prop osition 15.3. If r : I  Rn is a C1-function, then the curve 
r([a,b]) has a length  b 
L = r(t) dt. 
a 
Remark 15.4. The fractal curve above is continuous but it is nowher e 
dier entiable (the curve has too many sharp points). 
In general the exact formula for the arclength is only of theoretical 
interest. However there are some contrived examples where we can 
calculately the arclength precisely . 
Example 15.5. Let 
r : R  R2 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>. One can try to calculate the curvature using the parameter t. By 
the chain rule, 
dT(t) dT(s) ds = . dt dsdt 
So 
dT(s) dT
dt (t) 
= . ds ds 
dt 
The denominator is the speed. It follows that 
N(s) and dT(t) ,dt 
point in the same direction, so that the unit normal vector is the unit 
vector associated to 
dT(t) . dt 
On the other hand, the curvature is 
dT(t) 
dt 
ds 
dt 
Note that the normal vector and the unit tangen t vector are always 
orthogonal. 
Indeed, 
T(s) =1. 
So 
T(s) T(s)=1. 
Dieren tiate both sides with respect to s, to get 
T(s) T(s)+ T(s) T(s)=0.  
It follows that 
2T(s) T(s)=0, 
that is 
T(s) T(s)=0. 
As N(s) points in the same direction as T(s), it follows that the tan
gent vector and the normal vector are orthogonal. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>, 
 , be the parametrise d dier entiable curve given by 
r(t)= a cos t + a sin tj.
Then 
r(t)= a sin t + a cos tj,
and so 
r(t) = a. 
Henc e the length of the curve r([0, 2]) is 
 2 
L = a dt =2a, 
0 
which is indeed the circumfer ence of a circle of radius a. 
Example 15.6. Let 
r : R  R3 
be the parametrise d dier entiable curve given by 
r(t)= a cos tj + bt  + a sin tk, 
Then 
r(t)= a sin tj + b  + a cos tk, 
and so 
r(t) = 
a2 + b2 . 
Henc e the length of the curve r([0, 2]) is 
 2 
L = (a 2 + b2)1/2 dt =2(a 2 + b2)1/2 . 
0 
Example 15.7. Let 
r : R  R2 
be the parametrise d dier entiable curve given by 
r(t)= a cos t + b sin tj.
Then 
r(t)= a sin t + b cos tj,
and so 
r(t) =(a 2 sin2 t + b2 cos 2 t)1/2 
Henc e the length of the curve r([0, 2]) is 
 2 
L = (a 2 sin2 t + b2 cos 2 t)1/2 dt, 
0 
the length of an ellipse, with major and minor axes of length a and b. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Denition 15.8. Let r : 
1 I  Rn be a parametrise d dier entiable 
curve, which is of class C. Supp ose that r(t) is nowher e zero. Given 
a  I, dene the arclength parameter s(t), by the formula 
t 
s(t)= r() d = length of r([a,t]) if t  a
a length of r([t,a]) if t&lt;a.
By the fundam ental theorem of calculus 
d t 
s(t)= r() d dt a 
= r(t), 
which is the speed at time t. Since s(t) is nowhere zero, we can write t 
as a function of s, that is we can write down the inverse function, t(s), 
which will be C1 . 
Example 15.9. For the helix, 
j + b r(t)= a cos t + a sin tkt, 
we have 
1/2 s(t)= t 
r() d = 
a2 + b2 t. 
0 
Ther efore 
s t(s)= .
a2 + b2 
In this case 
r(s)= a cos 
a2 s 
+ b2  + a sin 
a2 s 
+ b2 j+ bk
a2 s 
+ b2 . 
In fact, one can always parametrise a curve by its arclength and in 
this case the deriv ative is a unit vector: 
Denition 15.10. Let r : I  Rn be a parametrise d dier entiable 
curve parametrise d by the arclength. Then 
T(s)= dr,ds
is the unit tangent vector. 
In the case of the helix, we get 
a s a s b  r(s)= 
a2 + b2 sin 
a2 + b2 +
a2 + b2 cos 
a2 + b2 j+ 
a2 + b2 k. 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Vectors in R2 and R3</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Example 1.10. A cycloid is the path traced in the plane, by a point 
on the circumfer ence of a circle as the circle rolls along the ground. 
Lets nd the parametric form of a cycloid. Lets suppose that the 
circle has radius a, the circle rolls along the x-axis and the point is at 
the origin at time t =0. We suppose that the cylinder rotates through 
an angle of t radians in time t. So the circumfer ence travels a distanc e 
of at. It follows that the centre of the circle at time t is at the point 
P =(at,a). Call the point on the circumfer ence Q =(x,y) and let O 
be the centre of coordinates. We have 
(x,y)= OP + OQ = PQ. 
Now relative to P , the point Q just goes around a circle of radius a. 
Note that the circle rotates backwar ds and at time t =0, the angle 
3/2. So we have 
PQ =(a cos(3/2  t),a sin(3/2  t)) = (a sin t, a cos t) 
Putting all of this together, we have 
(x,y)=(at  a sin t,a  a cos t). 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>One way to think of this is in terms of directed line segmen ts. Note 
that given a point P and a vector v we can add v to P to get another 
point Q. If P =(p1,p2,p3) and v =(v1,v2,v3) then 
Q = P + v =(p1 + v1,p2 + v2,p3 + v3). 
If Q = PQ, such that Q (q1,q2,q3), then there is a unique vector = 
P + v, namely 
PQ =(q1  p1,q2  p2,q3  p3). 
Lemma 1.6. Let P , Q and R be three points in R3 . 
Then QR = PQ + PR. 
Proof. Let us consider the result of adding QR to P , PQ + 
P +(QR)=(P + QR PQ + PQ)+ 
= Q + QR 
= R. 
On the other hand, there is at most one vector v such that when we 
add it P we get R, namely the vector So QR =  PR. PQ + PR. 
Note that (1.6) expresses the geometrically obvious statemen t that 
if one goes from P to Q and then from Q to R, this is the same as 
going from P to R. 
Vectors arise quite naturally in nature. We can use vectors to rep
resen t forces; every force has both a magnitude and a direction. The 
combined eect of two forces is repre sented by the vector sum. Sim
ilarly we can use vectors to measure both velocity and acceleration. 
The equation 
F= ma, 
is the vector form of Newtons famous equation. 
Note that R3 comes with three standard unit vectors 
 = (1, 0, 0) j= (0, 1, 0) and k= (0, 0, 1), 
which are called the standar d basis. Any vector can be written uniquely 
as a linear combination of these vectors, 
 v =(v1,v2,v3)= v1 + v2j+ v3k. 
We can use vectors to parametrise lines in R3 . Supp ose we are given 
two dieren t points P and Q of R3 . Then there is a unique line l 
containing P and Q. Suppose that R =(x,y,z) is a general point of 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>the line. Note that the vector PQ, so that PR is parallel to the vector 
PQ. PR is a scalar multiple of Algebraically , 
PQ, PR = t
for some scalar t  R. If P =(p1,p2,p3) and Q =(q1,q2,q3), then 
(x  p1,y  p2,z  p3)= t(q1  p1,q2  p2,q3  p3)= t(v1,v2,v3), 
where (v1,v2,v3)=(q1  p1,q2  p2,q3  p3). We can always rewrite 
this as, 
(x,y,z)=(p1,p2,p3)+ t(v1,v2,v3)=(p1 + tv1,p2 + tv2,p3 + tv3). 
Writing these equations out in coordinates, we get 
x = p1 + tv1 y = p2 + tv2 and z = p3 + tv3. 
Example 1.7. If P = (1, 2, 3) and Q = (1, 0, 1), then v = (0, 2, 4) 
and a gener al point of the line containing P and Q is given parametri
cally by 
(x,y,z) = (1, 2, 3) + t(0, 2, 4) = (1, 2+2t, 3  4t). 
Example 1.8. Wher e do the two lines l1 and l2 
(x,y,z) = (1, 2+2t, 3  4t) and (x,y,z) = (2t  1, 3+ t, 3t), 
interse ct? 
We are looking for a point (x,y,z) common to both lines. So we have 
(1, 2+2s, 3  4s) = (2t  1, 3+ t, 3t). 
Looking at the rst component, we must have t =1. Looking at the 
second component, we must have 2+2s = 2, so that s =0. By 
inspection, the third component comes out equal to 3 in both cases. So 
the lines interse ct at the point (1, 2, 3). 
Example 1.9. Wher e does the line 
(x,y,z) = (1  t, 2  3t, 2t + 1) 
interse ct the plane 
2x  3y + z = 6? 
We must have 
2(1  t)  3(2  3t) + (2t +1) = 6. 
Solving for t we get 
9t  3=6, 
so that t =1. The line interse cts the plane at the point 
(x,y,z) = (0, 1, 3). 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1. Vectors in R2 and R3 
Denition 1.1. A vector v  R3 is a 3-tuple of r eal numb ers (v1,v2,v3). 
Hopefully the reader can well imagine the denition of a vector in 
R2 . 
Example 1.2. (1, 1, 0) and (
2,, 1/e) are vectors in R3 . 
Denition 1.3. The zero vector in R3 , denote d 0, is the vector 
(0, 0, 0). If v =(v1,v2,v3) and w=(w1,w2,w3) are two vectors in 
R3, the sum of v and w, denote d v + w, is the vector (v1 + w1,v2 + 
w2,v3 + w3). 
If v =(v1,v2,v3)  R3 is a vector and   R is a scalar, the scalar 
product of  and v, denote d  v, is the vector (v 1,v2,v3).  
Example 1.4. If v = (2, 3, 1) and w= (1, 5, 3) then v + w= 
(3, 8, 4). If  = 3 then  v =(6, 9, 3). 
Lemma 1.5. If  and  are scalars and u, v and ware vectors in R3 , 
then 
(1) 0+ v = 0. 
(2) u +(v + w)=(u + v)+ w. 
(3) u + v = v + u. 
(4)  ( v)=() v.   
(5) ( + ) v =  v +  v.  
(6)  (u + v)=  u +  v.   
Proof. We check (3). If u =(u1,u2,u3) and v =(v1,v2,v3), then 
u + v =(u1 + v1,u2 + v2,u3 + v3) 
=(v1 + u1,v2 + u2,v3 + u3) 
= v + u.  
We can interpret vector addition and scalar multiplication geometri
cally. We can think of a vector as represen ting a displacem ent from 
the origin. Geometri cally a vector v has a magnitude (or length) 
|v| =(v12 + v22 + v2)1/2 and every non-zero vector has a direction 3 
v u = . |v| 
Multiplying by a scalar leaves the direction unchanged and rescales the 
magnitude. To add two vectors v and w, think of transp orting the tail 
of wto the endp oint of v. The sum of v and wis the vector whose tail 
is the tail of the transp orted vector. 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Manifolds with boundary</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_28/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;28</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Gran ted this, Greens Theorem follows very easily , 
     
M F2 
x  F1 
y k
dx dy =  
i=1 M Fi,2 
x  Fi,1 
y dx dy 
k  
= Fi  ds. 
i=1 M 
= F  ds.  
M 
Lemma 28.5. Let K  Rn . Supp ose that K is containe din the union 
of close d balls B1,B2,...,Bm, such that any point of K belongs to the 
interior of at least one of B1,B2,...,Bm. 
Then we may nd smooth functions 1,2,...,m such that i is zero 
outside Bi and 
m
1= i. 
i=1 
Proof. We prove the case n = 2. The general case is similar, only 
notationally more involved. First observ e that it is enough to nd 
smooth functions 1,2,...,m, such that i is zero outside Bi and 
such that 
m
 = i, 
i=1 
does not vanish at any point of K. Indeed, if we let 
ii = , 
then i is smooth, it vanishes outside Bi and dividing both sides of the 
equation above by , we have 
m
1= i. 
i=1 
In fact it suces to nd functions 1,2,...,m, such that i vanishe s 
outside Bi and which is non-zero on the interior of Bi (replacing i 
by i 2, so that i 2 is positiv e on the interior of Bi, we get rid of the 
anno ying possibilit y that the sum is zero because of cancelling). It is 
enough to do this for one solid circle Bi and we migh t as well assume 
that B = Bm = B1 is the solid unit circle. Using polar coordinates, we 
want a function of one variable r which is zero outside [0, 1] and which 
is non-zero on (0, 1), so we are now down to a one variable question. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>, 
  Proof. In the rst step we assume that 
M = H2 = { (u,v) | v  0 } R2 . 
By assumption we may nd a and b such that F= 0 outside the box 
[a/2,a/2]  [0,b/2]  H2 . 
So F(u,v)= 0 if u = a or v = b. Lets calculate the LHS, 
    F2 F1 F2 F1 
u  v du dv = u du dv  v du dv 
H2 H2 H2 
 b  a  a  bF2 F1 = du dv  dv du u v 
 0 
b a a 0  a 
= F2(a,v)  F2(a,v)dv  F1(u,b)  F1(u, 0)du 
0 a 
a 
= F1(u, 0)du. 
a 
Okay, now lets parametrise the boundary of the upper half plane, 
x: R  H2 
by the rule 
x(u) =(u, 0). 
Then 
x(u)=. 
Lets calculate the RHS, 
a 
Fds = F(x(u)) x(u)du 
H2   
a 
a 
= F(u, 0)  du 
a 
a 
= F1(u, 0)du. 
a 
So the result holds if M = H2 . This completes the rst step. 
In the second step, we supp ose that there is a dieomorphism 
g : H2  U  M  W, 
such that for some positiv e real numbers a and b, we have 
(1) [a,a]  [0,b]  H2  U, 
(2) F= 0 outside g([a/2,a/2]  [0,b]), and 
(3) det Dg(u,v) &gt; 0 for every (u,v)  H2  U. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Using this, we get 
     G2 G1 G2 G1 
H2 u  v du dv = 
H2u  v du dv 
 U  F2 F1 (x,y) = du dv 
H2U x  y (u,v) 
F2 F1 = x  y dx dy 
 M W  F2 F1 = x  y dx dy. 
M 
Putting all of this together, we have 
     F2 F1 G2 G1 
x  y dx dy = u  v du dv 
M H2 
= Gds 
H2 
= Fds. 
M 
This completes step 2. 
We now turn to the third and nal step. To complete the proof, we 
need to invoke the existence of partitions of unity. Starting with F,I 
claim that there are vector nitely many elds F1,F2,...,Fk, each of 
which satisfy the hypotheses of step 2, such that 
k
F= F1 + F2 + + Fk = Fi. 
i=1 
Indeed, start with a partition of unity, 
m
1= i, 
i=1 
multiply both sides by F, to get 
m
F= i =1miF= Fi. 
i=1 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>28. Manif olds with bound ary 
Denition 28.1. Upper half space is the set 
Hm = { (x1,x2,...,xm) | xm  0 } Rm . 
The boundary of Hm, is 
Hm = { (x1,x2,...,xm) | xm =0 } Mm . 
Denition 28.2. A subset M  Rk is a smooth m-manifold with 
boundary if for every a  M there is an open subset W  Rk and an 
open subset U  Rm, and a dieomorphism 
g : Hm  U  M  W. 
The boundary of M is the set of points a which map to a point of the 
boundary of Hm . 
Example 28.3. The solid ellipse, 
2 2 
M = { (x,y)  R2 | x
a + y
b  1 }, 
is a 2-manifold with boundary. 
Let 
U1 = { (u,v) | 0 &lt;u&lt; 2, 1 &lt;v&lt; 1 }
and 
W1 = R2 { (x, 0)  R2 | x  0 }. 
Dene a function 
g1 : U1  W1, 
by the rule 
g1(u,v)=(a(1  v)cos u,b(1  v)sin u). 
Similarly , let 
U2 = { (u,v) |  &lt; u &lt; , 1 &lt;v&lt; 1 } 
and 
W2 = R2 { (x, 0)  R2 | x  0 }. 
Dene a function 
g2 : U2  W2, 
by the rule 
g2(u,v)=(a(1  v)cos u,b(1  v)sin u). 
Finally , let 
U3 = { (u,v) | u 2 
1 +(v  b)2 &lt;b }</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>= and 
W3 = { (x,y) | x 2 + y 2 &lt;b }. 
Dene a function 
g3 : U3  W3, 
by the rule 
g3(u,v)=(u,v  b). 
Let 
F: R2  R2 , 
be the function 
F(x,y)=(y,x). 
Then 
 2 
Fds = (b sin t,a cos t)(a cos t,b sin t)dt   
M 0
 2
= ab dt 
0 
=2ab. 
On the other hand, 
curl F= F2 F1 =1  (1) = 2,x  y 
and so 
curl Fdx dy =2ab. 
M 
In fact this is not a coincidence: 
Theorem 28.4 (Greens Theorem). Let M  R2 be a smooth 2
manifold with boundary, and let F: M  R2 be a smooth vector eld 
such that 
{ (x,y)  M | F (x,y) 0 } R2 , 
is a bounde d subset. 
Then    F2 F1 
M x  y dx dy = 
M F ds. 
Here M is oriente d, so that M is on the left as we go around M (in 
the positive direction). 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>At this point we realise we want a smooth function, 
f : R  R, 
all of whose derivatives are zero at 0 and yet the function f is not the 
zero function. Such a function is given by 
f(x)= e1/x2 .  
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>In this case, parametrise M  W as follows; dene 
s:(a,a)  M  W, 
by the rule 
s(u) = g(x(u)) = g(u, 0). 
Note that this is compatible with the orientation, as we are assuming 
that the Jacobian of g is positiv e. 
a 
Fds = F(s(u)) s(u)du   
M a 
a 
= F(g(x(u)))Dg(x(u)) x(u)du 
a 
= Gds, 
H2  
where 
G: H2 , R2 
is dened by the rule 
G(u,v)= F(g(u,v))Dg(u,v) if(u,v)  U 
0 otherwise. 
Now we compute, 
G2 G1  x y x y
u  v = u F1 v + F2 v  v F1 u + F2 u
F1 x F1 y x 2x = + + F1x u y u v uv 
F2 x F2 y y 2y+ + + F2x u y u v uv 
F1 x F1 y x 2x  x v + y v u  F1 vu 
F2 x F2 y y 2x  x v + y v u  F2 vu 
F2 x y x y F1 x y x y = x u v  x u  y u v  x u 
F2 F1 (x,y) = x  y (u,v) . 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Chain rule</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Now a is dieren tiable (it is a polynomial, linear even). There is func
tion 
h: Rn  R2m , 
which sends Q to (f(Q),g(Q)). The comp osition a  h: Rn  Rm is 
the function we want to dieren tiate, it sends P to f(P )+ g(P ). The 
chain rule says that that the function is dieren tiable at P and 
D(f + g)(P )= Df(P )+ Dg(P ).
Now supp ose that m = 1. Instead of a, consider the function
m: R2  R, 
given by m(x,y)= xy. Then m is dieren tiable, with derivative 
Dm(x,y)=(y,x). 
So the chain rule says the comp osition of h and m, namely the func
tion which sends P to the product f(P )g(P ) is dieren tiable and the 
deriv ative satises the usual rule 
D(fg)(P )= g(P )D(f)(P )+ f(P )D(g)(P ). 
Here is another example of the chain rule, supp ose 
x = r cos  
y = r sin . 
Then 
f	f x f y = + r	x r y r 
f f = cos  + sin . x y 
Similarly , 
f	f x f y = +  x  y  
f f = x r sin  + y r cos . 
We can rewrite this as 	   	  cos  sin r	 x  =	 r sin r cos 	 y 
Now the determinan t of 
cos  sin  
r sin r cos  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>since u = f1(x,y) and v = f2(x,y). Notice that in the last line we were 
a bit slopp y and dropp ed P and Q. 
If we split this vector equation into its comp onents we get 
(gf) g f1 g f2  = (Q)(P )+ (Q) (P )x ux v x 
(gf) g f1 g f2  = (Q)(P )+ (Q) (P ). y uy v y 
Again, we could replace f1 by u and f2 by v in these equations, and 
maybe even drop P and Q. 
Example 12.3. Supp ose that f(x,y) = (cos(xy),exy) and g(u,v)= 
u2 sin v. If we apply the chain rule, we get 
D(g  f)(x) = (2u sin v(y sin xy)+ u 2 cos v(e xy), 2u sin vx sin xy  u 2 cos ve xy 
= (2 cos(xy )sin(e xy)(y sin xy) + cos2(xy)cos(e xy)e xy,... ). 
In general, the (i,k) entry of D(gf)(P ), that is  
(gf)i 
xk 
is given by the dot product of the ith row of Dg(Q) and the kth column 
of Df(P ), 
m(g  f)i =  gi (Q) fj (P ). xkj=1 yj xi 
If z =(gf)(P ), then we get  
mzi  zi yj= (Q)(P ). xkj=1 yj xi 
We can use the chain rule to prove some of the simple rules for 
deriv atives. Supp ose that we have 
f : Rn  Rm and g : Rn  Rm . 
Supp ose that f and g are dieren tiable at P . What about f + g? 
Well there is a function 
a: R2m , Rm 
which sends (u,v)  Rm  Rm to the sum u + v. In coordin ates 
(u1,u2,...,um,v1,v2,...,vm), 
a(u 1,u2,...,um,v1,v2,...,vm)=(u1 + v1,u2 + v2,...,um + vm). 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12. Chain rule 
Theorem 12.1 (Chain Rule) . Let U  Rn and let V  Rm be two 
open subsets. Let f : U  V and g : V  Rp be two functions. 
If f is dier entiable at P and g is dier entiable at Q = f(P ), then 
g  f : U  Rp is dier entiable at P , with derivative: 
D(gf)(P )=(D(g)(Q))(D(f)(P )).  
It is interesting to untwist this result in specic cases. Supp ose we 
are given 
f : R  R2 and g : R2  R. 
So f(x)=(f1(x),f2(x)) and w = g(y,z). Then 
df1 (P )	 g g dx Df(P )= df2 and Dg(Q)=((Q), (Q)). (P )	 y z dx 
So 
d(gf) g df1 g df2  = D(gf)(P )= Dg(Q)Df(P )= (Q)(P )+ (Q)(P ). dx 	y dx z dx 
Example 12.2. Supp ose that f(x)=(x2,x3) and g(y,z)= yz. If we 
apply the chain rule, we get 
D(gf)(x)= z(2x)+ y(3x 2)=5x 4 .  
On the other hand (gf)(x)= x5, and of course  
dx5
4=5x. dx 
Now supp ose that 
f : R2  R2 and g : R2  R 
So f(x,y)=(f1(x,y),f2(x,y)) and w = g(u,v). Then 
f1 (P )	f2 (P ) g g x	x Df(P )= f2 f2 and Dg(Q)=( (Q), (Q)). (P ) (P )	 uv x	x 
In this case 
D(gf)=( (g  f) ,(g  f)) 	x y 
g f1 g f2 g f1 g f2=( (Q) (P )+ (Q)(P ), (Q)(P )+ (Q)(P )). ux v x uy v y 
g u g v g u g v =( (Q) (P )+ (Q)(P ), (Q)(P )+ (Q)(P ))uxv xuy v y 
g u g v g u g v =( + , + ),u x v xu y v y 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>is 
r(cos2  + sin2 )= r. 
So if r = 0, then we can invert the matrix above and we get 
   1 r cos   sin x r  = rr sin  cos   
y  
We now turn to a proof of the chain rule. We will need: 
Lemma 12.4. Let A  Rn be an open subset and let f : A  Rm be 
a function. 
If f is dier entiable at P , then there is a constant M  0 and &gt; 0 
such that if PQ &lt;, then 
f(Q)  f(P ) &lt;MPQ. 
Proof. As f is dierentiable at P , there is a constan t &gt; 0 such that 
if PQ &lt;, then 
f(Q)  f(P )  Df(P )PQ 
 &lt; 1. 
PQ 
Hence 
f(Q)  f(P )  Df(P )PQ. PQ &lt; 
But then 
f(Q)  f(P ) = f(Q)  f(P )  Df(P )PQ PQ + Df(P )
PQ + Df(P )PQ f(Q)  f(P )  Df(P )
PQ + KPQ  
= MPQ, 
where M =1+ K.  
Proof of (12.1) . Lets x some notation. We want the deriv ative at P . 
Let Q = f(P ). Let P  be a point in U (whic h we imagine is close to 
P ). Finally , let Q = f(P ) (so if P  is close to P , then we expect Q 
to be close to Q). 
The trick is to carefully dene an auxiliary function G: V  Rp, 
 
g(Q)g(Q)Dg(Q)(
QQ) if Q = QG(Q)=  QQ 
0 if Q = Q. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Then G is continuous at Q = f(P ), as g is dieren tiable at Q. Now, 
(gf)(P )  (g PP ) f)(P )  Dg(Q)Df(P )(  
P P  
f(P )  f(P )  Df(P P )P )(
= Dg(Q) + G(f(P ))f(P )  f(P ) 
PP  . 
PP  
As P  approac hes P , note that 
PP ) f(P )  f(P )  Df(P )(
, 
PP  
and G(P ) both approac h zero and 
f(P )  f(P ) M. 
PP  
So then 
(g  f)(P )  (g  PP ) , f)(P )  Dg(Q)Df(P )(
PP  
approac hes zero as well, which is what we want.  
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Maxima and minima: I</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_20/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>20. Maxima and minima: I
Recall that K  Rn is closed if the complemen t is open. Recall also 
that this is equiv alent to saying that K contains all of its limit points. 
Denition 20.1. We that K  Rn is bounde d if there is a real num
ber M such that 
x M, 
for all x  K. 
We say that K is compact if K is close d and bounde d. 
Note that K is bounded if and only if 
K  BM (O), 
where O is the origin. 
Example 20.2. 
(1) [a,b]  R is compact. 
(2) (a,b]  R is bounde d but not close d (whenc e not compact). 
(3) [a, )  R is close d but not bounde d (whenc e not compact). 
(4)
K = { x  Rn |x M },
is compact. 
(5)
K = { x  Rn |x &lt;M },
is bounde d but not close d. 
Theorem 20.3. Let f : K  R be a continuous function. 
If K is compact then there are two points amin and amax in K such 
that 
f(amin)  f(x)  f(amax). 
The proof of (20.3) is highly non-trivial. 
Denition 20.4. Let K  Rn . We say that a  K is an interior 
point if there is an open ball containing a which is containe d in K. 
Otherwise a is a boundary point of K. 
Example 20.5. If K =[a,b]  R then every point a&lt;x&lt;b is an 
interior point and a and b are boundary points. 
To nd the maxima and minima of f : K  R we break the problem 
into two pieces: 
I. The interior points. Use the deriv ative test, this lecture. 
II. The boundary points. Use Lagrang e multipliers, see lecture 21. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Denition 20.9. If A is a symmetric n  n matrix, then the function
Q(h)= x tAx, 
is called a symmetric quadr atic form. 
We say that Q is positive denite if x =0 implies that Q(x) &gt; 0. 
We say that Q is positive denite if x =0 implies that Q(x) &lt; 0. 
Example 20.10. If A = I2 then    
10 x 2 2Q(x,y)=(x,y) = x + y,01 y 
which is positive denite. If A = I2 then Q(x,y)= x2  y2 is 
negative denite. Final ly if 
10 
0 1 
then Q(x,y)= x2  y2 is neither positive nor negative denite. 
Prop osition 20.11. If a  K  Rn is an interior point and f : K  
R is C3 and a is a critic al point, then 
(1)	If Q(h)= htHf(a)h is positive denite, then a is a minimum. 
(2)	If Q(h)= htHf(a)h is negative denite, then a is a maximum. 
(3) If Q(h)= htHf(a)h is not zero and is neither positive nor 
negative denite, then a is a sadd le point. 
Proof. Immediate from Taylors Theorem.	  
Prop osition 20.12. If A is a n  n matrix, then let di be the deter
minant of the upper left i  i submatrix. Let Q(h)= htAh. 
(1)	If di &gt; 0 for all i, then Q is positive denite. 
(2)	If di &gt; 0 for i even and di &lt; 0 for i odd, then Q is negative 
denite. 
Lets consider the 2  2 case. 
ab A = bd 
In this case 
Q(x,y)= ax 2 +2bxy + cy 2 . 
Assume that d1 = a&gt; 0. Lets complete the square. a = 2, some 
&gt; 0. 
Q(x,y)=(x + b/y)2 +(d  b2/2)y 2 =(x + b/y)2 +(ad  b2)/ay2 . 
In this case d1 = a&gt; 0 and d2 = ad  b2 . So the coecien t of y2 is 
positiv e if d2 &gt; 0 and negativ e if d2 &lt; 0. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Notice that the boundary can have a rather complicated structu re in 
higher dimensions. For example, in R3 the closed unit ball is compact. 
The boundary is the set of points in the open unit ball and the set of 
boundary points is the set of points on the unit sphere. 
Denition 20.6. Let f : K  R be a function and let a  K be an 
interior point. We say that f has a local minimum at a if there is 
an open ball U = B(a) centred at a containe d in K such that 
f(a)  f(x), 
for all x  U. 
We can dene local maxima in a similar fashion. 
Denition 20.7. Let f : K  R be a dier entiable function. We 
say that a point a  K in the interior of K is a critic al point if 
Df(a)= 0. 
Prop osition 20.8. Let K  Rn be a compact set and let f : K  R 
be a dier entiable function. Let a  K be an interior point. 
If a is a local maximum, then a is a critic al point. 
Proof. 
f (a) = limf(a + hei)  f(ei)  0 xih0 h 
f (a) = limf(a + hei)  f(ei)  0.  xih0 h 
Recall the one variable second deriv ative test: 
(i) If f(a)=0 and f(a) &lt; 0, then a is a local maxim um of f. 
(ii) If f(a)=0 and f(a) &gt; 0, then a is a local minim um of f. 
(iii) If f(a)=0 and f(a) = 0, then we dont know. 
The reason why the second deriv ative works follows from Taylors 
Theorem with remainder, applied to the second Taylor polynomial. 
To gure out the multi-v ariable form of the second deriv ative test, 
we need to consider the multi-v ariable second Taylor polynomial: 
Pa,2f(x)= f(a)+ f(a) h +1htHf(a)h. 2 
Recall that 
h = (h1, h2, . . . , hn) and Hf(a) = ( 2f 
xixj (a)). 
The importan t term is then 
Q(h)= htHf(a)h. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Surface integrals</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_30/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;30</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>So
T  T =
 j k
a sin  sin a sin  cos 
a cos  cos a cos  sin  a sin  
0 
= a 2 sin2  cos  + a 2 sin2  sin j+ a 2 cos  sin k. 
Ther efore, 
T  T = a 2 sin (sin2  cos 2  + sin2  sin2  + cos2 )1/2 
= a 2 sin . 
As 0 &lt;&lt;, note that a2 sin &gt; 0. Henc e 
area(M ) = area(M  W ) 
= dS 
 MW 
= T  T d d 
U 2   
= a 2 sin  d d 
0 0 2 
=2a 2 dt 
0 
=4a2 . 
Notic e that this is the surfac e area of a spher e of radius a. 
Lets now supp ose that there are two dieren t ways to parametrise 
the same piece M  W of the manifold M: 
g : U  M  W and h: V  M  W. 
Let use (u,v) coordinates for U  R2 and (s,t) coordinates for V  R2 . 
Then 
f=(h)1  g : U  V, 
is a dieomorph ism. Note that g = h f. We then have 
g (u,v)= (h  f)(u,v)
u u 
h s h t = (s,t)(u,v)+ (s,t)(u,v). s ut u
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Ther efore, 
Ts  Tt =(a + b cos t)b(cos2 s cos 2 t + sin2 s cos 2 t + sin2 t)1/2 
=(a + b cos t)b. 
As a  b, note that (a + b cos t)b&gt; 0. Henc e 
area(M ) = area(M  W ) 
= dS 
 MW 
= Ts  Tt ds dt 
U 2  2 
= (a + b cos t)b ds dt 
0 0 2 
=2b (a + b cos t)dt 
0 
=42ab. 
Notic e that this is the surfac e area of a cylinder of radius b and height 
2a, as expected. 
Example 30.2. We can parametrise the spher e, 
M = { (x,y,z) | x 2 + y 2 + z 2 = a 2 }, 
as follows. Let 
U = (0,)  (0, 2), 
and 
W = R3 \{ (x,y,z) | x  0 and y =0 }. 
Let 
g : U  M  W, 
be the function 
g(,)=(a sin  cos ,a sin  sin ,a cos ). 
Lets calculate the tangent vectors, 
gT =  =(a cos  cos ,a cos  sin , a sin ), 
T = g =(a sin  sin ,a sin  cos , 0).  
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>30. Surf ace integrals
Supp ose we are given a smooth 2-manifold M  R3 . Let
g : U  M  W, 
be a dieomorphism, where U  R2, with coordinates s and t. 
We can dene two tangen t vectors, which span the tangen t plane to 
M at P = g(s0,t0): 
gTs(s0,t0)= (s0,t0)s 
Tt(s0,t0)= g (s0,t0). t 
We get an elemen t of area on M, 
dS = Ts  Tt ds dt. 
Using this we can dene the area of M  W to be 
area(M  W )= dS = Ts  Tt ds dt. 
MW U 
Example 30.1. We can parametrise the torus, 
M = { (x,y,z) | (a  x2 + y2)2 + z 2 = b2 }, 
as follows. Let 
U = (0, 2)  (0, 2), 
and 
W = R3 \{ (x,y,z) | x  0 and y =0, or x 2 + y 2  a 2 and z =0 }. 
Let 
g : U  M  W, 
be the function 
g(s,t) = ((a + b cos t)cos s, (a + b cos t)sin s,b sin t). 
Lets calculate the tangent vectors, 
Ts = g =((a + b cos t)sin s, (a + b cos t)cos s, 0),s 
Tt = g =(b sin t cos s, b sin t sin s,b cos t). t 
So
Ts  Tt =
 j k
(a + b cos t)sin s (a + b cos t)cos s 0 
b sin t cos s b sin t sin sb cos t
=(a + b cos t)b cos s cos t +(a + b cos t)b sin s cos t k. j +(a + b cos t)b sin t
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Similarly 
g (u,v)= (h  f)(u,v)v v 
h s h t = (s,t)(u,v)+ (s,t)(u,v). s v t v 
g g h s h t h s h t 
u  v = s u + t u  s v + t v 
h h s t s t = s  t u v  v u 
h h (s,t) = . s  t (u,v)
It follows that
g g h h (s,t)
. u  v  =  s  t |(u,v)|
Hence
g g h h (s,t) 
U u  v  du dv = 
U  s  t |(u,v)| du dv 
h h =  s  t  ds dt. 
V 
Notice that the rst term is precisely the integral we use to dene 
the area of M W . This formula then says that the area is indep enden t 
of the choice of parametrisation. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Taylor polynomials</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Denition 19.3. Let A  Rn be an open subset which is convex (if a 
and b belong to A, then so does every point on the line segment between 
them). Supp ose that f : A  R is Ck . 
Given a  A, the kth Taylor polynomial of f centred at a is 
 f  2f Pa,kf(x)= f(a)+ xi (a)(xiai)+1/2 xixj (a)(xiai)(xjaj )+... 
1in 1i,jn 
1  kf + k! xi1 xi2 ...xik (a)(xi1 ai1 )(xi2 ai2 ) ... (xik aik ). 
1i1,i2,...,ik n 
The remainder is the dier ence 
Ra,kf(x)= f(x)  Pa,kf(x). 
Theorem 19.4. Let A  Rn be an open subset which is convex. Sup
pose that f : A  R is Ck+1, and let a and b belong to A. 
Then there is a vector on the line segment between a and b such 
that 
Ra,k(b)= 1  k+1f ()(bi1 ai1 )(bi2 ai2 ) ... (bik+1 aik+1 ). (k + 1)! xi1 xi2 ...xik+11l1,l2,...,lk+1n 
Proof. As A is open and convex, we may nd &gt; 0 so that the 
parametrised line 
r :(, 1+ )  Rn given by r(t)= a + t(b  a), 
is contained in A. Let 
g :(, 1+ )  R, 
be the comp osition of r(t) and f(x). 
Claim 19.5. 
P0,kg(t)= Pa,kf(r(t)). 
Proof of (19.5) . This is just the chain rule; 
 f g(t)= xi (r(t))(bi  ai)
1in
 2f g(t)= xixj (r(t))(bi  ai)(bj  aj ) 
1ijn 
and so on.  
So the result follows by the one variable result.  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>We can write out the rst few terms of the Taylor series of f and get 
something interesting. Let h = x  a. Then 
 f  2f Pa,2f(x)= f(a)+ (a)hi +1/2 (a)hihj . 
1in xi 1i&lt;jn xixj 
The middle term is the same as multiplying the row vector formed by 
the gradien t of f, 
f f f f(a)=( (a), (a),... (a)),x1 x2 xn 
and the column vector given by h. The last term is the same as mul
tiplying the matr ix with entries 
2f (a),xixj 
on the left by h and on the right by the column vector given by h and 
dividing by 2. 
The matrix 
2f Hf(a)=( (a)),xixj 
is called the Hessian of f(x). 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>If we let 
g(x)= Ra,k(x)  M(x  a)k+1 , 
then 
g k+1(x)= fk+1(x)  k!M. 
Then we are looking for  such that 
g k+1()=0. 
Now the rst k deriv atives of g at a are all zero, 
g i(a)=0 for 0  i  k. 
By choice of M, 
g(b)=0. 
So by the mean value theorem, applied to g(x), there is a 1 between 
a and b such that 
g(1)=0. 
Again by the mean value theorem, applied to g(x), there is a 2 between 
a and 1 such that 
g(2)=0. 
Continuing in this way, by inducti on we may nd i,1  i  k +1 
between a and i1 such that 
g i(i)=0. 
Let  = k+1.  
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lets try an easy example. Start with
f(x)= x 1/2
1
f(x)=	x1/2 
2 
1 f(x)= 22 x3/2
3
f(x)= 23 x5/2
135
f4(x)=   x7/2 
24 
1357 f5(x)=	 
2 
5  x9/2
13579
f6(x)=     x11/2 
26 
fk(x)=(1)k1 (2k  1)!! x(2k1)/2 
2k 
fk(9/4) = (1)k1 (2k  1)!! 22k1 
2k 32k1 
(2k  1)!!2k1 
=(1)k1 
32k1 . 
Lets write down the Taylor polynom ial centred at a =9/4. 
P9/4,5f(x)= f(9/4)+f(9/4)(x9/4)+f(9/4)/2(x9/4)2+f(9/4)/6(x9/4)3 
f4(9/4)/24(x  9/4)4 + f5(9/4)/120(x  9/4)5 . 
So, 
P9/4,5f(x)=3/2+1/3(x  9/4)  1/33(x  9/4)2 +2/35(x  9/4)3 
13523 135724  (x  9/4)4 +  (x  9/4)5 .  24 37	 120 39 	  
If we plug in x = 2, so that x 9/4= 1/4 we get an appro ximation 
to f(2) = 
2. 
10997 P9/4,3(2) = 3/2+1/ 3(1/4)1/33(1/4)22/35(1/4)3 =  1.41422 .... 7776 
On the other hand, 
13 13 |R3(2, 9/4)| = 4!  ()7/2(1/4)4 &lt; 4!  (1/2) = 1/16. 
In fact 
R3(2, 9/4) = 10997 
2  4  106 . |	| 7776  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>19. Taylor Polynomials 
If f : A  Rm is a dieren tiable function, and we are given a point 
P  A, one can use the deriv ative to write down the best linear ap
proximation to f at P . It is natural to wonder if one can do better 
using quadratic, or even higher degree, polynomials. We start with the 
one dimensional case. 
Denition 19.1. Let I  R be an open interval and let f : I  R be 
a Ck-function. Given a point a  I, let 
Pa,kf(x)= f(a)+ f(a)(x  a)+ f
2(a)(x  a)2 + f
3!(a)(x  a)3 +  + fk
k(
! a)(x  a)k 
k
=  fi(a)(x  a)i . i! i=0 
Then Pa,kf(x) is the kth Taylor polynomial of f, centred at a. The 
remainder is the dier ence 
Ra,kf(x)= f(x)  Pa,kf(x). 
Note that we have chosen Pa,kf so that the rst k deriv atives of 
Pa,kf at a are precisely the same as those of f. In other words, the 
rst k deriv atives at a of the remainder are all zero. The remainder is 
a measure of how good the Taylor polynomial appro ximates f(x) and 
so it is very useful to estimate Ra,k(x). 
Theorem 19.2 (Taylors Theorem with remainder) . Let I  R be an 
open interval and let f : I  R be a Ck+1-function. Let a and b be 
two points in I. 
Then there is a  between a and b, such that 
fk+1()(b  a)k+1Ra,kf(b)= . (k + 1)!
Proof. If a = b then take  = a. The result is clear in this case. 
Otherwise if we put 
Ra,kf(b)M = ,(b  a)k+1 
then 
Ra,kf(b)= M(b  a)k+1 . 
We want to show that there is some  between a and b such that 
fk+1()M = . (k + 1)! 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Derivative</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_9/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Denition 9.7. Let f : Rn  R be a dier entiable function. Then 
at P , Df(P ) is a row vector, which is called the gradient of f,and isdenote d (f)the derivative of f
P , 
f
f
f
(
 ).
 ,
,...,
x1 x2 xn P P P 
The point (x1,x2,...,xn,xn+1) lies on the graph of f : Rn  R if 
and only if xn+1 = f(x1,x2,...,xn). 
The point (x1,x2,...,xn,xn+1) lies on the tangen t hyperplane of 
f : Rn  R at P =(a1,a2,...,an) if and only if
P xn+1 = f(a1,a2,...,an)+(f) (x1  a1,x2  a2,...,xn  an).  
In other words, the vector 
f  
P ,...,
f
xn f
(
 , 1),
 ,
x1 x2 P P 
is a norm al vector to the tangen t hyperplane and of course the point 
(a1,a2,...,an,f(a1,a2,...,an)) is on the tangen t hyperplane. 
Example 9.8. Let 
D = { (x,y)  R2 | x 2 + y 2 &lt;r2 }, 
the open ball of radius r, centred at the origin. 
Let f : R2  R be the function given by 
f(x,y)= r2  x2  y2 . 
Then 
f 2x/2
 x,
 = = x r2 2 2 r2 2 2  x y x y
and so by symmetry, 
f y
x,
 = = y r2  x2  y2 r2  x2  y2 
At the point (a,b), the gradient is 
(f)
 = (a,b) 
r2 1
 a2  b2 (a,b).
So the equation for the tangent plane is 
1 z = f(a,b) 
r2 (a(x  a)+ b(x  b)).  a2  b2 
For example, if (a,b) = (0, 0), then the tangent plane is 
z = r, 
as expected. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>9. The deriv ative 
The deriv ative of a function represen ts the best linear appro ximation 
of that function. In one variable, we are looking for the equation of 
a straig ht line. We know a point on the line so that we only need to 
determine the slope. 
Denition 9.1. Let f : R  R be a function and let a  R be a real 
numb er. f is dier entiable at a, with derivative   R, if 
f(x)  f(a)lim = . 
xa x  a
To understand the denition of the deriv ative of a multi-v ariable 
function, it is slightly better to recast (9.1): 
Denition 9.2. Let f : R  R be a function and let a  R be a real 
numb er. f is dier entiable at a, with derivative   R, if 
f(x)  f(a)  (x  a)lim =0. 
xa x  a 
We are now ready to give the denition of the deriv ative of a function 
of more than one variable:z 
Denition 9.3. Let f : Rn  Rm be a function and let P  Rn be a 
point. f is dier entiable at P , with derivative the m  n matrix A, 
if 
f(Q)  f(P )  APQ lim =0. 
QP PQ 
We will write Df(P )= A. 
So how do we compute the deriv ative? We want to nd the matrix 
A. Supp ose that  
ab A = cd 
Then       
Ae1 = A a 
c b 
d 1 
0 = a 
c 
and       
Ae2 = A a 
c b 
d 0 
1 = b 
d . 
In general, given an m  n matrix A, we get the jth column of A, 
simply by multiplying A by the column vector determined by ej . 
So we want to know what happ ens if we approac h P along the line 
determined by ej . So we take = ej , where h goes to zero. In PQ h
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>other words, we take Q = P + hej . Lets assume that h&gt; 0. Sowe 
consider the fractio n 
f(Q)  f(P )  A(hej) f(Q)  f(P )  A(hej ) = 
PQ h 
f(Q)  f(P )  hAej= h 
= f(Q)  f(P )  Aej . h
Taking the limit we get the jth column of A,
Aej = lim f(P + hej )  f(P ) .
h0 h

Now f(P + hej )  f(P ) is a column vector, whose entry in the ith row 
is 
fi(P +ej )fi(P )= fi(a1,a2,...,aj1,aj +h,aj+1,...,an)fi(a1,a2,...,aj1,aj ,aj+1,...,an). 
and so for the expression on the right, in the ith row, we have 
fi(P + hej )  fi(P )lim . 
h0 h
Denition 9.4. Let g : Rn  R be a function and let P  Rn . The 
partial derivative of f at P =(a1,a2,...,an), with respect to xj is 
the limit 
f 
xj g(a1,a2,...,aj + h,...,an)  g(a1,a2,...,an) = lim . 
h0 hP 
Putting all of this together, we get 
Prop osition 9.5. Let f : Rn  Rm be a function. 
If f is dier entiable at P , then Df(P ) is the matrix whose (i,j) 
entry is the partial derivative 
fi 
xj P .
Example 9.6. Let f : A  R2 be the function 
f(x,y,z)=(x 3 y + x sin(xz ), log xyz). 
Here A  R3 is the rst octant, the locus wher e x, y and z are all 
positive. Supp osing that f is dier entiable at P , then the derivative is 
given by the matrix of partial derivatives, 
3x2y + sin(xz )+ xz cos(xz ) x3 x2 cos(xz )Df(P )=
 1 1 1 . 
x y z 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>n-dimensional space</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>by the rule 
f(v)= Av. 
If v =(x,y), then 
Av =(x + y,y). 
Here I cheat a little, and write row vectors instead of column vectors. 
Geometrically this is called a shear; it leaves the y-axis alone but one 
goes furth er along the x-axis according to the value of y. If 
ab A = cd 
the resulting function sends (x,y) to (ax + by,cx + dy). In fact the 
functions one gets this way are always linear. If 
20 A = ,0 1 
then f(x,y) = (2x  y), and this has the result of scaling by a factor 
of 2 in the x-direction and reects in the y-direction. 
In general if A is an m  n matrix, we get a function 
f : Rn , Rm 
using the same rule, f(v)= Av. If B is an n  p matrix, then we get 
a function 
g : Rp  Rn , 
by the rule g(w)= Bw. Note that we can comp ose the functions f 
and g, to get a function 
f  g : Rp  Rm . 
First we apply g to wto get a vector v in Rn and then we apply f to v 
to get a vector in Rm . The comp osite function fg is given by the rule 
(fg)(w)=(AB)w. In other words, matrix multiplication is chosen 
so that it represen ts comp osition of functions. 
As soon as one realises this, many aspects of matrix multiplication 
become far less mysterious. For example, comp osition of functions is 
not comm utativ e, for example 
sin2x = 2 sin x, 
and this is why AB = BA in general. Note that it is not hard to check 
that comp osition of functions is associativ e, 
f (gh)=(fg) h.   
This is the easiest way to check that matrix multiplication is associa
tive, that is, (8) of (5.10). 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Example 5.11. Note however that AB = BA in gener al. For example 
if A has shape 1  3 and B has shape 3  2, then it makes sense to 
multiply A and B but it does not make sense to multiply B and A. 
In fact even if it makes sense to multiply A and B and B and A, the 
two products might not even have the same shape. For example, if 
1 
2  


A =
,
1
and
B =2 13 ,
then AB has shape 3  3,
  
2 13
4 26
1

 
 AB =
 ,
2
3
but BA has shape 1  1, 
BA = (2  2  3) = (3). 
But even both products AB and BA make sense, and they have the 
same shape, the products still dont have to be equal. Supp ose
  
A = 1 
0 1 1 , and B = 1 1 0 1 . 
Then AB and BA are both 2  2 matric es. But 
21 11 AB = , and BA = .11 12 
One can also dene determinan ts for n  n matrices. It is probably 
easiest to explain the general rule using an example:
1 
21 1 
1 1002
01
 201
201 1 
1  2
1 21
1
=
 .
1 21
1
01
 0
 0
0
 01
Notice that we as expand about the top row, the sign alternates ++, 
so that the last term comes with a minus sign. 
Finally , we try to explain the real meaning of a matrix. Let 
11 A = .01 
Given A, we can construct a function 
f : R2  R2 , 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Denition 5.8. Supp ose that A =(aij ) is an m  n matrix and B = 
(bij ) is an n  p matrix. The product C = AB =(cij ) is the m  p 
matrix wher e 
n
cij = ai1b1j + ai2b2j + ai3b3j + + ainbnj = ailblj .  
l=1 
In other words, the entry in the ith row and jth column of C is the 
dot product of the ith row of A and the jth column of B. This only 
makes sense because the ith row and the jth column are both vectors 
in Rn . 
Example 5.9. Let 
A =1 21 ,1 15 
and   
2 1 
B =  1 
1 4 
1  . 
Then C = AB has shape 2  2, and in fact 
1	10 C = AB = . 4	10 
Theorem 5.10. Let A, B and C be three matric es, and let  and  be 
scalars. 
(1)	If A, B and C have the same shape, then (A + B)+ C = 
A +(B + C). 
(2)	If A and B have the same shape, then A + B = B + A. 
(3)	If A and B have the same shape, then (A + B)= A + B. 
(4)	If Z is the zero matrix with the same shape as A, then Z + A = 
A + Z. 
(5)	(A) =()A. 
(6) ( + )A = A + A. 
(7)	If In is the matrix with ones on the diagonal and zeroes every
wher e else and A has shape mn, then AIn = A and ImA = A. 
(8)	If A has shape m  n and B has shape n  p and C has shape 
p  q, then A(BC)=(AB)C. 
(9)	If A has shape m  n and B and C have the same shape n  p, 
then A(B + C)= AB + AC. 
(10)	 If A and B have the same shape m  n and C has shape n  p, 
then (A + B)C = AC + BC. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>So the quadr atic function f(x)= ax2 + bx + c has at most one root. It 
follows that the discriminan t is less than or equal to zero, with equalit y 
if and only if f(x) has a root. So 
4(v w)2  4v2w2 = b2  4ac  0.  
Rearranging, gives 
(v  w)2 v2w2 . 
Taking square roots, gives 
|v  w|vw. 
Now if we have equalit y here, then the discriminan t must be equal to 
zero, in which case we may nd a scalar  such that the vector v + w
has zero lengt h. But the only vector of length zero is the zero vector, so 
that v+w= 0. In other words, w= v and v and ware parallel.  
Denition 5.5. If v and w Rn are non-zer o vectors, then the angle 
between them is the unique angle 0     such that 
v wcos  =  . vw 
Note that the fraction is between 1 and 1, by (5.4), so this does 
makes sense, and we showed in (5.4) that the angle is 0 or  if and only 
if v and ware parallel. 
Denition 5.6. If A =(aij ) and B =(bij ) are two m  n matric es, 
then the sum A + B is the m  n matrix (aij + bij ). If  is a scalar, 
then the scalar multiple A is the m  n matrix (a ij ). 
Example 5.7. If 
A =1 1 , and B =1 1 ,3 4 2 1 
then  
20 A + B = ,5 5 
and  
3 3 3A = .9 12 
Note that if we attene d A and B to (1, 1, 3, 4) and (2, 0, 5, 5) 
then the sum corresp onds to the usual vector sum (3, 1, 8, 9). Ditto 
for scalar multiplication. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>5. n-dimensional space 
Denition 5.1. A vector in Rn is an n-tuple v =(v1,v2,...,vn). The 
zero vector 0 = (0, 0,..., 0). Given two vectors v and win Rn, the 
sum v + wis the vector (v1 + w1,v2 + w2,...,vn + wn). If  is a scalar, 
the scalar product v is the vector (v 1,v2,...,vn). 
The sum and scalar product of vectors in Rn obey the same rules as 
the sum and scalar product in R2 and R3 . 
Denition 5.2. Let v and w Rn . The dot product is the scalar 
v w= v1w1 + v2w2 + ...vnwn.  
The norm (or length) of v is the scalar 
v = 
v v.  
The scalar product obeys the usual rules. 
Example 5.3. Supp ose that v = (1, 2, 3, 4) and w= (2, 1, 1, 1) and 
 = 2. Then 
v + w= (3, 1, 4, 3) and w =(4, 2, 2, 2). 
We have 
v w=2  2+3  4= 1.  
The standard basis of Rn is the set of vectors, 
e1 = (1, 0,..., 0),e2 = (0, 1,..., 0),e1 = (0, 0, 1,..., 0), ...en = (0, 0,..., 1). 
Note that if v =(v1,v2,...,vn), then 
v = v1e1 + v2e2 + + vnen. 
Lets adopt the (somewhat ad hoc) convention that v and ware 
parallel if and only if either v is a scalar multiple of w, or vice-v ersa. 
Note that if both v and ware non-zero vectors, then v is a scalar 
multiple of wif and only if wis a scalar multiple of v. 
Theorem 5.4 (Cauc hy-Schwarz-Bunjak owski). If v and ware two vec
tors in Rn, then 
|v  w|vw, 
with equality if and only if v is parallel to w. 
Proof. If either v or wis the zero vector, then there is nothing to prove. 
So we may assume that neither vector is the zero vector. 
Let u = xv + w, where x is a scalar. Then 
0  u u =(v v)x 2 + 2(v w)x + ww= ax 2 + bx + c.   
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Functions given by matrices are obviously very special. Note that if 
f(v)= Av, then 
f(v + w)= A(v + w)= Av + Aw = f(v)+ f(w), 
and 
f(v)= A(v)= (Av)= f(v). 
Any function which respects both addition of vectors and scalar multi
plication is called linear and it is precisely the linear functions which 
are given by matrices. In fact if e1,e2,...,en and f1,f2,...,fm are 
standard bases for Rn and Rm, and f is linear, then 
f(ej )= aij fi, 
for some scalars aij , since f(ej ) is a vector in Rm and any vector in Rm 
is a linear combinaton of the standard basis vectors f1,f2,...,fm. If 
we put A =(aij ) then one can check that f is the function 
f(v)= Av. 
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Higher derivatives</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>then we may write down the inverse by hand, 
1 d b . ad  bc ca 
So   1 2y 2yDf(P )1 =2xy(2 + 3x) 3x2 2x 
So,    
Df(P )1f(P )= 1 2y 
2 2yx2 + 
2 y2 
3 1 
2xy(2 + 3x) 3x 2xy x
1 2x2y  2y +2x3y= 2xy(2 + 3x) x4 +3x2y2  3x2 +2xy2 
One nice thing about this metho d is that it is quite easy to implemen t 
on a computer. Here is what happ ens if we start with (x0,y0) = (5, 2), 
(x0,y0) = (5.00000000000000, 2.00000000000000) 
(x1,y1) = (3.24705882352941, 0.617647058823529) 
(x2,y2) = (2.09875150983980, 1.37996311951634) 
(x3,y3) = (1.37227480405610, 0.561220968705054) 
(x4,y4) = (0.959201654346683, 0.503839504009063) 
(x5,y5) = (0.787655203525685, 0.657830227357845) 
(x6,y6) = (0.755918792660404, 0.655438554539110) , 
and if we start with (x0,y0) = (5, 5), 
(x0,y0) = (5.00000000000000, 5.00000000000000) 
(x1,y1) = (3.24705882352941, 1.85294117647059) 
(x2,y2) = (2.09875150983980, 0.363541705259258) 
(x3,y3) = (1.37227480405610, 0.306989760884339) 
(x4,y4) = (0.959201654346683, 0.561589294711320) 
(x5,y5) = (0.787655203525685, 0.644964218428458) 
(x6,y6) = (0.755918792660404, 0.655519172668858) . 
One can sketch the two curves and check that these give reasonable 
solutions. One can also check that (x6,y6) lie close to the two given 
curves, by computing x62 + y62  1 and y62  x63 . 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>If f(x0) = 0, then the linear equation 
f(x0)+ f(x0)(x  x0)=0, 
has the unique solution, 
f(x0) x1 = x0  . f(x0) 
Now just keep going (assuming that f(xi) is never zero), 
f(x0) x1 = x0  f(x0) 
f(x1) x2 = x1  f(x1) 
.. ...= . 
xn = xn1  ff
(
(x
xn
n
1
1)
) . 
Claim 11.6. Supp ose that x = limn xn exists and f(x) == 0. 
Then f(x)=0. 
Proof of (11.6) . Indeed, we have 
xn = xn1  ff
(
(x
xn
n
1
1)
) . 
Take the limit as n goes to  of both sides: 
f(x) x= x ,   f(x)
we we used the fact that f and f are continuous and f(x) = 0. But 
then 
f(x)=0, 
as claimed.  
Supp ose that A  Rn is open and f : A  Rn is a function. Sup
pose that f is C1 (that is, supp ose each of the coordinate functions 
f1,f2,...,fn is C1). 
The objectiv e is to nd a solution to the equation 
f(P )= 0. 
Start with any point P0  A. The best linear appro ximation to f at 
P0 is given by 
f(P0)+ Df(P0)PP0. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11. Higher deriv atives 
We rst record a very useful: 
Theorem 11.1. Let A  Rn be an open subset. Let f : A  Rm and 
g : A  Rm be two functions and suppose that P  A. Let   A be 
a scalar. 
If f and g are dier entiable at P , then 
(1) f +g is dier entiable at P and D(f +g)(P )= Df(P )+Dg(P ). 
(2) f is dier entiable at P and D(f)(P )= D(f)(P ).  
Now suppose that m =1. 
(3) fg is dier entiable at P and D (fg)(P )= D(f)(P )g(P )+f(P )D(g)(P ). 
(4) If g(P )=0, then fg is dier entiable at P and 
D(f/g)(P )= D(f)(P )g(P )  f(P )D(g)(P ) . g2(P ) 
If the partial deriv atives of f and g exist and are continuous, then 
(11.1) follows from the well-kno wn single variab le case. One can prove 
the general case of (11.1), by hand (basicall y lots of s and s). How
ever, perhaps the best way to prove (11.1) is to use the chain rule, 
proved in the next section. 
What about higher deriv atives? 
Denition 11.2. Let A  Rn be an open set and let f : A  R be a 
function. The kth order partial derivative of f, with respect to 
the variables xi1 , xi2 , ... xik is the iterated derivative 
kf  f (P )= ( (... ( ) ... ))(P ). xik xik1 ...xi2 xi1 xik xik1 xi2 xi1 
We will also use the notation fxik xik1 ...xi2 xi1 (P ). 
Example 11.3. Let f : R2  R be the function f(x,t)= eat cos x. 
Then 
 fxx(x,t)= ((eat cos x))xx
 = (eat sin x)x
= eat cos x. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Assume that Df(P0) is an invertible matrix , that is, assume that 
det Df(P0) = 0. Then the inverse matri x Df(P0)1 exists and the 
unique solution to the linear equation 
f(P0)+ Df(P0)PP0 = 0, 
is given by 
P1 = P0  Df(P0)1f(P0). 
Notice that matrix multiplication is not comm utativ e, so that there is 
a dierence between Df(P0)1f(P0) and f(P0)Df(P0)1 . If possible, 
we get a sequence of solutions, 
P1 = P0  Df(P0)1f(P0) 
P2 = P1  Df(P1)1f(P1) 
.. ...= . 
Pn = Pn1  Df(Pn1)1f(Pn1). 
Supp ose that the limit P = limn Pn exists and that Df(P) is 
invertible. As before, if we take the limit of both sides, this implies 
that 
f(P)= 0. 
Let us try a concrete example . 
Example 11.7. Solve 
x 2 + y 2 =1 
2 3 y = x. 
First we write down an appropriate function, f : R2  R2, given 
by f(x,y)=(x2 + y2  1,y2  x3). Then we are looking for a point P 
such that 
f(P ) = (0, 0). 
Then  
2x 2y
Df(P )= 2 . 3x 2y 
The determinan t of this matrix is 
4xy +6x 2 y =2xy(2 + 3x). 
Now if we are given a 2  2 matrix 
ab 
cd, 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>On the other hand, 
 fxt(x,t)= ((eat cos x))xt
 = (aeat cos x)x
= aeat sin x. 
Similarly, 
 ftx(x,t)= ((eat cos x))tx
 = (eat sin x)t
= aeat sin x. 
Note that 
ft(x,t)= aeat cos x. 
It follows that f(x,t) is a solution to the Heat equation: 
2f f a = . x2 t 
Denition 11.4. Let A  Rn be an open subset and let f : A  Rm 
be a function. We say that f is of class Ck if all kth partial derivatives 
exist and are continuous. 
We say that f is of class C (aka smooth) if f is of class Ck for 
all k. 
In lecture 10 we saw that if f is C1, then it is dieren tiable. 
Theorem 11.5. Let A  Rn be an open subset and let f : A  Rm 
be a function. 
If f is C2, then 
2f2f = ,xixj xj xi 
for all 1  i,j  n. 
The proof uses the Mean Value Theorem. 
Supp ose we are given A  R an open subset and a funct ion f : A  
R of class C1 . The objectiv e is to nd a solution to the equation 
f(x)=0. 
Newtons meth od proceeds as follows. Start with some x0  A. The 
best linear appro ximation to f(x) in a neigh bourho od of x0 is given by 
f(x0)+ f(x0)(x  x0). 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Cylindrical and spherical coordinates</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>To calcula te e, we use the fact that it has unit length and it is 
orthogonal to both e and e. We have 
e = ee  
 jk
=
 sin  cos  0 
sin  cos  sin  sin  cos 
= cos  cos  + sin  cos j (sin2 sin  + cos2  sin )k
= cos  cos  + cos  sin j sin k
Now when  increases, z decreases. So we want the vector with 
negativ e z-comp onent, which is exactly the last vector we wrote down. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>er points in the direction of increasing r. The vector e is a unit vector 
pointing in the direction of increasing . It is orthogonal to er and so 
in fact 
e =  sin  + cos j.
We will call a set of unit vectors which are pairwise orthogonal, an 
orthonormal basis if we have two in the plane or three in space . 
We want do some thing similar in space but now there are two choices 
beyond Cartesian coordinates. The rst just takes polar coordinates 
in the xy-plane and throws in the extra variable z. So a point P is 
specied by three coordinates, (r,,z). r is the distance to the origin, 
of the projection P  of P down to the xy-plane,  is the angle OP  makes 
with the x-axis, so that (r,) are just polar coordinates for the point 
P  in the xy-plane, and z is just the heigh t of P from the xy-plane. 
x = r cos  
y = r sin  
z = z. 
Note that the locus r = a, species a cylinder in three space. For 
this reason we call (r,,z) cylindrical coordinates. The locus  = , 
species a half-plane which is vertical (if we allow r&lt; 0 then we get 
the full vertical plane). The locus z = a species a horizon tal plane, 
parallel to the xy-plane. 
The locus z = ar species a half cone. At heigh t one, the cone has 
radius a, so the larger a the more open the cone. 
The locus z = a is rather complicate d. If we x the angle, then we 
get a line of this heigh t and this angle. The resulting surface is called 
a helicoid, and looks a little bit like a spiral staircase. 
Again it is useful to write down an orthonorma l coordinate frame. In 
this case there are three vectors, pointing in the direction of increasing 
r, increasing  and increasing z: 
er = cos  + sin j
e =  sin  + cos j
ez = k. 
The third coordinate system in space uses two angles and the dis
tance to the origin, (,,).  is the distance to the origin,  is the 
angle made by the projection of P down to the xy-plane and  is the 
angle the radius vector makes with the z-axis. Typically we use coor
dinates such that 0  z ,0  &lt; 2 and 0    . To get 
from spherical coordin ates to Cartesian coordinates, we rst convert to 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>cylindrical coordinates, 
r =  sin  
 =  
z =  cos . 
So, in Cartesian coordinates we get 
x =  sin  cos  
y =  sin  sin  
z =  cos . 
The locus z = a represen ts a sphere of radius a, and for this reason 
we call (,,) cylindrical coordinates. The locus  = a represen ts a 
cone. 
Example 6.1. Describ e the region 
x 2 + y 2 + z 2  a 2 and x 2 + y 2  z 2 , 
in spheric al coordinates. The rst region is the region inside the spher e 
of radius, 
  a. 
The second is the region outside a cone. The surfac e of the cone is 
given by z2 = x2 + y2 . Now one point on this cone is the point (1, 1, 1), 
so that this a right-angle d cone, and the region is given by 
/4    3/4. 
So we can describ e this region by the inequalities 
  a and /4    3/4. 
Finally , lets write down the moving frame given by spherical coordi
nates, the one corresp onding to increasing , increasing  and increasing 
. 
x + yj+ zk
e = 
x2 + y2 + z2
= sin  cos  + sin  sin k. j + cos 
e =  sin  + cos j.
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>6. Cylindrical and spherical coordina tes 
Recall that in the plane one can use polar coordinates rather than 
Cartesian coordinates. In polar coordinates we specify a point using 
the distance r from the origin and the angle  with the x-axis. 
In polar coordina tes, if a is a constan t, then r = a represen ts a circle 
of radius a, centred at the origin, and if  is a constan t, then  =  
represen ts a half ray, starting at the origin, making an angle . 
Supp ose that r = a, a a constan t. This represen ts a spiral (in 
fact, the Archimedes spiral), starting at the origin. The smaller a, the 
tighter the spiral. 
By convention, if r is negativ e, we use this to mean that we point in 
the opposite direction to the direction given by . Also by convention, 
 and  +2 represen t the same point. We may require r  0 and 
0  &lt; 2 and if we are not at the origin, this gives us unique polar 
coordinates. 
It is straigh tforw ard to convert to and from polar coordinates: 
x = r cos  
y = r sin , 
and 
2 2 2 r = x + y 
tan  = y/x. 
For example, what curve does the equation r =2a cos  represen t? 
Well if we multiply both sides by r, then we get 
r 2 =2ar cos . 
So we get 
x 2 + y 2 =2ax. 
Completing the square gives 
(x  a)2 + y 2 = a 2 . 
So this is a circle radius a, centred at (a, 0). Polar coordin ates can be 
very useful when we have circles or lines through the origin, or there is 
a lot of radially symmetry . 
Instead of using the vectors  and j, in polar coordinates it makes 
sense to use orthogonal vectors of unit length, that move as the point 
moves (these are called moving frames). At a point P in the plane, 
with polar coordinates (r,), we use the vector er to denote the vector 
of unit length pointing in the radial direction: 
er = cos  + sin j.
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Moving frames</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Theorem 16.4 (F renet Formulae). Let r : I  R3 be a regular smo oth 
parametrise d curve. Then 
N(s) = 
   
0 (s) 0

T(s)
 T(s) 

 


N(s)
 (s) 0 (s) 
0 .
B(s) B(s)
 (s) 0
Of course, s represen ts the arclength parameter and primes denote 
deriv atives with respect to s. Notice that the 3  3 matrix A appearing 
in (16.4) is skew-symmetric, that is At = A. The way we have 
written the Frenet formulae, it appears that we have two 3  1 vectors; 
strictly speaking these are the rows of two 3  3 matrices. 
Theorem 16.5. Let I  R be an open interval and suppose we are 
given two smooth functions 
: I  R and  : I  R, 
wher e (s) &gt; 0 for all s  I. 
Then there is a regular smooth curve r : I  R3 parametrise d by 
arclength with curvatur e (s) and torsion (s). Further, any two such 
curves are congruent, that is, they are the same up to translation and 
rotation. 
Remark 16.6. Uniqueness is one of the hwk problems. 
Lets consider the example of the helix: 
Example 16.7. 
s sbs r(s)=(a cos ,a sin , ), c cc 
wher e 
c 2 = a 2 + b2 . 
Lets assume that a&gt; 0. By convention c&gt; 0. Then 
T(s)= 1(a sin s,a cos s,b). c cc 
Henc e 
dT ssa ssa (s)= a (cos , sin , 0)= ( cos ,  sin , 0) = N(s)ds c2 cc c2 c cc2 
It follows that 
(s) = a and N(s)=( cos s,  sin s, 0). 2c cc 
Final ly,
B(s)=
jk
a a ssin s cos c c c c b 
c 
 cos 
3 s  sin s 0 c c</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16. Moving frames 
Denition 16.1. We say a parametrise d dier entiable curve r : I  
Rn is regular if r(t)=0  (the speed is never zero). 
We say that r(t) is smooth if r(t) is C. 
Given a regular smooth parametrised dieren tiable curve r : I  
R3, we can parametrise by arclength , in which case we get can write 
down the unit tangen t vector 
T= dr (s). ds
The curvature (s) is dened as the magnitude of 
dT
(s). ds 
If the curvature is nowhere zero, then we dene the normal vector 
N(s) as the unit vector pointing in the direction of the deriv ative of 
the tangen t vector: 
dT
(s)= (s)N(s). ds 
We have already seen that T(s) and N(s) are orthogon al. 
Denition 16.2. 
B(s)= T(s)  N(s). 
is called the binormal vector. 
The three vectors T(s), N(s), and B(s) are unit vectors and pairwise 
orthogonal, that is, these vectors are an orthonormal basis of R3 . Notice 
that T(s), N(s), and B(s) are a right handed set. 
We call these vectors a moving frame or the Frenet-Serret frame. 
Now 
dB
(s)  B(s)=0,ds 
as 
B(s) B(s) =1. 
It follows that 
dB
(s),ds 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>lies in the plane spanned by T(s) and N(s).
dB
(s) T(s)= d(T N)(s) T(s)ds  
 ds  
 
dT dN
= ds (s)  N(s)+ T(s)  ds (s)  T(s) 
= (s)(N(s)  N(s)) T(s)+(T(s)  N(s)) T(s)   
=0+(T(s)  T(s)) N(s) 
=0. 
It follows that 
dB
(s) and T(s),ds 
are orthogonal, and so 
dB
(s) is parallel to N(s). ds 
Denition 16.3. The torsion of the curve r(s) is the unique scalar 
(s) such that 
dB
(s)= (s)N(s). ds 
If we have a helix, the sign of the torsion distinguishes between a 
right handed helix and a left handed helix. The magnitude of the 
torsion measures how spread out the helix is (the curvature measures 
how tight the turns are). Now 
dN
(s)ds 
is orthogonal to N(s), and so it is a linear combination of T(s) and 
B(s). In fact, 
dN
(s)= d(B T)(s)ds ds 
dB dT
= (s)  T(s)+ B(s)  (s)ds ds 
= (s)N(s)  T(s)+ (s)B(s)  N(s) 
= (s)B(s)  (s)T(s) 
= (s)T(s)+ (s)B(s). 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>It follows that 
B(s)=( b sin s,  b cos s, a )= 1(b sin s, b cos s,a). cccccc c c 
Final ly, note that 
dBbss b
ds (s)= c2 (cos c, sin c, 0) = c2 N. 
Using this we can compute the torsion: 
b (s)= 2 . c
It is interesting to use the torsion and curvature to characterise var
ious geom etric properties of curves. Lets say that a paramet rised dif
feren tiable curve r : I  R3 is planar if there is a plane  which 
contains the image of r. 
Theorem 16.8. A regular smooth curve r : I  R3 is planar if and 
only if the torsion is zero. 
Proof. We may assume that the curve passes through the origin. 
Supp ose that r is planar. Then the image of r is contained in a 
plane . As the curve passes through the origin,  contains the origin 
as well. Note that the unit tangen t vector T(s) and the unit normal 
vector N(s) are contained in . It follows that B(s) is a normal vector 
to the plane; as B(s) is a unit vector, it must be constan t. But then 
dB
(s)= 0=0 N(s),ds 
so that the torsion is zero. 
Now supp ose that the torsion is zero. Then 
dB (s)=0 N= 0,ds 
so that B(s)= B0, is a constan t vector. Consider the functio n 
f(s)= r(s) B(s)= r(s) B0. 
Then 
df (s)= d(r  B0)(s)ds ds 
= T(s).B0 =0. 
So f(s) is consta nt. It is zero when r(a)= 0 (the curve passes through 
the origin) so that f(s) = 0. But then r(s) is always orthogonal to a 
xed vector, so that r is contained in a plane, that is, C is planar.  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>It is interesting to try to gure out how to characterise curves which 
are contained in spheres or cylinders. 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Double integrals</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>given by 
iD(x)=	1 if x  D 
0 if x/ D. 
If iD is integrable, then we say that the area of D is the integral 
iD dx dy. 
R 
If iD is not integrable, then D does not have an area. 
Example 22.5. Let 
D = { (x,y)  [0, 1]  [0, 1] | x,y  Q }. 
Then D does not have an area. 
Denition 22.6. If f : D  R is a function and D is bounde d, then 
pick D  R  R2 a rectangle. Dene 
f: R  R, 
by the rule 
f(x)=	f(x) if x  D 
0 otherwise. 
We say that f is integrable over D if f is integrable over R. In this 
case   
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dx dy. 
D	 R 
Prop osition 22.7. Let D  R2 be a bounde d subset and let f : D  
R and g : D  R be two integrable functions. Let  be a scalar. 
Then 
(1) f + g	is integrable over D and 
	   
f(x,y)+ g(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dx dy + g(x,y)dx dy. 
D	 D D 
(2) f is integrable over D and 
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dx dy. 
D	 D 
(3) If f(x,y)  g(x,y) for any (x,y)  D, then 
	  
f(x,y)dx dy  g(x,y)dx dy. 
D	 D 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>(4) |f| is integrable over D and 
| 
D f(x,y)dx dy| 
D|f(x,y)| dx dy. 
It is straigh tforw ard to integrate continuous functions over regions 
of three special types: 
Denition 22.8. A bounde d subset D  R2 is an elementary region 
if it is one of three types: 
Type 1: 
D = { (x,y)  R2 | a  x  b,(x)  y  (x) }, 
wher e  :[a,b]  R and  :[a,b]  R are continuous functions. 
Type 2: 
D = { (x,y)  R2 | c  y  d,(y)  x  (y) }, 
wher e  :[c,d]  R and  :[c,d]  R are continuous functions. 
Type 3: D is both type 1 and 2. 
Theorem 22.9. Let D  R2 be an elementary region and let f : D  
R be a continuous function. 
Then 
(1) If D is of type 1, then 
  b  (x)  
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dy dx. 
D a(x) 
(2) If D if of type 2, then 
  d  (y)  
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x,y)dx dy. 
D c(y) 
Example 22.10. Let D be the region bounde d by the lines x =0, 
y =4 and the parabola y = x2 . Let f : D  R be the function given 
by f(x,y)= x2 + y2 . 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>If we view D as a region of type 1, then we get 
  2  4  
f(x,y)dx dy = x 2 + y 2 dy dx 
D 0 x2 
 2 3 4 
= x 2 y + ydx 30 x2  2 26 x6 
= 4x 2 +3  x 4  3dx 
0 4x3 26xx5 x7 2 
= 3+3  5  37 0 
25 27 25 27 
=3+3  5  37 
26 28 
= + 35 7 1 22 
=26 + . 35 7 
On the other hand, if we view D as a region of type 2, then we get 
  4  y  
f(x,y)dx dy = x 2 + y 2 dx dy 
D 0 0  4 3 yx= + xy 2 dy30 0 4 y3/2 
= + y 5/2 dy30  4 2y5/2 2y7/2 
= + 35 7 0 
26 28 
= + 35 7 1 22 
=26 + . 35 7 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>22. Double integrals 
Denition 22.1. Let R =[a,b]  [c,d]  R2 be a rectangle in the 
plane. A partition P of R is a pair of sequenc es: 
a = x0 &lt;x1 &lt; &lt;xn = b 
c = y0 &lt;y1 &lt; &lt;yn = d.
The mesh of P is
m(P) = max{ xi  xi1,yi  yi1 | 1  i  k }.
Now supp ose we are given a function
f : R  R
Pick
cij  Rij =[xi1,xi]  [yj1,yj ]. 
Denition 22.2. The sum 
nn
S = f(cij )(xi  xi1)(yj  yj1), 
i=1 j=1 
is called a Riemann sum . 
We will use the short hand notation
xi = xi  xi1 and yj = yj  yj1.
Denition 22.3. The function f : R  R is called integrable, with 
integral I, if for every &gt; 0, we may nd a &gt; 0 such that for every 
mesh P whose mesh size is less than , we have 
|I  S| &lt; , 
wher e S is any Riemann sum associate d to P. 
We write 
f(x,y)dx dy = I,
R 
to mean that f is integrable with integral I. 
We use a sneaky trick to integrate over regions other than rectangles. 
Supp ose that D is a bounded subset of the plane. Then we can nd a 
rectangle R which completely contains D. 
Denition 22.4. The indic ator function of D  R is the function 
iD : R 
1 R,</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Change of coordinates: I</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_25/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;25</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>computing I, we compute I2 , 
   
2  
2 I2 = exdxeydy 
    
2 2 = exydx dy 
  
2 2 = exydx dy 
 R2 
= rer2 dr d 
R2   2   
2 = rerd dr 
0 0 
 
2 2 
= rerd dr 
0 0 
 
2 =2 rerdr 
0 
er2  
=2  2 
0 
= . 
So I = . 
Example 25.6. Find the area of the region D bounde d by the four 
curves 
xy =1, xy =3,y = x 3 , and y =2x 3 . 
Dene two new variables, 
3xu = and v = xy. y 
Then D is a rectangle in uv-coordinates, 
D = [1/2, 1]  [1, 3] 
Now for the Jacobian we have 
(u,v)(x,y)= 
 3x
y 2 x
y23 
 =4x3 
=4u. (x,y) yx y 
It follows that 
(x,y) 1 (u,v)= . (u,v) 4u 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>This is nowher e zero. In fact note that we can solve for x and y ex
plicitly in terms of u and v. 
uv = x 4 and y = x. v 
So 
x =(uv)1/4 and y = u1/4 v 3/4 . 
Ther efore 
area(D )= dx dy 
 D 
1 = du dv 4u D 
3  1  1 1 = du dv 4 1 1/2 u 
 31 1 = 4 [ln u]1/2 dv 
1 31 = ln2dv 4 1 
1 = ln2. 2 
Theorem 25.7. Let g : U  V be a dieomorphism between open 
subsets of R3 , 
g(u,v,w)=(x(u,v,w),y(u,v,w),z(u,v,w)). 
Let W   U be a region and let W = f(W )  V . Let f : W  R be 
a function. 
Then  
f(x,y,z)dx dy dz = f(x(u,v,w),y(u,v,w),z(u,v,w))| det Dg(u,v,w)| du dv dw. 
W W  
As before, it is convenien t to introduce more notation:
(x,y,z)
(u,v,w) = det Dg(u,v,w). (u,v,w)
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>25. Change of coordin ates: I
Denition 25.1. A function f : U  V between two open subsets of 
Rn is called a dieomorphism if: 
(1) f is a bijection, 
(2) f is dier entiable, and 
(3) f1 is dier entiable. 
Almost be denition of the inverse function, f  f1 : V  V and 
f1  f : U  U are both the identity function, so that 
(ff1)(y)= y and (f1 f)(x)= x.   
It follows that 
Df(x)Df1(y)= In and Df1(y)Df(x)= In, 
by the chain rule. Taking determinan ts, we see that 
det(Df)det(Df1) = det In =1. 
Therefore, 
det(Df1) = (det(Df))1 . 
It follows that 
det(Df)=0. 
Theorem 25.2 (Inverse functio n theorem). Let U  Rn be an open 
subset and let f : U  R be a function. 
Supp ose that 
(1) f is injective, 
(2) f is C1, and 
(3) Df(x)=0  for all x  U. 
Then V = f(U)  Rn is open and the induc ed map f : U  V is a 
dieomorphism. 
Example 25.3. Let f(r,)=(r cos ,r sin ). Then 
cos  sin  Df(r,)= ,r sin r cos  
so that 
det Df(r,)= r. 
It follows that f denes a dieomorphism f : U  V between 
U = (0, )(0, 2) and V = R2 \{ (x,y)  R2 | y =0,x  0 }. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Theorem 25.4. Let g : U  V be a dieomorphism between open 
subsets of R2 , 
g(u,v)=(x(u,v),y(u,v)). 
Let D  U be a region and let D = f(D)  V . Let f : D  R be a 
function. 
Then 
f(x,y)dx dy = f(x(u,v),y(u,v))| det Dg(u,v)| du dv. 
D D 
It is convenien t to use the following notation: 
(x,y)(u,v) = det Dg(u,v). (u,v)
The LHS is called the Jacobian. Note that 
(x,y) (u,v) 1 
(u,v)= (x,y) . (u,v) (x,y)
2 Example 25.5. Ther e is no simple expression for the integral of ex. 
However it is possible to compute the following integral 
 
2 I = exdx. 
 
(In what follows, we will ignor e issues relating to the fact that the 
integrals are impr oper; in practic e all integrals conver ge). Inste ad of 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Limits</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>be given by t  (t, 0). As f is continuous, if we compose we must get 
a function with a limit, 
0 lim =lim 0=0. 
t0 t2 +0 t0  
Now suppose that we restrict to the line y = x. Now consider the 
function 
, f : R  R2 
be given by t  (t,t). As f is continuous, if we compose we must get 
a function with a limit, 
t2 11 lim =lim = . 
t0 t2 + t2 t0 22  
The problem is that the limit along two dier ent lines is dier ent. So 
the original limit cannot exist. 
Example 8.15. Does the limit 
3xlim , 
(x,y )(0,0) x2 + y2 
exist? Let us use polar coordinates. Note that 
x3 r3 cos3  = = r cos 3 . x2 + y2 r2 
So we guess the limit is zero. 
3 
lim x= lim r cos 3 
(x,y )(0,0) |x2 + y2 | 
r0 || 
 lim |r| =0. 
r0
Example 8.16. Does the limit 
xyz lim , 
(x,y,z)(0,0,0) x2 + y2 + z2 
exist? Same trick, but now let us use spheric al coordinates. 
xyz 3 cos2  sin  cos  sin  lim = lim 
(x,y,z)(0,0,0) |x2 + y2 + z2 | 
0 | 2 | 
= lim  cos 2  sin  cos  sin 
0 | | 
 lim =0. 
0 || 
Sometimes Norman needs to restrict to more complicat ed curves than 
just lines: 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>8. Limits
Denition 8.1. Let P  Rn be a point. The open ball of radius 
&gt; 0 about P is the set 
B(P )= { Q  Rn |PQ &lt; }. 
The close d ball of radius &gt; 0 about P is the set 
{ Q  Rn | PQ  }. 
Denition 8.2. A subset A  Rn is called open if for every P  A 
there is an &gt; 0 such that the open ball of radius  about P is entir ely 
containe d in A, 
B(P )  A. 
We say that B is close d if the complement of B is open. 
Put dieren tly, an open set is a union of open balls. Open balls are 
open and closed balls are closed. [0, 1) is neither open nor closed. 
Denition 8.3. Let B  Rn . We say that P  Rn is a limit point 
if for every &gt; 0 the interse ction 
B(P )  B =. 
Example 8.4. 0 is a limit point of 
1 { n | n  N } R. 
Lemma 8.5. A subset B  Rn is close d if and only if B contains all 
of its limit points. 
Example 8.6. Rn {0} is open. One can see this directly from the 
denition or from the fact that the complement {0} is close d. 
Denition 8.7. Let A  Rn and let P  Rn be a limit point. Supp ose 
that f : A  Rm is a function. 
We say that f approaches L as Q approaches P and write 
lim f(Q)= L, 
QP
if for every &gt; 0 we may nd &gt; 0 such that whenever Q  B(P )A 
f(Q)  B(L). In this case we call L the limit. 
It migh t help to understand the notion of a limit in terms of a game 
played between two people. Lets call the rst player Larry and the 
second player Norman. Larry wants to show that L is the limit of f(Q) 
as Q approac hes P and Norman does not. 
So Norman gets to choose &gt; 0. Once Norman has chosen &gt; 0, 
Larry has to choose &gt; 0. The smaller that Norman chooses &gt; 0, 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>= , the harder Larry has to work (typicall y he will have to make a choice 
of &gt; 0 very small). 
Prop osition 8.8. Let f : A  Rm and g : A  Rm be two func
tions. Let   R be a scalar. If P is a limit point of A and 
lim f(Q)= L and lim g(Q)= M, 
QP QP  
then 
(1) limQP (f + g)(Q)= L + M, and 
(2) limQP (f)(Q)= L. 
Now suppose that m =1. 
(3) limQP (fg)(Q)= LM, and 
(4) if M =0, then limQP (f/g)(Q)= L/M.  
Proof. We just prove (1). Supp ose that &gt; 0. As L and M are limits, 
we may nd 1 and 2 such that, if Q  P  &lt;1 and Q  A, then 
f(Q)  L &lt; /2 and if Q  P  &lt;2 and Q  A, then g(Q)  L &lt; 
/2. 
Let  = min(1,2). If Q  P  &lt; and Q  A, then 
(f + g)(Q)  L  M = (f(Q)  L)+(g(Q)  M) 
(f(Q)  L) + (g(Q)  M) 
 2+2 
where we applied the triangle inequalit y to get from the second line to 
the third line. This is (1). (2-4) have similar proofs.  
Denition 8.9. Let A  Rn and let P  A. If f : A  Rm is a 
function, then we say that f is continuous at P , if 
lim f(Q)= f(P ). 
QP
We say that f is continuous, if it continuous at every point of A. 
Theorem 8.10. If f : Rn  R is a polynomial function, then f is 
continuous. 
A similar result holds if f is a rational function (a quotien t of two 
polynomials). 
Example 8.11. f : R2  R given by f(x,y)= x2 + y2 is continuous. 
Sometimes Larry is very lucky: 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Example 8.17. Does the limit 
ylim , 
(x,y )(0,0) y + x2 
exist? If we restrict to the line t  (at,bt), then we get 
bt b lim =lim =1. 
t0 bt + a2t2 t0 b + at 
But if we restrict to the conic t  (t,at2), then we get 
at2 aa lim =lim = , 
t0 at2 + t2 t0 1+ a 1+ a  
and the limit changes as we vary a, so that the limit does not exist. 
Note that if we start with 
y 
y + xd , 
then Norman even needs to use curves of degree d, 
t  (t,atd). 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Example 8.12. Does the limit 
2 2 
lim x y, 
(x,y )(0,0)x  y 
exist? Here the domain of f is 
A = { (x,y)  R2 | x =y }. 
Note (0, 0) is a limit point of A. Note that if (x,y)  A, then 
2 2x y= x + y, x  y 
so that 
2 2 
lim x y= lim x + y =0. 
(x,y )(0,0) (x,y )(0,0) x  y 
So the limit does exist. 
Norman likes the following result: 
Prop osition 8.13. Let A  Rn and let B  Rm . Let f : A  B and 
. g : B  Rl 
Supp ose that P is a limit point of A, L is a limit point of B and 
lim 
QP f(Q) = L and lim 
ML g(M) = E. 
Then 
lim 
QP (g  f)(Q) = E. 
Proof. Let &gt; 0. We may nd &gt; 0 such that if M  L &lt;, and 
M  B, then g(M)  E &lt;. Given &gt; 0 we may nd &gt; 0 such 
that if Q  P  &lt; and Q  A, then |f(Q)  L &lt;. But then if 
Q  P  &lt; and Q  A, then M = f(Q)  B and M  L &lt;, so 
that 
(gf)(Q)  E = g(f(Q))  E  
= g(M)  E 
&lt; .  
Example 8.14. Does 
xylim 
(x,y )(0,0) x2 + y2 
exist? The answer is no. 
To show that the answer is no, we suppose that the limit exists. 
Supp ose we consider restricting to the x-axis. Let 
, f : R  R2 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Gauss theorem</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_33/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;33</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Step 2: We supp ose that there is a compact subset K  M and a 
parametrisation 
g : H3  U  M  W, 
such that 
(1) F(x)= 0 for any x  M \ K. 
(2) K  M  W .
We may write
g(u,v,w)=(x(u,v,w),y(u,v,w),z(u,v,w)). 
Dene 
G: H3  R3 , 
by 
(y,z) (x,z) (x,y)G1 = F1 + F3(v,w)  F2 (v,w) (v,w) 
(y,z) (x,z) (x,y)G2 = F1 (u,w)+ F2 (u,w)  F3 (u,w) 
(y,z) (x,z) (x,y)G3 = F1 + F3 ,(u,v)  F2 (u,v) (u,v)
for any (u,v,w)  V and otherwise zero. Put dieren tly, 
G(u,v,w)= F A if (u,v,w)  U 
0 otherwise, 
where A is the matrix of cofactors of the deriv ative Dg. 
One can check (that is, there is a somewhat long and involved cal
culation, similar, but much worse, than ones that appear in the proof 
of Greens Theo rem or Stokes Theorem) that 
div G= div Fdet Dg 
= div F(x,y,z) . (u,v,w) 
We have   
div Fdx dy dz = div Gdx dy dz 
M H3 
d = G S, 
H2  
d = FS,  
M 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>where the last equalit y needs to be checked (this is relativ ely straigh t
forward). 
This completes step 2. 
Step 3: We nish o in the standard way. We may nd a partit ion 
of unity 
k
1= i, 
i=1 
where i is a smooth function which is zero outside a compact subset 
Ki such that Fi = iFis a smooth vector eld, which satises the 
hypothesis of step 2, for each 1  i  k. We have 
k
F= Fi. 
i=1 
and so 
 k 
curl FdS= curl Fi  dS  
S Si=1 
k 
= Fi  ds 
i=1 M 
= Fds.   
M 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>33. Gauss Theo rem 
Theorem 33.1 (Gauss Theorem). Let M  R3 be a smo oth 3-manifold 
with boundary, and let F: M  R3 be a smooth vector eld with com
pact support. 
Then   
div Fdx dy dz = FdS,  
M M 
wher e M is given the outwar d orientation. 
Example 33.2. Three point charges are located at the points P1, P2 
and P3. Ther e is an electric eld 
E: R3 \{P1,P2,P3}  R3 , 
which satises div E=0. 
Supp ose there are four close d surfac es S1, S2, S3 and S4. Each Si 
divides R3 into two pieces, which we will informal ly call the inside and 
the outside. S1 and S2 and S3 are completely containe d in the inside 
of S4. The inside of S1 contains the point P1 but neither P2 nor P3, 
the inside of S2 contains the point P2 but neither P1 nor P3, and the 
inside of S3 contains the point P3 but neither P1 nor P2. The inside 
of S4, together with S4, minus the inside of S1, S2 and S3 is a smooth 
3-manifold with boundary. We have 
M = S1 S2 S3 S4. 
Recall that primes denote the reverse orientation. (33.1) implies that 
    
EdS EdS EdS EdS  
S4 S1 S2 S3    
= EdS+ EdS+ EdS+ EdS  
S4 S1S2S3
= EdS 
 M 
= div Edx dy dz 
M 
=0. 
In other words, we have 
    
dddd ES = ES + ES + E S.   
S4 S1 S2 S3 
Proof of (33.1) . The proof (as usual) is divided into three steps. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Step 1: We rst supp ose that M = H3, upper half space. Supp ose 
that we are given a vector eld G: H3  R3, which is zero outside 
some box 
K =[a/2,a/2]  [b/2,b/2]  [0,c/2]. 
We calculate:   c  b  a   
div Gdu dv dw = G1 + G2 + G1 du dv dw 
H3 0 u v w 
 c 
bb a 
= (G1(a,v,w)  G1(a,v,w)) dv dw 
0 b 
ca 
+ (G2(u,b,w)  G2(u, b,w)) du dw 
 0 
b a
a 
+ (G3(u,v,c)  G3(u,v, 0)) du dw 
 b
b  a
a 
=  G3(u,v, 0)du dw. 
b a 
On the other hand, lets parametrise the boundary H3, by 
g : R2  H3 , 
where 
g(u,v)=(u,v, 0). 
In this case 
g g 
u  v =  j= k. 
It follows that 
GdS= Gkdu dv  
(H2) R2 
 b  a 
= G3(u,v, 0)du dv. 
b a 
Therefore 
GdS= GdS
H2  
(H2)  
 b  a 
=  G3(u,v, 0)du dv. 
b a 
Putting all of this together, we have  
div Gdu dv dw = dG S. 
H3 H2  
This completes step 1. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Dot product</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Theorem 2.5. If v and ware any two vectors in R3, then 
v  w= v w cos . 
Proof. If v is the zero vector, then both sides are equal to zero, so that 
they are equal to each other and the formula holds (note though, that 
in this case the angle  is not determined ). 
By symmetry , we may assume that v and ware both non-zero. Let 
u = wv and apply the law of cosines to the triangl e with sides parallel 
to u, v and w: 
u2 = v2 + w2  2vw cos . 
We have already seen that the LHS of this equation expands to 
v v  2v w+ ww= v2  2v w+ w.   
Cancelling the common terms v2 and w2 from both sides, and 
dividing by 2, we get the desired formula.  
We can use (2.5) to nd the angle between two vectors: 
Example 2.6. Let v =  + kand w= +j. Then 
1= v  w= vw cos  = 2 cos . 
Ther efore cos  = 1/2 and so  =2/3. 
Denition 2.7. We say that two vectors v and win R3 are ortho g
onal if v w=0. 
Remark 2.8. If neither v nor ware the zero vector, and v w=0 then 
the angle between v and wis a right angle. Our convention is that the 
zero vector is ortho gonal to every vector. 
Example 2.9. , jand kare pairwise ortho gonal. 
Given two vectors v and w, we can project v onto w. The resulting 
vector is called the projection of v onto wand is denot ed projwv. For 
example, if Fis a force and wis a direction, then the projection of F
onto wis the force in the direction of w. 
As projwv is parallel to w, we have 
projwv = w, 
for some scalar . Lets determine . Lets deal with the case that 
  0 (so that the angle  between v and wis between 0 and /2). If 
we take the norm of both sides, we get 
 projwv = w = w, 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>(note that   0), so that 
 =  projwv. w 
But 
cos  =  projwv, v 
so that 
 projwv = v cos . 
Putting all of this together we get 
 = v cos  
w
= vw cos 
w2 
v w=  . w2 
There are a number of ways to deal with the case when &lt; 0 (so 
that  &gt; /2). One can carry out a similar analysis to the one given 
above. Here is another way. Note that the angle  between wand 
u = v is equal to    &lt; /2. By what we already proved 
u wprojw w. u = w2 
But proju =  projv and u w= v w, so we get the same formulaw w  
in the end. To summarise: 
Theorem 2.10. If v and ware two vectors in R3, where wis not zero, 
then   v wprojw w. v = w2 
Example 2.11. Find the distanc e d between the line l containing the 
points P1 = (1, 1, 2) and P2 = (4, 1, 0) and the point Q = (3, 2, 4). 
Supp ose that R is the closest point on the line l to the point Q. Note 
that P1P2 of the line. So we want the QR is ortho gonal to the direction 
length of the vector P1Q  proj
P1P
2 P1Q, that is, we want 
d = P1Q  projP1Q.P1P
2 
Now and P1P2 = (3, 2, 2). P1Q = (2, 3, 2) 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>We have 
2 =32 +22 +22 = 17 and P1Q =6+6  4=8. P1P2 P1P2  
It follows that 
proj 8 (3, 2, 2).P1P
2 P1Q = 17
Subtr acting, we get 
 8 (3, 2, 2)= 1(10, 35, 50)= 5(2, 7, 10). P1QprojP1Q = (2, 3, 2)P1P
2 17 17 17
Taking the length, we get 
5 (22 +72 + 102)1/2  3.64. 17
Theorem 2.12. The angle subtende d on the circumference of a circle 
by a diameter of the circle is always a right angle. 
Proof. Supp ose that P and Q are the two endp oints of a diameter of 
the circle and that R is a point on the circumf erence. We want to show 
that the angle between QR is a right angle. PR and 
Let O be the centre of the circle . Then
PO + and QR = OR. PR = OR QO + 
Note that PO. QO = Therefore 
PO + (OR) PR QR =(OR) QO +   
=(PO + OR) OR  (PO) 
= 2  PO2OR
= r 2  r 2 =0, 
where r is the radius of the circle. PR and It follows that QR are 
indeed orthogonal.  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>2. Dot product
Denition 2.1. Let v =(v1,v2,v3) and w=(w1,w2,w3) be two vectors 
in R3 . The dot product of v and w, denote d v w, is the scalar  
v1w1 + v2w2 + v3w3. 
Example 2.2. The dot product of v = (1, 2, 1) and w= (2, 1, 3) 
is 
1 2+(2) 1+(1) (3) = 2  2+3=3.  
Lemma 2.3. Let u, v and wbe three vectors in R3 and let  be a 
scalar. 
(1) (u + v) w= u w+ v w.   
(2) v w= wv. 
(3) (v) w= (v w). 
(4) v	v =0 if and only if v = 0.  
Proof. (13) are straigh tforw ard. 
To see (4), rst note that one direction is clear. If v = 0, then 
v v = 0. For the other direction, suppose that v v = 0. Then 	  
v12 + v22 + v32 = 0. Now the square of a real number is non-negativ e and 
if a sum of non-negativ e numbers is zero, then each term must be zero. 
It follows that v1 = v2 = v3 = 0 and so v = 0.  
Denition 2.4. If v  R3, then the norm or length of v =(v1,v2,v3) 
is the scalar 
v = 
v v =(v12 + v22 + v32)1/2 .  
It is interesting to note that if you know the norm, then you can 
calculate the dot product: 
(v + w)(v + w)= v v +2v w+ ww   
(v  w)(v  w)= vw +  vv  2ww.   
Subtracting and dividing by 4 we get 
1 v w= ((v + w)(v + w)  (v  w)(v  w)) 	4   
1 = 4(v + w2 v  w2). 
Given two non-zero vectors v and win space, note that we can dene 
the angle  between v and w. v and wlie in at least one plane (whic h 
is in fact unique, unless v and ware parallel). Now just measure the 
angle  between the v and win this plane. By convention we always 
take 0    . 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>More about derivatives</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Proof. Let a1,a2,...,am be the rows of A. Then the entry in the ith 
row of Av is ai  v. So, 
Av2 =(a1  v)2 +(a2  v)2 + +(an  v)2  
+ a12v2 + a22v2  + an2v2 
=(a12 + a22 +  + an2)v2 
= K2 2 .v
Now take square roots of both sides.  
Theorem 10.5. Let f : A  Rm be a function, wher e A  Rn is 
open. 
If f is dier entiable at P , then f is continuous at P . 
Proof. Supp ose that Df(P )= A. Then 
lim f(Q)  f(P )  A  
=0. PQ 
QP PQ 
This is the same as to require 
f(Q)  f(P )  A 
lim  PQ =0. 
QP PQ 
But if this happ ens, then surely 
lim 
P f(Q)  f(P )  A PQ =0.
Q 
So 
f(Q)  f(P ) = f(Q)  f(P )  A PQ + A PQ 
f(Q)  f(P )  A  PQ + A  PQ 
f(Q)  f(P )  A  PQ. PQ + K
Taking the limit as Q approac hes P , both terms on the RHS go to zero, 
so that 
lim 
P f(Q)  f(P ) =0, 
Q
and f is continuous at P .  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>10. More about deriv atives
The main result is:
Theorem 10.1. Let A  Rn be an open subset and let f : A  Rm 
be a function. 
If the partial derivatives 
fi ,xj 
exist and are continuous, then f is dier entiable. 
We will need: 
Theorem 10.2 (Mean value theorem) . Let f :[a,b]  R is con
tinuous and dier entiable at every point of (a,b), then we may nd 
c  (a,b) such that 
f(b)  f(a)= f(c)(b  a). 
Geometrically , (10.2) is clear. However it is surprisingly hard to give 
a complete proof. 
Proof of (10.1) . We may assume that m = 1. We only prove this in 
the case when n = 2 (the general case is similar, only notationally more 
involved). So we have 
f : R2  R. 
Supp ose that P =(a,b) and let  + h2Let PQ = h1 j. 
P0 =(a,b) P1 =(a + h1,b) and P2 =(a + h1,b + h2)= Q. 
Now 
f(Q)  f(P )=[f(P2)  f(P1)] + [f(P1)  f(P0)]. 
We apply the Mean value theorem twice. We may nd Q1 and Q2 such 
that 
f f f(P1)  f(P0)= (Q1)h1 and f(P2)  f(P1)= (Q2)h2. x y 
Here Q1 lies somewhere on the line segmen t P0P1 and Q2 lies on the 
line segmen t P1P2. Putting this together, we get 
f f f(Q)  f(P )= x (Q1)h1 + y (Q2)h2. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Thus 
(f (Q1)  f (P ))h1 +(f (Q2)  f (P ))h2 |f(Q)  f(P )  A  | = |x y y | PQ x 
PQ PQ 
(f f (f f 
x (Q1)  x (P ))h1|y (Q2)  (P ))h2|y |
| + 
PQ PQ 
(f (Q1)  f (P ))h1 (f (Q2)  f (P ))h2|x 
h1x ||y 
h2y |
+ || ||
f f f f = |(x(Q1)  x(P ))| + |( y (Q2)  y (P ))|. 
Note that as Q approac hes P , Q1 and Q2 both approac h P as well. As 
the partials of f are continuous, we have 
PQ f lim |f(Q)  f(P )  A  |  lim(( f (Q1) f (P ))+( f (Q2) (P ))) = 0. 
QP PQ QP |x x||y y |

Therefore f is dieren tiable at P , with deriv ative A.  
Example 10.3. Let f : A  R be given by 
x f(x,y)=  , 
x2 + y2 
wher e A = R2 Then{(0, 0)}.
f =(x2 + y2)1/2  x(2x)(1/2)(x2 + y2)1/2 
= y2 
.
x x2 + y2 (x2 + y2)3/2 
Similarly 
f xy . y = (x2 + y2)3/2 
Now both partial derivatives exist and are continuous, and so f is dif
ferentiable, with derivative the gradient, 
f = ( (x2 + y2 
y2)3/2 , (x2 + xy
y2)3/2 )= (x2 +1 
y2)3/2 (y 2 , xy). 
Lemma 10.4. Let A =(aij ) be an m  n matrix. 
If v  Rn then 
Av Kv, 
wher e  
K =( a 2 )1/2 .ij 
i,j 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Planes and distances</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>not parallel. The cross product is a vector which is orthog onal to both 
vectors, 
n = P0P2. P0P1  
So the equation we want is 
(P0P2)=0. P0PP0P1   
We can rewrite this a little. = OP  Expanding and rear P0P OP0. 
ranging gives 
OP (P0P2)= (P0P1  OP0  P0P1  P0P2).  
Note that both sides involve the triple scalar product. 
Example 4.3. What is the equation of the plane  through the three 
points, P0 = (1, 1, 1), P1 = (2, 1, 0) and P2 = (0, 1, 1)? 
and P0P2 =(1, 2, 2). P0P1 = (1, 2, 1) 
Now a vector ortho gonal to both of these vectors is given by the cross 
product: 
n = P0P1  P0P2 
jk
1 2 1 
1 2 2 =
+ k
2 1
2 2
1 1 
2 1 2 
2=
 j
1
1
= 2 + 3k. j  4
Note that 
n P0P1 =2  6+4=0, 
as expected. It follows that the equation of  is 
2(x  1) + 3(y  1)  4(z  1) = 0, 
so that 
2x +3y  4z =1. 
For example, if we plug in P2 = (0, 1, 1), then 
2 0+3 1+4=1,  
as expected. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>4. Planes and distances 
How do we represen t a plane  in R3? In fact the best way to specify 
a plane is to give a normal vector n to the plane and a point P0 on the 
plane. Then if we are given any point P on the plane, the vector P0P 
is a vector in the plane, so that it must be orthogonal to the normal 
vector n. Algebraically , we have 
P0P n =0. 
Lets write this out as an explicit equation. Supp ose that the point 
P0 =(x0,y0,z0), P =(x,y,z) and n =(A,B,C). Then we have 
(x  x0,y  y0,z  z0)(A,B,C)=0. 
Expanding, we get 
A(x  x0)+ B(y  y0)+ C(z  z0)=0, 
which is one common way to write down a plane. We can always rewrite 
this as 
Ax + By + Cz = D. 
Here 
D = Ax0 + By0 + Cz0 =(A,B,C)(x0,y0,z0)= n OP0.  
This is perhaps the most common way to write down the equation of 
a plane. 
Example 4.1. 
3x  4y +2z =6, 
is the equation of a plane. A vector normal to the plane is (3, 4, 2). 
Example 4.2. What is the e quation of a plane p assing thr ough (1, 1, 2), 
with normal vector n = (2, 1, 1)? We have 
(x  1,y +1,z  2) (2, 1, 1) = 0. 
So 
2(x  1) + y +1  (z  2) = 0, 
so that in other words, 
2x + y  z = 1. 
A line is determined by two points; a plane is determined by three 
points, provided those points are not collinear (that is, provided they 
dont lie on the same line). So given three points P0, P1 and P2, what is 
the equation of the plane  containing P0, P1 and P2? Well, we would 
like to nd a vector n orthogonal to any vector in the plane. Note that and are two vectors in the plane, which by assumption are P0P1 P0P2 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Example 4.4. What is the parametric equation for the line l given as 
the interse ction of the two planes 2x  y + z =1 and x + y  z =2? 
Well we need two points on the interse ction of these two planes. If 
we set z =0, then we get the interse ction of two lines in the xy-plane, 
2x  y =1 
x + y =2. 
Adding these two equations we get 3x =3, so that x =1. It follows 
that y =1, so that P0 = (1, 1, 0) is a point on the line. 
Now suppose that y =0. Then we get 
2x + z =1 
x  z =2. 
As before this says x =1 and so z = 1. So P1 = (1, 0, 1) is a point 
on l. P0P = tP0P1, 
for some parameter t. Expanding 
(x  1,y  1,z)= t(0, 1, 1), 
so that 
(x,y,z) = (1, 1  t, t). 
We can also calculate distances between planes and points, lines and 
points, and lines and lines. 
Example 4.5. What is the distanc e between the plane x  2y +3z =4 
and the point P = (1, 2, 3)? 
Call the closest point R. Then PR is ortho gonal to every vector in 
the plane, that is, n = (1, 2, 3) PR is normal to the plane. Note that 
is normal to the plane, so that PR is parallel to the plane. 
Pick any point Q belonging to the plane. Then the triangle PQR has 
a right angle at R, so that 
PR =  projPQ. n 
When x = z =0, then y = 2, so that Q = (0, 2, 0) is a point on the 
plane. PQ =(1, 4, 3). 
Now 
n2 = n.  n. = 12 + 22 + 32 = 14 and n  P Q = 4. 
So 
projn P Q = 2 
7(1, 2, 3). 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>is the distanc e between the two lines. 
Now if we plug in t =0 to both lines we get 
P  =(2, 1, 2) and P =(1, 2, 1). 
So P P = (1, 1, 1). 
Then 
n2 =12 +32 = 10 and nP P = 2. 
It follows that 
projn P P = 2(0, 1, 3) = 1(0, 1, 3). 10 5 
and so the distanc e between the two lines is 
1
10. 5 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>So the distanc e is 2
14. 7 
Here is another way to proceed. The line through P , pointing in the 
direction n, will interse ct the plane at the point R. Now this line is 
given parametric ally as 
(x  1,y  2,z  3) = t(1, 2, 3), 
so that 
(x,y,z)=(t +1, 2  2t, 3+3t). 
The point R corresponds to 
(t + 1)  2(2  2t) + 3(3 + 3t)=4, 
so that 
14t = 2 that is t = 2 
7 . 
So the point R is 
1 
thesame answer asbefore(phew!). 
 (9, 10, 27). 7
It follows that 
PR = 1(2, 4, 6)= 2(1, 2, 3),7 7
Example 4.6. What is the distanc e between the two lines 
(x,y,z)=(t2, 3t+1, 2t) and (x,y,z) = (2t1, 23t,t+1)? 
If the two closest points are R and R then RR is orhogonal to the 
direction of both lines. Now the direction of the rst line is (1, 3, 1) 
and the direction of the second line is (2, 3, 1). A vector ortho gonal 
to both is given by the cross product:
jk
13 1
2 31
= 3k. j  9
To simplify some of the algebr a, lets take 
n =k, j + 3
which is parallel to the vector above, so that it is still ortho gonal to both 
lines. 
It follows that RR is parallel to n. Pick any two points P and P  
on the two lines. Note that the length of the vector 
projn P P, 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Div grad curl and all that</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>A solution of the dier ential equation 
2f =0, 
is called a harmonic function . 
Example 18.11. The function 
c f(x,y,z)= (x2 + y2 + z2)1/2 , 
is harmonic. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>18. Div grad curl and all that 
Theorem 18.1. Let A  Rn be open and let f : A  R be a dier
entiable function. 
If r : I  A is a ow line for f : A  Rn, then the function 
f  r : I  R is increasing. 
Proof. By the chain rule, 
d(f r) 
dt  (t)= f(r(t))  r(t) 
= r(t) r(t)  0.   
Corollary 18.2. A close d parametrise d curve is never the ow line of 
a conservative vector eld. 
Once again, note that (18.2) is mainly a negativ e result: 
Example 18.3. 
F: R2{(0, 0)}  R2 given by F(x,y)=(x2 + y
y,x2 + x
y),2 2 
is not a conservative vector eld as it has ow lines which are circles. 
Denition 18.4. The del operator is the formal symb ol 
     =  + j+ k. x y z 
Note that one can formally dene the gradien t of a function 
grad f : R3  R3 , 
by the formal rule 
f f f  grad f = f = x  + y j+ z k. 
Using the operator del we can dene two other operations, this time 
on vector elds: 
Denition 18.5. Let A  R3 be an open subset and let F: A  R3 
be a vector eld. 
The diver gence of Fis the scalar function, 
div F: A  R, 
which is dene d by the rule 
f f f div F(x,y,z)=  F(x,y,z)= x + y + z . 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The curl of Fis the vector eld 
curl F: A  R3 , 
which is dene d by the rule 
curl F(x,x,z)=  F (x,y,z)
 
F F F F F F 3 2 3 1 2 1   j k. +   = y z x z x y 
Note that thedeloperator makessense forany ,notjust 3. n n = 
Sowecanden ethegradien tandthedivergence inalldimensions. 
Howevercurlonly makessense when =3. n
 3R Denition 18.6. The vector eld FA iscalled rotation :  
free if the curl is zero, curl F= 0, and it is called incompr essible if 
the diver gence is zero, div F=0. 
Prop osition 18.7. Let f be a scalar eld and Fa vector eld. 
(1) If f is C2, then curl(grad f)= 0. Every conservative vector eld 
is rotation free. 
(2) If Fis C2, then div(curl F)=0. The curl of a vector eld is 
incompr essible. 
Proof. We compute; jk
  =
x y z 
F1 F2 F3 
curl(grad f)=  (f) 
jk
   =
x y z 
f f f 
x y z 
2f 2f 2f 2f 2f 2f k
  j+   xz  zx yz 
zy
 xy 
yx
=
= 0. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>This gives (1). 
div(curl F)=  ( f) 
= 
jk
   
x y z 
F1 F2 F3 
=
   
x y z 
   
x y z 
F1 F2 F3 
2F3 2F2 2F3 2F1 2F2 2F1 = xy  xz  yx + yz + zx  zy 
=0. 
This is (2).  
Example 18.8. The gravitational eld 
cx cy cz  F (x,y,z)= + j+ k, (x2 + y2 + z2)3/2 (x2 + y2 + z2)3/2 (x2 + y2 + z2)3/2 
is a gradient vector eld, so that the gravitational eld is rotation free. 
In fact if c f(x,y,z)= (x2 + y2 + z2)1/2 , 
then F= grad f, so that 
curl F= curl(grad f)= 0. 
Example 18.9. A magnetic eld Bis always the curl of something, 
B= curl A, 
wher e Ais a vector eld. So 
div( B) = div(curl A)=0. 
Ther efore a magnetic eld is always incompr essible. 
There is one other way to combine two del operators: 
Denition 18.10. The L aplac e operator take a sc alar eld f : A  
R and outputs another scalar eld 
2f : A  R. 
It is dene d by the rule 
2f2f2f 2f = div(grad f)= x + y + z . 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Vector fields</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>As Fi is C1 for each i, it follows that f is C2 . But then 
Fi 2f = xj xj xi 
2f = xixj 
= Fj .  xi 
Notice that (17.4) is a negativ e result; one can use it show that 
various vector elds are not conserv ative. 
Example 17.5. Let 
F : R2  R2 given by F (x, y) = (y, x). 
Then 
F1 
y = 1 and F2 
x = 1 = 1. 
So F is not conservative. 
Example 17.6. Let 
F: R2 given by F(x,y)=(y,x + y).  R2 
Then 
F1 F2=1 and =1,y x 
so Fmight be conservative. Lets try to nd 
f : R2  R such that f(x,y)=(y,x + y). 
If f exists, then we must have 
f f = y and = x + y. x y 
If we integrate the rst equation with respect to x, then we get 
f(x,y)= xy + g(y). 
Note that g(y) is not just a constant but it is a function of y. Ther e are 
two ways to see this. One way, is to imagine that for every value of y, 
we have a separate dier ential equation. If we integrate both sides, we 
get an arbitr ary constant c. As we vary y, c varies, so that c = g(y) 
is a function of y. On the other hand, if to take the partial derivatives 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Then 
1 t x(t)=  sin 2 a a
y . = x2 + y2 
Similarly 
1 t y(t) = cos 2 a a
x = . x2 + y2 
So the ow lines are close d curves. In fact this means that Fis not 
conservative. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>of g(y) with respect to x, then we get 0. Now we take xy + g(y) and 
dier entiate with respect to y, to get 
(xy + g(y)) dg x + y = = x + (y). y dy 
So 
g(y)= y. 
Integrating both sides with respect to y we get 
g(y)= y 2/2+ c. 
It follows that 
(xy + y 2/2) = (y,x + y), 
so that Fis conservative. 
Denition 17.7. If F: A  Rn is a vector eld, we say that a 
parametrise d dier entiable curve r : I  A is a ow line for F, if 
r(t)= F(r(t)), 
for all t  I. 
Example 17.8. Let 
F: R2  R2 given by F(x,y)=(y,x). 
We check that 
r : R  R2 given by r(t)=(a cos t,a sin t), 
is a ow line. In fact 
r(t)=(a sin t,a cos t), 
and so 
F(r(t)) = F(a cos t,a sin t) 
= r(t), 
so that r(t) is indeed a ow line. 
Example 17.9. Let 
F: R2  R2 given by F(x,y)=(x,y). 
Lets nd a ow line through the point (a,b). We have 
x(t)= x(t) x(0) = a 
y(t)= y(t) y(0) = b. 
Ther efore, 
x(t)= aet and y(t)= bet , 
gives the ow line through (a,b). 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17. Vector fields 
Denition 17.1. Let A  Rn be an open subset. A vector eld on 
A is function F: A  Rn . 
One obvious way to get a vector eld is to take the gradien t of a 
dieren tiable function. If f : A  R, then 
,f : A  Rn 
is a vector eld. 
Denition 17.2. A vector eld F: A  Rn is called a gradient 
(aka conservative) vector eld if F= f for some dier entiable 
function f : A  R. 
Example 17.3. Let 
F: R3 {0}  R3 , 
be the vector eld 
cx cy cz  F (x,y,z)= + j+ k, (x2 + y2 + z2)3/2 (x2 + y2 + z2)3/2 (x2 + y2 + z2)3/2 
for some constant c. Then F(x,y,z) is the gradient of 
f : R3 {0}  R, 
given by 
c f(x,y,z)= (x2 + y2 + z2)1/2 . 
So Fis a conservative vector eld. Notice that if c&lt; 0 then Fmodels 
the gravitational force and f is the potential (note that unfortunately 
mathematicians and physicists have dier ent sign conventions for f). 
Prop osition 17.4. If Fis a conservative vector eld and Fis C1 
function, then 
Fi Fj= ,xj xi 
for all i and j between 1 and n. 
Proof. If Fis conserv ative, then we may nd a dieren tiable function 
f : A  Rn such that 
f Fi = . xi 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Example 17.10. Let 
F: R2  R2 given by F(x,y)=(x 2  y 2 , 2xy). 
Try 
x(t)=2a cos t sin t 
y(t)=2a sin2 t. 
Then 
x(t)=2a( sin2 t + cost) 
x2(t)  y2(t) = . y(t) 
Similarly 
y(t)=4a cos t sin t 
2x(t)y (t) = . y(t) 
So 
F(r(t))r(t)= . f(t) 
So the curves themselves are ow lines, but this is not the correct 
parametrisation. The ow lines are circles passing through the origin, 
with centre along the y-axis. 
Example 17.11. Let 
F: R2{(0, 0)}  R2 given by F(x,y)=(x2 + y
y2 ,x2 + x
y2 ). 
Then 
F1 x2 + y2 2 y2 2 
(x,y)=  2y=  x. y (x2 + y2)2 (x2 + y2)2 
and 
F2 x2 + y2 2 y2 2 
(x,y)=  2x=  x. x (x2 + y2)2 (x2 + y2)2 
So Fmight be conservative. Lets nd the ow lines. Try 
t x(t)= a cos 2a
t y(t)= a sin 2 . a
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Line integrals</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_27/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;27</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>As u is orien tation-rev ersing, we have u(c)= b and u(d) = a and so, 
 d  d 
f(y(t))y(t) dt = f(x(u(t )))u(t)x(u(t)) dt 
c c  d 
=  f(x(u(t )))x(u(t))u(t)dt 
c 
a 
=  f(x(u))x(u) du 
b b 
= f(x(u))x(u) du.  
a 
Now supp ose that we have a vector eld on C, 
. F: C  Rn 
Denition 27.4. The line integral of Falong C is 
  b 
Fds = F(x(u)) x(u)du.   
C a 
Note that now the orien tation is very importan t: 
Lemma 27.5. 
 b 
F(x(u)) x(u)du =  dF(y(t))  y(t)dtu(t) &gt; 0 c   
cdF(y(t)) y(t)dtu(t) &lt; 0 a  
Proof. We deal with the case that u is orien tation- reversing. The case 
that u is orien tation-preserving is simila r and easier. 
As u is orien tation-rev ersing, we have u(c)= b and u(d) = a and so, 
 d  d 
F(y(t)) y(t)dt = F(x(u(t ))) x(u(t))u(t)dt   
c c
a
= F(x(u)) x(u)du 
b  b 
=  F(x(u)) x(u)du.   
a 
Example 27.6. If C is a piece of wire and f(x) is the mass density 
at x  C, then the line integral 
f ds, 
C 
is the total mass of the curve. Clearly this is always positive, whichever 
way you parametrise the curve. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Example 27.7. If C is an oriente d path and F(x) is a force eld, then 
the line integral 
Fds, 
C 
is the work done when moving along C. If we reverse the orientation, 
then the sign ips. For example, imagine C is a spiral stair case and 
Fis the force due to gravity. Going up the stair case costs energy and 
going down we gain energy. 
Denition 27.8. Let U  Rk and V  Rl be two open subsets. 
We say that 
f : U  V, 
is smooth if all higher order partials 
nf (x1,x2,...,xk),xi1 ...xin 
exist and are continuous. 
Denition 27.9. Now suppose that X  Rk and Y  Rl are any two 
subsets. We say that a function 
f: X  Y, 
is smooth, if given any point a  X we may nd a  U  Rk open, 
and a smooth function 
, F: U  Rl 
such that f(x)= F(x), wher e x  X U (equivalently f|XU = F|XU ), 
and we put 
Df(x)= DF(x). 
We say that fis a (smo oth) dieomorphism if fis bijective and 
both fand f1 are smooth. 
Notice that in the denition of a dieomorphism we are now requir
ing more than we did (before we just required that fand f1 were 
dieren tiable). 
Remark 27.10. Note that if X is not very big then Df(x) might 
not be unique. For example, if X = {x} is a single point, then there 
are very many dier ent ways to extend fto a function Fin an open 
neighb ourho od of x. In the examples we consider in this class, this will 
not be an issue (namely, manifolds with boundary). 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Example 27.11. The map 
x:[a,b]  Rn , 
is smooth if and only if there is a constant &gt; 0 and a smooth function 
y :(a  ,b + )  Rn , 
whose restriction to [a,b] is the function x, 
y(t)= x(t) for all t  [a,b]. 
Lemma 27.12. If 
x:[a,b]  Rn , 
is injective for all t  [a,b], then 
x:[a,b]  C = x([a,b]), 
is a dieomorphism. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>27. Line integrals 
Let I be an open interval and let 
x: I  Rn , 
be a parametrised dieren tiable curve. If [a,b]  I then let C = 
x([a,b]) be the image of [a,b] and let f : C  R be a function. 
Denition 27.1. The line integral of f along C is 
  b 
f ds = f(x(u))x(u) du. 
C a 
Let u: J  I be a dieomorphism between two open intervals. 
Supp ose that u is C1 . 
Denition 27.2. We say that u is orientation-pr eserving if u(t) &gt; 
0 for every t  J. 
We say that u is orientation-r eversing if u(t) &lt; 0 for every 
t  J. 
Notice that u is always either orien tation-preserving or orien tation-
reversing (this is a consequence of the intermediate value theorem, ap
plied to the continuous function u(t)). 
Dene a functio n 
y : J  Rn , 
by comp osition, 
y(t)= x(u(t)), 
so that y = x u.
Now supp ose that u([c,d]) = [a,b]. Then C = y([c,d]), so that y 
gives another parametrisation of C. 
Lemma 27.3. 
 b  d 
f(x(u))x(u) du = f(y(t))y(t) dt. 
a c 
Proof. We deal with the case that u is orien tation- reversing. The case 
that u is orien tation-preserving is simila r and easier. 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Change of coordinates: II</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-022-calculus-of-several-variables-fall-2010/resources/mit18_022f10_l_26/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>&#160;26</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Example 26.4. Consider a ball of radius a. Put the centre of the ball 
at the point (0, 0, 0). 
vol(W )= dx dy dz 
 W 
= 2 sin  d d d 
 2W    a  
= 2 sin  d d d 
0 0 0 2    3 a  
= sin  d d 30 0 0
 2   3 
a= sin  d d 30 0 
3 2 a  =3 0 [ cos ]0 d 
 22a3 
= d 3 0 
4a3 
= . 3 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>26. Change of coordinates: II 
Example 26.1. Let D be the region bounde d by the cardiod, 
r =1  cos . 
If we multiply both sides by r, take r cos  over the other side, then we 
get 
(x 2 + y 2 + x)2 = x 2 + y 2 . 
We have 
area(D )= dx dy 
 D 
= r dr d 
D    1cos  
= r dr d

 0 1cos  2r= d 
 2 0  (1  cos )2 
= d 2 
 
1 cos2  =2  cos  + d 2 
 
=2  sin  2  
 = . 2 
In R3, we can either use cylindrical or spherical coordinates, instead 
of Cartesian coordinates. 
Lets rst do the case of cylindrical coordinates. Recall that 
x = r cos  
y = r sin  
z = z. 
So the Jacobian is given by 
(x,y,z)
cos  r sin  0 
r cos  (r,,z)=
sin 
 0
= r.
(r,,z)
0 0 1 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>vol(W )= dx dy dz 
 W 
= r dr d dz 
 aW 
 2  
a2z2  
= r dr d dz 
1 
 a
a 0 
 2  0 

a= r 2 2z2 d dz 2 00 

aa  2  
=1 a 2  z 2 d dz 2 a 0 
a 
= a 2  z 2 dz 
a 3 a z= a 2 z  3 a 
4a3 
= . 3 
Now consider using spherical coordinates. Recall that 
x =  sin  cos  
y =  sin  sin  
z =  cos . 
So 
(x,y,z) sin  cos  cos  cos   sin  sin 
(,,)(,,)= sin  sin  cos  sin  sin  cos    cos   sin  0  
= 2 cos 2  sin  + 2 sin3  = 2 sin . 
Notice that this is greater than zero, if 0 &lt;&lt;. So, 
  
f(x,y,z)dx dy dz = f(,,)2 sin  dr d dz. 
W W  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.022  Calculus of Several Variables 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>So,   
f(x,y,z)dx dy dz = f(r,,z)dr d dz. 
W W  
Example 26.2. Consider a cone of height b and base radius a. Put 
the vertex of the cone at the point (0, 0,b), so that the base of the cone 
is the circle of radius a, centred at the origin, in the xy-plane. Note 
that at height z, we have a circle of radius 
z a 1  . b 
vol(W )= dx dy dz 
 W 
= r dr d dz 
 b W   
2  a(1z/b  
= r dr d dz 
0 0 0 
1  b  2 a(1z/b  
= r 2 d dz 2 0 0 0 
 b  2 2  1 2 z = a 1  d dz 2 0 0 b  a  z 2 
= a2 1  dz ba  0 
= a2bu 2 du 
1 1 
= a2bu 2 du 
0 
a2b = . 3 
Example 26.3. Consider a ball of radius a. Put the centre of the ball 
at the point (0, 0, 0). Note that 
2 2 2 2 x + y + z = a, 
translates to the equation 
2 2 2 r + z = a, 
so that 
2 2 r = 
a z. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
