<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/</course_url>
    <course_title>Causes and Prevention of War</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>History </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>World War II</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec15-18_wwii/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15&#8211;18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>nuclear-scale damage from bombing if war erupted. 
b. The Brit government, doubting that defense against 
bombers was possible, nearly cancelled its Spitfire 
fighter program. This would have been unwise: Spitfires won the Battle of Britain. 
5. Adopted a strategy of appeasement toward Germany. Why? 
Three explanations are common: a. Craven cowardice. The British public and government 
were snivelling wimps who cowered before German belligerence. But if this is true, why did Britain declare war on Germany in 1939 and bravely fight on alone against Germany in 1940? 
b. Dilemmas of multiple contingencies. Some argue that 
Britain felt overextended and had to appease one of its adversaries--Japan, Italy, or Germany. Germany got the nod, purely for reasons of resource limitation. 
c. British belief that Germany was appeasable, due to false 
historical understanding. Too many Britons read and believed German propaganda, concluding that "We encircled and provoked the Germans; let's not do it again!" and "We were too mean at Versailles--German demands to revise it are legitimate." a. After WWII a dominant deterrence model paradigm arose 
around Munich, but... 
b. After WWI a dominant spiral model paradigm was 
inspired by the July crisis of 1914. And meanwhile, too few Britons read Ewald Banse and Mein Kampf. 
But also ask: what if Britain had gone to war without attempting appeasement, over issues of cloudy legitimacy? What if, therefore, the war had broken out in a way that failed to clearly illuminate German responsibility? How could a stable peace have then been made? 
E. The United States: 
1. Embraced isolationism. Most important, Congress passed a series of neutrality laws during 1935-1939 that tied the president to a policy of strict neutrality in event of war elsewhere--an open message to the Nazis and Japanese saying "We won't oppose your aggression!" 
2. Adopted a mobilization military strategy that included no large standing forces. 
3. Had no clear national grand strategy; hence the United States could not predict its own behavior; hence others (Germany, Japan) couldn't predict it either. 
F. France was absorbed in domestic left-right conflicts and 
unready for war. German rightists declared: "Better Hitler than (French socialist leader) Leon Blum!" 
G. The Soviet Union was is indifferent to--even helpful 
toward--the rise of Nazis in Germany in the early 1930s. Later it is confident that a war among western states would be a long stalemate, so it dismissed the danger that France 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>unless we act; and so nice it will let us conquer 
Asia, and will not respond fully if we attack them." 
ii. "Control of economic/industrial resources is so decisive in war that we must gain such control"--in a war against a state with 10 times Japan's net economic resources! 
iii. "In World War I blockades strangled states, hence 
we need an economically independent empire"--even a seaborne empire. But WWI also showed that a seaborne empire could be strangled by an enemy with a superior navy (like the USA). 
iv. "Our economy requires empire to expand"--even though Japan's economy grew by leaps and bounds during 1871-1929 without one. 
3. Did Japan have alternatives? What if Japan had accepted 
its island borders and sought security through alliances, trusting the operation of the balance-of-power/balance-of-threat to produce help from others if it were ever threatened? 
C. Italy was the land of blue smoke and mirrors. Mussolini's 
propaganda ministry had 890 employees--lots! His government: 
1. Badly misperceived the realities of the late 1930s: 
a. Mussolini's government believed gross overestimates of 
Italian military strength. -- Mussolini's government claimed an air force of 8530 
planes, large enough to blacken the sky and match the RAF. In fact it had 583 planes--a fact it learned only by dispatching fascist prefects to airfields to count the planes. Italy built more planes in World War I than World War II. The IAF was "at the level of a Balkan state" said an IAF commander after the war. 
-- Mussolini doubled the number of divisions in Italy's 
army--by splitting them in half. He then forgot he had done this. 
b. Mussolini's government believed gross overestimates of 
the value of empire. Specifically, that an empire in Africa could absorb 10 million Italians settlers. In fact it absorbed a few thousand. 
2. Believed false images of the past: "We, the Italians, won 
WWI for the Entente! Then we were cheated of our fair share of the spoils!" 
D. Britain: 
1. Was generally isolationist. 2. Was further weakened by WWI. 3. Was late to rearm in the 1930s. 4. Embraced an aerial cult of the offensive--"the bomber will 
always get through." This illusion had two effects: a. Brits greatly feared war, as they feared immense near-
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.42 Causes &amp; Prevention of War 
Stephen Van Evera 
ORIGINS OF THE SECOND WORLD WAR 
I. WORLD WAR II IN CONTEXT 
World War II was the greatest war in world history. It 
killed some 35-60 million people, 2-3 times the toll of World War I. 
This grisly episode closely followed the most elaborate 
effort ever made to design a peaceful world--the 1919 Versailles peace. Never before had world leaders sought so consciously to shape a peaceful world as they did in 1919. And never before had the world such violence as in 1939-45. In contrast, the peace that emerged in 1945 was undesigned yet proved far more durable. What does this say of our capacity to engineer a more peaceful world?
1 
WWII included three distinct wars: Hitler's war on the 
states of Europe and elsewhere; Hitler's genocidal war on non-"Aryan" peoples; and the Pacific War--Japan's war of aggression in Asia. These wars had different causes. 
II. WAR AND REMEMBRANCE: HOW ILLUSIONS REPLACED REALITY IN 
EUROPE'S MEMORY OF THE FIRST WORLD WAR (See Holger Herwig, "Clio Deceived", assigned.)
 Sometimes losers write history. Germany largely wrote the 
history of World War I and sold this false history to the winners.
 The German-authored Great Social Science Experiment of 
1898-1918 cost a bundle. (The experiment destroyed the laboratory!) Then someone falsified the lab notes. 
III. NATIONAL POLICIES AND IDEAS 
A. Germany: lies galore: 
1. The German government secretly organized a public 
relations campaign (run from a secret office, the kriegsschuldreferat, or "war guilt office") to convince Germans and the world of German innocence and others guilt for World War I. As a result Weimar-era (1920's) German schools and scholars told and believed lies about: a. The origins of WWI--"The Entente powers encircled 
Germany and instigated the war! We were innocent victims!" 
b. The causes and responsibility for Germany's defeat--
"the Jews and the socialists did it!" Those responsible--Ludendorff, Hindenburg, and other 
1 A professional political scientist, Woodrow Wilson, was 
the chief architect of Versailles. Not a high point for the field. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>superhawks--escaped blame. Germany's blunders were not 
evaluated. Those few scholars who did evaluate (e.g., Hermann Kantorowitz) were persecuted. 
c. The harshness of the peace--"Versailles was Draconian!" 
In fact the reparations that the allies demanded were not exorbitant, and could have been paid. Moral drawn by Germany: "We need a bigger empire to be safe from our rapacious neighbors!" Instead of learning that a reach for lebensraum ("living space") 
was dangerous--indeed suicidal--Germans learned that 
gaining lebensraum was essential! 
2. Germans first embraced Nazi-like ideas (1920s), then the 
Nazis themselves (1930s). Was World War II really just a one-man show--"Hitler did it!"? No--he had many helping hands. a. German neoconservative publishers, 1890-1930. Their 
aim: maintain the old oligarchy, minimize democratization of Germany. See Gary D. Stark, Entrepreneurs of Ideology: Neoconservative Publishers in Germany, 1890-1933 (1980). 
b. German war-cult literature, 1920s (e.g., Ernst Jnger). 
3. How Hitler rose: he came to power by exploiting the fear 
and anger that German WWI innocence propaganda stirred among Germans; and through the tactical blunders of the ideologically rigid German socialists. 
4. Nazi beliefs about international affairs. 
a. "Germany is insecure," especially "Germany can be 
strangled by cutting off food imports." 
b. "An empire is the answer. Germany needs more territory 
because it needs an autarkic economy. It especially needs to end German dependence on imported food by acquiring new farmland." 
c. "Germany can conquer an empire." Why? 
i. Bandwagon ideas. Hitler believed his "avalanche" theory. 
ii. Contempt for the Soviet Union--"Germans built the USSR, but mere Jews run it now" so "We have only to kick in the door and the whole rotten structure will come crashing down." 
iii. Stalin murdered many able Soviet military leaders 
in 1938. This opened a window for Germany. 
iv. The invention of Blitzkrieg and the Manstein war plan. This occurred late--during 1939-1940--but Hitler seemed to foresee them or their equivalent. 
v. Hitler thought the US would not oppose a German reach for empire, and in any case was "Judaized and Negrified." 
5. The German military buildup. During the late 1930s 
Germany spent a far larger share of its GNP on the military than did Britain and France (see attached Tables 30-31 from Paul Kennedy). This gave Germany a large but temporary military advantage during 1938-1940. 
6. German antisemitism. German society was bitten by 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>3. Hitler? (The "great man" theory, expressed in Haffner, 
Meaning of Hitler, assigned.) (But wasn't German 
society primed to accept Hitler?) 
4. Militarism? (But the Weimar German military, while 
hardly benign, wasn't the main purveyor of Nazi ideas.) 
Problematic explanations: 
1. The Great Depression, 1929-39--it brought the Nazis to 
power. (But the depression was worldwide. Why did it make only Germany crazy?) 
2. War ---&gt; War: Was 1914-1945 one great, single war? 
Germans were steeped in the propaganda of WWI, and it's effects lived on later. (But why didn't WWI propaganda have the same effects in Britain, France, and the USA? And why didn't WWII later have the same effects as WWI?) 
Other explanations: 
1. "Continuity" from before 1914: was Naziism an after-
echo of Germany's bad ideas of 1890-1914? a. "Germans steeped in the militarist and hyper-
nationalist ideas of 1890-1914 continued to believe these ideas after the war. Once polluted, German minds remained polluted." For example: Hitler himself was steeped in the crazed pre-1914 writings of Houston Stewart Chamberlain, Gobineau, and Haushofer. See Carr, Hitler. 
b. "The same German oligarchs who promoted 
hypernationalism and perhaps militarism before 1914 continued to purvey these ideas after 1918." See Stark, Entrepreneurs. 
2. Nationalist mythmaking? We saw plenty after 1918, 
especially in the form of German innocence propaganda. (A disease of a young democracy?) 
3. Non-evaluation: of the German policies of 1890-1918 
during 1919-32; and of Hitler's ideas, 1932-1941. (Another disease of a young democracy?) 
B. Allied diplomacy. Could the allies have deterred Germany? C. Allied military inaction. Could an allied preventive war in 
1935-37 have prevented WWII? 
D. Japanese Expansionism. E. Military factors: the security dilemma and its offspring. 
VII. ESCALATION OF WWII: Windows, first strikes, security wars 
VIII. HITLER'S OTHER WARS: THE HOLOCAUST AND HITLER'S OTHER MASS 
MURDERS 
IX. AFTERMATH OF WWII: A STABLE PEACE. WHY? 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>would lose quickly; hence it failed to pursue and alliance 
with Britain and France against Germany. This left the Soviets to fight a larger, stronger Germany alone. 
H. Everywhere except Germany a military "cult of the defensive" 
gained currency. National elites assumed that offense would be as difficult in the next war as it was during 1914-1918. 
IV. HOW THE STORM GATHERED: EVENTS IN EUROPE 
A. Withdrawal of the USA, Britain, and USSR from central 
European affairs. (Replaying Britain &amp; Russia's withdrawal in 1866, 1870.) 
B. German rearmament, 1934-39--giving Germany an offensive 
capability and a fleeting military superiority.
 Why didn't the allies prevent German rearmament? Would an 
allied preventive war in 1935-37 have prevented WWII? Churchill later said so. 
C. Hitler wins without a war: appeasement and peaceful German 
expansion. 1. Hitler's recoveries and conquests: 
-- German remilitarization of the Rhineland 1936 -- Austria 1938 -- Czech Sudetenland 1938 -- The Czech rump, 1939 -- Memel, 1939 a. This is quite a nice empire! Why didn't it sate 
Germany? (Should Britain and France have launched a preventive war while it was being assembled?) 
b. International effects of these German conquests: 
-- Growth of German power. -- Destruction of allied and German credibility. 
2. The failure of a strong anti-German defensive alliance to 
emerge. 
D. Hitler attacks Poland, Sept. 1 1939, launching World War II. 
Questions about the outbreak of war: 1. Why did deterrence fail, Sept. 1, 1939? 6 explanations: 
a. Appeasement destroyed British and French credibility. b. Hitler's bandwagon beliefs destroyed British and 
French credibility: Hitler assumed that Britain and France would shrink from war if the USSR agreed to stay neutral, as it did on August 24, 1939 (Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact). 
c. Growth of German power, 1932-39. 
-- When aggressors are stronger than status quo 
powers, we get war. 
-- This is particularly true when the aggressor 
advantage is fleeting--this spurs preventive war by the aggressor. 
d. British non-strategy; and American non-strategy. 
Britain doesn't frame its strategy; America doesn't know its strategy. 
e. Britain made the wrong threat to Germany? Some say 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>antisemitism although less severely than some East 
European states. Antisemitism was fostered by perennial Christian church teaching against the Jewish people. It also assumed a racial form in the late nineteenth century as social Darwinist ideas swept Europe. It assumed its most poisonous form in the Protocols of the Elders of Zion, which painted the Jewish people as a threat to the world. The Protocols were first read by Nazi leaders in the 1920s, and apparently were believed. 
B. Japan: 
1. Militarism appeared in Japan. The military came to 
dominate Japanese national ideas about foreign affairs, 1900-1941. 
2. Ideas the Japanese military believed and/or purveyed: 
a. "Japan is insecure, and an empire is the answer." 
i. "Others are hostile." Japan embraced the myth of "ABCD [American, British, Chinese, Dutch] encirclement." It spiralled with neighbors, unaware that it provoked the hostility it faced. 
ii. "These hostile powers could strangle Japan." Specifically, "World War I shows that states can strangle each other by blockading their maritime trade--as the Entente strangled Germany. We could be next." 
iii. "A Japanese empire is both necessary and 
sufficient to address this threat." Japanese believed that: a. Due to factors i and ii Japan needed an 
independent economy that could function without external trade. 
b. A wide empire could provide economic 
independence. 
c. The West is racist and won't ally with Japan so 
Japan can't secure itself by finding Western allies. 
iv. "Japan can conquer an empire." Seizing an empire is feasible. a. Bandwagon dynamics allow it: "With the Axis 
Alliance we can scare the US into accepting our expansion." 
b. The U.S. won't resist: "If we hit America hard 
it will not fight all-out." 
b. A sugar-coated self-image--"Our empire is good for our 
fellow-Asians" and "We Japanese are not aggressive." After 1937 the Japanese press was forbidden to print "articles that may give the impression that our foreign policy is aggressive." Japan's government absurdly named its barbaric empire the "Greater East Asian Co-Prosperity Sphere." 
c. Note the disintegrated character of Japanese ideas. 
i. "The US is so aggressive that it will destroy us 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Britain should have written off Poland, and only 
warned Germany not to invade the USSR--a threat that Britain had more capacity to carry out, and which therefore would have been more credible. 
f. Lack of allied (Franco-British) offensive capability 
against Germany? 
2. Could Hitler's policy of peaceful expansion have worked 
in a Europe of nuclear-armed powers? Specifically, what if Germany, Britain, France and the Soviet Union had possessed nuclear second-strike capabilities? 
E. Hitler declares war on the United States, December 11, 1941. 
Why? 
V. HOW THE STORM GATHERED: EVENTS IN ASIA 
A. The Japanese reach for empire, 1931, 1937 ff.: Japan's China 
advance ultimately requires the southern advance. 
B. The Berlin-Rome-Tokyo Axis alliance, Sept. 1940 (also called 
the Tripartite Pact). 
C. The progressive hardening of U.S. policy, 1931-1941. 
-- Why did the US goals expand?  Specifically, why did the 
U.S. begin demanding Japanese withdrawal from China as the price of peace in July 1941? Ideas that helped motivate the U.S. hard line position include: 1. The China Market beckons. "Sell every Chinaman a 
shirt and we'll all get rich." 
2. The strategic importance of British colonies in Asia 
to the British war effort in Europe--a myth the British helped promote. 
3. The illusion of the Axis monolith: "Japan is Germany's 
loyal and obedient ally; hence Japan's gains accrue to Germany." 
4. "An Asian war can be a back door to a European war." 
(But might it not also be a trap door to an Asian morass that diverts the U.S. from Europe?) 
Note: the China Lobby and the British government promoted some of these ideas. 
D. Japan's decision to attack Pearl Harbor. Was this smart? 
Why not just bypass the Philippines, and then let Roosevelt try to start a war if it wanted one? 
E. Lessons of Pearl Harbor: Munich in reverse? Japan wasn't 
appeased--and it still went to war! 
VI. WHAT CAUSED WORLD WAR II? 
A. Clearly, German expansionism caused the European war. But 
what caused German expansionism? 
Dubious explanations: 
1. German national character? (But look at today's 
peaceful Germans...) 
2. Versailles--a "harsh peace"? (But it wasn't harsh--and 
1945 was far harsher, but produced peace!) 
7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Cold War, Korea and Indochina</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec20-21_coldwar/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20&#8211;21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>future of U.S.-China relations? 
IV. THE KOREAN WAR, 1950: WHAT HAPPENED 
A. The U.S. and USSR agreed to partition Korea at the 38th
parallel in 1945.
B. The U.S. pulled its troops out of Korea in 1949. A U.S. blunder? 
C. Communist victory in China in 1949 triggered a bitter
"who lost China?" debate in the U.S. 
D. Dean Acheson gave a speech at the Washington Press Club
in January 1950 delineating an "American defenseperimeter in Asia." He omitted South Korea! Another U.S. blunder? 
E. North Korea attacked South Korea by surprise, June 25,1950. Why? Kim Il Sung and Stalin expected the U.S.would not intervene, or that the North could crush theSouth before the U.S. could intervene effectively. A huge miscalculation by them.
F. Truman decided to intervene. Reasons: 1. To preserve American credibility. But was it engagedin Korea? 
2. To avert a worldwide pro-Soviet bandwagon effect.U.S. leaders feared that other states would align
with the USSR, thinking it the tide of the future, if
Soviet-allied North Korea seized South Korea. But ... absent US intervention, was a worldwide pro-Soviet bandwagon effect likely? Do states generallybandwagon or balance?
3. Domestic politics. Truman feared being pilloried forlosing another Asian country to Communism.
G. U.S. forces landed at Inchon on Sept. 15, 1950 and routedthe North Korean army from South Korea.
H. In late September 1950 Truman decided to cross 38th
parallel and conquer North Korea. Part of the U.S. 
reasoning: "We must punish the aggressors to deter themfrom other aggression elsewhere." An American mega-blunder. 
I. September/October 1950: China decided to enter the war
against the U.S. if the U.S. invaded North Korea. Why?
1. China's leaders feared that after the U.S. conqueredNorth Korea it would destabilize Communist rule in northeast China (Manchuria) or even invade Chinadirectly. Mao wrote Stalin on October 2, 1950 that 
"if we allow the United States to occupy all of Korea
... the American invaders will run more rampant, andhave negative effects for the entire Far East." On 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>October 13 he wrote that U.S. victory in North Korea
"will be most disadvantageous to Manchuria; all ofthe South Manchurian electricity will be threatened."
&gt; because U.S. power will then be adjacent to China,
and 
&gt; because the U.S. and anti-communist Chinese will be 
emboldened by U.S. victory in Korea. "The 
arrogance of reactionaries at home and abroad
[will] grow," threatening Manchuria. See telegrams
attached to lecture notes. 
The U.S. was unaware of these Chinese fears. 
Is the U.S. approach to the Yalu is a "natural
experiment" that tests (and corroborates) offense-
defense theory? The U.S. applied a large, rapid
insecurity "treatment" to China. China responds withgreat violence despite long odds and high risks.
2. Chinese leaders hoped for total victory over U.S.forces. Mao suggested that "our forces can destroy
the American forces in Korea," and that "the scope of
this war will not be great, and the duration will notbe long." "If the American forces are defeated, theKorean problem is, in fact, finished."
J. Oct. 3, 1950: China warned the U.S.: "Don't cross 38th 
parallel or it's war with us!" Truman and Acheson didn't 
listen. UN troops crossed the 38th parallel on Oct. 7.Why?1. The warning came via an Indian diplomat not trustedby Dean Acheson (so said Acheson later).
2. China didn't explain the reasoning behind its warningor convey the warning directly to CongressionalRepublicans.
3. The Administration had already decided to cross theparallel in late September; backtracking is painful.
4. Truman feared attacks from Republican hawks if hestayed south.
5. U.S. contempt for Chinese military capability. One U.S. commander told his troops they faced "a bunch ofChinese laundrymen" before China's attack.
6. Some U.S. officials argued that (paraphrasing) "Chinawould have entered the war in July, when it had achance to win, if it meant to enter at all. It makes no sense for China to enter now when its prospectsare far worse." U.S. leaders dismissed the 
possibility that security fears would drive China to 
enter. 
K. Chinese baiting of the US: 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>the Cold War's cause!" (Adam Ulam.)
D. Capitalist expansionism? "The capitalist U.S. was the
aggressor, the socialist Soviet Union was the defender.
The U.S. feared a new depression. It hoped to avoid such
a depression by finding market outlets for surplus goods.It sought to control Eastern Europe to compel it to besuch a market. U.S. imperialism in Eastern Europecollided with a defensive Soviet desire to maintain a 
neutral buffer to its west." This is the now-largely-
discredited left-revisionist view. See e.g., writings byGabriel Kolko and Lloyd Gardner.
E. Revolutionary vs. oligarchic states? "Both sides were aggressors, for reasons Stephen Walt describes.
Revolutionary states are messianic and frightened; their
neighbors are defensively aggressive, and polluted byemigres." But if true why didn't the Cold War blossomfully in 1919?
F. The unshaped postwar European order/collapse of German
empire? "The lack of a clear Soviet-American wartime 
agreement on the postwar partition of the German empirecaused a collision of the two major allied powers in azone of uncertainty. Had each side's sphere of influencebeen more clearly delineated earlier the Cold War might
have been milder." Shades of the 7 Years' War. 
G. The international system: Bipolarity and the security
dilemma? "The world's two strongest states rarely getalong well because each is the main threat to the other.They will always compete for security. The Cold War was 
an inevitable result of the rise of the U.S. and USSR to 
the pinnacle of world power."
Variant #1: The two superpowers were in fact
insecure and contended for resources of real value--especially the industry and buffer room of Eastern
Europe.
Variant #2: The superpowers were secure due to the
nuclear revolution, their vast size, and their distance
from each other. But didn't know it; and they contendedfor assets (Eastern Europe) of no real value. Soviet 
control of Eastern Europe made the USSR less, not more,
secure by provoking the rest of the world into a hostilestance against the USSR.
Variant #3 (spiral model variant): The two 
superpowers felt insecure and contended for security but
both thought the other pursued unprovoked aggression for
non-security reasons and overreacted accordingly.
What does this systemic explanation portend for the 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.42 / Causes and Prevention of War
Stephen Van Evera 
THE COLD WAR (1947-1989) AND KOREA (1950-1953) 
I. THE COLD WAR IN A NUTSHELL 
A. Duration: ~1947-1989. Ended by the Soviet withdrawal
from Eastern Europe, 1989.
B. Wars of the Cold War: Korea 1950-53, Vietnam 1950-75,
Afghanistan 1979-89, Cambodia 1979-89, Nicaragua 1983-90,Angola 1975-1990s, El Salvador 1979-90, Sovietintervention in Ethiopia 1970s; massacres in Indonesia
1965, East Timor 1975. Millions were killed. 
C. US-sponsored coups in Iran 1953, Guatemala 1954, Chile
1973, Congo 1960, Brazil 1964, Greece 1967, maybeIndonesia 1965, East Timor 1975.
D. Crises: Berlin 1948; Berlin 1958-62; Cuban Missile Crisis 
1962; War Scare of 1983; China offshore islands, 1950s. 
II. HOW THE COLD WAR ERUPTED: EVENTS 
A. Poland and Eastern Europe:
1. Warsaw uprising, 1944. Stalin drew the Polish non-
communists into a futile rebellion against Hitler,
then watched passively while Hitler slaughtered them.Americans wondered what else Stalin intended. 
2. Stalin made a vague promise at Yalta (Feb. 1945) toallow democracy in Poland. Then he imposed communist
dictatorship instead.
B. Iran 1946: Stalin wouldn't leave northern Iran until 
pressured.
C. Turkey 1946: Stalin said "I want some Turkish territory!"Instead Truman sent the Missouri to the Mediterranean as 
a show of force. 
D. Greece 1947: the West thought Stalin was instigating the
Communist revolution in Greece. (He wasn't.Yugoslavia's communist Tito government was aiding theGreek communists, but not Stalin.)
E. The Berlin Crisis of 1948-1949. This grew from a Soviet-American struggle to control Germany.
F. Military aspects:1. The U.S. had false fears of Soviet militarysuperiority. U.S. intelligence and the Western press
depicted a vast Soviet conventional superiority in
Europe and downplayed the implications of the U.S.atomic monopoly. Hence a Soviet threat that was 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>largely political--the Soviets had some capacity to
disrupt or subvert Western Europe--was also perceivedas military.
2. The Soviets explode an atomic bomb, August 1949. Now the West is really scared. What if Stalin isn't deterrable? 
Western responses: the Marshall Plan (1947); the Berlinairlift (1948-49); the formation of NATO (1949); and a vast
American military buildup (1950-54), following a plan defined
in NSC 68 (1950). This triggered a large Soviet counter-buildup.
The Soviet threat, US response, 1944-50: a natural
experiment testing offense-defense theory, balance-of-threat
theory? 
III. WHAT CAUSED THE COLD WAR? WHO CAUSED THE COLD WAR? SEVEN 
EXPLANATIONS 
A. Communist totalitarian expansionism? "The totalitarian Soviets were the aggressor, the democratic West the
defender. Soviet aggression sprang from theaggressiveness of Communist political systems. Communist governments are aggressive because they are (a)inherently messianic--Communist ideology preaches global
communist rule; and/or because they are (b) frail, hence
aggressive for Orwellian reasons--they needed enemies tolegitimate their totalitarian rule."
Variant #1: Soviet expansion into Eastern Europe
threatened U.S. security, causing the Cold War. 
&gt; The US prime interest: to maintain the political
division of industrial Eurasia. Soviet expansion intoEastern Europe positioned the USSR to destroy thatinterest by achieving Eurasian hegemony.
Variant #2: The Soviets conquered the homelands of
powerful U.S. ethnic groups--especially Polish-Americans--when they seized Eastern Europe. These ethnic groupsthen pushed Washington to respond.
B. Communist totalitarian cruelty and barbarism? "The U.S. opposed the USSR less because the USSR was aggressive
than because it was tyrannical. The Cold War was a 
Western human rights crusade." But if true, why didn'tthe Cold War blossom fully in 1919?
C. U.S. softness? "U.S. softness early in the Cold War madethings worse--the U.S. led the Soviets forward by 
appeasement. Instead the U.S. should had given Stalin an
ultimatum in 1946: 'Get out of Eastern Europe or we'llthrow you out!'? The Soviets would have left, removing 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>a. "We must conquer the North to punish the
aggressor."
b. "We should hold POWs to scare future communist 
aggressors into thinking we'll do it again."
2. Chinese aims also widened in wartime. Mao inferred 
malign U.S. intent from the interposition of the U.S.fleet off Taiwan in June 1950 and the October 1950 U.S. invasion of North Korea. He responded by
expanding China's aims to include expelling the U.S.
from South Korea. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>1. U.S. forces encountered small Chinese forces in 
Korea, 26 Oct. 1950. MacArthur thought: "If this isall they can do they'll be a pushover," and ordered
an advance to the Yalu River. Another mega-blunder.
2. Chinese warnings of the U.S. all but ceased on
October 13, with only one later exception. Instead Chinese officials released US POWs with happy wavesand good wishes in October/November.
L. China launched a massive surprise attack on U.S. forcesin North Korea on Nov. 26, 1950 and routed the U.S. army,driving it from North Korea. This was the worst grounddefeat in U.S. military history!
M. A long and bloody war ensued, Dec. 1950-summer 1953,
ending in a tie. China tried and failed to drive the 
U.S. from Korea. Note: this war included a long-hiddenSoviet-American air war! 
V. KOREAN WAR, U.S.-CHINA WAR: WHAT CAUSED THEM? 
A. Background misperceptions:1. American self-sugar-coating: "We've always been niceto China--so China has nothing to fear from us!"
2. Chinese myths about U.S.: "The U.S. helped Japaneseaggressors in the 1930s! The U.S. is plotting to
rebuild and unleash Japan in Asia again!" Marxist-
Leninist dogma shaped Chinese thought.
B. Non-strategy: By the USA? No--the problem was thatAcheson did state US strategy, but misstated it. A misstated strategy is worse than none. By China? Yes. 
China told the US in late September that it wouldn't
intervene, then changed its mind too late.
C. Absence of Sino-American diplomatic relations. A mega-blunder by both sides.
D. McCarthyism in the U.S.? A powerful force. What caused 
it? Some blame the China Lobby, which fed lots of
information to McCarthy.
E. First-strike advantage. This is the likely reason whyChina never issued an ultimatum and sought to convincethe U.S. of China's weakness. 
F. U.S. window after Inchon ----&gt; too-hasty diplomacy, Sept.
15-Oct. 7. 
G. False optimism by everyone.
H. The security dilemma, and unawareness of it. Securitywas the basic goal pursued by both the U.S. and China but
neither realized this of the other. 
I. War ----&gt; War 
1. U.S. aims widened due to the war itself: 
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>World War I</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec12-14_prussian/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12&#8211;14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>After the Franco-Prussian war Bismarck deemed that German 
national aims were achieved and that Germany now needed only two things: to be at peace, and to avert the appearance of a overwhelmingly strong neighbor that could overmatch German power. Toward these goals Bismarck sought to prevent aggression among Germany's neighborhood. This would avoid Germany being sucked into wars among its neighbors, and would ensure that no neighbor won a decisive war that left it overwhelmingly powerful. To achieve these two goals Bismarck wove a web of defensive alliances with other European states. His web of defensive alliances included Russia and Austria-Hungary, which were hostile to each other. Germany assured each that it would defend them if they were attacked but warned that they would fight alone if they launched aggression. Result: Europe enjoyed 20 years of peace. 
VI. KEY CHANGES IN GERMAN POLICY AFTER 1890 
A. Germany was sated, 1871-1890; after 1890 it becomes expansionist. 
B. Germany pursues expansion by stealth and deception, 1864-71; after 1890 it pursues expansion by belligerence and intimidation. 
VII. LESSONS OF BOTH WARS AND THEIR AFTERMATH FOR U.S. FOREIGN 
POLICY 
A. These wars suggest that when offshore balancers don't balance against Europe's continental aggressors, the continental aggressors get frisky and start wars. Does this lesson still apply? 
B. The aftermath of these wars suggests that the U.S. can maintain peace elsewhere by weaving a web of defensive alliances. 
C. Other lessons re: effects of contempt v. respect? Dangers of being baited. E.g, some say al-Qaeda sought to bait the U.S. into an imperial lunge into the Mideast in 2001, and Bush 43 took the bait. Belligerence v. assurance as diplomatic strategies? 
VIII. PRELUDE TO WORLD WAR I. IMPORTANT CAUSES OF WAR 
DISAPPEARED DURING 1870-1914. SO WHY WAR IN 1914?? 
&gt; The partition of Africa was finally resolved in 1911, 
removing a major source of international conflict. 
&gt; The German question was finally resolved on terms very 
favorable to Germany, with Germany's unification in 1870-71. 
&gt; German power rose sharply relative to other European powers, 
1870-1914, and seemed likely to keep rising. Germany was on a roll! So why didn't Germany sit tight and enjoy the ride? 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>completely! And perhaps France!" Bismarck sarcastically 
responded: "Why not go all the way to Constantinople?" The army didn't get its way--fortunately for Prussia. 
B. Prussian war aims nevertheless did modestly widen. Prussia excluded Austria from Germany instead of dividing it with Austria at the Main river. 
IV. CAUSES OF THE WAR? PERHAPS AMONG THEM: 
A. Austria's false optimism. 
B. Prussia's search for security; and Prussia's offensive opportunity. 
C. Bismarck's baiting, and Austria's unwise decision to take the bait. 
V. WHAT CAUSED THE PEACE? AN EMERGING DEFENSIVE ALLIANCE 
AGAINST PRUSSIA. 
VI. WAS A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION TO THE CRISIS POSSIBLE? PROBABLY 
NO--SCARY THOUGHT. To get Austria to concede peacefully Bismarck 
would have had to scare Austria by showing muscle and a will to fight. But that would have mobilized the other powers against Prussia, tipping the overall balance of power against Prussia. So Bismarck could not use coercive diplomacy. 
THE FRANCO-PRUSSIAN WAR OF 1870 
I. BACKGROUND 
A. Bismarck's goal: to provoke France into serving as a bogey that Bismarck could use to tighten Prussia's grip on the lesser German states. Baiting! 
B. Bismarck continued/repeated his deceptions: "We're weak and we're benign!" 
C. Bismarck's provocations to France: 1. He authored a Hohenzollern candidacy for the Spanish throne, to spark French fears of Prussian encirclement of France. 
2. He edited a telegram to the French--the Ems telegram--to make it seem insulting to France. This telegram summarized an informal conversation between Prussian King William I and French ambassador Vincent Benedetti in July 13. Ir was drafted by Prussian royal secretary Abeken, then edited by Bismarck and released to the press also on July 13. Bismarck happily assured friends that the telegram, after his rewriting, "would have the effect of a red flag on the Gallic bull." It was the trigger for French mobilization on July 14, triggering war. 
D. Serendipity: the Salazar telegram of June 21 1870 was mis-translated as "Salazar will return July 9" not "June 25," hence the Spanish adjourned the Cortes to escape the summer heat, hence the election of the new king was deferred, hence the Hohenzollern candidature remained alive into July. Accidents matter. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>into false optimism. 
2. Spin regarding Prussian intentions: "We're benign!" 
Bismarck sent the Schweinitz mission to Russia to proclaim that Prussia had limited aims. &gt; Note: Prussian intentions were in fact limited. 
After defeating France in 1871 Bismarck proclaimed Germany "sated." But after Bismarck left office in 1890 Germany's appetite grew vastly. Bismarck could not speak for his successors. 
B. Britain, France, and Russia were indifferent to containing Prussia, in part due to Bismarck's deceptions. 1. Britain feared France more than Prussia, and was generally isolationist. 
2. France failed to foresee that Prussia would win a quick, decisive victory, instead expecting a long fratricidal Prussian-Austrian war. It saw advantage in such a war, thinking: "We can demand the Rhineland as our fee for breaking the stalemate for the victor." 
3. Russia felt solidarity with Prussia against the Poles, whom they both cruelly oppressed and who hated them both. Russia also was distracted from central European affairs by its focus on undoing the demilitarization of the Black Sea, imposed by Britain on Russia in the peace that ended the Crimean War in 1856. 
C. Prussia signed a 3-month offensive alliance with Italy, April 8, 1866. Terms include giving Italy parts of southern Austria. This was a provocation and threat to Austria. 
D. Austria mobilized its army against Italy and Prussia, April 21, 1866--a fateful step. Why did Austria take it? 1. Austria received false reports that Italy was mobilizing, and mobilized very quickly in response. Where did these false reports come from? Maybe the Austrian military deceived its civilians; or perhaps 
Bismarck deceived Austria. Alois Karoly, Austrian minister in Berlin, believed Bismarck was the source 
of the falsehood. 
2. Why did Austria mobilize against Prussia as well as Italy? a. Austrian leaders assumed Prussia had already decided for war. They didn't realize that Prussia couldn't start a war if Austria didn't move first. 
b. Austria had only one mobilization plan. It posited a 2-front mobilization. 
3. Results: Prussia's king was outraged, opted for war against Austria; and Britain, France and Russia stood aside indifferently. The table is set for Prussian victory. 
III. WARTIME EVENTS: 
A. In Prussia there was bitter civil-military conflict over war aims. The Prussian army said: "Let's smash Austria 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>E. Due mainly to Bismarck's deceptions and France's idiotic 
belligerence, Russia, Britain, and Austria all decided to be unconcerned about the possibility of German victory, and so stayed out of the war. 
F. First-move advantage? Michael Howard offers hints that France perceived such an advantage and mobilized to gain it. 
G. France launched military mobilization first on July 14, 1870, then Prussia on July 15. France declared war on Prussia on July 16. Fighting began July 19. 
II. THE WAR: EVENTS 
A. France thought Prussia would take 6 weeks to mobilize its army. In fact it took Prussia 3 weeks to mobilize; and Prussia's mobilized army was twice the size of France's mobilized army. 
B. The Prussians crushed the French army in 6 weeks, largely by inducing the French to unwisely take the offensive. 
C. The French then mounted a long war of guerilla resistance against Prussian occupying forces. Subduing France proved very difficult. 
D. During the war German aims widened to include keeping Alsace-Lorraine. In 1867 Prussia's chief of staff, Helmut von Moltke the Elder, declared: "We desire nothing from France." But Prussia then demanded Alsace-Lorraine. Why? Pressure from the Prussian military; and Bismarck saw advantage in keeping France hostile to Prussia! 
E. There was bitter civil-military conflict in Prussia over war aims and military operations. Moltke sought to smash France utterly, and (wrongly) dismissed Bismarck's fears of British or other intervention. Moltke also resisted civilian control over his military operations by keeping civilians in the dark. Bismarck complained that he learned about events on the battlefield only "five days later in the newspaper." 
III. MORE CAUSES OF THE WAR 
A. The Prussian and French militaries both (!) saw windows of opportunity. 
B. Prussia's search for security; and Prussia's offensive opportunity. Prussia saw an offensive opportunity arising from Britain, Russia and Austria's unusual failure to counterbalance Prussia. And Prussia, as always, feared for its safety if it failed to achieve German national union. 
C. France was falsely optimistic about the military outcome of the war. 
IV. THE FALSE LESSONS GERMANS LEARNED FROM THE WAR OF 1870: "BISMARCK USED BLOOD AND IRON TO MAKE FRIENDS AND INFLUENCE PEOPLE. YOU CAN TOO!" QUESTION: WHY WAS THIS FALSE LESSON LEARNED? 
V. BISMARCK PURSUES PEACE, 1871-1890. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Causes and Prevention of War // 17.42 // MIT 
Stephen Van Evera 
THE AUSTRO-PRUSSIAN WAR OF 1866 
I. BISMARCK'S PLAN TO UNIFY GERMANY: "LET'S BAIT AUSTRIA INTO 
STARTING A WAR!"
 In 1866 Germany was divided into several dozen mini-states, 
of which Prussia was the largest. Prussia's Chancellor Otto von Bismarck (1862-1890) sought to unify Germany under Prussian leadership. Main reasons: Prussia was geographically not contiguous, had long borders, and had a smaller total population than other European powers. This left Prussia insecure, and left Germany ripe for a rerun of the epic ruin it suffered at the hands of other powers during the Thirty Years' War (1618-1648). A united Germany would have better borders and more resources, and so be more secure.
 Toward the goal of dominating Germany Bismarck sought to 
remove Austrian influence in southern Germany by war. He saw three prerequisites for this campaign. (1) France, Britain and Russia had to be induced to stay neutral while Prussia beat Austria. A very tall order! Major states almost never allow other major states to increase their power by war. (2) The Prussian king had to be induced, against his sentiments, to declare war on his brother-German Austrians. (3) Prussian war aims had to remain limited. If Prussia pursued large aims it would likely provoke other powers to intervene to reverse its gains. It could reduce this risk by pursuing strictly limited aims. This required tight civilian control of Prussia's expansion-minded military.
 Bismarck's three solutions: (1) Prussia would sweet-talk 
the other European powers into not fearing Prussia, by talking 
down Prussian power and persuading others that Prussian aims 
were limited, even benign. He thought: "If other powers don't fear Prussia they will more readily allow it to grow, expanding its power." (2) Bismarck would bait Austria into 
starting the war. He thought: "If Austria acts aggressively it will alienate the other powers and thus be without allies; 
and the Prussian king will be outraged at Austria and declare war on it." (3) Bismarck would persuade the Prussian king to 
tightly control Prussia's tactically brilliant but expansion-
minded Chief of Staff Helmut von Moltke the Elder. Bismarck 
then could keep Prussian war aims tightly limited, and could promptly end the war when these aims were achieved. This would avert intervention against Prussia by Russia, France and 
Britain. 
II. BACKGROUND TO WAR: EVENTS AND CONDITIONS 
A. Bismarck's deceptions. 1. Deceptions regarding Prussian capability: "We're weak!" These deceptions were aimed chiefly at Britain, France, and Russia, but also fooled Austria 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Seven Years War</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec10_7yearswar/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Dinwiddie &amp; Friends! 
E. Chronology: 
1. During 1752-53 France destroyed a British trading post 
in the Ohio Valley and built two forts of its own there, at Presque Isle and Fort Le Boeuf. 
2. During 1753-54 Britain sent three expeditions to the Ohio Valley to eject the French. All three failed. &gt; Fall 1753: A Virginian expedition to Fort Le Boeuf, 
sent to warn the French to leave the Ohio Valley (and led by George Washington), was ignored and came home. 
&gt; February 1754: Virginians established a fort at the 
confluence of the Allegheny, Monongahela and Ohio rivers (now Pittsburgh). The French conquered it, renamed it Fort Duquesne, and expelled the British. 
&gt; May-July 1754: Virginians commanded by George 
Washington entered the Ohio Valley on a fort-building mission. They learned of the nearby presence of a force of 36 French troops sent into the Valley with a summons to warn any British troops or traders to leave the Valley (same as Washington did at Fort Le Boeuf). Washington's troops ambushed this French force at Jumonville Glen (the first fighting in the war), killing 10 including the French commander, May 28. Washington's force then pulled back and erect Fort Necessity in an effort to establish a defensible position. A larger French and Indian force then arrived and defeated this British force at Fort Necessity. The British surrendered and came home. 
3. In early 1755 Britain sent two army battalions under General Braddock from Britain to America to eject the French from the Ohio Valley. The British claimed Braddock's instructions were purely defensive. The French, who knew Braddock's instructions, thought the Ohio Valley was theirs, hence they saw his expedition as aggressive. 
4. Braddock led his two battalions into the Ohio Valley toward Fort Duquesne, aiming to eject the French. Braddock's force was annihilated and Braddock was killed by the French and Indians at the Battle of the Monongahela, July 9, 1755. A fiasco. 
5. Meanwhile ... In May 1755 France countered by sending six army battalions to America aboard 1/3 of the French battle fleet, stripped of its guns. 
6. In June 1755 Britain's Admiral Boscawen tried to intercept these six French battalions off Newfoundland. It captures only 2 of 18 French ships. 
7. Britain and France halted negotiations and war erupted, May 18, 1756. 
F. This was a war of illusions. Four types of misperceptions 
to look for: 1. Of one's own conduct. "We are being benign!" 
2. Of the other's conduct and intentions. "They are being 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>British leaders tried to limit the war to North America but 
failed. 
VI. AN INADVERTENT WAR? Historians once explained this war as 
the product of calculated aggression by great empires. Now many believe it was an inadvertent war. Who is right? 
VII. CURRENT PARALLELS: The Russia-NATO conflict over Ukraine, 
the China vs neighbors conflict over South China Sea, a possible 
US vs. Clina clash over spheres of influence in North Korea should the North Korean government collapse, ongoing conflict between the Turks, Kurds, Iranians, Russians, Syrian government and US over the carcass of the ISIS state, and the looming Arctic conflict are conflicts over domains where rights are unsettled. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>What changes would have prevented war? How about 
using Track II diplomacy--having private citizens who 
are close to the government unofficially exchange views on solutions? 
d. Britain exaggerated the value of the stakes at issue. Britain thought that by beating France it could consolidate control over North America. In fact Britain's victory cost it North America. British victory removed the French threat to Britain's North American colonies. The British colonists felt less reliant on London's protection, hence less willing to tolerate rule from London. Hence they rebelled in 1775-1776. Washington &amp; Co. stuck it to the Redcoats. 
B. Non-settlement of disputes: the 1748 Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle had gaps. 
C. Four windows of opportunity or vulnerability: a. Britain saw a waning British worldwide military advantage over France. British leaders thought Britain was better prepared for war than France but also saw France building up its fleet. 
b. France saw British power growing. The French saw Britain making alliances on the European continent (e.g., with Spain) and expanding into the Ohio Valley. 
c. The British deployment of Braddock's 2 battalions to North America in winter 1755 caused France to perceive a tactical window: "We must deploy offsetting forces to North America before a war starts and Britain closes the seas; we can't do it later." 
d. The subsequent French 6-battalion deployment to North America on disarmed French warships created dual British windows of opportunity and vulnerability: "We have a fleeting opportunity to destroy a third of the French fleet," and "If we don't strike the French will gain military superiority in North America!" 
Note: windows 'c' and 'd' were unwitting results of government decisions. What changes would have prevented war?  Better national 
security analysis in London and Paris? One of these capitols had to be wrong in seeing a window, as two opposing windows cannot co-exist at the same time. Also, preventive wars rarely look wise in retrospect. Good scholarship might have illuminated these realities, discouraging decisions for war. 
E. Competition for control of cumulative resources; also, competition for security. 
F. Expectation of a cheap, limited war. 
IV. OUTCOME: BRITAIN WINS WAR --&gt; BRITAIN LOSES ITS AMERICAN 
COLONIES (!) 
V. ESCALATION OF THE SEVEN YEARS WAR 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>French have invaded Massachusetts!" (but they hadn't). 
&gt; Dinwiddie wrote London that the French were attacking 
"the forces of this Dominion" in the Ohio Valley (but 
these forces were Ohio Company mercenaries, not British government troops). In his dispatches the Ohio Company fort-builders became "our people" and the fort was "our fort," wrongly implying that they were British government personnel and property. 
c. French intentions--Britain exaggerated French 
expansionism. &gt; Dinwiddie told London "the French are planning a 
general invasion of British North America!" (but they weren't). 
d. British conduct--Britain underestimated the 
aggressiveness of its own behavior. &gt; Dinwiddie failed to report his own fort-building in 
the Ohio Valley. 
&gt; Dinwiddie failed to report his collaboration with 
Indians fighting against the French in the Ohio Valley. 
Consider that misperceptions like these can feed each other, as follows: misperceptions of the status quo --&gt; false belief that another's defensive actions are aggressive --&gt; exaggeration of the other's aggressiveness --&gt; misperception of how the other will react to punishment. Some of this probably happened here. 
2. France suffered similar misperceptions, though we know fewer details. 
3. Additional beliefs and misperceptions (did some grow from those above?): 
a. Both sides saw the other as very expansionist. 
b. Both sides thought a tough policy would persuade the other side to back down. In fact the other counter-escalated in response. i. Britain thought France would not counter Braddock's 2-battalion deployment. But France did counter with 6 battalions. 
ii. France thought Britain would not counter its 6-battalion deployment. But Britain did with Boscawen's naval attack on that deployment. 
c. Both sides were reluctant to negotiate, because: i. They thought the other would take their willingness to talk as a sign of weakness. 
ii. They thought concessions would injure their credibility. 
iii. They thought negotiations were pointless, wouldn't 
succeed.
 However, without talks misperceptions on both sides 
went undiscovered.
 Were both sides applying the deterrence model to a 
spiral situation? 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Causes and Prevention of War // MIT 
Stephen Van Evera 
THE ANGLO-FRENCH SEVEN YEARS' WAR, 1756-1763: AN INADVERTENT WAR? 
AN AVOIDABLE WAR? 
I. INADVERTENT WAR: war caused by actions that actors did not 
expect or desire would cause war. Some believe inadvertent wars 
never happen, other think they are common. Was the Seven Years' War an inadvertent war? Was it avoidable? 
II. BACKGROUND TO WAR 
The Seven Years' War was a worldwide Anglo-French battle for 
empire. Americans call it the French and Indian War but it could be called the first world war. It saw fierce Anglo-French fighting in the Caribbean, South Asia, West Africa, and North America. Britain won but with little enduring gain. Background factors: A. Mercantilism. Before 1756 the European powers scrambled for 
gold to pay mercenaries, hence for trade surpluses, hence for empire. 
What changes would have prevented war? 
&gt; New ways to tax, to increase the state's tax base? &gt; Better scholarship explaining the economic 
efficiencies of free trade and the costs of mercantilism (e.g., David Ricardo's 1816 writing outlining the Theory of Comparative Advantage--it arrived too late!) 
&gt; Cheaper strategies for national defense (e.g., 
guerilla war) to replace expensive cash-dependent mercenary war &amp; naval war? 
B. The incomplete partition of North America. France had 
Quebec. Britain had what became the U.S. eastern seaboard. But who owned the Ohio Valley wilderness? This was left undecided by the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle (1748), which ended the last big war (the War of Austrian Succession, 1739-48). 
C. Military facts: 
1. Britain and France were the only powers with global military reach. 
2. The British navy was twice the strength of the French navy but France had far the stronger army. 
D. Economic facts: in 1748 a group of Virginians including 
Virginia Gov. Robert Dinwiddie form the Ohio Company to colonize and develop the Ohio Valley and to enrich themselves. They obtain a vast land grant of initially 200,000 acres (312.5 square miles, an area 20x16 miles) in the Ohio Valley from the British Crown, with 300,000 more acres to come if they achieve settle 100 families in the territory in 7 years. Total: 500,000 acres, or 781 square miles, an area 20x38 miles. Lots of $$$ on the table for 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>aggressive!" 
3. Of the other's likely response to one's own acts. 
Governments expected their threats to elicit compliance but they evoked defiance. Britain's deployment of Braddock evoked unexpected French counter-escalation (its six-battalion deployment); and this French counter-escalation evoked further British counter-counter-escalation unexpected by France. 
4. Of the value of the stakes in dispute. This value was greatly exaggerated by British and French leaders. 
What changes would have prevented war?? 
&gt; Enact British business regulations that forbid conflicts 
of interest by government officials, including the giving of royal land grants to government officials (Dinwiddie) and/or the acceptance of royal land grants by these officials; and forbidding the giving of land grants in territory disputed with another power? 
&gt; Develop a professional British intelligence agency (like 
today's MI6), to preclude the role of local business people with conflicts of interest (like Dinwiddie and Shirley) in British intelligence-collection? 
&gt; Develop of an independent British press with a culture 
of integrity, to provide transparency into situations like the Ohio Valley conflict of 1753-56, to dampen misperceptions about it? 
&gt; Somehow make British officials in London aware of the 
attitudes of the English colonists: "We will only stick with British rule as long as we face a threat from the French and the Indians!" 
&gt; Teach about the spiral model in British and French 
schools, as a self-denying prophecy. 
&gt; Assassinate Dinwiddie? &gt; Would war have occurred if Britain and France had 
possessed secure nuclear arsenals? 
III. CAUSES OF THE SEVEN YEARS' WAR 
A. Misperceptions. Do these constitute a Jervis spiral? 
1. Britain misperceived: 
a. The nature of the status quo -- "Ohio belongs to us!" 
&gt; Virginia Governor Dinwiddie described the Ohio Valley 
as "British property" in communiques to London (making the French "invaders of British property" in one of his communiques). But Ohio wasn't British--its ownership was undecided. 
b. French conduct--Britain exaggerated the aggressiveness 
of French behavior. &gt; Dinwiddie told London that "the French have invaded 
East of the Alleghanies!" (but they hadn't), and were preparing a general invasion of North America (but they weren't). 
&gt; Massachusetts' Governor Shirley told London "the 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Peloponnesian War</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec24_peloponnesian/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Korea 1950, Sebastopol 1855]. Was war causing war?
Athens was then sobered up by ...
2. Athenian defeats at Delium and Amphipolis. These 
defeats finally convinced Athens to make a truce--thePeace of Nicias, 421-415 BCE.
G. Mytilene, an Athenian colony, saw Athens' harsh treatmentof other colonies and decided to revolt before the same fate befell it. But Athens believed the revolt had "no 
reason" and was unprovoked. Hence Athens saw need to 
further scare its colonies with even harsher treatment. Athens considered killing all Mytilenians (Cleon pushedfor this) but relented.
H. Round #3 beginnings: the truce broke down.
I. Athens destroyed Melos, a rebellious Athenian colony.
Athens killed all military-age Melian men and sent theMelian women and children into slavery.
Compare the Mytilene Debate and the Melian Dialogue:
the latter was nastier. Ethical concerns disappeared
from the discussion. Regarding justice, the Athenians
simply declared that "the strong do what they have thepower to do and the weak accept what they have toaccept." (Thucydides, p. 402)
Did Thucydides' think ethics mattered? Yes. "Those 
who really deserve praise are the people who, while humanenough to enjoy power, nevertheless pay more attention tojustice than they are compelled to do by theirsituation." (Thucydides, p. 80.)
J. The Athenian expedition to Syracuse [Germany's
unrestricted submarine warfare campaign, 1917]
1. Athenians did little research before launching the
expedition. They were ignorant of basic facts such asSicily's size and population.
2. Athens' aims were vast; Syracuse's aims soon became
vast [Britain and France in 1755, US in 1941, US andChina in 1950.]
3. Athens expected easy victory, believing the expedition
was "an absolutely safe thing." This grew from: a. Athenian ignorance of Syracuse's power.
b. False expectation that others--Sparta and theSicilian states--would bandwagon with Athens,wouldn't balance against it. [Hitler and the AxisAlliance.] 
c. False expectations of help from Egesta (see
below).
4. Athens expected a fun, cheap war. Alcibiades told 
Athenians that the Syracusan Expedition was an
opportunity for "gaining new experience" and to avertthe "ruin" that comes with being "idle." [1914.] 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.42 // Causes and Prevention of War 
Stephen Van Evera 
THE PELOPONNESIAN WAR, 460-404 BCE 
Contents of brackets [] suggest analogies to later events. 
I. THUCYDIDES: WHAT A GUY!
 Many readers across many centuries felt that Thucydides'
Peloponnesian War evoked their own times and tragedies.
Yet readers often see different central arguments in this
book. Some see an anti-democratic Thucydides warning that
publics are folly-prone and popular rule is misrule. Some see a ruthless celebration of the inexorable cruelties of international politics and the use of force. Some see an anti-war book, warning that force often produces unforeseen or
unwanted results, and should only be used as a last resort.
Who is right?
Does this book identify general laws of motion that govern
events across time and circumstance? 
II. PHASES OF THE CONFLICT 
A. 480 BCE: Greece vs. Persia War 
B. 460-445 BCE: Athens vs. Sparta War Round #1
C. 431-421 BCE: Athens vs. Sparta War Round #2--the"Archidamean War" 
D. 421-415 BCE: Truce--the Peace of Nicias 
E. 415-404 BCE: Athens vs. Sparta War Round #3--theExpedition to Syracuse
Rounds #2 and #3 are the focus of Thucydides' book. 
III. MILITARY POWER: CHARACTER AND DISTRIBUTION 
A. Athens and Sparta were the two strongest powers inGreece. Each led a large alliance/empire.
B. Athenian power was growing relative to Spartan power.
C. Athens had a MAD-like military strategy. If Sparta
attacked it by land Athens would leave its farmland
undefended, instead withdrawing its population withinAthens' strong walls while sending its navy to torchSpartan coastal cities. 
IV. SPARTAN AND ATHENIAN SOCIETY 
A. Sparta: an oligarchic slave state--an oppressive "humanvolcano." A small Spartan population ruled a large slavepopulation. The Spartans themselves were ruled by aSpartan oligarchy. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5. Athenians wrongly thought their decision for war was
reversible. Alcibiades told Athenians that if things
went poorly the Athenian forces could simply "come
back again."
6. Athenian strategy was disintegrated. Athenians said 
Syracuse was so strong it was a serious threat, and so
weak it could be easily conquered.
7. Egestaean blue smoke and mirrors--Egesta manipulated
Athenian perceptions. Egesta told Athens: a. "Beware the transnational Dorian conspiracyagainst Athens! Syracuse, being Dorian, is partof it!" 
b. "If you fight Syracuse others in Sicily will join
your side!" 
c. "We Egesteans have huge financial resources and
can help a lot!"
8. When the Expedition later faced disaster Nicias (the
commander) feared making a necessary and prudent peace
because he feared being pilloried for it by Athens'
hawkish public. So he fought on to ruin.
K. Catastrophe for Athens. The Syracusan expedition wasdestroyed in 413 BCE. But Athens survived anyway fornine more years (413-404 BCE)! [Germany 1914-1918.] 
VII. WHAT CAUSED THE PELOPONNESIAN WAR? WHY DID IT ESCALATE AND 
CONTINUE? POSSIBLE CAUSES 
A. Windows: 1. Preventive war by Sparta, 431 BCE: a window of
vulnerability.
2. Preventive escalation by Sparta, 414 BCE: a window of
opportunity.
B. Offense and Defense: 1. Security was a major goal on all sides: 
a. Athens' goal: to maintain the political divisionof maritime Greece, since a unity of non-Athenianmaritime Greece could threaten Athens. 
b. Sparta's goal: to ease its vulnerability toinvaders that arose from its oppressive social 
structure. 
c. Sparta's and Corinth's goal: to avert the threat
posed by rising Athenian power.
2. "Chain gang" dynamics in the Spartan and Athenian
alliances: 
a. Corinth could drag Sparta to war because Sparta
feared that otherwise Corinth might defect;causing Megara to defect; causing Sparta'sdownfall. 
b. Athens was dragged into war by Corcyra for similar 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>with being "idle.")
3. Chauvinist mythmaking. Athenians indulged in this.
4. Both sides fought to control resources believed
cumulative, and to maintain credibility.
5. Manipulation by Allies: Corinth manipulated Sparta;
Egesta manipulated Athens.
H. War ----&gt; War 1. Reciprocal growth of war aims.
2. Rise of superhawks in wartime.
3. The tyranny of sunk costs. Alcibiades: "After having
sailed out in such forces [the Athenians] ought not todisgrace themselves by going home with nothing to showfor it." (Thuc. p. 440.)
4. Fear that negotiation will be taken as a sign of
weakness. Pericles warned: "Do not send embassies to Sparta: do not give the impression that you are boweddown under your present sufferings!" (Thuc. pp. 162-163.)
5. McCarthyism: evaluators were shouted down or worse.
See Thucydides, pp. 242-243. During the war Greekscame to believe that "anyone who held violent opinionscould always be trusted, and anyone who objected tothem became suspect." And "fanatical enthusiasm was 
the mark of a real man." And "to think of the future 
and wait was merely another way of saying one was acoward; any idea of moderation was just an attempt todisguise one's unmanly character; ability tounderstand a question from all sides meant that one
was totally unfitted for action." Not a climate 
conducive to calm evaluation of options.
6. Growing barbarism on both sides as the war proceeds. 
VIII. MORAL OF THE STORY: NEVER USE FORCE? 
Thucydides warns of the over-use of force. Does this 
warning apply universally? Does history also offer instanceswhen force brought good results? Does it offer instances of the under-uses of force? 
Consider history's many successful uses of force: the
Spanish/French/British/U.S. "Indian Wars" against nativeAmericans--a cruel but successful land grab; the U.S. waragainst Mexico, 1846-1848--a profitable escapade; the U.S.wars on Germany and Japan in World War II; Bismarck's wars ofGerman unification; the 1989 U.S. invasion of Panama; and the 
British war to recover the Falklands from Argentina, 1982.
Some might also list the U.S. Persian Gulf war, 1991;Israel's 1948 and 1967 wars against the Arabs; the Arabs'1973 war against Israel; and the Greeks' defensive waragainst Persia before 480 BCE. In these cases war aims were 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>B. Athens: a quasi-democracy. All male Athenian citizens 
could vote. But half of Athens' subjects weredisenfranchised slaves, and women could not vote. Public 
questions were decided by direct democracy at popular
assemblies of male voters. 
V. THE SECURITY DILEMMA IN ANCIENT GREECE 
A. The Spartan empire feared that its large slave population
would help an invader, hence it feared it could easily be
conquered if an enemy force penetrated its territory.[Like Austria 1914 and like Hitler's 1941 view of theUSSR.]
B. The Athenian empire depended on its fleet, which required
tribute from "allies" (really imperial vassals). So it 
had to keep its vassals in line and it did so by harsh measures. [Like the world imagined by mercantilists in1755--empire was a highly cumulative resource.]
Hence both states believed they were vulnerable to conquest
and had to maintain empires for their own safety. 
VI. CHRONOLOGY 
A. The Greco-Persian War: Athens acquired an empire as a
side-effect of war. [Like the USSR's conquest of Eastern
Europe, 1944-45.]
B. Round #1: the Sparta-Athens war of 460-445--of which we
know little. Thucydides has a sketchy account on pp. 87-103. 
C. Round #2 beginnings:
1. The dispute at Epidamnus, 433 BCE. Epidamnus was a
tiny colony of Corcyra, which in turn was a colony of
Corinth. Corcyra was now hostile to its progenitorCorinth, and was neutral in the Athens-Spartaconflict. Corinth was a major Spartan ally.
A civil war erupted in Epidamnus. The losers 
appealed for aid to Corcyra. It refused aid. The losers then appealed to Corinth.
Corinth agreed and sent settlers to seize
Epidamnus, which Corinth saw as a lost possession.
Corcyra objected to Corinth taking a Corcyran
colony and asked Athens to help defend it againstCorinth. Athens agreed because it feared thatCorinth, a major naval power, might conquer Corcyra'ssubstantial fleet and thereby tip the naval balance of
power against Athens. Hence Athens offered Corcyra a
defensive alliance. 
However, offensive and defensive behavior proved
hard to distinguish at sea. This allowed Corinth to later claim (to Sparta) that Athens had broken the 30-
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>reasons. [Serbia and Austria dragged Europe to
war in 1914]
3. Offensive and defensive conduct proved to be
indistinguishable. [1914]
4. Offense was believed easy militarily. Campaign after
campaign--by Thebes, Corinth, Sparta, and Athens--waslaunched amid assurances that "it's a sure thing."
5. Bandwagon beliefs prevailed on both sides.
C. Conflict spirals:1. Athens vs. Potidaea: Potidaea revolted in response to
Athens' efforts to tighten control. These efforts triggered more rebellion, not less.
2. Athens vs. Mytilene: Athens provoked the Mytilene
revolt but failed to see this, instead thinking therevolt was unprovoked. Hence it inferred that even harsher policies toward its colonies were called for.
3. Athens vs. Syracuse: Athens exaggerated Syracusan
hostility by imagining that Syracuse was part of a
false Dorian hostile conspiracy; then it made Syracuse
hostile by attacking it. Athens also expected thatSparta and the Sicilian states would bandwagon withAthens if Athens sent an imposing expedition withSyracuse; in fact they balanced against it. (Thuc VI J
3b.)
4. Sparta opted for war in 431 partly because (Thucydides
implies) it falsely thought Athens had broken the 30 
year truce. A case of "exaggerate the hostility ofothers' conduct." 
D. Lack of clear strategy ---&gt; Forgetting of original aimsand purposes in Athens. For example, Athens continuedthe Syracusan expedition even after the importantpremises that underlay it (e.g., that Sparta wouldn'tenter the fray on Syracuse's side) were disproven.
E. Poor evaluation of policy ideas, especially in wartime.Thucydides is dismayed by the quality of publicdiscourse. See, for example, above on Athenian mis-estimates of Syracuse's power and below on evaluatorsbeing shouted down in wartime and on the destructive
actions that Nicias took because he feared the Athenian 
mob. 
F. Pericles' hubris: "I can handle everything--I needn'ttrain successors." [Like Bismarck?]
G. Other war causes from this course found in the 
Peloponnesian war:
1. False optimism about war outcomes.
2. Cheap war, fun war expectations. (Alcibiades: theSyracusan Expedition was an opportunity for "gainingnew experience" and to avert the "ruin" that comes 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>year truce, which had ended the war of 460-445 BCE, by
acting offensively. Thus this local dispute was thefirst trigger to a vast war. [Sarajevo]
Background causes of the clash over Epidamnus: a. Security fears in Athens caused it to care who
controlled Corcyra.
b. Greeks had no agreed rules to determine
ownership of rebel colonies. Hence ownership of
rebel Epidamnus was undefined. Did it belong to
Corcyra or Corinth? The matter was unsettled. 
2. The dispute at Potidaea, 432 BCE. Athens, fearing war
with Corinth and Sparta, tightened control over itscolony Potidaea by ordering Potidaea to tear down its
city walls and hand over hostages. Potidaea rebelled 
instead. Corinth--fearing the long-term growth ofAthenian power and anxious to contain it--sent help toPotidaea. It thereby violated the 30-year truce of445. [Athens toward Potidaea = G.W. Bush to others:
"You are with us or with the terrorists."]
Background causes of the clash over Potidea: a. Security fears in Athens caused it to care who
controlled Potidea, hence to take harsh measuresto enforce Athenian control of Potidea. 
b. These harsh measures provoked Potidea to rebel,
not comply. The spiral model in action?
c. Security fears in Corinth then caused Corinth to
break the truce with Athens by supportingPotidea's rebellion. 
D. Sparta's decision for war, 431 BCE.1. Sparta saw the rise of Athenian power and feared that
a stronger Athens could destroy Sparta. [Germanyfeared rising Russia, 1914]
2. Corinth lied to Sparta--"Athens is breaking the 30
years truce! They are starting a war!"--and Athensfailed to reply to these lies. [Dinwiddie, Shirleyand Duquesne, 1754]
3. Sparta offered pretexts for war--priests, goddesses, 
curses. Every reason for war was trotted out except
the real one: Sparta's fear of Athens' rising power.
[Vietnam, Gulf of Tonkin 1964]
E. The moderate Pericles died and the violent Cleon and Alcibiades rose to power in Athens. The moderate Archidamus died and Brasidas rose to power in Sparta.
[The rise of the Ludendorff/Hindenburg ultra-hawkish
"silent dictatorship" in Germany, 1914-1918.]
F. The growth and later contraction of Athenian war aims.1. Athens won a big victory at Sphacteria. It then
refused to settle on its original peace terms. [US in 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>achieved without falling into a quagmire. How can quagmires
be distinguished from instances when force will succeed?
Consider also under-uses of force. Should the Wampanoag
and Narragansett nations have wiped out the New EnglandEnglish settlers when they could, in 1620-21? Should Britain and France have attacked Germany in 1936?
Were contemporary U.S. wars with Afghanistan (2001-) and
Iraq (2003-2011) a good or a bad use of force? 
8</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>8 Hypotheses on Military Factors as Causes of War</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec2-3_hypotheses/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2&#8211;3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Example: US policy toward Stalin, 1950-53? Recent U.S. 
policies toward North Korea and Iran? 
3. For scaring small or weak states into better behavior? 
4. For limiting one's own damage in wars, and for ending wars? 
5. For reforming otherwise-unreformable aggressor states? Examples: Nazi Germany, imperial Japan, Saddam's Iraq. 
6. When the offense already dominates? 
H. How easy is conquest in the real world? Do states exaggerate the ease of conquest? Does the nuclear revolution make conquest easier or harder? 
VII. EASY DESTRUCTION: "The more the power to destroy spreads to 
non-deterrable actors, the more war." 
A. The survival dilemma, a concept parallel to the security dilemma. "States conquer or destroy others when they fear being physically destroyed, even if they need not fear conquest." U.S. counterproliferation policy is driven not by fears that terrorists might conquer the U.S., but by fears they might destroy some of it. 
B. A hypotheses deduced from the survival dilemma: "The spread of destructive power to many hands (as forecast by Martin Rees) will magnify the survival dilemma. This will causes violence by psychopaths and terrorists, and wars by states trying to keep WMD out of the hands of terrorists and psychopaths." 
VIII. ARMS RACING AND WAR 
A. Causes of Arms Racing: 
1. Secrecy. 
2. Offense-dominance, offensive doctrines and force postures. a. Offensive forces spur more counter-building by the other side. 
b. Indirect effects: secrecy, less arms control. 
B. Does Arms Racing Cause War? Is it more a cause or a symptom of 
international conflict? 1. States infer malign intentions from other states' military buildups. "If they are buying arms they must intend to use them--on us! (Hence we might be wise to launch preemptive or preventive war!") 
2. Arms racing causes windows. 
3. Arms racing causes false optimism. 
4. Why the importance of arms racing is exaggerated: war and arms racing are correlated, but is the correlation spurious? (Does mutual hostility cause them both, creating an illusion of causation?) 
IX. WHAT ABOUT DISARMAMENT? IS IT POSSIBLE? WOULD IT CAUSE OR PREVENT WAR? 
A. Is total disarmament possible/desirable? 1. Is total disarmament possible? 
&gt; Could the human race ever really be disarmed?  Consider 
the slaughter of ancient wars waged with swords and 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>attacker's favor. 
3. The offense is strong relative to the defensive in warfare. 
If so, gains from moving first can be parlayed into further gains. If not, states gain little by moving first even if they can change force ratios in their favor by stealthy first moves. 
E. How can a first move advantage be prevented? Antidotes to a 
first-move advantage include the following: 
&gt; Transparency measures that make sneak attacks difficult. &gt; Limits on fast-to-target weapons. &gt; Strong defenses to protect forces that would be targeted by 
the first strike. 
&gt; Arrange a defense-dominant world where conquest is hard. 
F. How common are first-move advantages? Answer: very rare. Yet states often perceive large first-move advantages! FMAs are scarce but the illusion of first-move advantage is common and causes lots of trouble. 
G. A current example to worry about: North Korea's elite may believe that the first mover will have the advantage in a U.S.-North Korean war. See assigned reading by Vipin Narang. 
H. How could the first-move advantage hypothesis be tested? 
II. "WINDOWS" OF OPPORTUNITY AND VULNERABILITY (causing "preventive 
war"): "The greater the fluctuations in the relative power of states, the greater the risk of war." 
A. Varieties of preventive war: 
1. Domestic events within states can shift their relative power. Windows are opened if one state grows its military forces, or its economy, faster than its adversary. Examples: Germany vs. Russia 1914, Germany vs. Britain and France 1940, Germany and Japan vs. USA 1941, Israel vs. Egypt 1956, USA vs. Iraq 2003 CE, Sparta vs. Athens 440 BCE. "What caused the war was the rising power of Athens and the fear this caused in Sparta"--Thucydides. 
2. Shifts in alignments among states can cause shifts in their relative power: Japan vs. USA 1941, USA vs. Britain 1812; indeed all wide wars... 
3. Tactical vs. Strategic windows. 
B. Windows make declining states more aggressive: 
1. Attack pays for the declining state (it thinks "war is better now than later, and since war later is likely let's start a war now!"); and belligerent diplomacy makes more sense for the decliner (it thinks "a war now would not be such a bad thing, let's risk it!") (USA 1950s.) 
2. Promises by the rising state have less credibility; hence others won't settle disputes with it. (Others think: "After they gain strength they will break any promises they make now so agreements with them are worthless!") Arabs and Israelis 1930s. 
3. Haste, truncated diplomacy ("We must resolve any disputes before our power wanes"): 
a. Shortened negotiation ---&gt; No agreement. Examples: 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>USSR vs. Finland 1939, Britain vs. France 1755 (7 
Years War), Europe 1914. 
b. No time to warn ---&gt; one side underestimates another's will. Examples: Germany misread Britain, 1914; Finland misread the USSR, 1939. 
C. Windows may also make rising states more aggressive. Risers (says Bob Gilpin) believe their greater power entitles them to higher status, and to more trappings of status, e.g., a wider sphere of influence. Their demand for these trappings leads to conflict with other states. 
D. How common are windows? Answer: they are common in perception, rare in reality. As German Chancellor Otto von Bismarck (1862-1890) said, preventive war is usually to "commit suicide from fear of death." Why are nonexistent windows often imagined? 
E. Applications to today. 
&gt; Would nuclear proliferation open dangerous windows?  In 2002 
the Bush 43 Administration embraced a doctrine of preventive war against rogue states that reach for nuclear weapons and attacked Iraq for this reason. The Trump administration has voiced similar thoughts. Is this good policy or "suicide from fear of death"? 
&gt; Some U.S. policymakers now advocate attacking North Korea or 
Iran to forestall them from developing intercontinental nuclear arsenals. 
&gt; Would nuclear disarmament open dangerous windows? 
III. FALSE OPTIMISM: "If losers could foresee their defeat they 
would not fight; hence false optimism on the outcome of war raises the risk of war." (See Blainey, Causes of War, chapter 3, "Dreams and Delusions of the Coming War," assigned.) 
A. Three types of false optimism: 
1. Optimism about relative power: Hitler vs. USSR 1941, Arabs vs. Israel 1967, Israel vs. Arabs 1973, France vs. Prussia 1870, Saddam Hussein 1990-1991 (He proclaimed to the U.S.: "We will walk on your skulls!"); US vs. Iraq 2003. 
2. Optimism about relative will: Japan vs. USA 1941, The Confederacy 1861, USA vs. Vietnam 1965, Saddam Hussein of Iraq 1990-91 and 2003 ("The Americans have no stomach for casualties!"). 
3. Optimism about relative access to allies: Germany 1939, North Korea 1950, Germany 1914. 
B. Causes of false optimism: First-strike advantages? Arms races? Self-glorifying nationalist myths? Multipolarity? Personality disorder? Narcissism and related personality disorders cause decision making pathologies in government. 
IV. CUMULATIVE RESOURCES: "The greater the cumulativity of resources--that is, the more that control of one resource enables control of another--the greater the risk of war." Examples of cumulative resources: -- Buffer Room: "We need to control our lifelines/backyard 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>shields. For example, when Roman and Carthaginian forces 
fought at Cannae in 216 BCE some 76,000 of the 126,000 participants perished in an afternoon. And more recently (1994) Hutu extremists in Rwanda slaughtered 800,000 of their Tutsi and moderate Hutu compatriots in a few weeks with machetes. 
&gt; What quality of verification would be required before 
states would disarm? What arrangements to equalize both side's possible rate of "breakout" from the arms control regime would be required? 
2. Is it desirable? The problem of preventive war. 
3. If it's possible, is it necessary? If states already get along so well that they can agree to disarm, why is it needed? 
B. Is quantitative disarmament possible/desirable? (Clearly it's possible: see strategic arms agreements of 1972-present--SALT, START, etc. This saves money. Some say it also dampens mutual fear.) 
D. Is qualitative disarmament--i.e., limiting some types of arms--possible/desirable? Specifically: Limits on offensive arms? Limits on indiscriminate arms (nukes, bioweapons, chem weapons, mines)? Limits on first-move advantages by requiring transparency? 
Hypotheses I-VIII comprise the universe of major hypotheses on arms and war. If you can think of more you've found something new. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.42 / Causes and Prevention of War 
Stephen Van Evera 
MILITARY POWER AND THE CAUSES OF WAR: EIGHT HYPOTHESES 
I. FIRST MOVE ADVANTAGE (or "crisis instability"). "The greater 
the advantage that accrues to the side mobilizing or striking first, the greater the risk of war." See Schelling, Arms and Influence, chapter 6 (assigned). 
A. Dangers raised by a first-move advantage (FMA): 
1. Opportunistic war. ("If we strike first we win, so let's strike and capture the benefits of winning!") 
2. Preemptive war. "We fear they will strike, so we must strike to deny them the first-mover advantage." Examples: Israel's 1967 attack on Egypt; Russian and French pre-mobilization in 1914. And two extensions: -- "Accidental War."  Example: 1890 Battle of Wounded Knee. -- "The Reciprocal Fear of Surprise Attack"--Schelling. 
("We fear they fear we fear they will strike; so they may strike; so we must.") This is the common formulation of the problem but the least realistic. History shows that reciprocal fear almost never happens, perhaps because states seldom see themselves as threats to others so they seldom expect others to fear themselves. 
3. The dangers of candor. States conceal their grievances and their capabilities because they think: "We must lull them into believing we are weak and benign; otherwise we can't gain surprise." This makes inadvertent war and wars of false optimism more likely. a. States conceal their grievances: China vs. USA 1950, Egypt vs. Israel 1973, Prussia vs. Austria 1740. 
b. States conceal their capabilities, leaving others undeterred: China vs. USA 1950, Egypt vs. Israel 1973. 
c. States conceal their misperceptions, leaving others unable to correct these misperceptions: North Korea regarding U.S. intentions 1950; China regarding U.S. intentions 1950; Britain and France regarding U.S. intentions 1956, Prussia regarding other powers 1740, Japan regarding U.S. will 1941. 
B. Types of war caused by FMA: first mobilization vs. first strike; preemption of opponents vs. preemption of neutral states. 
C. Features of a first-move advantage. 
1. First-strike and first-mobilization advantages are both 
dangerous. 
2. First-move advantages are two-sided. If you gain by moving 
first, it also pays your opponent to move first, to deny you the advantage of moving first. 
D. Elements of a first-move advantage. 
1. A military move can be made secretly, catching the target by surprise. This is a function of two factors: (a) the degree of concealment of the attack; (b) the speed of the attack. 
2. A successful secret move can change the force ratio in the 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>D. 
E. 
F. 
G. are more common; and errors flowing therefrom have more 
catastrophic and less reversible consequences. (States think: "If they knew our plans and forces our enemies could conquer us; hence we must observe dark secrecy.") 
9. Arms racing is more intense, giving rise to windows of opportunity and vulnerability, and to false optimism. 
10. Offense-dominance is self-feeding: offense breeds offense. ("Offense is the stronger form of war; we should buy what works so let's buy offensive forces.") 
How can these hypotheses be tested? What are their observable implications? Tests and what they show: 1. In the past states were often driven to war by the search for security. In a world of very strong defenses this search would not be necessary, and the wars caused by this search could be avoided. 
2. War has been more common when and where security was believed scarce. &gt; Germany's borders are not defensible; Germany is 
aggressive. 
&gt; The Soviet Union recklessly caused the Cuban Missile 
Crisis in 1962 because it learned in late 1961 that the U.S. had nuclear superiority. Soviet leaders feared the U.S. might use this nuclear superiority to subjugate the USSR. 
&gt; European leaders thought conquest was unusually easy in 
1914, and were uncommonly belligerent. 
&gt; China's leaders launched a very dangerous war against 
the U.S. in 1950 to avert a feared U.S. invasion of Manchuria. 
3. Deduction from psychology. Fear is an especially hot button for humans. It makes people violent. 
How much history can offense-defense theory (ODT) explain? Wars stemming from the search for security are abundant. If so, ODT explains a lot. Causes of offensive and defensive advantage: 1. Military factors: i. Arms. 
ii. Geography: mountains and bodies of water are barriers to offense. 
iii. Nationalism. iv. Urban vs. Rural setting. 
2. Diplomatic factors: i. Are alliances defensive or defensive/offensive? 
ii. Do "balancer" states exist and do they balance? 
iii. Can "collective security" be made to work? 
3. The conflict between arms and diplomacy: can defending your allies require offensive forces? 
Are offensive military strategies always bad? Despite the dangers listed under "A", is offense sometimes the best strategy anyway? 1. For "extended deterrence" (i.e., protecting allies)? 
2. For scaring aggressor-states into better behavior? 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>etc." 
-- Resources that can be converted into military power, e.g., 
industry. 
-- Credibility of threats and promises. 
How does the nuclear revolution change things on this score? 
V. CHEAP WAR: "War is least common when its costs are greatest." 
VI. OFFENSE-DEFENSE THEORY. "War is more likely when conquest is 
easy." Offering this idea: Rousseau in 18th C ("Island states are more defensible, hence less involved in wars"), Jean de Bloch 1899, Hugh Gibson 1932, Robert Jervis 1978. A summary is the assigned reading by SVE, "Offense-Defense Theory in a Nutshell." A related idea: the "security dilemma." 
A. What is the "Security Dilemma"? It arises when states' efforts to secure themselves leave other states insecure. 
B. Are offensive forces and force postures distinguishable from defensive forces and force postures? (Sometimes.) Does the offense-defense balance vary across time and space? (Yes; compare the battles of France, 1914 and 1940.) 
C. Ten (10) Dangers that Arise When Conquest Is Easy: 1. Opportunistic aggression. When conquest is easy cheap gains can be had by war, so states go to war. 
2. Defensive aggression. States are less secure because their borders are harder to defend and their neighbors are more aggressive. Hence they seek to expand to make their borders more defensible; to cut their neighbors down to size; and to oust hostile nearby regimes. 
3. Fierce resistance to others' expansion. Small gains by an enemy can snowball, so every gain by the other must be strongly opposed. This intensifies the collision between expansionist states and others. 
4. First-move advantages are larger because states can make greater territorial gains with any military advantages gained by mobilizing first or striking first. 
5. Windows are larger for the same reason. Small force-ratio advantages can be converted into large territorial gains, and small force-ratio disadvantages may translate into large losses, so states are anxious to strike while they have the upper hand if they see themselves in relative decline. 
6. Fait Accompli tactics: a. These are more tempting to adopt ("We must gain our aims, since our safety is threatened if we fail; hence we should adopt even reckless diplomatic tactics if they will work.") 
b. These have more dangerous effects if adopted. 
7. Alliances are tighter, hence wars have a greater propensity to spread (e.g., 1914). (States think: "We can't let our allies go under or we'll be next; so we must join every war they get into, even wars they start.") 
8. Secrecy is tighter, hence false optimism and misperception 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec1_overview/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>human affairs are governed by regularities, or "laws of 
motion." These laws of political/social motion can be divined by using the scientific method, and knowledge of these laws can be used to solve social problems. 
B. Inferring and testing general social science theories. 1. Observation vs. experimentation. &gt; Controlled experiments can rarely be used to study 
international politics. 
&gt; In observational science, "natural experiments" or 
"quasi-experiments" are especially useful. These are situations that occur in history that have attributes of controlled experiments. They offer strong tests of theories. 
2. Large-n (statistical) method vs. case study method. 
C. Explaining specific events: Carl Hempel's "covering law" (or "deductive nomological") method. 1. Identify valid theories. 
2. Identify the scope conditions required for their operation. 
3. Investigate whether the theory's cause and required scope conditions are present in the case to be explained. If so, the theory helps explain the case. 
D. Criticisms of social science. 1. "Accidents drive history--'butterflies cause hurricanes' in history--hence general theories cannot explain much." Annie Oakley had a chance to shoot Kaiser Wilhelm while on tour in Europe before 1914. What if she had? 
2. "Each historical event is unique; hence generalization is futile, even misleading"--a claim made by historians. Implied: politics has no laws of motion. 
3. "Controlled experiments are necessary to test theories. They are often infeasible in political science, so it can't be a science." 
4. "Data on human affairs is unreliable or lacking, hence social science has no reliable empirical basis." This is sometimes true but often the reverse is true. Compare social science with paleontology: we can interview our subjects and read their memoirs; natural scientists can't. Social scientists really can't complain on this score. 
E. Controversies in social science about how to do it. 
1. Social scientists disagree on the best way to measure causal relationships between phenomena. Should scholars use large-n methods, experimental methods, or case methods? 
2. In the history field the study of international history and military history has been pushed aside by other subjects, such as the study of race, class and gender issues. Questions of race, class and gender are very important, but so are international and military history. Their marginalization harms our ability to study the causes and prevention of war. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>(2003). 
C. Religion as a cause of war and peace. Under what 
conditions do religions become aggressive and/or violent? 
D. Diplomatic/foreign policy bungles and blunders. Appeasement as a cause of war. 
E. Other causes of war: climate change, dictatorship, personality disorder, men and their testosterone. 
F. A class theme: pre-modern war was often about material conflicts of interest. Modern wars are often wars of illusions and misperceptions. 
V. CLASS MISSIONS 
A. Specific course missions: explaining historical cases; 
making/testing theories of war's causes; making prescriptions. How can war be prevented? 
B. Broad course missions: to help students learn how to ask 
questions, devise and frame explanations and arguments, marshall evidence, and present arguments and evidence. How to distinguish the essential from the trivial in an unformed domain. 
C. We focus on developing your communication skills. MIT 
alumni have reported that they later found they needed more communication and leadership skills to realize their potential. We are here to help with that. 
VI. NINE CASES EXPLORED: Peloponnesian War, Seven Years War, 
Wars of German Unification, World War I, World War II, Korea, Israel-Arab conflict, 2003 US-Iraq War, the US-al-Qaeda war/Clash of Civilizations. 
Other current wars will also be mentioned: India-
Pakistan, Ukraine, ISIS, the U.S.-North Korea confrontation. 
VII. GRADES AND REQUIREMENTS 
A. Background required: none. Students with zero history 
background are welcome. No knowledge of international or 
diplomatic history is assumed for this course. We start 
from the beginning. 
B. Requirements: see the syllabus. 
C. Discussion sections are important. Sections are small. 
Hence they won't work if you don't attend regularly and try to contribute to discussion. Help us make sections work! A section highlight: Debates on responsibility for the two world wars are featured in coming weeks. 
VIII. SOCIAL SCIENCE AND THE CAUSES OF WAR 
A. The premise of social science: like the physical world, 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.42 // Causes and Prevention of War // MIT 
Instructor: Stephen Van Evera 
17.42 COURSE OVERVIEW 
I. COURSE QUESTIONS 
&gt; What causes war?  Including: wars of the past, present, and 
future. 
&gt; What general phenomena cause war? 
&gt; What were the causes of specific wars?  Who caused 
specific wars (e.g., World War I? 
&gt; How can war best be prevented? &gt; Why has war changed?  Until 1945 most wars were interstate, 
now most wars are civil wars. Also, warfare diminished sharply after 1945. Why? 
&gt; Will another world war someday occur? If so, what will be its 
causes? 
&gt; We focus on interstate war.  For civil war, see 17.582, 
"Civil War," usually taught by Prof. Roger Petersen, sometimes by Prof. Fotini Christia, and open to undergraduates with permission of the instructor. 
II. SCHOLARSHIP ON THE CAUSES OF WAR IS INCOMPLETE. John 
Burgess started the Columbia School of Political Science in 1881 to find a solution to the war problem. We now have some answers but big questions remain. 
III. WHAT THEORIES OF WAR ARE YOU EXPECTING TO HEAR DISCUSSED IN 
THIS CLASS? 
Please share your expectations. 
IV. IDEAS OF THE COURSE: FAMILIES OF HYPOTHESES 
A. Military factors: &gt; Arms cause war, arms control or disarmament can prevent 
war. 
&gt; "First-move advantage" causes war.  Examples: the 1967 
Israel-Arab war and World War I. 
&gt; "War is more likely when states are insecure.  This 
happens when conquest is easy." World War I is the classic example but most wars illustrate, including the Cold War, US vs. China 1950, Germany vs. Europe 1939, the Peloponnesian War, and the 2003 Iraq war. 
&gt; Do weapons of mass destruction (WMD)--nuclear or 
biological weapons--cause peace or war? Is the possible future spread of WMD to more states, or even to sub-state organizations like terrorists or individuals, a cause of war? 
B. Misperception: false optimism; nationalist mythmaking; militarism; the stupidity of bureaucracies; myths purveyed by religious establishments; ingroup-outgroup dynamics and their role in causing misperception. Examples of misperceiving states: Germany before WWI and WWII; Japan before WWII; Athens before its expedition to Syracuse; al-Qaeda today; Saddam Hussein before the 1991 and 2003 Gulf wars; the US in Vietnam and before the second Gulf war 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Israel-Arab Conflict</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec22_israelarab/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>1. Israel has developed a secure nuclear arsenal that makes
Israel unconquerable.
2. Israel achieved peace with Egypt in 1979, lifting threat
of Egyptian attack.
3. The Soviet Union collapsed in 1991, removing Syria's
source of weapons.
4. The Syrian, Iraqi, and Iranian economies have stagnated,
while Israel has prospered.
5. The U.S. invaded Iraq in 2003 and occupied it during
2003-2011.  Iraq is now a failed state, incapable of
aggression.
6. Syria fell into civil war in 2011 and is also incapable 
of aggression.
7. The Israeli military has adopted new technologies while
Arab militaries have stagnated.
Overall, threat of Arab/Iranian invasion from the east hasbecome implausible. 
VI. SOLUTIONS TO THE ARAB-ISRAELI CONFLICT: LARGE OPTIONS 
A. Partition the land of Palestine--the two-state solution. 1. Through agreement, and failing that,
2. By Israeli fiat.
3. By UN fiat.
B. Create a binational state with power-sharing between Jews and Arabs. Once proposed by dovish Zionists (MartinBuber, Judah Magnes, Ahad Ha'am); later proposed byPalestinian hard-liners. 
C. Palestinian exhaustion, eventual submission to Israeli 
domination. A greater Israel solution.
D. Expel (or "transfer") Palestinians into Jordan if they
don't submit to Israel.  Eventually the Palestinians wouldaccept life in Jordan. Another greater Israel solution.
E. The Jews eventually leave the Middle East as the Crusaders
did in 1300. This is the rejectionist Palestinian
solution--often masked under solution B, "binational state." 
Which solutions are feasible? How do we know? What evidence is needed to judge their feasibility? 
VII. MEANS TO A 2-STATE SOLUTION 
Most experts argue that only solution VI "A", partition,
holds promise of durable peace in the near term.
If so, how could partition be achieved?
A. New historical narratives. 1. Israelis and Palestinians could take responsibilityfor their own misdeeds and stop false blaming of the 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>c. "Israeli expansion raises the risk of WMD terror 
against Israel." Yitzhak Rabin and Ehud Barak both 
worried that the conflict could produce WMD terror
against Israel unless it is resolved.
Would better policy evaluation among Israelis or
Palestinians have produced peace?
F. War ---&gt; War.  Specifically, 1948 war ---&gt; 1967 war ---&gt; 
1973 war, war today.
G. Strategy debates.
1. In Israel: Does Israel have a Palestinian partner for
peace? Related: Does Arab hostility to Israel stemmainly from Israel's seizure of Arab lands and expulsionof Arab peoples in 1947-48?  Or from anti-semitism 
embedded in Muslim scripture?
2. Among Palestinians: Is Israel a partner for peace?
Related: Is Israeli hostility toward Palestinian
statehood fueled mainly by Israeli doubts that thePalestinians are willing to accept Israel and make a 
durable peace with it? Or by Jewish religious extremism
(i.e., desire for Biblical fulfillment) and a desire formore land for settlement? 
Polls show that both sides greatly underestimate theproportion of the other public that is willing to agree a 
two-state solution. 
V. EVENTS 1949-PRESENT 
A. Religions motivations and religious extremism have risen on
both sides since 1949, 1. In the late 1960s an extremist religious Israeli settler
movement appeared. It aimed to colonize the West Bank 
and perhaps more.
2. In the 1980s an extremist religious Palestinian
movement, Hamas, appeared. Its stated goal is to
destroy Israel. It now controls Gaza. (The secular
Fatah still controls the West Bank.)
B. Secular communities on both sides have greatly moderated 
their views, and now largely accept the need to sharePalestine/Israel with one another. Secular Israelis (for
example, former Prime Minister Ehud Olmert and former
Kadima party leader Tzipi Livni) accept the notion of aPalestinian state.  Secular Palestinians (for example,Palestinian President Abu Mazen) accept the need torecognize and live with Israel.
C. Since 1949 Israel has become far more secure from conquest,
and control of the West Bank has become far less importantto Israeli security. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.42 / Causes and Prevention of War 
Stephen Van Evera 
CAUSES OF/SOLUTIONS TO THE ISRAEL-ARAB CONFLICT 
I. ISRAEL/PALESTINE IN ANCIENT TIMES
The Israelites, forbearers of today's Jews, emerged in ~1200
BCE in today's West Bank. Twice in ancient times they
established independent kingdoms (~1000-586 BCE, ~140-63 BCE).These Israelite kingdoms were eventually conquered anddestroyed by others. Many Jews fled to Europe at some point.
There they were relentlessly oppressed--driven into ghettoes
and sometimes murdered en masse--by the Christian majority.
The Arabs are a Mideast people racially and linguistically
related the Jews and Canaanites. In ancient times they weredesert people. 
II. THE BIRTH OF ZIONISM, 1896
Theodor Herzl and other early Zionist leaders sought to createa safe haven for the Jewish people in an anti-semitic worldthat rejected them. 
III. ISRAEL-ARAB CONFLICTS: SIX BIG WARS, THREE SMALL WARS, TWOINTIFADAS 
A. Big wars in 1947-49 (the "1948 War," or the "Nakba" or
"Catastrophe"); 1956 (the "Sinai War"), 1967 (the "Six Day
War"), 1969-70 (the "Canal War"); 1973 (the "Yom Kippur War"
or "October War"); and 1982-2000 (the "Lebanon War").
B. Small wars in 2006 (the "Second Lebanon War" or "July War"),
2008-9 ("Operation Cast Lead" or "the Battle of al-Furqan"),and 2014 ("Operation Protective Edge" or the "2014 Gaza
Massacre").
C. Intifadas (Palestinian uprisings) in 1987-1991, 2000-2005.
D. Serious peace talks in 2000 ("Camp David"), 2001 ("Taba"),
and 2008 (Olmert-Abu Mazen talks). 
IV. CAUSES OF THE CONFLICT 
A. Conflict over land. The Jews and Palestinians both claim 
the same place. Oh dear! No settler-colonial movement has ever avoided war with the indigenous people of the landsthat it colonized. If so, the cause of the conflict lies in 
the cause of Jewish settler-colonialism (Christian
antisemitism).
B. The security dilemma. Geography--close proximity and 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Jewish state."  (A Jewish claim.)
G. Religious importance of the land--"Israel-Palestine is key
to our faith!"  Jews point to the central importance to
Judaism of the ancient Jewish temple in Jerusalem and theGrave of the Patriarchs in Hebron. Palestinian Muslims point to the Dome of the Rock mosque in Jerusalem.(Christians once made similar claims; interesting they nolonger do so.)
H. Illegitimacy of the opponent's status as heir--"You arenot descendants of those from whom you claim you inheritedrights to Palestine." A Palestinian claim, arguing that
today's Jews are descended from Jewish converts fromKhazaria, and cannot trace family lineage back to ancient
Palestine. 
I. Human rights--"You can't take Palestine without
subjugating and expelling us, because we live there now.That's barbaric!"  (Mainly a Palestinian claim, although
Israelis make a parallel claim to denounce Palestinian
rejection of Israel's right to exist.)
J. Best use--"You wasted the land, we made it bloom."  (A
Jewish claim.)
K. Forfeit by misconduct:
&gt; "You should have shared Palestine with us but 
refused--so you lose it by moral forfeit." (A Jewish
claim.) Related: "You started the wars between us,especially the 1948 and 1967 wars--so you lost Palestineby moral forfeit." (A Jewish claim.) Related: "The Arab states expelled many Jews in 1948 and after; this
expulsion negates any wrong that the Jews committed
against the Palestinians in 1948." (A Jewish claim.)
&gt; "You came here to create an ethnically exclusive
Jewish state that would dominate us and expel us, not tolive together with us in a secular state. You are the 
ones who wouldn't share Palestine! Hence your Zionist
enterprise is morally illegitimate." (A Palestinianclaim.) Related: "You started the wars between us. You knew that any indigenous people in our shoes would resistyour movement by force but you pushed ahead anyway. Thus 
you knowingly provoked war by colonizing Palestine."
Related: "You lost Palestine fair and square when youfoolishly launched the Bar Kokhba rebellion in 134 CE.That folly canceled your claims based on ancientpossession, as you threw the possession away." (A
Palestinian claim.)
How can these moral claims be assessed? 
A formula to consider: "Both the Jews and the Palestinians 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>other. 
2. Israelis and Palestinians could put more blame for the
conflict where it belongs--on the Christian west--and
less on each other. 
a. Palestinians could then grant the Zionistenterprise some moral legitimacy.
b. Israelis could more easily admit their owncruelties toward the Palestinians, knowing that
they could attribute these in a final sense to the
Christians instead of taking full responsibilityfor these cruelties themselves. 
B. Could the U.S. impose peace? Specifically, could it framean American final-status peace agreement and then persuade
both sides to accept it with carrots and sticks? 
VIII. WHERE LIES JUSTICE IN THIS CONFLICT? JUDGING MORAL CLAIMS 
TO ISRAEL/PALESTINE: CRITERIA
A. Religious claims--"God gave it to us."  (A Jewish claim,
echoed by the Jews' evangelical Christian allies; and aPalestinian claim.) Jews point to the Covenant passagesof Genesis and Exodus. Palestinians claim that Palestine is "Muslim land" and that Palestinians are enjoined todefend it by the religious requirement to defend all
Muslim lands under attack. 
B. Ancient ownership--"We had it first."  A Jewish and 
Palestinian claim. Jews note their ancient presence in
Palestine back to 1200 BCE. Palestinians counter bynoting their likely relationship to the Canaanites and
other ancients who owned Palestine before the Jews. They
also note that in ancient times the Jews lived mainly inthe highlands of the West bank. Jewish settlement in the lowlands, including Tel Aviv, was sparse and brief. Under an "ancient ownership" principle the Israeli Jews and
Palestinians would trade places.
C. Longest tenure--"We had it longest."  (A Palestinian and
Jewish claim. In fact it's a close-run thing.)
D. Most recent tenure--"We had it last."  (A Palestinian
claim.)
E. Current tenure--"We have it now."  (A Jewish claim
regarding Israel within 1967 lines; and a Palestinian
claim regarding the West Bank, Gaza, East Jerusalem.)Related: "It's ours under civil law. Please respectproperty rights!" (A Palestinian claim.)
F. Necessity--"Our straits are more dire than yours--we needPalestine to survive, you don't."  Also, "Palestinians can 
live in any one of 21 Arab states; Jews have only one 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>indefensible borders--made the Palestinians and Israelis a 
threat to each other.  This drove each to seek to dominate the other. Israel sought wide territories in 1947-48, 
expelling many Palestinians in the process, to gain secure
borders. Israel also sent settlers into the West Bank after 1967 to avert a two-state solution, to ensure Israel retained secure borders. 
Some argue that Israel no longer needs large territories
to be secure. Does Israel's nuclear deterrent make it unconquerable?
C. Invented chauvinist history. Both Arabs and Israelis 
wallowed in historical mythmaking about the origins of Zionism, the 1948 war and later wars. Each exculpated
itself of wrongdoing while casting all blame on the other.
Neither put much blame for the conflict on the mostresponsible party, the Christian West. &gt; These chauvinist histories lie mainly by what they omit.
D. Religious extremism.
1. In Israel. 
a. An Israeli settler movement has emerged since 1967
that claims vast Arab lands beyond Israel's 1967borders, roughly following the borders of David'skingdom. This settler movement is fueled by 
scripture-based claims that God gave the West Bank and 
much more to the Jews. This reflects a literalist reading of scripture, and a selective readingscripture that omits the command to "love thestranger, for you were strangers in the land of Egypt" 
(Deut. 16:11).
b. Some religious Israelis now demand that Israel must
retain control of the Temple Mount. This is a change
of position the old days; in 1938 Zionist leadersexpressed more interest in Mount Scopus (Hebrew
University) than the Temple Mount. 
2. Among Palestinians. Hamas, an extremist Palestinian
organization that rejects a two-state solution with 
Israel, emerged in 1987 and gained large influence.Hamas is fueled by the view that Islam requires jihad,
jihad requires the defense of all Muslim land, and Israel 
is Muslim land. This view reflects militant sections of the Koran written in Medina, when Muhammad and hisfollowers were at war. 
&gt; The Israeli settler and Hamas views of scripture are 
contestable but rarely contested.
3. Among Christians. Christian anti-semitism through the 
ages has been fueled by barbs against the Jews in the 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>gospels of Matthew and John. These barbs (e.g., Matthew
27:20-26; John 8:44-47; also 7:1, 10:31) were written during growing conflict between the mainstream Jewish 
community and the early Christian secessionists.
E. False optimism. Both sides have relentlessly believed that
force could make the other fold. Neither has proven right
so far. 1. The Palestinians refused the 1947 partition and then
refused to accept the 1949 armistice lines, wrongly believing that force could gain them better terms.
2. Israel refused Egypt's peace offer in 1971, and pursued
later peace efforts indifferently or not at all, wronglybelieving that Israel could instead compel the Arabs to 
concede the gains Israel made in the 1967 war. These 
policies set the stage for the 1973 war and laterviolence. 
E. Bad strategies and tactics, arising from illusions and
misperceptions.
&gt; Regarding Palestinian strategy:
1. Some argue that the Palestinians' strategy of violence 
has served them poorly. In this view the methods of 
Gandhi and Martin Luther King would serve them betterat this stage of the conflict. Likewise, more use of 
public relations instead of violence would serve them
better.  "Use your words."
2. Some complain that the Palestinians have missed
opportunities to settle the conflict--they have "never missed an opportunity to miss an opportunity."
&gt; Regarding Israeli strategy:
1. Some argue that Israel cannot be expansionist and 
Zionist. They note that Israel will soon become anArab-majority country unless it divests itself of the territories it conquered in 1967.
2. Some argue that Israeli expansion (that is, Israeli
colonization of West Bank and vassalization of Gaza) onbalance harms Israeli security.a. "Israeli expansion retards Israel's ability to
attract Jewish immigrants."
b. "Israeli expansion could trigger a resurgent pan-
Arabism, or an even wider Muslim mobilizationagainst Israel. Pan-Arabism could lead to an Arab union of some kind--as German, Italian, and Vietnamese movements of union produced nation 
states. This would gravely threaten Israeli
security. A still-wider Muslim mobilization would be even more dangerous to Israel." 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>are right. The Christian west is wrong; it is morally
responsible for the conflict." 
8</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>More Causes of War and Peace</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec8-9_warpeace/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8&#8211;9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>agree on terms for settling all possible conflicts interest 
before they become politicized." Settlements on almost any terms are often better than no settlement. 
XVI. CULTURAL LEARNING CAUSES PEACE / HUMAN ETHICAL PROGRESS 
CAUSES PEACE
 "War was delegitimated as a human practice by the slaughter of 
the World Wars, just as slavery and duelling were earlier 
delegitimated." An hypothesis from John Mueller.
 Is this hypothesis valid? What about World War II, Korea, 
Vietnam, and the Iraq wars of 1991 and 2003-present? The civil wars in Angola and Sudan? The great Central African war of 1996-present? The growing Islam-Western collision?
 Perhaps war is not now being delegitimated as a human 
practice, but could it be? What if peace religions (Mennonites, Bahai's, Buddhist peace sects) expanded in size? Some believe this is the answer to war. Surely human ethics have advanced since the Romans entertained themselves at the Coliseum by watching people die and the Aztecs and Philistines practiced human sacrifice. Can they advance further? 
XVII. NATIONALISM CAUSES WAR 
"The rise of nationalism--the doctrine that people owe their 
prime loyalty to their ethno-cultural group and that this group 
deserves a state--is a prime cause of conflict. Replace nationalism with a pan-human identity and we abolish a prime cause of intergroup conflict."
 Nationalism is indeed new (post 18th century) and sets up 
great conflicts between ethno-national groups. But how can national identities be abolished?
 A more practical idea: accept national identities as 
inevitable but make them more benign by inducing national groups to abandon nationalist mythmaking and commonize their histories--as discussed last week. 
XVIII. EMOTIONS CAUSE WAR OR PEACE 
"Emotions like desire for honor, desire for vengeance, pride, 
backlash against displays of contempt, and jealously at a status 
reversal can trigger war. Apology and displays of contrition can bolster peace." 
IX. BIPOLARITY CAUSES PEACE 
"A bipolar international order is more peaceful and a 
multipolar order, because false optimism is less likely. States 
can't have illusions about how many allies will join their side in the next war because there are no major nonaligned states in the system." An idea from Kenneth Waltz.
 Is this hypothesis valid? Does it point to a manipulable 
cause? 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>of being overthrown by counterrevolution--leading to foreign 
campaigns against counterrevolutionary regimes. (3) They misperceive the world because revolutionary regimes tolerate no dissent, hence they do not correct their own errors by self-evaluation. (4) They produce emigrs who seek to manipulate their new homelands into attacking their old homeland." An argument made by Stephen Walt in a book and an article on the subject. (5) They select sociopathic leaders with personality disorders, e.g., Stalin, Mao.
 This theory seems well-supported by evidence. See for 
example, the wars gotten into by revolutionary France during 1792-1815, by revolutionary Russia during 1920-21 and then during the Cold War (1947-89), by revolutionary Cambodia in 1979, and by revolutionary Iran with Iraq in 1980-1988 and its cold war with the U.S. 1979-present. But the world's mass revolutions seem largely behind us; and mass revolution is hard to influence.
 A variant of this theory: "Petro-states run by 
revolutionaries--e.g., post-1979 Iran, Saddam's Iraq, Qadafy's Libya, are aggressive, warlike" (Jeff Colgan). 
XII. COMMUNISM CAUSES WAR 
"Communist regimes are infused with a revolutionary messianism 
that leads them into foreign wars."
 This is basically a variant of the previous proposition, "Mass 
Revolution." XIII. CAPITALISM CAUSES WAR--an idea in two variants 
1. "Capitalist states must conquer the markets that their 
economies require to avoid recessions and depressions. This 
leads to wars over colonies and wars against colonies." A favorite Marxist argument.
 This hypotheses fits some wars during 1890-1918, especially 
the Spanish-American and US-Filipino wars, but not more recent wars. And it points to a cause that is not manipulable. 
2. "Capitalist states spawn multinational corporations that 
manipulate their home states to intervene in states where they do business."
 This hypothesis fits the U.S. intervention in Guatemala in 
1954 and perhaps British and U.S. covert action against Iran in 1953. But major wars don't illustrate, despite the charge that "oil companies pushed the U.S. to war in Iraq 2003." 
XIV. IMPERIAL DECLINE AND COLLAPSE CAUSE WAR 
"The collapse of empires leaves the zone of imperial 
retraction without settled borders and leaves nearby powers 
unsure of their rights and responsibilities in this zone. Conflict results."
 Historical evidence supports this hypothesis. Some current 
conflicts may also illustrate, e.g., the ongoing Russia-Ukraine-U.S. conflict, and Turkish-Kurdish conflict in Syria. But imperial collapse is now rare. It's a war-cause that is largely defunct--those empires prone to collapse have already collapsed. And it is very hard to manipulate.
 A related hypothesis ...: 
XV. UNSETTLED DISPUTES CAUSE WAR 
"Conflicts of interest that are unsettled can become 
politicized and then become causes of war. States should move to 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>A cheery scenario.) 
FOUR IDEAS ABOUT EFFECTS OF SOCIAL/ECONOMIC CONDITIONS ... V. DEMOCRACY CAUSES PEACE: THREE ARGUMENTS 
Variant #1:
 "Democratic states very rarely fight one another. This is 
because (a) publics are more anti-war than elites, making states 
ruled by the public more peaceful; and/or because (b) democratic publics are infused with democratic values that clash with the notion of conquering and ruling others against their will." An argument by Imanuel Kant, Woodrow Wilson, and Michael Doyle.
 Is this hypothesis valid? What evidence would test it? 
(Strong evidence supports it.)
 Is this cause of war/peace manipulable? Can democracy be 
conjured up and sustained in non-democratic societies?
 Does democratization promote peace in multiethnic 
authoritarian states? Civil conflict in Sri Lanka and Kenya warns that democratization can cause war in such settings. Iraq, Afghanistan, and Iran have worrisome demography from this viewpoint.
 Does democratization cause war while states are still 
democratizing? Some (Jack Snyder and Ed Mansfield) argue that democratizing states are prone to hyper-nationalism and hence are bellicose. 
Variant #2:
 "Democracies have free debate. This weeds out bad ideas (says 
John Stuart Mill), hence better ideas govern policy, hence democracies wage fewer foolish wars, and so wage fewer wars overall." In fact, though, democracies don't wage fewer wars than dictatorships (as this hypothesis predicts). 
Variant #3:
 "Democracies are less stratified than other societies (see 
Hypo #5, below), and their governments draw legitimacy from being elected. Hence elites in democracies feel less need to purvey self-glorifying and self-white-washing myths in order to legitimate themselves. Hence war-causing myths are less pervasive." 
VI. PROSPERITY CAUSES PEACE 
"Prosperity gives people more to lose in war, so they avoid 
war more carefully. And wealthy societies are less desperate for 
economic gain than poor societies, and so wage fewer wars of plunder. Also, prosperity promotes democracy, which independently promotes peace."
 Prosperity may cause peace by promoting democracy, which in 
turn causes more equality and therefore less nationalism.
 But history does not reveal a clear correlation between 
prosperity and peace. Today wealthy global regions are far more peaceful than poor regions. But during 1914-1945 the world's richest states unleashed immense violence on one another, wreaking vast ruin.
 Also, prosperity is hard to foster from outside. 
VII. ECONOMIC INTERDEPENDENCE CAUSES PEACE--OR WAR? 
"Economic interdependence between states raises the cost of 
cutting economic ties between states. This dampens the risk of war by raising its costs. Interdependence also fosters 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>communication that dampens conflict." An argument by Imanuel 
Kant among others. The opposite may also occur. States that depend on imported food, oil or other materials may fear being strangled by embargo or blockade and so wage aggressive wars to gain control over these resources. Such fears fueled German and Japanese aggression in World War II.
 Recently China has sought to integrate its economy with 
Taiwan's economy to draw the two societies together, with some success. 
VIII. SOCIAL EQUALITY, SOCIAL JUSTICE CAUSE PEACE 
"Social inequity causes war by creating social conflict that 
elites defuse by pursuing conflict with other states. Social 
inequity also spurs elites to sow war-causing nationalist myths in order to defuse demands from below."
 Is this cause of war manipulable? Not easily! 
IX. MINORITY RIGHTS, OTHER HUMAN RIGHTS CAUSE PEACE 
"Minorities that are treated fairly are less likely to pursue 
secession by force. This dampens the risk of civil war." 
The 1969-1998 Catholic rebellion in Northern Ireland ("The 
Troubles") and the 1983-2009 Tamil rebellion in Sri Lanka were provoked by the oppression of the Catholic and Tamil minorities. Accordingly, the European Union and U.S. government promoted minority rights in Eastern Europe after 1991 to prevent/abate civil war. Likewise Kofi Anan and the George W. Bush administration ended the 2007-8 civil war in Kenya by brokering a new power-sharing political system that empowers minorities more than the previous winner-take-all system. Many argue that civil peace persists in Switzerland and Belgium because their political systems empower minorities.
 But minority rights are often hard to nurture. How could the 
U.S. do this in Syria and Iraq today? This is much debated. Also, some warn that systems that recognize minority rights increase ethnic conflict by reinforcing ethnic identities. And some warn that outside powers can trigger secessionism among minorities by insisting that governments recognize their rights--once they get these rights the minorities will use force to gain full independence. 
X. PARTITION OF DIVIDED SOCIETIES CAUSES PEACE 
"Sometimes a divorce is the best answer to internal conflict. 
Divided societies should be partitioned into separate states, as 
groups in conflict will fight less as separate states than as citizens of the same state." For example, in 1919 Woodrow Wilson proposed self-determination for the nationalities of Europe as a means to bring greater peace to Europe. Past partitions include: India/Pakistan 1947, Ireland 1922, Palestine 1947, Yugoslavia 1995, and all European colonial empires in the 1950s and 1960s. 
XI. MASS REVOLUTION CAUSES WAR 
"Regimes that seize power by mass revolution are more warlike 
because: (1) They are infused with myths of their own enormous 
goodness, leading to a messianic expansionism. (2) They exaggerate the ease of overthrowing regimes, since their own experience of revolutionary success makes overthrows seem easier than they are. This leads them to recklessly attempt to overthrow neighboring regimes, and also to an unreasonable fear 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>II. GENDER AND WAR 
A. "Men cause war. War would diminish with the greater 
empowerment of women." See the assigned course reading on this subject by Joshua Goldstein. 
Is this explanation valid? What evidence would test it?
 Are observed correlations between gender and attitudes 
on war causal or spurious? For example, might women be more dovish because they depend more on government services? Or play a large role in raising children?
 Does the greater dovishness of women mean states would 
better avoid war if women were more powerful? Or might states then appease their way into war? 
Is this cause of war manipulable? 
B. "Polygamy causes intense competition among men for wealth, causing conflict and war." 
III. PERSONALITY DISORDER CAUSES WAR 
Personality disorders include narcissism, megalomania, 
paranoia, antisocial pathology, and sadism. Some argue that rulers with these disorders govern badly. For example, narcissists have little empathy for others, and thus rule heartlessly; and are enraged at challenge, and thus punish truthful staff who bring them bad news. Hence they live in a world of delusions.
 Some claim that these disorders are over-represented among 
governing elites in many states. Giant pulsating egos ("GPEs") run the world and make a mess of it! Examples include Hitler, Stalin, Mao Zedong, Napoleon, Saddam Hussein, Osama Bin Laden, Muammar Qadafy, Foday Sankoh, and Juan Peron.
 Studies of this hypothesis are few--more are needed. What prescriptions follow, if any? We need to know what 
conditions allow/cause the rise of disordered people to power. What are they?
 Important writers on this idea: Rose McDermott, Jerrold Post. 
IV. CLIMATE CHANGE WILL CAUSE WAR / ENVIRONMENTAL DESTRUCTION WILL CAUSE WAR
 "Climatologists worry that human-caused global warming could 
cause sea levels to rise, flooding vast coastal regions across the world; and could change rainfall patterns, turning verdant lands to deserts and vice-versa. This calamity will displace hundreds of millions of people. These vast refugee flows will directly cause conflict as refugees clash with established populations. The refugees may also develop a Luddite ideology--'Western civilization has destroyed our lives, so we now should destroy Western civilization before it does more harm'--that will fuel anti-Western terror and other violence. Marry this trend with proliferating weapons of mass destruction and you could have trouble. Global warming will also open new conflicts between states, who will quarrel over newly-valuable mineral rights in the now-ice-free arctic. What fun!" 
&gt; Related: "Environmental destruction of all kinds will 
cause war. Human civilization is now colliding with the natural world on which civilization depends. As humans destroy this environment they will struggle more fiercely to control ever-scarcer resources, including water and arable land." (Some warn that human folly will cause the Nile river to dry up, leaving many millions of Egyptians without water. They might be upset! 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.42 // Causes &amp; Prevention of War // Stephen Van Evera 
MORE CAUSES OF WAR AND PEACE 
Culture, Gender, Personality Disorder, Democracy, Social equality 
and social justice, Minority rights and human rights, Partition, Prosperity, Economic interdependence, Revolution, Communism, Capitalism, Imperial decline and collapse, Cultural learning, Nationalism, Emotional factors (revenge, backlash from contempt, honor, alpha-male status competition), Catastrophic climate change, Polarity of the international system. Causes of civil war. 
PROLOGUE: CRITERIA FOR JUDGING THE UTILITY OF THEORIES OF WAR 
Consider the following criteria for judging the utility of 
theories of war: A. Validity &amp; potency. Does the independent variable affect the 
likelihood of war? If so, how much? Invalid theories are not useful. 
B. Satisfaction. Is the theory satisfying? Or does it leave us 
curious? "The candidate lost because she didn't get enough votes" is a valid explanation for an election outcome but is not satisfying. We want to know: why didn't she get enough votes? 
C. Explanatory power.  What is the range and importance of the 
phenomena explained by the theory? For example, "petro-states run by revolutionaries cause war" (narrow application) vs. "insecurity causes war" (broad application). 
D. Prescriptive utility. Does the theory give rise to policy 
prescriptions--that is, to feasible ways to prevent war? 1. Is the cause of war identified by the theory manipulable? 
2. Even if the cause is not manipulable, does awareness of the danger framed by the theory help us devise 
countermeasures to mitigate or abate its effects? 
3. Is the cause of war identified by the theory common or scarce in the real world? If it is scarce it may cause 
little war even if it is a potent cause of war when it is present. Hence it may not be worth our time to think about. 
4. Are the conditions for the operation of the theory known? 
Are these conditions common? To use a theory as a basis for policy, policymakers need to know when/under what 
conditions the theory operates. Otherwise they could mis-apply the theory to situations where it does not work. For example, they might foster democracy under conditions when democracy causes war (as it rarely does) instead of peace (as it usually does). 
I. CULTURAL CAUSES OF WAR 
"Some national cultures incline toward war. For example, 
harsh German child-rearing practices makes Germans belligerent." See, e.g., Leopold Bellak's op-ed about Germans in the course reading.
 Is this explanation satisfying? What causes culture? Is this cause of war manipulable? 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Interlude:
Hypotheses on Escalation and Limitation of War
Nuclear Weapons, Nuclear Strategy, Other Weapons of Mass Destruction and the Causes of War.</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec19_intensewar/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>B. The use of force is blackmail, but states pay large
reputation costs if they concede to blackmail. So using
force makes others less as well as more willing to
concede. 
C. War creates false optimism. Belligerents' optimism
grows as they fight.
D. States at war infuse their populations with hyper-
nationalism and chauvinist mythmaking to persuade them tosupport costly war policies.
E. Wartime non-evaluation: 
1. Critical assessment of official policy becomes "aid
and comfort to the enemy"--and in fact it is!
Question: should wartime dissent therefore be 
suppressed?
2. Ingroup-outgroup dynamics get going. Those who find 
fault with official policies are excoriated for the
crime of sowing disunity in the tribe. Hence war policies are not properly evaluated.
3. Wartime breakdown of communication between 
adversaries ---&gt; no external evaluation of each side's domestic debate ---&gt; lopsided debates on waraims. Sealed information bubbles appear. Hawks can spread unanswered lies about the enemy.
F. Sunk-cost dynamics and ego-investment by elites who
can't admit they were wrong.
G. War creates a popular desire for vengeance. An 
emotional factor. 
H. Do "Cleon's" (military hawks, other hawks) wield
more political power in wartime?
A missing concept in wartime: The "Treason of the Hawks."Collaborating with enemies is reviled as treason, but ruiningone's country in avoidable warfare is a crime with no nameand no punishment. 
VI. DOES WAR BEGET WIDE WAR? WHY? 
Wars tend to spread laterally and engulf other states:1. Wars open windows that other states jump through. WWI 
opened a window for the Ottoman empire to regain Russian
territory, and for Bulgaria to regain Serb territory, and
for Italy to gain Austrian territory. So they joined the war. World War II in Europe opened a window for Japanthat caused WWII in the Pacific. 
2. Wars have crossfire effects: neutrals are damaged, as
the US was damaged in 1914-17; and as in the Gulf TankerWar of the 1980s. The neutrals enter to stop the damage. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.42 
Stephen Van Evera 
THE CAUSES OF INTENSE WAR 
I. THE MYSTERY OF LIMITED/INTENSE WAR 
Some wars are total from the outset, like World War I. Some 
start quietly but end with a bang, like World War II inEurope, which opened with the near-bloodless 1939-40"Sitzkrieg" but became total. Some remain limited, likeKorea and Vietnam. Why? 
II. SEVEN COMMON HYPOTHESES ON LIMITED WAR 
A. "Destructive Weapons Cause Destructive War"--and its
less-popular opposite: "Destructive Weapons Cause MutualDeterrence; Mutual Deterrence Prevents Destructive War."
 Consider four hypotheses on arms and the intensity of 
war: 
1. States destroy what they can. The violence of war 
corresponds to the destructive power of states.
2. States destroy what they cannot avoid destroying.
The violence of war depends on whether weapons are
discriminating, e.g., accurate or not.
3. States destroy what they must to accomplish their
war goals. The violence of war corresponds to thescope of those goals, and hence to the scope of
political conflict between the belligerents.
4. States destroy least when they fear large punishment
in return. The violence of war corresponds inversely
to the ability of both belligerents to punish theother. 
Note: Propositions #A1 and #A2 produce oppositeprescriptions from #A4. Indeed, #A1 and #A4 are logicalmirror opposites. What to make of this? 
Solutions implied by Proposition #A1: 
&gt; Disarmament. 
&gt; Deploy forces that can disarm the other side--e.g.,
strategic nuclear counterforce forces (accurate silo-busting ICBMs and national missile defense). 
Solutions implied by Proposition #A2: &gt; Deploy discriminating weapons that can be used
without collateral damage--e.g., laser-guided bombs. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>3. Decisive wars threaten the security interests of
states threatened by the enlarged power of the winner.
E.g., Hitler's victories in 1939-40 threatened US
security, spurring it to join WWII. Some argue (Buerhig)
that possible German success also brought the US into WWI.
These dynamics sucked the USA into three of Europe's fivegreat wars of 1792-1945. 
VII. WHAT WILL WORLD WAR III BE LIKE? THE NUCLEAR 
REVOLUTION/BIO REVOLUTION AND THE INTENSITY OF WAR 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Ban land mines, especially hard-to-clear anti-
personnel mines; and weapons of mass destruction. 
Solution implied by Proposition #A3: &gt; All states should adopt defensive force postures so
that their neighbors will not be insecure, hence willnot feel the need to adopt desperate measures in asearch for security. 
Solution implied by Proposition #A4: &gt; States should arm themselves abundantly with well-
protected weapons of mass destruction. "Nuclear weapons are your friend!" 
&gt; We should fear the proliferation of weapons of mass
destruction to non-deterrable states or non-state actors (nihiliist terrorists or psychopaths). Non-state actors are hard to punish (they have no returnaddress) and non-deterrable crazy states and non-state
actors are indifferent to punishment. 
&gt; Wars of counterinsurgency will be especially
violent, as they are wars in which governments and
insurgents compete to coerce unarmed publics. The publics cannot punish either government or insurgents,
so violence directed at them is intense. 
B. "Total War Doctrine Causes Total War, Limited War
Doctrines Allow Limited War." 
C. "Defining and Observing Thresholds Helps Keep War
Limited"--e.g., "I won't use gas if you won't."
D. "Don't destroy your opponent's command, control,
communications, and intelligence (C3I)"--otherwise they
can't observe your restraint or make peace with you. See an old science fiction novel, Berserker, on this danger. 
III. CAUSES OF WAR AS CAUSES OF ESCALATION 
A. First-strike advantages. When these exist, wars
1. Start at an intense level. Cf. the 1941 Japanese
attack on the U.S.; the 1941 German attack on the 
USSR; and the 1967 Arab-Israeli war. Compare with the
slow-growing 1939 war in Europe, U.S. in Vietnam.
2. Are fought intensely as each attacks before it is
attacked. 
3. Widen as belligerents preempt neutrals. Cf. the 
German invasion of Norway 1940. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>4. Are harder to stop due to the treachery displayed by a
surprise attack--why should the attacker now be
trusted to keep peace?
B. Large windows--i.e., impending fluctuations in
relative power. When these exist, wars1. Start at an intense level. Cf. World War I, 1941
Pacific War. 
2. Escalate as states jump through windows of opportunity
in wartime. Cf. Hitler's 1940 attack on France, andGermany's 1918 offensive.
3. Widen as neutrals jump in to exploit windows opened by 
war. State A seizes the opportunity to attack state Bwhen B becomes tied down fighting state C.
Note: windows also make war more barbaric. Belligerentsoften massacre POWs and populations because otherwisethey will escape and rejoin the fight. See e.g., the1976 massacre of Tal Zataar in Lebanon. Moreover, suchhorrors make losers fight to the end.
C. False optimism. This makes war 
1. Persist--see e.g., World War I, World War II,
Vietnam. 
2. Escalate--see e.g., Germany's 1917 unlimited
submarine campaign against the U.S.; and Athens'
expedition to Syracuse in the Peloponnesian War, both
fueled by false optimism.
3. Widen. 
D. Cumulative resources. When resources are cumulative 
states struggle to control them for themselves, and to
destroy them, in order to deny them to their opponent.
These two motives drive much wartime destruction. 
E. Offense vs. Defense: Does a strong offense make war
more or less intense? 1914-1918 vs. 1792, 1939. 
IV. WARFIGHTING STRATEGY AND ESCALATION 
A. Do offensive military operations cause or dampen
escalation? Both can happen. The U.S. rush to the Yalu in 1950 sparked escalation. The US invasion of Germanyin 1945 didn't spark chemical use and ended the war.
B. Military operations open windows. Example: France
tempted British Admiral Boscawen's attack on Frenchwarships in 1756 by stripping these ships of guns andusing them as troop transports. A self-opened window. 
V. DOES WAR BEGET MORE INTENSE WAR? IF SO, WHY?
A. War aims may expand in wartime as each side adopts a
darker image of the other's intentions. 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Testing &amp; Applying Theories of War Causation
The Future of War
Solutions to War</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec25-26_futurewar/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>25&#8211;26</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.42 / Causes  and Prevention of War 
Stephen Van Evera 
THE F UTURE O F WAR A ND S OLUTIONS T O WAR 
I. TESTING T HEORI ES OF T HE CAUSES O F WAR WITH T HE CASES C OVERED 
IN TH IS COURSE 
A. Which theories of war perform bes t when tested against history?  To test 
them, evaluate their cross -time, cross -space, and within- case predictions. 
Looking back on cases covered in this class, do you think the case method helps 
us understand the causes of war? 
B. Are there missing theories that should be added to our tool kit? 
II. THE FUTURE OF WAR 
A. The current picture: inter -state wars are few, civil wars are many.  Today's 
20-40 wars (which kill several hundred thousand people each year) are mostly 
civil. 
B. The short term future : 
1. Some important causes of 20th century wars have abated. 
a. Insecurity borne of fear of being attacked and conquered by conventional 
arms has sharply abated with the nuclear revolution. 
b. Militarism has largely faded worldwide, with one major exceptio n: Pakistan. 
c. Historical mythmaking has sharply abated among industrialized 
democracies but not disappeared.  It continues to flourish in the Mideast, 
East Asia, and among extremist religion -driven groups like al -Qaeda. 
d. Democracy has spread, and with it the democratic peace.  Wars stemming 
from the absence of democracy have faded. 
2. Western Europe looks deeply peaceful --an amazing change from 
conditions before 1945.  Those seeking peace should consider how this deep peace in Europe was created, and how it might be replicated elsewhere. 
3. Possible future interstate conflicts include: 
a. Wars of WMD counter- proliferation and counterterror.  These wars would 
reprise the U.S. wars against Iraq (2003 -2011) and in Afghanistan (2001 -). 
Possibilities: U.S. w ars against North Korea, or Iran if the Iran nuclear deal 
unravels, or military action to seize Pakistan's nuclear weapons if they seem insecure, or more war against al Qaeda and its affiliates in Pakistan and elsewhere, or more war against ISIS if it resurges.  In such wars the U.S. would seek to de- fang rising WMD states and destroy movements that 
aspire to WMD terror before they unleash great horrors on the world. New developments that raise this specter: i. The rise of terrorists with ambitions to use WMD.  Before 1990 
scholars of terror argued that "terrorists want a lot a people watching, not a lot of people dead."  Aum Shinrikyo, Al Qaeda and ISIS want a lot of people dead.  The rise of millennarian religious thinking around the world raises the danger that more groups 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>seeking to end the world for religious reasons will appear. 
ii. The rise of skilled terrorists capable of acquiring and using weapons 
of mass destruction.  Before 9/11/2001 it was widely assumed that 
any terrorists crazy enough to want to commit vast murder would be too incompetent to pull it off.  But on 9/11 Al Qaeda displayed impressive skills.  They have since lost capacity under Western counter -attack.   Can they regain it?  Could other terrorist 
organizations? 
iii. The sharply fal ling cost of WMD.  Building them is markedly cheaper 
than it once was. 
iv. Nuclear materials remains vulnerable to theft or sale in Pakistan and 
in research reactors around the world. 
v. Is the global nuclear nonproliferation regime fraying?  In the 199 0s 
proliferation was rolled back.  Ukraine, Belarus, Kazakhstan, and South Africa gave up nuclear weapons, and Brazil and Argentina dropped nuclear programs.   Earlier Taiwan and South Korea dropped their nuclear weapons programs.  Then North Korea and Iran sprouted nuclear weapons programs (bad sign).  Then Iran 
agreed to drop its nuclear weapons program under US/Chinese/Russian/EU pressure (good sign).  Then the U.S. abrogated the agreement (bad sign).  The overall trend line is unclear. 
b. Wars of nation alism.  Conflicts fueled by nationalism are especially 
dangerous! i. Russia vs. Ukraine.  Russia sees a possible NATO presence in Ukraine 
or Georgia as a threat to its security.  Hence in 2014 it answered 
US/EU efforts to incorporate Ukraine into the EU/ NATO orbit by 
moving to detach Ukraine's Russian- speaking areas and by 
generally disrupting Ukraine.  This sparked warfare that could 
escalate. 
ii. Israel -Arab: Jewish vs. Palestinian nationalism.  This conflict is quiet 
now but will explode again if it is not resolved. 
iii. China vs. Taiwan.  Ingredients: 
&gt; China's rising nationalism, which includes a claim to Taiwan, and 
to the South China Sea. 
&gt; U.S. underestimation of this Chinese nationalism, leading the U.S. 
not to accommodate it. 
&gt; During the 2000s Taiwan's lobby in Washington pushed for a U.S. 
unconditional guarantee to Taiwan.  Should this pressure recur, and the U.S. acquiesce to it, Taiwan could take belligerent action that sparks war, such as declaring independence.  (This risk abated after the reckless Taiwanese nationalist Chen Shui -bian 
left Taiwan's presidency in 2008.) 
&gt; A desire for a cold war with China in some U.S. circles. 
c. Wars of religion.  The demon of hateful or aggressive religion is again loose 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>3. Would U.S. nuclear superiority (a first -strike capability ) against all other 
states promote peace or war?  A U.S. first- strike capability is quietly favored 
as a solution to war by proponents of U.S. hegemony.  Is it a solution to war? 
("It will deter rogue states from starting wars and discourage rogues from seeking nuclear weapons.")  Or a cause of war?  ("It will provoke an arms race 
and a cold war, perhaps even a hot war, between the U.S. and Russia and the U.S. and China.") 
A closely related question: would U.S. national missile defense (NMD) cause 
peace or war?  NMD would contribute to a U.S. first -strike capability, so its 
effects should likely be judged by the effects that a first- strike capability would 
have. 
B. Build International Institutes to enforce peace. 
1. World Government.  An old -time favorite solution. 
2. Collective Security.  Another popular solution.  Skeptics note that it's 
already been tried with the League of Nations 1919 -1939.  Why did it fail? 
3. A Concert System, similar to the 1815 Concert of Europe.  It worked in 1815, 
but failed wh en tried again in 1945 with the UN. 
C. Disarmament.  A popular solution with serious shortcomings.  (We've talked 
about them--see our early classes on arms and war.) 
D. Arms control --specifically, tighter controls on the spread of weapons of 
mass destruction.  Can this prevent wars of counter -proliferation?  Can the world 
be persuaded to accept a WMD monopoly by the current WMD powers?  If so how? 
E. National perceptual engineering; and/or Values engineering. 
&gt; "Amnesia International."  Create institutions that track and oppose 
historical mythmaking, especially myths of the more poisonous kind. Replicate globally the work of the Eckert Institute (a.k.a. the Brunswick 
Schoolbook Institute). 
Much human hate stems from historical myths, especially myths of 
victimhood.  Can we dampen hatred by dampening these myths? 
&gt; Create institutions that track and oppose other war -causing ideas, and 
"name and shame" those who purvey these ideas.  For example these 
institutions might expose and oppose cults of the off ensive, "war is fun" 
concepts, and exaggerations of others' hostility.  They might expose aggressive states and movements and warn others against appeasing them. They might raise consciousness about global warming.  Is this worth considering? &gt; An included idea: expose the pervasiveness and destructiveness of 
ingroup -outgroup thinking in human affairs.  If people understand it better 
they will do it less.  Perhaps wider awareness of the problem would create a self -denying prophecy. 
&gt; Create institutions that name and shame those who use religious 
authority for hate. Such conduct strikes many as perverse but it persists.  Is there a way to delegitimate such conduct? &gt; Create a non -governmental organization (NGO), "Religious Hate Watch," 
to "name and sham e" those who use religious authority for hate. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>industries --against the general interest of the global public.  Concentrated 
interests usually win such fights. 
(2) Solutions to climate change require international cooperation. 
Implementing a carbon tax would require cooperation among the world's 
major states. But governments are bad at cooperation, and bad at solving problems that require cooperation with others. 
(3) The destructive impact of greenhouse gas emissions on the climate is 
delayed until long after the emissions occur. But Americans widely resi st 
spending public money to solve problems that do not yet hurt.  The rule is: "We will act when we feel pain."  Problem: by the time we feel pain it will be too late. 
(4) Western ethical traditions do not emphasize moral duties to future 
generations. (Contrast with the Iroquois, whose General Law requires that we 
consider the effects of our actions down to the seventh generation).  Instead our ethics assume that each generation must solve its own problems.  Hence we see little duty to sacrifice to preserve the world for future generations. Watch out grandchildren!  We live for ourselves, not for you! 
(5) The climate change danger has no direct analogies in human history. 
Humans often think analogically; so, seeing no analogies to the danger, people dismiss it.  (Usefully discussing close analogies is Jared Diamond, Collapse ). 
(6) The climate change danger does not have a primordial signature.  It 
presents no big teeth, big eyes, gushing blood, fire, or roaring large -animal 
noises.  Humans over -respond to dangers with such primordial signatures, 
but under -respond to slow -rising dangers that lack them, like climate change. 
(7) The climate science community does not understand how to use/does not 
like to use public relations techniques to make its findings known to publics. 
But such techniques are necessary to reach global publics. 
Bottom line: climate change has a clear solution but the human race is 
probably incapable of implementing that solution.  Oh dear! 
III. SOLUTIONS TO WAR 
A. Hegemon ic America.  The USA polices the world, preventing or stopping 
wars, promoting democracy (which in turn promotes peace), and enforcing non-proliferation of WMD.  Pax Americana.  Good idea? 1. Would it work?  Would the USA prevent more wars than it caused? 
a. Does the U.S. have the needed power?  Some say U.S. hegemony is 
infeasible. 
b. Does the U.S. have the needed wisdom?  Some say the U.S. will cause more 
trouble than it cures by imposing its will on the world.  It will spiral with others.  The threat of U.S. power will provoke others to acquire WMD, instead of deterring them from acquiring WMD.  (Some argue this is happening now with North Korea and Iran.) 
2. Would such policing serve U.S. interests?  Some say faraway wars don't do 
much injury to the U.S. Others note that wars tend to spread engulf others, including the USA; and spark dangerous WMD proliferation and nurture terror networks.  So the U.S. would serve itself well by imposing peace. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>in the world.  In recent times we'v e seen horrific religion -fueled civil wars 
in Sudan (1983- 2005) and in Algeria (1991 -2002).  The 1980- 88 Iran -Iraq 
war, the 1991- 1995 Serb -Croat -Bosniak war, and the current civil wars in 
Iraq, Syria and Yemen have large religious dimensions.  The India -
Pakistan conflict has a large religious dimension.  The Israel -Palestinian 
conflict has a growing religious dimension.  Al Qaeda and ISIS are religion-
based terror movements. What conflicts will the future see?  Some possibilities. i. Religion -based Wars o f Civilization, as Samuel Huntington fears.  The 
biggest current fear: a conflict between the West and the Islamic world.  Bin Laden wanted to trigger such a war.  Will the West be so foolish as to help al -Qaeda start it? 
ii. More Israel -Arab and India -Pakistan conflict. 
iii. Sunni -Shi'a wars in the Mideast, e.g., as in Iraq, Syria, Yemen. 
iv. Muslim -Christian conflict in Egypt? 
d. Wars of geopolitics and security. 
i. China vs. U.S. cold war or hot war: the world's top two states again 
clash for global power.  Perhaps sparked by conflict over Taiwan, or the South China Sea, or control of North Korea. 
ii. China vs. India, Russia, and Japan as China rises and they move to 
contain it. 
C. The long term future: 
1. Kaysen vs. "Factor 'X'."  Material reasons f or war are declining but war itself 
may not be.  Why is this? 
2. Will WMD technology continue to proliferate? The march of technology 
seems to make this inevitable.  In one view bioweapons are becoming much 
more lethal than before.  Defenses against bioweapons are also advancing, 
but more slowly, so the forces of destruction are outrunning impediments to them.  Where will this end? 
Is science inventing a version of Kurt Vonnegut's "ice nine" --a very 
destructive technology for which we are politically, s ocially and morally 
unready?  Crispr -cas9, anyone? If so, will this ice nine someday be acquired by 
nihilistic groups or individuals and used against civilization?  And will our fear of an ice nine and our efforts to contain it spawn wars of counter -proli feration? 
3. Resource wars and wars of environmental calamity?  Under some 
scenarios climate change could make hundreds of millions of people homeless and destroy whole countries.  Will these refugees use force to compel compensation or gain vengeance?  Food supplies will shrink as agricultural yields diminish.  Will this unleash global conflict to control food supplies? 
An obvious response: let's halt climate change.  But can it be stopped?  Coal 
and oil can be replaced by new green energy technologies at modest cost--less than 1 percent of gross world product per year --by instituting a global 
carbon tax.  But these problems make it unlikely that governments will act: 
(1) Climate change pits a concentrated special interest--the oil and coal 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>&gt; Persuade organized religions to create truth commissions that would 
record the wrongs committed by the religion in the past, express 
contrition for these wrongs, and create institutions [religious rituals] to 
purvey and sustain memory of the wrong among the flock. 
&gt; Should religions be asked to temper or abandon teachings that they are 
the only way to God?  Christian gospels teach that "those who do not believe will be condemned" (Jesus in Mark 16:16) and t hat "I am the way; ... 
no one comes to the Father except by me" (Jesus in John 14:6).  Muslim scripture teaches that "the basest creatures in the sight of God are the faithless who will not believe" (God in The Koran , 8:55).  Such claims lead 
those who make them to view people who believe differently with contempt and to claim superior rights above them.  This causes conflict and violence between religious communities and toward unbelievers --
conflicts that bring religion itself into disrepute.
1 Perhaps thi s situation 
requires a movement of religious reinterpretation. 
F. Global values engineering.  Can war someday be delegitimated, perhaps by 
the work of religious institutions, much as child sacrifice, slavery and duelling have now been delegitimated worldwide?  Can we all learn to be better people? 
G. Be evaluative units yourselves!  You can be part of the answer. 
1 Maureen Dowd reports that after the 9/11/01 al -Qaeda attacks a wall 
graffiti appeared in Washington, DC that expressed such thinking: "Dear 
God, please save us from the people who believe in you." 
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Misperception and War; Religion and War</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-42-causes-and-prevention-of-war-spring-2018/resources/mit17_42s18_lec4-7_mispercept/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4&#8211;7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>commissions that would record the wrongs committed by the 
religion in the past, offer contrition, and create institutions (religious rituals) to sustain memory of the wrong among the flock.
 Another idea, from Sam Harris, End of Faith: abolish religion. 
Will this happen any time soon? (Hint: no.) Would it be a good thing? 
VII. HYPOTHESES FROM ORGANIZATION THEORY #3: BARRIERS TO ANALYSIS--
NON-SELF EVALUATION AND NON-STRATEGY 
A. "Non-self-evaluation" by states and societies: "The wish of the 
powerful to stifle criticism leads societies to punish those who evaluate dominant policies and ideas; hence evaluation is scarce and inferior." ("National Auto-lobotomization"? :)) Relevant works: Irving Janis, Groupthink; Aaron Wildavsky, "The Self-Evaluating Organization." 1. Non-evaluation in government bureaucracy: two explanations. 
a. The "groupthink" hypothesis, offered by Irving Janis. b. The "punishment of evaluators" hypothesis. c. Examples of "punishment" hypothesis. Robert Fitzgerald 
was fired for exposing huge cost overruns on the C5A aircraft in the early 1970s. Billy Mitchell was fired for demonstrating the effectiveness of airpower at sea. The U.S. "China hands" were fired in the U.S. in the late 1940s and early 1950s for speaking truths about China's Chiang Kai Shek regime. Saddam Hussein murdered anyone who brought him bad news. In 1941 the Japanese government punished the analyst who warned superiors that the U.S. had ten times Japan's industrial power. J. Colin, who argued against unduly offensive military doctrines in France before 1914, was hounded out of the French army for his heresy. 
d. Motives for punishing/expunging evaluators: the clash 
between requirements of sound policy formulation and sound policy implementation. Dissenters make policy implementation difficult, so they are purged in advance. This injures policy formulation. 
2. Non-evaluation in the press and academe. See, e.g., Robert 
Lynd, Knowledge for What? German scholars were "fleet professors" who evangelized for Germany's unwise naval buildup before 1914. Honest historians such as Hermann Kantorowicz and Eckert Kehr were hounded out of Germany after 1918 for telling the truth about World War I. Fritz Fischer was attacked in the 1960s for truth-telling about World War I. 
3. What motivates press and scholarly non-evaluation? The 
press believes its job is to report, not to evaluate. The press also fears alienating the official sources on which it often depends for information; and it wants to please its audience so they will buy its product, so it tells them what they want to hear even if it ain't true. Scholars do little evaluation from fear of retaliation from those evaluated, and from disbelief that evaluation is their job. They often think they don't owe evaluation to society, and instead deem themselves free to ask irrelevant questions whose answers interest only themselves. 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>10. Evangelizing by religions causes conflict between the 
evangelizing religion and target religious communities who 
see evangelism as aggression. (Christianity is notably evangelical.) 
11. Religions that adopt chauvinist narratives about themselves 
(to include undue claims of their own goodness toward others and of their own innocence of wrongdoing toward others--"We have brought great goodness to others, and nothing else! We have never wronged others!") are more aggressive. They have a sense that their greater virtue entitles them to dominate others, and their unawareness of their own past wrongdoing leaves their hubris undampened by the humility that comes with awareness of one's own past or present injustices to others. For example, most Christians have little sense of the cruelties committed by Christian majorities against the Jewish minority in Europe over the past thousand years.
3
 Do religions need truth commissions? 
12. Religions that adopt victim narratives ("We are oppressed! 
We have always been oppressed! We are always right because we are always victims!") feel release from the duty to behave ethically and have a related sense of total entitlement. Hence they are more likely to commit mass murder. For example, radical Islamist thinking since 1900 has a strong victim narrative. Such thinking is also growing among U.S. Christian conservative religious believers, who complain of being oppressed by an anti-Christian secular American society--despite the flourishing of religion in the U.S. 
13. Threatened religions become aggressive. Example: 
backlashing fundamentalist movements that feel threatened by secular culture. (See an MIT Ph.D. thesis by Heather Gregg on this idea; and David Kertzer. The Popes against the Jews, on the enlightenment-fearing papacy.) 
14. Status reversal: religious communities that once dominated 
but then fell to inferiority are prone to violence, as status reversal is a powerful general spur to human violence. For example, some people argue that Islamic extremism is a response to the decline of power of the Muslim world relative to the West since 1683. 
15. Religious faiths that claim exclusivity--to be the only 
valid faith, the only path to heaven, the only way to God--are more aggressive toward others as they hold other faiths in implicit contempt. Christianity is quite exclusivist.
4 
Hinduism and Buddhism are less exclusivist--Hinduism probably because it is polytheist (see below), Buddhism because its followers do not worship God. Judaism is also less exclusivist, as it accepts that non-Jews can be 
3 The best account is James Carroll, Constantine's Sword: 
The Church and the Jews (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 2001). See also the film Constantine's Sword. 
4 To support the exclusivist view some Christians quote the 
gospels of Mark and John: "Those who do not believe will be condemned" (Jesus in Mark 16:16); and "I am the way; ... no one comes to the Father except by me" (Jesus in John 14:6). 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>bring about the end of the world!") Every major faith 
includes millennialist sub-groups.2 E.g., In the U.S. 
roughly 25 million Christians follow the premillennial dispensationalism of John Nelson Darby and Tim LaHaye. But what causes millennialism? A doctrinal focus on the afterlife instead of this life? Or what? This suggests ... 
5. Religious dogma that includes belief in an afterlife causes 
millenarianism. Many faiths include belief in afterlife but some--most notably Buddhists and Jews--downplay it. 
A contrary thought: belief in an afterlife creates an 
incentive to do the right thing while on earth, from fear of punishment in the afterlife, a la Ebenezer Scrooge, who hears Jacob Marley's warning from beyond the grave. If so, followers of faiths that require peacefulness will behave better if they believe in an afterlife. 
6. Illegitimacy--a "diversionary religious war" theory: 
religious elites that are losing their legitimacy seek to win support for themselves by demonizing outsiders as threats, and seeking conflict with those outsiders. A possible example is Christianity of the Middle Ages, which demonized Jews and Muslims as it fell into corruption. Also the enlightenment-fearing papacy of 1750-1932. (See David Kertzer, The Popes Against the Jews, 2001). 
7. Highly institutionalized religions with large cash flow need 
to keep cash coming in. Hence they arouse their flocks to contribute by demonizing outsiders, painting them as dark threats to the church. This arouses the flock against outsiders. Christianity in the Middle Ages may illustrate. 
8. Lack of central religious authority (like the Islamic 
Caliphate or Catholic Papacy) leaves a faith open to hijacking by apostles of hate, like Osama Bin Laden, who knew little about Islam but much about sowing hate and killing people. Some offer Islam since the abolition of the Caliphate in 1924 as an example. Is Protestantism since Luther a counter-example? 
9. Debate weeds out extreme ideas. An absence of debate allows 
crazed ideas to thrive because they are unchallenged. Hence crazed religious ideas will thrive in societies that lack a context where religious ideas face debate and challenge. a. A lack of democracy can produce the stifling of free 
debate of any kind in society. This allows extreme religious ideas go unchallenged, hence to thrive. Thus hateful Wahhabism has flourished without challenge in authoritarian Saudi Arabia. Perhaps it would have moderated under greater challenge in a democratic Saudi Arabia. But ... 
b. Excessive religious tolerance in the wider society ("no 
religion can be questioned or challenged!") can allow extreme religious ideas go unchallenged and undebated, allowing hatred to fester and grow. Thus the murderous Buddhist cult Aum Shinrikyo flourished in Japan partly because it went unchallenged. 
2 Daniel Benjamin and Steven Simon, Age of Sacred Terror, 
chapter 12 ("A World of Terror"). 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>and draftees' time. They must justify these demands. 
-- Militaries have natural political opponents, such as 
peace groups and pacific religious organizations, who 
have qualms about the military's task and must be countered. 
-- Military officers have only one potential employer, 
the military establishment, hence they are especially concerned about its welfare. 
b. Professional militaries have persuasive power because 
they have: -- A monopoly of information and expertise. -- A monolithic internal character, a hierarchic internal 
structure, and high esprit de corps. 
-- A large work force. -- Great prestige. See S.E. Finer, Man on Horseback, for more discussion. 
5. What misperceptions do militaries sometimes purvey? 
(Debating this: Samuel Huntington and Richard Betts vs. Bernard Brodie, Martin Kitchen.) a. "Others are hostile"--others' hostility is exaggerated. 
See for example the German military before 1914, the Soviet cold war military, today's Pakistani military. 
b. "Bandwagoning is common, threats make others more 
compliant." Cf. Wilhelmine (pre-1914) Germany's Admiral Tirpitz's risk theory, and Wilhelmine Germany's General Bernhardi. &gt; In fact great powers balance much more than they 
bandwagon. 
c. "Conquest is Easy." Cf. European armies, 1914; European 
air forces, 1930s; the Soviet Strategic Rocket Forces, 1950-1980s. Two arguments are made: a. "Conquest is easy." 
b. "Offensive military force postures and doctrines are better than defensive postures and doctrines." 
d. "Striking first pays off." Cf. militaries of France and 
Russia, 1914; Japan 1941, Soviet Union cold war era. 
e. "Windows are common and large." Cf. German and Austrian 
armies, 1914; British Navy 1898--"the French are rising, let's attack them while we can!"; French and Prussian armies, 1867; U.S. Generals Power and Twining, 1950s. 
f. "Empires are valuable, resources are cumulative." Cf. 
U.S. Admiral A.T. Mahan; Prussian army, 1871. 
g. "War is cheap, healthy, beneficial." Cf. European 
militaries, 1914; U.S. Gen. Daniel Graham 1979. 
h. Optimism in wartime--cf. Japanese military in WWII--but 
not peacetime. 
i. "Escalation is the answer" in wartime. Cf. German 
military 1917; US military in Korea, Vietnam. 
6. In militarized states militaries may come to believe their own propaganda, and hence advocate war. If so the militaries of militarized states may be more hawkish. 1914 Germany and 1937 Japan may illustrate. 
7. What states are prone to "militarism?" Big states; isolated states; insecure states; states whose militaries form a separate society. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>often harsh ethics. There is less room for later moderates 
to put a humanizing gloss on the founding dogma. Examples might include Muslims who quote as live scripture the "sword verses" of the Koran; Jews who quote the Covenant passages of Genesis and Exodus as giving Jews title to vast Arab lands; Jews and Christians who take the harsher teachings of Leviticus and Deuteronomy as literal truth; and Christians who quote anti-Jewish scripture (e.g., the Matthew passion scene) and other cruel scripture ("slaves, obey your masters!") from the New Testament. In such religions it is also easier for later hardline philosophers to reject the humanizing spin of post-founding philosophers and revert to the harsh founding text. Examples include ibn Taymiyya, ibn Abdul Wahhab, Sayyid Qutb, and other Islamists who reject the humanizing gloss of post-Muhammed Islamic philosophers such as the Mutazilites.
 This theory assumes that later philosophers in most 
religions tend to be more humanistic than their predecessors. (Examples might include the Jewish rabbinic movement that authored the Talmud; and the Jesus movement, which moderated the Jewish purity laws.) Where this is untrue the theory will fail.
 Scriptural inerrancy combined with cherry-picking my 
hateful demagogues is a worst case scenario. The flock is taught that every word is true, but taught only the hateful words. Teachings to "love your neighbor as yourself" and "be compassionate as your father is compassionate" are omitted. 
3. Religious faiths born in conflict tend to have original 
religious texts that are xenophobic and/or call for violence. Violence ensues if those texts are still quoted. Possible illustrations include: &gt; Islam from Mohammed's time, or from ibn Taymiyya's--
colored by the violence in which Islam was born, and by the violence of ibn Taymiyya's times. 
&gt; The contrast between tolerant sections of the Koran that 
were written in peaceful Mecca and more belligerent sections that were written in wartime Medina. 
&gt; Perhaps the Old Testament/Tanakh, especially the violent 
sections of Numbers, Leviticus, Deuteronomy and Joshua, if one believes that the early Israelites fought their way into Judea/Samaria (some historians are skeptical of this). 
&gt; A counter-example is Mennonite Christianity, which was 
born in warfare and developed an embedded pacifism in response. 
Corollary: secessionist or supersessionist religions tend to develop scriptures that are hostile to the religions from which they secede or which they attempt to supersede. Examples: the anti-Jewish barbs in the New Testament;
1 and 
the anti-Jewish and anti-Christian barbs in the Koran. 
4. Millennialism--the belief that the end times are coming, 
salvation will follow--causes globacidal thinking ("let's 
Marcus Borg, The Heart of Christianity: 196, 215-16. 
61</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>exaggerate the similarities they share with ingroup members and 
exaggerate differences with the outgroup. They create false narratives that exaggerate the virtues of their ingroup and the shortcomings of the outgroup. They favor the ingroup over the outgroup. Loyalties to one's nation, race or religion may illustrate; also loyalties to colleges and sports teams; also middle school cliques. 
IV. HYPOTHESES FROM ORGANIZATION THEORY #1: MILITARIES OR OTHER 
GOVT. BUREAUCRACIES AND PRIVATE ORGANIZATIONS AS THE SOURCES OF ELITE AND PUBLIC MISPERCEPTION 
Prefatory note: propaganda is self-concealing, hence hard to observe and hard to study. Nevertheless we must study it. A. Organization theory. 
1. Organization theory posits that large organizations have 
souls and goals of their own, distinct from the souls and goals of the humans who comprise them. Often their conduct is harmful or pathological. 
2. Six hypotheses from organization theory: 
a, b, c, d: Organizations want size and wealth, conservation of their "essence," autonomy, and minimal uncertainty in their task environment. d. Organizations infuse their work force with myths that 
exaggerate the goodness of the organization, in order to motivate the work force. e. Organizations deter or destroy sub-units that are tasked 
with evaluating the performance of individuals or units within the organization. 
B. "Militarism." 
1. Militarism theories were largely inferred from World War I. 2. Two militarism theories: 
a. "Militaries live by war so they cause war." Suggested by 
Joseph Schumpeter, Richard Cobden, Alexis de Tocqueville, and others. Historical facts give this version little support. 
b. "Militaries infuse civilian society with organizationally 
self-serving ideas that lead civilians to start wars. Militaries do this to preserve/protect their organizational interests." The professional military and associated agencies and industries as causes of misperception. See Jack Snyder, Myths of Empire. i. Prime examples: Germany before 1914 and Japan in the 1930s and 1940s. Also Serbia, Austria, and the Ottoman empire before 1914; and Pakistan today. 
ii. Counter-example: Germany since 1945; the US since 1985. 
iii. This theory does not cover many, even most, 
militaries. Can it still be useful? 
3. Organization theory relevant here: organizations want size &amp; 
wealth, conservation of "essence," autonomy, minimal uncertainty. 
4. Arguments about why some militaries are willful and powerful 
actors--why they want to shape national perceptions, and why they can. a. Professional militaries are willful because: 
-- Militaries demand a lot from society--lots of money, 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>8. How could the militarism hypothesis be tested? What 
predictions does it make? Does history seem to confirm or infirm them? 
The U.S. military was markedly more dovish than U.S. 
civilian policymakers during ~1980-2003. E.g., General Colin Powell and Admiral William Crowe were markedly more dovish than Paul Wolfowitz or Richard Perle. Does this discredit this theory? 
C. Other domestic organizations: the foreign policy bureaucracy; 
foreign lobbies (the China Lobby, the Egestaens); businesses (Gov. Dinwiddie in 1756; United Fruit Company in 1954); etc. 
V. HYPOTHESES FROM ORGANIZATION THEORY #2: NATIONAL MYTHMAKING 
States, ethnic groups, and other entities (businesses, universities, sports teams) manufacture self-glorifying, self-whitewashing and other-maligning myths and infuse these into their members. 
A. Nationalism and nationalist mythmaking in education--"value 
infusion" and what might be called the "non-guilt complex"--ideas from Philip Selznick, Carleton Hayes. "Elites seek to persuade publics to support the regime, pay taxes and join the army by purveying myths that glorify state and national institutions." 1. Why are myths purveyed and believed? 
a. Myths are purveyed to make citizens contribute to the 
nation--pay taxes, join the army, etc.; and to bolster the political power of illegitimate elites. 
b. Myths are often believed because they play to ingroup-
outgroup reflexes. We are hard-wired to think in self-glorying and other-denigrating terms (claim ingroup-outgroup theorists, e.g., Sherif and Sherif). It feels great to wallow in self-glorying pap! These are strong forces, hence mythmaking is common, though not universal. 
2. Three types of myth about the past: 
a. Self-glorifying myths--"we're brilliant, ingenious, 
chosen by God. We invented all the world's better mousetraps!" The Soviet government claimed that Soviets invented the lightbulb, airplane, and railroad. Hindu nationalists claim civilization started with the Hindus; Turks say the same; etc. 
b. Self-whitewashing myths--"we've started no wars, 
committed no crimes!" E.g., Germans in 1920s ("we didn't start WWI--Britain did!"); Turkish denial of Turkey's 1895 and 1915 mass-murder of Armenians; Soviet denial of responsibility for Cuban Missile Crisis (they called it "The Caribbean Crisis"); Croatian denial of Croat mass murders during WWII; Arab and Israeli mutual myths of innocence; American forgetting of King Philip's War 1675-1677--few remember this horror; al-Qaeda's narrative of recent history, which omits all crimes of Muslim societies against both Muslims and non-Muslims. 
c. Other-maligning myths--"our neighbors are culturally 
inferior/aggressive/dangerous." Israelis and Arabs both blame the other for a conflict caused by the West. Al Qaeda propaganda paints non-Muslims as rapaciously 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>vicious and aggressive, far beyond what the historical 
record supports. 
3. A short history of mythmaking. 
Chauvinist mythmaking surged in Europe in the 19th century; peaked during 1870-1945; then diminished sharply after 1945. Why? Chauvinist mythmaking remains common outside Europe today. 
B. Myths about the present: Some allege (with George Orwell) that 
governments purvey "diversionary war" myths, a.k.a. "social imperial" myths--"our neighbors are out to get us, so you better back the government!"--to bolster support for the regime. 
C. Do chauvinist myths cause war? Or are they just excuses for 
making war? 
Myths cause conflict by convincing the two sides that they 
have large legitimate historical grievances against the other that justify large claims; that the other side has malign intent; and that the other side views them with contempt. 
In extreme cases myths foster victim ideologies that give 
the myth-believers a sense of release from the duty to obey normal ethics. Groups that wallow in victim ideologies can believe that "We are the victims and so are always right! Don't ask us to respect others' rights--that would be blaming the victim!" Many groups with this mindset have committed great crimes (e.g., the Germans 1933-1945, Croats in the 1990s, Serbs in 1990s. China today?). 
How could we test the "chauvinist myths cause war" 
hypothesis? 
D. Can nationalist myths be cured? If so, how? (Start "Amnesia 
International"--an NGO dedicated to naming and shaming mythmakers?) 
VI. RELIGION AND WAR 
A. Scholarship on the causes of religious conflict is thin. 
Scholars have avoided touchy issues, such as "Are some religions more violent than others?" Hence we understand the nexus between religion and war only poorly. A serious omission. 
B. Religious difference was a common cause of war before the 20th 
century. It then faded as a cause of war until recent times. Now it's back! We see chauvinist or violent religious movements in Islam, Judaism, Hinduism, Christianity, and even Buddhism. 
C. Preliminary hypotheses: 
1. Scriptural inerrancy--a belief that holy texts are the 
literal word of God, hence inerrant--makes compromise on religion-related matters impossible, as this would compromise God's will. Without compromise we see greater conflict as literalists insist on getting their way. 
2. Scriptural inerrancy--a belief that holy texts are the 
literal word of God, hence inerrant--leaves little room for interpretation of scripture, hence little room for humanist religious philosophers to spin belligerent or xenophobic religious texts in benign directions or to decommission hateful scripture. This gives a more belligerent content to religious faith. The faith is frozen with its original, 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>evil, others are evil." Sometimes included are claims that 
cult leaders are divine, or in touch with the divine. 
VIII. THE "SPIRAL MODEL" VERSUS "DETERRENCE" (OR THE "DETERRENCE 
MODEL"): CHOOSING BETWEEN HARD-LINE POLICIES AND APPEASEMENT, AND THE DANGERS THAT FOLLOW FROM WRONG CHOICES 
A. Defining the spiral model and the deterrence model. B. Explaining spirals: 
1. Can psychological dynamics explain spirals? (See IIIA, 
IIIB above). 
2. Can nationalist mythmaking explain spirals? 
C. What conditions determine whether carrots or sticks work 
better? 1. Is the other an aggressor state or a status quo power? 
(And: does it see itself as the aggressor or not?) 
2. Are the other's claims legitimate or illegitimate? (And: 
does it see its claims as legitimate or not?) 
3. Does the other understand that threats or punishments 
directed at it are conditional on its bad conduct, and will be withheld if it behaves well? 
4. Is the other weak or strong? 5. Will the concessions demanded by the other strengthen its 
ability to commit further aggression? 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
17.42 Causes and Prevention of War 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>4. Results: consider the many follies and folly-makers lionized 
by their peoples. Napoleon led France to ruin but is still 
fawned over by the French. General Eric von Ludendorff led Germany to ruin but was later honored by the Germans. The German Schlieffen plan of 1914 was a folly that was not assessed until 1956. Austro-Hungarian General Conrad von Htzendorf was a World War I blunderer who was not criticized within Austria until decades after World War I. 
5. Solutions: pass whistle-blower protection laws? (It's been 
done.) Give job tenure to policy evaluators and whistle-blowers? (That's been done too. University professors are supposed to be policy evaluators, and have tenure, but many waste their freedom writing on questions of little importance.) Instill better ethics in those who are supposed to evaluate? Support democratization? Democracies must protect free speech, and evaluation is easier when free speech is guaranteed. (But clearly democracy, while probably necessary, is insufficient to empower evaluators.) 
6. Related ideas: "speaking truth to power"--something often 
lauded, because it is both valuable and dangerous. "Concentrated interests nearly always defeat the common interest" (Beth Rogers): Why? Because concentrated interests can effectively defeat evaluation. 
B. "Non-strategy": "States tend to leave national grand strategy 
and basic foreign policy vague or fail to frame it at all." Results: -- Less learning.  E.g., U.S. policy in Asia didn't learn and 
adjust following the Sino-Soviet split in the 1960s. 
-- Less storing of knowledge.  E.g., by 1965 the U.S. forgot 
what it learned about Vietnam in 1954. 
-- Explaining is more difficult.  E.g., Britain failed to 
explain its policy to Germany before 1939, hence Hitler miscalculated. 
C. Control cults as causes of misperception. Bolshevism, extreme 
Islamism, North Korean communism, the Moonies, the Heaven's Gate cult, and other religious cults may illustrate. Control cults are groups that venerate or worship a person or entity of some sort; and that separate their followers from the outside world, propagandize them, and include in that propaganda paranoid and chauvinist messages. Control cult leaders can be coercive, even terroristic, toward members in enforcing isolation, stifling dissent and free thought. The cult comprises an entire social community and forms the only society enjoyed by its members. 
Points about cults: (1) The ideas of members are controlled 
in order to maintain loyalty, discipline, and esprit de corps. (2) This control is established by (a) isolating members from the outside world--a task achieved by enforcing members' isolation and by providing members with a comprehensive internal community to replace their social ties with the external community; (b) propagandizing members heavily, (c) stifling dissent among members, usually by coercion, and (d) sometimes keeping members too busy to think, dissent, or organize. (3) The content of the propaganda aimed at members stresses paranoid and chauvinist messages: "We are threatened, we are victims, we are superior, we are saving the world from 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>righteous if they follow the seven Noahide laws, which 
forbid murder, theft, blasphemy and other misdeeds.5 And 
mainstream Islam is less exclusivist, as it accepts that Jews and Christians that behave righteously "shall be rewarded by their Lord; they have nothing to fear or to regret."
6 
16. Monotheism causes conflict. Unlike polytheists, monotheists 
reject the notion of more than one legitimate God. Hence they are more inclined to reject the notion that more than one faith is legitimate.
 Behind these hypotheses is the argument that religious hate 
ideologies are more dangerous than other hate ideologies because their adherents assume they act with God's moral authority, to fulfil God's will. This provides followers with a moral release 
from normal ethics; and the promise of large rewards of God's approval, to include admission to paradise in the hereafter. 
Hence followers observe less restraint in conflicts with others while pursuing them with more energy. Hence a religious hate idea is dangerous to a special, extra degree. See Scott Appleby's work on this argument.
 Consider also the opposite important proposition: "Religion is 
a cause of peace. Most of the world's great religions proscribe killing and emphasize the value of human life. This inhibits war."
 A case to consider: Christian premillennial dispensationalism. 
Its violent worldview is found the best-selling Left Behind book series by Tim F. LaHaye and Jerry B. Jenkins.
7
 How to address religious hatred? One idea: start "Religious Hate Watch," an NGO that names and 
shames those who use religious authority--God's authority or the authority of one's faith--to sow hatred and stir violence; and calls on all religions to decommission their hate scripture. Would this be effective?
 Another idea: persuade organized religions to create truth 
5 Rabbi Joseph Telushkin, Jewish Literacy: The Most 
Important Things to Know About the Jewish Religion, Its People, and Its History (New York: William Morrow, 2001): 127, 560-61, 591-92. 
6 God in The Koran: 2:62. Other statements from The Koran 
are more exclusivist. 
7 The last book in the series is Glorious Appearing: The 
End of Days (Wheaton IL: Tyndale House, 2004). It describes a mass-killing Jesus returned to earth, hurling the religiously incorrect into an abyss of everlasting fire: 
"Jesus merely raised one hand a few inches and a yawning chasm opened in the earth, stretching far and wide enough to swallow all of them. They tumbled in, howling and screeching, but their wailing was soon quashed and all was silent when the earth closed itself again." At a mere word from Jesus other unfortunates saw "their own flesh dissolved, their eyes melted and their tongues disintegrated." The landscape was covered with "splayed and filleted bodies of men and women." Quotes from Nicholas D. Kristof, "Jesus and Jihad," New York Times, July 17, 2004. 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>// Causes &amp; Prevention of War 
Stephen Van Evera 
"WHAT WERE THEY THINKING?" NATIONAL MISPERCEPTIONS AS CAUSES OF WAR 
I. HOW COMMON IS MISPERCEPTION? HOW DANGEROUS? 
Sometimes misperceptions prevent war. For example, if states are insecure but don't know it they may refrain from wars they might start if they knew the truth. However, it's more often true that misperceptions raise the risk of war, e.g.: -- Exaggerating or underestimating others' hostility can cause 
war. 
-- Both false optimism (about success in war) or false pessimism 
(about one's ability to defend oneself) can cause war. 
-- Commonly-cited examples of states that caused wars under sway 
of misperception: Germany before World War I and II; Japan before World War II; Italy before World War II; Korean war. 
II. THREE PARADIGMS OF NATIONAL MISPERCEPTION: PSYCHOLOGY, 
OPACITY, COZENOLOGY 
III. HYPOTHESES FROM PSYCHOLOGY. From Jervis 1968, Jervis 1976 
(assigned) and from "Social Psychology of Intergroup 
Relations," International Encyclopedia of Social Sciences. 
A. "Attribution error." States tend to attribute their own 
aggressive behavior to their situation, while attributing others' aggressive behavior to their innate disposition. States therefore see their own nasty conduct as excused by necessity while others' nasty conduct is unprovoked and unjustified. 
B. A related syndrome: states tend to ascribe others' good 
behavior to their own efforts to make the other behave well, and to blame others' bad conduct on the other's innate disposition. (Jervis 1968, hypo #11.) Result: States tend to underestimate their own role in causing others' hostility; hence they exaggerate the immutability of that hostility. 
C. Belief perseverance. States are slow to absorb new realities 
that clash with their leaders' existing beliefs. (Jervis 1968, hypos #1, #2.) 
D. States tend to exaggerate the shared character of information, 
hence to exaggerate the effectiveness of communication. Hence they are unaware of their own and others' misperceptions. (Jervis 1968, hypos #5, #6, #12.) 
E. States tend to infer too much from isolated or unique events, 
and to mis-apply domestic analogies to international politics. 
F. States tend to exaggerate the centralized, disciplined, 
coordinated character of others' behavior. (Jervis 1968, hypo #9.) 
Question: can you think of competing non-psychological explanations for any of these misperceptions (e.g., misperceptions B or C?) G. Hypotheses from in-group-out-group theory (a.k.a. social 
identity theory). Humans have a strong propensity to separate themselves into cohesive and mutually hostile groups. They 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
