<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-484-comparative-grand-strategy-and-military-doctrine-fall-2004/</course_url>
    <course_title>Comparative Grand Strategy and Military Doctrine</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>History </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/17-484-comparative-grand-strategy-and-military-doctrine-fall-2004/resources/milorg_and_war</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-484-comparative-grand-strategy-and-military-doctrine-fall-2004/resources/milorg_and_war/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4
E. The Purpose of Mutual Dest ruction Creates a Special 
Environment  
1. This has the effect, as Cl ausewitz observed of giving 
warfare an inherent compe titive quality far more intense 
than almost any other aspect of social life.  The greater 
the exposure of the state th at a military organization 
servesthe more competitive that military's peacetime 
behavior is likely to be, but as I'll suggest, this does not 
necessarily cause innovation.   
2. The activity itself creates a new environment.  Clausewitz talks about friction and the dearth of good information, often called fog.   
-It is hard to make things happen on the battlefieldeven 
when the adversary is not fighting very hard.   -It is hard to figure out what is going on on the 
battlefield.  Getting useful in formation from the mass of 
impressions and data, often deliberately obstructed by the 
enemy (again due to the competitiveness factor) makes 
the conduct of war a hugely  uncertain activity.   
-Getting information often risks and costs lives and 
machines.   
--Nothing is easy or free. 
3. Within this environment, th ese organizations are in a 
relative sensefragile.  
a) Most modern military orga nizations (not actually 
allguerrillas, or MAD ex cepted ) but most, are 
trying to coordinate the r ational application of a 
range of technologies, e ach of which requires a 
little administrative tail to fix it, fuel it, arm it, 
replace it, as well as  brain, eyes, nervous system.   
A very high level of internal interdependence in modern arms, which has grown since the industrial 
revolution.  Thus the organizations suffer a kind of  
fragile internal interdependence. AND</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2
view.  Purpose is the driver. Functional Specialization of the 
Organization and within it, with an Internal Division of Labor, 
coordinated through a Hierarch ically arranged system of 
Command and Control.  Decision ma de on Rationality criteria, 
cost and benefit. Professionaliza tion of the officials/managers 
with education and developing e xpertise. "Files."  The neutral 
tool.  The living machine.   
1. Weber, one of the earliest st udents of large scale formal 
organizations, bureaucracy, understood that the very 
evolution of bureaucracy was a in part a function of the 
military struggles among the monarchs of Europe,  "War made the state and the state made war."  Bureaucracies 
grew to feed armies, and it' s not an exaggeration to say 
that the professionalization of armies and of bureaucracies occurred hand in hand, each learning from the other. 
2. The over-riding commitment to purpose, and the effort to achieve rationality in pursu it of that purpose make 
uncertainty of any kind an enemy.  Organizations do what they can to reduce uncertainty. 
3. The need to pursue purpose with people, whose rationality is limited, and who in any case are not actually 
going to be perfect cogs in a rational machine, creates special motivation and control problems for 
organizational leaders in their efforts to keep the 
organization focused on the achievement of purpose.  People are a source of uncertainty. 
4. How might a military organi zation's specific purpose 
produce special behaviors or qualities, especially 
qualities that might bear on their ability to innovate? 
B. Military organizations do something unusualthey try to 
destroy one another, directly.  Samuel Huntingtons notion of 
the officer corps as specialists in  the management of violence in 
service to the state does not do it ju stice.  I am not sure that any 
other organization has the explic it purpose of bashing its like to</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>12
WWII, US bombers attack ed US ground forces 
very heavily on several oc casions during the Battle 
of the Bulge,  Desert Storm etc.] 
2. Special, because you need them in the moment of truth 
but you don't have too much influence over them in many militaries and central institutio ns across services are often 
not strong 
3. Each organization has some incentives to get into those aspects of the other's business that affect it the most.  Can 
cause Tension and rivalry, pe rhaps creative, as Harvey 
will argue, but can also cause redundancy, and the over-consumption of scarce resources.   
a) I will not try to answer the perpetual question, do we really need all these air forces in the United 
States, but this basic question did provide the 
impetus for the failed roles and missions commission. 
b) Some of you may remember "air land battle"- IT is striking that as late as Desert Storm, the "air-" part 
seemed pretty under-devel oped, and does to this 
day; the Army seems to still be trying to complete 
the development of the autonomous deep strike capability to destroy the Soviet Second Echelon 
with long range rockets, which the air force never 
quite offered. 
4. On the other hand, cooperative relationships, and divisions of responsibility that  have been negotiated with 
difficulty over many years ma y deter innovation efforts- 
a) When General DePuy was head of TRADOC and 
was working up the much maligned Active 
Defense, he more or less decided that changing the 
Army was hard enough without trying to change the air force, and more or less signed a private 
treaty with the AF saying everything on the other 
side of the FSCL is yours, I hope it all goes well</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>11
E. Comparative WealthMilitaries in  societies that face any kind 
of plausible threat tend to have considerable influence over 
their own situation.  
1. Control great material resources,. Great Powers in particular tend to perceive other great powers as  their Greatest Threats which causes  them to allocate Great 
Resources to their defense, which they have because they are great powers.  Even today,  3% of GDP is a pretty big 
war chest, 
2. They tend to have significan t prestige, which may arise 
from heroic history, conservative political values, or in advanced liberal democratic society simple deference to 
technical expertise.  Although this will vary as well with 
perceived threats to the stat e, history, and constitution. 
3. Significant internal influence, especially on its own issues. Political power if it confines itself to its own issues where it has legitimacy.  Thus very great influence 
over security policyie it affe cts the task it is given.  
And it tries to use that power to minimize its own uncertainties.   
a) Not the same everywhere, US very high, Israel 
probably very high, much of western Europe probably less. 
F. In Most Countries, especially in modern times, there are several 
military organizations, armies, na vies, and air forces but there 
can even be others 
1. Other services in peacetim e and wartime can create 
sizeable interdependencies and thus sizeable sources of uncertainty. 
a) Fratricide for example, between army or navy surface air defenses, and air force aircraft 
b) Fratricide between aircra ft and ground forces. 
[sometimes truly devasta ting, Leslie McNair was 
killed in the Cobra br eakout from Normandy in</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>14
c) Movie, Command Decisions (Le May), 12 o'clock 
high as well 
d) CS Forester, The General  (Haig caricature) 
3. Stalwart troops who trust th eir commanders and rely on 
each other.  
4. Know your weaponie proficiency in the actual 
technical task of using it. 
5. Neither of these have much to  do with tactics, doctrine, 
operational art, or anything  else.  But I advance the 
hypothesis that they are bot h central to the informal 
organization.  Its culture. 
C. To keep them happy you mu st go well beyond utilitarian 
incentives, to solidary and purposive ones.   
1. But war is off on the horizonso some intermediate 
goals, conducive to solid arity are needed.   
2. One source of non-monetary incentives is allegiance to weapons and tactics of the last  glorious episode, "branch" 
or "platform community" (as Owen would say) loyalty.  
[the horse, the tank, the light infantryman with his rifle -
LIDs, the pilot-ed fighter aircraft] 
D. Officer Corpspeculiar kind of profession.   
1. Truly fundamental differen ces between doctors or 
lawyers, vs Officers. Doctors and Lawyers can take 
clients or not.  They have  considerable professional 
mobility.  In some cases they can even change countries.   
2. But not officersparticularly the ones closest to the core 
technology of management of violence.  Officers have one buyerthe government, and they usually cant switch countries.   
3. This produces extremely pow erful utilitarian loyalties to 
the organizationonce you are in, the thought of being 
out is scarey purely on these grounds.  (Forget the</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>10
b) Do we encourage civilians to closely oversee the 
conduct of military operati ons?  You can't prevent 
it if that is what they want  to do, But this threatens 
the organization's core mi ssion, and causes it to 
fight to regain its autonomy, 
(1) Churchill's incessant demands on Dowding for more Fighter squadrons to support 
France in May/June 1940, even though Dowding had tried to explain gently that at some point too few would be left to defend 
Britain, finally an open disagreement in a 
key meetings, Churchill had to cease his requests but he never forgave Dowding. 
c)  It is at this point that the fetish for secrecy to deceive enemies without, becomes a handy 
rationale for fending off meddlers at home.  
(WeberSecrecy is the fighting posture of the bureaucracy.) 
(1) SAC's great effort to keep SIOP information out of the hands of politicians, pentagon 
officials etc. 
(2) General disinclination to  share details of war 
plans with civilians, even Pentagon civilians. 
(3) Old pedigree, some question as to whether the German Foreign Minister, Bethman 
Hollweg understood that the Schlieffen Plan not only called for violation of Belgian 
neutrality, which he proba bly did, but that it 
required a surprise coup de main even 
before German mobilization was complete. 
Thus the FM did not understand that his 
timeline for successful diplomacy was shorter than he thought.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>16
V. Conclusions:  Implications 
A. The more encompassing the Innovation, the harder it should be 
to implement.  The commit ment to big macro-level 
organizational understandings--" Service doctrine," should be 
very great. 
B. Innovations in doctrine and tact ics, should be very hard to 
achieve in peacetime.  Not much  can be proven; few sources 
of pressure.  Much energy a nd capability for resistance to 
external meddlers. 
C. The human organization has a set of values and characteristics 
that help prepare for war in a very general way.  But these 
preferred characteristics are probably not conducive to 
innovation.  1. Loyalty can easil y drift into Conformity.  2.  
Respect for the human values that get you through combat may 
drift into a vaguely unscientif ic attitude 3. Sentimental 
attachment to old branches, arms, etc.may stack the deck 
against new ideas and proposals 
D. Bernard Brodie says, improved weapons should not cause any 
great resistance, it is their implic ations for doctrine, tactics, and 
organization that a military ha s a hard time seeing, (although 
probably a little more technology. resistance than he admits.) 
E. Civilian control, for direct intervention to try to spur 
innovation, or even for  policy infusion into military strategy, 
(Political-Military Integration)  should be difficult, the 
organization has a lot of assets to  resist civilian control, and a 
lot of incentives to do it.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
(1) The campaign in the low countries took the 
Germans about six weeks in 1940 to finish 
off the better half of the French Army.   
(2) A new term was introduced during Desert Storm for the Iraqi army's efforts to avoid US electronic intelligence by the very 
sparing use of their radio communications 
networks: EMCON suicide 
 
b) Often, they are surprisingly dependent on relatively small numbers of high value assets 
(navies especially) and as both sides know this, the 
high value assets get a lot of destructive attention. 
(1) The Israelis destroyed the Egyptian Air Force in a day, the Army in six, in 1967.   
(2) The japanese lost 4 carriers in a day at Midway.   
c) Battle doesnt always, or even often, turn out quite so dramatically.  But these organizations are 
fragile given their taskand they know it. 
d) The knowledge of how quickly and easily things can go very wrong, coupled with great uncertainty about the precise ways it may go wrong, influences 
the organization's day to day behavior, in war, and 
also in time of peace. 
e) Competing businesses, at least the larger ones, 
destroy each other throug h competition over many 
years; 
- to my knowledge, govern ment bureaucracies are 
seldom actually killed off. 
F. There is also a funny, and extr emely scary, gray area, the 
"Transition to Conflict," the mome nt when peace turns into war</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
 
Military Organizations, the Business of War, and what it means for 
Innovation 
I. Introduction: 
Organization theorists often think in term s of the effects of three big factors 
on the behavior of large scale organizationsPurpose; People; and 
Environment.  
A. This discussion is organized around the specifics of military 
purposes, military people, and the environment"combat," domestic, and foreign.   
B. These are tied together by the theme of uncertaintyits sources, and its management.   
1. Mean-Ends, or "cause-effect"  Uncertainty, ie uncertainty 
about how to complete the task in the world 
2. Interdependence Related Uncertainties-  -Internal:  How are my own component parts going to 
work together -External: How will outsiders  upon whom I depend going 
to work with me, or even at cross purposes 
C. How much difference these specifics about  military 
organizations make for considering the behavior of  military organizations relative to to non-m ilitary ones is a fit subject for 
discussion, and comment.:  Much  of organization theory and 
management theory is about larg e scale organizations that are 
similar, but not identical to modern militaries; a lot of 
academics have used organization theory to look directly at 
militaries in one way or another.   
II. Purpose 
A. Like all organizations, in caricatur e, and in the abstract modern 
militaries arrange people for th e mass production of rationality. 
(This may be changing, as I'll di scuss later in the week)  Max 
Webers message.  The classical  administrative-bureaucratic</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
either for the organization as a whole, or even for unblooded 
units in an organization already at war. 
1. Fraught with Uncertainty, given what the organization 
knows in a general way about the course and risks of 
combat, coupled with the fact  that the normal peacetime 
existence of the organizati on, regardless of training 
regimen, is quite different from war. 
2. Examples: 
a) Kasserine Pass for the US Army in WWII 
b) The green 106th division in the Battle of the Bulge 
c) Task force Smith, but really all of the early 
arriving divisions during the first weeks of the 
Korean War 
d) French Army in May of 1940 
3. How do you get your organization intact through this 
transition. 
4. Both the Environment of wa r and the problem of the 
transition to conflict Raise the Question for the 
Organization of How it Prepares/Buffers itself in 
Peacetime. 
5. May produce a very high premium on simplicity, stability, and acceptance of "doc trine; cohesion is a very 
high value 
6. Even if someone could prove, at  the last minute, that the 
doctrine was not quite right, w ould you try to change it?  
An agreed poor doctrine may be preferable to none at all 
to an organization looking forward to an imminent 
transition from the pleasures of garrison life to the rigors of the campaign.  
G. The Combination of Friction an d Fog, with Competitiveness 
and Fragility (You could say Fear but I think it goes deeper 
than that) Creates a Very Hi gh Degree of Uncertainty</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>13
for you. He eschewed what the ALB folk hoped to, 
but failed to, achieve.  
5. In general, "innovations" that straddle the boundaries of services should face extremely hard going   
["our targets your platforms, our platforms, your targets"].   
a) Close Air Support,  Maybe tactical aviation in general 
b) Luftwaffe support of the German Navy 
c) USAAF Long Range maritime patrol aircraft in the 
Battle of the Atlantic 
d) [Naval carrier aircraft support for long range 
strategic bombers?] 
IV. The People within the organization 
A. How do you keep them happy in peacetime; get them to think at 
least somewhat seriously about preparation for war; and then 
actually make them function when the crunch comesand keep 
them functioning? 
B. Informal Organization/Human Relations School.   
1. Traditional Preparation For Wa r--  We dont really know 
how to do it, but we know what  its like.  Gives rise to 
two fundamental peacetime behaviors. 
2. Cultivate traits in officers that will at least hold the 
organization togetherie Phlegmatic (intrepid coolness or calm fortitude) commande rs, who can do without 
sleep; eat little, no or poor  food; still approximate 
rational decision making.   
a) Soldiers Once and Young, General, then Col. 
Harold Moore. 
b) Rommel, Infantry Attacks</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8
B. The flip side of this expectatio n however, is that most of the 
time trouble never comes; the more successful you are at 
deterring war, or simply avoiding it,  the higher your 
uncertainty about what it is that you do.   
1. Absolutely key to the life of military organizations is that 
most spend years with no reliable test of their 
capabilitiestechnological, organizational, doctrinal, 
tactical.   
2. And given everything I have said so far about the 
conduct of war--  Virtually no way to reliably simulate 
the process.  You trybut it is very hard to prove 
anything.  It is also quite costly.  Just simulating the 
friction of a corps level operation by trotting out a full 
two or three division corps is sufficiently expensive and disruptive that you virtually never do it.   
3. War games and simulations ha ve gotten better and better, 
as have actual maneuvers.  Militaries do what they can, 
and in recent years have invested vast sums.  But there is simply a lot you cannot know, as I suspect an honest "before and after" study of the Kosovo War last year 
would show. 
4. And we have another problem, truly realistic training is 
dangerous, and with all volunteer militaries, and 
significant competition from the private sector, it's not clear how many training deaths you can really afford. 
C. During these periods of peace, much can change from your last 
combat. Peace is full of military uncertainty.  
1. The civilian economy thro ws off new technologies, 
which your old or new adve rsaries may exploit and 
which some members of your own organization, as well 
as its clients, want you to exploit..   
2. New adversaries arise, or civilian leaders choose new 
ones, with new or at least different methods of warfare, 
in different climates and topography.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3
pieces, with the possible exception of criminal ones in 
competition with each other.  Very Competitive.    
1. Sometimes you only notice this at the micro-level, the 
early minutes of Hal Moore's ai rcav battalion at its LZ in 
the Drang river area; the s udden realization of the size 
force encountered and the de sperate need to secure a 
defensible perimeter,  and bring in the reinforcements to 
do so. 
C. Mistakes have potentially very  great Consequences.  Many 
organized activitiesincluding  the Boston commuteinvolve 
risk to life an limb, some risk to a few friends and colleagues,  
Almost none risk the lives or f reedom of family members and 
friends not present.  One must make decisions that at minimum 
involve very serious risks a nd costs for other organization 
members.  The consequences of failure for ones self, ones 
associates, ones country are absurdly great. Very Risky  
1. Churchill's (?) remark durin g WWI that Jellicoe, the 
commander of the High Seas fleet was the only man who 
could lose the war in an afternoon. 
2. Perhaps less dramatically, Keith Park, commander of 
Number 11 Group, the one cl osest to the Germans in 
France, and defending the a pproaches to London, while 
not able to lose the whole wa r with a mistake, failure to 
intercept, break up a German  raid could produce very 
serious consequences on the gr ound, either for industrial 
targets, or for bases the Germans were trying to hit; also huge arguments about what is the right thing to do, try to 
"defend"  or as those in the neighboring groups, wait, 
muster larger concentrated fo rces, and try to shoot down 
more german planes, and worry less about defending 
targets on the ground. 
D. A very powerful tension between boldness or dynamism necessary for competition and conservatism imposed by the great consequences??</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>15
solidary aspects, which are also very important once you 
have lived in these organizations for long.)   
a) Thus the incentives to favor classical 
organizational preferences to enhance size, wealth, 
and autonomy, is even higher than it is for most organizations.   
b) Could change if/as more and more officers are doing things that transf er easily to the civilian 
economy, but that would not be combat arms. 
4. Samuel Huntington  argues that the professional military's emphasis on obedience,  loyalty, and the chain 
of command stems from the militarys organizational commitment to infu se the conduct of war with goals of 
state policy.  I don't think this is quite right.   
a) This emphasis is part of both the formal and informal organization, and in my view arises from 
the grave fears of keeping any control at all once 
the battle starts.   
a) Chain of command is the hardware of military command, loyalty is the informal glue that helps commanders believe that subordinates will try to execute their wishes even  when the fog and the 
friction make continuous communication impossible 
5. But both the professional dependence on the organization, and the stress on chain of command, obedience, and loyalty for comb at effectiveness, may put 
a kind of premium on maintain ing the unified external 
face of the organization; we handle our own problems in private in order not to provide outsiders a way in.  
May make innovation debates hard to have.  Could explain the decline of public inter-service fights in the 
US and more generally.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9
3. Civil society, which provide s the materiel and human 
contributions for war may changealtering notions of 
acceptable costs of combat, av ailable resources, and even 
what it is permissible to do to the enemy .  
D. The domestic political environmen t in modern societies is a 
source of uncertainty centering around the basic purpose of the 
organization.   
1. Most modern states, to a greater or lesser degree, 
subscribe to nominal civilian control over foreign policy, 
and of the the military.  
2. The military's function is to manage violence in service 
to state policy.  But how can this be achieved?   
3. In early Organization theory, Woodrow Wilson for example,  people believed in policy and administration.  
Carried into military this w ould mean (as soldiers often 
hope, according to Richard Betts's 
Soldiers Statesmen 
and Cold War Crises ) statesmen make policy, provide a 
mission, stand back and watch the neutral tool execute.  
But it seldom works this wa y; Nobody believes it.  They 
are mixed up together.   
4. Clausewitz did not believe it either.  And insisted policy 
ought to infuse every aspect of the conduct of war.  But 
he did not have very intere sting ideas on how to do it. 
This gives rise to a very  basic  Cause Effect 
Uncertainty.   
a) Do we Make our soldiers into 
politicians/statesmen? Runni ng risk that their 
professionalism as war fighters will suffer? 
(1) Did Gamelin, the interwar French Army 
Chief of Staff spend too much time on 
diplomacy and alliances, to the detriment of his responsibilities as a soldier, it looks like 
it?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7
1. War is at some level a struggl e of rival organizations, not 
just rival orbats, doctrines, or war plans. 
2. A stable, agreed way of warfa re,  a doctrine, is a very 
appealing way to deal with friction and fog, with 
fragility, especially at the mo ment of the transition from 
peace to war. 
3. The adversary has the same set of problems, and the 
same set of incentives, so you want to "operate" your 
own doctrine, and deny the adversary his. Impose your 
plans on him. 
4. Live by the golden rule, do unto others as they would do unto you,, but do it first.--"Offensive" is more honored 
than the Defensive;  Striking fi rst is tempting, even if the 
state is a status quo power; Surprise is honored, though at 
least one of the better known theorists, Clausewitz, 
discounts its utility.   
5. One key aspect of this is secrecy.  For purely functional reasons militaries wish to keep  a lot of things secret, it 
helps in this process of imposing your own sop's and 
denying the enemy his but it has some implications for 
other aspects of organizational life..   
III. The "Peacetime Environment" 
A. Realist theorists of  International Politics see international politics as an anar chical realm 
1. With no sovereign warfare is always possible and there is 
nobody to protect the state but th e state, or its allies.  And 
allies are often unreliable.   
2. As Samuel Huntington notes in Soldier and the State, 
militaries tend toward a vers ion of this belief.  He 
correctly in my view gives th e standard rationale which is 
not as I have stated itanarc hy, but rather human nature.  
Have a pessimistic view thereof. --an unchanging 
expectation of trouble, a nd attention to how you are 
going to deal with it.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/17-484-comparative-grand-strategy-and-military-doctrine-fall-2004/resources/milorg_and_war</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-484-comparative-grand-strategy-and-military-doctrine-fall-2004/resources/milorg_and_war/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4
E. The Purpose of Mutual Dest ruction Creates a Special 
Environment  
1. This has the effect, as Cl ausewitz observed of giving 
warfare an inherent compe titive quality far more intense 
than almost any other aspect of social life.  The greater 
the exposure of the state th at a military organization 
servesthe more competitive that military's peacetime 
behavior is likely to be, but as I'll suggest, this does not 
necessarily cause innovation.   
2. The activity itself creates a new environment.  Clausewitz talks about friction and the dearth of good information, often called fog.   
-It is hard to make things happen on the battlefieldeven 
when the adversary is not fighting very hard.   -It is hard to figure out what is going on on the 
battlefield.  Getting useful in formation from the mass of 
impressions and data, often deliberately obstructed by the 
enemy (again due to the competitiveness factor) makes 
the conduct of war a hugely  uncertain activity.   
-Getting information often risks and costs lives and 
machines.   
--Nothing is easy or free. 
3. Within this environment, th ese organizations are in a 
relative sensefragile.  
a) Most modern military orga nizations (not actually 
allguerrillas, or MAD ex cepted ) but most, are 
trying to coordinate the r ational application of a 
range of technologies, e ach of which requires a 
little administrative tail to fix it, fuel it, arm it, 
replace it, as well as  brain, eyes, nervous system.   
A very high level of internal interdependence in modern arms, which has grown since the industrial 
revolution.  Thus the organizations suffer a kind of  
fragile internal interdependence. AND</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2
view.  Purpose is the driver. Functional Specialization of the 
Organization and within it, with an Internal Division of Labor, 
coordinated through a Hierarch ically arranged system of 
Command and Control.  Decision ma de on Rationality criteria, 
cost and benefit. Professionaliza tion of the officials/managers 
with education and developing e xpertise. "Files."  The neutral 
tool.  The living machine.   
1. Weber, one of the earliest st udents of large scale formal 
organizations, bureaucracy, understood that the very 
evolution of bureaucracy was a in part a function of the 
military struggles among the monarchs of Europe,  "War made the state and the state made war."  Bureaucracies 
grew to feed armies, and it' s not an exaggeration to say 
that the professionalization of armies and of bureaucracies occurred hand in hand, each learning from the other. 
2. The over-riding commitment to purpose, and the effort to achieve rationality in pursu it of that purpose make 
uncertainty of any kind an enemy.  Organizations do what they can to reduce uncertainty. 
3. The need to pursue purpose with people, whose rationality is limited, and who in any case are not actually 
going to be perfect cogs in a rational machine, creates special motivation and control problems for 
organizational leaders in their efforts to keep the 
organization focused on the achievement of purpose.  People are a source of uncertainty. 
4. How might a military organi zation's specific purpose 
produce special behaviors or qualities, especially 
qualities that might bear on their ability to innovate? 
B. Military organizations do something unusualthey try to 
destroy one another, directly.  Samuel Huntingtons notion of 
the officer corps as specialists in  the management of violence in 
service to the state does not do it ju stice.  I am not sure that any 
other organization has the explic it purpose of bashing its like to</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>12
WWII, US bombers attack ed US ground forces 
very heavily on several oc casions during the Battle 
of the Bulge,  Desert Storm etc.] 
2. Special, because you need them in the moment of truth 
but you don't have too much influence over them in many militaries and central institutio ns across services are often 
not strong 
3. Each organization has some incentives to get into those aspects of the other's business that affect it the most.  Can 
cause Tension and rivalry, pe rhaps creative, as Harvey 
will argue, but can also cause redundancy, and the over-consumption of scarce resources.   
a) I will not try to answer the perpetual question, do we really need all these air forces in the United 
States, but this basic question did provide the 
impetus for the failed roles and missions commission. 
b) Some of you may remember "air land battle"- IT is striking that as late as Desert Storm, the "air-" part 
seemed pretty under-devel oped, and does to this 
day; the Army seems to still be trying to complete 
the development of the autonomous deep strike capability to destroy the Soviet Second Echelon 
with long range rockets, which the air force never 
quite offered. 
4. On the other hand, cooperative relationships, and divisions of responsibility that  have been negotiated with 
difficulty over many years ma y deter innovation efforts- 
a) When General DePuy was head of TRADOC and 
was working up the much maligned Active 
Defense, he more or less decided that changing the 
Army was hard enough without trying to change the air force, and more or less signed a private 
treaty with the AF saying everything on the other 
side of the FSCL is yours, I hope it all goes well</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>11
E. Comparative WealthMilitaries in  societies that face any kind 
of plausible threat tend to have considerable influence over 
their own situation.  
1. Control great material resources,. Great Powers in particular tend to perceive other great powers as  their Greatest Threats which causes  them to allocate Great 
Resources to their defense, which they have because they are great powers.  Even today,  3% of GDP is a pretty big 
war chest, 
2. They tend to have significan t prestige, which may arise 
from heroic history, conservative political values, or in advanced liberal democratic society simple deference to 
technical expertise.  Although this will vary as well with 
perceived threats to the stat e, history, and constitution. 
3. Significant internal influence, especially on its own issues. Political power if it confines itself to its own issues where it has legitimacy.  Thus very great influence 
over security policyie it affe cts the task it is given.  
And it tries to use that power to minimize its own uncertainties.   
a) Not the same everywhere, US very high, Israel 
probably very high, much of western Europe probably less. 
F. In Most Countries, especially in modern times, there are several 
military organizations, armies, na vies, and air forces but there 
can even be others 
1. Other services in peacetim e and wartime can create 
sizeable interdependencies and thus sizeable sources of uncertainty. 
a) Fratricide for example, between army or navy surface air defenses, and air force aircraft 
b) Fratricide between aircra ft and ground forces. 
[sometimes truly devasta ting, Leslie McNair was 
killed in the Cobra br eakout from Normandy in</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>14
c) Movie, Command Decisions (Le May), 12 o'clock 
high as well 
d) CS Forester, The General  (Haig caricature) 
3. Stalwart troops who trust th eir commanders and rely on 
each other.  
4. Know your weaponie proficiency in the actual 
technical task of using it. 
5. Neither of these have much to  do with tactics, doctrine, 
operational art, or anything  else.  But I advance the 
hypothesis that they are bot h central to the informal 
organization.  Its culture. 
C. To keep them happy you mu st go well beyond utilitarian 
incentives, to solidary and purposive ones.   
1. But war is off on the horizonso some intermediate 
goals, conducive to solid arity are needed.   
2. One source of non-monetary incentives is allegiance to weapons and tactics of the last  glorious episode, "branch" 
or "platform community" (as Owen would say) loyalty.  
[the horse, the tank, the light infantryman with his rifle -
LIDs, the pilot-ed fighter aircraft] 
D. Officer Corpspeculiar kind of profession.   
1. Truly fundamental differen ces between doctors or 
lawyers, vs Officers. Doctors and Lawyers can take 
clients or not.  They have  considerable professional 
mobility.  In some cases they can even change countries.   
2. But not officersparticularly the ones closest to the core 
technology of management of violence.  Officers have one buyerthe government, and they usually cant switch countries.   
3. This produces extremely pow erful utilitarian loyalties to 
the organizationonce you are in, the thought of being 
out is scarey purely on these grounds.  (Forget the</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>10
b) Do we encourage civilians to closely oversee the 
conduct of military operati ons?  You can't prevent 
it if that is what they want  to do, But this threatens 
the organization's core mi ssion, and causes it to 
fight to regain its autonomy, 
(1) Churchill's incessant demands on Dowding for more Fighter squadrons to support 
France in May/June 1940, even though Dowding had tried to explain gently that at some point too few would be left to defend 
Britain, finally an open disagreement in a 
key meetings, Churchill had to cease his requests but he never forgave Dowding. 
c)  It is at this point that the fetish for secrecy to deceive enemies without, becomes a handy 
rationale for fending off meddlers at home.  
(WeberSecrecy is the fighting posture of the bureaucracy.) 
(1) SAC's great effort to keep SIOP information out of the hands of politicians, pentagon 
officials etc. 
(2) General disinclination to  share details of war 
plans with civilians, even Pentagon civilians. 
(3) Old pedigree, some question as to whether the German Foreign Minister, Bethman 
Hollweg understood that the Schlieffen Plan not only called for violation of Belgian 
neutrality, which he proba bly did, but that it 
required a surprise coup de main even 
before German mobilization was complete. 
Thus the FM did not understand that his 
timeline for successful diplomacy was shorter than he thought.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>16
V. Conclusions:  Implications 
A. The more encompassing the Innovation, the harder it should be 
to implement.  The commit ment to big macro-level 
organizational understandings--" Service doctrine," should be 
very great. 
B. Innovations in doctrine and tact ics, should be very hard to 
achieve in peacetime.  Not much  can be proven; few sources 
of pressure.  Much energy a nd capability for resistance to 
external meddlers. 
C. The human organization has a set of values and characteristics 
that help prepare for war in a very general way.  But these 
preferred characteristics are probably not conducive to 
innovation.  1. Loyalty can easil y drift into Conformity.  2.  
Respect for the human values that get you through combat may 
drift into a vaguely unscientif ic attitude 3. Sentimental 
attachment to old branches, arms, etc.may stack the deck 
against new ideas and proposals 
D. Bernard Brodie says, improved weapons should not cause any 
great resistance, it is their implic ations for doctrine, tactics, and 
organization that a military ha s a hard time seeing, (although 
probably a little more technology. resistance than he admits.) 
E. Civilian control, for direct intervention to try to spur 
innovation, or even for  policy infusion into military strategy, 
(Political-Military Integration)  should be difficult, the 
organization has a lot of assets to  resist civilian control, and a 
lot of incentives to do it.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
(1) The campaign in the low countries took the 
Germans about six weeks in 1940 to finish 
off the better half of the French Army.   
(2) A new term was introduced during Desert Storm for the Iraqi army's efforts to avoid US electronic intelligence by the very 
sparing use of their radio communications 
networks: EMCON suicide 
 
b) Often, they are surprisingly dependent on relatively small numbers of high value assets 
(navies especially) and as both sides know this, the 
high value assets get a lot of destructive attention. 
(1) The Israelis destroyed the Egyptian Air Force in a day, the Army in six, in 1967.   
(2) The japanese lost 4 carriers in a day at Midway.   
c) Battle doesnt always, or even often, turn out quite so dramatically.  But these organizations are 
fragile given their taskand they know it. 
d) The knowledge of how quickly and easily things can go very wrong, coupled with great uncertainty about the precise ways it may go wrong, influences 
the organization's day to day behavior, in war, and 
also in time of peace. 
e) Competing businesses, at least the larger ones, 
destroy each other throug h competition over many 
years; 
- to my knowledge, govern ment bureaucracies are 
seldom actually killed off. 
F. There is also a funny, and extr emely scary, gray area, the 
"Transition to Conflict," the mome nt when peace turns into war</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
 
Military Organizations, the Business of War, and what it means for 
Innovation 
I. Introduction: 
Organization theorists often think in term s of the effects of three big factors 
on the behavior of large scale organizationsPurpose; People; and 
Environment.  
A. This discussion is organized around the specifics of military 
purposes, military people, and the environment"combat," domestic, and foreign.   
B. These are tied together by the theme of uncertaintyits sources, and its management.   
1. Mean-Ends, or "cause-effect"  Uncertainty, ie uncertainty 
about how to complete the task in the world 
2. Interdependence Related Uncertainties-  -Internal:  How are my own component parts going to 
work together -External: How will outsiders  upon whom I depend going 
to work with me, or even at cross purposes 
C. How much difference these specifics about  military 
organizations make for considering the behavior of  military organizations relative to to non-m ilitary ones is a fit subject for 
discussion, and comment.:  Much  of organization theory and 
management theory is about larg e scale organizations that are 
similar, but not identical to modern militaries; a lot of 
academics have used organization theory to look directly at 
militaries in one way or another.   
II. Purpose 
A. Like all organizations, in caricatur e, and in the abstract modern 
militaries arrange people for th e mass production of rationality. 
(This may be changing, as I'll di scuss later in the week)  Max 
Webers message.  The classical  administrative-bureaucratic</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
either for the organization as a whole, or even for unblooded 
units in an organization already at war. 
1. Fraught with Uncertainty, given what the organization 
knows in a general way about the course and risks of 
combat, coupled with the fact  that the normal peacetime 
existence of the organizati on, regardless of training 
regimen, is quite different from war. 
2. Examples: 
a) Kasserine Pass for the US Army in WWII 
b) The green 106th division in the Battle of the Bulge 
c) Task force Smith, but really all of the early 
arriving divisions during the first weeks of the 
Korean War 
d) French Army in May of 1940 
3. How do you get your organization intact through this 
transition. 
4. Both the Environment of wa r and the problem of the 
transition to conflict Raise the Question for the 
Organization of How it Prepares/Buffers itself in 
Peacetime. 
5. May produce a very high premium on simplicity, stability, and acceptance of "doc trine; cohesion is a very 
high value 
6. Even if someone could prove, at  the last minute, that the 
doctrine was not quite right, w ould you try to change it?  
An agreed poor doctrine may be preferable to none at all 
to an organization looking forward to an imminent 
transition from the pleasures of garrison life to the rigors of the campaign.  
G. The Combination of Friction an d Fog, with Competitiveness 
and Fragility (You could say Fear but I think it goes deeper 
than that) Creates a Very Hi gh Degree of Uncertainty</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>13
for you. He eschewed what the ALB folk hoped to, 
but failed to, achieve.  
5. In general, "innovations" that straddle the boundaries of services should face extremely hard going   
["our targets your platforms, our platforms, your targets"].   
a) Close Air Support,  Maybe tactical aviation in general 
b) Luftwaffe support of the German Navy 
c) USAAF Long Range maritime patrol aircraft in the 
Battle of the Atlantic 
d) [Naval carrier aircraft support for long range 
strategic bombers?] 
IV. The People within the organization 
A. How do you keep them happy in peacetime; get them to think at 
least somewhat seriously about preparation for war; and then 
actually make them function when the crunch comesand keep 
them functioning? 
B. Informal Organization/Human Relations School.   
1. Traditional Preparation For Wa r--  We dont really know 
how to do it, but we know what  its like.  Gives rise to 
two fundamental peacetime behaviors. 
2. Cultivate traits in officers that will at least hold the 
organization togetherie Phlegmatic (intrepid coolness or calm fortitude) commande rs, who can do without 
sleep; eat little, no or poor  food; still approximate 
rational decision making.   
a) Soldiers Once and Young, General, then Col. 
Harold Moore. 
b) Rommel, Infantry Attacks</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8
B. The flip side of this expectatio n however, is that most of the 
time trouble never comes; the more successful you are at 
deterring war, or simply avoiding it,  the higher your 
uncertainty about what it is that you do.   
1. Absolutely key to the life of military organizations is that 
most spend years with no reliable test of their 
capabilitiestechnological, organizational, doctrinal, 
tactical.   
2. And given everything I have said so far about the 
conduct of war--  Virtually no way to reliably simulate 
the process.  You trybut it is very hard to prove 
anything.  It is also quite costly.  Just simulating the 
friction of a corps level operation by trotting out a full 
two or three division corps is sufficiently expensive and disruptive that you virtually never do it.   
3. War games and simulations ha ve gotten better and better, 
as have actual maneuvers.  Militaries do what they can, 
and in recent years have invested vast sums.  But there is simply a lot you cannot know, as I suspect an honest "before and after" study of the Kosovo War last year 
would show. 
4. And we have another problem, truly realistic training is 
dangerous, and with all volunteer militaries, and 
significant competition from the private sector, it's not clear how many training deaths you can really afford. 
C. During these periods of peace, much can change from your last 
combat. Peace is full of military uncertainty.  
1. The civilian economy thro ws off new technologies, 
which your old or new adve rsaries may exploit and 
which some members of your own organization, as well 
as its clients, want you to exploit..   
2. New adversaries arise, or civilian leaders choose new 
ones, with new or at least different methods of warfare, 
in different climates and topography.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3
pieces, with the possible exception of criminal ones in 
competition with each other.  Very Competitive.    
1. Sometimes you only notice this at the micro-level, the 
early minutes of Hal Moore's ai rcav battalion at its LZ in 
the Drang river area; the s udden realization of the size 
force encountered and the de sperate need to secure a 
defensible perimeter,  and bring in the reinforcements to 
do so. 
C. Mistakes have potentially very  great Consequences.  Many 
organized activitiesincluding  the Boston commuteinvolve 
risk to life an limb, some risk to a few friends and colleagues,  
Almost none risk the lives or f reedom of family members and 
friends not present.  One must make decisions that at minimum 
involve very serious risks a nd costs for other organization 
members.  The consequences of failure for ones self, ones 
associates, ones country are absurdly great. Very Risky  
1. Churchill's (?) remark durin g WWI that Jellicoe, the 
commander of the High Seas fleet was the only man who 
could lose the war in an afternoon. 
2. Perhaps less dramatically, Keith Park, commander of 
Number 11 Group, the one cl osest to the Germans in 
France, and defending the a pproaches to London, while 
not able to lose the whole wa r with a mistake, failure to 
intercept, break up a German  raid could produce very 
serious consequences on the gr ound, either for industrial 
targets, or for bases the Germans were trying to hit; also huge arguments about what is the right thing to do, try to 
"defend"  or as those in the neighboring groups, wait, 
muster larger concentrated fo rces, and try to shoot down 
more german planes, and worry less about defending 
targets on the ground. 
D. A very powerful tension between boldness or dynamism necessary for competition and conservatism imposed by the great consequences??</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>15
solidary aspects, which are also very important once you 
have lived in these organizations for long.)   
a) Thus the incentives to favor classical 
organizational preferences to enhance size, wealth, 
and autonomy, is even higher than it is for most organizations.   
b) Could change if/as more and more officers are doing things that transf er easily to the civilian 
economy, but that would not be combat arms. 
4. Samuel Huntington  argues that the professional military's emphasis on obedience,  loyalty, and the chain 
of command stems from the militarys organizational commitment to infu se the conduct of war with goals of 
state policy.  I don't think this is quite right.   
a) This emphasis is part of both the formal and informal organization, and in my view arises from 
the grave fears of keeping any control at all once 
the battle starts.   
a) Chain of command is the hardware of military command, loyalty is the informal glue that helps commanders believe that subordinates will try to execute their wishes even  when the fog and the 
friction make continuous communication impossible 
5. But both the professional dependence on the organization, and the stress on chain of command, obedience, and loyalty for comb at effectiveness, may put 
a kind of premium on maintain ing the unified external 
face of the organization; we handle our own problems in private in order not to provide outsiders a way in.  
May make innovation debates hard to have.  Could explain the decline of public inter-service fights in the 
US and more generally.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9
3. Civil society, which provide s the materiel and human 
contributions for war may changealtering notions of 
acceptable costs of combat, av ailable resources, and even 
what it is permissible to do to the enemy .  
D. The domestic political environmen t in modern societies is a 
source of uncertainty centering around the basic purpose of the 
organization.   
1. Most modern states, to a greater or lesser degree, 
subscribe to nominal civilian control over foreign policy, 
and of the the military.  
2. The military's function is to manage violence in service 
to state policy.  But how can this be achieved?   
3. In early Organization theory, Woodrow Wilson for example,  people believed in policy and administration.  
Carried into military this w ould mean (as soldiers often 
hope, according to Richard Betts's 
Soldiers Statesmen 
and Cold War Crises ) statesmen make policy, provide a 
mission, stand back and watch the neutral tool execute.  
But it seldom works this wa y; Nobody believes it.  They 
are mixed up together.   
4. Clausewitz did not believe it either.  And insisted policy 
ought to infuse every aspect of the conduct of war.  But 
he did not have very intere sting ideas on how to do it. 
This gives rise to a very  basic  Cause Effect 
Uncertainty.   
a) Do we Make our soldiers into 
politicians/statesmen? Runni ng risk that their 
professionalism as war fighters will suffer? 
(1) Did Gamelin, the interwar French Army 
Chief of Staff spend too much time on 
diplomacy and alliances, to the detriment of his responsibilities as a soldier, it looks like 
it?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7
1. War is at some level a struggl e of rival organizations, not 
just rival orbats, doctrines, or war plans. 
2. A stable, agreed way of warfa re,  a doctrine, is a very 
appealing way to deal with friction and fog, with 
fragility, especially at the mo ment of the transition from 
peace to war. 
3. The adversary has the same set of problems, and the 
same set of incentives, so you want to "operate" your 
own doctrine, and deny the adversary his. Impose your 
plans on him. 
4. Live by the golden rule, do unto others as they would do unto you,, but do it first.--"Offensive" is more honored 
than the Defensive;  Striking fi rst is tempting, even if the 
state is a status quo power; Surprise is honored, though at 
least one of the better known theorists, Clausewitz, 
discounts its utility.   
5. One key aspect of this is secrecy.  For purely functional reasons militaries wish to keep  a lot of things secret, it 
helps in this process of imposing your own sop's and 
denying the enemy his but it has some implications for 
other aspects of organizational life..   
III. The "Peacetime Environment" 
A. Realist theorists of  International Politics see international politics as an anar chical realm 
1. With no sovereign warfare is always possible and there is 
nobody to protect the state but th e state, or its allies.  And 
allies are often unreliable.   
2. As Samuel Huntington notes in Soldier and the State, 
militaries tend toward a vers ion of this belief.  He 
correctly in my view gives th e standard rationale which is 
not as I have stated itanarc hy, but rather human nature.  
Have a pessimistic view thereof. --an unchanging 
expectation of trouble, a nd attention to how you are 
going to deal with it.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/17-484-comparative-grand-strategy-and-military-doctrine-fall-2004/resources/nationalismandmilitarypower_9_29v2</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-484-comparative-grand-strategy-and-military-doctrine-fall-2004/resources/nationalismandmilitarypower_9_29v2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/17-484-comparative-grand-strategy-and-military-doctrine-fall-2004/resources/com_grd_strgy_04</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-484-comparative-grand-strategy-and-military-doctrine-fall-2004/resources/com_grd_strgy_04/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>0</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
why not?  
--Did it keep th e state secure?  
--Help it expand its power, if  that was the objective  
--Were the costs affordable?  
 
--Some of the explanations for success or failure can be found in answers  
to the preceding questions?  But there may be additional reasons for success or  
failure not covered by the questions I have outlined.  If we discover any we  
shall surely wish to remember them.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 
COMPARATIVE GRAND STRATEGY AND  
MILITARY DOCTRINE-(Fall 2004) 
 
Lecture I----Part One--Course Overview 
I. Purpose of the Course 
 A. MAJOR-To provide you with an inte llectual framework that will permit  
you to analyze systematically  how states organize or fail to organize their  
military forces to achieve their politica l objectives.  This framework is not  
exhaustive, it is rather a base that you can amend, add to, subtract from.  
1. The framework has three im portant components:   
-Causes of Strategy/  
-Elaboration of Stra tegy as a Concept/ 
-Consequences of strategi es of different kinds. 
 2.   This framework is useful fo r both "practitioners" and "scholars." 
 B. MINOR- To study "on a crash basi s" the diplomatic and military  
history of the first half of the centur y in the traditional cockpit of world  
politics--Europe.   
1. As a matter of principle, securi ty specialists who wish to  
work on present day problems ought to have some sense as  to how we arrived at  
our current situation, and how  well or poorly our forbea rers have done at our  
chosen profession. 
II. Approach-- CONCEPTUAL/ THEOR ETICAL-SCIENTIFIC/ COMPARATIVE-
HISTORICAL/ "POLICY SCIENTIFIC" 
A. Conceptual--We will treat "strategy" as more than a mere plot or plan/ we will try to 
unpack the concept. 
B. Theoretical Scientific--We will ask why states seem to get the strategies these get, what 
explains the outcomes we see, are ther e important causal variables at work? 
C. Comparative-Historical:  Permits us to test th e overall utility of our  concept of strategy--
does it illuminate across space  and time, and the overall va lidity of our hypothesized 
influences on strategy and the weights we assign them--aga in by looking across space 
and time. 
D. Policy-Scientific--In that we ask ourselves  could we do better? to school our own 
strategic faculties. 
III. PREDICTIVE/ DESCRIPTIVE/ AND PRESCRIPTIVE--Why try to do all these things  
at once? 
A. In principle one could simply teac h theories with a few examples, or  
teach a history course in ch ronological fashion with the expectation that wisdom  
would simply emerge, or one  could simply concentrate on how to make "good  
strategy" without both ering about explaining why stra tegies in the past have  
turned out the way they have. 
 B. Trying to do all three things makes for a busy  semester, complicated  
intellectual gymnastics, and runs the risk of too casual an a pproach to any or  
all of the three exercises. 
C. But for all the compression of th e course, there are some benefits. 
--Those who see themselves as professionals, working where the action is, may do</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
international politics--especially balanc e of power theory and organization  
theory;  
 --substantial dipl omatic history  
 --a great deal of military history, including the development of tactics  
and technology, as well as the conduct of key battles and campaigns. 
 
 
 
"Grand" or "Political-Milit ary" Strategy Defined 
Lecture I- Part Two 
I. Caveats 
 A.  States do not always, or even frequently, st ate their grand strategies  
clearly, or write them down in one place.  More often th an not, they do not use  
the term.  U.S. in recent y ears has used the terms  N ational Strate gy for Grand 
Strategy,  and National Mili tary Strategy  for Milita ry Doctrine. (Eisenhower's 
Massive Retaliation Strategy stated in NSC 162 is an  
example of one that was.  Can be  found in the Pentagon Papers.) 
 B.  Statesmen and soldiers do, howe ver, --implicitly or explicitly--  
think, plot, and conspire in "strategic" fashion. 
II.   What then do we mean by the term "Grand Strategy?" 
 A.  A core set of beliefs about nati onal security  found in the members of  
state's foreign policy and military elit e. (Consensus would be too strong a  
word.) 
 B.  These beliefs can us ually be characterized as a set of inter-connected 
political and military means and ends  
expected to produce "security."   
--(This term is not an obj ective one; a state's defini tion of security is not  
always one that an outside observer would agree with.   
 1. Highest-level political objectiv es are linked to middle-level  
political objectives, which are in turn  linked to highest level military  
objectives, which are linked to lower orde r military objectives.  Each link in  
the chain is both an end of  the link below, and a means to the link above.  This  
is merely an extension of Clausewitz's  view of the military-political, means- 
ends relationship.  Dual ity of Means and Ends.  
 --This image, which impl ies linearity, shoul d not be taken too literally;  
it would be more exact to view Grand Strategy as a system of interlinked  
political and military means and ends. 
 C.  An IDEAL grand strategy would not only specify political and military  
means and ends, but explain why the proposed connections are expected to hold  
true?    
 1.  For example a simple  question during mu ch of the 1990s would have been 
"Why is the commitment of rough ly one-fifth of active US m ilitary resources to actual 
presence in Europe or its wa ters on a daily basis expected  to produce "security" for the 
US?"  Explanations of critical hypo thesized linkages ough t to be embedded 
somewhere in the strategy. 
 D.  This chain of politic al and military means and ends may thus, also be</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
viewed as a state's THEORY about how it can best "cause " security for itself.   
That theory is tested every day in the unregulated, competitiv e environment of  
international politics.  
 
III. What are the key questions that we  shall wish to ask of each grand  
strategy that we examine? 
 A. What is the grand strategy?  As best we can, we shall draw a map of  
the core political-military means-ends chain. 
 B.  What are the key factors that seem to have influenced the grand  
strategy in question? 
 1.  If we can systematiz e our understanding of these factors we will be  
better able to predict the strategies of  other states, or at  least explain them. 
 C. What are the salient characteristics of the strate gy.  Those that  
seem to hold the greatest implications both for the security of the state  
itself, and the stabil ity of the internatio nal political system. 
 1.  At the political level, does the state aim to preser ve or upset the  
status quo?  To what extent?  (Key ? because revisionist strategies seem to have  
important effects on the beha vior of other states.)  
  a. Those of us who subscribe to ba lance of power theory would  
argue that expansionists, or those who appear so, se nd to provoke coalitions  
against themselves unless they are very very clever..  
  --One fundamental question we shall ask this year is how was it that  
Wilhelmine Germany seemed to encircle itself, promoting a fairly cohesive  
opposing coalition, whereas Hitler managed to prevent such a coalition from  
forming until rather late in the game? 
 2.  At the military level is the st rategy OFFENSIVE, DEFENSIVE, OR  
DETERRENT 
 --OFFENSIVE--DISARMING- BLITZKRIEG GERMAN AND ISRAELI 
STYLE  
 --DEFENSIVE-DENIAL- US IN LATE 19TH AND EARLY 20TH CENTURY, WITH BRITISH,  
TWO OCEANS, and a FLEET;  The BRI TISH WITH THE CHANNEL AND THE 
FLEET;  MAGINOT  
LINE 
 --DETERRENT-PUNISHMENT- FINLAND, SWITZERLAND, YUGOSLAVIA, PRC, FRANCE AND  
BRITAIN WITH NUCLEAR WEAPONS 
 --This is important because some have argued it affect s the odds of arms races, 
probability of war, and perhaps even the intens ity of war.  Some w ould also say that it 
affects probability of success- -since there are many strategists today, as has been true  
historically, who simply reje ct defense or punishment as appropriat e ways to  
wage war, insist they are doomed to ultimate failure.  
 --President Bush extols th e virtues of the offensive in  the War on Terror; says a 
purely defensive strategy won t do the job.  Even if you ag ree, is the mix right? 
 
 3.  Is there a coherent  relationship between the political and military</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
aspects of the strategy ? POLITICAL-MILITARY INTEGRATION--Is this tight 
means-ends relationship for which Clausewitz argues present?  
 a.   Does the statesman have at hand the tools necessary to  support his or her 
diplomatic ac tivities.  
  
--A defensive milita ry doctrine could not support revision  of the status  
quo; no gunboat diplomacy w ithout gunboats; you can't defe nd a global empire  
with meager resources; hard to  practice coercive  diplomacy with fo rces that have  
a go-no-go quality-such as mobilization army or the late 1950s US plans for  
general thermonuclear war.  
  
--Examples?? 
 
 
As the cold war ended, US military deployments took the form of wars of 
observation/peace keep ing.  Our forces were organi zed and their equipment was 
engineered for big wars.  Th e inadvertent downing of an Iranian airliner revealed a 
problem.  Bernard Trainor formerly  
of the NYT, formerly Deputy Ch ief of Staff of the USMC.  
NYT, "US as PeaceKeeper When Role Blurs"  NYT, 8/6/88 p.3 
--"The military has not ye t found a formula, which in sures its read iness to  
fight a war, while at the same time fieldi ng forces that can walk the thin line  
between restrain and violence in po litically complicated crises."  
--"...modern military equipment such as th e Aegis system,...is also designed for  
battlefield situations that involve only friends and targets.."  
 
Swedish Submarine Incursions-  
--On a smaller scale, the Swedish Navy began to design homing torpedos with  
pipsqueak warheads-designed to  damage but not kill an  enemy submarine--for  
peacetime defense against submarine intrusi ons by a great power whose submarines  
you'd rather warn than sink. 
 
--Between the Bush administra tions decision to add political re-engi neering to the war 
on terror, and the European propensity to  make peace and order on their periphery, 
especially throwing a wet bl anket on civil wars a priori tywe have seen a pretty 
significant growth in th e Wests steady state re quirement for ground force 
deployments.  Yet, ground fo rces are probably the capabil ity we shrunk the most after 
the Cold War.  Steady state maybe a capaci ty to keep 300,000 persons in the field, 
with great strain.  This perm its you to have a ghost of a chance policing populations of 
roughly 30 million.  Between Afghan, Iraq , and the Balkans were trying to do 60 
million. And there is a move to add Sudan.  We have to do less, get a lot better at 
doing it, or build more ground forcesw hich are both expe nsive and not too 
glamorous.  
 
 
 b. Conversely has the statesman</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
V. Organization (SEE SYLLABUS) 
 Section 1 , roughly the first three weeks of the course will  
-define the concep t of grand strategy, and offer a se t of questions and analytical  
categories that we shall use to evaluate the strategies  selected for study.    
 --Examine some of the critical influenc es that shape the grand strategies  
of nations-- including  
NATIONAL POWER/  GEOGRAPHICAL POSITION/ MILITARY 
TECHNOLOGY/ THE STRUCTURE AND  
NATURE OF MODERN MILITARY ORGANIZATIONS/ SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT, ESPECIALLY  
NATIONALISM.        (EXPL ANATION part of the exercise) 
--Examine the nature of the international political system to better  
understand some of the consequences of strategies of diffe rent types.   
(JUDGEMENT part of the exercise) --Well spend a week talking a bout historical case  studies; and use my old book as our 
reference point. 
  
 Section 2  of the course deals with the st rategy of the grea t powers in the  
years leading up to World Wa r I:  France, Germany, Britain, Russia, the outbreak  
and conduct of the war.  (also Austria-Hungary)  
--Expecially interested in the causes an d consequences of the "Cult of the  
Offensive" 
 Section 3   deals with the strategy of the three major powers in central  
Europe in the inter-war period--France, Br itain, and Germany, (my book); the  
initial battles of the war.  It also deals a bit with Soviet strategy in the  
l930's.    
--Especially interested in th e "Cult of the Defensive" 
  
In both periods, we will endeavor to determine  
-what the grand strategy  
seems to have been;  -what were the principal in fluences on the strategy;  
-what were the political and military c onsequences; including success or not.   
 -We will always have three broad  
tasks in mind CHARACTERIZATION, JUDGEMENT and EXPLANATION.  
 
 --CAVEAT--Very little diplomatic and military history is rigorously  
organized around the concept of  Grand Strategy.  Indeed, there is not a lot of  
agreement on what a grand st rategy actually is.  So one  cannot simply pick up a  
book or an essay that summari zes the grand strate gy of most of th e states that I  
have selected for study. 
       --CONSOLATION PRIZE-- even if you determine in the en d that the whole  
analytical framework of the course is a figment of my tortured imagination, it  
will have:  
 --exposed you to some ba sic theories of why stat es do what they do in</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
asked "certain military moves and actions to produce effects that are foreign to  
their nature."  
"..orders that defeat  the purpose they are meant to serve."  
Examples?   
--Bethman-Hollweg's submarine rules of engagement.   
--US constraints on bomb run profiles of aircraft hitti ng the Yalu bridges in  
late 1950  
--Perhaps US Marines in Beirut? 
--US military in Najaf??   
 
c. Does the strategy set priorities for both for ends and means.  
 --The notion of priority is critical , because we live in a world of  
scarcity; (Why we have  a science of economics)  Bern ard Brodie use to say that  
strategy wears a dollar sign;  One could look at strategy as  the production and  
distribution of scarce military means in  terms of alternat e political ends. 
--Big World  
 --Many threats and many pr izes imaginable.  Whic h are most critical?  
 --Many kinds of forces from which to choose.  Air,sea,la nd, heavy light,  
which ones are most appropriate  to the ends in view.   
 
   
 --In World War II, over 40% of US GNP was mobilized  for defense, but we  
still had to choose our battles; Europe , at least theoretically had first  
priority, the Pacific s econd, and Burma third.  
 --Clausewitz makes much of concentration  
on the decisive point, whic h is a priority issue. 
  
4.  Innovation-  
 -- Do the political aspects of the st rategy adapt to alterations in the  
political circumstances  of the state?  
 --Does the military strategy adapt to  changes in the political strategy,  
military technology, or enemy military technique?  
(Example: some scholars argue that Sadat believed that Egypt and the whole Arab  
world had to give up the ob jective of destroying Israel , since it was probable  
that Israel owned nuclear weapons and could impose a prohibitive cost on the  
Arabs even if they did succeed ag ainst Israeli conventional forces.) 
(Example: in the 1930's , as we shall see, the German  military adapted in  
superior fashion to the in ternal combustion engine a nd the radio --especially  
for the operations of  tanks and fighter a nd tactical bombing ai rcraft.  This put  
Germany in a position to wi n a series of major, swift, initial victories vs.  
France, Britain, and Russia.  Germany's de fensive potential was thus improved  
with territory and resource s, substantially raising th e dollar and human costs  
of ending her bid for hegemony.  France  and Britain responded less well to  
technological opportunities , and paid the price. 
  
5.  Finally, a "residual"  category:  Was the stra tegy successful?  Why or</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
a better job if they have a sense of the underlying dynamics at work in the  
formulation of strategy. 
--Those who see themselves primarily as scholars can guard against excessive  
determinism by considering how th ey might have done better 
--The focused study of hist orical cases imposes discipline on theorists--the  
discipline of "testing", and provides vicarious experience for the prospective  
practitioner.  
[A little like Clausewitz vi ew of the study of the st udy of military history] 
 
 
 
IV. FORMAT-Reading--Classroom-Writing 
 A. This is a reading course.  Lots  of it.  A good bit of it is not in  
the books.   
--Course will not work especi ally well for you if  you do not read what has been  
assigned--includes au ditors, especially true of discussion. 
 
 
 B. Writing Assignments--    
Basis for your grade in the course    
--Two short essays, and a take-home finalTa kehome, technically du e the last official 
class day of the term; I have been known to gran t blanket extensions.  
--The paper due da tes are real.  
--Paper due dates coincide roughly with the reading.  First paper should cover  
theoretical-conceptual materi al.  Second paper should de al with the first world  
war.    
The final will cover everything ; I write the questions. 
--Papers will be based larg ely on assigned readings.  You will determine your  
own topic. You may consult me, however, on topic and executio n.  I will not,  
however, read and critique drafts.  Papers  could take the form  of a critique of  
several pieces, a synthetic effort, the application of c oncepts or theories to  
particular historical episodes presen ted in the course, a more daring  
application of same to a s ubstantive area not de veloped in the cour se; or if you  
choose to read an entire b ook listed as supplementary re ading, a review essay.   
The stress here is on essay writing, not story-te lling. I want to se e you really wrestle 
with the material.  These instructions also ap ply to the final.  See the syllabus for  bit 
more elaboration. 
 C. Class-Meeting-Format.  Since you are mostly graduate students, I do  
not believe that I should  simply confine our mee tings to lectures.    
-But You are entitled to hear what I have to say about the literature and the  
issues raised each week.    
-Therefore, I will usually come in with some prepared material in the earlier part of the 
term and well move to almost all discussi on as the term progresses. Please come in 
with some prepared questions or comments  just to k eep things ro lling along.  
D.   Undergraduates:.[ See me after class.]</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
