<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-942-cosmology-fall-2001/</course_url>
    <course_title>Cosmology</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Physics </list>
      <list>Astrophysics</list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Newtonian Structure Formation Theory</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://de.arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0101009</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Cosmography 1: H0t0, Angular Diameter Test</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-942-cosmology-fall-2001/resources/cosmog/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Gyr. Even if it took 1 Gyr before the globular clusters could form (and I suspect that is 
an overestimate), H0t0 0.9 is now estimated to be less than unity. While this value is 
still too high for the Einstein-de Sitter model, it is consistent with the currently favored 
model, which has a cosmological constant. 
Cosmological models with a cosmological constant plus nonrelativistic matter are 
called Friedmann-Lemaitre models (for a review see Felten and Isaacman 1986; Rev. Mod. 
Phys., 58, 689). A cosmological constant is equivalent to a vacuum energy density v = 
/(8G). The general solution for H0t0 in such a model requires numerical quadrature 
of equation (10). However, in the special case of a at (k = 0) universe, the solution 
may be obtained in closed form: 
1/22 1 + vH0t0 =1/2 ln 1/2 for m + v = 1 (k = 0) . (13)3 v
m
Here we have dened m = 8Gm/(3H2) and v = 8Gv/(3H2) = /(3H2). Present 
values are implied although the subscript 0 is deleted for notational convenience. From 
equation (13) we see that a model with a cosmological constant can have arbitrarily large 
H0t0 provided that m 1. This restriction can be relaxed in a universe with curvature. 
For example, for m = 0.2 (consistent with several determinations), H0t0  for 
v 1.5476. 
4 Proper Motion Distance and Mattig Formula 
Most cosmological tests rely, directly or indirectly, on the angular part of the Robertson-
Walker metric and not only on the radial part used above. Before introducing the other 
standard cosmological tests, we introduce the proper motion distance to redshift z, 
which makes use of the angular radius r(): 
c 
Ha0r(z) = a0r((z)) = d(z) F (d(z)) , 
0 
 

sin[d(01)1/2] ,d(01)1/2 0 &gt; 1 (k &gt; 0) ; 
sinh[d(10)1/2 ] r()F (d) = (14) = , 0 &lt; 1 (k &lt; 0) ;  d(10)1/2 
1 , 0 = 1 (k = 0) . 
The proper motion distance relates the transverse speed v (perpendicular to the radial 
direction) and the angular speed d/dt0 (assuming d = 0) by v= a0rd/dt 0. If the  
&gt;angular and physical velocities of distant objects could be measured at z 1 (currently 
there is no way to do this), then a powerful cosmological test could be performed by 
observationally determining r(z). 
In the general case the proper motion distance a0r(z) is rather complicated and can 
be evaluated only by using equation (14) with d(z) obtained by numerical quadrature of 
equation (6). (For small z, eq. 6 gives the correct leading behavior for a0H0r/c.) 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>8 bursts) are not standard but evolve strongly in their properties as a function of cosmic 
time. 
Recently, two groups have rened the use of Type Ia supernovae as standard candles 
and have used them to measure the angular diameter-distance relation out to a redshift 
about 1 (Garnavich et al 1998, ApJ, 509, 74; Perlmutter et al 1999, ApJ 517, 565). These 
results are among the most exciting in cosmology during the last two years. They have 
garnered widespread attention because of the implication for cosmic acceleration. We 
will explore the evidence in detail in the lecture and in a problem set. 
Number-Flux Test 
As a last cosmological test, suppose that number counts of objects are measured as 
a function of ux but not redshift. There are many cosmological objects for which 
redshifts are diculty to determine (e.g. very faint galaxies and gamma ray bursts). If an 
object were a standard candle, then its ux would give the luminosity through equations 
(20) and (21), modulo the uncertain cosmological model. If, however, the evolution of 
comoving number density were known, then one could combine the angular-diameter and 
number counts techniques to obtain the number-ux test, commonly known as N (S). 
The number-ux test has been used for radio sources and gamma ray bursts, neither 
of which are standard candles. An assumption must therefore be made about the lumi
nosity distribution of the sources. Unfortunately, it is dicult to disentangle evolution of 
the luminosity distribution from cosmological eects. Nonetheless, the test is suciently 
clean for gamma-ray bursts so that N (S) gave strong evidence for a cosmological origin 
(as did the isotropy on the sky) before the rst redshifts were measured in 1997 (Metzger 
et al 1997, Nature, 387, 878). At that point, the debate was over: classical gamma ray 
bursts occur in high-redshift galaxies. However, their physics is still too poorly under
stood to allow their use in precision cosmological tests. Hogg &amp; Fruchter (1999, ApJ, 
520, 54) have investigated the number-ux-redshift distribution of gamma-ray bursts. 
They found that while the data do not signicantly constrain the spacetime geometry, 
they do constrain models for the evolution of the source population. 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>7 of the microwave background). Birkinshaw (1999, Phys. Rep., 310, 97) gives a detailed 
review. Finally, other possibilities have been proposed based on the clustering of quasar 
absorption lines (Hui et al 1999, ApJ, 511, L5) or high-redshift galaxies (Nair 1999, ApJ, 
522, 569). These methods are statistical and are based on comparing clustering in the 
radial and transverse directions, following a suggestion by Alcock &amp; Paczynski (1979, 
Nature, 281, 358). 
The cosmic microwave background anisotropy spectrum oers the cleanest version of 
the angular diameter test, based on the acoustic horizon size (the distance sound waves 
travel since the big bang) at the time of photon decoupling. This test will be discussed 
later in the course. 
Hubble Diagram 
Astronomers measure uxes (or magnitudes, i.e., logarithms of uxes, if they are optical 
astronomers) in addition to angular sizes. A radiation source of proper luminosity (i.e., 
power) L emitting isotropically at redshift z produces a ux at the observer 
L (1 + z)2 L S = (20) 
0 r24a2  4d2 
L(z) 
where we have dened the luminosity distance dL(z). 
Flux is power per unit area. The proper area of the sphere surrounding the source 
is 4a2 
0 r2 but the power is diminished by two powers of (1 + z): one for the redshifting 
of energy and another for the diminished rate of arrival of the energy. Note that we are 
implicitly assuming that the total ux is measured, i.e. the spectral ux integrated over 
all energy (the bolometric ux). In practice this is usually not possible and a correction 
must be applied for the redshifting of the spectral bandpass. (In optical astronomy this 
is called the K-correction). From equation (20) we can express the luminosity distance 
in terms of the angular-size and proper motion distances: 
HdL(z) = a0 r(z) (1 + z) = (1 + z)2dA(z) = c (1 + z) d(z) F (d(z)) . (21) 
0 
Sources of known proper luminosity (standard candles) would oer a test of cos
mological models (the magnitude-redshift test) through measurement of dL(z). The 
magnitude-redshift test was pioneered by Hubble; the plot of magnitude vs. redshift for 
a sample of objects such as galaxies or quasars is known as the Hubble diagram. 
The magnitude-redshift test has been a mainstay of observational cosmology for more 
than four decades (e.g. Humason, Mayall, &amp; Sandage 1956, AJ, 61, 97). It is basically 
an extension to high redshift (high means z &gt; 0.5) of the methods used to estimate 
the Hubble constant. The diculty lies in nding standard candles. Most objects bright 
enough to be visible at high redshift (e.g. galaxies, quasars, or, more recently, gamma ray 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>All density contributions (including vacuum energy, i.e., a cosmological constant) are 
included in the density parameter . Using the Friedmann equation we may write the 
curvature constant as  2 a0H0k = (0  1) . (4) c 
Present values will be written with a subscript 0. 
aRedshift is widely used as a measure of time through the relation 1 + z = a0/a( ) 
where a0 = a(0) is the present value of the expansion scale factor. (Often one sets 
0 = 1 for convenience.) Likewise, the coordinate distance  is implicitly a function of 
redshift through the relation for a radial null geodesic, 
 z 1dz  = c(0   ) = c dz . (5)  d0 
Redshift can therefore be used as a measure of distance and vice versa. These relations 
are more complicated if one uses cosmic proper time t instead of conformal time. 
Using the Friedmann equation to evaluate dz/d , we get the proper distance to 
redshift z: 
 z  c H0 dz H0 
Ha0(z) = d(z) , d(z)  H(z) ,H(z)= 0 (z) + (1  0)(1 + z)2 1/2 
. 
0 0 0 
(6) 
If we normalize the expansion factor as usual, a0 = 1, then (z) is really the comoving 
distance . The comoving distance happens to equal (up to a factor a0) the proper 
distance at conformal time 0. 
Lets pause to ask what do we mean by proper distance in a nonstatic spacetime. 
The meaning is the same as in special relativity. The proper distance is measured 
between two spacetime events with the same  . For equation (6), one of the events 
is the observer today ( = 0,  = 0) and the other is elsewhere (radial coordinate 
(z)), also today. It is the distance that one would measure if one could travel innitely 
fast and string a tape measure across the universe. Since we are not tachyons, such a 
measurement is impossible. The proper distance is useful principally as an intermediate 
step in theoretical calculations of the physically measurable distances to be discussed 
below. 
The redshift-dependence of the density (z) in equation (6) follows from the equation 
of state p = p() and the equation of energy conservation, 
3  
d/dz =  + pc2. (7)1 + z 
Nonrelativistic matter (with p  c2) has m  (1 + z)3, radiation (with 3p = c2) has 
r  (1 + z)4 and vacuum energy (with p = c2) has v  (1 + z)0 . Other dependences 
are possible for more exotic equations of state, e.g. quantum elds. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 Massachusetts Institute of Technology
Department of Physics
Physics 8.942 Fall 1999
Cosmography in a Robertson-Walker
universe
c1999 Edmund Bertschinger. All rights reserved. 
Introduction 
Cosmography is the study of the large-scale structure of spacetime. The goal of cosmog
raphy is to measure spacetime geometry or, in other words, to determine the spacetime 
metric. For obvious practical reasons astronomers cannot use clocks and measuring rods 
or even lasers to measure spacetime structure, making this a challenging endeavor that 
has yet to fully succeed. 
Observational tests of the Robertson-Walker family of cosmological models (or any 
others) are made by comparing predictions with observations of astronomically measur
able quantities such as the redshift, age, angular size, ux (of electromagnetic radiation) 
and abundance of objects of various types (galaxies, quasars, etc.). Because of the non-
Minkowski geometry of spacetime the dependence of these quantities on distance  and 
even the meaning of distance itself  are more complicated than in special relativity. 
In these notes we derive the predictions relating observables in standard cosmological 
models. Much of this material is also given in Peacock (1999, sections 3.4 and 5.1). 
Another concise summary is given by Hogg (1999, astro-ph/9905116). 
We assume throughout a Robertson-Walker spacetime metric. For most purposes this 
metric is thought to be a satisfactory approximation even in a universe with perturbations 
like our own. 
There are ve standard cosmological tests plus several variants: 
1. The age of the universe in units of the Hubble time H1;0 
2. Number counts of sources as a function of redshift; 
3. Angular size as a function of redshift; 
4. Magnitude (logarithm of ux) as a function of redshift (Hubble diagram); and 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 5. Number counts of sources versus magnitude. 
Some other tests, such as galaxy surface brightness as a function of redshift, are closely 
related to one or more of our ve tests. We will not consider here other tests such as 
those involving gravitational lensing. An old but excellent review of cosmological tests 
is given by Sandage (1988; Ann. Rev. Astr. Ap., 26, 561). 
A historical perspective is useful. For six decades after Hubbles discovery of cosmo
logical expansion, these ve classic tests were the main activity of observational cosmol
ogy. Progress was frustrated by the diculty of separating intrinsic evolution of source 
properties (e.g. galaxies at high redshift are intrinsically more luminous than nearby 
ones) from cosmological eects due to the non-Minkowski spacetime geometry. During 
the 1990s, new tests have been developed based on gravitational lensing, quasar absorp
tion line systems and, especially, the microwave background radiation. Very recently, 
one of the classic tests (the Hubble diagram for distant supernovae) has been improved 
suciently to yield good (but not conclusive) evidence for accelerated expansion. 
The present notes summarize the theoretical elements of cosmology needed for the 
ve classic tests but do not present the detailed results of their application. Chapter 5 
of Peacock (1999) presents a recent summary of the observations. The newer tests will 
be discussed later in the course. 
Proper Distance 
Before proceeding to the tests, we begin by writing the Robertson-Walker line element 
in the preferred form used in these notes (note that we restore the speed of light, c): 
2ds2 = a ( )  
c 2d 2 + d2 + r 2() d2 + sin2  d2, (1) 
where  
 k1/2 sin(k1/2 ) , k &gt; 0 ; 
r() = (k)1/2 sinh[(k)1/2 ] , k &lt; 0 ; (2)  , k = 0 . 
Beware that Peacock (1999) uses r for our ; his notation is nonstandard and one must 
be careful not to confuse his r with the angular radius appearing in the line element. He 
and many other authors choose units so that k = 1 or k = 0, in which case the factors 
of k are absent above. Our r() is Sk(r) in Peacocks notation. 
The Friedmann equation is 
21 da 8G kc2 kc2 
H2 = =3  a= H2 . (3)2 a2 d 2  a
Note that  , called conformal time (and denoted  by Peacock), is not the proper time 
measured by a comoving (fundamental) observer: ds2 = a2d 2 so that the proper time 
is t = a( )d and therefore the Hubble parameter is H(t) = d ln a/dt = a2da/d . 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>The proper motion distance simplies for a Friedmann (matter-dominated) universe. 
In this case one obtains a simple result known as the Mattig formula (Mattig 1958; 
Astron. Nachr., 284, 109): 
 2   a0H0 r(z) = d(z)F (d(z)) = 
0(1 + z) (2  0)(1  1 + 0z ) + 0z for p = 0 . c 2 
(15) 
Many of the discussions of distances in the cosmology literature implicitly assume a 
Friedmann universe or a Friedmann-Lemaitre universe (one dominated by matter plus 
a cosmological constant). (Unfortunately, analytical results for the proper motion dis
tance exist only for the Friedmann models and not those with a cosmological constant.) 
However, the modern view of physical cosmology is that almost arbitrary equations of 
state may be possible, so that the cosmological proper motion distance-redshift relation 
should not in general be restricted to equation (15). 
Stated another way, measurement of r(z) is really a test of the equation of state 
(implicit in (z) in eq. 6) at least as much as it is a test of the geometry of spacetime. 
5 Number Counts 
Now consider the volume corresponding to a given range of coordinates. The proper 
volume element at conformal time  is dVol = a3r2()dd, giving the dierential 
proper volume element 
3  2H0 dVol a0H0r = (1 + z)3 H0 = (1 + z)3 H0 d2(z) F 2(d(z)) . (16) c dz d H(z) c H(z) 
The comoving volume element is dVc  (1 + z)3 dVol. 
The proper and comoving volume elements are useful for computing number densities 
from redshift distributions. Suppose that there exists a homogeneous distribution of 
objects with comoving number density nc(z), corresponding to a proper number density 
(1 + z)3nc(z) (nc is constant if the objects are conserved). Then the dierential number 
of objects per unit redshift and solid angle is 
dN = nc(z) H0 d2(z) F 2(d(z)) . (17)dz d H(z) 
If a population of objects such as galaxies were known to have constant comoving 
number density and to be visible at all redshifts, measurement of dN/dz would pro
vide a test of the cosmological model (the number-redshift test) through the dependence 
of dN/dz on H0/H(z). This test is complicated by the fact that the number density 
&lt;05.. of galaxies shows signicant inhomogeneity on scales of z 
ing much leverage on cosmological parameters requires observations extending to z In addition, acquir 
&gt;1. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>6 Many dierent kinds of objects have been proposed for this test, including galaxies, 
quasars, radio galaxies, gravitational lenses, X-ray clusters, and Lyman alpha clouds. 
Several diculties have rendered this test dicult and inconclusive. 
The biggest diculty is that all known astronomical objects evolve with redshift. The 
comoving number density is not constant. Indeed, number counts are now used more 
to constrain the evolution of the source population more than to test the geometry of 
the universe. A second problem is the practical diculty of measuring redshifts for a 
complete and well-dened sample of objects at high redshift. This diculty has been 
ameliorated in recent years with the advent of large telescopes such as Keck and the 
development of powerful spectrophotometric redshift estimation methods for galaxies, as 
well as large observational surveys conducted with Hubble Space Telescope and ground-
based instruments. As a result, number counts have become a useful tool for studying 
galaxy (and other source) evolution. 
To complete the discussion of number count tests, we derive the total comoving 
volume to redshift z: 
 3   
2Vc(z) = 4a 3  (z) 
r ()d =4c d3(z) 3 [1  F (2d)] . (18)0 3 H0 2 (0  1)d2 0 
For 0 = 1 the factor in parentheses in equation (18) is 1. We noted earlier that d(z) 
increases with decreasing q. Therefore, the total comoving volume is larger in models 
with small q, e.g., models with vacuum energy. 
Angular-Diameter Test 
Next we dene the angular-diameter distance: 
a0 r(z) c d(z)F (d(z))dA(z) = a r(z) = = . (19)1 + zH0 1 + z 
The angular-diameter distance is dened so that an object of proper size l at redshift 
z subtends an angle  = l/dA(z) (for 2  1; for large angles trigonometric functions 
appear). 
If a population of objects of known proper size (standard meter-sticks) existed 
throughout the universe, cosmological models could be tested using measurements of 
dA(z). This is known as the angular diameter-redshift test. 
Unfortunately, good meter-sticks are hard to nd in cosmology. Gurvits et al (1999, 
A&amp;A, 342, 378) have used compact radio sources (typically, relativistic jets of plasma 
emitting synchrotron radiation, powered by massive black holes in quasars and radio 
galaxies) but they have not demonstrated rigorously that the objects should have the 
same physical size. A better test will come from measurements of hot gas in clusters 
of galaxies by combining X-ray emission with the Sunyaev-Zeldovich eect (shadowing 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>For small redshifts the Hubble expansion rate may be expanded in a power series, 
yielding the standard result 
d(z) = z  1(1 + q0)z 2 + O(z 3) . (8)2 
We have introduced the deceleration parameter 
a (d2a/dt2) 4G   3p = 1 + . (9) q  (da/dt)2 3H2  + 3pc2=2 c2 
Note that if the universe is matter-dominated, q0 = 0/2. However, there is no com
pelling observational or theoretical reason to believe that pc2 . Physical equations 
of state can be constructed theoretically with c2 p |
c|
2 . 
At small redshifts (z 1) the large-scale geometry of spacetime is fully specied 
by three numbers, H0, 0 and q0. For this reason, observational cosmology through the 
1960s was sometimes described as a search for three numbers. However, this is no longer 
true as our cosmological models have become more complete and observations test them 
to higher redshifts. 
At large redshifts (as z ) the proper distance approaches a constant provided 
(z) increases as least as rapidly as (1 + z)2 . This condition is equivalent to q &gt; 0 
(decelerated expansion). The limiting proper distance as z is called the causal 
(or particle) horizon distance . The actual universe may be far larger (either nite 
or innite) than the causal horizon distance but the latter in principle is the limiting 
distance to which we can see today. If q 0, the causal horizon distance is approximately 
c H1 multiplied by a numerical factor of order unity that scales inversely with q. For 0 
k = 0 and q being a positive constant, the coecient is exactly 1/q. 
If q &lt; 0 (accelerated expansion) at large z, the causal horizon distance is much larger 
and may even be innite. Inationary universe models have this behavior. 
3 Age-Hubble Parameter Relation 
The simplest cosmological test relies on measurements made at low redshift  the age 
of the universe (current proper time t0 measured by a fundamental observer) in units of 
the Hubble time H1 . Using d = dt/a together with equations (5) and (6) we obtain 0 
 z H0 dz 
. (10) H0[t0 t(z)] = H(z) 1 + z0 
For practically all equations of state in a Robertson-Walker universe, t0 is nite and 
equation (10) converges as z . However, if the universe was dominated by vacuum 
energy as z (with q = 1), H(z) was a constant and the age diverges logarith
mically. This behavior occurs in Lindes eternal chaotic ination model. However, this 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>result has no practical consequences for the astronomer, who cannot measure the total 
age of the universe. Rather, astronomers at best can measure the ages of old stars and 
galaxies, giving the proper time elapsed since the redshift of formation of these objects. 
Therefore cosmological tests based on H0t0 should be performed by truncating the inte
&lt;gral in equation (10) at some formation redshift, plausibly in the range 5 &lt;  100 for  z 
the oldest objects. 
For a Friedmann universe, i.e., a universe dominated by nonrelativistic matter so that 
p  c2, equation (10) may be evaluated analytically. For 0 = 1 (the Einstein-de Sitter 
universe), H0t0 = 2/3. For 0 &lt; 1, 
1 0 2 2 H0t0 = (1  0)1/2  2(1  0)3/2 ln 0  1 + 0 (1  0)1/2 for p = 0 and 0 &lt; 1 . 
(11) 
One may verify that for 0  0  1, 1  H0t0  2/3. 
A formula similar to equation (11) holds for 0 &gt; 1, with H0t0 &lt; 2/3. Thus, matter-
dominated universes have H0t0 &lt; 1. Adding the radiation that we know (the microwave 
background radiation) decreases H0t0 very slightly. 
Historically, equation (11) has been a crucial test of cosmological theories and the 
source of many newspaper articles declaring crisis in cosmology. Before the late 1940s, 
the Hubble constant was estimated to be several times larger than it is now, and for a 
time this was in clear conict with the age of the Earth. This discrepancy gave impetus 
to the steady-state theory, in which H0t0 is unbounded. More recently, during the 
1990s estimates of both H0 and t0 improved and there again seemed to be a signicant 
discrepancy with standard models. 
This discrepancy has lessened, if not entirely disappeared, during the last two years. 
To translate the test into more common units, we write 
h t0H0t0 = 1.023 (12)10 Gyr 
where H0 = 100 h km s1 Mpc1 and 1 Gyr=109 yr. The latest results of the Hubble 
Space Telescope Cepheid Key Project indicate h = 0.71  0.07 (Sakai et al. 1999, astro-
ph/9909269). The error bar is dominated by systematic errors, the largest of which 
remains the distance to the Large Magellanic Cloud, a nearby dwarf galaxy containing 
many Cepheid variables. 
For a long time the ages of the oldest stars in our galaxy was thought to exceed 16 
Gyr, which was a real embarrassment for matter-dominated models and especially the 
simplest cold dark matter model (with m = 1 which predicted H0t0 = 2/3. However, 
recently the distances to globular clusters in our galaxy were revised upwards based 
indirectly on astrometric observations by the Hipparcos satellite. For a given measured 
ux, this meant that the stars must be more luminous, hence younger. Chaboyer et al 
(1998, ApJ 449, 96) now estimate the age of the oldest globular clusters as 11.5  1.3 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Baryogenesis, CMB Basics</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://de.arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/9902027</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Radiation Era, Nucleosynthesis</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://de.arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0010171</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>CMB Anisotropy 3</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-942-cosmology-fall-2001/resources/cmbfluct03/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>where T is the Thomson cross section and the factor outside the parentheses on the 
right-hand side is the Thomson scattering rate (up to a factor c = 1). The electrons have 
proper number density ne and peculiar velocity vi . (The unperturbed electron densitye
may be used when considering primary anisotropies because the terms in parentheses are 
all rst-order perturbations.) The photon number density uctuation is   n /n = 
3 
4  / where n and  are the photon number density and energy density, respectively. 
The perturbation can be obtained from an angular average of the anisotropy:  = 
3  d/(4). (Note that n  T 3 implies  = 3 ln T .) 
Heuristically, equation (10) is easy to understand. Scattering corresponds to absorp
tion (the  term) and re-radiation in a dierent direction. To the extent that the 
scattering is isotropic in the electron frame, the emitted radiation is just the angular 
average of the absorbed radiation ( 1  is the angular average of ). Scattering therefore3 
isotropizes the radiation eld, a phenomenon familiar to anyone driving a car through 
fog. The second term is due to the motion of the electron gas: scattering by moving 
targets introduces a dipole anisotropy. 
The third term, ij ninj , arises from the dependence of Thomson scattering on di
rection and polarization. It is easy to understand qualitatively from Rayleighs Law of 
scattered light. When a photon scatters from an electron, the incoming and outgoing 
momenta lie in a plane called the scattering plane. The photon is polarized with its elec
tric eld orientation either in the plane or perpendicular to it. In the former case, the 
scattered ux is reduced by a factor cos2  compared with the perpendicular case where 
 is the scattering angle. This result follows classically from the angular dependence 
of electric dipole radiation caused when the incoming light makes the electron oscillate. 
Another way to express the same result is to say that the scattering rate is proportional 
to ( 1  2)2 where  1 and  2 are the polarization directions for the incoming and outgoing 
photons, respectively. 
These considerations imply that the dierential cross section for unpolarized incident 
radiation is proportional to 1 + cos2 . Normalizing the total cross section, we nd 
d 3T = (1 + cos 2 ) . (11)d 16 
If the incident radiation is polarized, then the cross-section becomes a 22 matrix giving 
scattering rates for each orthogonal polarization. Thus, the dependence of the scattering 
rate on polarization and direction add corrections to the isotropic scattering implied by 
the  + 1  terms in equation (10). These corrections are only a few percent for the3 
temperature anisotropy but they are crucial for polarization. Scattering induces a small 
polarization of the CMB. We will ignore the polarization and the quadrupolar scattering 
term ij ninj in the following. 
Note that the unperturbed (spatially homogeneous) electron density may be used 
in equation (10) because it multiplies a rst-order quantity. Spatial variations in the 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>electron density only appear in second-order perturbation theory. 
In evaluating the primary CMB anisotropy, we need not take into account that recom
bination takes place at dierent times in dierent places. The reason physically is that 
the radiation eld is in nearly perfect thermal equilibrium with the electrons. For perfect 
(everywhere homogeneous and isotropic) blackbody radiation, nonrelativistic scattering 
by an electron gas at rest with respect to the radiation eld has no eect whatsoever on 
the radiation. In the absence of pre-existing CMB uctuations, scattering alone cannot 
produce any anisotropy no matter how inhomogeneous the electron distribution. The 
only possible eect occurs from the motion of the electron gas, and this is included 
already in equation (10). 
3.2 Solution of the radiative transfer equation 
We can easily integrate equation (9) in the instantaneous recombination approximation, 
in which we assume that ne drops sharply to zero at  = e. Prior to this time the photon 
mean-free path is very short; we assume it is eectively zero. Under these conditions, 
integrating equation (9) along the backwards light cone to e  0  e gives the desired 
CMB anisotropy seen by the fundamental observer at  = 0: 
 e 
0(n i) = e + e  0 + d  ( + )ret (12) 
0 
where subscript e means to evaluate the quantity at  = e,  = e = 0  e, 
in direction ni (with a minus sign because the photon travels toward decreasing ). 
Subscript ret means to evaluate the quantity in the integrand at retarded time  = 
0  . 
The rst three terms on the right-hand side of equation (12) are all boundary terms 
which arise as constants of integration. The rst two represent brightness temperature 
and gravitational potential uctuations present at recombination and are the major 
contributors to CMB anisotropy. The third term, the gravitational potential at  = 0, is 
an unobservable monopole contribution. The integral term is anisotropy produced after 
recombination due to time-changing gravitational potentials. 
Before examining the physical content of equation (12) in the next section, it is 
instructive to compare with the exact solution of the full radiative transfer equation. 
Including the Thomson scattering terms of equation (10), equation (9) has solution 
(Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga 1996) 
 0 
0(n i) = d e T() n ii +   + aneT 1  + vei ni + 1ij ninj (13) 
0 3 2 ret 
where   
T()  d (aneT)ret (14) 
0 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>function,   ikx d3(k,  ) = (1)(x,  ) e x (62) 
 
where r =  x . The transfer function contains the same information as either its one | |
dimensional or three-dimensional Fourier transform. Thus, the choice of approach is 
purely a matter of convenience, numerical ease or accuracy, and/or ease of interpretation. 
Recalling the initial condition (k, 0) = 1 for the transfer function, from equation (62) 
it follows that (1)(x,  ) is the Greens function for initial condition ( x, 0) = D(x). The 
initial perturbation is sheet-like (i.e., constant on planes of constant Cartesian coordinate 
x) rather than point-like. We use the superscript (1) to distinguish such plane-parallel 
Greens functions from the spherical variety. 
Analytic solutions for the plane-parallel Greens functions in the radiation era are 
given by Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2002). Because the dynamics involve two potentials 
(for gravity and entropy), initial conditions must be set for both. The calculations have 
all assumed isentropic initial conditions with (x,  ) = 0 at  = 0. It would be interesting 
to work out Greens functions for isocuravture initial conditions with (x, 0) = 0 and 
(x, 0)  1/r (so that the entropy perturbation 2 is a delta function) but this has not 
been done. 
Bashinsky (2001) constructed numerical solutions for the isentropic case by evolv
ing equations (52) in one space dimension and time, with 2 = 2/x2 . Usually it is 
much harder to accurately solve partial dierential equations than ordinary dierential 
equations, and this is an argument for the Fourier space approach. However, the equa
tions in question are linear wave equations and they may be solved by the method of 
characteristics. This method is fast and accurate. 
Figure 1 shows the results of this numerical integration for the radiation and CDM 
gravitational potentials at recombination. The initial conditions were (1)(x, 0) = D(x)r 
and (1)(x, 0) = 0. The delta function separated into left-going and right-going waves, c 
whose evolution spread (1) over space and diminished the central peak. The gravitar 
tional potential hill of the radiation caused outward-directed gravitational forces which 
expelled the CDM away from x = 0. The CDM has a central cusp reecting the initial 
repulsive singularity in the gravitational potential (1); this cusp is preserved because r 
the CDM particles have no thermal motion. In fact, once the universe becomes matter-
dominated (1)(x,  ) stops evolving, as may be seen from the second of equations (52) in c 
the limit y  1. 
Figure 2 shows three snapshots of the time evolution of the Greens functions for 
the radiation and CDM potentials. Only the range x &gt; 0 needs to be plotted since the 
Greens functions depend only on x. Note that while the amplitude of r decreases | |
rapidly with time, c changes much more slowly and becomes constant in the matter 
era as expected. We also see the eect of changing the baryon content. This changes 
the photon-baryon sound speed in equation (28), thereby changing the distance to the 
29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>0.5 
0 
0.6 0.4 0.2 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 
x / c rec 
Figure 1: Plane-parallel Greens functions for the potentials r (solid) and c (dashed) 
at recombination, in the uid approximation. The cosmological parameter values are 
m = 0.35,  = 0.65, bh2 = 0.02, and h = 0.65. By recombination the universe has 
become matter-dominated. From Bashinsky (2001). 
wavefront. Adding baryons decreases the sound speed. 
The density and velocity perturbations of photons, baryons, and the CDM uid 
follow from r , c and their derivatives. The photon perturbations contribute directly to 
CMB anisotropy while the CDM perturbations eventually seed the formation of galaxies. 
Figure 3 shows the plane-parallel Greens functions at recombination for the photon 
and CDM density uctuations. (Recall that b =  in the uid approximation.) The 
singularities of  and c arise from the d2/dx2 term of the Poisson equation. Comparing 
with Figure 1, we see why these singularities occur at the wavefronts for  but at x = 0 
for CDM. The central spike for the CDM is negative because of the repulsive sign of the 
initial gravitational potential peak (top row of Fig. 2). It is surrounded by positive tails 
because of mass conservation: the CDM pushed out from x = 0 piles up into the region 
between x = 0 and the acoustic wavefront. 
Note from Figures 13 that our spacetime is unperturbed outside of the acoustic 
wavefront. This is a consequence of our initial condition that left the metric unperturbed 
everywhere except at x = 0. Had we instead made  a Dirac delta function with zero 
velocity perturbation, then the gravitational potential  would have been nonzero for all 
x. However, our treatment in the earlier sections shows that the gravitational potential, 
not the density, is the fundamental physical quantity for CMB anisotropy. That is why 
our Greens functions are chosen so that (x, 0) = D(x). 
The Dirac delta function contributions of  (x,  ) at the acoustic wavefronts make 
30  (1)(x) and  (1)(x) r c 2 
1.5 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>where t0( ) = a d and t = a d . The density perturbation is computed at xed  
using /= (d ln /dt)t = 2(t)/t 0. If   = 0, then t = t0 giving /= 2. 
This is simply the gravitational redshift: clocks run slower in a gravitational potential 
well. 
If   = 0, the gravitational redshift is time-dependent and a more careful calculation 
is needed. Matters are complicated because of the particular, somewhat arbitrary choice 
of constant- hypersurfaces implied by our metric equation (1). Our intuition is not 
always a good guide for physics on scales larger than the Hubble length. Fortunately, 
the Einstein equations will guide us to the correct solution even if we cannot guess it 
from Newtonian considerations. 
The photon density perturbation on large scales follows simply from combining equa
tion (42) with equation (34). (One must combine the photon and matter perturbations 
with appropriate weights to obtain the net density perturbation.) The result is 
9 2 = cw 2(1 + y)y (y) + (2y/3) 2 . (43)e  2 4 
Similarly, the large-scale peculiar velocity follows from equation (20). For a matter 
plus radiation universe on scales much larger than the curvature and acoustic scales, 
uc = u . The velocity potential is then 
1 y1 + y u = ey (y) . (44)2 1 + (3/4)y 
6.1 Isentropic and Isocurvature modes 
We now have all the ingredients needed to compute the CMB anisotropy on large angular 
scales. The treatment here is equivalent to that of Sachs &amp; Wolfe (1967) for isentropic 
initial uctuations and extends their treatment to more general initial conditions. 
Equation (39) has two physically relevant quantities: the gravitational potential  
and specic entropy perturbation . Because the equation is second-order, one might 
think there are two physical solutions for any , and therefore a vast family of solutions. 
However, we have seen that  cannot change with time over distance scales larger than the 
acoustic length. Moreover, there is only one combination of the homogeneous solutions 
of equations (41) that remains nite as y  0. Consequently, physical initial conditions 
set in the very early universe must be a linear combination of the nite solution with 
2 = 0 but  = 0 and of the nite solution with 2 = 0 but  = 0. Because the 
evolution equations are all linear in the perturbations, then general solution is a linear 
combination of the solutions starting from these two types of initial conditions. 
The two sets of solutions we have identied are called isentropic and isocurvature. 
In both cases we assume that the uctuations are produced in the very early universe. 
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Thus, treating both the metric perturbations and  as being of the same order, we can 
ireplace dxi/d by nin equation (6). A similar argument shows that we can drop the 
(/ni)(dni/d ) term: both factors are rst-order quantities. This is equivalent to 
neglecting gravitational lensing of anisotropies. Lensing by nonlinear (highly overdense) 
structures at low redshift has a small eect on the CMB on arcminute angular scales 
(Seljak 1996). 
We are left with calculating the rate of change of proper energy E, which is straight
forward from the geodesic equation. The result is 
d ln(aE) = n ii +   . (8)d 
The factor a accounts for the cosmological redshift while the rst term on the right-hand 
side is the familiar gravitational redshift. (Both terms arise from g00.) The second term, 
due to spatial curvature uctuations, is unfamiliar in the Newtonian limit but can be 
signicant for photons and other relativistic particles. 
Because the right-hand side of equation (8) is independent of E, it follows that the 
d ln(aE)/d contribution to equation (6) cannot induce any energy-dependence of the 
brightness temperature perturbation. (As in gravitational lensing, gravity is achro
matic.) The dominant collision process, Compton scattering, is also independent of 
energy (at temperatures much less than the electron mass). Thus, unless some other 
physical process causes a departure of the photon spectrum from blackbody, /E = 0 
to an excellent approximation. None of the standard sources of primary anisotropy 
(primeval potential, density, or entropy perturbations) generates any signicant black
body distortion, so we assume E = 0 in the following. (Departures of order the 
baryon-to-photon ratio 1010 are generated during recombination, but these are orders 
of magnitude smaller than the eects we retain.) 
Combining equations (6), (7), and (8), we obtain the fundamental equation of CMB 
anisotropy: 
d d =   + n ii = n ii +   + . (9)d d c 
Equation (9) has a very simple physical interpretation. Aside from changes due to 
gravitational redshift, time-varying spatial curvature uctuations, or radiative processes 
(emission, absorption, and scattering), the CMB anisotropy (brightness temperature 
uctuation) is constant along null geodesics. 
For completeness, we present without derivation the collision terms arising from non
relativistic photon-electron scattering: 
d = aneT  + 1  + vei ni + 1ij ninj (10)d 3 2 c 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>The 0i component of the Einstein equations helps us to understand the time-derivative 
terms in equation (19): 
a2   + = 4Ga2 ( + p)v i . (20)  a i 
The term in brackets is the momentum density measured by a fundamental observer, or 
T 0i in an orthonormal basis. In general relativity, momentum density (and momentum 
ux, i.e. stress) is a source of spacetime curvature. The momentum density, hence 
its eect on curvature, is typically smaller than  by a factor v/c. However, it is 
gravitationally signicant on large scales (Hubble-length and beyond). Thus, the time-
derivative terms in equation (19) are unimportant on scales much less than the Hubble 
length but are important on larger scales. They are important for CMB anisotropy on 
scales larger than a degree or so. 
With the neglect of gravitomagnetism and gravitational radiation, the metric pertur
bations follow from spatial scalars and not, for example, a vector potential (Bertschinger 
1996). In the limit of small uctuations, it follows that the velocity elds of the various 
matter and radiation components are the gradients of scalar elds. That is, the velocity 
elds have no vorticity (or are longitudinal, in the language of classical eld theory). 
Using this fact, we may write 
v i = ij 
a j ua (21) 
for the mean (uid) velocity of any component a (e.g. photons, baryons, CDM, neutrinos) 
where u(xi, ) is the velocity potential and ij is the inverse of the unperturbed spatial 3
metric ij dened so that the comoving spatial line element is dl2 = ij dxidxj in equation 
(1). This fact allows us to combine equations (19) and (20) into a cosmological Poisson 
equation, 
 2 + 3K  = 4Ga2  
a + 3 a(a + pa)ua . (22) aa 
Aside from the curvature and velocity potential terms, equation (22) is an obvious gen
eralization of the Newtonian Poisson equation. The source for the metric perturbation 
must be  rather than  because  =  = 0 for an unperturbed Robertson-Walker 
spacetime with  = . The presence of the velocity potential shows that, in cosmology, 
momentum as well as mass-energy is a source for Newtonian gravity. This should not 
be surprising, given that momentum in one Lorentz frame transforms into energy in 
another frame. It can be shown that a small, spatially-varying transformation of the 
time coordinate can be performed which eliminates the momentum density (basically by 
transforming to the local uid rest frame) and thereby converts the term in brackets to a 
pure density uctuation (Bardeen 1980). However, it proves more convenient to use the 
coordinates implied by equation (1) and simply evaluate both the density and momen
tum contributions to gravity in these coordinates. (For a discussion of other coordinate 
systems, see Bardeen 1980 and Bertschinger 1996.) 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>the behavior of the neutrinos by supposing that they trace photons, with  =  and 
p / = p / . This is not correct on scales smaller than the Hubble length, but it 
is a good approximation on larger scales because the neutrinos have then not yet had 
enough time to separate from the photons. Our assumption overestimates the neutrino 
perturbations on small scales because, in the absence of collisions, neutrinos easily dif
fuse out of perturbations. However, the eects of this error are not large because the 
gravitational eect of neutrinos is important only during the radiation-dominated era, 
and during this time the photon perturbations rapidly oscillate on small scales so that 
their time average is small. Doing better would require that we solve the Boltzmann 
equation for neutrinos (Ma &amp; Bertschinger 1995), which will not be discussed here. 
The source term in equation (31) is proportional to the entropy per unit mass of cold 
dark matter, 
  
ln T 3 
 
c  
=   c = p  c2 
w  
cc2 
w , (33) 
so that 
 2 = 4Ga2 cy (  c) . (34) 
Neutrino eects are included implicitly through the eective sound speed cw . 
Equation (31) is rather remarkable. It allows us to compute the gravitational po
tential through a damped, driven wave equation whose source is the specic entropy 
perturbation. In Newtonian gravitation we think of the potential as being determined 
by action-at-a-distance (eq. 19 without the time-derivative terms). However, the Ein
stein equations also enforce local energy-momentum conservation, providing us with 
alternatives for the computation of the metric perturbations. Heuristically, the potential 
 is computed from the instantaneous distribution of energy density (and momentum 
density, as may be shown by combining eqs. 19 and 20). Because the source of the 
potential may have acoustic waves, then it, too, displays acoustic waves. Note that the 
wave speed is the eective sound speed cw . 
True gravitational waves (which propagate at c) are described by a transverse-traceless 
metric perturbation hij , which we are ignoring here. Thus, despite its appearance, equa
tion (31) really is gravitational action-at-a-distance. Although gravitational waves are 
needed to restore causality, we are ignoring them here for the CMB anisotropy calcula
tion. This is justied in linear perturbation theory by the fact that gravity waves have 
no coupling to the scalar-mode (density and entropy) perturbations we are consider
ing here. In linear perturbation theory, the eects of density and entropy perturbations 
propagate at the speed of sound, not the speed of light. 
Our next step is to obtain an evolution equation for the entropy potential . Using 
the fact that a2cy is constant, from equations (34) together with equations (28)(30) 
we obtain 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>1  (1)2eff = 1/3  (1) +  (1) 
2
1
0
b= 0.03 h2 
b= 0 
| | | | | 
 c  0.5 c 0 0.5 c c rec rec rec recx 
Figure 4: Plane-parallel Greens function for the combined intrinsic ( 1  ) plus gravita3 
tional redshift contributions to CMB anisotropy at recombination in the uid approxi
mation, for the same parameters as shown in Fig. 2. The solid (dashed) lines show the 
results for b h2 = 0.03 (b h2 = 0). The quantity e not only gives the Sachs-Wolfe 
contribution to CMB anisotropy on large scales, it also measures the departure of the 
photon-baryon uid from hydrostatic equilibrium. Based on Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger 
(2001). 
uctuations that will be measured in the sky? No. That is impossible because the uc
tuations originate from random uctuations in the early universe (quantum uctuations 
during ination or perhaps thermal uctuations in some rst-order phase transition). At 
best, we can predict only the statistical properties of the CMB anisotropy. But then 
what statistical properties should we calculate? 
Ination predicts a gaussian random eld of primeval potential uctuations. That is, 
in a Fourier decomposition (here assuming a K = 0 background) 
k( x,) = d3ke ix (k,) , (66) 
each mode (k) is a zero-mean, normally distributed random variable. Actually, the 
Fourier transform of a real eld is a complex eld, so each mode is a pair of normally 
distributed variables with the same variance. Also note that our denition of the Fourier 
transform here diers from that in equation (59). 
For a Gaussian random eld, the two-point correlation, i.e. the covariance of eld 
values at dierent points, completely characterizes the statistical properties of the eld. 
For (k), its covariance denes the power spectrum (or spectral density) P (k): 
 (k) (k)  P (k) D(k  k) . (67) 
Had we used the alternative Fourier transformation denition implied by equation (59), 
the right-hand side would be larger by a factor (2)3 . Note the three-dimensional Dirac 
33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Laplacian operators in equations (31) and (37) both operate on the same quantity, namely 
 + /y. This suggests that we consider linear combinations of  and  to separate the 
wave components. Amazingly, there is a simple set of variables that does the trick: 
 2cw  r =  + , c =   r . (49) cs y 
We use the subscripts r for radiation (the photon-baryon uid, with an approximate 
inclusion of neutrinos) and c for CDM. The reason for doing so is that the Poisson 
equation now holds separately for each potential with a corresponding source (for K = 0): 
a, = 4Ga2r  + 3 u  2r a 
a= 4Ga2c c + 3 u , (50)   2c a 
where r u + cuc 4  , r (  ) +   + b . (51) u  r + c  3 
Thus, we may interpret r as the gravitational potential produced by radiation (pho
tons, neutrinos, and baryons) while c is the gravitational potential produced by CDM. 
(One must be careful not to push the Newtonian analogy too far, since here we have 
contributions from the peculiar velocity potentials.) Equations (50) are equivalent to 
equation (22) applied separately to each of our two uids. 
Equations (31) and (37) now separate into a pair of coupled wave equations with the 
expected behavior: 
a2 a 3(c2 + ) r  2c2  4 + 3c2 
2 w s w2r + 3(1 + cs )  r + 3cw  c + c = cs2  2r , a a 4e 2y 3e 2y2
aa 3
2 2 2c + 3(cw  cs )  r + 3  c  r +2cs 2  3 c = 0 , (52)2 a a 4e 2y 3e 2y
where (y) is a ratio of two quartic polynomials given by Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger 
(2002). 
The rst of equations (52) shows that perturbations in the photon-baryon uid indeed 
propagate as sound waves with speed cs. As the sound wave passes by a CDM uid 
element, its gravity acts on the CDM, causing the CDM to evolve as given by the second 
equation. 
25</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>distance e = 0  e. The subscript e stands for emitter and reminds us that we are 
looking at radiation emitted from a photosphere, the edge of the plasma layer that exists 
for  &gt; e, i.e. for times  &lt; e. We see the CMB as though we live in a transparent 
spherical cavity of radius e beyond which is a hot glowing plasma. Of course, e really 
represents a boundary in time rather than space; every fundamental observer has a 
dierent photosphere. 
In the absence of emission, absorption, and scattering, conservation of photons im
plies that the photon phase space density is conserved along null geodesics. In the 
language of basic astronomy, dI /ds = 0 where I is the specic intensity and ds mea
sures path length. However, unlike most other astronomical situations, the path length 
measures not just distance in space; d/ds measures the rate of change in phase space. 
The radiation eld varies with time, energy (photon frequency) and photon direction as 
well as with position in space. We will work out these dependencies to calculate the 
CMB anisotropy. First, however, we must examine the cosmological radiative transfer 
equation more closely. 
3.1 Derivation of radiative transfer equation 
In place of the specic intensity, we use the radiation brightness temperature to character
ize the phase space distribution. Let E be the photon energy measured by a fundamental 
observer and let ni = pi/E be a unit vector (with respect to the observers orthonormal 
basis) in the direction of photon travel. The brightness temperature Tbr(xi, , E, ni) is 
dened implicitly through I = B (Tbr) where B (T) is the Planck function and I is 
the specic intensity measured by the fundamental observer at (xi, ). 
Because the radiation perturbations are small, we write Tbr = a1T0(1 + ) where 
T0 is the present unperturbed blackbody temperature and 2  1. Our  coincides 
with Peacocks T/T; most other workers write T/T. Thus, the photon phase space 
distribution (summed over polarizations) is 
f(x i, , E, n i) = c2I 
2h43 = fP  aE 
1 +   
, where fP()  2h3 [exp(/T 0)  1]1 . 
(4) 
[The unperturbed temperature T0 can, in fact, never be measured because we see 
only the perturbed universe. Separating the radiation eld into an unperturbed back
ground plus perturbations is really a ction chosen for the calculational convenience of 
linear perturbation theory. In practice, T0 is replaced by the average of the brightness 
temperature taken over the sky. Anisotropy measurements are made by subtracting pairs 
of brightness temperatures from dierent directions in the sky. Uncertainty in T0 aects 
only the monopole anisotropy, which is unmeasurable and consequently ignored by 
observers of CMB anisotropy. The same is true of the dipole anisotropy, which re
ceives contributions from both the observers motion and an intrinsic anisotropy due to 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>of the modication made in deriving equation (37), these equations are not exactly 
equivalent to the uid equations (29) plus the Poisson equation (22) when neutrinos are 
included. They agree with the approximations made by Seljak (1994) and Bashinsky &amp; 
Bertschinger (2001, 2002). We will nd in Section 9 that the two-uid approximation 
made here is remarkably accurate. 
6 Large-scale anisotropy: the Sachs-Wolfe Eect 
Using the wave equations we have derived for the gravitational potential  and entropy 
potential , it is possible analytically to solve for the perturbations on large scales. In 
this context, large scale means that we can neglect c2 
w 2 and cs22 relative to ( a/a)2 
in equations (31) and (37). This is valid provided that we consider scales larger than the 
comoving acoustic length, dened by 
cs . (38) Lac  aH 
The acoustic length subtends an angle of about one degree at recombination. We also 
will neglect the spatial curvature K, which makes a negligible contribution to equations 
(31) and (37) before and during recombination because K ( a/a)2 .| |
Under these conditions, equations (31) and (37) reduce to ordinary dierential equa
tions in time. We change variables from  to y through equation (3), obtaining 
  3c2 
y y w+ 3 1 + c 2  (cw e)2 
(39) + 2(1 + y) w + 4(1 + y) = (1 + y)  2 
and 
(c2 2 
y y 
2 2 + 2(1 + y) + 1 + 3cw  3cs = s  cy)e 2 
y 2 2 , (40)1 + y  
where a prime denotes y . We have retained the Laplacian terms that link the potential 
and density because we have said nothing yet about the relative sizes of  and . 
As y  0, the gravitational potential makes a negligible contribution to  in equation 
(40), at least insofar as that contribution feeds back to equation (39). Thus, in solving 
for the gravitational potential it is safe to drop the right-hand side of equation (40), 
which then becomes an ordinary dierential equation in y whose solutions as y  0 
are   ln y and  = (x) with y  = 0. The logarithmic solution is unphysical; it 
corresponds to a large separation between photons and CDM at the big bang, which 
does not occur in standard cosmology. Thus, the only possibility for the entropy is to 
have a constant or spatially-varying distribution of primeval entropy uctuations that is 
constant in time early in the radiation era. 
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>l3 
2 
1 
0 
0 500 1000 1500 2000 
l 5
4
l (l+1) C
Figure 6: The angular power spectrum of CMB temperature anisotropy calculated using 
the two-uid approximation (solid line, including the Doppler contribution) and using 
CMBFAST (dashed line). The CDM model parameters are the same as for the thick 
solid curve in Fig. 5. From Bashinsky (2001). 
spectrum. With a phenomenological correction for photon diusion, the error of our nu
merical calculations in uid approximation is within 5% on angular scales from 2 to a 
few arcminutes, see Fig. 9. It can also compute the gravitational radiation (tensor mode) 
and gravitational lensing (secondary) contributions to anisotropy. 
The agreement between the two-uid approximation and CMBFAST is much better 
in Figure 6 than in Figure 5. There are several reasons for this improvement. First, all 
injthe anisotropy contributions in equation (80) have now been included except for ij n
(polarization and anisotropic scattering terms). Second, photon diusion was included 
approximately in a phenomenological manner. Third, recombination was gradual rather 
than instantaneous. Seljak (1994) included these eects in his earlier two-uid treat
ment, however he did not include the integrated Sachs-Wolfe eect and he used the 
instantaneous recombination approximation, with some analytic corrections that are not 
as accurate as our numerical integrations. Our two-uid model achieves accuracy better 
than 5% in Cl for l  1500. 
It appears that the approximate description given by equations (52) captures well 
the essential physics of the cosmological dynamics of the CMB photons and the other 
components with which they interact. Although CMBFAST remains the method of 
choice for accurate calculations and data analysis, the simplied model presented in 
39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Given the time-independent solution for the entropy , it is easy to solve equation 
(39) for (y). The homogeneous ( = 0) solutions for (y) are (Kodama &amp; Sasaki 1984, 
1986) 
1(y) = 1 + 2 
9y  8 
9y2  16 
9y3 + 16 
9 1 + y 
y3 , 2(y) = 1 + y 
y3 . (41) 
10 1For y  1, 1 = 9 (1  ). The density perturbations associated with 1 grow in 16 y + 
the matter-dominated era y  1 (hence 1 is often called the growing mode) although 
1 itself does not. The other mode, 2, is called the decaying mode. From the these 
homogeneous solutions, we can construct particular solutions subject to any desired 
initial conditions. Using the Greens function method we can also construct solutions 
with nonzero 2. 
Before presenting the solutions, we recall from equation (13) that the CMB anisotropy 
icomputation requires  and v in addition to . On large scales, where pressure-gradient 
forces are unimportant so that dark matter and photons move together, we can deter
mine these quantities from the Einstein equations without having to solve the coupled 
equations of motion for all the matter and radiation species. This is because, on scales 
larger than the acoustic length, the matter plus radiation behaves as a single uctu
ating perfect uid. The Einstein equations have built-in redundancy  they enforce 
local energy-momentum conservation  so we can use them to get the net energy den
sity and velocity perturbations without having to solve the uid equations. (That is a 
radical concept to a Newtonian physicist, but it is a direct consequence of the Einstein 
equations!) 
From equation (19), dropping the curvature and Laplacian terms (they are both small 
on scales larger than the Hubble length) and neglecting anisotropic stress (i.e. setting 
 = ), we obtain 
 
= 2 (aa + ) = 2y (y) . (42) 
Note that we are using a gravitational eld equation to solve for the mass density pertur
bation, having used time-evolution equations to solve for the potential. By contrast, in 
Newtonian physics we are used to solving time evolution equations for the uid variables 
and then solving a gravitational eld equation for the potential. In general relativity, we 
have more exibility in how to compute gravity. 
Equation (42) has a simple physical interpretation. By assumption, the density is 
smoothly varying on scales of the Hubble length. Thus, each Hubble volume behaves like 
a homogeneous universe (slightly closed or slightly open depending on the sign of ). In 
a homogeneous model, the density and cosmic proper time t measured by a fundamental 
observer are related by (x,  )  (Gt2)1 . Because of the long-wavelength perturbations 
in g00, however, the relative clock rate between proper time t(x,  ) and conformal time 
depends on position: dt/d = a( )(1 + ). Thus, we may write t = t0( ) + t(x,  ) 
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>2 2  a2 22 + 1 + 3cw  3cs    (cs  cw ) 2 a 
a 3 c2 a 
2 2 w= 4Ga2 y(cs  cw ) c c + 3 uc +4 c2  c2 c  + 4 u . (35) a as w 
Using equations (28) and (30), we obtain 
   3 c2 3  b 1 
w c =  + 4 cs2  cw  + b 1 +  1  c . (36)2 4 
Using this result, if we compare the right-hand sides of equations (22) and (35), we 
see that they would be identical for our multicomponent uid if we neglect neutrinos. 
Including neutrinos requires approximation because we are not solving the Boltzmann 
equation for neutrinos. One approximation is to suppose that neutrinos have identical 
density and velocity perturbations as photons. Under this assumption,  would simply 
be replaced by  +  in equation (22) and similarly for p . This assumption was made 
in deriving equations (33) and (35). However, we know that this approximation is not 
exact, and so we are free to consider other approximations that make errors of the same 
order. That is, we can consider corrections to equation (36) that are of order  . 
We choose to approximate the right-hand side of equation (36) by dropping the 
factors in parentheses (Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger 2002). This approximation is exact 
when neutrinos are neglected. The reason for making this choice is that now equations 
(35) becomes a simple wave equation that is very similar to equation (31), 
2 2  a2 2 2 22 + 1 + 3cw  3cs    (cs  cw ) 2 = y(cs  cw )  2 + 3K  . (37) a 
This equation is exact only when neutrinos are neglected. However, as we will see in 
Section 7, when neutrinos are included it preserves the correct propagation of sound 
waves through the photon-baryon uid at sound speed cs. 
The two-uid approximation introduced here is equivalent to including neutrinos 
assuming that they have the same dynamics as photons. The baryon abundance is 
increased over the true abundance by a factor (1 +  / ) so that the photon-baryon 
sound speed is unchanged. Finally, the CDM abundance is decreased so that the total 
matter density c + b is unchanged. This model has the advantage of preserving the 
important time and length scales eq and cs d while working with perfect uids. For 
more discussion of the two-uid approximations, see Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2002). 
Equations (31) and (37) completely characterize the evolution of matter, radiation, 
and gravity in our simplied two-uid model (CDM and the photon-baryon uid, with 
neutrinos added in a way that preserves the photon-baryon sound speed). Because 
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>a possible large-scale gradient of brightness temperature across our Hubble volume. The 
choice of rest frame for fundamental observers is arbitrary; in practice it is chosen so 
that the dipole anisotropy vanishes at the solar system barycenter.] 
In general, the brightness temperature is a function of photon energy. However, we 
will see that for primary CMB anisotropies, the energy-dependence disappears:  = 
(xi, , ni). That is, in every direction, a fundamental observer nds that the specic 
intensity is a perfect black-body as a function of photon energy but with the tempera
ture varying with photon direction. A simple example of this behavior is the Doppler 
anisotropy derived by Peacock in his Section 9.4. However, it holds also for all forms of 
CMB anisotropy that do not involve large-amplitude perturbations. 
Secondary anisotropies induced by nonlinear structures at low redshift often de
pend on energy (i.e. the spectrum is distorted from blackbody). An example is the 
Sunyaev-Zeldovich eect caused by scattering of CMB photons by hot ionized gas 
in clusters of galaxies. The spectral signature makes it easy to distinguish Sunyaev-
Zeldovich anisotropy from primary CMB anisotropy. These notes consider only the 
primary anisotropies. 
iOur goal is to determine 0(ni) = ( = 0, 0, n), the anisotropy measured by the 
fundamental observer at the origin. (The anisotropy measured by a moving observer at 
the origin, e.g. one on the Earth, follows by a simple Doppler shift following Peacock eq. 
9.62.) We use the fact that the photon phase space density is conserved in the absence of 
emission, absorption, and scattering. From equation (4), the total change in the phase 
space density is (assuming 2  1) 
df aEf  aE d ln(aE) d df , = = d 1 +  P 1 +  d  d d c 
d   dxi  dE  dni 
where = + + + . (5)d xi d E d ni d 
We may thus write the radiative transfer equation as 
  dxi  dE  dni d ln(aE) d + + + = + (6) xi d E d ni d d d c 
where the term with a subscript c accounts for collisions (emission, absorption, and 
scattering of photons). 
We can simplify equation (6) by linearizing it assuming small perturbations in both 
 and the phase space trajectories. From the metric, using the fact that we dened ni to 
be the photon direction measured by a fundamental observer in an orthonormal frame, 
we have 
(1  ) dxi 
i = n . (7)(1 + ) d 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>(1) (1) 
r c e 15 3 
2 
1 
0  0.1  e 1.5 3 
1 2 
0.5 1 
0 0 10 
5 
0 
0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 
0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0 0.2 0.4 0.6  rec3
0.4 
2 
0.2 1 
0 0 
0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 
x / c x / c rec rec 
Figure 2: Time evolution of the plane-parallel Greens functions for the potentials r 
(left) and c (right) in the uid approximation. The solid (dashed) lines show the results 
for bh2 = 0.03 (bh2 = 0). The three rows give snapshots at the times (0.1e, e, and 
rec = 2.5e). The speed of sound is decreased below c/
3 by the inclusion of baryons. 
From Bashinsky (2001). 
a signicant contribution to the total CMB anisotropy. So does the dip at x = 0. To 
understand the physics of this dip, let us examine the combination of photon density and 
gravitational potential appearing in the Sachs-Wolfe eect on large scales, which is given 
by equation (48) without the Doppler and   (integrated Sachs-Wolfe) contributions: 
1 e  3  +  . (63) 
(Recall that  is dened here as the fractional perturbation in photon number density.) 
The plane-parallel Greens function for e at recombination is shown in Figure 4. Note 
that the relation of e to potential on small scales in position space is quite dierent 
1from the e 3  of the large-scale Sachs-Wolfe eect. However, this relation still holds 
if one integrates the Greens functions over x to get the long wavelength contributions. 
The positive Dirac delta functions more than compensate for the negative  (x) behind 
the acoustic wavefronts so that e (x) dx  1 (r + c) dx.3 
31</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>4 is the Thomson optical depth (and not a conformal time). Equation (13) is the familiar 
solution of the radiative transfer equation. Emission (the terms in square brackets) at 
optical depth T is reduced by an exponential absorption factor. In contrast with equation 
(12), there is no explicit indication of the photosphere. The radial integration is taken 
over the entire past lightcone to  = 0 ( = 0). Contributions from  &gt; e (which may 
be dened by T(e) = 1 as in stellar astrophysics) are exponentially suppressed. 3 
Equation (13) may be claried by dening the integral visibility function 
	 0  
( )  exp  
 d  a( )ne( )T = exp [T(0   )] . (15) 
This function rises rapidly from zero to unity as  increases through e. The conformal 
time derivative d/d = aneT exp(T) is precisely the factor multiplying the scattering 
terms in equation (13). 
The spatial derivative term in equation (13) may be converted into a convective 
derivative through nii = (d/d ) +  . The convective derivative term (but not the 
partial derivative terms) may be integrated by parts. Using the function ( ) dened 
above, we obtain 
 0 
0(n i) = d(0  )  +1  + vei ni + 1ij ninj 
0 3 2 ret  0 
+	d (0  ) ( + )ret (16) 
0 
where we have discarded the unobservable monopole 0. 
Equation (16) simplies in the instantaneous recombination approximation, for which 
( ) is a unit step function at  = e and = D(  e) is a Dirac delta function. In 
this limit, we recover equation (12) with 
e =1  + vei ni + 1ij ninj .	 (17)3 2 e 
Equation (16) also shows us the eects of a nite width to the cosmic photosphere. 
The primary contributions multiplying are averaged over the nite timespan of recombi
nation while the eects of the time derivatives of the potentials turn on gradually during 
recombination. (As a result, the time derivative terms make a signicant contribution 
to anisotropy in models with low h2, because then recombination occurs only a little 
after the universe becomes matter-dominated, while the potentials are still changing.) 
Contributions to Primary Anisotropy 
In the instantaneous recombination approximation, there are a total of four contributions 
to primary CMB anisotropy measured by a fundamental observer: intrinsic, Doppler, 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>9 u , etc., are all transfer functions, i.e. they are solutions to the equations of motion in 
Fourier space subject to the initial conditions (k) = 1, (k) = 0. 
The transfer functions may be computed directly in k-space or by Fourier transfor
mation of the plane-parallel Greens functions by equation (59). The publicly available 
CMBFAST code (Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga 1996) computes them directly in k-space, while 
Bashinsky (2001) and Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2002) have computed them (in the 
uid approximation) by transforming the Greens functions. 
Numerical results 
In Section 6 we derived approximate results for the CMB anisotropy on large scales 
in the Sachs-Wolfe approximation, equation (48). Later, in Section 7, we worked out 
the plane-parallel Greens function solutions in the two-uid approximation. Section 8 
showed how to compute the angular correlation function and angular power spectrum 
from these ingredients. Here we present results for the two-uid approximation and 
compare with the exact computation by CMBFAST. The CMBFAST code includes three 
physical processes that are excluded by the two-uid approximation: a full treatment of 
neutrinos; photon diusion; and the polarization-dependence and anisotropic scattering 
contributions of Thomson scattering. 
Figure 5 shows the angular correlation function on small scales ( &lt;2). There 
are four notable phenomena. First, the curves all show a prominent dip. This feature 
is associated with the overlap of acoustic rings in the CMB photosphere. Recall that 
the spherical Greens functions correspond to acoustic waves expanding at the speed of 
sound. By the time of recombination, these waves reach a comoving distance of about 
0.5rec (Fig. 4). At the distance of recombination, rec (the diameter of the acoustic 
sphere) subtends an angle of about 1.2 . Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2002) show how the 
sharp feature occurring at this angle (thin curve in Fig. 5) arises from the singularities 
of  at the acoustic wavefronts. For angular separations less than this, sound waves are 
able to establish acoustic contact. For larger angular separations, the correlations reect 
the correlations present in the unmodied inationary spectrum. (Causal eects extend 
to about twice the acoustic length because the speed of sound is about half the speed of 
light.) 
The second notable result from Figure 5 is that the two-uid approximation with 
instantaneous recombination (thin curve) recovers much of the qualitative behavior of 
the CMBFAST result (thick curve) but underestimates the anisotropy on small scales. 
The main reason for this is that the Doppler contribution has been neglected here. 
Thus, the largest source of CMB anisotropy is accounted for by the intrinsic (
1 
3 ) and 
gravitational redshift contributions, but the Doppler contribution is appreciable on scales 
less than the acoustic length. 
37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>8 10 5 0 5 10  r(1) (x) 
20 10 0 10 20  c(1) (x) 
0.5 0 0.5 0.5 0 0.5 
x / c x / c rec rec 
Figure 3: Plane-parallel Greens functions for the density uctuations of photons (r = 
 , solid) and CDM (dashed) at recombination, in the uid approximation, for the same 
parameters shown in Fig. 1. Thick vertical lines represent Dirac delta functions of  (x) 
at its acoustic wavefronts and of c(x) at the origin. From Bashinsky (2001). 
Figure 4 suggests that baryons are responsible for the central dip in e . This dip is 
easy to understand. From Figure 1, the total gravitational potential has a sharp peak at 
x = 0. The photon-baryon uid has a high sound speed and therefore quickly adjusts to 
this potential by settling into hydrostatic equilibrium near x = 0. (Obviously hydrostatic 
equilibrium does not apply at the acoustic wavefronts, but it does hold as x 0 where 
the elapsed time is many sound-crossing times.) From the second of equations (25) we 
obtain the equation of hydrostatic equilibrium, 
i+ (+ p)i = 0 . (64) 
Linearizing this for the photon-baryon uid gives 
      1 3 b 3 b + 1 +  = i e +  = 0 . (65) i 4 4  4  
Thus, if b = 0, e has zero gradient in hydrostatic equilibrium. If b = 0, on the 
3 
other hand, e (0,) =  4 ( b/ )+ constant as x  0. The positive cusp of the CDM 
potential becomes a negative cusp of CMB anisotropy whose amplitude is proportional 
to b. Thus, baryons have two main eects on CMB anisotropy: they slow the sound 
speed and thereby decrease the acoustic distance compared with a pure photon gas, and 
they create a central dip in the Greens function. 
Angular Power Spectrum 
The goal of CMB integrations is to predict the anisotropy in a given cosmological model. 
We must ask carefully what this means. Does it mean to predict the actual pattern of 
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>As usual, we construct an orthonormal basis (a tetrad) at each spacetime point with 
e= V and with the spatial axes being parallel to the coordinate axes assuming that 0 
we use orthogonal coordinates for the background Robertson-Walker spacetime. (The 
spatial curvature perturbation 1   does not aect the orthogonality of the comoving 
coordinate axes as it is a conformal factor for dl2.) Energy, momentum, three-velocity 
(i.e. proper peculiar velocity), energy density, entropy density, etc. all have the same 
meanings as in special relativity when obtained from tensor components with a funda
mental observers orthonormal basis. Note that there is such an observer at every point 
in space; we dont (yet) preferentially single out the observer at  = 0. 
In the absence of anisotropic, relativistic stresses (produced mainly by neutrinos in 
the early universe),  =  and the spacetime metric perturbations are described by 
a single Newtonian-like gravitational potential. In this case, equation (1) is identical 
to the usual weak-eld metric in the Newtonian limit aside from the conformal factor 
a2( ) arising from cosmic expansion. In the following, we will distinguish the two metric 
functions in order to keep track of which physical eects arise from the gravitational 
redshift part of the metric () and which arise from the spatial curvature part (). 
The unperturbed, or background, density (t) obeys the Friedmann equation: 
 2d ln a 8 = G a2  K . (2)d 3 
  a3   a4Note that because  in the matter-dominated era and  in the radiation-
dominated era, the curvature term is negligible at high redshift. However, spatial curva
ture aects the geometry at low redshift and does have an eect on CMB anisotropy. 
For later use, we provide the solution to equation (2) for a model consisting of only 
matter (with present density parameter m) and radiation (whose energy density equals 
that of matter at a = aeq = 2.41  104 mh2): 
a( )  1  2 aeq 1/2 
= + , where H0e . (3) aeq e 4 e  m 
1Note that a = aeq at  = 2(
2  1)e. For m = 0.35 and h = 0.7, aeq = 4100 and 
e = 110 Mpc. This solution neglects curvature and a cosmological constant but should 
be accurate to better than 0.1% during recombination. 
3 CMB Radiative Transfer 
We wish to determine the specic intensity I measured by the observer at  = 0 and 
 = 0 as a function of photon direction and energy. Conceptually, the way we will do it 
is by tracing photon trajectories back from  = 0 to recombination at radial coordinate 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>The angular analogue of equation (68) is the angular correlation function 
1  
n1)( n2) = (2l + 1)ClPl( n1  n2) (71) C() (4 l=0 
where  n1  n2 = cos  and Pl(x) is the Legendre polynomial of degree l. Notice that the 
angular correlation function C() and power spectrum Cl are Fourier-Legendre transfor
mations of each other and therefore contain the same information. 
To calculate the angular power spectrum we must relate the anisotropy to the po
tential in k-space. We do this by expanding the anisotropy in plane waves. In the 
Sachs-Wolfe approximation, from equation (48) we get 
      e 2ik  n k iek0( n) = d3k e n C  (k, e) + 2 d e in  (k, 0 ) (72)3e 0 
with C  1 for the isentropic mode and C 2 for isocurvature modes. The minus sign 3 
in the plane waves occurs because  n is the radial unit vector. 
Now we use the spherical wave expansion of a plane wave, 
 
ix  
e= il(2l + 1)jl(x)Pl() (73) 
l=0 
where jl(x) is the spherical Bessel function (e.g. Jackson Classical Electromagnetism). 
Substituting into equation (72) yields 
  
k 0( n) = d3k  
(i)l(2l + 1)l(k, 0)Pl( n) (74) 
l=0 
where k = k/k and, in the Sachs-Wolfe approximation, 
 e 
l(k, 0) = Cjl(ke) + 2 jl (ke) (k, e) + 2 d jl(k)  (k, 0 ) . (75)3e 0 
(The derivative term j came from dierentiating eq. 73 with respect to x, which brings l 
k down the factor i = i n needed for the Doppler term in eq. 72.) 
We need one more mathematical result, the addition theorem for spherical harmonics, 
l4   Pl(  n2) = Ylm( n1)Ylm( n2) . (76) n1 2l + 1 m=l 
Using equations (69), (74), and (76), we obtain 
 alm = (i)l4 d3k Y lm(k) l(k, 0) . (77) 
35</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Combining all our results, the perturbed uid equations for CDM (subscript c) and the 
photon-baryon uid (subscript ) are 
 c = 2 uc + 3  ,  
a uc = uc +  ,  a 
  = 2 u + 3  , 
9yb a2 u = cs   u +  . (29)4 a 
These agree with equations (3) of Seljak (1994) if neutrino shear stress is neglected so 
that  = . They are valid on all length scales provided that the photons are tightly 
coupled to the baryons. 
Equations (29) must be supplemented by an equation for the gravitational potential 
. We have a choice of equations (19)(23). If we evolve the matter and radiation 
exactly, then all of these components of the Einstein equations are equivalent. We will 
choose a linear combination involving the eective sound speed squared 
p/d 1 3 1 b +  d c 2 c /d = 1 + y , y  . (30)w  d 3 4  +  
Note that cw would be the speed of sound if all matter (CDM and baryons) were tightly 
coupled to all radiation (photons and neutrinos). However, because this multi-component 
medium is not a single perfect uid, cw is not a true sound speed. Nonetheless, it is a 
useful quantity for obtaining a physical evolution equation for the gravitational potential. 
We choose a linear combination of equations (19)(23) that yields the simplest de
scription of motion, by multiplying equation (19) by c2 and subtracting it from equation w 
(23). Using equation (2), and setting  = , the resulting perturbed Einstein equation 
is (Bardeen 1980) 
a2 a2 
2 2 2 + 3(1 + cw )   + 3(cw  w)  (5 + 3w)K   cw  2 a a 
2 
2 w 2= 4Ga2(p  c )  c , (31)w y  
where  is a dimensionless entropy potential that will be discussed below, and 
p 1 = . (32) w  3(1 + y) 
In equation (31), p and  are the total pressure and energy density perturbations 
summed over baryons, cold dark matter, photons, and neutrinos. Let us approximate 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Newtonian-inspired calculation (Rees &amp; Sciama 1968) would include only the   term 
because   is due to space curvature and has no eect on nonrelativistic particles (nor 
does it have any Newtonian interpretation). But just as the deection of light in a weak 
gravitational eld is twice the Newtonian-inspired value, if  =  the change in energy 
due to a time-varying potential is twice the result from  . 
Note that the integrated Sachs-Wolfe term is the only contribution to anisotropy 
in the linear regime (i.e. arising from linearized uctuations) that is produced after 
recombination. In most models the contribution is small, although there is a measurable 
eect on large angular scale anisotropy in models with curvature and/or vacuum energy. 
5 Evolution of Matter and Metric Perturbations 
To evaluate the solutions given above (e.g. eqs. 12 plus 18 in the instantaneous re
combination approximation) we must determine the density, velocity, and gravitational 
potential uctuations present at the time of recombination (and later, to get the inte
grated Sachs-Wolfe contribution). This is non-trivial. Accurate results can be obtained 
only by integrating numerically two of equations (19)(23) plus the coupled relativis
tic perturbation equations for photons, baryons, neutrinos, dark matter, and any other 
components present in the universe (e.g. Ma &amp; Bertschinger 1995; Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga 
1996). This integration is performed numerically by the CMBFAST code of Seljak &amp; 
Zaldarriaga as well as by its slower predecessors (e.g. Ma &amp; Bertschinger 1995). 
Despite the complexity of this evolution, we can learn a great deal by examining the 
behavior on large scales and at early times in the universe. In this section we will derive 
the equations of motion for the metric and the coupled uids responsible for metric 
perturbations. We will solve these analytically on large scales. This approach gives good 
physical insight to the various sources of CMB anisotropy. 
5.1 Einstein equations 
The Einstein equations for metric (1) are given by Bertschinger (1996); beware that  
and  are reversed there. 
The 00 Einstein equation give 
  aa 2 + 3K   3   +  = 4Ga2 (19) a a 
where  = (t) is the perturbation in the proper energy density at (xi, ) measured by 
a fundamental observer and K is the spatial curvature constant of a non-at Robertson-
Walker background spacetime. (We reserve the lower-case k for comoving wavenumber 
below.) Although we will later drop curvature, it is included here for completeness. 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>must be negligible at late times because 2 diverges as y  0.) In the matter-dominated 
era, y  1, the general solution including both isentropic and isocurvature modes is a 
constant potential, 
9 1 2 (x, )  i(x) + e 2  2i for y  1 .	 (46)10 5 3 
The entropy term in parentheses is simply the relative variation of the photon-to-CDM 
ratio from equation (34). The relative sizes of the coecients in equation (46) (0.9 vs 
0.2) shows how inecient entropy is in producing a gravitational potential uctuation. 
This will cause the isocurvature mode to have a much larger CMB anisotropy than the 
isentropic mode, for a given post-recombination gravitational potential. 
The Sachs-Wolfe anisotropy follows from substituting into equations (12) and (18) 
the potential, density and velocity perturbations computed on large scales assuming that 
recombination occurs at y  1. First, from equations (18), (43), (44), and (46), we get 
e =	(2/3)e  (2/3e)niie , isentropic ; (47)e  (2/3e)niie , isocurvature , 
where e  ( a/a)e and subscript e refers to recombination. Note that the velocity term 
becomes small for comoving wavelengths much larger than the Hubble distance 1 
e 
at recombination. Note also the critical dierence between isentropic and isocurvature 
initial conditions as far as the post-recombination potential. Combining equation (12 
with (47), we get the nal Sachs-Wolfe eect for the anisotropy in direction (, ): 
 e 2  (, ) = C + (e, , , e) + 2 d  (, , , 0  ) , (48)3e 	 0 
where C = 1/3 for isentropic uctuations and C = 2 for isentropic uctuations. Note that 
equation (48) includes only the gravitational potential at and after recombination  by 
ignoring all acoustic eects (and neutrinos) we have simplied the evolution suciently 
to express the primary anisotropy entirely in terms of the potential and its derivatives 
for   e. To the extent that the rst two terms (intrinsic and Doppler anisotropy) 
dominate the anisotropy, maps of the CMB anisotropy reveal (on scales larger than the 
acoustic horizon) the gravitational potential at recombination. 
The coecient C is six times larger for isocurvature uctuations than for isentropic 
ones. (This is, of course, an approximation  the solution assumed zrec  zeq which is 
not exact.) For a given amplitude of gravitational potential uctuations, hence dark mat
ter uctuations (dark matter being the dominant component at recombination), isocur
vature uctuations produce a much larger CMB anisotropy. This is because the initial 
entropy uctuations directly perturb the radiation with no compensating time dilation 
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>solution of equation (54) in spherical coordinates with delta function initial condition. 
The result is 3 (3)(r, ) = (cs)3(cs  r) (60)r 4 
where (x) is the Heaviside step function, (x) = 0 for x &lt; 1 and (x) = 1 for x &gt; 1. 
The Greens function for the radiation potential is remarkably simple: it is a spatially 
uniform wave expanding at the speed of sound, with unit volume integral (from eq. 59 
for k = 0). In short, it is a spherical sound wave! The oscillations of the transfer 
function 3j1(k)/(k) arise because of the nite extent of the Greens function and they 
are characteristic of causal behavior. This phenomenon is essentially the origin of the 
acoustic peaks of the CMB power spectrum, which we will discuss below. 
This beautifully simple result suggests that we apply the Greens function method to 
the full problem of equations (52) for all times. However, there is a practical problem with 
the three-dimensional Greens functions. The Poisson equation tells us that the photon 
2(3)density uctuation  is given, in part, by . The derivative of the Heaviside function r 
is a Dirac delta function. The Laplacian takes one more derivative, so that (3)(r, ) has  
a term proportional to dD(r  cs)/dr. Great care must be exercised when dealing 
with derivatives of delta functions, especially when (3) is determined numerically. Ther 
numerical challenges are serious enough to dissuade us from using three-dimensional 
Greens functions. 
These delta function singularities are a consequence of the perfect uid assumption. If 
photon diusion is included, then the acoustic wavefront will spread slightly. Even with 
diusion, however, the spherical transfer function for  is sharply peaked at the radius of 
the acoustic sphere. This means that an initial point-like perturbation in the potential, 
located on or near the CMB photosphere, will produce a ring of temperature anisotropy 
on the sky. The observed pattern is a superposition of such rings like the ripples from 
stones dropped in a pond. The maximum size of the rings  twice the acoustic radius 
at recombination  imprints a characteristic scale in the CMB anisotropy. 
7.2 Plane-parallel Greens functions 
For numerical integration purposes it is preferable to modify the Greens function method 
to avoid derivatives of delta functions. The singular behavior is reduced if we superpose 
many spherical waves to create a plane wavefront using the Huyghens construction. This 
works for any Greens function as follows: 
  
(1)(x, ) = (3)(r, ) 2rdr . (61) 
|x| 
The integral ensures that (1) is less singular than (3) at the wavefronts. From equation 
(59) it follows that (1) is the one-dimensional inverse Fourier transform of the transfer 
28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
Department of Physics 
Physics 8.942 
Cosmic Microwave Background Anisotropy
c2001-2003 Edmund Bertschinger. All rights reserved. 
1 Introduction 
These notes present a simplied computation of cosmic microwave background anisotropy 
induced by primeval gravitational potential or entropy uctuations. The basic treatment 
is equivalent to the calculation of anisotropy on large angular scales presented rst by 
Sachs &amp; Wolfe (1967). The discussion here goes beyond the Sachs-Wolfe treatment to 
include a discussion of the dominant contributions to anisotropy on small angular scales. 
The presentation given here is based in part on the PhD thesis of Sergei Bashinsky 
(Bashinsky 2001) and Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2001, 2002). More elementary treat
ments of CMB anisotropy are given by Chapter 18 of Peacock and online by Wayne Hu 
at http://background.uchicago.edu/). 
We adopt several assumptions in order to simplify the algebra without losing the 
main physical eects: 
1.	Instantaneous recombination. We assume that, prior to hydrogen recombination 
at a = ar , photons scatter so frequently with electrons that the photon gas is 
a perfect gas with spatially-varying energy density r and uid three-velocity vi 
(orthonormal components of peculiar velocity). This gas is tightly coupled to the 
baryons (electrons plus all ionization states of atomic matter). The gradual 
decoupling of photons and baryons is approximated by instantaneous decoupling 
at a = ar . We will indicate how to improve on this treatment by treating the 
radiation eld prior to recombination as an imperfect gas coupled to baryons by 
Thomson scattering. An accurate treatment of hydrogen and helium recombination 
is needed in this case. With non-instantaneous recombination, photon polarization 
must also be considered. We ignore polarization here. The resulting errors are a 
few percent in rms temperature anisotropy at small angular scales. 
2.	No large-scale spatial curvature. We suppose that the universe is a perturbed 
Robertson-Walker spacetime. Although the curvature terms (proportional to 1) 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>5 presents a simplied set of evolution equations. Section 6 solves these equations on 
large scales to derive the famous Sachs-Wolfe formula. Section 7 presents a real-space 
Greens function approach to solving and understanding the small-scale behavior, espe
cially the acoustic peaks. Section 8 shows how to compute the angular power spectrum 
from the solution of the radiative transfer equation. Numerical results are presented in 
Section 9. 
2 Perturbed Robertson-Walker Spacetimes 
This section summarizes the elementary treatment of a weakly perturbed Robertson-
Walker spacetime. 
We write the spacetime line element as 
2ds2 = a ( ) (1 + 2)d 2 + (1  2)dl2 (1) 
where dl2 is the usual spatial line element in comoving coordinates (e.g. dl2 = d2 + 
r2d2, or dl2 = dx2 + dy2 + dz2 in Cartesian coordinates if the background space is at). 
The metric perturbations are characterized by two functions (xi,  ) and (xi,  ) which 
we assume are small (we neglect all terms quadratic in these elds). 
Equation (1) is a cosmological version of the standard weak-eld metric used in 
linearized general relativity. It ignores gravitomagnetism (present in a g0i metric term) 
and gravitational radiation (present in a transverse-traceless strain tensor hij added to 
the spatial metric). Note that the Newtonian limit follows from equation (1) when 
a = 0 and  = . Dots denote derivatives with respect to conformal time  , while 
gradient symbols (e.g. i) represent gradients (covariant derivatives) with respect to the 
comoving spatial coordinates using the unperturbed 3-metric of dl2 . In a at background 
with Cartesian coordinates, i = i. 
As in the standard treatment of linearized general relativity, we describe spacetime 
by perturbations added to a background model. The coordinate-freedom allows us many 
ways to do this for a given set of physical perturbations. We will not discuss this gauge-
xing problem in these notes. Bertschinger (1996) discusses this issue in detail. Equation 
(1) conveniently avoids gauge artifacts and enables us to focus on the physics. 
In the following, we often speak of fundamental (or comoving) observers by 
which we mean observers at xed xi . The 4-velocity of a fundamental observer is V = 
a1(1) e . In general, fundamental observers are not freely-falling (as one can see from 
the geodesic equation for dV i/d), nor do they correspond to the rest frame of a galaxy 
or to the frame in which the CMB dipole anisotropy vanishes. (See Peacock section 9.4 
for a discussion of the dipole anisotropy caused by the Doppler eect.) However, they 
dene a very convenient set of local rest frames in which to project tensor components. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>To get the angular power spectrum we must now relate the potentials in equation 
(75) to the initial random eld of potential or entropy uctuations that induced the CMB 
anisotropy. We dene the CMB transfer function 
l(k, 0) (78) Dl(k)  
i(k) 
where i(k) is the Fourier transform of the primeval potential eld of equation (46). 
(This assumes the initial uctuations were isentropic; if they were isocurvature, then i 
should be replaced by the initial entropy perturbation eld.) The universe is like a linear 
amplier in electronics: each harmonic component is modulated by an analog lter. Note 
that the transfer function depends on spatial frequency but not direction, because the 
equations of motion are rotationally invariant. 
Using equations (70), (76), (77), and (78), plus the orthonormality of the spherical  k)Ylm ( harmonics ( d Ylm(k) = ll mm ), we get the key result for the angular power 
spectrum of the CMB: 
Cl = 4 d3k P(k)Dl 2(k) .	 (79) 
Here, P(k) is the primeval power spectrum. For scale-invariant initial uctuations, 
P  k3 . 
The dominant contribution to large-scale anisotropy is the Sachs-Wolfe eect, for 
which Dl = C(e/i)jl(ke). For a scale-invariant spectrum, equation (79) can be 
integrated exactly giving Cl  1/[l(l + 1)], corresponding to equal power per logarithmic 
interval of angular degree l, i.e. a at spectrum on the sphere. (In d dimensions, a 
scale-invariant spectrum is kd . For large l, the eective wavenumber is k  l.) This is 
why plots of the CMB power spectrum always show l(l + 1)Cl. 
We can go beyond the Sachs-Wolfe approximation by replacing equation (72) with the 
exact equation (16). Each eld such as  (x, ) is written as a Fourier integral with the 
Fourier components proportional to the initial gravitational potential through a transfer 
function, e.g.  (k, ) =  (k, )i(k ), a straightforward generalization of equation (56). 
Thus, we may generalize equation (72) to (Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga 1996; note the modied 
coecient of  due to our dierent denition here) 
 0  1 jDl(k) = d(0  )1  +  + u + ij n i n jl(k) 
0	 3  2 ret  0  +	d (0  ) ( + )(k, 0  ) , (80) 
0  
where () = exp[T(0  )] is the visibility function of equation (15) and subscript 
ret means to evaluate the quantity in brackets at (k,  = 0  ). The functions  , , 
36</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>changes through linear evolution. Every linear eld has a transfer function (e.g. c,  , 
etc.). The transfer function is spherically symmetric in k-space because of the rotational 
invariance of the equations of motion. Note carefully the notation: r (k,) is the transfer 
function, i.e. the solution subject to initial condition r = 1, while r (k,) is the solution 
subject to the initial condition r = i(k). The point is that once the transfer function is 
known, then the solution for arbitrary initial condition follows by simple multiplication. 
The transfer function is the solution to the evolution equation with initial condition 
exp(ik  x). Plane wave initial conditions are but one possible choice of initial condition.  
Another useful choice is a point-like perturbation at the origin, 
(3)( x,)  (3)( x) as  0 (57)r D  
where (3)( x) is the three-dimensional Dirac delta function. The superscript (3) is placed D 
on r to remind us that the initial condition is point-like in three dimensions. 
The solution subject to a point-like initial condition is called a Greens function. The 
solution at any later time is then simply a convolution of the initial eld by the Greens 
function:  
r ( x,) = d3 x  r ( x  ,0)(3)( x  x ,) . (58)r 
Heuristically, we can imagine decomposing the initial eld into a sum of delta functions. 
Each delta function evolves into the Greens function. The evolved eld is therefore a 
superposition of Greens functions. 
The Greens function description is mathematically equivalent to the Fourier space 
description with a transfer function. In fact, the Greens function is simply the inverse 
Fourier transform of the transfer function: 
k(k,) = (3)(r,) e ix d3 x . (59) 
(We remove the subscript r since this relation is not restricted to the radiation potential 
but is true for any transfer function and Greens function pair.) Note that since the 
transfer function is spherically symmetric in k-space, the Greens function is also spher
ically symmetric in position space. That is, (3) depends only on the length r = | x|. 
(Assuming a at cosmology, we use r interchangeably with the radial comoving coor
dinate .) The spherical Greens function and transfer function are Fourier transform 
pairs. 
In the Fourier domain, the evolved eld follows by multiplication with the transfer 
function. In the position domain, the evolved eld follows by convolution with the 
Greens function. The Fourier transform of a convolution is the product of Fourier 
transforms, and the Fourier transform of a product becomes a convolution. 
So what is the Greens function corresponding to the radiation transfer function 
r (k,)? It is easily found either by Fourier transformation of equation (55) or by 
27</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>delta function D. The complex conjugation may be removed provided that the argument 
of the delta function is changed to k + k . 
It is easy to check that the spatial covariance, i.e. the two-point correlation function, 
is the Fourier transform of the power spectrum: 
x1 ( x1)( x2)= d3ke ik( x 2) P(k) . (68) 
Note that the correlations of dierent points in space are generally nonzero  in par
ticular, scale-invariant uctuations are a statistical fractal, with correlations extending 
over all scales  but that the correlation at dierent points vanishes in k-space because 
of the Dirac delta function in equation (67). This is a general feature of stationary 
random elds, i.e. random elds whose statistical properties are invariant under spatial 
translation. It is a natural outcome of inationary models, where the uctuations are 
the zero-point uctuations of a nearly massless free eld; each mode is independent. 
Our calculations have shown that the primary CMB anisotropy  is linear in the 
gravitational potential (and its derivatives and integrals). Thus, the anisotropy at any 
point in the sky is a linear combination of gaussian-distributed random numbers. A linear 
combination of normal (gaussian) random numbers is itself normal. Thus, the anisotropy 
0( n) should be a gaussian random eld on the sphere. Thus, to fully characterize its 
statistical properties we need only to calculate the analogue of the power spectrum on a 
sphere. 
The angular power spectrum is straightforward to dene by analogy with equations 
(66) and (67). We rst expand the temperature anisotropy in the orthonormal basis 
functions appropriate for a sphere, spherical harmonics: 
 l 
0( n) = almYlm( n) (69) 
l=0 m=l 
where Ylm( n) is shorthand for Ylm(,) for spherical angles (,) giving the observational 
direction  n. (Note that here we are dening  n to have opposite sign to the rest of these 
notes, for consistency with usage by experimentalists:  n is the direction the photon 
travels.) The angular power spectrum is now dened by the covariance of the expansion 
coecients: 
 almalm Cl ll mm (70) 
where ll is now the Kronecker delta. Each angular coecient is independent for a 
random eld with rotational invariance on a sphere. This is the angular analogue to 
translational invariance, which led to a Dirac delta function in equation (67). The 
compactness of the sphere makes the sum over harmonics discrete rather than continuous, 
leading to a Kronecker delta rather than a Dirac delta function. 
34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>7.1 Radiation era 
Equations (52) are still too complicated to solve analytically. To gain insight, let us 
examine the solutions in the radiation era, y  1. In this limit, equations (52) become 
1 1  2r +  (4r + c)  c = cs2  2r , 2 
3 1 3 1 4  2c +  c + c = (y  yb)  r + r . (53)2 4 2 
We will solve these for isentropic initial conditions,  = 0 as y  0. From equations 
(49), c/r  y. Thus, CDM has negligible eect on the dominant radiation component 
in the radiation era. On the other hand, the radiation perturbations provide the source 
for c. 
Thus, we must solve the simple damped wave equation 
4  2r +  r = cs2  2r (54) 
with constant sound speed cs = 31/2 . Since this is a partial dierential equation, we 
must specify the initial conditions for all space. However, the problem simplies because 
it is a linear partial dierential equation. The linear superposition principle means that 
we can expand the solution in any convenient set of spatial basis functions. The common 
choice in cosmology for at (Euclidean) space is the plane wave basis exp(ik  x ), so that  
2 = k2 for any given plane wave component. We use the usual notation of at space 
in which k and  x are 3-vectors. 
The Fourier space solution to equation (54) is 
j1(k)r (k, ) = 3 , (55)k 
where j1(x) = (sin x  x cos x)/x2 is a spherical Bessel function. Note that the normal
ization chosen so that r = 1 for  = 0. 
Suppose that the initial potential uctuations at the end of the inationary era are 
i( x ). The Fourier transform is i(k ). (Note the common practice of using the same 
function name to denote the real-space function and its Fourier transform. The meaning 
becomes clear from the argument:  x is always a spatial position and k is always a 
wavevector.) Linear superposition means that the Fourier transform at any later time is 
r (k, ) = r (k, )i(k ) (56) 
By analogy with linear lters in electrical systems, r (k, ) is called the transfer function 
for the radiation potential. It is the factor by which every Fourier component of r (k, ) 
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>0.4 0.8 1.2 1.6 2 2 4 6 8 C () , 10 9 K 2 CDM , bh2= 0.02 
1/3  +  , inst. rec. 
CDM , bh2= 0.03 
 m =  = 0.35 
, degrees 
Figure 5: Angular CMB temperature correlation function. The parameters of the CDM 
model are m = 0.35,  = 0.65, h = 0.65 with a scale-invariant spectrum P  k3 . 
For this set of parameters and the displayed bh2 values, the acoustic sphere subtends 
an angle s  1.2 . The thin solid curve is calculated using the two-uid approximation 
with instantaneous recombination. All the other curves are calculated using CMBFAST. 
The dip in C() is shifted to smaller angles for the open model (dashed-dotted line). 
The slope for &lt;s/2 is dependent on the baryon density (dashed vs. solid line). Based 
on Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2001). 
The third notable result is that the acoustic length in the open model (dashed-dotted 
curve in Fig. 5) subtends a smaller angle. This is simply because the angular distance 
r() to the CMB photosphere is larger for an open model (Weinberg 2000). 
Finally, Figure 5 shows that the baryon contribution has the most signicant eect 
for angles less than half the diameter of the acoustic sphere. The baryon eect arises 
from the interplay between the wavefront singularity and the central valley in Figure 
4. As we showed, the depth of that valley is proportional to b. This translates into a 
roughly linear dependence of the inner slope of C() on b. 
The angular correlation function has the attractive property of associating acoustic 
phenomena with localized features. The localization in angle means that a Fourier-
Legendre representation will produce ringing (oscillations) in the angular frequency. 
Because the sphere is a compact manifold, the angular frequency l is discrete. Figure 
6 plots the angular power spectrum Cl to show us that this ringing corresponds to the 
famous acoustic peaks. 
The uid approximation yields surprisingly accurate prediction of the CMB anisotropy 
38</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>This assumption is consistent with ination but not with some other models of structure 
formation where the density uctuations are generated much later. 
Isentropic uctuations are dened by the condition  = 0 but  = 0. They cor
respond to the energy density of all components (photons, baryons, dark matter, etc) 
varying together in such a way that the entropy perturbation vanishes. In particular, 
the photon-to-baryon number density ratio is a universal constant in this model (until 
after recombination, when photons and baryons decouple), as is the initial photon-to-
dark matter particle number density ratio. This it exactly the condition resulting from 
standard ination plus reheating. Inationary uctuations are often called adiabatic 
although isentropic (i.e.  = 0 initially) is more accurate and descriptive. 
Isocurvature uctuations have  = 0 initially (i.e. no curvature perturbation) but 
 = 0. Physically, they correspond to an equation of state p(, S) with spatially-varying 
entropy S but initially constant . Isocurvature uctuations can be created by a rst-
order phase-transition or any other process that produces spatial variations in the pho-
ton/baryon or photon-to-dark matter ratio while leaving the net energy density unper
turbed. As the universe expands, as long as particle collisions are rapid, the specic 
entropy of each uid element is conserved. That is, prior to decoupling for any particle 
species, the ratio of number densities of that particle to photons is conserved. If the 
ratio varies spatially, then pressure gradients develop which move matter and cause a 
gravitational potential perturbation to develop. Nonstandard models of ination can be 
constructed in which entropy perturbations are generated during or after reheating. 
In our particular case we are considering isocurvature CDM perturbations, since 
 = 0 corresponds to a spatially varying photon-to-CDM ratio in equation (33). It is 
also possible to consider models with a xed T 3/c but with spatially varying T 3/b, or 
isocurvature baryon models. Indeed, isocurvature-type perturbations can be produced 
that have the ratio of any two or more species varying in space initially, as long as the 
total energy density is constant so that the metric is unperturbed ( = 0). 
It is easy to recognize the isentropic and isocurvature modes (as they are often 
called in the literature) as homogeneous and particular solutions of equation (39). We 
impose initial conditions at  = i such that yi  1. Isentropic initial conditions have 
(x, i) = i(x) and (x, i) =  (x, i) = 0. (For example, the uctuations produced by 
ination are frozen in and unchanging during the radiation-dominated era on scales larger 
than the acoustic length.) Isocurvature initial conditions have (x, i) =  (x, i) = 0 
and (x, i) = i(x), with   = 0 on scales larger than the acoustic length. 
We leave it as an exercise for the student to show that the desired solutions of equation 
(39) are 
9 1(y)i(x) , isentropic ; (x,  ) = 10 2y isocurvature . 5(4+3y) 1(y)e 22i(x) , (45) 
(The 2 solution is not included here because it is the decaying mode. Its amplitude 
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>7 eect. For isentropic uctuations, we saw that the large-scale photon density perturba
tion has opposite sign to the gravitational potential (because of the time dilation eect 
discussed following eq. 42), which results in a cancellation of the CMB anisotropy. Hence 
the famous Sachs-Wolfe formula  = 1 . Although Sachs &amp; Wolfe (1967) did not con3 
sider isocurvature initial conditions, we have seen that it is just as easy to estimate their 
contribution to large-scale anisotropy. The much larger ratio of CMB uctuations to 
dark matter perturbations has led to a rejection of most isocurvature models. 
Greens function solution for small-scale anisotropy 
As we have seen, the coupled Einstein and uid equations can be solved analytically 
on large scales, with the result that the temperature anisotropy basically traces the 
gravitational potential uctuations on the CMB photosphere. However, this is not the full 
story for CMB anisotropy. On smaller scales, the potential uctuations set the photon-
baryon uid into motion, sending sound waves propagating through the universe. These 
sound waves leave a characteristic signature in the correlations of CMB anisotropies on 
angular scales of about one degree. This signature is reected in the acoustic peaks of 
the angular power spectrum. 
On scales smaller than the acoustic length, it is hard to solve the coupled Einstein and 
uid equations for a multicomponent medium. The usual procedure is to work in Fourier 
space so that the partial dierential equations become ordinary dierential equations in 
time. Seljak (1994) solved equations (29) and (20) numerically in Fourier space. Ma &amp; 
Bertschinger (1995) solved the complete coupled system including the Boltzmann equa
tion for photons and neutrinos, which are necessary for imperfect uids or collisionless 
plasmas. Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga (1996) introduced CMBFAST, a fast computer code for 
solving the complicated system of equations. These developments are valuable, especially 
CMBFAST because it has revolutionized CMB data analysis and model testing. 
Here, however, we seek physical insight more than numerical results. The approach 
is based on work by Sergei Bashinsky (Bashinsky 2001, Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger 2001, 
2002). Instead of solving the uid and Einstein equations in Fourier space, we solve the 
coupled wave equations (31) and (37) in conguration space (x,  ). 
Our model for CMB anisotropy is based on two uids coupled by gravity: the photon-
baryon uid (with sound speed cs) and CDM (with vanishing sound speed). On physical 
grounds, we would expect waves to propagate through the photon-baryon uid with speed 
cs but no waves to propagate through the CDM. It is intriguing that equations (31) and 
(37) have almost the expected form, namely a coupled system of damped wave equations 
with the appropriate sound speeds. However, the fundamental variables appearing there 
are the gravitational and entropy potentials, which do not cleanly separate the two uids. 
If we ignore curvature by setting K = 0 (as is justied at high redshift), then the 
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>these notes provides a useful way to comprehend the dynamics of CMB anisotropy. 
I would like to thank Sergei Bashinsky for his collaboration and for many helpful 
discussions, without which these notes would be impossible. 
References 
[1] Bardeen, J. M. 1980, PRD, 22, 1882. 
[2] Bashinsky, S. 2001, MIT PhD thesis. 
[3] Bashinsky, S., &amp; Bertschinger, E. 2001, PRL, 87, 081301. 
[4] Bashinsky, S., &amp; Bertschinger, E. 2002, PRD, 65, 123008. 
[5] Bertschinger, E. 1996, in Cosmology and Large Scale Structure, proc. Les Houches 
Summer School, Session LX, ed. R. Schaeer, J. Silk, M. Spiro, and J. Zinn-Justin 
(Amsterdam: Elsevier Science), 273-347. 
[6] Hu, W., Seljak, U., White, M., &amp; Zaldarriaga, M. 1998, PRD, 57, 3290. 
[7] Kodama, H., &amp; Sasaki, M. 1984, Prog. Theor. Phys. Suppl., 78, 1. 
[8] Kodama, H., &amp; Sasaki, M. 1986, Int. J. Mod. Phys., A1, 265. 
[9] Ma, C.-P., &amp; Bertschinger, E. 1995, ApJ, 455, 7. 
[10] Rees, M. J., &amp; Sciama, D. W. 1968, Nature, 517, 611. 
[11] Sachs, R. K., &amp; Wolfe, A. M. 1967, ApJ, 147, 73. 
[12] Seljak, U. 1994, ApJ, 435, L87. 
[13] Seljak, U. 1996, ApJ, 463, 1. 
[14] Seljak, U., &amp; Zaldarriaga, M. 1996, ApJ, 469, 437. 
[15] Spergel, D. N., &amp; Zaldarriaga, M. 1997, PRL, 79, 2180. 
[16] Weinberg, S. 2000, PRD, 62, 127302. 
[17] Weinberg, S. 2002, astro-ph/0207375. 
[18] Zaldarriaga, M., &amp; Seljak, U. 1997, PRD, 55, 1830. 
[19] Zaldarriaga, M., Seljak, U., &amp; Bertschinger, E. 1998, ApJ, 494, 491. 
40</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>gravitational, and integrated Sachs-Wolfe. We will discuss them in turn so as to give a 
physical interpretation to the sources of CMB anisotropy. 
The intrinsic and Doppler anisotropies correspond to the rst term in equation (12), 
i.e. the brightness temperature perturbation e present at the time of recombination. 
Equation (17) gives this term. However, further simplication results because of the 
tight coupling of photons and baryons (and electrons) prior to recombination. Under 
ithese conditions, vei = v . Also, the intrinsic quadrupole anisotropy source term due to 
polarization eects vanishes because multiple scattering prior to recombination damps 
the polarization caused by single scattering. This is the reason why CMB polarization 
is predicted to be so small (Zaldarriaga &amp; Seljak 1997; Spergel &amp; Zaldarriaga 1997). 
Thus, in the instantaneous recombination approximation, we may write 
1 i . (18) e  3  + niv 
e 
iThis gives the explicit form of the intrinsic ( 1  ) and Doppler (niv ) contributions. (Re3 3call that  = 4  / .) It has a simple interpretation which does not require the full 
treatment of scattering used in deriving equation (16). In the instantaneous recombi
nation approximation, the photon-baryon gas is a perfect uid up to the moment of 
recombination. In the rest frame of this uid, the radiation is isotropic blackbody radi
ation at temperature T . Spatial variations of T translate into number density variations 
 = 3 ln T , explaining the rst term. But the photon-baryon uid moves with a local 
ithree-velocity v . (Fluids ow!) For small velocities, the linear Doppler formula gives a 
ibrightness temperature shift niv . In some directions, the photosphere is moving toward 
us (relative to unperturbed Hubble expansion) while in other places it recedes, producing 
anisotropy in the emitted radiation. 
The next contribution to anisotropy in equation (12) is the gravitational redshift 
e  0. Each photon travelling to us falls through a gravitational potential dierence 
e  0 and the energies are changed correspondingly. 
The literature contains some misstatements about the gravitational redshift eect. 
1The primary anisotropy for isentropic uctuations on large scales is  = 3 e (Sachs &amp; 
Wolfe 1967), a factor of 3 dierent from the gravitational redshift anisotropy to which 
it is sometimes erroneously ascribed. We will see below that the Sachs-Wolfe result 
comes from combining the intrinsic anisotropy ( 1  ) and gravitational redshift eects. 3 
(Moreover, it is valid only for isentropic uctuations but not for isocurvature ones. More 
on that below.) 
The nal contribution to anisotropy comes from the integral term in equations (12) 
and (16), which is commonly called the Integrated Sachs-Wolfe term. If the gravi
tational potential changes with time, photons suer dierent amounts of gravitational 
redshift falling into and climbing out of potential wells between recombination and today. 
(This eect on the CMB was rst pointed out by Rees &amp; Sciama in 1968.) However, a 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>will be included in the basic equations, our numerical calculations will not fully 
include them. This simplies the harmonic decomposition and is consistent with 
ination as the origin of uctuations. The only important eect we miss is the 
anisotropy produced by the time-changing gravitational potential at redshift z &lt; 
10, the integrated Sachs-Wolfe eect. 
3.	Adopt a simplied description of matter. Aside from baryons prior to recombina
tion, we will treat the matter as cold. This is appropriate for CDM and for other 
types of matter on scales larger than the Jeans length (an excellent approximation 
for CMB anisotropy). The complex gravitational interaction between photons, 
neutrinos, and dark matter prior to recombination will be treated in a simplied 
manner. However, we include correctly, without approximation, a possible nonzero 
cosmological constant (vacuum energy). 
4.	Neglect gravitational radiation. In the linearized treatment of small-amplitude uc
tuations, gravitational radiation is a distinct mode and so its eect on the CMB 
may be treated as a separate contribution computed independently of the density 
and entropy uctuations studied here. 
5.	Assume that all perturbations have small (linear) amplitude. This is valid for pri
mary anisotropies but not for secondary anisotropies caused by nonlinear struc
tures forming at low redshift. Secondary anisotropies are negligible on angular 
scales larger than about 10 arcminutes. 
The justication for these simplications is mainly pedagogical, although in general 
they do not introduce serious errors on angular scales larger than a few degrees of arc. 
(Gravitational radiation, if present, can contribute signicantly to the CMB anisotropy 
on large angular scales. Curvature also has a signicant eect on large scales.) Once the 
student understands CMB anisotropy in this simplied model, a more realistic treatment 
can be undertaken (Ma &amp; Bertschinger 1995; Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga 1996; Zaldarriaga, 
Seljak, &amp; Bertschinger 1998; Hu et al 1998, and references therein). 
Aside from the simplications given above and some computational approximations 
stated later, the treatment given herein is rigorous and complete. We will discuss both 
the adiabatic (i.e. isentropic) and isocurvature (entropy) modes, the integrated 
Sachs-Wolfe eect, and both intrinsic and Doppler anisotropies. 
The computation of microwave background anisotropy has several ingredients. The 
rest of these notes give a systematic presentation of these ingredients. In Section 2 we 
present the Einstein equations for a perturbed Robertson-Walker spacetime. In Section 
3 we derive and formally integrate the radiative transfer equation for CMB anisotropy. 
Section 4 gives a physical interpretation of the primary contributions to CMB anisotropy. 
These contributions cannot be calculated until the evolution of metric, matter, and radia
tion perturbations is given, as they provide the source terms for CMB anisotropy. Section 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>It is easy to interpret the various terms in equations (25). The terms proportional 
to a/a are Hubble damping terms arising because we are using comoving coordinates. 
The   term appears in the continuity equation because, from the metric (1), the homo
geneous expansion factor a( ) is eectively modied by spatial curvature perturbations 
to become a(1  ). The pressure p is present with  in the energy ux (momentum 
density) because we let  be the energy density (not the rest-mass density), which is 
aected by the work done by pressure forces in compressing the gas. 
For convenience in what follows, we dene the perturbation in energy density relative 
to the enthalpy density  + p, 
 . (26)+   p 
Beware, this is a non-standard notation: most authors (including the present one in the 
papers listed in the bibliography) dene   /. For cold dark matter, with p = 0, 
there is no dierence. However, for photons or other relativistic particles,  is nonzero. p/ 
Our denition of  agrees with Weinberg (2002). It has a simple physical interpretation: 
 is the fractional perturbation in the number density or particles (rather than the energy 
density of particles). This choice simplies the equations and calculations that follow. 
The unperturbed matter and radiation uids are perfect uids, i.e. they have zero 
shear stress. For these uids, w = p/ depends only on . The speed of sound for a 
uid component is cs = (dp/d)1/2 . Linearizing equations (25) about the unperturbed 
solution and using equation (26), we now obtain (cf. Ma &amp; Bertschinger 1995) 
  = ( 2 u + 3 ) , 
a2 u + (1  3cs )u = c 2 +  . (27)s a 
We have used the assumption of potential ow, equation (21). 
Our goal now is to obtain equations of motion for the density and velocity potentials 
of our two uids, CDM and the photon-baryon plasma. The CDM case is simple with 
w = c2 = 0. The photon-baryon plasma is more complicated. First let us consider s 
the perturbations of photons and baryons separately. Because of the large photon-to-
baryon ratio (about 2  109), a negligible amount of heat is transferred to photons 
from baryons compared with the energy in the photons. Thus, photons with density 
1perturbation  obey the rst of equations (27) with w = 3 while baryons with density 
perturbation  b obey the same equation with w = 0 (since they are nonrelativistic). Now, 
the tight coupling due to Thomson scattering ensures that the photons and baryons 
have a common velocity potential, ub = u . Thus, if the photon-to-baryon ratio was 
unperturbed initially, it follows from the rst of equations (27) that b =  . With 
 +  equation of state w = p/= p /( b), we get 
dp /d 1 3 1 b 2 c = d(  )/d = 1 + yb , yb  . (28)s b +  3 4  
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>The summed ii components of the Einstein equations give a result that will be useful 
later: 
 2  K + a d aa2 1 2 ( + 2) + 2 +  +3  (  ) = 4Ga2p (23) a d a a 
where p = p  p is the perturbation in the pressure (isotropic stress). 
Finally, the trace-free part of the ij components of the Einstein equations give a 
relation between the two gravitational potentials: 
1 ij  3 ij  2 (  ) = 8Ga2ij, (24) 
where ij, is the longitudinal shear stress. Longitudinal shear stress arises from quadrupole 
anisotropy in the angular distribution of the particle momenta; for a weakly imperfect 
uid it is the stress arising from shear viscosity. A perfect uid has no shear stress. The 
major contribution to ij, comes from massless neutrinos; photons make a small con
tribution after recombination. When the universe becomes matter-dominated, ij   
and therefore   is small compared with . In the following we will neglect shear | |
stress, with resulting errors of order one percent in the CMB anisotropy. For a full 
treatment including shear stress, see Ma &amp; Bertschinger (1995). 
5.2 Fluid equations 
The Einstein equations (19)(23) require that we specify the density, velocity, and pres
sure perturbations of matter and radiation. We will approximate the contents of the 
universe before recombination by two decoupled perfect uids: cold dark matter and 
the photon-baryon plasma. Cold dark matter is a pressureless uid that interacts only 
by gravity. Photons are tightly coupled to electrons by Thomson scattering, which are 
themselves tightly coupled to protons and helium atoms and ions by Coulomb scatter
ing. We apply this description at temperatures below 1 MeV, after electron-positron 
annihilation and neutrino decoupling. Thus the neutrinos should be regarded as a third, 
decoupled gas. Their nite temperature and lack of collisions make the neutrinos an 
imperfect gas. We will discuss the neutrinos below. 
The uid equations follow from T  = 0 applied to a perfect uid with stress-
energy tensor T  = ( + p)V V  + pg where V  is the 4-velocity. We dene the 
three-velocity vi = V i/V 0 . Working to rst order in the metric perturbations and the 
uid 3-velocity, we nd 
a  + 3 a    ( + p) + i ( + p)v i = 0 , 
  a ( + p)v i + 4 ( + p)v i + ip + ( + p)i = 0 . (25) a 
14</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Structure Formation Models 2</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://de.arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/9901168</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>CMB Anisotropy 2</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-942-cosmology-fall-2001/resources/cmbfluct03/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>where T is the Thomson cross section and the factor outside the parentheses on the 
right-hand side is the Thomson scattering rate (up to a factor c = 1). The electrons have 
proper number density ne and peculiar velocity vi . (The unperturbed electron densitye
may be used when considering primary anisotropies because the terms in parentheses are 
all rst-order perturbations.) The photon number density uctuation is   n /n = 
3 
4  / where n and  are the photon number density and energy density, respectively. 
The perturbation can be obtained from an angular average of the anisotropy:  = 
3  d/(4). (Note that n  T 3 implies  = 3 ln T .) 
Heuristically, equation (10) is easy to understand. Scattering corresponds to absorp
tion (the  term) and re-radiation in a dierent direction. To the extent that the 
scattering is isotropic in the electron frame, the emitted radiation is just the angular 
average of the absorbed radiation ( 1  is the angular average of ). Scattering therefore3 
isotropizes the radiation eld, a phenomenon familiar to anyone driving a car through 
fog. The second term is due to the motion of the electron gas: scattering by moving 
targets introduces a dipole anisotropy. 
The third term, ij ninj , arises from the dependence of Thomson scattering on di
rection and polarization. It is easy to understand qualitatively from Rayleighs Law of 
scattered light. When a photon scatters from an electron, the incoming and outgoing 
momenta lie in a plane called the scattering plane. The photon is polarized with its elec
tric eld orientation either in the plane or perpendicular to it. In the former case, the 
scattered ux is reduced by a factor cos2  compared with the perpendicular case where 
 is the scattering angle. This result follows classically from the angular dependence 
of electric dipole radiation caused when the incoming light makes the electron oscillate. 
Another way to express the same result is to say that the scattering rate is proportional 
to ( 1  2)2 where  1 and  2 are the polarization directions for the incoming and outgoing 
photons, respectively. 
These considerations imply that the dierential cross section for unpolarized incident 
radiation is proportional to 1 + cos2 . Normalizing the total cross section, we nd 
d 3T = (1 + cos 2 ) . (11)d 16 
If the incident radiation is polarized, then the cross-section becomes a 22 matrix giving 
scattering rates for each orthogonal polarization. Thus, the dependence of the scattering 
rate on polarization and direction add corrections to the isotropic scattering implied by 
the  + 1  terms in equation (10). These corrections are only a few percent for the3 
temperature anisotropy but they are crucial for polarization. Scattering induces a small 
polarization of the CMB. We will ignore the polarization and the quadrupolar scattering 
term ij ninj in the following. 
Note that the unperturbed (spatially homogeneous) electron density may be used 
in equation (10) because it multiplies a rst-order quantity. Spatial variations in the 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>electron density only appear in second-order perturbation theory. 
In evaluating the primary CMB anisotropy, we need not take into account that recom
bination takes place at dierent times in dierent places. The reason physically is that 
the radiation eld is in nearly perfect thermal equilibrium with the electrons. For perfect 
(everywhere homogeneous and isotropic) blackbody radiation, nonrelativistic scattering 
by an electron gas at rest with respect to the radiation eld has no eect whatsoever on 
the radiation. In the absence of pre-existing CMB uctuations, scattering alone cannot 
produce any anisotropy no matter how inhomogeneous the electron distribution. The 
only possible eect occurs from the motion of the electron gas, and this is included 
already in equation (10). 
3.2 Solution of the radiative transfer equation 
We can easily integrate equation (9) in the instantaneous recombination approximation, 
in which we assume that ne drops sharply to zero at  = e. Prior to this time the photon 
mean-free path is very short; we assume it is eectively zero. Under these conditions, 
integrating equation (9) along the backwards light cone to e  0  e gives the desired 
CMB anisotropy seen by the fundamental observer at  = 0: 
 e 
0(n i) = e + e  0 + d  ( + )ret (12) 
0 
where subscript e means to evaluate the quantity at  = e,  = e = 0  e, 
in direction ni (with a minus sign because the photon travels toward decreasing ). 
Subscript ret means to evaluate the quantity in the integrand at retarded time  = 
0  . 
The rst three terms on the right-hand side of equation (12) are all boundary terms 
which arise as constants of integration. The rst two represent brightness temperature 
and gravitational potential uctuations present at recombination and are the major 
contributors to CMB anisotropy. The third term, the gravitational potential at  = 0, is 
an unobservable monopole contribution. The integral term is anisotropy produced after 
recombination due to time-changing gravitational potentials. 
Before examining the physical content of equation (12) in the next section, it is 
instructive to compare with the exact solution of the full radiative transfer equation. 
Including the Thomson scattering terms of equation (10), equation (9) has solution 
(Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga 1996) 
 0 
0(n i) = d e T() n ii +   + aneT 1  + vei ni + 1ij ninj (13) 
0 3 2 ret 
where   
T()  d (aneT)ret (14) 
0 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>function,   ikx d3(k,  ) = (1)(x,  ) e x (62) 
 
where r =  x . The transfer function contains the same information as either its one | |
dimensional or three-dimensional Fourier transform. Thus, the choice of approach is 
purely a matter of convenience, numerical ease or accuracy, and/or ease of interpretation. 
Recalling the initial condition (k, 0) = 1 for the transfer function, from equation (62) 
it follows that (1)(x,  ) is the Greens function for initial condition ( x, 0) = D(x). The 
initial perturbation is sheet-like (i.e., constant on planes of constant Cartesian coordinate 
x) rather than point-like. We use the superscript (1) to distinguish such plane-parallel 
Greens functions from the spherical variety. 
Analytic solutions for the plane-parallel Greens functions in the radiation era are 
given by Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2002). Because the dynamics involve two potentials 
(for gravity and entropy), initial conditions must be set for both. The calculations have 
all assumed isentropic initial conditions with (x,  ) = 0 at  = 0. It would be interesting 
to work out Greens functions for isocuravture initial conditions with (x, 0) = 0 and 
(x, 0)  1/r (so that the entropy perturbation 2 is a delta function) but this has not 
been done. 
Bashinsky (2001) constructed numerical solutions for the isentropic case by evolv
ing equations (52) in one space dimension and time, with 2 = 2/x2 . Usually it is 
much harder to accurately solve partial dierential equations than ordinary dierential 
equations, and this is an argument for the Fourier space approach. However, the equa
tions in question are linear wave equations and they may be solved by the method of 
characteristics. This method is fast and accurate. 
Figure 1 shows the results of this numerical integration for the radiation and CDM 
gravitational potentials at recombination. The initial conditions were (1)(x, 0) = D(x)r 
and (1)(x, 0) = 0. The delta function separated into left-going and right-going waves, c 
whose evolution spread (1) over space and diminished the central peak. The gravitar 
tional potential hill of the radiation caused outward-directed gravitational forces which 
expelled the CDM away from x = 0. The CDM has a central cusp reecting the initial 
repulsive singularity in the gravitational potential (1); this cusp is preserved because r 
the CDM particles have no thermal motion. In fact, once the universe becomes matter-
dominated (1)(x,  ) stops evolving, as may be seen from the second of equations (52) in c 
the limit y  1. 
Figure 2 shows three snapshots of the time evolution of the Greens functions for 
the radiation and CDM potentials. Only the range x &gt; 0 needs to be plotted since the 
Greens functions depend only on x. Note that while the amplitude of r decreases | |
rapidly with time, c changes much more slowly and becomes constant in the matter 
era as expected. We also see the eect of changing the baryon content. This changes 
the photon-baryon sound speed in equation (28), thereby changing the distance to the 
29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>0.5 
0 
0.6 0.4 0.2 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 
x / c rec 
Figure 1: Plane-parallel Greens functions for the potentials r (solid) and c (dashed) 
at recombination, in the uid approximation. The cosmological parameter values are 
m = 0.35,  = 0.65, bh2 = 0.02, and h = 0.65. By recombination the universe has 
become matter-dominated. From Bashinsky (2001). 
wavefront. Adding baryons decreases the sound speed. 
The density and velocity perturbations of photons, baryons, and the CDM uid 
follow from r , c and their derivatives. The photon perturbations contribute directly to 
CMB anisotropy while the CDM perturbations eventually seed the formation of galaxies. 
Figure 3 shows the plane-parallel Greens functions at recombination for the photon 
and CDM density uctuations. (Recall that b =  in the uid approximation.) The 
singularities of  and c arise from the d2/dx2 term of the Poisson equation. Comparing 
with Figure 1, we see why these singularities occur at the wavefronts for  but at x = 0 
for CDM. The central spike for the CDM is negative because of the repulsive sign of the 
initial gravitational potential peak (top row of Fig. 2). It is surrounded by positive tails 
because of mass conservation: the CDM pushed out from x = 0 piles up into the region 
between x = 0 and the acoustic wavefront. 
Note from Figures 13 that our spacetime is unperturbed outside of the acoustic 
wavefront. This is a consequence of our initial condition that left the metric unperturbed 
everywhere except at x = 0. Had we instead made  a Dirac delta function with zero 
velocity perturbation, then the gravitational potential  would have been nonzero for all 
x. However, our treatment in the earlier sections shows that the gravitational potential, 
not the density, is the fundamental physical quantity for CMB anisotropy. That is why 
our Greens functions are chosen so that (x, 0) = D(x). 
The Dirac delta function contributions of  (x,  ) at the acoustic wavefronts make 
30  (1)(x) and  (1)(x) r c 2 
1.5 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>where t0( ) = a d and t = a d . The density perturbation is computed at xed  
using /= (d ln /dt)t = 2(t)/t 0. If   = 0, then t = t0 giving /= 2. 
This is simply the gravitational redshift: clocks run slower in a gravitational potential 
well. 
If   = 0, the gravitational redshift is time-dependent and a more careful calculation 
is needed. Matters are complicated because of the particular, somewhat arbitrary choice 
of constant- hypersurfaces implied by our metric equation (1). Our intuition is not 
always a good guide for physics on scales larger than the Hubble length. Fortunately, 
the Einstein equations will guide us to the correct solution even if we cannot guess it 
from Newtonian considerations. 
The photon density perturbation on large scales follows simply from combining equa
tion (42) with equation (34). (One must combine the photon and matter perturbations 
with appropriate weights to obtain the net density perturbation.) The result is 
9 2 = cw 2(1 + y)y (y) + (2y/3) 2 . (43)e  2 4 
Similarly, the large-scale peculiar velocity follows from equation (20). For a matter 
plus radiation universe on scales much larger than the curvature and acoustic scales, 
uc = u . The velocity potential is then 
1 y1 + y u = ey (y) . (44)2 1 + (3/4)y 
6.1 Isentropic and Isocurvature modes 
We now have all the ingredients needed to compute the CMB anisotropy on large angular 
scales. The treatment here is equivalent to that of Sachs &amp; Wolfe (1967) for isentropic 
initial uctuations and extends their treatment to more general initial conditions. 
Equation (39) has two physically relevant quantities: the gravitational potential  
and specic entropy perturbation . Because the equation is second-order, one might 
think there are two physical solutions for any , and therefore a vast family of solutions. 
However, we have seen that  cannot change with time over distance scales larger than the 
acoustic length. Moreover, there is only one combination of the homogeneous solutions 
of equations (41) that remains nite as y  0. Consequently, physical initial conditions 
set in the very early universe must be a linear combination of the nite solution with 
2 = 0 but  = 0 and of the nite solution with 2 = 0 but  = 0. Because the 
evolution equations are all linear in the perturbations, then general solution is a linear 
combination of the solutions starting from these two types of initial conditions. 
The two sets of solutions we have identied are called isentropic and isocurvature. 
In both cases we assume that the uctuations are produced in the very early universe. 
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Thus, treating both the metric perturbations and  as being of the same order, we can 
ireplace dxi/d by nin equation (6). A similar argument shows that we can drop the 
(/ni)(dni/d ) term: both factors are rst-order quantities. This is equivalent to 
neglecting gravitational lensing of anisotropies. Lensing by nonlinear (highly overdense) 
structures at low redshift has a small eect on the CMB on arcminute angular scales 
(Seljak 1996). 
We are left with calculating the rate of change of proper energy E, which is straight
forward from the geodesic equation. The result is 
d ln(aE) = n ii +   . (8)d 
The factor a accounts for the cosmological redshift while the rst term on the right-hand 
side is the familiar gravitational redshift. (Both terms arise from g00.) The second term, 
due to spatial curvature uctuations, is unfamiliar in the Newtonian limit but can be 
signicant for photons and other relativistic particles. 
Because the right-hand side of equation (8) is independent of E, it follows that the 
d ln(aE)/d contribution to equation (6) cannot induce any energy-dependence of the 
brightness temperature perturbation. (As in gravitational lensing, gravity is achro
matic.) The dominant collision process, Compton scattering, is also independent of 
energy (at temperatures much less than the electron mass). Thus, unless some other 
physical process causes a departure of the photon spectrum from blackbody, /E = 0 
to an excellent approximation. None of the standard sources of primary anisotropy 
(primeval potential, density, or entropy perturbations) generates any signicant black
body distortion, so we assume E = 0 in the following. (Departures of order the 
baryon-to-photon ratio 1010 are generated during recombination, but these are orders 
of magnitude smaller than the eects we retain.) 
Combining equations (6), (7), and (8), we obtain the fundamental equation of CMB 
anisotropy: 
d d =   + n ii = n ii +   + . (9)d d c 
Equation (9) has a very simple physical interpretation. Aside from changes due to 
gravitational redshift, time-varying spatial curvature uctuations, or radiative processes 
(emission, absorption, and scattering), the CMB anisotropy (brightness temperature 
uctuation) is constant along null geodesics. 
For completeness, we present without derivation the collision terms arising from non
relativistic photon-electron scattering: 
d = aneT  + 1  + vei ni + 1ij ninj (10)d 3 2 c 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>The 0i component of the Einstein equations helps us to understand the time-derivative 
terms in equation (19): 
a2   + = 4Ga2 ( + p)v i . (20)  a i 
The term in brackets is the momentum density measured by a fundamental observer, or 
T 0i in an orthonormal basis. In general relativity, momentum density (and momentum 
ux, i.e. stress) is a source of spacetime curvature. The momentum density, hence 
its eect on curvature, is typically smaller than  by a factor v/c. However, it is 
gravitationally signicant on large scales (Hubble-length and beyond). Thus, the time-
derivative terms in equation (19) are unimportant on scales much less than the Hubble 
length but are important on larger scales. They are important for CMB anisotropy on 
scales larger than a degree or so. 
With the neglect of gravitomagnetism and gravitational radiation, the metric pertur
bations follow from spatial scalars and not, for example, a vector potential (Bertschinger 
1996). In the limit of small uctuations, it follows that the velocity elds of the various 
matter and radiation components are the gradients of scalar elds. That is, the velocity 
elds have no vorticity (or are longitudinal, in the language of classical eld theory). 
Using this fact, we may write 
v i = ij 
a j ua (21) 
for the mean (uid) velocity of any component a (e.g. photons, baryons, CDM, neutrinos) 
where u(xi, ) is the velocity potential and ij is the inverse of the unperturbed spatial 3
metric ij dened so that the comoving spatial line element is dl2 = ij dxidxj in equation 
(1). This fact allows us to combine equations (19) and (20) into a cosmological Poisson 
equation, 
 2 + 3K  = 4Ga2  
a + 3 a(a + pa)ua . (22) aa 
Aside from the curvature and velocity potential terms, equation (22) is an obvious gen
eralization of the Newtonian Poisson equation. The source for the metric perturbation 
must be  rather than  because  =  = 0 for an unperturbed Robertson-Walker 
spacetime with  = . The presence of the velocity potential shows that, in cosmology, 
momentum as well as mass-energy is a source for Newtonian gravity. This should not 
be surprising, given that momentum in one Lorentz frame transforms into energy in 
another frame. It can be shown that a small, spatially-varying transformation of the 
time coordinate can be performed which eliminates the momentum density (basically by 
transforming to the local uid rest frame) and thereby converts the term in brackets to a 
pure density uctuation (Bardeen 1980). However, it proves more convenient to use the 
coordinates implied by equation (1) and simply evaluate both the density and momen
tum contributions to gravity in these coordinates. (For a discussion of other coordinate 
systems, see Bardeen 1980 and Bertschinger 1996.) 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>the behavior of the neutrinos by supposing that they trace photons, with  =  and 
p / = p / . This is not correct on scales smaller than the Hubble length, but it 
is a good approximation on larger scales because the neutrinos have then not yet had 
enough time to separate from the photons. Our assumption overestimates the neutrino 
perturbations on small scales because, in the absence of collisions, neutrinos easily dif
fuse out of perturbations. However, the eects of this error are not large because the 
gravitational eect of neutrinos is important only during the radiation-dominated era, 
and during this time the photon perturbations rapidly oscillate on small scales so that 
their time average is small. Doing better would require that we solve the Boltzmann 
equation for neutrinos (Ma &amp; Bertschinger 1995), which will not be discussed here. 
The source term in equation (31) is proportional to the entropy per unit mass of cold 
dark matter, 
  
ln T 3 
 
c  
=   c = p  c2 
w  
cc2 
w , (33) 
so that 
 2 = 4Ga2 cy (  c) . (34) 
Neutrino eects are included implicitly through the eective sound speed cw . 
Equation (31) is rather remarkable. It allows us to compute the gravitational po
tential through a damped, driven wave equation whose source is the specic entropy 
perturbation. In Newtonian gravitation we think of the potential as being determined 
by action-at-a-distance (eq. 19 without the time-derivative terms). However, the Ein
stein equations also enforce local energy-momentum conservation, providing us with 
alternatives for the computation of the metric perturbations. Heuristically, the potential 
 is computed from the instantaneous distribution of energy density (and momentum 
density, as may be shown by combining eqs. 19 and 20). Because the source of the 
potential may have acoustic waves, then it, too, displays acoustic waves. Note that the 
wave speed is the eective sound speed cw . 
True gravitational waves (which propagate at c) are described by a transverse-traceless 
metric perturbation hij , which we are ignoring here. Thus, despite its appearance, equa
tion (31) really is gravitational action-at-a-distance. Although gravitational waves are 
needed to restore causality, we are ignoring them here for the CMB anisotropy calcula
tion. This is justied in linear perturbation theory by the fact that gravity waves have 
no coupling to the scalar-mode (density and entropy) perturbations we are consider
ing here. In linear perturbation theory, the eects of density and entropy perturbations 
propagate at the speed of sound, not the speed of light. 
Our next step is to obtain an evolution equation for the entropy potential . Using 
the fact that a2cy is constant, from equations (34) together with equations (28)(30) 
we obtain 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>1  (1)2eff = 1/3  (1) +  (1) 
2
1
0
b= 0.03 h2 
b= 0 
| | | | | 
 c  0.5 c 0 0.5 c c rec rec rec recx 
Figure 4: Plane-parallel Greens function for the combined intrinsic ( 1  ) plus gravita3 
tional redshift contributions to CMB anisotropy at recombination in the uid approxi
mation, for the same parameters as shown in Fig. 2. The solid (dashed) lines show the 
results for b h2 = 0.03 (b h2 = 0). The quantity e not only gives the Sachs-Wolfe 
contribution to CMB anisotropy on large scales, it also measures the departure of the 
photon-baryon uid from hydrostatic equilibrium. Based on Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger 
(2001). 
uctuations that will be measured in the sky? No. That is impossible because the uc
tuations originate from random uctuations in the early universe (quantum uctuations 
during ination or perhaps thermal uctuations in some rst-order phase transition). At 
best, we can predict only the statistical properties of the CMB anisotropy. But then 
what statistical properties should we calculate? 
Ination predicts a gaussian random eld of primeval potential uctuations. That is, 
in a Fourier decomposition (here assuming a K = 0 background) 
k( x,) = d3ke ix (k,) , (66) 
each mode (k) is a zero-mean, normally distributed random variable. Actually, the 
Fourier transform of a real eld is a complex eld, so each mode is a pair of normally 
distributed variables with the same variance. Also note that our denition of the Fourier 
transform here diers from that in equation (59). 
For a Gaussian random eld, the two-point correlation, i.e. the covariance of eld 
values at dierent points, completely characterizes the statistical properties of the eld. 
For (k), its covariance denes the power spectrum (or spectral density) P (k): 
 (k) (k)  P (k) D(k  k) . (67) 
Had we used the alternative Fourier transformation denition implied by equation (59), 
the right-hand side would be larger by a factor (2)3 . Note the three-dimensional Dirac 
33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Laplacian operators in equations (31) and (37) both operate on the same quantity, namely 
 + /y. This suggests that we consider linear combinations of  and  to separate the 
wave components. Amazingly, there is a simple set of variables that does the trick: 
 2cw  r =  + , c =   r . (49) cs y 
We use the subscripts r for radiation (the photon-baryon uid, with an approximate 
inclusion of neutrinos) and c for CDM. The reason for doing so is that the Poisson 
equation now holds separately for each potential with a corresponding source (for K = 0): 
a, = 4Ga2r  + 3 u  2r a 
a= 4Ga2c c + 3 u , (50)   2c a 
where r u + cuc 4  , r (  ) +   + b . (51) u  r + c  3 
Thus, we may interpret r as the gravitational potential produced by radiation (pho
tons, neutrinos, and baryons) while c is the gravitational potential produced by CDM. 
(One must be careful not to push the Newtonian analogy too far, since here we have 
contributions from the peculiar velocity potentials.) Equations (50) are equivalent to 
equation (22) applied separately to each of our two uids. 
Equations (31) and (37) now separate into a pair of coupled wave equations with the 
expected behavior: 
a2 a 3(c2 + ) r  2c2  4 + 3c2 
2 w s w2r + 3(1 + cs )  r + 3cw  c + c = cs2  2r , a a 4e 2y 3e 2y2
aa 3
2 2 2c + 3(cw  cs )  r + 3  c  r +2cs 2  3 c = 0 , (52)2 a a 4e 2y 3e 2y
where (y) is a ratio of two quartic polynomials given by Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger 
(2002). 
The rst of equations (52) shows that perturbations in the photon-baryon uid indeed 
propagate as sound waves with speed cs. As the sound wave passes by a CDM uid 
element, its gravity acts on the CDM, causing the CDM to evolve as given by the second 
equation. 
25</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>distance e = 0  e. The subscript e stands for emitter and reminds us that we are 
looking at radiation emitted from a photosphere, the edge of the plasma layer that exists 
for  &gt; e, i.e. for times  &lt; e. We see the CMB as though we live in a transparent 
spherical cavity of radius e beyond which is a hot glowing plasma. Of course, e really 
represents a boundary in time rather than space; every fundamental observer has a 
dierent photosphere. 
In the absence of emission, absorption, and scattering, conservation of photons im
plies that the photon phase space density is conserved along null geodesics. In the 
language of basic astronomy, dI /ds = 0 where I is the specic intensity and ds mea
sures path length. However, unlike most other astronomical situations, the path length 
measures not just distance in space; d/ds measures the rate of change in phase space. 
The radiation eld varies with time, energy (photon frequency) and photon direction as 
well as with position in space. We will work out these dependencies to calculate the 
CMB anisotropy. First, however, we must examine the cosmological radiative transfer 
equation more closely. 
3.1 Derivation of radiative transfer equation 
In place of the specic intensity, we use the radiation brightness temperature to character
ize the phase space distribution. Let E be the photon energy measured by a fundamental 
observer and let ni = pi/E be a unit vector (with respect to the observers orthonormal 
basis) in the direction of photon travel. The brightness temperature Tbr(xi, , E, ni) is 
dened implicitly through I = B (Tbr) where B (T) is the Planck function and I is 
the specic intensity measured by the fundamental observer at (xi, ). 
Because the radiation perturbations are small, we write Tbr = a1T0(1 + ) where 
T0 is the present unperturbed blackbody temperature and 2  1. Our  coincides 
with Peacocks T/T; most other workers write T/T. Thus, the photon phase space 
distribution (summed over polarizations) is 
f(x i, , E, n i) = c2I 
2h43 = fP  aE 
1 +   
, where fP()  2h3 [exp(/T 0)  1]1 . 
(4) 
[The unperturbed temperature T0 can, in fact, never be measured because we see 
only the perturbed universe. Separating the radiation eld into an unperturbed back
ground plus perturbations is really a ction chosen for the calculational convenience of 
linear perturbation theory. In practice, T0 is replaced by the average of the brightness 
temperature taken over the sky. Anisotropy measurements are made by subtracting pairs 
of brightness temperatures from dierent directions in the sky. Uncertainty in T0 aects 
only the monopole anisotropy, which is unmeasurable and consequently ignored by 
observers of CMB anisotropy. The same is true of the dipole anisotropy, which re
ceives contributions from both the observers motion and an intrinsic anisotropy due to 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>of the modication made in deriving equation (37), these equations are not exactly 
equivalent to the uid equations (29) plus the Poisson equation (22) when neutrinos are 
included. They agree with the approximations made by Seljak (1994) and Bashinsky &amp; 
Bertschinger (2001, 2002). We will nd in Section 9 that the two-uid approximation 
made here is remarkably accurate. 
6 Large-scale anisotropy: the Sachs-Wolfe Eect 
Using the wave equations we have derived for the gravitational potential  and entropy 
potential , it is possible analytically to solve for the perturbations on large scales. In 
this context, large scale means that we can neglect c2 
w 2 and cs22 relative to ( a/a)2 
in equations (31) and (37). This is valid provided that we consider scales larger than the 
comoving acoustic length, dened by 
cs . (38) Lac  aH 
The acoustic length subtends an angle of about one degree at recombination. We also 
will neglect the spatial curvature K, which makes a negligible contribution to equations 
(31) and (37) before and during recombination because K ( a/a)2 .| |
Under these conditions, equations (31) and (37) reduce to ordinary dierential equa
tions in time. We change variables from  to y through equation (3), obtaining 
  3c2 
y y w+ 3 1 + c 2  (cw e)2 
(39) + 2(1 + y) w + 4(1 + y) = (1 + y)  2 
and 
(c2 2 
y y 
2 2 + 2(1 + y) + 1 + 3cw  3cs = s  cy)e 2 
y 2 2 , (40)1 + y  
where a prime denotes y . We have retained the Laplacian terms that link the potential 
and density because we have said nothing yet about the relative sizes of  and . 
As y  0, the gravitational potential makes a negligible contribution to  in equation 
(40), at least insofar as that contribution feeds back to equation (39). Thus, in solving 
for the gravitational potential it is safe to drop the right-hand side of equation (40), 
which then becomes an ordinary dierential equation in y whose solutions as y  0 
are   ln y and  = (x) with y  = 0. The logarithmic solution is unphysical; it 
corresponds to a large separation between photons and CDM at the big bang, which 
does not occur in standard cosmology. Thus, the only possibility for the entropy is to 
have a constant or spatially-varying distribution of primeval entropy uctuations that is 
constant in time early in the radiation era. 
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>l3 
2 
1 
0 
0 500 1000 1500 2000 
l 5
4
l (l+1) C
Figure 6: The angular power spectrum of CMB temperature anisotropy calculated using 
the two-uid approximation (solid line, including the Doppler contribution) and using 
CMBFAST (dashed line). The CDM model parameters are the same as for the thick 
solid curve in Fig. 5. From Bashinsky (2001). 
spectrum. With a phenomenological correction for photon diusion, the error of our nu
merical calculations in uid approximation is within 5% on angular scales from 2 to a 
few arcminutes, see Fig. 9. It can also compute the gravitational radiation (tensor mode) 
and gravitational lensing (secondary) contributions to anisotropy. 
The agreement between the two-uid approximation and CMBFAST is much better 
in Figure 6 than in Figure 5. There are several reasons for this improvement. First, all 
injthe anisotropy contributions in equation (80) have now been included except for ij n
(polarization and anisotropic scattering terms). Second, photon diusion was included 
approximately in a phenomenological manner. Third, recombination was gradual rather 
than instantaneous. Seljak (1994) included these eects in his earlier two-uid treat
ment, however he did not include the integrated Sachs-Wolfe eect and he used the 
instantaneous recombination approximation, with some analytic corrections that are not 
as accurate as our numerical integrations. Our two-uid model achieves accuracy better 
than 5% in Cl for l  1500. 
It appears that the approximate description given by equations (52) captures well 
the essential physics of the cosmological dynamics of the CMB photons and the other 
components with which they interact. Although CMBFAST remains the method of 
choice for accurate calculations and data analysis, the simplied model presented in 
39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Given the time-independent solution for the entropy , it is easy to solve equation 
(39) for (y). The homogeneous ( = 0) solutions for (y) are (Kodama &amp; Sasaki 1984, 
1986) 
1(y) = 1 + 2 
9y  8 
9y2  16 
9y3 + 16 
9 1 + y 
y3 , 2(y) = 1 + y 
y3 . (41) 
10 1For y  1, 1 = 9 (1  ). The density perturbations associated with 1 grow in 16 y + 
the matter-dominated era y  1 (hence 1 is often called the growing mode) although 
1 itself does not. The other mode, 2, is called the decaying mode. From the these 
homogeneous solutions, we can construct particular solutions subject to any desired 
initial conditions. Using the Greens function method we can also construct solutions 
with nonzero 2. 
Before presenting the solutions, we recall from equation (13) that the CMB anisotropy 
icomputation requires  and v in addition to . On large scales, where pressure-gradient 
forces are unimportant so that dark matter and photons move together, we can deter
mine these quantities from the Einstein equations without having to solve the coupled 
equations of motion for all the matter and radiation species. This is because, on scales 
larger than the acoustic length, the matter plus radiation behaves as a single uctu
ating perfect uid. The Einstein equations have built-in redundancy  they enforce 
local energy-momentum conservation  so we can use them to get the net energy den
sity and velocity perturbations without having to solve the uid equations. (That is a 
radical concept to a Newtonian physicist, but it is a direct consequence of the Einstein 
equations!) 
From equation (19), dropping the curvature and Laplacian terms (they are both small 
on scales larger than the Hubble length) and neglecting anisotropic stress (i.e. setting 
 = ), we obtain 
 
= 2 (aa + ) = 2y (y) . (42) 
Note that we are using a gravitational eld equation to solve for the mass density pertur
bation, having used time-evolution equations to solve for the potential. By contrast, in 
Newtonian physics we are used to solving time evolution equations for the uid variables 
and then solving a gravitational eld equation for the potential. In general relativity, we 
have more exibility in how to compute gravity. 
Equation (42) has a simple physical interpretation. By assumption, the density is 
smoothly varying on scales of the Hubble length. Thus, each Hubble volume behaves like 
a homogeneous universe (slightly closed or slightly open depending on the sign of ). In 
a homogeneous model, the density and cosmic proper time t measured by a fundamental 
observer are related by (x,  )  (Gt2)1 . Because of the long-wavelength perturbations 
in g00, however, the relative clock rate between proper time t(x,  ) and conformal time 
depends on position: dt/d = a( )(1 + ). Thus, we may write t = t0( ) + t(x,  ) 
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>2 2  a2 22 + 1 + 3cw  3cs    (cs  cw ) 2 a 
a 3 c2 a 
2 2 w= 4Ga2 y(cs  cw ) c c + 3 uc +4 c2  c2 c  + 4 u . (35) a as w 
Using equations (28) and (30), we obtain 
   3 c2 3  b 1 
w c =  + 4 cs2  cw  + b 1 +  1  c . (36)2 4 
Using this result, if we compare the right-hand sides of equations (22) and (35), we 
see that they would be identical for our multicomponent uid if we neglect neutrinos. 
Including neutrinos requires approximation because we are not solving the Boltzmann 
equation for neutrinos. One approximation is to suppose that neutrinos have identical 
density and velocity perturbations as photons. Under this assumption,  would simply 
be replaced by  +  in equation (22) and similarly for p . This assumption was made 
in deriving equations (33) and (35). However, we know that this approximation is not 
exact, and so we are free to consider other approximations that make errors of the same 
order. That is, we can consider corrections to equation (36) that are of order  . 
We choose to approximate the right-hand side of equation (36) by dropping the 
factors in parentheses (Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger 2002). This approximation is exact 
when neutrinos are neglected. The reason for making this choice is that now equations 
(35) becomes a simple wave equation that is very similar to equation (31), 
2 2  a2 2 2 22 + 1 + 3cw  3cs    (cs  cw ) 2 = y(cs  cw )  2 + 3K  . (37) a 
This equation is exact only when neutrinos are neglected. However, as we will see in 
Section 7, when neutrinos are included it preserves the correct propagation of sound 
waves through the photon-baryon uid at sound speed cs. 
The two-uid approximation introduced here is equivalent to including neutrinos 
assuming that they have the same dynamics as photons. The baryon abundance is 
increased over the true abundance by a factor (1 +  / ) so that the photon-baryon 
sound speed is unchanged. Finally, the CDM abundance is decreased so that the total 
matter density c + b is unchanged. This model has the advantage of preserving the 
important time and length scales eq and cs d while working with perfect uids. For 
more discussion of the two-uid approximations, see Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2002). 
Equations (31) and (37) completely characterize the evolution of matter, radiation, 
and gravity in our simplied two-uid model (CDM and the photon-baryon uid, with 
neutrinos added in a way that preserves the photon-baryon sound speed). Because 
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>a possible large-scale gradient of brightness temperature across our Hubble volume. The 
choice of rest frame for fundamental observers is arbitrary; in practice it is chosen so 
that the dipole anisotropy vanishes at the solar system barycenter.] 
In general, the brightness temperature is a function of photon energy. However, we 
will see that for primary CMB anisotropies, the energy-dependence disappears:  = 
(xi, , ni). That is, in every direction, a fundamental observer nds that the specic 
intensity is a perfect black-body as a function of photon energy but with the tempera
ture varying with photon direction. A simple example of this behavior is the Doppler 
anisotropy derived by Peacock in his Section 9.4. However, it holds also for all forms of 
CMB anisotropy that do not involve large-amplitude perturbations. 
Secondary anisotropies induced by nonlinear structures at low redshift often de
pend on energy (i.e. the spectrum is distorted from blackbody). An example is the 
Sunyaev-Zeldovich eect caused by scattering of CMB photons by hot ionized gas 
in clusters of galaxies. The spectral signature makes it easy to distinguish Sunyaev-
Zeldovich anisotropy from primary CMB anisotropy. These notes consider only the 
primary anisotropies. 
iOur goal is to determine 0(ni) = ( = 0, 0, n), the anisotropy measured by the 
fundamental observer at the origin. (The anisotropy measured by a moving observer at 
the origin, e.g. one on the Earth, follows by a simple Doppler shift following Peacock eq. 
9.62.) We use the fact that the photon phase space density is conserved in the absence of 
emission, absorption, and scattering. From equation (4), the total change in the phase 
space density is (assuming 2  1) 
df aEf  aE d ln(aE) d df , = = d 1 +  P 1 +  d  d d c 
d   dxi  dE  dni 
where = + + + . (5)d xi d E d ni d 
We may thus write the radiative transfer equation as 
  dxi  dE  dni d ln(aE) d + + + = + (6) xi d E d ni d d d c 
where the term with a subscript c accounts for collisions (emission, absorption, and 
scattering of photons). 
We can simplify equation (6) by linearizing it assuming small perturbations in both 
 and the phase space trajectories. From the metric, using the fact that we dened ni to 
be the photon direction measured by a fundamental observer in an orthonormal frame, 
we have 
(1  ) dxi 
i = n . (7)(1 + ) d 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>(1) (1) 
r c e 15 3 
2 
1 
0  0.1  e 1.5 3 
1 2 
0.5 1 
0 0 10 
5 
0 
0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 
0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0 0.2 0.4 0.6  rec3
0.4 
2 
0.2 1 
0 0 
0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 
x / c x / c rec rec 
Figure 2: Time evolution of the plane-parallel Greens functions for the potentials r 
(left) and c (right) in the uid approximation. The solid (dashed) lines show the results 
for bh2 = 0.03 (bh2 = 0). The three rows give snapshots at the times (0.1e, e, and 
rec = 2.5e). The speed of sound is decreased below c/
3 by the inclusion of baryons. 
From Bashinsky (2001). 
a signicant contribution to the total CMB anisotropy. So does the dip at x = 0. To 
understand the physics of this dip, let us examine the combination of photon density and 
gravitational potential appearing in the Sachs-Wolfe eect on large scales, which is given 
by equation (48) without the Doppler and   (integrated Sachs-Wolfe) contributions: 
1 e  3  +  . (63) 
(Recall that  is dened here as the fractional perturbation in photon number density.) 
The plane-parallel Greens function for e at recombination is shown in Figure 4. Note 
that the relation of e to potential on small scales in position space is quite dierent 
1from the e 3  of the large-scale Sachs-Wolfe eect. However, this relation still holds 
if one integrates the Greens functions over x to get the long wavelength contributions. 
The positive Dirac delta functions more than compensate for the negative  (x) behind 
the acoustic wavefronts so that e (x) dx  1 (r + c) dx.3 
31</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>4 is the Thomson optical depth (and not a conformal time). Equation (13) is the familiar 
solution of the radiative transfer equation. Emission (the terms in square brackets) at 
optical depth T is reduced by an exponential absorption factor. In contrast with equation 
(12), there is no explicit indication of the photosphere. The radial integration is taken 
over the entire past lightcone to  = 0 ( = 0). Contributions from  &gt; e (which may 
be dened by T(e) = 1 as in stellar astrophysics) are exponentially suppressed. 3 
Equation (13) may be claried by dening the integral visibility function 
	 0  
( )  exp  
 d  a( )ne( )T = exp [T(0   )] . (15) 
This function rises rapidly from zero to unity as  increases through e. The conformal 
time derivative d/d = aneT exp(T) is precisely the factor multiplying the scattering 
terms in equation (13). 
The spatial derivative term in equation (13) may be converted into a convective 
derivative through nii = (d/d ) +  . The convective derivative term (but not the 
partial derivative terms) may be integrated by parts. Using the function ( ) dened 
above, we obtain 
 0 
0(n i) = d(0  )  +1  + vei ni + 1ij ninj 
0 3 2 ret  0 
+	d (0  ) ( + )ret (16) 
0 
where we have discarded the unobservable monopole 0. 
Equation (16) simplies in the instantaneous recombination approximation, for which 
( ) is a unit step function at  = e and = D(  e) is a Dirac delta function. In 
this limit, we recover equation (12) with 
e =1  + vei ni + 1ij ninj .	 (17)3 2 e 
Equation (16) also shows us the eects of a nite width to the cosmic photosphere. 
The primary contributions multiplying are averaged over the nite timespan of recombi
nation while the eects of the time derivatives of the potentials turn on gradually during 
recombination. (As a result, the time derivative terms make a signicant contribution 
to anisotropy in models with low h2, because then recombination occurs only a little 
after the universe becomes matter-dominated, while the potentials are still changing.) 
Contributions to Primary Anisotropy 
In the instantaneous recombination approximation, there are a total of four contributions 
to primary CMB anisotropy measured by a fundamental observer: intrinsic, Doppler, 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>9 u , etc., are all transfer functions, i.e. they are solutions to the equations of motion in 
Fourier space subject to the initial conditions (k) = 1, (k) = 0. 
The transfer functions may be computed directly in k-space or by Fourier transfor
mation of the plane-parallel Greens functions by equation (59). The publicly available 
CMBFAST code (Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga 1996) computes them directly in k-space, while 
Bashinsky (2001) and Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2002) have computed them (in the 
uid approximation) by transforming the Greens functions. 
Numerical results 
In Section 6 we derived approximate results for the CMB anisotropy on large scales 
in the Sachs-Wolfe approximation, equation (48). Later, in Section 7, we worked out 
the plane-parallel Greens function solutions in the two-uid approximation. Section 8 
showed how to compute the angular correlation function and angular power spectrum 
from these ingredients. Here we present results for the two-uid approximation and 
compare with the exact computation by CMBFAST. The CMBFAST code includes three 
physical processes that are excluded by the two-uid approximation: a full treatment of 
neutrinos; photon diusion; and the polarization-dependence and anisotropic scattering 
contributions of Thomson scattering. 
Figure 5 shows the angular correlation function on small scales ( &lt;2). There 
are four notable phenomena. First, the curves all show a prominent dip. This feature 
is associated with the overlap of acoustic rings in the CMB photosphere. Recall that 
the spherical Greens functions correspond to acoustic waves expanding at the speed of 
sound. By the time of recombination, these waves reach a comoving distance of about 
0.5rec (Fig. 4). At the distance of recombination, rec (the diameter of the acoustic 
sphere) subtends an angle of about 1.2 . Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2002) show how the 
sharp feature occurring at this angle (thin curve in Fig. 5) arises from the singularities 
of  at the acoustic wavefronts. For angular separations less than this, sound waves are 
able to establish acoustic contact. For larger angular separations, the correlations reect 
the correlations present in the unmodied inationary spectrum. (Causal eects extend 
to about twice the acoustic length because the speed of sound is about half the speed of 
light.) 
The second notable result from Figure 5 is that the two-uid approximation with 
instantaneous recombination (thin curve) recovers much of the qualitative behavior of 
the CMBFAST result (thick curve) but underestimates the anisotropy on small scales. 
The main reason for this is that the Doppler contribution has been neglected here. 
Thus, the largest source of CMB anisotropy is accounted for by the intrinsic (
1 
3 ) and 
gravitational redshift contributions, but the Doppler contribution is appreciable on scales 
less than the acoustic length. 
37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>8 10 5 0 5 10  r(1) (x) 
20 10 0 10 20  c(1) (x) 
0.5 0 0.5 0.5 0 0.5 
x / c x / c rec rec 
Figure 3: Plane-parallel Greens functions for the density uctuations of photons (r = 
 , solid) and CDM (dashed) at recombination, in the uid approximation, for the same 
parameters shown in Fig. 1. Thick vertical lines represent Dirac delta functions of  (x) 
at its acoustic wavefronts and of c(x) at the origin. From Bashinsky (2001). 
Figure 4 suggests that baryons are responsible for the central dip in e . This dip is 
easy to understand. From Figure 1, the total gravitational potential has a sharp peak at 
x = 0. The photon-baryon uid has a high sound speed and therefore quickly adjusts to 
this potential by settling into hydrostatic equilibrium near x = 0. (Obviously hydrostatic 
equilibrium does not apply at the acoustic wavefronts, but it does hold as x 0 where 
the elapsed time is many sound-crossing times.) From the second of equations (25) we 
obtain the equation of hydrostatic equilibrium, 
i+ (+ p)i = 0 . (64) 
Linearizing this for the photon-baryon uid gives 
      1 3 b 3 b + 1 +  = i e +  = 0 . (65) i 4 4  4  
Thus, if b = 0, e has zero gradient in hydrostatic equilibrium. If b = 0, on the 
3 
other hand, e (0,) =  4 ( b/ )+ constant as x  0. The positive cusp of the CDM 
potential becomes a negative cusp of CMB anisotropy whose amplitude is proportional 
to b. Thus, baryons have two main eects on CMB anisotropy: they slow the sound 
speed and thereby decrease the acoustic distance compared with a pure photon gas, and 
they create a central dip in the Greens function. 
Angular Power Spectrum 
The goal of CMB integrations is to predict the anisotropy in a given cosmological model. 
We must ask carefully what this means. Does it mean to predict the actual pattern of 
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>As usual, we construct an orthonormal basis (a tetrad) at each spacetime point with 
e= V and with the spatial axes being parallel to the coordinate axes assuming that 0 
we use orthogonal coordinates for the background Robertson-Walker spacetime. (The 
spatial curvature perturbation 1   does not aect the orthogonality of the comoving 
coordinate axes as it is a conformal factor for dl2.) Energy, momentum, three-velocity 
(i.e. proper peculiar velocity), energy density, entropy density, etc. all have the same 
meanings as in special relativity when obtained from tensor components with a funda
mental observers orthonormal basis. Note that there is such an observer at every point 
in space; we dont (yet) preferentially single out the observer at  = 0. 
In the absence of anisotropic, relativistic stresses (produced mainly by neutrinos in 
the early universe),  =  and the spacetime metric perturbations are described by 
a single Newtonian-like gravitational potential. In this case, equation (1) is identical 
to the usual weak-eld metric in the Newtonian limit aside from the conformal factor 
a2( ) arising from cosmic expansion. In the following, we will distinguish the two metric 
functions in order to keep track of which physical eects arise from the gravitational 
redshift part of the metric () and which arise from the spatial curvature part (). 
The unperturbed, or background, density (t) obeys the Friedmann equation: 
 2d ln a 8 = G a2  K . (2)d 3 
  a3   a4Note that because  in the matter-dominated era and  in the radiation-
dominated era, the curvature term is negligible at high redshift. However, spatial curva
ture aects the geometry at low redshift and does have an eect on CMB anisotropy. 
For later use, we provide the solution to equation (2) for a model consisting of only 
matter (with present density parameter m) and radiation (whose energy density equals 
that of matter at a = aeq = 2.41  104 mh2): 
a( )  1  2 aeq 1/2 
= + , where H0e . (3) aeq e 4 e  m 
1Note that a = aeq at  = 2(
2  1)e. For m = 0.35 and h = 0.7, aeq = 4100 and 
e = 110 Mpc. This solution neglects curvature and a cosmological constant but should 
be accurate to better than 0.1% during recombination. 
3 CMB Radiative Transfer 
We wish to determine the specic intensity I measured by the observer at  = 0 and 
 = 0 as a function of photon direction and energy. Conceptually, the way we will do it 
is by tracing photon trajectories back from  = 0 to recombination at radial coordinate 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>The angular analogue of equation (68) is the angular correlation function 
1  
n1)( n2) = (2l + 1)ClPl( n1  n2) (71) C() (4 l=0 
where  n1  n2 = cos  and Pl(x) is the Legendre polynomial of degree l. Notice that the 
angular correlation function C() and power spectrum Cl are Fourier-Legendre transfor
mations of each other and therefore contain the same information. 
To calculate the angular power spectrum we must relate the anisotropy to the po
tential in k-space. We do this by expanding the anisotropy in plane waves. In the 
Sachs-Wolfe approximation, from equation (48) we get 
      e 2ik  n k iek0( n) = d3k e n C  (k, e) + 2 d e in  (k, 0 ) (72)3e 0 
with C  1 for the isentropic mode and C 2 for isocurvature modes. The minus sign 3 
in the plane waves occurs because  n is the radial unit vector. 
Now we use the spherical wave expansion of a plane wave, 
 
ix  
e= il(2l + 1)jl(x)Pl() (73) 
l=0 
where jl(x) is the spherical Bessel function (e.g. Jackson Classical Electromagnetism). 
Substituting into equation (72) yields 
  
k 0( n) = d3k  
(i)l(2l + 1)l(k, 0)Pl( n) (74) 
l=0 
where k = k/k and, in the Sachs-Wolfe approximation, 
 e 
l(k, 0) = Cjl(ke) + 2 jl (ke) (k, e) + 2 d jl(k)  (k, 0 ) . (75)3e 0 
(The derivative term j came from dierentiating eq. 73 with respect to x, which brings l 
k down the factor i = i n needed for the Doppler term in eq. 72.) 
We need one more mathematical result, the addition theorem for spherical harmonics, 
l4   Pl(  n2) = Ylm( n1)Ylm( n2) . (76) n1 2l + 1 m=l 
Using equations (69), (74), and (76), we obtain 
 alm = (i)l4 d3k Y lm(k) l(k, 0) . (77) 
35</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Combining all our results, the perturbed uid equations for CDM (subscript c) and the 
photon-baryon uid (subscript ) are 
 c = 2 uc + 3  ,  
a uc = uc +  ,  a 
  = 2 u + 3  , 
9yb a2 u = cs   u +  . (29)4 a 
These agree with equations (3) of Seljak (1994) if neutrino shear stress is neglected so 
that  = . They are valid on all length scales provided that the photons are tightly 
coupled to the baryons. 
Equations (29) must be supplemented by an equation for the gravitational potential 
. We have a choice of equations (19)(23). If we evolve the matter and radiation 
exactly, then all of these components of the Einstein equations are equivalent. We will 
choose a linear combination involving the eective sound speed squared 
p/d 1 3 1 b +  d c 2 c /d = 1 + y , y  . (30)w  d 3 4  +  
Note that cw would be the speed of sound if all matter (CDM and baryons) were tightly 
coupled to all radiation (photons and neutrinos). However, because this multi-component 
medium is not a single perfect uid, cw is not a true sound speed. Nonetheless, it is a 
useful quantity for obtaining a physical evolution equation for the gravitational potential. 
We choose a linear combination of equations (19)(23) that yields the simplest de
scription of motion, by multiplying equation (19) by c2 and subtracting it from equation w 
(23). Using equation (2), and setting  = , the resulting perturbed Einstein equation 
is (Bardeen 1980) 
a2 a2 
2 2 2 + 3(1 + cw )   + 3(cw  w)  (5 + 3w)K   cw  2 a a 
2 
2 w 2= 4Ga2(p  c )  c , (31)w y  
where  is a dimensionless entropy potential that will be discussed below, and 
p 1 = . (32) w  3(1 + y) 
In equation (31), p and  are the total pressure and energy density perturbations 
summed over baryons, cold dark matter, photons, and neutrinos. Let us approximate 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Newtonian-inspired calculation (Rees &amp; Sciama 1968) would include only the   term 
because   is due to space curvature and has no eect on nonrelativistic particles (nor 
does it have any Newtonian interpretation). But just as the deection of light in a weak 
gravitational eld is twice the Newtonian-inspired value, if  =  the change in energy 
due to a time-varying potential is twice the result from  . 
Note that the integrated Sachs-Wolfe term is the only contribution to anisotropy 
in the linear regime (i.e. arising from linearized uctuations) that is produced after 
recombination. In most models the contribution is small, although there is a measurable 
eect on large angular scale anisotropy in models with curvature and/or vacuum energy. 
5 Evolution of Matter and Metric Perturbations 
To evaluate the solutions given above (e.g. eqs. 12 plus 18 in the instantaneous re
combination approximation) we must determine the density, velocity, and gravitational 
potential uctuations present at the time of recombination (and later, to get the inte
grated Sachs-Wolfe contribution). This is non-trivial. Accurate results can be obtained 
only by integrating numerically two of equations (19)(23) plus the coupled relativis
tic perturbation equations for photons, baryons, neutrinos, dark matter, and any other 
components present in the universe (e.g. Ma &amp; Bertschinger 1995; Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga 
1996). This integration is performed numerically by the CMBFAST code of Seljak &amp; 
Zaldarriaga as well as by its slower predecessors (e.g. Ma &amp; Bertschinger 1995). 
Despite the complexity of this evolution, we can learn a great deal by examining the 
behavior on large scales and at early times in the universe. In this section we will derive 
the equations of motion for the metric and the coupled uids responsible for metric 
perturbations. We will solve these analytically on large scales. This approach gives good 
physical insight to the various sources of CMB anisotropy. 
5.1 Einstein equations 
The Einstein equations for metric (1) are given by Bertschinger (1996); beware that  
and  are reversed there. 
The 00 Einstein equation give 
  aa 2 + 3K   3   +  = 4Ga2 (19) a a 
where  = (t) is the perturbation in the proper energy density at (xi, ) measured by 
a fundamental observer and K is the spatial curvature constant of a non-at Robertson-
Walker background spacetime. (We reserve the lower-case k for comoving wavenumber 
below.) Although we will later drop curvature, it is included here for completeness. 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>must be negligible at late times because 2 diverges as y  0.) In the matter-dominated 
era, y  1, the general solution including both isentropic and isocurvature modes is a 
constant potential, 
9 1 2 (x, )  i(x) + e 2  2i for y  1 .	 (46)10 5 3 
The entropy term in parentheses is simply the relative variation of the photon-to-CDM 
ratio from equation (34). The relative sizes of the coecients in equation (46) (0.9 vs 
0.2) shows how inecient entropy is in producing a gravitational potential uctuation. 
This will cause the isocurvature mode to have a much larger CMB anisotropy than the 
isentropic mode, for a given post-recombination gravitational potential. 
The Sachs-Wolfe anisotropy follows from substituting into equations (12) and (18) 
the potential, density and velocity perturbations computed on large scales assuming that 
recombination occurs at y  1. First, from equations (18), (43), (44), and (46), we get 
e =	(2/3)e  (2/3e)niie , isentropic ; (47)e  (2/3e)niie , isocurvature , 
where e  ( a/a)e and subscript e refers to recombination. Note that the velocity term 
becomes small for comoving wavelengths much larger than the Hubble distance 1 
e 
at recombination. Note also the critical dierence between isentropic and isocurvature 
initial conditions as far as the post-recombination potential. Combining equation (12 
with (47), we get the nal Sachs-Wolfe eect for the anisotropy in direction (, ): 
 e 2  (, ) = C + (e, , , e) + 2 d  (, , , 0  ) , (48)3e 	 0 
where C = 1/3 for isentropic uctuations and C = 2 for isentropic uctuations. Note that 
equation (48) includes only the gravitational potential at and after recombination  by 
ignoring all acoustic eects (and neutrinos) we have simplied the evolution suciently 
to express the primary anisotropy entirely in terms of the potential and its derivatives 
for   e. To the extent that the rst two terms (intrinsic and Doppler anisotropy) 
dominate the anisotropy, maps of the CMB anisotropy reveal (on scales larger than the 
acoustic horizon) the gravitational potential at recombination. 
The coecient C is six times larger for isocurvature uctuations than for isentropic 
ones. (This is, of course, an approximation  the solution assumed zrec  zeq which is 
not exact.) For a given amplitude of gravitational potential uctuations, hence dark mat
ter uctuations (dark matter being the dominant component at recombination), isocur
vature uctuations produce a much larger CMB anisotropy. This is because the initial 
entropy uctuations directly perturb the radiation with no compensating time dilation 
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>solution of equation (54) in spherical coordinates with delta function initial condition. 
The result is 3 (3)(r, ) = (cs)3(cs  r) (60)r 4 
where (x) is the Heaviside step function, (x) = 0 for x &lt; 1 and (x) = 1 for x &gt; 1. 
The Greens function for the radiation potential is remarkably simple: it is a spatially 
uniform wave expanding at the speed of sound, with unit volume integral (from eq. 59 
for k = 0). In short, it is a spherical sound wave! The oscillations of the transfer 
function 3j1(k)/(k) arise because of the nite extent of the Greens function and they 
are characteristic of causal behavior. This phenomenon is essentially the origin of the 
acoustic peaks of the CMB power spectrum, which we will discuss below. 
This beautifully simple result suggests that we apply the Greens function method to 
the full problem of equations (52) for all times. However, there is a practical problem with 
the three-dimensional Greens functions. The Poisson equation tells us that the photon 
2(3)density uctuation  is given, in part, by . The derivative of the Heaviside function r 
is a Dirac delta function. The Laplacian takes one more derivative, so that (3)(r, ) has  
a term proportional to dD(r  cs)/dr. Great care must be exercised when dealing 
with derivatives of delta functions, especially when (3) is determined numerically. Ther 
numerical challenges are serious enough to dissuade us from using three-dimensional 
Greens functions. 
These delta function singularities are a consequence of the perfect uid assumption. If 
photon diusion is included, then the acoustic wavefront will spread slightly. Even with 
diusion, however, the spherical transfer function for  is sharply peaked at the radius of 
the acoustic sphere. This means that an initial point-like perturbation in the potential, 
located on or near the CMB photosphere, will produce a ring of temperature anisotropy 
on the sky. The observed pattern is a superposition of such rings like the ripples from 
stones dropped in a pond. The maximum size of the rings  twice the acoustic radius 
at recombination  imprints a characteristic scale in the CMB anisotropy. 
7.2 Plane-parallel Greens functions 
For numerical integration purposes it is preferable to modify the Greens function method 
to avoid derivatives of delta functions. The singular behavior is reduced if we superpose 
many spherical waves to create a plane wavefront using the Huyghens construction. This 
works for any Greens function as follows: 
  
(1)(x, ) = (3)(r, ) 2rdr . (61) 
|x| 
The integral ensures that (1) is less singular than (3) at the wavefronts. From equation 
(59) it follows that (1) is the one-dimensional inverse Fourier transform of the transfer 
28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
Department of Physics 
Physics 8.942 
Cosmic Microwave Background Anisotropy
c2001-2003 Edmund Bertschinger. All rights reserved. 
1 Introduction 
These notes present a simplied computation of cosmic microwave background anisotropy 
induced by primeval gravitational potential or entropy uctuations. The basic treatment 
is equivalent to the calculation of anisotropy on large angular scales presented rst by 
Sachs &amp; Wolfe (1967). The discussion here goes beyond the Sachs-Wolfe treatment to 
include a discussion of the dominant contributions to anisotropy on small angular scales. 
The presentation given here is based in part on the PhD thesis of Sergei Bashinsky 
(Bashinsky 2001) and Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2001, 2002). More elementary treat
ments of CMB anisotropy are given by Chapter 18 of Peacock and online by Wayne Hu 
at http://background.uchicago.edu/). 
We adopt several assumptions in order to simplify the algebra without losing the 
main physical eects: 
1.	Instantaneous recombination. We assume that, prior to hydrogen recombination 
at a = ar , photons scatter so frequently with electrons that the photon gas is 
a perfect gas with spatially-varying energy density r and uid three-velocity vi 
(orthonormal components of peculiar velocity). This gas is tightly coupled to the 
baryons (electrons plus all ionization states of atomic matter). The gradual 
decoupling of photons and baryons is approximated by instantaneous decoupling 
at a = ar . We will indicate how to improve on this treatment by treating the 
radiation eld prior to recombination as an imperfect gas coupled to baryons by 
Thomson scattering. An accurate treatment of hydrogen and helium recombination 
is needed in this case. With non-instantaneous recombination, photon polarization 
must also be considered. We ignore polarization here. The resulting errors are a 
few percent in rms temperature anisotropy at small angular scales. 
2.	No large-scale spatial curvature. We suppose that the universe is a perturbed 
Robertson-Walker spacetime. Although the curvature terms (proportional to 1) 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>5 presents a simplied set of evolution equations. Section 6 solves these equations on 
large scales to derive the famous Sachs-Wolfe formula. Section 7 presents a real-space 
Greens function approach to solving and understanding the small-scale behavior, espe
cially the acoustic peaks. Section 8 shows how to compute the angular power spectrum 
from the solution of the radiative transfer equation. Numerical results are presented in 
Section 9. 
2 Perturbed Robertson-Walker Spacetimes 
This section summarizes the elementary treatment of a weakly perturbed Robertson-
Walker spacetime. 
We write the spacetime line element as 
2ds2 = a ( ) (1 + 2)d 2 + (1  2)dl2 (1) 
where dl2 is the usual spatial line element in comoving coordinates (e.g. dl2 = d2 + 
r2d2, or dl2 = dx2 + dy2 + dz2 in Cartesian coordinates if the background space is at). 
The metric perturbations are characterized by two functions (xi,  ) and (xi,  ) which 
we assume are small (we neglect all terms quadratic in these elds). 
Equation (1) is a cosmological version of the standard weak-eld metric used in 
linearized general relativity. It ignores gravitomagnetism (present in a g0i metric term) 
and gravitational radiation (present in a transverse-traceless strain tensor hij added to 
the spatial metric). Note that the Newtonian limit follows from equation (1) when 
a = 0 and  = . Dots denote derivatives with respect to conformal time  , while 
gradient symbols (e.g. i) represent gradients (covariant derivatives) with respect to the 
comoving spatial coordinates using the unperturbed 3-metric of dl2 . In a at background 
with Cartesian coordinates, i = i. 
As in the standard treatment of linearized general relativity, we describe spacetime 
by perturbations added to a background model. The coordinate-freedom allows us many 
ways to do this for a given set of physical perturbations. We will not discuss this gauge-
xing problem in these notes. Bertschinger (1996) discusses this issue in detail. Equation 
(1) conveniently avoids gauge artifacts and enables us to focus on the physics. 
In the following, we often speak of fundamental (or comoving) observers by 
which we mean observers at xed xi . The 4-velocity of a fundamental observer is V = 
a1(1) e . In general, fundamental observers are not freely-falling (as one can see from 
the geodesic equation for dV i/d), nor do they correspond to the rest frame of a galaxy 
or to the frame in which the CMB dipole anisotropy vanishes. (See Peacock section 9.4 
for a discussion of the dipole anisotropy caused by the Doppler eect.) However, they 
dene a very convenient set of local rest frames in which to project tensor components. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>To get the angular power spectrum we must now relate the potentials in equation 
(75) to the initial random eld of potential or entropy uctuations that induced the CMB 
anisotropy. We dene the CMB transfer function 
l(k, 0) (78) Dl(k)  
i(k) 
where i(k) is the Fourier transform of the primeval potential eld of equation (46). 
(This assumes the initial uctuations were isentropic; if they were isocurvature, then i 
should be replaced by the initial entropy perturbation eld.) The universe is like a linear 
amplier in electronics: each harmonic component is modulated by an analog lter. Note 
that the transfer function depends on spatial frequency but not direction, because the 
equations of motion are rotationally invariant. 
Using equations (70), (76), (77), and (78), plus the orthonormality of the spherical  k)Ylm ( harmonics ( d Ylm(k) = ll mm ), we get the key result for the angular power 
spectrum of the CMB: 
Cl = 4 d3k P(k)Dl 2(k) .	 (79) 
Here, P(k) is the primeval power spectrum. For scale-invariant initial uctuations, 
P  k3 . 
The dominant contribution to large-scale anisotropy is the Sachs-Wolfe eect, for 
which Dl = C(e/i)jl(ke). For a scale-invariant spectrum, equation (79) can be 
integrated exactly giving Cl  1/[l(l + 1)], corresponding to equal power per logarithmic 
interval of angular degree l, i.e. a at spectrum on the sphere. (In d dimensions, a 
scale-invariant spectrum is kd . For large l, the eective wavenumber is k  l.) This is 
why plots of the CMB power spectrum always show l(l + 1)Cl. 
We can go beyond the Sachs-Wolfe approximation by replacing equation (72) with the 
exact equation (16). Each eld such as  (x, ) is written as a Fourier integral with the 
Fourier components proportional to the initial gravitational potential through a transfer 
function, e.g.  (k, ) =  (k, )i(k ), a straightforward generalization of equation (56). 
Thus, we may generalize equation (72) to (Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga 1996; note the modied 
coecient of  due to our dierent denition here) 
 0  1 jDl(k) = d(0  )1  +  + u + ij n i n jl(k) 
0	 3  2 ret  0  +	d (0  ) ( + )(k, 0  ) , (80) 
0  
where () = exp[T(0  )] is the visibility function of equation (15) and subscript 
ret means to evaluate the quantity in brackets at (k,  = 0  ). The functions  , , 
36</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>changes through linear evolution. Every linear eld has a transfer function (e.g. c,  , 
etc.). The transfer function is spherically symmetric in k-space because of the rotational 
invariance of the equations of motion. Note carefully the notation: r (k,) is the transfer 
function, i.e. the solution subject to initial condition r = 1, while r (k,) is the solution 
subject to the initial condition r = i(k). The point is that once the transfer function is 
known, then the solution for arbitrary initial condition follows by simple multiplication. 
The transfer function is the solution to the evolution equation with initial condition 
exp(ik  x). Plane wave initial conditions are but one possible choice of initial condition.  
Another useful choice is a point-like perturbation at the origin, 
(3)( x,)  (3)( x) as  0 (57)r D  
where (3)( x) is the three-dimensional Dirac delta function. The superscript (3) is placed D 
on r to remind us that the initial condition is point-like in three dimensions. 
The solution subject to a point-like initial condition is called a Greens function. The 
solution at any later time is then simply a convolution of the initial eld by the Greens 
function:  
r ( x,) = d3 x  r ( x  ,0)(3)( x  x ,) . (58)r 
Heuristically, we can imagine decomposing the initial eld into a sum of delta functions. 
Each delta function evolves into the Greens function. The evolved eld is therefore a 
superposition of Greens functions. 
The Greens function description is mathematically equivalent to the Fourier space 
description with a transfer function. In fact, the Greens function is simply the inverse 
Fourier transform of the transfer function: 
k(k,) = (3)(r,) e ix d3 x . (59) 
(We remove the subscript r since this relation is not restricted to the radiation potential 
but is true for any transfer function and Greens function pair.) Note that since the 
transfer function is spherically symmetric in k-space, the Greens function is also spher
ically symmetric in position space. That is, (3) depends only on the length r = | x|. 
(Assuming a at cosmology, we use r interchangeably with the radial comoving coor
dinate .) The spherical Greens function and transfer function are Fourier transform 
pairs. 
In the Fourier domain, the evolved eld follows by multiplication with the transfer 
function. In the position domain, the evolved eld follows by convolution with the 
Greens function. The Fourier transform of a convolution is the product of Fourier 
transforms, and the Fourier transform of a product becomes a convolution. 
So what is the Greens function corresponding to the radiation transfer function 
r (k,)? It is easily found either by Fourier transformation of equation (55) or by 
27</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>delta function D. The complex conjugation may be removed provided that the argument 
of the delta function is changed to k + k . 
It is easy to check that the spatial covariance, i.e. the two-point correlation function, 
is the Fourier transform of the power spectrum: 
x1 ( x1)( x2)= d3ke ik( x 2) P(k) . (68) 
Note that the correlations of dierent points in space are generally nonzero  in par
ticular, scale-invariant uctuations are a statistical fractal, with correlations extending 
over all scales  but that the correlation at dierent points vanishes in k-space because 
of the Dirac delta function in equation (67). This is a general feature of stationary 
random elds, i.e. random elds whose statistical properties are invariant under spatial 
translation. It is a natural outcome of inationary models, where the uctuations are 
the zero-point uctuations of a nearly massless free eld; each mode is independent. 
Our calculations have shown that the primary CMB anisotropy  is linear in the 
gravitational potential (and its derivatives and integrals). Thus, the anisotropy at any 
point in the sky is a linear combination of gaussian-distributed random numbers. A linear 
combination of normal (gaussian) random numbers is itself normal. Thus, the anisotropy 
0( n) should be a gaussian random eld on the sphere. Thus, to fully characterize its 
statistical properties we need only to calculate the analogue of the power spectrum on a 
sphere. 
The angular power spectrum is straightforward to dene by analogy with equations 
(66) and (67). We rst expand the temperature anisotropy in the orthonormal basis 
functions appropriate for a sphere, spherical harmonics: 
 l 
0( n) = almYlm( n) (69) 
l=0 m=l 
where Ylm( n) is shorthand for Ylm(,) for spherical angles (,) giving the observational 
direction  n. (Note that here we are dening  n to have opposite sign to the rest of these 
notes, for consistency with usage by experimentalists:  n is the direction the photon 
travels.) The angular power spectrum is now dened by the covariance of the expansion 
coecients: 
 almalm Cl ll mm (70) 
where ll is now the Kronecker delta. Each angular coecient is independent for a 
random eld with rotational invariance on a sphere. This is the angular analogue to 
translational invariance, which led to a Dirac delta function in equation (67). The 
compactness of the sphere makes the sum over harmonics discrete rather than continuous, 
leading to a Kronecker delta rather than a Dirac delta function. 
34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>7.1 Radiation era 
Equations (52) are still too complicated to solve analytically. To gain insight, let us 
examine the solutions in the radiation era, y  1. In this limit, equations (52) become 
1 1  2r +  (4r + c)  c = cs2  2r , 2 
3 1 3 1 4  2c +  c + c = (y  yb)  r + r . (53)2 4 2 
We will solve these for isentropic initial conditions,  = 0 as y  0. From equations 
(49), c/r  y. Thus, CDM has negligible eect on the dominant radiation component 
in the radiation era. On the other hand, the radiation perturbations provide the source 
for c. 
Thus, we must solve the simple damped wave equation 
4  2r +  r = cs2  2r (54) 
with constant sound speed cs = 31/2 . Since this is a partial dierential equation, we 
must specify the initial conditions for all space. However, the problem simplies because 
it is a linear partial dierential equation. The linear superposition principle means that 
we can expand the solution in any convenient set of spatial basis functions. The common 
choice in cosmology for at (Euclidean) space is the plane wave basis exp(ik  x ), so that  
2 = k2 for any given plane wave component. We use the usual notation of at space 
in which k and  x are 3-vectors. 
The Fourier space solution to equation (54) is 
j1(k)r (k, ) = 3 , (55)k 
where j1(x) = (sin x  x cos x)/x2 is a spherical Bessel function. Note that the normal
ization chosen so that r = 1 for  = 0. 
Suppose that the initial potential uctuations at the end of the inationary era are 
i( x ). The Fourier transform is i(k ). (Note the common practice of using the same 
function name to denote the real-space function and its Fourier transform. The meaning 
becomes clear from the argument:  x is always a spatial position and k is always a 
wavevector.) Linear superposition means that the Fourier transform at any later time is 
r (k, ) = r (k, )i(k ) (56) 
By analogy with linear lters in electrical systems, r (k, ) is called the transfer function 
for the radiation potential. It is the factor by which every Fourier component of r (k, ) 
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>0.4 0.8 1.2 1.6 2 2 4 6 8 C () , 10 9 K 2 CDM , bh2= 0.02 
1/3  +  , inst. rec. 
CDM , bh2= 0.03 
 m =  = 0.35 
, degrees 
Figure 5: Angular CMB temperature correlation function. The parameters of the CDM 
model are m = 0.35,  = 0.65, h = 0.65 with a scale-invariant spectrum P  k3 . 
For this set of parameters and the displayed bh2 values, the acoustic sphere subtends 
an angle s  1.2 . The thin solid curve is calculated using the two-uid approximation 
with instantaneous recombination. All the other curves are calculated using CMBFAST. 
The dip in C() is shifted to smaller angles for the open model (dashed-dotted line). 
The slope for &lt;s/2 is dependent on the baryon density (dashed vs. solid line). Based 
on Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger (2001). 
The third notable result is that the acoustic length in the open model (dashed-dotted 
curve in Fig. 5) subtends a smaller angle. This is simply because the angular distance 
r() to the CMB photosphere is larger for an open model (Weinberg 2000). 
Finally, Figure 5 shows that the baryon contribution has the most signicant eect 
for angles less than half the diameter of the acoustic sphere. The baryon eect arises 
from the interplay between the wavefront singularity and the central valley in Figure 
4. As we showed, the depth of that valley is proportional to b. This translates into a 
roughly linear dependence of the inner slope of C() on b. 
The angular correlation function has the attractive property of associating acoustic 
phenomena with localized features. The localization in angle means that a Fourier-
Legendre representation will produce ringing (oscillations) in the angular frequency. 
Because the sphere is a compact manifold, the angular frequency l is discrete. Figure 
6 plots the angular power spectrum Cl to show us that this ringing corresponds to the 
famous acoustic peaks. 
The uid approximation yields surprisingly accurate prediction of the CMB anisotropy 
38</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>This assumption is consistent with ination but not with some other models of structure 
formation where the density uctuations are generated much later. 
Isentropic uctuations are dened by the condition  = 0 but  = 0. They cor
respond to the energy density of all components (photons, baryons, dark matter, etc) 
varying together in such a way that the entropy perturbation vanishes. In particular, 
the photon-to-baryon number density ratio is a universal constant in this model (until 
after recombination, when photons and baryons decouple), as is the initial photon-to-
dark matter particle number density ratio. This it exactly the condition resulting from 
standard ination plus reheating. Inationary uctuations are often called adiabatic 
although isentropic (i.e.  = 0 initially) is more accurate and descriptive. 
Isocurvature uctuations have  = 0 initially (i.e. no curvature perturbation) but 
 = 0. Physically, they correspond to an equation of state p(, S) with spatially-varying 
entropy S but initially constant . Isocurvature uctuations can be created by a rst-
order phase-transition or any other process that produces spatial variations in the pho-
ton/baryon or photon-to-dark matter ratio while leaving the net energy density unper
turbed. As the universe expands, as long as particle collisions are rapid, the specic 
entropy of each uid element is conserved. That is, prior to decoupling for any particle 
species, the ratio of number densities of that particle to photons is conserved. If the 
ratio varies spatially, then pressure gradients develop which move matter and cause a 
gravitational potential perturbation to develop. Nonstandard models of ination can be 
constructed in which entropy perturbations are generated during or after reheating. 
In our particular case we are considering isocurvature CDM perturbations, since 
 = 0 corresponds to a spatially varying photon-to-CDM ratio in equation (33). It is 
also possible to consider models with a xed T 3/c but with spatially varying T 3/b, or 
isocurvature baryon models. Indeed, isocurvature-type perturbations can be produced 
that have the ratio of any two or more species varying in space initially, as long as the 
total energy density is constant so that the metric is unperturbed ( = 0). 
It is easy to recognize the isentropic and isocurvature modes (as they are often 
called in the literature) as homogeneous and particular solutions of equation (39). We 
impose initial conditions at  = i such that yi  1. Isentropic initial conditions have 
(x, i) = i(x) and (x, i) =  (x, i) = 0. (For example, the uctuations produced by 
ination are frozen in and unchanging during the radiation-dominated era on scales larger 
than the acoustic length.) Isocurvature initial conditions have (x, i) =  (x, i) = 0 
and (x, i) = i(x), with   = 0 on scales larger than the acoustic length. 
We leave it as an exercise for the student to show that the desired solutions of equation 
(39) are 
9 1(y)i(x) , isentropic ; (x,  ) = 10 2y isocurvature . 5(4+3y) 1(y)e 22i(x) , (45) 
(The 2 solution is not included here because it is the decaying mode. Its amplitude 
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>7 eect. For isentropic uctuations, we saw that the large-scale photon density perturba
tion has opposite sign to the gravitational potential (because of the time dilation eect 
discussed following eq. 42), which results in a cancellation of the CMB anisotropy. Hence 
the famous Sachs-Wolfe formula  = 1 . Although Sachs &amp; Wolfe (1967) did not con3 
sider isocurvature initial conditions, we have seen that it is just as easy to estimate their 
contribution to large-scale anisotropy. The much larger ratio of CMB uctuations to 
dark matter perturbations has led to a rejection of most isocurvature models. 
Greens function solution for small-scale anisotropy 
As we have seen, the coupled Einstein and uid equations can be solved analytically 
on large scales, with the result that the temperature anisotropy basically traces the 
gravitational potential uctuations on the CMB photosphere. However, this is not the full 
story for CMB anisotropy. On smaller scales, the potential uctuations set the photon-
baryon uid into motion, sending sound waves propagating through the universe. These 
sound waves leave a characteristic signature in the correlations of CMB anisotropies on 
angular scales of about one degree. This signature is reected in the acoustic peaks of 
the angular power spectrum. 
On scales smaller than the acoustic length, it is hard to solve the coupled Einstein and 
uid equations for a multicomponent medium. The usual procedure is to work in Fourier 
space so that the partial dierential equations become ordinary dierential equations in 
time. Seljak (1994) solved equations (29) and (20) numerically in Fourier space. Ma &amp; 
Bertschinger (1995) solved the complete coupled system including the Boltzmann equa
tion for photons and neutrinos, which are necessary for imperfect uids or collisionless 
plasmas. Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga (1996) introduced CMBFAST, a fast computer code for 
solving the complicated system of equations. These developments are valuable, especially 
CMBFAST because it has revolutionized CMB data analysis and model testing. 
Here, however, we seek physical insight more than numerical results. The approach 
is based on work by Sergei Bashinsky (Bashinsky 2001, Bashinsky &amp; Bertschinger 2001, 
2002). Instead of solving the uid and Einstein equations in Fourier space, we solve the 
coupled wave equations (31) and (37) in conguration space (x,  ). 
Our model for CMB anisotropy is based on two uids coupled by gravity: the photon-
baryon uid (with sound speed cs) and CDM (with vanishing sound speed). On physical 
grounds, we would expect waves to propagate through the photon-baryon uid with speed 
cs but no waves to propagate through the CDM. It is intriguing that equations (31) and 
(37) have almost the expected form, namely a coupled system of damped wave equations 
with the appropriate sound speeds. However, the fundamental variables appearing there 
are the gravitational and entropy potentials, which do not cleanly separate the two uids. 
If we ignore curvature by setting K = 0 (as is justied at high redshift), then the 
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>these notes provides a useful way to comprehend the dynamics of CMB anisotropy. 
I would like to thank Sergei Bashinsky for his collaboration and for many helpful 
discussions, without which these notes would be impossible. 
References 
[1] Bardeen, J. M. 1980, PRD, 22, 1882. 
[2] Bashinsky, S. 2001, MIT PhD thesis. 
[3] Bashinsky, S., &amp; Bertschinger, E. 2001, PRL, 87, 081301. 
[4] Bashinsky, S., &amp; Bertschinger, E. 2002, PRD, 65, 123008. 
[5] Bertschinger, E. 1996, in Cosmology and Large Scale Structure, proc. Les Houches 
Summer School, Session LX, ed. R. Schaeer, J. Silk, M. Spiro, and J. Zinn-Justin 
(Amsterdam: Elsevier Science), 273-347. 
[6] Hu, W., Seljak, U., White, M., &amp; Zaldarriaga, M. 1998, PRD, 57, 3290. 
[7] Kodama, H., &amp; Sasaki, M. 1984, Prog. Theor. Phys. Suppl., 78, 1. 
[8] Kodama, H., &amp; Sasaki, M. 1986, Int. J. Mod. Phys., A1, 265. 
[9] Ma, C.-P., &amp; Bertschinger, E. 1995, ApJ, 455, 7. 
[10] Rees, M. J., &amp; Sciama, D. W. 1968, Nature, 517, 611. 
[11] Sachs, R. K., &amp; Wolfe, A. M. 1967, ApJ, 147, 73. 
[12] Seljak, U. 1994, ApJ, 435, L87. 
[13] Seljak, U. 1996, ApJ, 463, 1. 
[14] Seljak, U., &amp; Zaldarriaga, M. 1996, ApJ, 469, 437. 
[15] Spergel, D. N., &amp; Zaldarriaga, M. 1997, PRL, 79, 2180. 
[16] Weinberg, S. 2000, PRD, 62, 127302. 
[17] Weinberg, S. 2002, astro-ph/0207375. 
[18] Zaldarriaga, M., &amp; Seljak, U. 1997, PRD, 55, 1830. 
[19] Zaldarriaga, M., Seljak, U., &amp; Bertschinger, E. 1998, ApJ, 494, 491. 
40</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>gravitational, and integrated Sachs-Wolfe. We will discuss them in turn so as to give a 
physical interpretation to the sources of CMB anisotropy. 
The intrinsic and Doppler anisotropies correspond to the rst term in equation (12), 
i.e. the brightness temperature perturbation e present at the time of recombination. 
Equation (17) gives this term. However, further simplication results because of the 
tight coupling of photons and baryons (and electrons) prior to recombination. Under 
ithese conditions, vei = v . Also, the intrinsic quadrupole anisotropy source term due to 
polarization eects vanishes because multiple scattering prior to recombination damps 
the polarization caused by single scattering. This is the reason why CMB polarization 
is predicted to be so small (Zaldarriaga &amp; Seljak 1997; Spergel &amp; Zaldarriaga 1997). 
Thus, in the instantaneous recombination approximation, we may write 
1 i . (18) e  3  + niv 
e 
iThis gives the explicit form of the intrinsic ( 1  ) and Doppler (niv ) contributions. (Re3 3call that  = 4  / .) It has a simple interpretation which does not require the full 
treatment of scattering used in deriving equation (16). In the instantaneous recombi
nation approximation, the photon-baryon gas is a perfect uid up to the moment of 
recombination. In the rest frame of this uid, the radiation is isotropic blackbody radi
ation at temperature T . Spatial variations of T translate into number density variations 
 = 3 ln T , explaining the rst term. But the photon-baryon uid moves with a local 
ithree-velocity v . (Fluids ow!) For small velocities, the linear Doppler formula gives a 
ibrightness temperature shift niv . In some directions, the photosphere is moving toward 
us (relative to unperturbed Hubble expansion) while in other places it recedes, producing 
anisotropy in the emitted radiation. 
The next contribution to anisotropy in equation (12) is the gravitational redshift 
e  0. Each photon travelling to us falls through a gravitational potential dierence 
e  0 and the energies are changed correspondingly. 
The literature contains some misstatements about the gravitational redshift eect. 
1The primary anisotropy for isentropic uctuations on large scales is  = 3 e (Sachs &amp; 
Wolfe 1967), a factor of 3 dierent from the gravitational redshift anisotropy to which 
it is sometimes erroneously ascribed. We will see below that the Sachs-Wolfe result 
comes from combining the intrinsic anisotropy ( 1  ) and gravitational redshift eects. 3 
(Moreover, it is valid only for isentropic uctuations but not for isocurvature ones. More 
on that below.) 
The nal contribution to anisotropy comes from the integral term in equations (12) 
and (16), which is commonly called the Integrated Sachs-Wolfe term. If the gravi
tational potential changes with time, photons suer dierent amounts of gravitational 
redshift falling into and climbing out of potential wells between recombination and today. 
(This eect on the CMB was rst pointed out by Rees &amp; Sciama in 1968.) However, a 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>will be included in the basic equations, our numerical calculations will not fully 
include them. This simplies the harmonic decomposition and is consistent with 
ination as the origin of uctuations. The only important eect we miss is the 
anisotropy produced by the time-changing gravitational potential at redshift z &lt; 
10, the integrated Sachs-Wolfe eect. 
3.	Adopt a simplied description of matter. Aside from baryons prior to recombina
tion, we will treat the matter as cold. This is appropriate for CDM and for other 
types of matter on scales larger than the Jeans length (an excellent approximation 
for CMB anisotropy). The complex gravitational interaction between photons, 
neutrinos, and dark matter prior to recombination will be treated in a simplied 
manner. However, we include correctly, without approximation, a possible nonzero 
cosmological constant (vacuum energy). 
4.	Neglect gravitational radiation. In the linearized treatment of small-amplitude uc
tuations, gravitational radiation is a distinct mode and so its eect on the CMB 
may be treated as a separate contribution computed independently of the density 
and entropy uctuations studied here. 
5.	Assume that all perturbations have small (linear) amplitude. This is valid for pri
mary anisotropies but not for secondary anisotropies caused by nonlinear struc
tures forming at low redshift. Secondary anisotropies are negligible on angular 
scales larger than about 10 arcminutes. 
The justication for these simplications is mainly pedagogical, although in general 
they do not introduce serious errors on angular scales larger than a few degrees of arc. 
(Gravitational radiation, if present, can contribute signicantly to the CMB anisotropy 
on large angular scales. Curvature also has a signicant eect on large scales.) Once the 
student understands CMB anisotropy in this simplied model, a more realistic treatment 
can be undertaken (Ma &amp; Bertschinger 1995; Seljak &amp; Zaldarriaga 1996; Zaldarriaga, 
Seljak, &amp; Bertschinger 1998; Hu et al 1998, and references therein). 
Aside from the simplications given above and some computational approximations 
stated later, the treatment given herein is rigorous and complete. We will discuss both 
the adiabatic (i.e. isentropic) and isocurvature (entropy) modes, the integrated 
Sachs-Wolfe eect, and both intrinsic and Doppler anisotropies. 
The computation of microwave background anisotropy has several ingredients. The 
rest of these notes give a systematic presentation of these ingredients. In Section 2 we 
present the Einstein equations for a perturbed Robertson-Walker spacetime. In Section 
3 we derive and formally integrate the radiative transfer equation for CMB anisotropy. 
Section 4 gives a physical interpretation of the primary contributions to CMB anisotropy. 
These contributions cannot be calculated until the evolution of metric, matter, and radia
tion perturbations is given, as they provide the source terms for CMB anisotropy. Section 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>It is easy to interpret the various terms in equations (25). The terms proportional 
to a/a are Hubble damping terms arising because we are using comoving coordinates. 
The   term appears in the continuity equation because, from the metric (1), the homo
geneous expansion factor a( ) is eectively modied by spatial curvature perturbations 
to become a(1  ). The pressure p is present with  in the energy ux (momentum 
density) because we let  be the energy density (not the rest-mass density), which is 
aected by the work done by pressure forces in compressing the gas. 
For convenience in what follows, we dene the perturbation in energy density relative 
to the enthalpy density  + p, 
 . (26)+   p 
Beware, this is a non-standard notation: most authors (including the present one in the 
papers listed in the bibliography) dene   /. For cold dark matter, with p = 0, 
there is no dierence. However, for photons or other relativistic particles,  is nonzero. p/ 
Our denition of  agrees with Weinberg (2002). It has a simple physical interpretation: 
 is the fractional perturbation in the number density or particles (rather than the energy 
density of particles). This choice simplies the equations and calculations that follow. 
The unperturbed matter and radiation uids are perfect uids, i.e. they have zero 
shear stress. For these uids, w = p/ depends only on . The speed of sound for a 
uid component is cs = (dp/d)1/2 . Linearizing equations (25) about the unperturbed 
solution and using equation (26), we now obtain (cf. Ma &amp; Bertschinger 1995) 
  = ( 2 u + 3 ) , 
a2 u + (1  3cs )u = c 2 +  . (27)s a 
We have used the assumption of potential ow, equation (21). 
Our goal now is to obtain equations of motion for the density and velocity potentials 
of our two uids, CDM and the photon-baryon plasma. The CDM case is simple with 
w = c2 = 0. The photon-baryon plasma is more complicated. First let us consider s 
the perturbations of photons and baryons separately. Because of the large photon-to-
baryon ratio (about 2  109), a negligible amount of heat is transferred to photons 
from baryons compared with the energy in the photons. Thus, photons with density 
1perturbation  obey the rst of equations (27) with w = 3 while baryons with density 
perturbation  b obey the same equation with w = 0 (since they are nonrelativistic). Now, 
the tight coupling due to Thomson scattering ensures that the photons and baryons 
have a common velocity potential, ub = u . Thus, if the photon-to-baryon ratio was 
unperturbed initially, it follows from the rst of equations (27) that b =  . With 
 +  equation of state w = p/= p /( b), we get 
dp /d 1 3 1 b 2 c = d(  )/d = 1 + yb , yb  . (28)s b +  3 4  
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>The summed ii components of the Einstein equations give a result that will be useful 
later: 
 2  K + a d aa2 1 2 ( + 2) + 2 +  +3  (  ) = 4Ga2p (23) a d a a 
where p = p  p is the perturbation in the pressure (isotropic stress). 
Finally, the trace-free part of the ij components of the Einstein equations give a 
relation between the two gravitational potentials: 
1 ij  3 ij  2 (  ) = 8Ga2ij, (24) 
where ij, is the longitudinal shear stress. Longitudinal shear stress arises from quadrupole 
anisotropy in the angular distribution of the particle momenta; for a weakly imperfect 
uid it is the stress arising from shear viscosity. A perfect uid has no shear stress. The 
major contribution to ij, comes from massless neutrinos; photons make a small con
tribution after recombination. When the universe becomes matter-dominated, ij   
and therefore   is small compared with . In the following we will neglect shear | |
stress, with resulting errors of order one percent in the CMB anisotropy. For a full 
treatment including shear stress, see Ma &amp; Bertschinger (1995). 
5.2 Fluid equations 
The Einstein equations (19)(23) require that we specify the density, velocity, and pres
sure perturbations of matter and radiation. We will approximate the contents of the 
universe before recombination by two decoupled perfect uids: cold dark matter and 
the photon-baryon plasma. Cold dark matter is a pressureless uid that interacts only 
by gravity. Photons are tightly coupled to electrons by Thomson scattering, which are 
themselves tightly coupled to protons and helium atoms and ions by Coulomb scatter
ing. We apply this description at temperatures below 1 MeV, after electron-positron 
annihilation and neutrino decoupling. Thus the neutrinos should be regarded as a third, 
decoupled gas. Their nite temperature and lack of collisions make the neutrinos an 
imperfect gas. We will discuss the neutrinos below. 
The uid equations follow from T  = 0 applied to a perfect uid with stress-
energy tensor T  = ( + p)V V  + pg where V  is the 4-velocity. We dene the 
three-velocity vi = V i/V 0 . Working to rst order in the metric perturbations and the 
uid 3-velocity, we nd 
a  + 3 a    ( + p) + i ( + p)v i = 0 , 
  a ( + p)v i + 4 ( + p)v i + ip + ( + p)i = 0 . (25) a 
14</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>High-z Galaxies and QSOs</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://de.arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/9902228</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Frontiers of Cosmology</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://de.arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0103391</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>26</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>QSO Absorption Lines 1</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://de.arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0005106</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Cosmography 2: SNe Ia</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://www.cfa.harvard.edu/supernova//HighZ.html</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Inflation 2</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://de.arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/0109439</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
