<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-996-cross-cultural-leadership-fall-2004/</course_url>
    <course_title>Cross-Cultural Leadership</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Leadership </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Business </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction and Overview (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-996-cross-cultural-leadership-fall-2004/resources/lec1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Cross Cultural Leadership  15.996 
Lecture Notes 
Class One  Introduction and Overview 
	Set the baseline. What understanding of le aders and leadership has ea ch of us already 
acquired? How does that refl ect our global experiences? 
	Identify teams 
	Team introductory presentation of the teams region:  geography, history, regional 
differences, politics, economic issues 
	Brief overview of the theories  and themes in this course 
Agenda 
	Welcome  agenda, purpose of class 
	Class Introductions  
name, class, work experience, what cultural background?
	Create teams 
	Introductory presentation by each team
Give teams 20 minutes to prepare 
Presentation is short (5 minutes):  30,000 foot 
What do you think might be distinctive about your region? 
Geography, history, politics, econom ic issues, regional differences 
	(if time permits)Brief overview of theories and themes 
	Explanation of Syllabus and Next Weeks Assignment 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2004 	 Page 1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Create Teams 
I do this real time.  When I ask them (earlier) to introduce themselves, I ask particularly that they 
state where in the world they have lived. Then at  this point in the cla ss I create teams based on a 
blend of supply and demand. 
First I determine the demand  I ask for a list of pl aces the class would like to  learn about, expecting 
they will remember the places mentioned during th e introductions.  I write down the places that they 
mention on the board.  Europe is clearly too broad and Ghana too narrow.  But for the most part 
I just write down what they say. 
Then we explore the supply. Of the countries/regi ons listed  how many st udents have lived/worked 
in each?  Im looking for a minimum of two students  for each country/region; individuals who have 
lived/worked in the area long enoug h that they can be spokespeople for the culture.  Ive tried teams 
anchored by people who are really interested or have friends who live there -- but that hasnt 
worked. Those teams just cannot pr ovide a thick, rich description or  answer the questions the other 
students have. I am open to experiment.  For ex ample  having one person from Saudi Arabia and 
one from Yemen (even though those are culturally dis tinct countries) makes a pe rfectly adequate base 
for a Middle East team. Especially  since most of the students in my class have very little personal 
knowledge of that area of the world. 
Then I step back and see what we have. Im looki ng for 5 to 8 teams.  Fewer teams means each team 
gets more time to speak.  More teams mean that mo re of the world is discu ssed and I have to do a lot 
of active time management.  I decide what regions we will use.  (For example: US, Germany, China, 
Japan, and Mexico). 
I then write the names of each team across the boar d  so that there is space underneath each team 
name.  I invite the students then to come up and choose teams.  I set minimum and maximum team 
sizes. For example, if there are 8 teams and 35 stude nts I say that a team must  have at least 3 and no 
more than 5 members. 
Once the teams are created, I give them the first a ssignment.  They are given 20 minutes to create 
overview presentations about their countries/regions.  I ask them to briefly describe the geography, 
history, politics, economic issues, and regional differences of their ta rget area.  Usually a 5 minute 
presentation with 5-10 minutes Q&amp;A is fine.  At this point Im looking at the clock  I try to have 
every team present their overview in this class.  Some teams use PowerPoint.  Others use flip charts 
that I have available to them. 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2004 Page 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Overview and Purpose of Class 
	Explain Agenda 
	Purpose  to examine what constitutes  effective leadership across cultures. 
o	My definition of leadership  use this as your default definition until you find 
something you feel is more compelling 
o	Leadership  the ability to influence a group of people to achieve a shared goal 
	Assumption of class: If someones behaviors and skills enable them to be an effective 
leader in a particular setting/culture  th at those same behaviors and skills will not
necessarily enable that pers on to be effective elsewhere 
o	That is  what is experienced as effective leadership is continge nt on the context.  
What industry, what phase the company is in (start-up, growth, blue chip, etc), 
corporate culture, economic context, re gional (ethnic, cultural) context. 
o	We will focus on regional context 
	Pragmatic Goal  to prepare you for business assignments outside of your native country/ 
culture. (At least you will know some of the parameters to watch out for) 
 Roadmap    
o	You will form teams.  Each team will focus on a particular region/culture. 
o	Each week 
	the class is structured around an aspect of  what its like to work in a culture 
that various theorists have identified as  differentiated.  Something that is not 
the same across cultures.  Notions of time.  Notions of power. 
	We will discuss what was in the readings.   
	Each team will present st ories/anecdotes that help  to illustrate how your 
culture/region responds to the aspect of  the week.  Sometimes as a stand-up 
presentation, others as round-robin informal presentations 
	Usually one pair of teams will prepare a Cross-cultural dialogue.  Each team will present how its region handles a sp ecific situation.  For example: hiring. 
Other teams are expected to  provide content as well.  All comment/discuss.   
	If somethings not working, let me know and we will change it. 
	Caveat about stereotypes. These are anecdotes . May not be indicative of the norm of the 
culture. 
o	Do not take offense. 
o	Offer alternate concepts.  Offer alternate interpretations   
o	This is toolkit and framework  sonar to  help you improve your own international 
navigation  but what we do here (based on anecdotes a nd personal viewpoints)  may 
not be what you encounter. 
	Course Evaluation  
o	Graded Pass/Fail 
o	Class participation and attendance 
o	Team presentations/notes  
o	End of course paper (may be done by self or by small group (no more than 3).  Must 
compare/contrast some aspect of leadership  (influencing people in a business context) 
from at least 2 cultures/regions.  5  10 pages.  Due last day of class. 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2004 	 Page 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Orientation to Time and Space (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-996-cross-cultural-leadership-fall-2004/resources/lec4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Cross Cultural Leadership  15.996 
Lecture Notes 
Class Four  Orientation to Time and Space 
	Focus on past, present or future 
o	Short- or long-term horizon 
	Monochronic or polychronic activities 
o	Rigid or fluid schedules 
	Space: public, private or mixed 
	Cross-cultural dialogue 
Read: 
	Trompenaars, Fons and Hampden-Turner, Charles.  Riding the Waves of Culture: 
Understanding Cultural Diversity in Global Business  (2nd edition).  New York: 
McGraw-Hill, 1998, pages 123128, 132-144. 
	Gesteland, Richard R. Cross-Cultu ral Business Behavior: Marketing, 
Negotiating and Managing across Cultures  (2nd edition).  Copenhagen: 
Copenhagen Business School Press, 2000, pages 55-62. 
Agenda 
	Welcome.  Reminder on Course Paper Assignment 
	Time 
o	Past vs. Present vs. Future 
o	Monochronic or Polychronic 
	Space 
	Cross-Cultural Dialogue 
	Next Weeks Assignment 
Process: 
Same as last week.  Dimensions posted on boa rd.  Teams explain where their regions fit 
along the dimension and tell stories. 
Content: 
Time 
Past vs. present vs. Future   Know what matters! 
Ascription vs. current achievement vs. potential  
History as determinant (bloodlines) 
Current abilities as determinant (current race) 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2004 	 Page 1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Potential as determinant (aspirations, training plans) 
Monochronic  Polychronic  Richard Gesteland 
Number of concurrent tasks: Single task to multi-task 
Flexibility of schedule  time allo cation AND sequencing: rigid to fluid 
Degree of punctuality: absolute to absent 
Space 
Size of personal bubble  Edward Hall 
 What is too close in what situations? 
 Close family
 Close friends 
 Business partners 
 Social acquaintances 
 Business acquaintances 
Strangers 
What is private? 
	If I work with you, how much access do you expect to have to my office space, my personal life and home?  re: Specific vs. Diffuse  -- (level of involvement)  
access is to a specific portion of someones life  or diffuse  access to one private area is access to all private areas.  Plus wide ra nge of delineation of what 
is public (shared readily) and what is pr ivate (your refrigerator or your car?).  
Separation of business and private vs. merging of biz and private. 
	How do you create a private space? (physic al barriers, visual delineations, aural 
cues, eye contact, etc) 
Cross Cultural Dialogue 
Each lead team does a presentation.  Five minut es plus Q&amp;A is fine.  I look for themes 
and variations. Then I lead a discussion  l ooking for similarities across cultures as well 
as differences. And always  stories, stories, stories. 
If there is not enough time for discussion, I will hold that over for the next week. 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2004 	 Page 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Leadership Effectiveness (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-996-cross-cultural-leadership-fall-2004/resources/lec5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>UK  The Diplomat 
 Germany  The Master , expert in field 
 Japan  Senior Statesman 
 China  Warlord, has local power 
Traits of Chinese Leader 
Graham and Lam (Chinese Negotiation): 
 Guanxi (Personal connections a nd individual social capital) 
 Zhongjian Ren (The intermediary) 
 Shehui Dengji (Social status and deference to superiors) 
 Renji Hexie (Interpersonal harmony) 
 Zhengti Guannian (H olistic thinking ) 
 Jiejian (Thrift) 
 Mianzi (Face) 
 Chiku Nailao (Endurance) 
Leadership Presentations 
In this section each team give s a presentation.  They imagine the audience is a group of 
ex-pats just arrived to the teams region/coun try.  The presentation is  advice to these ex
pats on how to be recognized as a strong, effective leader in that country/region.  As ever, 
a short presentation with room for Q&amp;A works best. 
Summary of Paper Topics 
If there is time, I ask each student (or group) to describe their paper topics and share with the class the key learning of the paper. 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2004 Page 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Inspire a Shared Vision  vision of what could be, total belief in making that 
vision a reality, AND can inspire commitment to  that vision in others.  Forging a 
unity of purpose. In credibly enthusiastic 
	Challenge the Process  take risk.  Pione er.  Willing to step into the unknown and 
change the status quo. Dont have to invent  do have to  adopt early.  Help others 
feel safe in risk-taking. Problems shap e leaders  who learn from failure (and 
successes). 
	Enable others to Act  trust, empowerme nt, teamwork.  Give people the chance of 
autonomy, discretion, authority.  Provide both the resources and the safety net. 
	Encourage the Heart  help others feel strong and capable.  Show appreciation.  
Create celebration.  Recognition. (from the heart).  Lship IS about strong and 
sustainable relationships. 
K&amp;P list (top four) 
	Honest 
	Forward Looking 
	Competent 
	Inspiring 
Goleman 
	Threshold capabilities (int elligence, appropriate skills,  cognitive skills  big-
picture thinking, long-term vision) 
	Emotional Intelligence (twice as im portant for outstanding performance) 
o	Self-awareness 
o	Self-regulation  reasonable people cr eate an environment of trust and 
fairness.  Roll with the changes. 
o	Motivation  achieve for the sake of achievement 
o	Empathy 
o	Social Skill  knack for building rapport 
Welch (4 Es) 
	Integrity 
	Intelligence (breadth of knowledge  plus emotional intelligence) 
	Energy 
	Energize 
	Edge (courage to make tough decisions) 
	Execute 
	Passion 
Leadership metaphors 
Derr, Rousillon and Bournois: 
	USA  The Free Agent, superstar 
	Latin America  The General, strong man in charge 
	France  The Genius, intellectual elite 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2004 	 Page 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Cross Cultural Leadership  15.996 
Lecture Notes 
Class Five  Leadership Effectiveness 
	Leadership Traits 
	Leadership Styles 
	Presentations on Leadership Effectiveness 
	Presentation of student papers 
	Critique of course 
Read: 
	Kouzes, James and Posner, Barry. The Leadership Challenge.  San Francisco: 
Jossey-Bass, 2002 (3rd edition), pages 13  22, 24-25. 
	Goleman, Daniel. Leadership that Ge ts Results.  Harvard Business Review , 
March-April 2000, pages 78-90. 
	Derr, C. Brooklyn; Roussillon, Sylvie  and Bournois, Frank.  Cross-Cultural 
Approaches to Leadership Development.  Westport, Connecticut: Quorum Books, 
2002, pages 290-292. 
	Graham, John l. and Lam, N. Mark. The Chinese Negotiation. Harvard 
Business Review , October 2003, pages 82-91. 
Agenda 
	Welcome.   
	This weeks theories 
	Leadership Presentations 
	Summary of Paper Topics  
	Closing Comments 
	Feedback on Course 
This weeks theories 
Here I just briefly walk through the leader ship skills and behaviors mentioned in the 
readings. I use this to set the stage for the presentations. 
Kouzes &amp; Posner 
	Model the Way  behavior that wins you re spect, lead from own values, examples 
are often on the simple things  spending time with people, working side by side, 
telling stories, being visi ble during crisis/uncertainty 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2004 	 Page 1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Cultural Styles (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-996-cross-cultural-leadership-fall-2004/resources/lec2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>o	masculinity/femininity 
o	later discussed a 5th  dimension = long term view (Asia) 
Late 1980s Fons Trompenaars a nd Charles Hampden-Turner  
Consultants 
By 1998: 15 years of research  questionnaire based. Framework from Talcott Parsons, US 
Sociologist (Harvard 1927-1973) 
	30 companies, 50 countries, 30,000 people 
	7 fundamental dimensions of culture: 
relationships with people 
universalism vs. particularism 
individualism vs. commun itarianism (collectivism ) 
neutral vs. emotional 
specific vs. diffuse 
achievement vs. ascription 
understanding of time 
attitudes toward environment 
Late 1990s Robert J House et al  Project GLOBE Professor at Wharton since 1988. 
	 by 2004: 10 years of research, 150 resear chers, 18,000 managers in 62 countries.  
Questionnaire. A few industries. 
	9 cultural dimensions 
o	assertiveness 
o	future orientation 
o	gender differentiation 
o	uncertainty avoidance 
o	power distance 
o	collectivism vs. individualism 
o	in-group collectivism 
o	performance orientation 
o	humane orientation 
	Plus looking for leadership traits that are consistent across cultures - charisma 
Todays topics: 
Fons Trompenaars and Charles Hampden-Turner  
	4 of their 7 fundamental dimensions of culture: 
relationships with people 
universalism vs. particularism 
individualism vs. commun itarianism (collectivism ) 
neutral vs. emotional 
specific vs. diffuse 
achievement vs. ascription 
Process: 
I use flip-chart sheets.  I post four sheets,  one fo r each dimension.  I draw a line at the top of each 
page indicating a continuum for a dimension, for exam ple from universalism to particularism.  I then 
label the ends of each line. 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2004 	 Page 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Cross Cultural Leadership  15.996 
Lecture Notes 
Class Two  Cultural Styles 
	Universalism vs. Particularism 
	Individualism vs. Collectivism 
	Neutral vs. Emotional 
	Achievement vs. Ascription 
	Dialogue: making a joint hiring de cision including compensation 
Read: 
	Trompenaars, Fons and Hampden-Turner, Charles.  Riding the Waves of Culture: 
Understanding Cultural Diversity in Global Business  (2nd edition).  New York: McGraw-Hill, 
1998, pages: 1-10, 29-36, 49-53, 68-75, 80-81, 105-111, 121-122. 
Agenda 
	Welcome.  Explanation of E nd of Course Paper Assignment 
	Theories and Themes 
	Universalism vs. Particularism 
	Individualism vs. Collec tivism (Communtarianism ) 
	Neutral vs. Emotional 
	Achievement vs. Ascription 
	Cross-Cultural Dialogue 
	Next Weeks Assignment 
Theories and Themes 
A brief overview of the theorists whose id eas are the framework for this course. 
Late 1950s  Edward Hall 
	Anthropologist.  World War II -- U.S. Army in Europe and the Philippines. Later, Director 
of the Foreign Service Institute traini ng program. He observed first hand the many 
difficulties created by failures of intercultural communication.   
	Proxemics  human use of space within the context of culture 
	Personal space and community (town) space 
	Also looked at monochromic and polychromic time 
Late 1960s  Geert Hofstede 
Founded and managed personnel resear ch dept of IBM Europe.   
	Surveyed 116,000 IBM employees in 40 count ries on preferences around management 
style and work environment 
	4 dimensions where differences  by country were significant 
o	power distance 
o	uncertainty avoidance 
o	individualism/collectivism 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2004 	 Page 1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>As part of the discussion I expect each team to  tell me where their country/region falls on each 
continuum.  I also expect each team to tell me a st ory that illustrates why that point of the continuum 
is appropriate.  For example the US team may point to the how cont racts are used and how pervasive 
they are as illustration of the unive rsalist nature of the US culture. 
I look to hear from each team for each dimension.  The more stories the better.  The more the 
students are querying eac h other, the better. 
Before we start, I reiterate some caveats: 
	There will be anecdotes and stereotypes.  S how each other respect.  Try not to offend each 
other. 
	This is about NOT making assumptions!!!   
	These continua are frameworks.  Lenses th rough which you can assess a situation AND 
yourself. Do not expect your own experiences to map perfectly to the anecdotes you hear. 
	This course looks to build your awareness that  the same action/activity/situation may very 
well have different meanings.  (Is stating your earned degree appropriate or rude?) 
Content: 
Universalism vs. Particularism   -- universal standards and rules vs. particular people  and particular 
situations. Contract s vs. relationships. 
Individualism vs. Collec tivism/Communitarianism   the wants and needs of the individual vs. the 
interests of the group. Your group can be local or more general.  Community = classmates, left
handers, US.  I vs. we. Pervasive teamwork of hi  tech consulting is at o dds with watching out for 
#1 tradition in US. 
Neutral vs. Emotional   show little emotion vs. show emotions readily in many different situations.  
Controlled vs. animated.  Humor gets very tricky here 
Achievement vs. Ascription   what you have done vs. who you are. The importance of the right 
school in France (Ascription) vs . the importance of what you did yesterday (US - achievement). 
Cross Cultural Dialogue 
Each lead team does a presentation.  Five minutes  plus Q&amp;A is fine.  I look for themes and 
variations. Then I lead a discussi on  looking for similarities across cultu res as well as differences.    
And always  stories, stories, stories. 
If there is not enough time for discussion, I will hold that over for the next week. 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2004 	 Page 3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Social Dimensions (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-996-cross-cultural-leadership-fall-2004/resources/lec3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Cross Cultural Leadership  15.996 
Lecture Notes 
 
Class Three  Social Dimensions  
 
 Assertiveness 
 Gender Differentiation 
 Uncertain ty Avoidance 
 Power Distance 
 Cross-cultural dialogue 
 
Read: 
 Javidan, Mansour and House, Robert J.  Cultu ral Acumen for the Global Manager: L essons 
from Project GLOBE.  Organizational Dynamics , Vol. 29, No. 4, pages 289-304, Spring 
2001.   
 House, Robert J.; Hanges, Paul J.; Javidan, Mansour; Dorfm an, Peter W. and Gupta, Vipin.  
Culture, Leadership, and Organizations : The GLOBE Study of 62 Societies.   Thousand Oaks, 
Californ ia, 2004, pages: 410, 411;  365, 366;   622, 623; 539, 540;  250, 251; 573, 574. 
 Schneider, Susan and Barsoux, Jean-Louis.  Managing Across Cultures  (2nd edition) .  Essex, 
England: Pearson Education Limited, 2003, pages 87-95. 
 
Agenda 
 
 Welcom e.   
 Context for this weeks theory 
 Assertiv eness 
 Gender Differentiation 
 Uncerta inty Avoidance 
 Power Distance 
 Cross-Cultural Dialogue 
 Next W eeks Assignm ent 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2 004        Page 1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3. Motivated by stability and security 
4. Leaders  plan, organize, coordinate, control 
 
(GLOBE) society seeks orderlin ess, consistency, structure 
 
NOTE  Be explicit about difference between discomfort  in unstruc tured situa tions (are there traffic 
rules for cro ssing the str eet) and risk avoidance 
 
Power distance , the ex tent to which the less powe rful members of  organiz ations and in stitutions (like 
the fam ily) accept and ex pect th at po wer is dis tributed unequ ally.  
 (Schneider and Barsoux) High power distance 
1. More hierarchy 
2. More supe rvision (n arrow span of control) 
3. More cen tralized d ecision-making 
4. Motivated by status and power 
5. Leaders rev ered or ob eyed as autho rities 
 
(GLOBE)  expectation that power is shared Unequally. 
 
 
 
Correlation across tw o dimensions : 
 
Hofstede found that there was a correlation betw een power distance and uncer tainty avoidance that 
provided insight into the kinds of organization that tend to be successf ul in those environm ents.
 
 
      Cross Cultural Dialogue 
 
Each lead team does a presentation.  Five minutes  plus Q&amp;A is fine.  I look for themes and 
variations.  Then I lead a discussi on  looking for similarities across cultu res as well as differences.    
And always  stories, stories, stories. 
 
If there is not enough time for discussion, I will hold that over for the next week. 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2 004        Page 3      See chart, p. 93 in: 
 
Schneider, Susan, and Jean-Louis Barsoux. Managing Across Cultures. 2nd ed. 
Essex, England: Pearson Education Limited, 2003, pp. 87-95.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Context for  this w eeks  theory 
 
Reminder -- Late 1960s  Geert Hofstede 
Founded and m anaged personnel resear ch dept of IBM Europe.   
Surveyed 116,000 IBM employees in 40 countries  on preferences around m anage ment style and 
work environm ent 
 4 dim ensions where differences  by country were significant 
o power distance 
o uncertainty avoidance 
o individualism /collectivism  
o masculinity/f emininity 
o 5th = long term  view (As ia) 
 
GLOBE takes m asculine/fem inine and creates 2 catego ries 
o assertiven ess 
o gender differentiation 
 
Additional studies did not always  get the sam e resu lts.  Dim ensions still useful  even though results 
variable.  (World is dif ferent  not just IBM being studied) 
 
Process: 
 
Same as last week.  Di mensions posted on board.  Team s explain where their regions fit along the 
dimension and tell stories. 
 
Content: 
Assertiv eness and Gender Dif ferentia tion 
 (Schneider &amp; Barsoux) High m asculine 
1. Task not relationships 
2. Motivation by m oney and thi ngs, not quality of life 
3. Leadersh ip  ensure bottom  line profits and set targets 
4. Fem inine leader would safe-guard  employee well-being and dem onstrate 
concern for social responsibility 
 (GLOBE)  Gender Differentiation = society m aximizes gender role differentiation.  Who gets status 
and decision-m aking power 
(GLOBE) Assertive = society en courages people to be tough, c onfrontational, assertive and 
competitive (not m odest and tender).  Can-do vs. cooperation and harm ony. 
 
Uncertainty avoidance  deals with a society' s tolerance for uncertainty and am biguity. 
 (Schneider &amp; Barsoux) Hi gh uncertainty avoidance 
1. More form alization, m ore written rules and regs 
2. Risk avoidance 
Cross-Cultural Lship Fall 2 004        Page 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
