<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-735-double-affine-hecke-algebras-in-representation-theory-combinatorics-geometry-and-mathematical-physics-fall-2009/</course_url>
    <course_title>Double Affine Hecke Algebras in Representation Theory, Combinatorics, Geometry, and Mathematical Physics</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Mathematics </list>
      <list>Algebra and Number Theory </list>
      <list>Topology and Geometry </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Parabolic induction and restriction functors for rational Cherednik algebras</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-735-double-affine-hecke-algebras-in-representation-theory-combinatorics-geometry-and-mathematical-physics-fall-2009/resources/mit18_735f09_ch05/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Remark 5.18. If G is the trivial group, the functor Res is just the KZ functor from [GGOR], 
which we will discuss later. Thus, Res is a relativ e version of the KZ functor. 
Remark 5.19. Note that the object Res(M ) is naturally equiv arian t under the group 
NG(G)/G. 
Thus, we see that the functor Resb does not depend on b, up to an isomorphism. A similar 
statemen t is true for the functors Indb, res, ind. 
Conjecture 5.20. For any b  h,  h such that Gb = G, we have isomorphi sms of 
functors Resb = ind. = res, Indb 
Remark 5.21. Conjecture 5.20 would imply that Indb is left adjoint to Resb, and that Resb 
maps injectiv e objects to injectiv e ones, while Indb maps projectiv e objects to projectiv e 
ones. 
Remark 5.22. If b and  are generic (i.e., Gb = G = 1) then the conjecture holds. Indeed, 
in this case the conjectu re reduces to showing that we have an isomorphism of functors 
Fiberb(M) Fiber(M) (M Oc Since both functors are exact functors to the = (G, h)). 
category of vector spaces, it suces to check that dim Fiberb(M) = dimFiber(M). But this 
is true because both dimensions are given by the leading coecien t of the Hilbert polynomial 
of M (characterizin g the growth of M). 
It is importan t to mention, however, that although Resb is isomorphi c to Resb if Gb = Gb , 
this isomorphism is not canonical. So let us examine the dependence of Resb on b a little 
more carefully . 
Theorem 5.16 implies that if c is generic, then 
Res(Mc(G, h,)) = Mc(G, h/hG ,) L, 
where L is a local system on hG of rank n. Let us characterize the local system L reg 
explicitly . 
Prop osition 5.23. The local system L is given by the conne ction on the trivial bund le 
given by the formula 
 2cs ds  =d  (1  s). 
sS:s/G 1  s s 
with values in HomG (, |G ). 
Proof. This follows immediately from formula (5.1).  
Denition 5.24. We will call the connection of Proposition 5.23 the parab olic KZ (Knizhnik-
Zamolo dchikov) connecti on. 
Example 5.25. Let G = Sn and G = Sn1  Snk with n1 +  + nk = n. In this case, 
there is only one parameter c. 
Let h = Cn be the permutation represen tation of G. Then 
hG =(Cn)G = {v  hv =(z1,...,z1,z2,...,z2,...,zk,...,zk)}. |  
n1 n2 nk 
42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Prop ositions 5.26 and 5.27 allow us to attac h to every irreducible module M Oc(G, h), 
a conjugacy class of parab olic subgroups, CM  Par(G), namely , the conjugacy class of the 
stabilizer of a generic point of the supp ort of M. Also, for a parab olic subgroup G  G, 
denote by X (G) the set of points b  h whose stabilizer contains a subgroup conjugate to 
G. 
The following proposition is immediate. 
Prop osition 5.28. (i) Let M Oc(G, h)0 be irreducible. If b is such that Gb  CM , 
then Resb(M) is a nonzer o nite dimensional module over H1,c(Gb, h/hGb ). 
(ii) Conversely, let b  h, and L be a nite dimensional module H1,c(Gb, h/hGb ). Then 
the support of Indb(L) in h is X (Gb). 
Let FD(G, h) be the set of c for which H1,c(G, h) admits a nite dimensional represen tation. 
Corollary 5.29. Let G be a parabolic subgroup of G. Then X (G) is the support of some 
irreducible representation from Oc(G, h)0 if and only if c  FD(G, h/hG ). 
Proof. Immediate from Prop osition 5.28.  
Example 5.30. Let G = Sn, h = Cn1 . In this case, the set Par(G) is the set of partitions 
of n. Assume that c = r/m,(r, m) = 1, 2  m  n. By a result of [BEG], nite dimensional 
represen tations of Hc(G, h) exist if and only if m = n. Thus the only possible classes CM 
for irreducible modules M have stabilizers Sm  Sm, i.e., corresp ond to partitions into 
parts, where each part is equal to m or 1. So there are [n/m] + 1 possible supports for 
modules, where [a] denotes the integer part of a. 
5.12. Notes. Our discussion of the geometric approac h to rational Cherednik algebras in 
Section 5.1 follows [E1] and Section 2.2 of [BE]. Our exposition in the other sections follows 
the corresp onding parts of the paper [BE]. 
44</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.735 Double Affine Hecke Algebras in Representation Theory, Combinatorics, Geometry, 
and Mathematical Physics 
Fall 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>generalized eigenspace is nite dimensional. Now for each   C denote by Nj, the general
ized -eigenspace of h in N/mjN. We have surjectiv e homomorphisms Nj+1,  Nj,, and 
for large enough j they are isomorphisms. This implies that the map E(N) N/mj N is 
surjectiv e for every j, as desired.  
 
Example. Supp ose that c = 0. Then Theorem 5.1 specializes to the well known fact that 
the category of G-equiv arian t local systems on h with a locally nilpotent action of partial 
dieren tiations is equiv alent to the category of all G-equiv arian t local systems on the formal 
neigh borhood of zero in h. In fact, both categories in this case are equiv alent to the category 
of nite dimensio nal represen tations of G. 
We can now dene the comp osition functor J 
J (M)= E(M). The functor J is called the Jacquet functor ([Gi2]). : Oc(G, h) Oc(G, h)0, by the formula 
5.3. The dualit y functor. Recall that in Section 3.11, for any H1,c(G, h)-mo dule M, the 
full dual space M is naturally an H1,c(G, h)-module, via M  (a)= M ((a)). 
It is clear that the dualit y functor  denes an equivalence between the category Oc
(G, h)op, and that M = E(M) (where M is the contragredien t, or restricted dual O(G, h)0 
and
c
module to M dened in Secti on 3.11). 
5.4. Generalized Jacquet functors. 
Prop osition 5.2. For any M 
h-nilp otent. Oc(G, h), a vector v  M is h-nite if and only if it is
Proof. The if part follows from Theorem 3.20. To prove the only if part, assume that 
(h  )N v = 0. Then for any u  Srh v, we have (h   + r)N u = 0. But by Theorem 5.1,  
the real parts of generalized eigen values of h in M are bounde d below. Hence Srh v = 0 for  
large enough r, as desired.  
According to Prop osition 5.2, the functor E can be alternativ ely dened by setting E(M) 
to be the subspace of M which is locally nilpotent under the action of h. 
This gives rise to the following generalization of E: for any   h 
(G, h) Oc(G, h) by settin g E(M) to be the space of generalized eigen vectors of 
C[h]G in M with eigen value . Ocwe dene the functor
E :
This way, we have E0 = E. 
We can also dene the generalized Jacquet functor J 
formula J(M)= E(M). Then we have J0 
J to Oc(G, h) is the identity functor. : Oc(G, h) Oc(G, h) by the 
= J , and one can show that the restriction of
5.5. The centralizer construction. For a nite group H, let eH = H1|
|
g be the
gH 
symmetrizer of H.
If G  H are nite groups, and A is an algebra containing C[H], then dene the algebra 
Z(G, H, A) to be the centralizer EndA(P ) of A in the right A-mo dule P =FunH (G, A) of 
H-invarian t A-valued functions on G, i.e. such functions f : GA that f(hg)= hf(g). 
Clearly , P is a free A-mo dule of rank |G/H|, so the algebra Z(G, H, A) is isomorphic to 
Mat|G/H|(A), but this isomorphism is not canonical. 
The following lemma is trivial. 
Lemma 5.3. The functor N  I(N) := P A N =FunH (G, N) denes an equivalenc e of 
categories A  mod Z(G, H, A)  mod.  
37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Thus, the parab olic KZ connection on the trivial bundle with ber being a represen tation  
of Sn has the form 
 n1++np n1++nq  
d  c dzp  dzq (1  sij ). 
1p&lt;qki=n1++np1+1 j=n1++nq1+1 zp  zq  
So the dieren tial equatio ns for a at section F (z) of this bundle have the form 
F  n1++np n1++nq (1  sij )F = c . zpq=pi=n1++np1+1 j=n1++nq1+1 zp  zq 
So F (z)= G(z) (zp  zq)cnpnq , where the function G satises the dieren tial equation p&lt;q
G  n1++np n1++nq sij G . zp = c 
q=pi=n1++np1+1 j=n1++nq1+1 zp  zq 
Let  = V n where V is a nite dimensional space with dim V = N (this class of repre
sentations contains as summands all irreducible represen tations of Sn). Let Vp = V np , so 
that  = V1  Vk. Then the equation for G can be written as 
G  pqG 
zp = czp  zq ,p =1, . . . , k, 
q=p 
Nwhere  = Es,t  Et,s is the Casimir elemen t for glN (Ei,j is the N by N matrix with s,t=1 
the only 1 at the (i, j)-th place, and the rest of the entries being 0). 
This is nothing but the well known Knizhnik-Zamolo dchikov system of equations of the 
WZW conformal eld theory , for the Lie algebra glN , see [EFK]. (Note that the repre
sentations Vi are the most general in the sense that any irreducible nite dimensional 
represen tation of glN occurs in V r for some r, up to tensoring with a character.) 
This motiv ates the term parab olic KZ connection. 
5.11. Supp orts of modules. The following two basic propositions are proved in [Gi1], 
Section 6. We will give dierent proofs of them, based on the restriction functors. 
Prop osition 5.26. Consider the stratic ation of h with respect to stabilizers of points in G. 
Then the (set-the oretical) support SuppM of any object M of Oc(G, h) in h is a union of 
strata of this stratic ation. 
Proof. This follows immediately from the existence of the at connection along the set of 
points b with a xed stabilizer G on the bundle Resb(M).  
Prop osition 5.27. For any irreducible object M in Oc(G, h), SuppM/G is an irreducible 
algebr aic variety. 
Proof. Let X be a comp onent of SuppM/G. Let M be the subspace of elemen ts of M 
whose restriction to a neigh borhood of a generic point of X is zero. It is obvious that M is 
an H1,c(G, h)-submo dule in M. By denition, it is a proper submo dule. Therefore, by the 
irreducibilit y of M, we have M = 0. Now let f  C[h]G be a function that vanishes on X. 
Then there exists a positiv e integer N such that fN maps M to M, hence acts by zero on 
M. This implies that SuppM/G = X, as desired.  
43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>5.6. Completion of rational Cherednik algebras at arbitrary points of h/G. The 
following result is, in essence, a consequence of the geometric approach to rational Cherednik 
algebras, describ ed in Subsection 5.1. It should be regarded as a direct generalization to the 
case of Cherednik algebras of Theorem 8.6 of [L] for ane Hecke algebras. 
Let b  h. Abusing notation, denote the restriction of c to the set Sb of reections in Gb 
also by c. 
Theorem 5.4. One has a natur al isomorphism 
H1,c H H 1 1 ,c ,c  :
 (G, h)b  Z(G, Gb, (Gb, h)0), 
dene d by the following formulas. Supp ose that f  P =FunGb (G, (Gb, h)0). Then 
((u)f)(w)= f(wu),u  G; 
for any   h, 
(b)((x)f)(w)=(xw +(w, b))f(w), 
wher e x  h  H1,c(G, h), x (b)  h  H1,c(Gb, h) are the elements corresponding to ; and 
for any a  h, 
2cs s(wa)(b)(5.1) ((ya)f)(w)= ywaf(w)  (f(w)  f(sw)).
sS:s/Gb 1  s x(b
s ) + s(b) 
wher e ya  h  H1,c(G, h), ya (b)  h  H1,c(Gb, h). 
Proof. Theproofisbyadirect computation. Wenote that inthelastformula,thefraction 
s(wa)/(x(b
s ) + s(b)) is viewed as a power series (i.e., an elemen t of C[[h]]), and that only 
the entire sum, and not each summand separately , is in the centralizer algebra.  
Remark. Let us explain how to see the existence of  without writing explicit formulas, 
and how to guess the formula (5.1) for . It is explained in [E1] (see e.g. [E1], Section 
2.9) that the sheaf of algebras obtained by sheacation of H1,c(G, h) over h/G is generated 
(on every ane open set in h/G) by regular functions on h, elements of G, and Dunkl 
operators. Therefore, this statemen t holds for formal neigh borhoods, i.e., it is true on the 
formal neigh borhood of the image in h/G of any point b  h. However, looking at the formula 
for Dunkl operators near b, we see that the summands corresp onding to s S,s /Gb are 
actually regular at b, so they can be safely deleted without changing the generated algebra 
(as all regular functions on the formal neigh borhood of b are included into the system of 
generators). But after these terms are deleted, what remains is nothing but the Dunkl 
operators for (Gb, h), which, together with funct ions on the formal neigh borhood of b and 
the group Gb, generate the compl etion of H1,c(Gb, h). This gives a construction of  without 
using explicit formulas. 
Also, this argum ent explain s why  should be dened by formula (5.1) of Theorem 5.4. 
Indeed, what this formula does is just restores the terms with s/Gb that have been 
previously deleted. 
The map  denes an equiv alence of categories 
H1,c H1,c 
 : (G, h)b  mod Z(G, Gb, (Gb, h)0)  mod. 
38</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>5.9. Some evaluations of the parabolic induction and restriction functors. For 
generic c, the category Oc(G, h) is semisimple, and natur ally equiv alent to the category 
RepG of nite dimensional represen tations of G, via the funct or   Mc(G, h,). (If G is 
a Coxeter group , the exact set of such c (whic h are called regular) is known from [GGOR] 
and [Gy]). 
Prop osition 5.16. (i) Supp ose that c is generic. Upon the above identic ation, the 
functors Indb, ind and Resb, res go to the usual induction and restriction functors 
between categories RepG and RepG. In other words, we have 
Resb(Mc(G, h,)) = cnMc(G, h/hG ,),G 
and 
Indb(Mc(G, h/hG ,)) = GbnMc(G, h,), 
wher e n is the multiplicity of occurrence of  in |G , and similarly for res, ind. 
(ii) The equations of (i) hold at the level of Grothendie ck groups for all c. 
Proof. Part (i) is easy for c = 0, and is obtained for generic c by a deformation argumen t. 
Part (ii) is also obtained by deformatio n argumen t, taking into accoun t that the functors 
Resb and Indb are exact and at with respect to c.  
Example 5.17. Supp ose that G = 1. Then Resb(M) is the ber of M at b, while Indb(C)= 
PKZ , the object dened in [GGOR], which is projectiv e and injectiv e (see Remark 5.22). This 
shows that Prop osition 5.16 (i) does not hold for special c, as PKZ is not, in general, a direct 
sum of standard modules. 
5.10. Dependence of the functor Resb on b. Let G  G be a parab olic subgroup. In 
the construction of the functor Resb, the point b can be made a variable which belongs to 
the open set hG .reg
Ghreg 
h/G be the natural map (note that this map is an etale covering of the image with be the formal neigh borhood of the locally closed set hG 
reg Namely , let
 in h, and let
reg  Gh :
H1,c
be the pullbac k of the sheaf H1,c,G, h under . We can regard it as a sheaf of algebras over 
hG . Similarly to Theorem 5.4 we have an isomor phism regthe Galois group NG(G)/G, where NG(G) is the normalizer of G in G). Let (G, h)hG
reg 
H1,c H1,c
where D(hG ) is the sheaf of dieren tial operators on hG , and is an appropriate comp letion reg reg
of the tensor product. 
Thus, repeating the construction of Resb, we can dene the functor 
Res : Oc(G, h)0 Oc(G, h/hG )0  Loc(hG ),reg
where Loc(hG ) stands for the category of local systems (i.e. O-coheren t D-modules) on hG .reg reg
This functor has the property that Resb is the ber of Res at b. Namely , the functor Res is 
dened by the formula (G, h/hG )0)regD(hGZ(G, G,  :
 (G, h)hG
reg ),
 
Res(M )=(EI1 )(MhG
reg ),


is the restriction of the sheaf M on h to the formal neigh borhood of hG 
reg where
MhG
reg .
41</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5.8. Parabolic induction and restriction functors for rational Cherednik algebras. 
Theorem 5.4 allows us to dene analogs of parab olic restriction functors for rational Chered
nik algebras. 
Namely , let b  h, and Gb = G. Dene a functor Resb : Oc(G, h)0 Oc(G, h/hG )0 by 
the formula 
Resb(M)=(E )(I1 Mb).   
We can also dene the parab olic induction functors in the opposite direction. Namely , let 
N Oc(G, h/hG )0. Then we can dene the object Indb(N) Oc(G, h)0 by the formula 
Indb(N)=(Eb 1 I)(1(N)0).    
Prop osition 5.11. (i) The functors Indb, Resb are exact. 
(ii) One has Indb(Resb(M)) = Eb(Mb). 
Proof. Part (i) follows from the fact that the functor Eb and the completion functor  b are 
exact (see Prop osition 5.10). Part (ii) is straigh tforw ard from the denition.  
Theorem 5.12. The functor Indb is right adjoint to Resb. 
Proof. We have 
Hom(Res b(M),N) = Hom((E )( I1 )( I1 Mb),N) = Hom((E Mb),1(N))   
= Hom((I1 )(1(N)0Mb, (1 I)(1(N)0)) Mb), ) = Hom(    
= Hom(M, (Eb 1 I)(1(N)0)) = Hom(M, Indb(N)).    
At the end we used Prop osition 5.8.  
Then we can obtain the following corollary easily. 
Corollary 5.13. The functor Resb maps projective objects to projective ones, and the functor 
Indb maps injective objects to injective ones. 
We can also dene functors res : Oc(G, h)0 Oc(G, h/hG )0 and ind : Oc(G, h/hG )0 
(G, h)0, attac hed to   hG , by Oc reg 
res :=  Res , ind :=  Ind , 
where  is as in Subsection 5.3. 
Corollary 5.14. The functors res, ind are exact. The functor ind is left adjoint to res. 
The functor ind maps projective objects to projective ones, and the functor res injective 
objects to injective ones. 
Proof. Easy to see from the denition of the functors and the Theorem 5.12.  
We also have the following proposition, whose proof is straigh tforw ard. 
Prop osition 5.15. We have 
ind(N)=(J 1)(N), and res(M)=(  M),E)( 
wher e  is dene d in Corollary 5.5. 
40</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Corollary 5.5. We have a natur al equivalenc e of categories 
 : Oc(G, h) Oc(G, h/hG )0. 
Proof. The categor y Oc(G, h) is the category of modules over H1,c(G, h) which are nitely 
generated over C[h] and extend by continuity to the completion of the algebra H1,c(G, h) 
at . So it follows from Theorem 5.4 that we have an equiv alence Oc(G, h) Oc(G, h)0. 
Comp osing this equiv alence with the equiv alence  : Oc(G, h)0 Oc(G, h/hG )0, we obtain 
the desired equiv alence .  
Remark 5.6. Note that in this proof, we take the completion of H1,c(G, h) at a point of 
  h rather than b  h. 
H1,c
which are nitely generat ed over 
b.C[h]Oc(G, h)b5.7. The completion functor. Let
 be the category of modules over
 (G, h)b 
Prop osition 5.7. The duality functor  denes an anti-e quivalenc e of c ategories Oc(G, h)  
(G, h)Oc .
Proof. This follows from the fact (already mentioned above) that Oc(G, h) is the category 
of modules over H1,c(G, h) which are nitely generated over C[h] and extend by continuity 
to the completi on of the algebra H1,c(G, h) at .  
Let us denote the functor inverse to  also by ; it is the functor of continuous dual (in 
the formal series topology). 
Oc Mb. 
Oc(G, h)0 in the opposite direction, sending a module N to 
the space Eb(N) of h-nilp otent vectors in N. (G, h)bWe have an exact functor of completion at b, Oc
Oc have a functor Eb :(G, h)0  , M 
 We also
(G, h)b 
Prop osition 5.8. The functor Eb is right adjoint to the completion functor b. 
Proof. We have 
H1,c Hom d (H1,c(G,h)b Mb,N) = Hom dH1,c(G,h)b (
 (G, h)b H1,c(G,h) M, N) 
= HomH1,c(G,h)(M, N|H1,c(G,h)) = HomH1,c(G,h)(M, Eb(N)). 
Remark 5.9. Recall that by Theorem 5.1, if b = 0 then these functors are not only adjoint 
but also inverse to each other. 
M)(G, h)b, one has Eb(M)=( Prop osition 5.10.
 (i) For M O
Mb) = Eb(M) in Oc(G, h)b. 
are exact. in Oc(G, h)0. c
(ii) For M Oc(G, h)0, (
(iii) The functors Eb, Eb 
Proof. (i),(ii) are straigh tforw ard from the denitions. (iii) follows from (i),(ii), since the 
completion functors are exact.  
39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>5. Parabolic induction and restriction functors for rational Cherednik 
algebras 
5.1. A geometric approac h to rational Cherednik algebras. An importan t property 
of the rational Cherednik algebra H1,c(G, h) is that it can be sheaed, as an algebra, over 
h/G (see [E1]). More specically , the usual sheac ation of H1,c(G, h) as a Oh/G-module 
is in fact a quasicoheren t sheaf of algebras, H1,c,G,h . Namely, for every ane open subset 
U  h/G, the algebra of sections H1,c,G,h (U) is, by denition, C[U] C[h]G H1,c(G, h). 
The same sheaf can be dened more geometr ically as follows (see [E1], Section 2.9). Let 
Ube the preimage of U in h. Then the algebra H1,c,G, h(U) is the algebra of linear operators 
on O(U) generated by O(U), the group G, and Dunkl operators 
 2cs s(a)a  (1  s), where a  h. 1  s s sS 
5.2. Completion of rational Cherednik algebras. For any b  h we can dene the 
completion (G, h)b to be the algebra of sections of the sheaf H1,c,G,h on the formal neigh H1,c
borhood of the image of b in h/G. Namely , (G, h)b is generated by regular functions on H1,c
the formal neigh borhood of the G-orbit of b, the group G, and Dunkl operators. 
The algebra (G, h)b inherits from H1,c(G, h) the natural ltration F by order of dif H1,c 
feren tial operators, and each of the spaces F n (G, h)b has a projectiv e limit topology; the H1,c
whole algebra is then equipp ed with the topology of the nested union (or inductiv e limit). 
Consider the completi on of the rational Cherednik algebra at zero, (G, h)0. It natur ally H1,c
contains the algebra C[[h]]. Dene the category Oc(G, h) of represen tations of (G, h)0H1,c
which are nitely generat ed over C[[h]] 0 = C[[h]]. 
We have a completion functor : Oc(G, h) Oc(G, h), dened by  
M = H1,c(G, h)0 H1,c(G,h) M = C[[h]] C[h] M. 
Also, for N Oc(G, h), let E(N) be the subspace spanned by generalized eigen vectors of 
h in N where h is dened by (3.2). Then it is easy to see that E(N) Oc(G, h)0. 
Theorem 5.1. The restriction of the completion functor  to Oc(G, h)0 is an equivalenc e 
of categories Oc(G, h)0 Oc(G, h). The inverse equivalenc e is given by the functor E. 
Proof. It is clear that M   M) (as M is spanned by generalized eigen vectors M, so M  E(
of h). Let us demonstrate the opposite inclusion. Pick generators m1,...,mr of M which 
are generalized eigen vectors of h with eigen values 1,...,r. Let 0 M). Then v = v  E( = 
fimi, where fi  C[[h]]. Assume that (h )N v = 0 for some N. 
Then v = f(i)mi,i ii 
= E( where for f  C[[h]] we denote by f(d) the degree d part of f. Thus v  M, so MM). 
It remains to show that E(N)= N, i.e. that N is the closure of E(N). In other words, 
letting m denote the maximal ideal in C[[h]], we need to show that the natura l map E(N) 
N/mj N is surjectiv e for every j.  
To do so, note that h preserv es the descending ltration of N by subspaces mj N. On 
the other hand , the successiv e quotien ts of these subspaces, mj N/mj+1N, are nite dimen
sional, which implies that h acts locally nitely on their direct sum grN, and moreo ver each 
36</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-735-double-affine-hecke-algebras-in-representation-theory-combinatorics-geometry-and-mathematical-physics-fall-2009/resources/mit18_735f09_ch01/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1. Introduction
Double ane Hecke algebras, also called Cherednik algebras, were introduced by Chered
nik in 1993 as a tool in his proof of Macdonalds conjectures about orthogonal polynomials for 
root systems. Since then, it has been realized that Chered nik algebras are of great indep en
dent interest; they appeared in many dieren t mathematical contexts and found numerous 
applications. 
The presen t notes are based on a course on Cherednik algebras given by the rst author 
at MIT in the Fall of 2009. Their goal is to give an introduction to Cherednik algebras, and 
to review the web of connections between them and other mathema tical objects. For this 
reason, the notes consist of many parts that are relativ ely indep endent of each other. Also, 
to keep the notes within the bounds of a one-semester course, we had to limit the discussion 
of many importan t topics to a very brief outline, or to skip them altogether. For a more 
in-depth discussion of Cherednik algebras, we refer the reader to researc h articles dedicated 
to this subject. 
The notes do not contain any original material. In each section, the sources of the expo
sition are listed in the notes at the end of the section . 
The organization of the notes is as follows. 
In Section 2, we dene the classical and quan tum Calogero-Moser systems, and their 
analogs for any Coxeter groups introduced by Olshanetsky and Perelomo v. Then we intro
duce Dunkl operators, prove the fundamen tal result of their comm utativit y, and use them to 
establish integrabilit y of the Calogero-Moser and Olshanetsky-P erelomo v systems. We also 
prove the uniqueness of the rst integrals for these systems. 
In Section 3, we conceptualize the commutation relations between Dunkl operators and 
coordinate operators by introducing the main object of these notes -the rational Cherednik 
algebra. We develop the basic theory of rational Cherednik algebras (proving the PBW 
theorem), and then pass to the represen tation theory of rational Cherednik algebras, more 
precisely , study the structure of category O. After developing the basic theory (parallel to 
the case of semisimple Lie algebras), we completely work out the represen tations in the rank 
1 case, and prove a number of results about nite dimensional represen tations and about 
represen tations of the rationa l Cherednik algebra attac hed to the symmetric group. 
In Section 4, we evaluate the Macdonald- Mehta integral, and then use it to nd the sup
ports of irrieducible modules over the rational Cheredni k algebras with the trivial lowest 
weight, in particular giving a simple proof of the theorem of Varagnolo and Vasserot, classi
fying such represen tations which are nite dimensional. 
In Section 5, we describ e the theory of parab olic induction and restriction functors for 
rational Cherednik algebras, developed in [BE], and give some applications of this theory , 
such as the description of the category of Whittak er modules and of possible supp orts of 
modules lying in category O. 
In Section 6, we dene Hecke algebras of complex reection groups, and the Knizhnik-
Zamolo dchikov (KZ) functor from the category O of a rational Cherednik algebra to the 
category of nite dimensional represen tations of the corresp onding Hecke algebra. We use 
this functor to prove the formal atness of Hecke algebras of complex reection groups (a 
theorem of Brou e, Malle, and Rouquier), and state the theorem of Ginzbu rg-Gua y-Op dam-
Rouquier that the KZ functo r is an equiv alence from the category O modulo its torsion part 
to the category of represen tations of the Hecke algebra. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>In Section 7, we dene rational Cherednik algebras for orbifolds. We also dene the 
corresp onding Hecke algebras, and dene the KZ functor from the categ ory of modules over 
the former to that over the latter. This generalize s to the curv ed case the KZ functor 
for rational Cherednik algebras of complex reection groups, dened in Section 6. We then 
apply the KZ functor to showing that if the universal cover of the orbifold in question has 
a trivial H2 (with complex coecien ts), then the orbifold Hecke algebra is formally at, 
and explai n why the condition of trivial H2 cannot be dropp ed. Next, we list examples of 
orbifold Hecke algebras which satisfy the condition of vanishing H2 (and hence are formally 
at). These include usual, ane, and double ane Hecke algebra s, as well as Hecke algebras 
attac hed to Fuchsian groups, which include quan tizations of del Pezzo surfaces and their 
Hilbert schemes; we work these examples out in some detail, highligh ting connections with 
other subjects. Finally , we discuss the issue of algebraic atness, and prove it in the case of 
algebras of rank 1 attac hed to Fuchsian groups, using the theory of deforma tions of group 
algebras of Coxeter groups developed in [ER]. 
In Section 8, we dene symplectic reection algebras (whic h inlude rational Cherednik al
gebras as a special case), and generalize to them some of the theory of Section 3. Namely , we 
use the theory of deformations of Koszul algebras to prove the PBW theorem for symplectic 
reection algebras. We also determine the center of symplectic reection algeb ras, showing 
that it is trivial when the parameter t is nonze ro, and is isomorphic to the shperical subal
gebra if t = 0. Next, we give a deformation-theoretic interpretation of symplectic reection 
algebras as universal deformation s of Weyl algebras smashed with nite groups. Finally , we 
discuss nite dimensional represen tations of symplectic reection algebras for t = 0, show
ing that the Azuma ya locus on the space of such represen tations coincides with the smooth 
locus. This uses the theory of Cohen-Macaula y modules and of homological dimension in 
comm utativ e algebra. In particular, we show that for Cherednik algebras of type An1, the 
whole represen tation space is smooth and coincides with the spectrum of the center. 
In Section 9, we give another description of the spectrum of the center of the rational 
Cherednik algebra of type An1 (for t = 0), as a certain space of conjugacy classes of pairs 
of matrices, introduced by Kazhdan, Kostan t, and Stern berg, and called the Calogero-Moser 
space (this space is obtained by classical hamiltonian reduction, and is a special case of a 
quiver variety). This yields a new construction of the Calogero-Moser integrable system. 
We also sketch a proof of the Gan-Ginzbu rg theorem claiming that the quotien t of the 
comm uting scheme by conjugation is reduced, and hence isomorphic to C2n/Sn. Finally , we 
explain that the Calogero-Moser space is a topologica lly trivial deformation of the Hilbert 
scheme of the plane, we use the theory of Cherednik algebras to compute the cohomology 
ring of this space. 
In Section 10, we generalize the results of Section 9 to the quan tum case. Namely , we 
prove the quan tum analog of the Gan-Ginzburg theore m (the Harish Chandra-Lev asseur-
Staord theorem), and explain how to quan tize the Caloger o-Moser space using quan tum 
Hamiltonian reduction. Not surprisingly , this gives the same quan tization as was constructed 
in the previous sections, namely, the spherical subalgebra of the rational Cherednik algebra. 
Acknowledgemen ts. We are grateful to the particip ants of the course on Cherednik 
algebras at MIT, especially to Roman Travkin and Aleksander Tsym balyuk, for many useful 
commen ts and corrections. This work was partially supp orted by the NSF grants DMS
0504847 and DMS-0 854764. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.735 Double Affine Hecke Algebras in Representation Theory, Combinatorics, Geometry, 
and Mathematical Physics 
Fall 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Knizhnik-Zamolodchikov functor</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-735-double-affine-hecke-algebras-in-representation-theory-combinatorics-geometry-and-mathematical-physics-fall-2009/resources/mit18_735f09_ch06/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Proof. Assume rst that c is generic. Then the category Oc(G, h)0 is semisimple, with simple 
objects Mc(), so it is enough to check the statemen t on Mc(). Consider the trivia l bundle 
over hreg with ber . The KZ connection on it has the form 
 2cs dsd  (1  s). 1  s s sS 
The residue of the connection form of this connection on the hyperplane H on the j-th 
irreducible represen tation of Z/mH Z is 
mH 1 cs21  e2H 
i/mH (1  e 2ij/mH ). 
=1 
Therefore, the mono drom y operator around this hyperplane is diagonalizable, and the eigen
values of this operator are 1 and exp(2ij/mH )qj,H , as desired. 
For special c, introduce the generalized Verma module 
Mc,n( )= Hc(G, h) CGS h (  Sh/m n+1), 
where m Sh is the maximal ideal of 0, n 0. Clearly , Mc,0 = Mc(). Moreo ver,  
Mc,n (G, h)0 for any n, since it has a nite ltration whose successiv e quotien ts are Oc
Verma modules. 
Theorem 6.5. For large enough n, Mc,n(CG) contains a direct summand which is a projec
tive gener ator of Oc(G, h)0. 
Proof. From the denition, Mc,n = Sh  CG  Sh/mn+1 . Let  be the degree operator on 
Mc,n(CG) with deg h =1, deg h = 1, and deg G = 0, i.e., we have 
[, x]= x, [, y]= y, where x  h,y  h. 
So h   is a module endomorphism of Mc,n(CG) where h is the operator dened in (3.2). 
Moreo ver, h   acts locally nitely . In particular, we have a decomp osition of Mc,n(CG) 
into generalized eigenspaces of h  : 
Mc,n(CG) = M (CG).c,n
C 
We have 
Hom(Mc,n(CG),N)= {vectors in N which are killed by m n+1}, 
and 
Hom(M (CG),N)= {vectors in N which are killed by m n+1 
c,n
and are generaliz ed eigen vectors of h with generalized eigen value }. 
Let   = {hc()| is a irreducible represen tation of G} (recall that 
hc()= dim h 2cs s ), and let 2  sS 1s |
M (CG) = M (CG).c,n c,n
 
Claim: for large n, M (CG) is a projectiv e generator of Oc(G, h)0.c,n
46</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.735 Double Affine Hecke Algebras in Representation Theory, Combinatorics, Geometry, 
and Mathematical Physics 
Fall 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>6. The Knizhnik-Zamolodchik ov functor
6.1. Braid groups and Hecke algebras. Let G be a complex reection group and let h 
be its reection represen tation. For any reection hyperplane H  h, its pointwise stabilizer 
is a cyclic group of order mH . Fix a collection of nonzero constan ts q1,H ,...,qmH 1,H which 
are G-invarian t, namely , if H and H are conjuga te to each other under some elemen t in G, 
then qi,H = qi,H for i =1,...,mH  1. 
Let BG = 1(hreg/G, x0) be the braid group of G, and TH  BG be a represen tative of 
the conjugacy class dened by a small circle around the image of H in h/G orien ted in the 
counterclo ckwise direction. 
The following theorem follows from elemen tary algebraic topology . 
Prop osition 6.1. The group G is the quotient of the braid group BG by the relations 
THmH =1 
for all reection hyperplanes H. 
Proof. See, e.g., [BMR] Prop osition 2.17.  
Denition 6.2. The Hecke algebra of G is dened to be 
mH 1 
Hq(G)= C[BG]/(TH  1) (TH  exp(2 ij/mH )qj,H ), for all H. 
j=1 
Thus, by Prop osition 6.1 we have an isomorphism 
= CG. H1(G) 
So Hq(G) is a deformation of CG. 
Example 6.3 (Coxeter group case). Now let W be a Coxeter group. Let S be the set of 
reections and let s = 0 be the reection hyperplane corresp onding to s S. The Hecke 
algebra Hq(W ) is the quotien t of C[BW ] by the relations 
(Ts  1)(Ts + qs)=0, 
for all reections s where Ts is a small counterclo ckwise circle around the image of the 
hyperplane s =0 in h/W . 
6.2. KZ functors. For a complex reection group G, let Loc(hreg) be the category of local 
systems (i.e., O-coheren t D-modules) on hreg, and let Loc(hreg)G be the category of G
equiv arian t local systems on hreg, i.e. of local systems on hreg/G. 
Supp ose that G = 1 is the trivial subgroup in G. Then the restriction functor dened in 
Section 5.10 denes a functor Res : Oc(G, h)0  Loc(hreg/G). Also, we have the mono drom y 
functor Mon : Loc(hreg/G) Rep(BG). The comp osition of these two functors is a functor = 
from Oc(G, h)0 to Rep(BG), which is exactly the KZ functor dened in [GGOR]. We will 
denote this funct or by KZ. 
Theorem 6.4 (Ginzburg, Guay, Opdam, Rouquier, [GGOR]) . The KZ functor factors 
through 
RepHq(G), wher e 
mH 1 c (1  e2ij/mH ) 
qj,H = exp(2 ibj,H /mH ), and bj,H =2 sH . 1  e2i/mH 
=1 
45</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Now let Oc(G, h)tor be the full subcategory of Oc(G, h)0 consisting of modules supp orted 0 
on the reection hyperplanes. It is a Serre subcategory , and ker(KZ) = Oc(G, h)tor
0 . Thus 
we have a functor: 
KZ : Oc(G, h)0/Oc(G, h)tor RepHq(G).0  
Theorem 6.10 (Ginzburg, Guay, Opdam, Rouquier, [GGOR]) . If dim Hq(G)= |G|, the 
functor KZ is an equivalenc e of categories. 
Proof. See [GGOR], Theo rem 5.14.  
6.4. Example: the symmetric group Sn. Let h = Cn , G = Sn. Then we have (for 
q  C): 
Hq(Sn)= T1,...,Tn1/the braid relation s and (Ti  1)(Ti + q)=0.
The following facts are known:
(1) dim Hq(Sn)= n!; 
(2) Hq(Sn) is semisimple if and only if ord(q)=2, 3, . . . , n. 
Now supp ose q is generic. Let  be a partition of n. Then we can dene an Hq(Sn)
module S, the Specht module for the Hecke algebra in the sense of [DJ]. This is a certain 
deformation of the classical irreducible Specht module for the symmetric group . The Specht 
module carries an inner product , . Denote D = S/Rad, . 
Theorem 6.11 (Dipp er, James, [DJ]). D is either an irreducible Hq(Sn)-mo dule, or 0. 
D =0 if and only if  is e-regular wher e e = ord(q ) (i.e., every part of  occurs less than 
e times).
Proof. See [DJ], Theorem 6.3, 6.8. 
Now let Mc() be the Verma module associated to the Specht module for Sn and Lc() 
be its irreducible quotien t. Then we have the following theorem. 
Theorem 6.12. If c  0, then KZ(Mc()) = S and KZ(Lc()) = D. 
Proof. See Section 6.2 of [GGOR].  
Corollary 6.13. If c  0, then SuppLc()= Cn if and only if  is e-regular. If c&gt; 0, 
then SuppLc()= Cn if and only if  is e-regular, or equivalently,  is e-restricte d (i.e.,
i  i+1 &lt;e for i =1,...,n  1).
Proof. Directly from the denition and the above theorem. 
6.5. Notes. The references for this section are [GGOR], [BMR]. 
48</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Proof of the claim. First, for any , there exists n such that M (CG) is projectiv e (since c,n
the condition of being killed by mn+1 is vacuous for large n). 
Secondly , consider the functor Hom(M (CG), ). For any module N Oc(G, h)0, ifc,n
Hom(M (CG),N) = 0, then N[]=0. So N = 0. Thus this functor does not kill c,n
nonzero objects, and so M (CG) is a generator. c,n
Theorem 6.5 is proved.  
Corollary 6.6. (i) Oc(G, h)0 has enough projectives, so it is equivalent to the category 
of modules over a nite dimensional algebr a. 
(ii) Any object of Oc(G, h)0 is a quotient of a multiple of Mc,n(CG) for large enough n. 
Proof. Directly from the denition and the above theorem.  
Now we can nish the proof of Theorem 6.4. We have shown that for generic c, 
KZ(Mc,n(CG))  RepHq(G). Hence this is true for any c, since Mc,n(CG) is a at fam
ily of modules over Hc(G, h). Then, KZ(M) is a Hq(G)-mo dule for all M, since any M is a 
quotien t of Mc,n(CG) and the functor KZ is exact.  
Corollary 6.7 (Brou e, Malle , Rouquier, [BMR]) . Let qj,H = exp(tj,H ) wher e tj,H s are 
formal parameters. Then Hq(G) is a free module over C[[tj,H ]] of rank |G|. 
Proof. We have 
Hq(G)/(t) = H1(G)= CG. 
So it remains to show that Hq(G) is free. To show this, it is sucien t to show that any 
  IrrepG admits a at deformat ion q to a represen tation of Hq(G). We can dene this 
deformation by letting q = KZ(Mc( )).  
Remark 6.8. 1. The validit y of this Corollary in characteristic zero implies that it is also 
valid over a eld positiv e characteristic. 
2. It is not known in general if the Corollary holds for numerical q (even generically). This 
is a conjecture of Brou e, Malle , and Rouquier. But it is known for many cases (including all 
Coxeter groups). 
3. The proof of the Corollary is analytic (it is based on the notion of mono drom y). There 
is no known algeb raic proof, except in special cases, and in the case of Coxeter groups, which 
well discuss later. 
6.3. The image of the KZ functor. First, let us recall the denition of a quotien t catego ry. 
Let A be an abelian category and BA a full abelian subcategory . 
Denition 6.9. B is a Serre subcategory if it is closed under subquotien ts and extensions 
(i.e., if two terms in a short exact sequence are in B, so is the third one). 
If BA is a Serre subcategory , one can dene a category A/B as follows: 
objects in A/B = objects in A, 
HomA/B(X, Y ) = lim HomA(X, Y/Y ). 
 
Y ,X/XB 
The category A/B is an abelian category with the following universal property: any exact 
functor F : AC that kills B must factor through A/B. 
47</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The rational Cherednik algebra</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-735-double-affine-hecke-algebras-in-representation-theory-combinatorics-geometry-and-mathematical-physics-fall-2009/resources/mit18_735f09_ch03/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3. The rational Cherednik algebra
3.1. Denition and examples. Above we have made essen tial use of the comm utation 
relations between operators x  h,g  G, and Da,a  h. This makes it natural to consider 
the algebra generated by these operators. 
Denition 3.1. The rational Cherednik algebra associated to (G, h) is the algebra Hc(G, h) 
generated inside A = Rees(CG  D(hreg)) by the elemen ts x  h,g  G, and Da(c, ),a  h. 
If t  C, then the algebra Ht,c(G, h) is the specialization of Hc(G, h) at  = t. 
Prop osition 3.2. The algebr a Hc is the quotient of the algebr a CG  T(h  h)[] (wher e 
T denotes the tensor algebr a) by the ideal gener ated by the relations 
[x, x]=0, [y, y]=0, [y, x]= (y, x)  cs(y, s)(x, )s,s 
sS 
wher e x, x  h, y, y  h. 
Proof. Let us denote the algebra dened in the proposition by Hc= Hc(G, h). Then accord
ing to the results of the previous sections, we have a surje ctive homomorphism  : HcHc 
dened by the formula (x)= x, (g)= g, (y)= Dy(c, ).  
Let us show that this homomorphism is injectiv e. For this purpose assume that yi is a 
basis of h, and xi is the dual basis of h. Then it is clear from the relations of Hcthat Hcis 
spanned over C[] by the elemen ts 
rr
(3.1) gyimi xini . 
i=1 i=1 
Thus it rema ins to show that the images of the elemen ts (3.1) under the map , i.e. the 
elemen ts 
r r
gDyi (c, )mi xini . 
i=1 i=1 
are linearly indep endent. But this follows from the obvious fact that the symbols of these 
elemen ts in CG C[h  hreg][] are linearly indep enden t. The proposition is proved.  
Remark 3.3. 1. Similarly , one can dene the universal algeb ra H(G, h), in which both  
and c are variables. (So this is an algebra over C[,c].) It has two equiv alent denitions 
similar to the above. 
2. It is more convenien t to work with algebr as dened by generators and relations than 
with subalgeb ras of a given algebra generated by a given set of elemen ts. Theref ore, from 
now on we will use the statemen t of Prop osition 3.2 as a denition of the rational Cherednik 
algebra Hc. According to Prop osition 3.2, this algebra comes with a natural embedding 
c : Hc  Rees(CG  D(hreg)), den ed by the formula x  x, g  g, y  Dy(c, ). This 
embedding is called the Dunkl operator embedding . 
Example 3.4. 1. Let G = Z2, h = C. In this case c reduces to one parameter, and the 
algebra Ht,c is generated by elemen ts x, y, s with dening relations 
s 2 =1, sx = xs, sy = ys, [y, x]= t  2cs. 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>3.10. Irreducible modules. Let  be an irreducible represen tation of G.
Prop osition 3.29. Mc() has a maximal proper submo dule Jc().
Proof. The proof is standard. Jc() is the sum of all proper submo dules of Mc(), and it is
not equal to Mc() because any proper submo dule has a grading by generalized eigenspaces 
of h, with eigen values  such that   hc() &gt; 0.  
We dene Lc()= Mc( )/Jc(), which is an irreducible module. 
Prop osition 3.30. Any irreducible object of Oc(G, h)0 has the form Lc() for an unique . 
Proof. Let L Oc(G, h)0 be irreducible, with lowest eigenspace of h containing an irreducible 
G-mo dule . Then by Prop osition 3.24, we have a nonzero homomorphism Mc() L, which 
is surjectiv e, since L is irreducible. Then we must have L = Lc().  
 
Remark 3.31. Let  be a character of G. Then we have an isomorphism H1,c(G, h) 
H1,c(G, h), mapping g  G to 1(g)g. This automorphism maps Lc() to Lc(1  ) 
isomorphically . 
3.11. The contragredien t module. Set c(s)= c(s1). We have a natural isomorphism 
 : H1,c(G, h)op  H1,c(G, h), acting trivially on h and h, and sending g  G to g1 . 
Thus if M is an H1,c(G, h)-mo dule, then the full dual space M is an H1,c(M, h)-module. 
If M Oc(G, h)0, then we can dene M, which is the h-nite part of M. 
Prop osition 3.32. M belongs to Oc(G, h)0. 
Proof. Clearly , if L is irreducible, then so is L. Then L is generated by its lowest h
eigenspace over H1,c(G, h), hence over Sh. Thus, L Oc(G, h)0. Now, let M Oc(G, h)0 
be any object. Since M has nite length, so does M. Moreo ver, M has a nite ltration 
with successiv e quotients of the form L, where L Oc(G, h)0 is irreducible. This implies 
the required state ment, since Oc(G, h)0 is closed under taking extensions.  
Clearly , M = M. Thus, M  M is an equiv alence of categories Oc(G, h) Oc(G, h)op. 
3.12. The contravarian t form. Let  be an irreducible represen tation of G. By Prop o
sition 3.24, we have a unique homomorphism  : Mc(G, h,) Mc(G, h,) which is the 
identity in the lowest h-eigenspace. Thus, we have a pairing 
c : Mc(G, h,)  Mc(G, h,)  C, 
which is called the contravariant form. 
Remark 3.33. If G = = = c, and  W is a real reection group, then h h, c  = viaa 
symmetric form. So for real reection groups, c is a symmetric form on Mc( ). 
Prop osition 3.34. The maximal proper submo dule Jc( ) is the kernel of  (or, equivalently, 
of the contravariant form c). 
Proof. Let K be the kernel of the contravarian t form. It suces to show that Mc()/K is 
irreducible. We have a diagram: 
 Mc(G, h,) Mc(G, h,) 
 
 
Lc(G, h,)   Lc(G, h,) 
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Proof. The rst statemen t is clear from the above. The second statemen t follows from the 
fact that gr(B 0,c)= B0,0 = C[h  h]G, which is nitely generated by Hilberts theorem.  
Corollary 3.9. Mc = SpecB 0,c is an irreducible ane algebr aic variety. 
Proof. Directly from the denition and the proposition.  
We also obtain 
Prop osition 3.10. Bc is a at quantization (non-c ommutative deformation) of B0,c over 
C[]. 
So B0,c carries a Poisson bracket {, }(thus Mc is a Poisson variety), and Bc is a quanti
zation of the Poisson bracket, i.e. if a, b  Bc and a0,b0 are the corresp onding elements in 
B0,c, then 
[a, b]/ {a0,b0} (mod ). 
Denition 3.11. The Poisson variety Mc is called the Calo gero-Moser space of G, h with 
parameter c. 
3.4. The localization lemma. Let Hloc = Ht,c[1] be the localization of Ht,c as a module t,c 
over C[h] with respect to the discriminan t  (a polynomial vanishing to the rst order on 
each reection plane). Dene also Bloc = eHloc e.t,c t,c 
Prop osition 3.12. (i) For t =0 the map t,c induc es an isomorphism of algebr as 
Hloc 
), which restricts to an isomorphism Bloc )G .t,c  CG  D(hreg t,c D(hreg
(ii) The map 0,c induc es an isom orphism of algebr as Hloc  CG C[h  hreg], which 0,c
restricts to an isomorphism Bloc ]G .
0,c  C[h  hreg
Proof. This follows immediately from the fact that the Dunkl operators have poles only on 
the reection hyperplanes.  
Since gr(B0,c)= B0,0 = C[h  h]G, we get the following geometric corollary . 
Corollary 3.13. (i) The family of Poisson varieties Mc is a at deformation of the 
Poisson variety M0 := (h  h)/G. In particular, Mc is smooth outside of a subset of 
codimension 2. 
(ii) We have a natur al map c : Mc h/G, such that c1(hreg/G) is isomorphic to 
(hreg h)/G. The Poisson structur e on Mc is obtaine d by extension of the symple ctic 
Poisson structur e on (hreg  h)/G. 
Example 3.14. Let W = Z2, h = C. Then B0,c = x2, xp, p2 c2/x2. Let X := x2,Z := xp 
and Y := p2 c2/x2 . Then Z2  XY = c2 . So Mc is isomorphic to the quadric Z2 XY = c2 
in the 3-dimensio nal space and it is smooth for c = 0. 
3.5. Category O for rational Cherednik algebras. From the PBW theorem, we see that 
H1,c = Sh  CG  Sh. It is similar to the structure of the universal enveloping algebra of a 
simple Lie algebra: U(g)= U(n)U(h)U(n+). Namely , the subalgebra CG plays the role 
of the Cartan subalgebra, and the subalgebras Sh and Sh play the role of the positive and 
negativ e nilpotent subalgebras. This similarit y allows one to dene and study the category 
O analogous to the Bernstein-Gelfand-Gelfa nd category O for simple Lie algebras. 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>nRecall that c,C satises c,C(x,xn)= c,C(xn1, yxn), which gives 
an = an1(n  bn), 
where bn are new param eters: 
m11  jn 
bn := 2 cj (b0 =0,bn+m = bn). 1  j 
j=1 
Thus we obtain the following proposition. 
Prop osition 3.40. (i) Mc(C) is irreducible if only if n  bn =0  for any n  1. 
(ii)	Assume that r is the smal lest positive integer such that r = br. Then Lc(C) has 
dimension r (which can be any numb er not divisible by m) with basis 1, x, . . . , xr1 . 
Remark 3.41. According to Remark 3.31, this proposition in fact describ es all the irre
ducible lowest weight modules. 
Example 3.42. Consider the case m = 2. The Mc(C) is irreducible unless c  1/2+ Z0. 
If c = (2n + 1)/2  1/2+ Z, n  0, then Lc(C) has dimension 2n + 1. A similar answ er is 
obtained for lowest weight C, replacing c by c. 
3.15. The Frobenius property. Let A be a Z+-graded comm utativ e algebra. The algebra 
A is called Frobenius if the top degree A[d] of A is 1-dimensional, and the multiplication 
map A[m]  A[d  m] A[d] is a nondege nerate pairing for any 0  m  d. In particular, 
the Hilbert polynomial of a Frobenius algebra A is palindromic. 
Now, let us go back to considering modules over the rational Cherednik algebra H1,c. Any 
submo dule J of the polynomial represen tation Mc(C)= Mc = C[h] is an ideal in C[h], so 
the quotien t A = Mc/J is a Z+-graded comm utativ e algebra. 
Now supp ose that G preserv es an inner product in h, i.e., G  O(h). 
Theorem 3.43. If A = Mc(C)/J is nite dimensional, then A is irreducible (A = Lc(C)) 
 A is a Frobenius algebr a. 
Proof. 1) Supp ose A is an irreducible H1,c-module, i.e., A = Lc(C). By Prop osition 3.19, A 
is naturally a nite dimensional sl2-module (in particular, it integrates to the group SL2(C)). 
Hence, by the represen tation theory of sl2, the top degre e of A is 1-dimensional. Let   A 
denote a nonzero linear function on the top comp onent. Let c be the contravarian t form 
on Mc(C). Consider the form 
0	1 (v1,v2)  E(v1,v2) := c(v1, gv2), where g = 10  SL2(C). 
Then E(xv1,v2)= E(v1, xv2). So for any p, q  Mc(C)= C[h], E(p, q)= (p(x)q (x)) (for a 
suitable normalization of ). 
Since E is a nondegenerat e form, A is a Frobenius algeb ra. 
2)	Supp ose A is Frobenius. Then the highest component is 1-dimensional, and 
E : A  A  C, E(a, b)= (ab) is nondegenerate. We have E(xa, b)= E(a, xb). So 
set (a, b)= E(a, g1b). Then  satises (a, xib)= (yia, b). Thus, for all p, q  C[h], 
(p(x),q(x)) = (q(y)p(x), 1). So  = c up to scaling. Thus, c is nondegenerate and A is 
irreducible.  
Remark 3.44. If G  O(h), this theorem is false, in general. 
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.735 Double Affine Hecke Algebras in Representation Theory, Combinatorics, Geometry, 
and Mathematical Physics 
Fall 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Proof. Let us prove the rst relation; the second one is proved similarly . We have 
[h,x]=  
xi[yi,x]   
12
 cs 
s  s 
2  1(,x)s  ss 
i  sS  
= xi(yi,x)  (,x)(s,yi)s + (,x)s  s. xi css css 
i i  sS  sS 
The last two terms cancel since i xi(s,yi)= s, so we get i xi(yi,x)= x.  
Prop osition 3.19. Let G = W be a real reection group. Let 
 1  1  1 
h = xiyi + dim h  css, E =  xi 2 , F = yi 2 .
2	 2 2 i	 i i sS 
Then 
(i)	h = i(xiyi + yixi)/2; 
(ii)	h, E, F form an sl2-triple. 
Proof. A direct calculatio n.	  
Theorem 3.20. Let M be a module over H1,c(G, h). 
(i)	If h acts locally nilpotently on M, then h acts locally nitely on M. 
(ii)	If M is nitely gener ated over Sh, then M Oc(G, h)0 if and only if h acts locally 
nitely on M. 
Proof. (i) Assume that Sh acts locally nilpotently on M. Let v  M. Then Sh v is a nite  
dimensional vector space and let d = dim Sh v. We prove that v is h-nite by induction  
in dimension d. We can use d = 0 as base, so only need to do the inductio n step. The 
space Sh v must contain a nonzero vector u such that yu = 0, y  h. Let U  M be 	  
the subspace of vectors with this property. h acts on U by an elemen t of CG, hence locally 
nitely . So it is sucien t to show that the image of v in M/U is h-nite (where U is 
the submo dule generated by U). But this is true by the induction assumption, as u =0 in 
M/U. 
(ii) We need to show that if h acts locally nitely on M, then h acts locally nilpotently 
on M. Assume h acts locally nitely on M. Then M = B M[], where B  C. Since M 
is nitely generated over Sh, B is a nite union of sets of the form z + Z0, z  C. So Sh 
must act locally nilpotently on M.  
We can obtain the following corollary easily . 
Corollary 3.21. Any nite dimensional H1,c(G, h)-mo dule is in Oc(G, h)0. 
We see that any module M Oc(G, h)0 has a grading by generalized eigen values of h: 
M =  M[]. 
3.7. Standard modules. Let  be a nite dimensional represen tation of G. The standard 
module over H1,c(G, h) corresp onding to  (also called the Verma module) is 
Mc(G, h,)= Mc()= H1,c(G, h) CGS h  Oc(G, h)0, 
where Sh acts on  by zero. 
So from the PBW theorem, we have that as vector spaces, Mc() =   Sh. 
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Now consider the Frobenius property of Lc(C) for any G  GL(h). 
Theorem 3.45. Let U  Mc(C)= C[h] be a G-subr epresentation of dimension l = dim h, 
sitting in degree r, which consists of singular vectors. Let J = U. Assume that A = Mc/J 
is nite dimensional. Then 
(i)	A is Frobenius. 
(ii)	A admits a BGG type resolution:
A  Mc(C)  Mc(U)  Mc(2U)    Mc(lU)  0.
(iii) The character of A is given by the formula 
l 2cs A(g, t)= t2  P 
1s detU (1  gtr) .sS 
deth (1  gt) 
In particular, dim A = rl . 
(iv) If G preserves an inner product, then A is irreducible. 
Proof. (i) Since Spec A is a complete intersection, A is Frobenius. 
(ii) We will use the following theorem: 
Theorem 3.46 (Serre) . Let f1,...,fn  C[t1,...,tn] be homo geneous polynomials, and 
assume that C[t1,...,tn] is a nitely gener ated module over C[f 1,...,fn]. Then this is a free 
module. 
Consider SU  Sh. Then Sh is a nitely generated SU-module (as Sh/U is nite 
dimensional). By Serres theorem, we know that Sh is a free SU-module. The rank of this 
module is rl . Consider the Koszul complex attac hed to this module. Since the module is 
free, the Koszul complex is exact (i.e., it is a resolution of the zero ber). At the level of 
SU-modules, it looks exactly like we want in (3.45). 
So we only need to show that the maps of the resolution are morphisms over H1,c. This 
is shown by induction. Namely , let j : Mc(j U)  Mc(j1U) be the corresp onding 
dieren tials (so that 0 : Mc(C) A is the projection). Then 0 is an H1,c-morphism, which 
is the base of induction. If j is an H1,c-morphism, then the kernel of j is a submo dule 
Kj  Mc(j U). Its lowest degree part is j+1U sitting in degree (j + 1)r and consisting of 
singular vectors. Now, j+1 is a morphi sm over Sh which maps j+1U identically to itself. 
By Prop osition 3.24, there is only one such morphism, and it must be an H1,c-morphism. 
This completes the induction step. 
(iii) follows from (ii) by the Euler-P oincar e formula. 
(iv) follows from Theorem 3.43. 
3.16. Represen tations of H1,c of type A. Let us now apply the above results to the case 
of type A. We will follow the paper [CE]. 
Let G = Sn, and h be its reection represen tation. In this case the function c reduces 
to one number. We will denot e the rational Cherednik algebra H1,c(Sn) by Hc(n). Itis 
generated by x1,...,xn, y1,...,yn and CSn with the following relation s: 
	 1 yi =0,xi =0, [yi,xj]= n + csij ,i =j, 
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Denition 3.15. The category Oc(G, h) is the category of modules over H1,c(G, h) which 
are nitel y generated over Sh and locally nite under Sh (i.e., for M Oc(G, h), v  M, 
(Sh)v is nite dimensiona l). 
If M is a locally nite (Sh)G-module, then 
M = h/GM, 
where 
M = {v  M|p  (Sh)G , N s.t. (p  (p))N v =0}, 
(notice that h/G = Specm(S h)G). 
Prop osition 3.16. M are H1,c-submo dules. 
Proof. Note rst that we have an isomorphism  : H1,c(G, h) H1,c= (G, h), which is given 
by xa Now let x1,...,xr be a basis of h and y1,...,yr a basis of h.  ya,yb  xb,g  g. 
Supp ose P = P (x1,...,xr)  (Sh)G . Then we have 
 [y, P ]= y P  Sh, where y  h, 
(this follows from the fact that both sides act in the same way in the polynomial represen
tation, which is faithful). So using the isomorphism , we conclude that if Q  (Sh)G,Q = 
Q(y1,...,yr), then [x, Q]= xQ for x  h. 
Now, to prove the propositio n, the only thing we need to check is that M is invarian t 
under x  h. For any v  M, we have (Q  (Q))N v = 0 for some N. Then 
(Q  (Q))N+1 xv =(N + 1)xQ (Q  (Q))N v =0.  
So xv  M. 
Corollary 3.17. We have the following decomposition: 
Oc(G, h)= Oc(G, h), 
h/G 
wher e Oc(G, h) is the subcategory of modules wher e (Sh)G acts with gener alized eigenvalue 
. 
Proof. Directly from the denition and the proposition.	  
Note that Oc(G, h) is an abelian category closed under taking subquotien ts and exten
sions. 
3.6. The grading elemen t. Let 
 1  2cs(3.2)	 h = xiyi + 2 dim h  1  s s. 
i sS 
Prop osition 3.18. We have 
[h,x]= x, x  h, [h,y]= y, y  h. 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>n  1  
[yi,xi]=  csij . n j=i 
The polynomial represen tation Mc(C) of this algebra is the space of C[x 1,...,xn]T of poly
nomials of x1,...,xn, which are invarian t under simultaneou s translation T : xi  xi + a. 
In other words, it is the space of regular functions on h = Cn/, where  is the diagona l. 
Prop osition 3.47 (C. Dunkl). Let r be a positive integer not divisible by n, and c = r/n. 
Then Mc(C) contains a copy of the reection representation h of Sn, which consists of 
singular vectors (i.e. those killed by y  h). This copy sits in degree r and is spanne d by the 
functions 
dz
r 
n fi(x1,...,xn) = Res[(z  x1)(z  xn)] .
z  xi 
(the symb ol Res denotes the residue at innity). 
Remark 3.48. The space spanned by fi is (n  1)-dimensional, since fi = 0 (this sum i 
is the residue of an exact dieren tial). 
Proof. This proposition can be proved by a straigh tforw ard computati on. The functions fi 
are a special case of Jack polynomials.  
Let Ic be the submo dule of Mc(C) generated by fi. Consider the Hc(n)-mo dule Vc = 
Mc(C)/Ic, and regard it as a C[h]-mo dule. We have the following results. 
Theorem 3.49. Let d =(r, n) denote the greatest common divisor of r and n. Then the 
(set-the oretical) support of Vc is the union of Sn-translates of the subsp aces of Cn/, dene d 
by the equations 
;
x
 ;
...
x(d1) x1 = x2 = = x +1 =  = x2 +1 =  = xn. nn n n 
dd d d
In particular, the Gelfand-Kiril lov dimension of Vc is d  1. 
Corollary 3.50 ([BEG]) . If d =1 then the module Vc is nite dimensional, irreducible, 
admits a BGG type resolution, and its character is 
Vc (g, t)= t(1r)(n1)/2 det |h(1  gtr) . det |h(1  gt) 
Proof. For d = 1 Theorem 3.49 says that the supp ort of Mc(C)/Ic is {0}. This implies that 
Mc(C)/Ic is nite dimensional. The rest follows from Theorem 3.45.  
Proof of Theorem 3.49. The supp ort of Vc is the zero set of Ic, i.e. the common zero set of 
n 
fi. Fix x1, . . . , xn  C. Then fi(x1, . . . , xn) = 0 for all i i ifi = 0 for all i, i.e. 
  i=1 
n n ri n Res (z  xj ) dz =0.
z  xij=1 i=1 
Assume that x1,...xn take distinct values y1,...,yp with positiv e multiplicities m1,...,mp. 
The previous equation implies that the point (x1,...,xn) is in the zero set i 
p p
(z yi) r Res (z  yj )mjn 1 i(z  y1) 
(z  yp)dz =0 i. 
j=1 i=1 
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2. Let G = Sn, h = Cn . In this case there is also only one complex parameter c, and the 
algebra Ht,c is the quotien t of Sn Cx1,...,xn,y1,...,yn by the relations 
[xi,xj ]=[yi,yj ]=0, [yi,xj ]= csij , [yi,xi]= t  csij . 
j=i 
Here CE denotes the free algebra on a set E, and sij is the transp osition of i and j. 
3.2. The PBW theorem for the rational Cherednik algebra. Let us put a ltration 
on Hc by setting deg y = 1 for y  h and deg x = deg g = 0 for x  h,g  G. Let gr(Hc) 
denote the associated graded algebra of Hc under this ltration, and similarly for Ht,c. We 
have a natural surjectiv e homomorphism 
 : CG C[h  h][]  gr(Hc). 
For t  C, it specializes to surjec tive homo morphisms 
t : CG C[h  h]  gr(Ht,c). 
Prop osition 3.5 (The PBW theorem for rational Cherednik algebras) . The maps  and t 
are isomorphisms. 
Proof. The statemen t is equiv alent to the claim that the elemen ts (3.1) are a basis of Ht,c, 
which follows from the proof of Prop osition 3.2.  
Remark 3.6. 1. We have 
H0,0 = CG C[h  h] and H1,0 = CG  D(h). 
2. For any   C, the algebra Ht,c is naturally isomor phic to Ht,c. 
3. The Dunkl operator embedding c specializes to embeddings 
0,c : H0,c  CG C[h  hreg], 
given by x  x, g  g, y  D0, and a
1,c : H1,c  CG  D(hreg), 
given by x  x, g  g, y  Da. So H0,c is generate d by x, g, D0, and H1,c is generat ed by a
x, g, Da. 
Since Dunkl operators map polynomials to polynomials, the map 1,c denes a represen
tation of H1,c on C[h]. This represen tation is called the polynomial representation of H1,c. 
3.3. The spherica l subalgebra. Let e  CG be the symmetrizer, e = |G|1 
gG g. We 
have e 2 = e.
Denition 3.7. Bc := eHce is called the spheric al subalgebr a of Hc. The spherical subalgebra
of Ht,c is Bt,c := Bc/(  t)= eHt,ce.
Note that 
e (CG  D(hreg)) e = D(hreg)G , e (CG C[h reg  h]) e = C[h reg  h]G . 
Therefore, the restriction gives the embeddings: 1,c : B1,c )G, and 0,c : B0,c 
C[h  hreg]G . In particular, we have D(hreg  
Prop osition 3.8. The spheric al subalgebr a B0,c is commutative and does not have zero 
divisors. Also B0,c is nitely gener ated. 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Remark 3.22. More generally ,   h, let G = Stab(), and  be a nite dimensional 
represen tation of G. Then we can dene Mc,(G, h,)= H1,c(G, h) CGSh  , where Sh 
acts on  by . These modules are called the Whittaker modules. 
Let  be irreducible, and let hc() be the number given by the formula
dim h  2cs
hc()= 2  1  s s| . 
sS 
Then we see that h acts on   Smh by the scalar hc()+ m. 
Denition 3.23. A vector v in an H1,c-module M is singular if yiv = 0 for all i. 
Prop osition 3.24. Let U be an H1,c(G, h)-mo dule. Let   U be a G-submo dule consisting 
of singular vectors. Then there is a unique homomorphism  : Mc( ) U of C[h]-mo dules 
such that | is the identity, and it is an H1,c-homomorphism. 
Proof. The rst statemen t follows from the fact that Mc() is a free module over C[h] gen
erated by . Also, it follows from the Frobenius recipro city that there must exist a map  
which is an H1,c-homomorphism. This implies the proposition.  
3.8. Finite length. 
Prop osition 3.25. K  R such that for any M  N in Oc(G, h)0, if M[]= N[] for
Re ()  K, then M = N.
Proof. Let K = max Re hc(). Then if M = N, M/N begins in degree 0 with Re 0 &gt;K,
which is impossible since by Prop osition 3.24, 0 must equal hc() for some .  
Corollary 3.26. Any M Oc(G, h)0 has nite length. 
Proof. Directly from the proposition.  
3.9. Characters. For M Oc(G, h)0, dene the character of M as the following formal 
series in t:  
ch M (g, t)= tTr M[](g) = Tr M (gth),g  G. 
 
Prop osition 3.27. We have 
 (g)thc( ) 
ch Mc( )(g, t)= . deth (1  tg) 
Proof. We begin with the following lemma. 
Lemma 3.28 (MacMahons Master theorem) . Let V be a nite dimensional space, A : V 
V a linear operator. Then 
 1 tnTr (SnA)= . 
n0 det(1  tA) 
Proof of the lemma. If A is diagonalizable, this is obvious. The general statemen t follows by 
continuity.  
1 The lemma implies that Tr Sh (gtD) = where D is the degree operator. This det(1  gt) 
implies the requir ed statemen t.  
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Since i are arbitrary , this is equiv alent to the condition 
p
Res (z  yj )mj nr 1 z idz =0,i =0,...,p  1. 
j=1 
We will now need the following lemma. 
p
Lemma 3.51. Let a(z)= (z yj )j , wher e j  C, j j  Z and j j &gt; p. Supp ose 
j=1 
Resa(z)z idz =0,i =0, 1,...,p  2. 
Then a(z) is a polynomial. 
Proof. Let g(z) be a polynomial. Then 
0=Resd(g(z) a(z)) = Res(g(z)a(z)+ a(z)g(z))dz,  
and hence   
Resg(z)+ j g(z) a(z)dz =0.  z  yji 
Let g(z)= z l (z  yj). Then g(z)+ z  j 
yj g(z) is a polynomi al of degree l + p  1 
j  j  with highest coecien t l + p + j = 0 (as j &gt; p). This means that for every l  0, 
Resz l+p1 a(z)dz is a linear combination of residues of zqa(z)dz with q&lt;l + p  1. By 
the assumption of the lemma, this implies by induction in l that all such residues are 0 and 
hence a is a polynomial.  
In our case (mj r/n  1) = r  p (since mj = n) and the conditions of the lemma are 
p
satised. Hence (x1,...,xn) is in the zero set of Ic i (z  yj)mj nr 1 is a polynomial. This 
j=1 
is equiv alent to saying that all mj are divisible by n/d. 
We have proved that (x1,...,xn) is in the zero set of Ic if and only if (z  x1)(z  xn) 
is the (n/d)-th power of a polynomial of degree d. This implies the theorem.  
Remark 3.52. For c&gt; 0, the above represen tations are the only irreducible nite di
mensional represen tations of H1,c(Sn). Namely , it is proved in [BEG] that the only nite 
dimensional represen tations of H1,c(Sn) are multiples of Lc(C) for c = r/n, and of Lc(C) 
(where C is the sign represen tation) for c = r/n, where r is a positiv e integer relativ ely 
prime to n. 
3.17. Notes. The discussion of the denition of rational Cherednik algebras and their basic 
properties follows Section 7 of [E4]. The discussion of the category O for ration al Cherednik 
algebras follows Section 11 of [E4]. The material in Sections 3.14-3.16 is borrowed from [CE]. 
25</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Indeed, a nonzero map  exists by Prop osition 3.24, and it factors through Lc(G, h,), 
with  being an isomorphism, since Lc(G, h,) is irreducible. Now, by Prop osition 3.24 
(uniqueness of ), the diagram must comm ute up to scaling , which implies the statemen t.  
Prop osition 3.35. Assume that hc()  hc( ) never equals a positive integer for any ,   
IrrepG. Then Oc(G, h)0 is semisimple, with simple objects Mc(). 
Proof. It is clear that in this situation, all Mc() are simple. Also consider Ext1(Mc(),Mc( )). 
If hc()hc() /Z, it is clearly 0. Otherwise, hc()= hc(), and again Ext1(Mc(),Mc()) = 
 0, since for any extension 
0 Mc( ) N   Mc()  0, 
by Prop osition 3.24 we have a splitting Mc() N.  
Remark 3.36. In fact, our argumen t shows that if Ext1(Mc(),Mc()) = 0, then hc() 
hc()  N. 
3.13.	 The matrix of multiplicities. For ,   IrrepG, write  &lt; if 
Re hc()  Re hc()  N. 
Prop osition 3.37. Ther e exists a matrix of integers N =(n, ), with n,  0, such that 
n, =1, n, =0 unless &lt; , and 
Mc()= n, Lc()  K0(Oc(G, h)0). 
Proof. This follows from the Jordan-H older theorem and the fact that objects in Oc(G, h)0 
have nite length.  
Corollary 3.38. Let N1 = (n,). Then 
Lc()= n,Mc(). 
Corollary 3.39. We have 
n,(g)thc( ) 
ch Lc( )(g, t)=	 . deth (1  tg) 
Both of the corollaries can be obtained from the above proposition easily . 
One of the main problems in the represen tation theory of rational Cherednik algebras is 
the following problem. 
Problem: Compute the multiplicities n, or, equiv alently, ch Lc( ) for all . 
In general, this problem is open. 
3.14. Example: the rank 1 case. Let G = Z/mZ and  be an m-th primitiv e root of 1. 
Then the algeb ra H1,c(G, h) is generated by x, y, s with relations 
m1
[y, x]=1  2 cj sj , sxs1 = x, sys1 = 1 y. 
j=1 
Consider the one-dimensional space C and let y actby 0and g  G act by 1. We have 
Mc(C)= C[x]. The contravariant form c,C on Mc(C) is dened by 
n	 nc,C(x ,x n)= an; c,C(x ,x n )=0,n = n. 
21</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rational Cherednik algebras and Hecke algebras for varieties with group actions</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-735-double-affine-hecke-algebras-in-representation-theory-combinatorics-geometry-and-mathematical-physics-fall-2009/resources/mit18_735f09_ch07/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>7.	Rational Cherednik algebras and Hecke algebras for varieties with 
group actions 
7.1. Twisted dieren tial operators. Let us recall the theory of twisted dieren tial oper
ators (see [BB], section 2). 
Let X be a smooth ane algebraic variety over C. Given a closed 2-form  on X, the 
algebra D(X) of dieren tial operators on X twisted by  can be dened as the algebra 
generated by OX and Lie deriv atives Lv, v  Vect(X ), with dening relations 
fLv = Lfv, [Lv,f]= Lvf, [Lv, Lw]= L[v,w] + (v, w). 
This algebra depends only on the cohomology class [] of , and equals the algebra D(X) 
of usual dieren tial operators on X if [] = 0. 
An importan t special case of twisted dieren tial operators is the algebra of dier ential 
operators on a line bundle. Namely , let L be a line bundle on X. Since X is ane, L admits 
an algebraic connection  with curvature , which is a closed 2-form on X. Then it is easy 
to show that the algebra D(X, L) of dieren tial operators on L is isomorphic to D(X). 
If the variety X is smooth but not necessarily ane, then (shea ves of) algebras of twisted 
dieren tial operators are classied by the space H2(X, 1), where 1 is the two-step com-X X 
plex of sheaves 1 
X X 2,cl, given by the De Rham dieren tial acting from 1-forms to closed 
2-forms (sitting in degrees 1 and 2, respectively). If X is projectiv e then this space is 
isomorphic to H2,0(X, C)  H1,1(X, C). We refer the reader to [BB], Section 2, for details. 
Remark 7.1. One can show that D(X) is the universal deformation of D(X) (see [E1]). 
7.2. Some algebraic geometry preliminaries. Let Z be a smooth hypersurface in a 
smooth ane variety X. Let i : ZX be the corresp onding closed embedding. Let 
N denote the normal bundle of Z in X (a line bundle). Let OX (Z) denote the module 
of regular functions on X \ Z which have a pole of at most rst order at Z. Then we 
have a natural map of OX -modules  : OX (Z) iN. Indeed, we have a natural residue 
map  : 1 
X  iOZ (where 1 
is the module of 1-forms), hence a map OX (Z) OX X 
 : OX (Z)  iOZ OX TX = i(TX|Z ) (where TX is the tangen t bundle). The map 
 is obtained by comp osing  with the natura l projection TX|Z  N. 
We have an exact sequence of OX -modules: 
 0 OX OX (Z)  iN 0 
Thus we have a natural surjectiv e map of OX -modules Z : TX OX (Z)/OX . 
7.3. The Cherednik algebra of a variety with a nite group action. We will now 
generalize the denition of Ht,c(G, h) to the global case. Let X be an ane algebraic variety 
over C, and G be a nite group of automo rphisms of X. Let E be a G-invarian t subspace 
of the space of closed 2-forms on X, which projects isomorphically to H2(X, C). Consider 
the algebra G  OT X , where T X is the cotangen t bundle of X. We are going to dene a 
deformation Ht,c,(G, X) of this algebra parametrized by 
(1) compl ex numbers t, 
(2)	G-invarian t function s c on the (nite) set S of pairs s =(Y, g), where g  G, and Y 
is a connected comp onent of the set of xed points Xg such that codimY = 1, and 
(3) eleme nts   EG =H2(X, C)G . 
49</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>sheaf G  DX to X/G (i.e. on X/G, the dependence of the sheaf on the parameters c and 
 disapp ears). This follows from the fact that the line bund les OX (Y ) become trivial when 
restricted to X. 
Now let M be a module over H1,c,,0,G,X which is a locally free coheren t sheaf when 
restricted to X/G. Then the restriction of M to X/G is a G-equiv arian t D-module on 
X which is coheren t and locally free as an O-module. Thus, M corresp onds to a locally 
constan t sheaf (local system) on X/G, which gives rise to a mono drom y represen tation of 
the braid group 1(X/G, x0) (whe re x0 is a base point). This repre sentation will be denoted 
by KZ(M ). This denes a functor KZ, which is analogous to the one in [GGOR]. 
It follows from the theory of D-modules that any OX/G-coheren t H1,c,,0,G,X -module is 
locally free when restricted to X/G. Thus the KZ functor acts from the abelian category 
Cc, of OX/G-coheren t H1,c,,0,G,X -modules to the category of represen tations of 1(X/G, x0). 
It is easy to see that this functor is exact. 
For any Y , let gY be the generator of GY which has eigen value e2i/nY in the conormal 
bundle to Y . Let (c, ) (c, ) be the invertible linear transfo rmation dened by the 
formula 
nY 1 1  e2jmi/nY 
jY =2i(2 c(Y, gYm)1  e2mi/nY  (Y ))/nY . 
m=1 
Prop osition 7.22. The functor KZ maps the category Cc, to the category of representations 
of the algebr a H (c,)(G, X). 
Proof. The result follows from the corresp onding result in the linear case (whic h we have 
already proved) by restricting M to the union of G-translates of a neighborhood of a generic 
point y  Y , and then linearizing the action of GY on this neigh borhood.  
7.10. Proof of Theorem 7.15. Consider the module M = IndGDX OX . Then KZ(M)DX is the regular represen tation of G which is denoted by regG. We want to show that M 
deforms uniquely (up to an isomorphism) to a module over H1,c,0,,G,X for formal c, . The 
obstruction to this deformation is in Ext2 (M, M) and the freedom of this deformation GDX 
is in Ext1 (M, M). Since GDX 
Exti (M, M) = Exti (OX , ResM ) = Exti 
GDX DX DX (OX , OX  CG) 
= Exti (OX , OX )  CG =Hi(X, C)  CG,DX 
and X is simply connecte d, we have 
Ext1 (M, M)=0, and Ext2 (M, M)=0 if H2(X, C)=0.GDX GDX 
Thus such deformation exists and is unique if H2(X, C) = 0. 
Now let Mc, be the deformation. Then KZ(Mc,) is a H (c,)(G, X)-module from Prop o
sition 7.22 and it deforms atly the module regG. This implies H (c,)(G, X) is at over 
C[[ ]]. 
Remark 7.23. When X is not simply connected, the theorem is still true under the as
sumption 2(X)  C = 0 (i.e. H2(  Xis the universal cover of X), and the X, C) = 0, where 
proof is contained in [E1]. 
56</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Theorem 7.13. K is dene d by relations TYnY =1, for all reection hypersurfac es Y (i.e., 
K is the interse ction of all normal subgroups of BG containing TYnY ). 
Proof. See, e.g., [BMR] Prop osition 2.17.  
For any conjugacy class of hypersurfaces Y such that (Y, g) S we introduce formal 
parameters 1Y ,...,nY Y . The entire collection of these parameters will be denoted by . 
Let A0 = C[G]. 
Denition 7.14. We dene the Hecke algebra of (G, X), denoted A = H (G, X, x0), to be 
the quotien t of the group algebra of the braid group, C[BG][[]], by the relations 
nY
(7.3) (T  e 2ji/nY e jY )=0,T  CY 
j=1 
(i.e., by the closed ideal in the formal series topology generated by these relations). 
Thus, A is a deformation of A0. 
It is clear that up to an isomorphism this algebra is indep enden t on the choice of x0, so 
we will sometimes drop x0 form the notation . 
The main result of this section is the following theorem . 
Theorem 7.15. Assume that H2(X, C)=0. Then A = H (G, X) is a at formal defor
mation of A0, which means A = A0[[ ]] as a module over C[[]]. 
Example 7.16. Let h be a nite dimensional vector space, and G be a complex reection 
group in GL(h). Then H (G, h) is the Hecke algebra of G studied in [BMR]. It follows 
from Theorem 7.15 that this Hecke algebra is at. This proof of atness is in fact the same 
as the original proof of this result given in [BMR] (based on the Dunkl-Op dam-Cherednik 
operators, and explained above). 
Example 7.17. Let h be a universal covering of a maximal torus of a simply connected 
simple Lie group G, Q be the dual root lattice, and G= G  Q be its ane Weyl group. 
Then H (h,G) is the ane Hecke algeb ra. This algeb ra is also at by Theorem 7.15. In 
fact, its atness is a well known result from represen tation theory; our proof of atness is 
essen tially due to Cherednik [Ch]. 
Example 7.18. Let G, h,Q be as in the previous example,   C+ be a comple x number 
with a positiv e imaginary part, and G= G  (Q  Q) be the double ane Weyl group. 
Then H (h,G) is (one of the v ersion s of) the double ane Hec ke algebr a of Cherednik ([Ch]), 
and it is at by Theorem 7.15. The fact that this algebra is at was proved by Cherednik, 
Sahi, Noumi, Stokman (see [Ch],[Sa],[NoSt],[St]) using a dieren t approac h (q-deformed 
Dunkl operators). 
7.7. Hecke algebras attac hed to Fuchsian groups. Let H be a simply connected com
plex Riemann surface (i.e., Riemann sphere, Euclidean plane, or Lobac hevsky plane), and  
be a cocompact lattice in Aut(H ) (i.e., a Fuchsian group). Let  = H/. Thenisacom
pact complex Riemann surface. When  contains elliptic elemen ts (i.e., nontrivial elemen ts 
53</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Supp ose  acts on H where H is a simply connected complex Riemann surface as in 
Section 7.7. We have the Hecke algebra of , H (H, ), dened by the same (invertible) 
generators cj and relations 
r
(cj  exp(2 ik/nj )qjk)=0,cj =1, 
k j=1 
where qjk = exp(jk). 
We saw above (Theorem 7.15) that if jks are formal, the algebra H (,H) is at in  if 
|| is innite (i.e., H is Euclidean or hyperbolic). Here is a much stronger non-formal version 
of this theorem. 
Theorem 7.27. The algebr a H (,H) is free as a left module over R := C[q1] if and only  jk 
if (1  1/mj )  2 (i.e., H is Euclide an or hyperbolic). j 
Proof. Let us consider the Coxeter datum: mij , i, j =1,...,r, such that mi,i+1 := mi 
(i  Z/rZ), and mij =  otherwise. Supp ose the corresp onding Coxeter group is W . Then 
wecanseethat  = W+. Notice that the algebra H (,H) for genus 0 orbifolds is the 
algebra A+(W ), i.e., we have H (,H)= A+(W ). 
The condition (1  1/mj )  2 is equiv alent to the condition that W has no nite j 
parab olic subgroups of rank 3. From Theorem 7.26 (ii) and Theorem 7.15, we can see that 
A+(W ) is free as a left module over R. We are done.  
7.15. Notes. Section 7.8 follows Section 6 of the paper [EOR]; Cheredniks denition of the 
double ane Hecke algeb ra of a root system is from Cheredniks book [Ch]; Sections 7.7 and 
7.14 follow the paper [ER]; The other parts of this section follow the paper [E1]. 
61</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Dene also the algebra A+(W ) over R := C[tij,k](tij,k = t1 ) by generators aij , i = jji,k 
(aij ji ), and relation s = a1 
mij
(aij  tij,k)=0 if mij &lt; ,aij ajpapi =1. 
k=1 
If w is a word in letters si, let Tw be the corresp onding elemen t of A(W ). Choose a 
function w(x) which attac hes to every elemen t x  W , a reduced word w(x) represen ting x 
in W . 
Theorem 7.26 (Etingof, Rains, [ER]). (i) The elements Tw(x), x  W , form a spanning 
set in A(W ) as a left R-module. 
(ii)	The elements Tw(x), x  W+, form a spanning set in A+(W ) as a left R-module. 
(iii)	 The elements Tw(x), x  W , are linearly indep endent if W has no nite parabolic 
subgroups of rank 3. 
Proof. We only give the proof of (i). Statemen t (ii) follows from (i). Proof of (iii), which is 
quite nontrivial, can be found in [ER] (it uses the geom etry of constructible sheaves on the 
Coxeter complex of W ). 
Let us write the relation mij
(sisj  tij,k)=0 
k=1 
as a deformed braid relation: 
sj sisj ... + S.L.T. = tij sisj si ... + S.L.T., 
where tij =(1)mij +1tij,1  tij,mij , S.L.T. mean smaller length terms, and the products 
on both sides have length mij . This can be done by multiplying the relation by sisj  (mij 
factors). 
Now let us show that Tw(x) span A(W ) over R. Clearly , Tw for all words w span A(W ). 
So we just need to take any word w and express Tw via Tw(x). 
It is well known from the theory of Coxeter groups (see e.g. [B]) that using the braid 
relations, one can turn any non-reduced word into a word that is not square free, and any 
reduced expression of a given elemen t of W into any other reduced expression of the same 
elemen t. Thus, if w is non-red uced, then by using the deformed braid relations we can reduce 
Tw to a linear combination of Tu with words u of smaller length than w. On the other hand, 
if w is a reduced expression for some element x  W , then using the deform ed braid relations 
we can reduce Tw to a linear combination of Tu with u shorter than w, and Tw(x). Thus Tw(x) 
are a spanning set. This proves (i).  
Thus, A+(W ) is a deformation of C[W +] over R, and similarly A(W ) is a twiste d 
deformation of C[W ]. 
Now let = (m1,...,mr), r  3, be the Fuchsian group dened by generators cj , 
j =1,...,r, with dening relations 
r
c m
j j =1,cj =1. 
j=1 
Here 2  mj &lt; . 
60</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>(2) The construction and main properties of the (shea ves of) Cherednik algebras of alge
braic varieties can be extended without signican t changes to the case when X is a 
complex analytic manifold, and G is not necessarily nite but acts properly discon
tinuously . In the following lectures, we will often work in this generalized setting. 
7.5. Modied Cherednik algebra. It will be convenient for us to use a slight modication 
of the sheaf Ht,c,,G,X . Namely , let  be a function on the set of conjugacy classes of Y such 
that (Y, g) S. We dene Ht,c,,,G,X in the same way as Ht,c,,G,X except that the Dunkl-
Opdam operato rs are dened by the formula 
 2c(Y, g)  
(7.2)	 D := tLv + fY (x) (g  1) + fY (x)(Y ). 
(Y,g)S 1  Y,g Y 
The following result shows that this modication is in fact tautological. Let Y be the class 
in H2(X, 1) dened by the line bundle OX (Y )1, whose sections are funct ions vanishing X 
on Y . 
Prop osition 7.12. One has an isomorphism 
Ht,c,,,G,X  Ht,c,+ P 
Y (Y )Y ,G,X . 
Proof. Let y  Y and z be a function on the formal neigh borhood of y such that z|Y =0 
and dzy = 0. Extend it to a system of local formal coordinates z1 = z, z2,...,zd near y.A 	
Dunkl-Op dam operator near y for the vector eld z can be written in the form 
 1 n12c(Y, gm) mD = z + z (1  m (g  1) + (Y )). 
m=1 Y,g 
Conjugating this operator by the formal expression z(Y ) := (zm)(Y )/m, we get 
n1 1  2c(Y, gm) z (Y )  D  z(Y ) = z + z 1  m (g m  1) 
m=1 Y,g 
This implies the required statemen t.	  
We note that the sheaf H1,c,,0,G,X localizes to G  DX on the complemen t of all the 
hypersurfaces Y . This follows from the fact that the line bundle OX (Y ) is trivial on the 
complemen t of Y . 
7.6. Orbifold Hecke algebras. Let X be a connected and simply connected complex man
ifold, and G is a discrete group of automorphisms of X which acts properly discon tinuously . 
Then X/G is a complex orbifold. Let X  X be the set of points with trivial stabilizer. Fix 
a base point x0  X. Then the braid group of X/G is dened to be BG = 1(X/G, x0). 
We have an exact sequence 1 KBG  G 1.  
Now let S be the set of pairs (Y, g) such that Y is a component of Xg of codimension 1 in 
X (such Y will be called a reection hypersurface). For (Y, g) S, let GY be the subgroup of 
G whose elemen ts act trivially on Y . This group is obviously cyclic; let nY = |GY |. Let CY 
be the conjugacy class in BG corresp onding to a small circle going counterclo ckwise around 
the image of Y in X/G, and TY be a represen tative in CY . 
The following theorem follows from elemen tary topology: 
52</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7.8. Hecke algebra s of wallpap er groups and del Pezzo surfaces. The case when H 
is the Euclidea n plane (i.e.,  is a wallpap er group) deserv es special atten tion. If there are 
elliptic elemen ts, this reduces to the following congurations: g = 0 and 
m =3, (n1,n2,n3) = (3, 3, 3), (2, 4, 4), (2, 3, 6) (cases E6, E7, E8), 
or 
m =4, (n1,n2,n3,n4) = (2, 2, 2, 2) (case D4). 
In these cases, the algebra H (,H) (for numerical ) has Gelfand-Kirillo v dimension 2, 
so it can be interpreted in terms of the theory of noncomm utativ e surfaces. 
Recall that a del Pezzo surface (or a Fano surfa ce) is a smooth projectiv e surface, whose 
anticanonical line bundle is ample. It is known that such surfaces are CP1  CP1, or a blow
up of CP2 at up to 8 generic points. The degree of a del Pezzo surface X is by denition the 
self intersection number KK of its canonical class K. For example, a del Pezzo surface of  
degree 3 is a cubic surface in CP3, and the degree of CP2 with n generic points blown up is 
d =9  n. 
n1Now supp ose  is numerical. Let  = j,k j kj . Also let n be the largest of nj , and c 
be the corresp onding cj . Let e  C[c]  H (,H) be the projector to an eigenspace of c. 
Consider the sphe rical subalgebra B (,H) := eH (,H)e. 
Theorem 7.19 (Etingof, Oblomk ov, Rains, [EOR]). (i) If  =0 then the algebr a B (,H) 
is commutative, and its spectrum is an ane del Pezzo surfac e. More precisely, in 
the case (2, 2, 2, 2), it is a del Pezzo surfac e of degree 3 (a cubic surfac e) with a tri
angle of lines remove d; in the cases (3, 3, 3), (2, 4, 4), (2, 3, 6) it is a del Pezzo surfac e 
of degrees 3,2,1 respectively with a nodal rational curve remove d. 
(ii)	The algebr a B (,H) for  =0 is a quantization of the unique algebr aic symple ctic 
structur e on the surfac e from (i) with Plancks constant . 
Proof. See [EOR].	  
Remark 7.20. In the case (2, 2, 2, 2), H (, ) is the Cherednik-Sahi algebra of rank 1; it 
controls the theory of Askey-Wilson polynomials. 
Example 7.21. This is a multivariate version of the Hecke algebr as attac hed to Fuchsian 
groups, dened in the previous subsection. Namely , letting ,H be as in the previous 
subsection, and N  1, we consider the manifold X = HN with the action of N = SN N . 
If H is a Euclidean or Lobac hevsky plane, then by Theorem 7.15 H (N ,XN ) is a at 
deformation of the group algebra C[N ]. If N&gt; 1, this algebra has one more essen tial 
parameter than for N = 1 (corresp onding to reections in SN ). In the Eucli dean case, one 
expects that an appropriate spherical subalgebra of this algebra is a quan tization of the 
Hilbert scheme of a del Pezzo surface. 
7.9. The Knizhnik -Zamolo dchikov functor. In this subsection we will dene a global 
analog of the KZ functor dened in [GGOR]. This functor will be used as a tool of proof of 
Theorem 7.15. 
Let X be a simply connected complex manifold, and G a discrete group of holomorphic 
transformations of X acting on X properly discon tinuously . Let X  X be the set of points 
with trivial stabilize r. Then we can dene the sheaf of Cherednik algebras H1,c,,0,G,X on 
X/G. Note that the restriction of this sheaf to X/G is the same as the restriction of the 
55</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.735 Double Affine Hecke Algebras in Representation Theory, Combinatorics, Geometry, 
and Mathematical Physics 
Fall 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>of nite order), we are going to regard  as an orbifold: it has special points Pi, i =1,...,m 
with stabilizers Zni . Then  is the orbifold fundamen tal group of .1 
Let g be the genus of , and al,bl,l =1,...,g, be the a-cycles and b-cycles of . Let cj 
be the counterclockwise loops around Pj . Then  is generated by al,bl,cj with relations 
nj b1 cj =1,cm = alblal1 
l . c1c2  
l 
For each j, introduce formal parameters kj , k =1,...,nj . Dene the Hecke algebra H () 
of  to be generated over C[[]] by the same generators al,bl,cj with dening relations 
nj
(cj  e 2ji/nj 
ll e kj )=0,cm = albla1b1 . c1c2  
k=1 l 
Thus H () is a deformation of C[]. 
This deformation is at if H is a Euclidean plane or a Lobac hevsky plane. Indeed, H () = 
H (,H), so the result follows from Theorem 7.15 and the fact that H2(H, C) = 0. 
On the other hand, if H is the Riemann sphere (so that the condition H2(H, C) = 0 is 
violated) and  = 1 then this deformation is not at. Indeed, let   = () be a 1-parameter 
subdeformation of H () which is at. Let us comp ute the determ inant of the product 
c1  cm in the regular represen tation of this algebra (whic h is nite dimensional if H is the 
sphere). On the one hand, it is 1, as c1  cm is a product of comm utators. On the other 
hand, the eigen values of cj in this represen tation are e2ji/nj ekj with multiplicit y ||/nj . 
Computing determinan ts as products of eigen values, we get a nontrivial equation on kj (), 
which means that the deformation H is not at. 
Thus, we see that H () fails to be at in the following forbidden cases: 
g =0,m =2, (n1,n2)=(n, n); 
m =3, (n1,n2,n3) = (2, 2,n), (2, 3, 3), (2, 3, 4), (2, 3, 5). 
Indeed, the orbifold Euler characteristic of a closed surface  of genus g with m special 
points x1,...,xm whose orders are n1,...,nm is 
m 1 orb(,x1,...,xm)=2  2g  m + , nii=1 
and above solutions are the solutions of the inequalit y 
orb(CP 1 ,x1,...,xm) &gt; 0. 
(note that the solutions for m = 1 and solutions (n1,n2) with n1 = n2 dont arise, since they 
dont corresp ond to any orbifolds). 
1Let X be a connected topological space on with a properly discon tinuous action of a discrete group G. 
Then the orbifold fundamen tal group of the orbifold X/G with base point x  X, denoted orb (X/G, x),1 
is the set of pairs (g, ), where g  G and  is a homotop y class of paths leading from x to gx, with 
multiplication law (g1,1)(g2,2)=(g1g2,), where  is 1 followed by g1(2). Obviously , in this situation 
we have an exact sequence 
1 1(X, x) 1orb (X/G, x) G 1.   
54</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>7.11. Example: the simplest case of double ane Hecke algebras. Now let G = 
Z2 Z2 acting on C. Then the conjugacy classes of reection hyperplanes are four points: 
0, 1/2, 1/2+ /2, /2, where we supp ose the lattice in C is Z  Z. Corresp ondingly , the 
presen tation of G is as follows: 
generators: T1,T2,T3,T4; relations: T1T2T3T4 =1,Ti 2 =1. 
Thus, the corresp onding orbifold Hecke algebra is the following deformation of CG: 
generators: T1,T2,T3,T4; relations: T1T2T3T4 =1, (Ti  pi)(Ti  qi)=0, 
where pi,qi (i =1,..., 4), are paramete rs. 
If we renormalize the Ti, these relations turn into 
(Ti  ti)(Ti + t
i 1)=0,T1T2T3T4 = q, 
and we get the type CC1 double ane Hecke algebra. If we set three of the four Tis 
satisfying the undeformed relation Ti 2 = 1, we get the double ane Hecke algebra of type 
A1. More precisely , this algebra is generated by T1,...,T4 with relations 
T22 = T32 = T42 =1, (T1  t)(T 1 + t1)=0,T1T2T3T4 = q. 
Another presen tation of this algebra (whic h is more widely used) is as follows. Let E = 
C/Z2, an elliptic curve with an Z2 action dened by z  z. Dene the partial braid group 
B = orb(E\{0}/Z2,x),1 
where x is a generic point. Notice that compar ing to the usual braid group, we do not 
delete three of the four reection points. The generators of the group 1(E \{0},x) (the 
fundamen tal group of a punctured 2-torus) are X (corresp onding to the a-cycle on the torus), 
Y (corresp onding to the b-cycle on the torus) and C (corresp onding to the loop around 0). In 
order to construct B, which is an extension of Z2 by 1(E \{0},x), we introduce an elemen t 
T s.t. T 2 = C (the half-l oop around the puncture). Then X, Y, T satisfy the following 
relations: 
TXT = X1 ,T 1YT 1 = Y 1 ,Y 1X1Y XT 2 =1. 
The Hecke algebra of the partial braid group is then dened to be the group algebra of B 
plus an extra relation: (T  q1)(T + q2) = 0. 
A common way to presen t this Hecke algebra is to renormalize the generators so that one 
has the following relations: 
TXT = X1,T 1YT 1 = Y 1,Y 1X1Y XT 2 = q, (T  t)(T + t1)=0. 
This is Cheredniks denition for HH(q, t), the double ane Hecke algebra of type A1 which 
depends on two parameters q, t. 
There are two degenerations of the algebra HH(q, t). 
1. The trigonometric degeneration. 
Set Y = ey, q = e , t = ec and T = secs, where s  Z2 is the reection . Then s, X, y 
satisfy the following relations modulo : 
s 2 =1, sXs1 = X1 , sy + ys =2c, X1yX  y =1  2cs. 
The algebra generated by s, X, y with these relations is called the type A1 trigonomet
ric Cherednik algeb ra. It is easy to show that it is isomorphic to the Cheredni k algebra 
H1,c(Z2, C), where Z2 acts on C by zz1 . 
57</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>If all the parameters are zero, this algebra will conicide with G  OT X . 
Let t, c = {c(Y, g)},  EG be variables. Let D/t(X)r be the algebra (over C[t, t1,]) 
of twisted (by /t) dieren tial operators on X with rational coecien ts. 
Denition 7.2. A Dunkl-Op dam operator for (X, G) is an elemen t of D/t(X)r[c] given by 
the formula 
 2c(Y, g)(7.1) D := tLv  1  Y,g  fY (x)  (1  g), 
(Y,g)S 
where Y,g is the eigen value of g on the conormal bundle to Y , v  (X, T X) is a vector 
eld on X, and fY OX (Z) is an elemen t of the coset Y (v) OX (Z)/OX (recall that Y 
is dened in Subsection 7.2). 
Denition 7.3. The algebra Ht,c,(X, G) is the subalgebra of G  D/t(X)r[c] generated 
(over C[t, c, ]) by the function algebra OX , the group G, and the Dunkl-Op dam operators. 
By specializing t, c,  to numerical values, we can dene a family of algebras over C, which 
we will also denote Ht,c,(G, X). Note that when we set t = 0, the term tLv does not become 
0 but turns into the classical momen tum. 
Denition 7.4. Ht,c,(G, X) is called the Cher ednik algebr a of the orbifold X/G. 
Remark 7.5. One has H1,0,(G, X)= G  D(X). Also, if  = 0 then Ht,c, (G, X)= 
Ht,c,(G, X). 
Example 7.6. X = h is a vector space and G is a subgroup in GL(h). Let v be a constan t 
vector eld, and let fY (x)=(Y ,v)/Y (x), where Y  h is a nonzero function al vanishing 
on Y . Then the operator D is just the usual Dunkl- Opdam operator Dv in the complex 
reection case (see Section 2.5). This implies that all the Dunkl-Op dam operators in the 
sense of Denition 7.2 have the form fiDyi + a, where fi  C[h], a  G C[h], and Dyi 
are the usual Dunkl-Op dam operators (for some basis yi of h). So the algebra Ht,c(G, h)= 
Ht,c,0(G, X) is the rational Cherednik algebra for (G, h), see Section 3.1. 
The algebra Ht,c,(G, X) has a ltration F  which is dened on generators by deg(OX )= 
deg(G) = 0, deg(D) = 1 for Dunkl-Op dam operators D. 
Theorem 7.7 (the PBW theorem) . We have 
grF (Ht,c,(G, X)) = G  O(T X)[t, c, ]. 
Proof. Supp ose rst that X = h is a vector space and G is a subgroup in GL(h). Then, as 
we mentioned, Ht,c,(G, h)= Ht,c(G, h) is the rational Cherednik algebra for G, h. So in this 
case the theorem is true. 
Now consider arbitrary X. We have a homomorphism of graded algebras 
 : grF (Ht,c,(G, X))  G  O(T X)[t, c, ] (the principal symbol homomorphism) . 
The homomorphism  is clearly surjectiv e, and our job is to show that it is injectiv e (this 
is the nontrivial part of the proof). In each degree,  is a morphism of nitely generat ed 
OG -modules. Therefore, to check its injectivit y, it suces to check the injectivit y on the 
formal neigh borhood of each point z  X/G. 
Let x be a preimage of z in X, and Gx be the stabilizer of x in G. Then Gx acts on the 
formal neigh borhood Ux of x in X. 
50 X</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>2. The rational degeneration.
In the trigonometric Cherednik algebra, set X = ex and y = y/. y satisfy the
  Then s, x, 
following relations modulo : 
s 2 =1, sx = xs, sys, y =1  2cs. y = yx  x
The algebra generated by s, x, ywith these relations is the rational Cherednik algebra 
H1,c(Z2, C) with the action of Z2 on C is given by z z. 
7.12. Ane and extended ane Weyl groups . Let R = be a root system {} Rn 
with respect to a nondegenera te symmetric bilinear form (, ) on Rn . We will assume that 
R is reduced. Let {i}n
i=1  R be the set of simple roots and R+ (resp ectively R) be the 
set of positiv e (resp ectively negativ e) roots. The coroots are denoted by  =2/(, ). 
Let Q = n
i=1 Z
i be the coroot lattice and P  = n
i=1 Zithe coweight lattice, where 
is are the fundamen tal coweights, i.e., (i,j )= ij . Let  be the maximal positive root, 
and assume that the bilinear form is normalized by the condition (, ) = 2. Let W be the 
Weyl group which is generated by the reections s (  R). 
By denition, the ane root system is 
Ra = {=[, j]  Rn  R| where   R, j  Z}. 
The set of positiv e ane roots is Ra = {[, j] Dene 0 = + | j  Z&gt;0}{[, 0] |   R+}. 
[, 1]. We will identify   R with  =[, 0]  Ra . 
For an arbitrary ane root  =[, j] and a vector z =[z, ]  Rn  R, the corresp onding 
ane reection is dened as follows: 
s(z)= z 2(z, ) = z (z, ). (, ) 
The ane Weyl group W a is generated by the ane reections {s|  R+}, and we have 
an isomorphism: 
= W  Q, W a 
where the transla tion   Q is naturally identied with the comp osition s[,1]s  W a. 
ext Dene the extended ane Weyl group to be W a = W  P  acting on Rn+1 via b(z)= 
ext [z,  (b, z)]for z =[z, ],b  P . Then W a  W . Moreo ver, W a is a normal subgroup of a ext ext W and W /W a = P /Q. The latter group can be identied with the group  = {r} ofa a 
the elemen ts of W ext 
a permuting simple ane roots under their action in Rn+1 . It is a normal 
comm utativ e subgroup of Aut = Aut(Dyna) (Dyna denotes the ane Dynkin diagram). 
The quotien t Aut/ is isomorphic to the group of the automorphisms preserving 0, i.e. the 
group AutDyn of automorphisms of the nite Dynkin diagram. 
7.13. Cheredniks double ane Hecke algebra of a root system. In this subsection, 
we will give an explicit presen tation of Cheredniks DAHA for a root system, dened in 
Example 7.18. This is done by giving an explicit presentation of the corresp onding braid 
group (whic h is called the elliptic braid group), and then imposing quadratic relations on the 
generators corresp onding to reections. 
For a root system R, let m =2 if R is of type D2k, m =1 if R is of type B2k,Ck, and 
otherwise m = . Let mij be the number of edges between vertex i and vertex j in the ||
58</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>ane Dynkin diagram of Ra . Let Xi (i =1,...,n) be a family of pairwise comm utativ e and 
algebraically indep enden t elemen ts. Set 
n n
X[b,j] = Xii qj, where b = ii  P, j  Z/mZ. 
i=1 i=1 
ext For an elemen t w W , we can dene an action on these X[b,j] by wX[b,j] = Xw[b,j].a 
Denition 7.24 (Cherednik) . The double ane Hecke algebr a (DAHA) of the root system 
R, denoted by HH, is an algebra dened over the eld Cq,t = C(q1/m,t1/2), gener ated by 
Ti,i =0, . . . , n, ,Xb,b  P , subject to the following relations: 
(1) TiTj Ti  = Tj TiTj  , mij factors each side; 
(2) (Ti  ti)(Ti + t1)=0 for i =0,...,n;i 
(3) Ti1 = T(i), for    and i =0,...,n; 
(4) Xb1 = X(b), for   ,b  P ; 
(5) TiXbTi = XbX
i 1 , if i&gt; 0 and (b, 
i ) = 1; TiXb = XbTi, if i&gt; 0 and (b, i) = 0; 
(6) T0XbT0 = Xb0 if (b, )= 1; T0Xb = XbT0 if (b, ) = 0. 
Here ti are parameters attac hed to simple ane roots (so that roots of the same length 
give rise to the same parameters). 
The degener ate double ane Hecke algebr a (trigonometric Cher ednik algebr a) HHtrig is 
ext  ngenerated by the group algebra of W a ,  and pairwise comm utativ e yb = i=1(b, )yi + u 
for b =[b, u]  P  Z, with the following relations: 
siyb  ysi(b)si = ki(b, i), for i =1, . . . , n, 
s0yb  ys0(b)s0 = k0(b, ),rybr1 = yr (b) for r  . 
Remark 7.25. This degeneration can be obtained from the DAHA similarly to the case of 
A1, which is describ ed above. 
7.14. Algebraic atness of Hecke algebras of polygonal Fuchsian groups. Let W 
be the Coxeter group of rank r corresp onding to a Coxeter datum: 
mij (i, j =1, . . . , r, i =j), such that 2  mij  and mij = mji. 
So the group W has generators si i =1,...,r, and dening relations 
s 2 
i =1, (sisj )mij =1 if mij =. 
It has a sign character  : W  {1} given by (si)= 1. Denote by W+ the kernel of  
(the even subgroup of W ). It is generated by aij = sisj with relations: 
= a1 mijaij ji ,aij ajkaki =1,aij =1. 
We can deform the group algebra C[W ] as follows. Dene the algebra A(W ) with invertible 
generators si, and tij,k, i, j =1,...,r, k  Zmij for (i, j) such that mij &lt;  and dening 
relations 
tij,k = t1 si 2 =1, [tij,k,tij,k ]=0,sptij,k = tji,ksp,ji,k,
mij
(sisj  tij,k)=0 if mij &lt; . 
k=1 
Notice that if we set tij,k = exp(2ki/mij ), we get C[W ]. 
59</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lemma 7.8. Any action of a nite group on a formal polydisk over C is linearizable. 
Proof. Let D be a formal polydisk over C. Supp ose we have an action of a nite group G 
on D. Then we have a group homomorphism: 
 : G Aut(D ) = GLn(C)  AutU (D),  
where AutU (D) is the group of unipotent automorphisms of D (i.e. those whose derivative 
at the origin is 1), which is a prounip otent algebr aic group. 
Our job is to show that the image of G under  can be conjugated into GLn(C). The 
obstruction to this is in the cohomology group H1(G, AutU (D)), which is trivial since G is 
nite and AutU (D) is prounip otent over C.  
It follows from Lemma 7.8 that it suces to prove the theorem in the linear case, which 
has been accomplished already . We are done.  
Remark 7.9. The following remark is mean t to clarify the proof of Theorem 7.7. In the case 
X = h, the proof of Theorem 7.7 is based, essen tially , on the (fairly nontrivial) fact that the 
usual Dunkl -Opdam operators Dv comm ute with each other. It is therefore very importan t 
to note that in contrast with the linear case, for a general X we do not have any natural 
comm uting family of Dunkl-Op dam operators. Instead, the operators (7.1) satisfy a weaker 
property, which is still sucien t to validate the PBW theorem. This property says that if 
D1,D2,D3 are Dunkl-Op dam operators corresp onding to vector elds v1,v2,v3 := [v1,v2] 
and some choices of the functions fY , then [D1,D2]  D3  G  O(X) (i.e., it has no poles). 
To prove this property, it is sucien t to consider the case when X is a formal polydisk, with 
a linear action of G. But in this case everything follows from the comm utativ ity of the usual 
Dunkl operators Dv. 
Example 7.10. (1) Supp ose G = 1. Then for t = 0, Ht,0,(G, X)= D/t(X). 
(2) Supp ose G is a Weyl group and X = H the corresp onding torus. Then H1,c,0(G, H) 
is called the trigonometric Cher ednik algebr a. 
7.4. Globalization. Let X be any smooth algebraic variety, and G  Aut(X ). Assume 
that X admits a cover by ane G-invarian t open sets. Then the quotien t variety X/G 
exists. 
For any ane open set U in X/G, let U be the preimage of U in X. Then we can 
dene the algebra Ht,c,0(G, U) as above. If U  V , we have an obvious restriction map 
Ht,c,0(G, V ) Ht,c,0(G, U). The gluing axiom is clearly satised. Thus the collection of 
algebras Ht,c,0(G, U) can be extended (by sheacation ) to a sheaf of algebras on X/G. We 
are going to denot e this sheaf by Ht,c,0,G,X and call it the sheaf of Cherednik algebras on 
X/G. Thus, Ht,c,0,G,X (U)= Ht,c,0(G, U). 
Similarly , if   H2(X, 1)G , we can dene the sheaf of twisted Cherednik algebras X 
Ht,c,,G,X . This is done similarly to the case of twisted dieren tial operator s (whic h is the 
case G = 1). 
Remark 7.11. (1) The construction of Ht,c,(G, X) and the PBW theor em extend in a 
straigh tforw ard manner to the case when the ground eld is not C but an algebraically 
closed eld k of positiv e characteristic, provided that the order of the group G is 
relativ ely prime to the characteristic. 
51</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Symplectic reflection algebras</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-735-double-affine-hecke-algebras-in-representation-theory-combinatorics-geometry-and-mathematical-physics-fall-2009/resources/mit18_735f09_ch08/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>product in A is completely determined by the product of elemen ts of A0, which has the form 
of a star-pro duct 
(a, b)= a  b = 0(a, b)+ 1(a, b)+ 2 2(a, b)+  , 
where i : A0  A0  A0 are linear maps, and 0(a, b)= ab. 
8.7.2. Hochschild cohomolo gy. The main tool in deformation theory of associativ e algebras 
is Hochschild cohomology . Let us recall its denition. 
Let A be an associativ e algebra. Let M be a bimo dule over A. A Hochschild n-cochain of 
A with coecien ts in M is a linear map An M. The space of such cochains is denoted 
by Cn(A, M). The dieren tial d : Cn(A, M) 
Cn+1(A, M) is dened by the formula 
df(a1,...,an+1)= f(a1,...,an)an+1  f(a1,...,anan+1)+ f(a1,...,an1an,an+1) 
 +(1)nf(a1a2,...,an+1)+(1)n+1 a1f(a2,...,an+1). 
It is easy to show that d2 = 0. 
Denition 8.16. The Hochschild cohomology HH(A, M) is dened to be the cohomology 
of the complex (C(A, M), d). 
Prop osition 8.17. One has a natur al isomorphism 
HHi(A, M) Exti  Abimo d(A, M), 
wher e Abimo d denotes the category of A-bimo dules.
Proof. The proof is obtained immediately by considering the bar resolution of the bimo dule
A: 
  A  A  A  A  A  A, 
where the bimo dule structure on An is given by 
b(a1  a2  an)c = ba1  a2  anc, 
and the map n : An An1 is given by the formula  
n(a1  a2  ...  an)= a1a2  an  +(1)n a1  an1an. 
Note that we have the associativ e Yoneda product 
HHi(A, M)  HHj (A, N)  HHi+j (A, M A N), 
induced by tensoring of cochains. 
If M = A, the algebra itself, then we will denote HH(A, M) by HH(A). For example, 
HH0(A) is the center of A, and HH1(A) is the quotien t of the Lie algebra of deriv ations of A 
by inner deriv ations. The Yoneda product induces a graded algebra structure on HH(A); it 
can be shown that this algebr a is supercomm utativ e. 
67</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Now, we claim that if Z, M are positiv ely ltered and grM is a Cohen-Macaula y grZ
module then M is a Cohen-Macaula y Z-module. Indeed, let z1,...,zn be homogeneous 
algebraically indep enden t elemen ts of grZ such that grZ is a nite module over the subalge
bra generated by them. Let z1,...,znbe their liftings to Z. Then z1,...,znare algebraically 
indep enden t, and the module M over C[z1,...,zn] is nitely generated and (locally) free since 
so is the module grM over C[z1,...,zn]. 
Recall now that grH0,ce = SV , grZ0,c =(SV )G . Thus the c = 0 case implies the genera l 
case, and we are done. 
Now let us show that any Azuma ya point of Mc is smooth. Let U be an ane open set 
in Mc consisting of Azuma ya points. Then the localization H0,c(U) := H0,c Z0,c OU is an 
Azuma ya algebra. Moreo ver, for any   U, the unique irreducible represen tation of H0,c(U) 
with central character  is the regular represen tation of G (since this holds for generic  by 
Prop osition 8.24). This means that e is a rank 1 idemp otent in H0,c(U)/ for all . In 
particular, H0,c(U)e is a vector bundle on U. Thus the functor F : OU -mod H0,c(U)-mo d 
given by the formula F (Y )= H0,c(U)e OU Y is an equiv alence of categories (the quasi-
inverse functor is given by the formula F 1(N)= eN). Thus H0,c(U) is Morita equiv alent 
to OU , and therefore their homological dimensions are the same. 
On the other hand, the homological dimension of H0,c is nite (in fact, it equals to dim V ). 
To show this, note that by the Hilbert syzygies theorem, the homologic al dimension of 
SV is dim V . Hence, so is the homological dimension of G  SV (as Ext (M, N)= GSV 
Ext 
SV (M, N)G). Thus, since grH 0,c = G  SV , we get that H0,c has homological dimension 
 dim V . Hence, the homological dimension of H0,c(U) is also  dim V (as the homological 
dimension clearly does not increase under the localization). But H0,c(U) is Morita equiv alent 
to OU , so OU has a nite homological dimension. By Theorem 8.43, this implies that U 
consists of smooth points. 
Corollary 8.44. Az(Mc) is also the set of points at which the Poisson structur e of Mc is 
symple ctic. 
Proof. The variety Mc is symplectic outside of a subset of codimension 2, because so is M0. 
Thus the set S of smooth points of Mc where the top exterior power of the Poisson bivector 
vanishe s is of codimension  2. Since the top exterior power of the Poisson bivector is locally 
a regular function, this implies that S is empty. Thus, every smooth point is symplectic, and 
the corollary follows from the theorem.  
8.13. Notes. Our exposition in this section follows Section 8  Section 10 of [E4]. 
75</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Theorem 8.27. Let G = Sn, V = h  h, h = Cn (the rational Cher ednik algebr a for Sn). 
Then for c =0, every irreducible representation of H0,c has dimension n! and is isomorphic 
to the regular representation of Sn. 
Proof. Let E be an irreducible represen tation of H0,c. Let us calculate the trace in E of any 
permutation  = 1. Let j be an index such that (j)= i = j. Then sij (j)= j. Hence in 
H0,c we have 
[yj ,xisij ]=[yj,xi]sij  = csij 2  = c. 
Hence Tr E () = 0, and thus E is a multiple of the regular represen tation of Sn. But by 
Theorem 8.25, dim E  n!, so we get that E is the regular represen tation, as desired.  
8.10. Azuma ya algebras. Let Z be a nitely generated comm utativ e algebra over C, M = 
SpecZ the corresp onding ane scheme, and A a nitely generated Z-algebra. 
Denition 8.28. A is said to be an Azuma ya algebra of degree N if the completion A of 
A at every maximal ideal  in Z is the matrix algebra of size N over the completion Z of 
Z. 
Thus, an Azuma ya algebra should be though t of as a bund le of matrix algebras on M. 5 
For example, if E is an algebraic vector bundle on M then End(E ) is an Azuma ya algebra. 
However, not all Azuma ya algebras are of this form. 
Example 8.29. For q  C, consider the quan tum torus 
Tq = CX1,Y 1/XY  qY X. 
If q is a root of unity of order N, then the center of Tq is XN ,Y N  = C[M ] where 
M =(C)2 . It is not dicult to show that Tq is an Azuma ya algebra of degree N, but 
Tq C[M] C(M ) = MatN (C(M )), so Tq is not the endomorphism algebra of a vector bundle. 
Example 8.30. Let X be a smooth irreducible variety over a eld of characteristic p. Then 
D(X), the algebra of dieren tial operators on X, is an Azuma ya algebra with rank pdim X , 
which is not an endomo rphism algebra of a vector bundle. Its center is Z = O(T X)F, the 
Frobenius twisted functions on T X. 
It is clear that if A is an Azuma ya algebra (say, over C) then for every central character 
 of A, A/ is the algebra MatN (C) of complex N by N matrices, and every irreducible 
represen tation of A has dimension N. 
The following importan t result is due to M. Artin. 
Theorem 8.31. Let A be a nitely gener ated (over C) polynomial identity (PI) algebr a of 
degree N (i.e. all the polynomial relations of the matrix algebr a of size N are satise d in 
A). Then A is an Azumaya algebr a if and only if every irreducible representation of A has 
dimension exactly N. 
Proof. See [Ar] Theorem 8.3.  
5If M is not ane, one can dene, in a standard mann er, the notion of a sheaf of Azuma ya algebras on 
M. 
72</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>deformations will be a closed subsc heme of the formal neighborhood of zero in H, which 
is often singular. On the other hand, even when HH3(A0)=0, the universal deforma tion 
parametrized by (the formal neigh borhood of zero in) H may exist (although its existence 
may be more dicult to prove than in the vanishing case). In this case one says that the 
deformations of A0 are unobstructed (since all obstructions vanish even though the space of 
obstructions doesnt). 
8.8. Deformation-theoretic interpretation of symplectic reection algebras. Let V 
be a symplectic vector space (over C) and Weyl(V ) the Weyl algebra of V . Let G be a nite 
group acting symplectically on V . Then from the denition, we have 
A0 := H1,0[G, V ]= G  Weyl(V ). 
Let us calculate the Hochschild cohomology of this algebra. 
Theorem 8.18 (Alev, Farinati, Lambre, Solotar, [AFLS]). The cohomolo gy space 
HHi(G  Weyl(V )) is natur ally isomorphic to the space of conjugation invariant functions 
on the set Si of elements g  G such that rank (1  g)|V = i. 
Corollary 8.19. The odd cohomolo gy of G  Weyl(V ) vanishes, and HH2(G  Weyl(V )) 
is the space C[S]G of conjugation invariant functions on the set of symple ctic reections. In 
particular, there exists a universal deformation A of A0 = G  Weyl(V ) parametrize d by 
C[S]G . 
Proof. Directly from the theorem.  
Proof of Theorem 8.18. 
Lemma 8.20. Let B be a C-algebr a together with an action of a nite group G. Then 
HH(G  B, G  B)=( HH(B, Bg))G , 
gG 
wher e Bg is the bimo dule isomorphic to B as a space wher e the left action of B is the usual 
one and the right action is the usual action twiste d by g. 
Proof. The algebra G  B is a projectiv e B-module. Therefore, using the Shapiro lemma, 
we get 
HH(G  B, G  B) = Ext 
(GG)(BBop)(G  B, G  B) 
= Ext (B, G  B) = Ext (B, G  B)G 
Gdiagonal(BBop) BBop 
= ( Ext 
BBop (B, Bg))G =( HH(B, Bg))G , 
gG gG 
as desired.  
Now apply the lemma to B =Weyl(V ). For this we need to calculate HH(B, Bg), 
where g is any elemen t of G. We may assume that g is diagonal in some symplectic basis: 
g = diag(1,11,...,n,n1). Then by the Kunneth formula we nd that 
n
HH(B, Bg)= HH(A1, A1gi), 
i=1 
69</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>this bivector is homogeneous, it must have degree 2, and if it has degree 2 then it 
must be with constan t coecien ts, so being G-invarian t, it is a multiple of . The lemma is 
proved.  
Now, for each t, c we have a natural Poisson bracket on A0 of degree 2, which depends 
linearly on t, c. So by the lemma, this bracket has to be of the form f(t, c), where  is the 
unique up to scaling Poisson bracket of degree 2, and f a homogeneous linear function. 
Thus the algebra A = Bt,c is not comm utativ e unless f(t, c) = 0. On the other hand, if 
f(t, c) = 0, and Bt,c is not comm utativ e, then, as weve shown, A0 has a nonzero Poisson 
bracket of degree &lt; 2. But By Lemma 8.11, there is no such brackets. So Bt,c must be 
comm utativ e if f(t, c) = 0. 
It remains to sho w that f(t, c) is in fact a nonzero multiple of t. First note that f(1, 0) = 0, 
since B1,0 is denit ely noncomm utativ e. Next, let us take a point (t, c) such that Bt,c is 
comm utativ e. Look at the Ht,c-module Ht,ce, which has a comm uting action of Bt,c from the 
right. Its associated graded is SV as an (CG  SV, (SV )G)-bimo dule, which implies that 
the generic ber of Ht,ce as a Bt,c-module is the regular represen tation of G. So we have a 
family of nite dimensional represen tations of Ht,c on the bers of Ht,ce, all realized in the 
regular represen tation of G. Computing the trace of the main comm utation relation (8.1) of 
Ht,c in this represen tation , we obtain that t = 0 (since Tr (s) = 0 for any reection s). The 
proposition is proved.  
Note that B0,c has no zero divisors, since its associated graded algebra (SV )G does not. 
Thus, like in the Cher ednik algebra case, we can dene a Poisson variety Mc, the spectrum 
of B0,c, called the Calogero-Moser space of G, V . Moreo ver, the algebra Bc := B,c over C[] 
is an algebraic quan tization of Mc. 
8.6. The center of the symplectic reection algebra Ht,c. Consider the bimo dule Ht,ce, 
which has a left action of Ht,c and a right comm uting action of Bt,c. It is obvious that 
End Ht,c Ht,ce = Bt,c (with opposite product). The following theorem shows that the bimo dule 
Ht,ce has the double centralizer property (i.e., End Bt,c Ht,ce = Ht,c). 
Note that we have a natural map t,c : Ht,c  End Bt,c Ht,ce. 
Theorem 8.12. t,c is an isomorphism for any t, c. 
Proof. The complete proof is given [EG]. We will give the main ideas of the proof skippin g 
straigh tforw ard technical details. The rst step is to show that the result is true in the 
graded case, (t, c) = (0, 0). To do so, note the following easy lemma: 
Lemma 8.13. If X is an ane complex algebr aic variety with algebr a of functions OX and 
G a nite group acting freely on X then the natural map X : G  OX  EndOX OX is an G 
isomorphism. 
Therefore, the map 0,0 : G  SV End (SV )G (SV ) is injectiv e, and moreo ver becomes an 
isomorphism after localization to the eld of quotien ts C(V )G . To show its surjectiv e, take 
a  End (SV )G (SV ). There exists a  G C(V ) which maps to a. Moreo ver, by Lemma 
8.13, a can have poles only at xed points of G on V . But these xed points form a subset 
of codimension  2, so there can be no poles and we are done in the case (t, c) = (0, 0). 
Now note that the algebra End Bt,c Ht,ce has an increasing integer ltration (bounded be
low) induced by the ltration on Ht,c. This is due to the fact that Ht,ce is a nitely generated 
65</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>where A1 is the Weyl algebra of the 2-dimensional space, (generated by x, y with dening 
relation xy  yx = 1), and gi = diag(i,1).i 
Thus we need to calculate HH(B, Bg), B = A1, g = diag(, 1). 
Prop osition 8.21. HH(B, Bg) is 1-dimensional, concentrated in degree 0 if  =1 and in 
degree 2 otherwise. 
Proof. If B = A1 then B has the following Koszul resolution as a B-bimo dule: 
B  B  B  C2  B  B  B  B. 
Here the rst map is given by the formula 
b1  b2  b1  x  yb2  b1  y  xb2  b1y  x  b2 + b1x  y  b2, 
the second map is given by 
b1  x  b2  b1x  b2  b1  xb2,b1  y  b2  b1y  b2  b1  yb2, 
and the third map is the multiplication . 
Thus the cohomology of B with coecien ts in Bg can be computed by mapping this 
resolution into Bg and taking the cohomology . This yields the following complex C: 
(8.2) 0 Bg Bg  Bg Bg 0,   
where the rst nontrivial map is given by bg  [bg, y]  x  [bg, x]  y, and the second 
nontrivial map is given by bg  x  [x, bg], bg  y  [y, bg]. 
Consider rst the case g = 1. Equip the complex C with the Bernstein ltra tion (deg(x)= 
deg(y) = 1), starting with 0, 1, 2, for C0,C1,C2, respectively (this makes the dieren tial 
preserv e the ltratio n). Consider the associated graded complex C . In this complex, gr
brackets are replace d with Poisson brackets, and thus it is easy to see that C is the De gr 
Rham complex for the ane plane, so its cohomology is C in degree 0 and 0 in other degrees. 
Therefore, the cohomology of C is the same. 
Now consider g = 1. In this case, declare that  C0,C1,C2 start in degrees 2,1,0 respectively 
(whic h makes the dieren tial preserv e the ltration), and again consider the graded complex 
C . The graded Euler characteristic of this complex is (t2  2t + 1)(1  t)2 = 1. gr
The cohomolog y in the C0 term is the set of b  C[x, y] such that ab = bag for all a. Thisgr 
means that HH0 = 0. 
gThe cohomology of the C2 term is the quotien t of C[x, y] by the ideal generated by a  agr , 
a  C[x, y]. Thus the cohom ology HH2 of the rightmost term is 1-dimensional, in degree 0. 
By the Euler characteristic argum ent, this implies that HH1 = 0. The cohomology of the 
ltered complex C is therefore the same, and we are done.  
The proposition implies that in the n-dim ensional case HH(B, Bg) is 1-dimen sional, con
centrated in degree rank (1  g). It is not hard to check that the group G acts on the sum 
of these 1-dimension al spaces by simply permuting the basis vectors. Thus the theorem is 
proved.  
Remark 8.22. Another proof of Theorem 8.18 is given in [Pi]. 
Theorem 8.23. The algebr a H1,c[G, V ], with formal c, is the universal deformation of 
H1,0[G, V ]= G  Weyl(V ). More specically, the map f : C[S]G  HH2(G  Weyl(V )) 
induc ed by this deformation coincides with the isomorphism of Corollary 8.19. 
70</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.735 Double Affine Hecke Algebras in Representation Theory, Combinatorics, Geometry, 
and Mathematical Physics 
Fall 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Thus, by Theorem 8.27, for G = Sn, the rational Cherednik algebra H0,c(Sn, Cn) for c =0 
is an Azuma ya algebra of degre e n!. Indeed, this algebra is PI of degree n! because the clas
sical Dunkl represen tation embeds it into matrices of size n! over C(x1,...,xn,p1,...,pn)Sn . 
Let us say that   M is an Azuma ya point if for some ane neigh borhood U of  the 
localization of A to U is an Azuma ya algebra. Obviously , the set Az(M) of Azuma ya points 
of M is open. 
Now we come back to the study the space Mc corresp onding to a symplectic reection 
algebra H0,c. 
Theorem 8.32. The set Az(Mc) coincides with the set of smooth points of Mc. 
The proof of this theorem is given in the following two subsections. 
Corollary 8.33. If G = Sn and V = h  h, h = Cn (the rational Cher ednik algebr a case) 
then Mc is a smooth algebr aic variety for c =0. 
Proof. Directly from the above theorem.  
8.11. Cohen-Macaula y prop erty and homological dimension. To prove Theorem 8.32, 
we will need some commutativ e algebra tools. Let Z be a nitely generated comm utative 
algebra over C without zero divisors. By Noethers normalization lemma, there exist ele
ments z1,...,zn  Z which are algebraically independen t, such that Z is a nitely generated 
module over C[z1,...,zn]. 
Denition 8.34. The algebra Z (or the variety SpecZ) is said to be Cohen-Macaula y if Z 
is a locally free (=projectiv e) module over C[z1,...,zn]. 6 
Remark 8.35. It was shown by Serre that if Z is locally free over C[z1,...,zn] for some 
choice of z1,...,zn, then it happ ens for any choice of them (such that Z is nitely generated 
as a module over C[z1,...,zn]). 
Remark 8.36. Another denition of the Cohen-Macaula y property is that the dualizing 
complex Z  of Z is concen trated in degree zero. We will not discuss this denition here. 
It can be shown that the Cohen-Macaula y property is stable under localization. Therefore, 
it makes sense to make the following denition. 
Denition 8.37. An algebraic variety X is Cohe n-Macaula y if the algebra of functio ns on 
every ane open set in X is Cohen-Macaula y. 
Let Z be a nitely generated comm utativ e algebra over C without zero divisors, and let 
M be a nitely generated module over Z. 
Denition 8.38. M is said to be Cohen-Macau lay if for some algebraic ally independen t 
z1,...,zn  Z such that Z is nitely generated over C[z1,...,zn], M is locally free over 
C[z1,...,zn]. 
Again, if this happ ens for some z1,...,zn, then it happ ens for any of them. We also 
note that M can be Cohen-Macau lay without Z being Cohen-Macaula y, and that Z is a 
Cohen-Macaula y algebra i it is a Cohen -Macaula y module over itself. 
We will need the following standard properties of Cohen-Macaula y algebras and modules. 
6It was proved by Quillen that a locally free module over a polynomial algebra is free; this is a dicult 
theorem, which will not be needed here. 
73</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Theorem 8.6. Let  : 2V  C[G] be a linear G-equivariant function. Dene the algebr a 
H to be the quotient of the algebr a C[G]T(V ) by the relation [x, y]= (x, y), x, y  V . Put 
an increasing ltration on H by setting deg(V )=1, deg(G)=0, and dene  : CG  SV  
grH to be the natur al surje ctive homomorphism. Then  is an isomorphism if and only if  
has the form 
(x, y)= t(x, y)  2 css(x, y)s, 
sS 
for some t  C and G-invariant function c : S C. 
Unfortunately , for a general symple ctic reection algebra we dont have a Dunkl operator 
represen tation, so the proof of the more dicult if part of this Theorem is not as easy 
as the proof of Prop osition 3.5. Instead of explicit compu tations with Dunkl operators, it 
makes use of the deformation theory of Koszul algebras, which we will now discuss. 
8.3. Koszul algebras. Let R be a nite dimensional semisimple algebra (over C). Let A 
be a Z+-graded algebra, such that A[0] = R, and assume that the graded comp onents of A 
are nite dimen sional. 
Denition 8.7. (i) The algebra A is said to be quadratic if it is generated over R by 
A[1], and has dening relations in degree 2. 
(ii) A is Koszul if all eleme nts of Exti(R, R) (where R is the augmen tation module over 
A) have grade degree precisely i. 
Remark 8.8. (1) Thus, in a quadratic algebra, A[2] = A[1] R A[1]/E, where E is the 
subspace (R-subbimo dule) of relations. 
(2) It is easy to show	that a Koszul algebra is quadra tic, since the condition to be 
quadratic is just the Koszulit y condition for i =1, 2. 
Now let A0 be a quadratic algebra, A0[0] = R. Let E0 be the space of relations for A0. Let 
E  A0[1] R A0[1][[]] be a free (over C[[]]) R-subbimo dule which reduces to E0 modulo  
(deformation of the relations). Let A bethe (-adically complete) algebra generated over 
R[[]] by A[1] = A0[1][[]] with the space of dening relation s E. Thus A is a Z+-graded 
algebra. 
The following very importan t theorem is due to Beilinson, Ginzburg, and Soergel, [BGS] 
(less general versions appeared earlier in the works of Drinfeld [Dr], Polishc huk-Positselski 
[PP], Braverman-Gaitsgory [BG]). We will not give its proof. 
Theorem 8.9 (Koszul deformation principle) . If A0 is Koszul then A is a topologically free 
C[[]] module if and only if so is A[3]. 
Remark. Note that A[i] for i&lt; 3 are obviously topologically free. 
We will now apply this theorem to the proof of Theorem 8.6. 
8.4. Proof of Theorem 8.6. Let  : 2V C[G] be a linear G-equiv arian t map. We write 
(x, y)=  
gG g(x, y)g, where g(x, y)  
2V . To apply Theorem 8.9, let us homogenize 
our algebras. Namely , let A0 =(CG  SV )  C[u] (where u has degree 1). Also let  be a 
formal parameter, and consider the deformation A = Hu2 of A0. That is, A is the quotien t 
of G  T(V )[u][[]] by the relations [x, y]= u2(x, y). This is a deformation of the type 
considered in Theorem 8.9, and it is easy to see that its atness in  is equiv alent to Theorem 
63</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>eHt,ce-mo dule (since it is true in the associated graded situat ion, by Hilberts theorem about 
invarian ts). Also, the natural map grEnd Bt,c Ht,ce End grBt,c grHt,ce is clearly injectiv e. 
Therefore, our result in the case (t, c) = (0, 0) implies that this map is actually an iso
morphism (as so is its composition with the associated graded of t,c). Identifying the two 
algebras by this isomorphism, we nd that gr(t,c)= 0,0. Since 0,0 is an isomorphism, t,c 
is an isomorphism for all t, c, as desired. 2  
Denote by Zt,c the center of the symplectic reection algebr a Ht,c. We have the following 
theorem. 
Theorem 8.14. If t =0, the center of Ht,c is trivial. If t =0, we have grZ0,c = Z0,0. In 
particular, H0,c is nitely gener ated over its center. 
Proof. The t = 0 case was proved by Brown and Gordon [BGo] as follows. If t = 0, we have 
grZt,c  Z0,0 =(SV )G . Also, we have a map 
t,c : Zt,c  Bt,c = eHt,ce,z  ze = eze. 
The map t,c is injectiv e since gr(t,c) is injectiv e. In particular, the image of gr(t,c) is 
contained in Z(Bt,c), the center of Bt,c. Thus it is enough to show that Z(Bt,c) is trivial. To 
show this, note that grZ(Bt,c) is contained in the Poisson center of B0,0 which is trivial. So 
Z(Bt,c) is trivial. 
Now supp ose t = 0. We need to show that gr( 0,c) : gr(Z0,c) Z0,0 is an isomorphism. It 
suces to show that 0,c is an isomorphism. To show this, we construct 0
,c 1 : B0,c  Z0,c as 
follows. 
For any b  B0,c, since B0,c is comm utativ e, we have an elemen t b  End B0,c (H0,ce) which 
is dened as the right multiplication by b. From Theorem 8.12, b  H0,c. Moreo ver, b  Z0,c 
since it comm utes with H0,c as a linear operator on the faithful H0,c-module H0,ce. Sob  Z0,c. 
It is easy to see that be = b. So we can set b = 0
,c 1(b) which denes the inverse map to 
0,c.  
8.7. A review of deformation theory. Now we would like to explain that symple ctic 
reection algebras are the most general deformations of algebras of the from G  Weyl(V ). 
Before we do so, we give a brief review of classical deformation theory of associativ e algebras. 
8.7.1. Formal deformations of associative algebr as. Let A0 be an associativ e algebra with 
unit over C. Denote by 0 the multiplication in A0. 
Denition 8.15. A (at) formal n-parameter deformation of A0 is an algebra A over 
C[[]] = C[[ 1,..., n]] which is topologically free as a C[[]]-mo dule, together with an 
algebra isomo rphism 0 : A/mA  A0 where m = 1,..., n is the maximal ideal in C[[]]. 
When no confusion is possible, we will call A a deformation of A0 (omitting formal). 
Let us restrict ourselv es to one-parameter deformatio ns with parameter . Let us choose 
an identication  : AA0[[]] as C[[]]-mo dules, such that  = 0 modulo . Then the  
2Here we use the fact that the ltration is bounded from below. In the case of an unbounded ltration, 
it is possible for a map not to be an isomorphism if its associated graded is an isomorphism. An example of 
this is the operator of multiplication by 1 + t1 in the space of Lauren t polynomials in t, ltered by degree . 
66</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Proof. The proof (whic h we will not give) can be obtained by a direct computation with the 
Koszul resolution for G  Weyl(V ). Such a proof is given in [Pi]. The paper [EG] proves 
a slightly weaker statemen t that the map f is an isomorphism, which suces to show that 
H1,c(G, V ) is the universal deformation of H1,0[G, V ].  
8.9. Finite dimensional represen tations of H0,c. Let Mc = SpecZ0,c. We can regard 
H0,c = H0,c[G, V ] as a nitely generated module over Z0,c = O(Mc). Let   Mc be a central 
character,  : Z0,c  C. Denote by  the ideal in H0,c generated by the kernel of . 
Prop osition 8.24. If  is generic then H0,c/ is the matrix algebr a of size |G|. In par
ticular, H0,c has a unique irreducible representation V with central character . This repre
sentation is isomorphic to CG as a G-mo dule. 
Proof. It is shown by a standard argumen t (whic h we will skip) that it is sucient to check 
the statemen t in the associated graded case c = 0. In this case, for generic , G  SV/ = 
G  Fun(O), where O is the (free) orbit of G consisting of the points of V  that map to 
  V /G, and Fun(O) is the algebra of functions on O. It is easy to see that this algebra 
is isomorphic to a matrix algebra, and has a unique irreducible represen tation, Fun(O), 
which is a regular represen tation of G.  
Corollary 8.25. Any irreducible representation of H0,c has dimension |G|. 
Proof. We will use the following lemma. 
Lemma 8.26 (The Amitsur-Levitzki identity). For any N  N matric es X1,...,X2N with 
entries in a commutative ring A, 
(1)X(1)  X(2N ) =0. 
S2n 
Proof. Consider the ring MatN (A) (1,...,2n). Let X = i Xii  R. So we have 
X2 = [Xi,Xj ]ij  MatN (A even(1,...,2n)). 
i&lt;j 
It is obvious that Tr X2 = 0. Similarly , one can easily show that Tr X4 =0,..., Tr X2N = 0. 
Since the ring A even(1,...,2n) is comm utativ e, from the Cayley-Hamilton theorem, we 
know that X2N = 0 which implies the lemma.  
Since for generic  the algebra H0,c/ is a matrix algebra, the algebra H0,c satises the 
Amitsur-Levitzki identity. Next, note that since H0,c is a nitely generated Z0,c-module (by 
passing to the associated graded and using Hilberts theore m), every irreducib le represen ta
tion of H0,c is nite dimensional. If H0,c had an irreducible represen tation E of dimension 
m&gt; |G|, then by the densit y theorem the matrix algebra Matm would be a quotien t of 
H0,c. But one can show that the Amitsur-Levitzki identity of degree |G| is not satised for 
matrices of bigger size than |G|. Contradiction. Thus, dim E |G|, as desired.  
In general, for special central characters there are represen tations of H0,c of dimension less 
than |G|. However, in some cases one can show that all irreducible represen tations have 
dimension exactly G. For example, we have the following result. ||
71</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>8.6. Also, the algebra A0 is Koszul, because the polynomial algebra SV is a Koszul algebra. 
Thus by Theorem 8.9, it suces to show that A is at in degree 3. 
The atness conditi on in degree 3 is the Jacobi identity 
[(x, y),z]+[(y, z),x]+[(z, x),y]=0, 
which must be satised in CG  V . In comp onents, this equat ion transforms into the system 
of equations 
g(x, y)(z  zg)+ g(y, z)(x  xg)+ g(z, x)(y  yg)=0 
for every g  G (here zg denotes the result of the action of g on z). 
This equation, in partic ular, implies that if x, y, g are such that g(x, y) = 0 then for any 
g g g
z  Vz  zis a linear combination of x  xand y  y. Thus g(x, y) is identically zero 
unless the rank of (1  g)|V is at most 2, i.e. g =1 or g is a symplectic reection. 
If g = 1 then g(x, y) has to be G-invarian t, so it must be of the form t(x, y), where 
t  C. 
If g is a symplectic reect ion, then g(x, y) must be zero for any x such that x  xg = 0. 
Indeed, if for such an x there had existed y with g(x, y) = 0 then z  zg for any z would 
be a multiple of y  yg, which is impossible since Im(1  g)|V is 2-dimensional. This implies 
that g(x, y)=2cgg(x, y), and cg must be invarian t. 
Thus we have shown that if A is at (in degree 3) then  must have the form given in 
Theorem 8.6. Conversely , it is easy to see that if  does have such form, then the Jacobi 
identity holds. So Theorem 8.6 is proved. 
8.5. The spherical subalgebra of the symplectic reection algebra. The properties of 
symplectic reection algebras are similar to the properties of rational Chered nik algebras we 
have studied before. The main dierence is that we no longer have the Dunkl represen tation 
and localizati on results, so some proofs are based on dieren t ideas and are more complicated. 
The spherical subalgebra of the symplectic reection algebra is dened in the same way 
as in the Cherednik algebra case. Namely , let e = |G|1 
gG g, and Bt,c = eHt,ce. 
Prop osition 8.10. Bt,c is commutative if and only if t =0. 
Proof. Let A be a Z+-ltered algebra. If A is not comm utativ e, then we can dene a nonzero 
Poisson bracket on grA in the following way. Let m be the minim um of deg(a) + deg(b) 
deg([a, b]) (over a, b  A such that [a, b] = 0). Then for homogeneous elemen ts  a0,b0  A0 of 
degrees p, q, we can dene {a0,b0} to be the image in A0[p + q  m] of [a, b], where a, b are 
any lifts of a0,b0 to A. It is easy to check that { , } is a Poisson bracket on A0 of degree 
m. 
Let us now apply this construction to the ltered algebra A = Bt,c. We have gr(A) = 
A0 =(SV )G . 
Lemma 8.11. A0 has a unique, up to scaling, Poisson bracket of degree 2, and no nonzer o 
Poisson brackets of degrees &lt; 2. 
Proof. A Poisson bracket on (SV )G is the same thing as a Poisson bracket on the variety 
V /G. On the smooth part (V /G)s of V /G, it is simply a bivector eld, and we can lift 
it to a bivector eld on the preimage Vs  of (V /G)s in V , which is the set of points in V 
with trivial stabilizers. But the codimension on V  \ Vs  in V  is 2 (as V  \ Vs  is a union 
of symp lectic subspaces), so the bivector on Vs  extends to a regul ar bivector on V . So if 
64</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>8.7.3. Hochschild cohomolo gy and deformations. Let A0 be an algebra, and let us look for 
1-parameter deformations A = A0[[]] of A0. Thus, we look for such series  which satisfy 
the associativit y equation, modulo the automorphisms of the C[[]]-mo dule A0[[]] which are 
the identity modulo . 3 
The associativit y equation  (  Id) =  (Id  ) reduces to a hierarc hy of linear 	
equations: 
N	 N
s(Ns(a, b),c)= s(a, Ns(b, c)). 
s=0 s=0 
(These equations are linear in N if i, i&lt;N, are known). 
To study these equatio ns, one can use Hochschild cohomology . Namely , we have the 
following standard facts (due to Gerstenhab er, [Ge]), which can be checked directly . 
(1) The linear equation for 1 says that 1 is a Hochschild 2-cocycle. Thus algebra struc
tures on A0[]/2 deforming 0 are parametrized by the space Z2(A0) of Hochschild 
2-cocycles of A0 with values in M = A0. 
(2) If 1,
1 are two 2-cocycles such that 1  
1 is a coboundary , then the algebra struc
tures on A0[]/2 corresp onding to 1 and 
1 are equiv alent by a transformation of 
A0[]/2 that equals the identity modulo , and vice versa. Thus equiv alence classes 
of multiplications on A0[]/2 deforming 0 are parametrized by the cohomology 
HH2(A0). 
(3) The linear equation for	N says that dN is a certain quad ratic expression bN in 
1,...,N1. This expression is always a Hochschild 3-cocycle, and the equation is 
solvable if and only if it is a coboundary . Thus the cohom ology class of bN in HH3(A0) 
is the only obstruction to solvin g this equation. 
8.7.4. Universal deformation. In particu lar, if HH3(A0) = 0 then the equation for n can be 
solved for all n, and for each n the freedom in choosing the solution, modulo equiv alences, 
is the space H = HH2(A0). Thus there exists an algebr a structure over C[[H ]] on the space 
Au := A0[[H]] of formal functions from H to A0, a, b  u(a, b)  A0[[H]], (a, b  A0), such 
that u(a, b)(0) = ab  A0, and every 1-parameter at formal deformation A of A0 is given 
by the formula (a, b)() = u(a, b)(()) for a unique formal series   H[[]], with the 
property that (0) is the cohomology class of the cocycle 1. 
Such an algebra Au is called a universal deformation of A0. It is unique up to an isomor
phism (whic h may involve an automorphism of C[[H ]]). 4 
Thus in the case HH3(A0) = 0, deformation theory allows us to complete ly classify 1
parameter at formal deformations of A0. In particula r, we see that the moduli space 
parametrizing formal deform ations of A0 is a smooth space  it is the formal neigh borhood 
of zero in H. 
If HH3(A0) is nonzero then in general the universal deformation parametrized by H does 
not exist, as there are obstructions to deformations. In this case, the moduli space of 
3Note that we dont have to worry about the existence of a unit in A since a formal deformation of an 
algebra with unit always has a unit. 
4In spite of the universal property of Au, it may happ en that there is an isomorphism between the algebras 
A1 and A2 corresp onding to dieren t paths 1(),2() (of course, reducing to a nontrivial automorphism of 
A0 modulo ). For this reason, sometimes Au is called a semiuniversal, rather than universal, deformation 
of A0. 
68</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>8. Symplectic reflection algebras
8.1. The denition of symplectic reection algebras. Rational Cheredn ik algebras for 
nite Coxeter groups are a special case of a wider class of algebras called symplectic reection 
algebras. To dene them, let V be a nite dimensional symplectic vector space over C with 
a symplectic form , and G be a nite group acting symple ctically (linearly) on V . For 
simplicit y let us assume that (2V )G = C (i.e., V is symplectica lly irreducible) and that 
G acts faithfully on V (these assumptions are not importan t, and essen tially not restrictiv e). 
Denition 8.1. A symplectic reection in G is an element g such that the rank of the 
operator 1  g on V is 2. 
If s is a symplectic reection, then let s(x, y) be the form  applied to the projections of 
x, y to the image of 1  s along the kernel of 1  s; thus s is a skewsymmetric form of rank 
2 on V . 
Let S G be the set of symplectic reections, and c : S C be a funct ion which is 
invarian t under the action of G. Let t  C. 
Denition 8.2. The symplectic reection algebra Ht,c = Ht,c[G, V ] is the quotien t of the 
algebra C[G]  T(V ) by the ideal generated by the relation 
(8.1) [x, y]= t(x, y)  2 css(x, y)s. 
sS 
Example 8.3. Let W be a nite Coxeter group with reectio n represen tation h. We can set 
V = h  h, (x, x)= (y, y) = 0, (y, x)=(y, x), for x, x  h and y, y  h. In this case 
(1) symplec tic reections are the usual reections in W ; 
(2) s(x, x)= s(y, y) = 0, s(y, x)=(y, s)(
s ,x)/2. 
Thus, Ht,c[G, h  h] coincide s with the rational Cherednik algebra Ht,c(G, h) dened in 
Section 3. 
Example 8.4. Let  be a nite subgroup of SL2(C), and V = C2 be the tautological 
represen tation, with its standard symplectic form. Then all nontrivial elemen ts of  are 
symplectic reections, and for any symplectic reection s, s = . So the main comm utation 
relation of Ht,c[,V ] takes the form 
[y, x]= t  2cgg. 
g,g=1
Example 8.5. (Wreath products) Let  be as in the previous example, G = Sn  n, and 
V =(C2)n . Then symplectic reections are conjugates (g, 1, ..., 1), g  , g =1, and also 
conmjugates of transp ositions in Sn (so there is one more conjugacy class of reections than 
in the previous example). 
Note also that for any V, G, H0,0[G, V ]= G  SV , and H1,0[G, V ]= G  Weyl(V ), where 
Weyl(V ) is the Weyl algebra of V , i.e. the quotien t of the tensor algebra T(V ) by the 
relation xy  yx = (x, y), x, y  V . 
8.2. The PBW theorem for symplectic reection algebras. To ensure that the sym
plectic reectio n algebras Ht,c have good properties, we need to prove a PBW theorem for 
them, which is an analog of Prop osition 3.5. This is done in the following theorem, which 
also explains the special role played by symplectic reections. 
62</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Theorem 8.39. (i) Let Z1  Z2 be a nite extension of nitely gener ated commutative 
C-algebr as, without zero divisors, and M be a nitely gener ated module over Z2. Then 
M is Cohen-Mac aulay over Z2 i it is Cohen-Mac aulay over Z1. 
(ii)	Supp ose that Z is the algebr a of functions on a smooth ane variety. Then a Z-
module M is Cohen-Mac aulay if and only if it is projective. 
Proof. The proof can be found in the text book [Ei].	  
In particular, this shows that the algebra of functions on a smooth ane variety is Cohen-
Macaula y. Algebras of functions on many singular varieties are also Cohen-Macaula y. 
Example 8.40. The algebra of regular functions on the cone xy = z2 is Cohen-Macaula y. 
2This algebra can be identied as C[a, b]Z2 by letting x = a,y = b2 and z = ab, where the Z2 
action is dened by a  a, b  b. It contains a subal gebra C[a2,b2], and as a module 
over this subalgebra, it is free of rank 2 with generators 1, ab. 
Example 8.41. Any irreducible ane algebraic curve is Cohen-Macaula y. For example, the 
algebra of regular functions on y2 = x3 is isomorphic to the subalg ebra of C[t] spanned by 
1,t2,t3 ,.... It contains a subalgebra C[t2] and as a module over this subalgebra, it is free of 
rank 2 with generators 1, t3 . 
Example 8.42. Consider the subalgebra in C[x, y] spanned by 1 and xiyj with i+j  2. Itis 
a nite generated module over C[x2,y2], but not free. So this algebra is not Cohen-Macaula y. 
Another tool we will need is homological dimension. We will say that an algeb ra A has 
homological dimension  d if any (left) A-mo dule M has a projectiv e resolution of length 
 d. The homological dimension of A is the smallest integer having this property. If such 
an integer does not exist, A is said to have innite homological dimension. 
It is easy to show that the homological dimension of A is  d if and only if for any A-
modules M, N one has Exti(M, N) = 0 for i&gt;d. Also, the homolo gical dimension clearly 
does not decrease under taking associated graded of the algebra under a positive ltration 
(this is clear from considering the spectral sequence attached to the ltration). 
It follows immediately from this denition that homological dimension is Morita invarian t. 
Namely , recall that a Morita equiv alence between algebras A and B is an equiv alence of 
categories A-mo d B-mod. Such an equiv alenc e maps projectiv e modules to projectiv e 
ones, since projectivit y is a categori cal property (P is projective if and only if the functor 
Hom(P, ) is exact). This implies that if A and B are Morita equiv alent then their homological 
dimensions are the same. 
Then we have the following importan t theorem. 
Theorem 8.43. The homolo gical dimension of a commutative nitely gener ated C-algebr a 
Z is nite if and only if Z is regular, i.e. is the algebr a of functions on a smooth ane 
variety. 
8.12. Proof of Theorem 8.32. First let us show that any smooth point  of Mc is an 
Azuma ya point. Since H0,c = End B0,c H0,ce = End Z0,c (H0,ce), it is sucien t to show that 
the coheren t sheaf on Mc corresp onding to the module H0,ce is a vector bundle near . By 
Theorem 8.39 (ii), for this it suces to show that H0,ce is a Cohen-Macaula y Z0,c-module. 
To do so, rst note that the statemen t is true for c = 0. Indeed, in this case the claim is 
that SV is a Cohen-Macaula y module over (SV )G . But SV is a polynomial algebra, which 
is Cohen-Macaula y, so the result follows from Theorem 8.39, (i). 
74</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Classical and quantum Olshanetsky-Perelomov systems for finite Coxeter groups</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-735-double-affine-hecke-algebras-in-representation-theory-combinatorics-geometry-and-mathematical-physics-fall-2009/resources/mit18_735f09_ch02/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>So we get 
m( r
Dy2 
i )= r
y2 
i  csrs
(y
si)2 
s= H, 
 i=1 i=1 sS i=1 
since r
i=1 s(yi)2 =(s,s).  
Recall that by the Chev alley-Shepard-T odd theorem, the algebra (Sh)W is free. Let P1 = 
p2,P2,...,Pr be homogeneous generator s of (Sh)W . 
Corollary 2.17. The dier ential operators Lj = m(Pj (Dy1 ,...,Dyr )) are pairwise commu
tative, have symb ols Pj , homo geneity degree dj , and L1 = H. 
Proof. Since Dunkl operators comm ute, the operators Lj are well dened. Since m(AB)= 
m(A)m (B) when B is invarian t, the operators Lj are pairwise comm utativ e. The rest is 
clear.  
Now to prove Theorem 2.9, we will show that the operators H and H are conjugate to 
each other by a certain function; this will complete the proof. 
Prop osition 2.18. Let c(x) := s(x)cs . Then we have sS 
1 Hc = H. c  
Remark 2.19. The function c(x) is not rational. It is a multivalued analyt ic function. 
Nevertheless, it is easy to see that for any dieren tial operator L with rational coecien ts, 
c1 Lc also has rational coecien ts.  
Proof of Proposition 2.18. We have 
r  cs(s,s)yi (log c)yi = s .2si=1 sS 
Therefore, we have 
c  Hc1 =h   cs(s,s) 
s + U,  s 
sS 
where 
U = c(h1  cs(cs + 1)(s,s) .c )  2 
sS s 
Let us compute U. We have 
 cs(cs + 1)(s,s)  cscu(s,u)c(hc1)= 2 + . 
s su sS s=uS 
We claim that the last sum  is actually zero. Indeed, this sum is invarian t under the Coxeter 
group, so sS s   is a regular anti-invarian t function of degree |S|  2. But the smallest 
degree of a nonze ro anti-invarian t is |S|, so  = 0, U = 0, and we are done (Prop osition 2.18 
and Theorem 2.9 are proved).  
Remark 2.20. A similar metho d works for any complex reection group G. Namely , the 
operators Li = m(Pi(Dy1 ,...,Dyr )) form a quan tum integrable system. However, if G is not 
a real reection group, this system does not have a quadratic Hamiltonian in momen tum 
variables (so it does not have a physical meaning). 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Example 2.25. Let W = Sn, h = Cn1 . Then 
n 1 H0 = p 2 
i  c 2 
(xi  xj )2 ( the classical Calogero-Moser Hamiltonian). 
i=1 i=j 
So the theorem says that there are functions L0 
j ,j =1,...,n  1, 
L0 
j = pij+1 + lower terms, 
i 
homogeneous of degree zero, such that L0 = H0 and {L0,Lk0 } = 0. 1 j 
2.9. Rees algebras. Let A be a ltered algebra over a eld k: k = F 0A  F 1A   , 
iF iA = A. Then the Rees algebr a A = Rees(A) is dened by the formula A = 
n=0F nA. 
This is an algebra over k[], where  is the elemen t 1 of the summand F 1A. 
2.10. Proof of Theorem 2.24. The proof of Theorem 2.24 is similar to the proof of its 
quan tum analog. Namely, to construct the functions Lj 0 , we need to introduce classical 
Dunkl operators. To do so, we introduce a parameter  (Planc ks constan t) and dene 
Dunkl operators Da()= Da(c, ) with : 
Da(c, )= Da(c/) = a   
(12c
 s
s
s(
)a
) 
s (1  s), where a  h. 
sS 
These operators can be regarded as elements of the Rees algebra A = Rees(CW  D(hreg)), 
where the ltration is by order of dieren tial operators (and W sits in degree 0). Reducing 
these operators modulo , we get classical Dunkl operators Da0(c)  A0 := A/A = CW  
O(T hreg). They are given by the formula 
D0(c)= pa   
(12c
 s
s
s(
)a
) 
s (1  s),a
sS 
where pa is the classical momen tum (the linear function on h corresp onding to a  h). 
It follows from the comm utativit y of the quan tum Dunkl operators Da(c) that the Dunkl 
operators Da(c, ) comm ute. Hence, so do the classical Dunkl operators Da0: 
[Da0,Db 0]=0. 
We also have the following analog of Prop osition 2.14: 
Prop osition 2.26. (i) For any x  h, one has 
[Da0 ,x]=  cs(a, s)(x, s)s. 
sS 
(ii) If g  W then gD0g1 = D0 .a ga
Now let us construct the classical Olshanetsky-P erelomo v Hamiltonians. As in the quan
tum case, we have the operation m(), which is given by the formula gW Bg  g  Bg, 
B O(T hreg). We dene the Hamiltonian 
r
H0 := m((Dy0 
i )2). 
i=1 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>2.	Classical and quantum Olshanetsky-Pe relomov systems for finite 
Coxeter groups 
2.1. The rational quan tum Calogero-Moser system. Consider the dieren tial operator 
n 2  1 H = 
i=1 xi 2  c(c + 1) 
i=j (xi  xj )2 . 
This is the quan tum Hamiltonian for a system of n particles on the line of unit mass and the 
interaction potential (between particle 1 and 2) c(c + 1)/(x1  x2)2 . This system is called 
the rational quantum Calo gero-Moser system . 
It turns out that the rational quan tum Calogero-Moser system is completely integrable. 
Namely , we have the following theorem. 
Theorem 2.1. Ther e exist dier ential operators Lj with rational coecients of the form 
n  Lj = ()j + lower order terms,j =1, . . . , n, xii=1 
which are invariant under the symmetric group Sn, homo geneous of degree j, and such 
that L2 = H and [Lj ,Lk]=0, j, k =1,...,n. 
We will prove this theorem later. 
  Remark 2.2. L1 = i . xi 
2.2. Complex reection groups . Theorem 2.1 can be generalized to the case of any nite 
Coxeter group. To describ e this generalization, let us recall the basic theory of nite Coxeter 
groups and, more generally , complex reection groups. 
Let h be a nite-dimensional complex vector space. We say that a semisimple elemen t 
s  GL(h) is a (complex) reection if rank (1  s) = 1. This means that s is conjugate to 
the diagonal matrix diag(, 1,..., 1) where  = 1. 
Now assume h carries a nondegenera te inner product (, ). We say that a semisimple 
elemen t s  O(h) is a real reection if rank (1  s) = 1; equivalently, s is conjugate to 
diag(1, 1,..., 1). 
Now let G  GL(h) be a nite subgr oup. 
Denition 2.3. (i) We say that G is a complex reection group if it is generated by 
complex reections. 
(ii) If	h carries an inner product, then a nite subgroup G  O(h) is a real reection 
group (or a nite Coxeter group) if G is generated by real reections. 
For the complex reection groups, we have the following importan t theorem. 
Theorem 2.4 (The Chev alley-Shepard-T odd theorem, [Che]). A nite subgroup G of GL(h) 
is a complex reection group if and only if the algebr a (Sh)G is a polynomial (i.e., free) 
algebr a. 
By the Chev alley-Shepard-T odd theorem, the algebra (Sh)G has algebraically indep enden t 
generators Pi, homogeneous of some degrees di for i =1,..., dim h. The numbers di are 
uniquely determined, and are called the degrees of G. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>By taking the limit of quan tum situati on, we nd
 cs(s,s) = p . H02  s(x) ps 
sS 
Unfortunately , this is no longer conjugate to H0. However, consider the (outer) automor
phism c of the algebra CW  O(T hreg) dened by the formulas 
c(x)= x, c(s)= s, c(pa)= pa + a log c, 
for x  h, a  h, s  W . It is easy to see that if b0  A0 and b  A is a deformation of 
b0 then c(b0) = limc/bc/. Therefore, taking the limit  0 in Prop osition 2.16, we 0 1 
  
nd that H0 = c(H0). 
Now set Lj 0 = m(c(Pj (Dy0 
1 ,...,Dy0 
r ))). These functions are well dened since Da 0 com
mute, are homogeneous of degree zero, and L0
1 = H0. 
Moreo ver, we can dene the operators Lj () in Rees(D(hreg)W ) in the same way as Lj , but 
using the Dunkl operators Dyi () instead of Dyi . Then [Lj (),Lk()]=0, and Lj ()=0 = 
L0 
j . This implies that L0 Poisson comm ute: {L0,Lk0} = 0. |
j j 
Theorem 2.24 is proved. 
Remark 2.27. As in the quan tum situation, Theorem 2.24 can be generalize d to complex 
reection groups, giving integrabl e systems with Hamiltonians which are non-quadratic in 
momen tum variables. 
2.11. Notes. Section 2.1 follows Section 5.4 of [E4]; the denition of complex reection 
groups and their basic properties can be found in [GM]; the denition of parab olic subgroups 
and the notations are borrowed from Section 3.1 of [BE]; the remaining parts of this section 
follow Section 6 of [E4]. 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.735 Double Affine Hecke Algebras in Representation Theory, Combinatorics, Geometry, 
and Mathematical Physics 
Fall 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>The main result about Dunkl operators, on which all their applications are based, is the 
following theorem. 
Theorem 2.15 (C. Dunkl, [Du1]) . The Dunkl operators commute: 
[Da,Db]=0 for any a, b  h. 
Proof. Let x  h. We have 
[[Da,Db],x] = [[Da,x],Db]  [[Db,x],Da]. 
Now, using Prop osition 2.14, we obtain: 
[[Da,x],Db]= [ cs(a, s)(x, 
s )s, Db] 
sS 
=   
cs(a, s)(x, s)(b, s)sDs  1  
2 
s 1 
. 
sS 
Since a and b occur symmetrically , we obtain that [[Da,Db],x] = 0. This means that for any 
f f  C[h], [Da,Db]f = f[Da,Db]1=0. Sofor f, g  C[h], g [Da,Db] g =[Da,Db]f = 0. Thus 
f [Da,Db] = 0 which implies [Da,Db] = 0 in the algebra CG  D(hreg) (since this algebra g 
acts faithfully on C(h)).  
2.6. Proof of Theorem 2.9. For any elemen t B  CW  D(hreg), dene m(B) to be the 
dieren tial operator C(h)W C(h), dened by B. That is, if B = ),  gW Bgg, Bg D(hreg
then m(B)= gW Bg. It is clear that if B is W -invarian t, then A  CW  D(hreg), 
m(AB)= m(A)m (B). 
Prop osition 2.16 ([Du1], [He1]) . Let {y1,...,yr} be an orthonormal basis of h. Then we 
have 
r
m( Dy2 
i )= H, 
i=1 
 cs(s,s)wher e H =h  . s sS s 
Proof. For any y  h, we have m(Dy 2)= m(Dyy). A simpl e computation shows that 
Dyy = y 2   cs
s
s (y)(1  s)y 
sS 
= y 2   css(y)(y(1  s)+ s(y)s). s s 
sS 
This means that 
m(Dy2)= y 2   cs
s(
s y)2 
. s 
sS
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>This theorem is obviously a generalization of Theorem 2.1 about W = Sn.
To prove Theore m 2.9, one needs to develop the theory of Dunkl operators.
Remark 2.10. 1. We will show later that the operators Lj are unique. 
2. Theorem 2.9 for classical root systems was proved by Olshanetsky and Perelomov 
(see [OP]), following earlier work of Calogero, Sutherland, and Moser in type A. For a 
general Weyl group, this theorem (in fact, its stronger trigonometric version) was proved by 
analytic metho ds in the series of papers [HO],[He3],[Op3],[Op4]. A few years later, a simple 
algebraic proof using Dunkl operators, which works for any nite Coxeter group, was found 
by Heckman, [He1]; this is the proof we will give below. 
For the trigonometric version, Heckman also gave an algebraic proof in [He2], which used 
non-comm uting trigonometric counterparts of Dunkl operators. This proof was later im
proved by Cheredn ik ([Ch1]), who dened commuting (although not Weyl group invarian t) 
versions of Heckman s trigonometric Dunkl operators, now called Dunkl-Cherednik opera
tors. 
2.5. Dunkl operators. Let G  GL(h) be a nite subgroup. Let S be the set of reections 
in G. For any reection s S, let s be the eigen value of s on s  h (i.e. ss = ss), 
and let  h be an eigen vector such that s= 1. We normalize them in such a way s sss 
that s,
s  = 2. 
Let c : S C be a function invarian t with respect to conjuga tion. Let a  h. 
The following denition was made by Dunk l for real reection groups, and by Dunkl and 
Opdam for complex reection groups. 
Denition 2.11. The Dunkl operator Da = Da(c) on C(h) is dened by the formula 
 2css(a)Da = Da(c) := a  (1  s)s (1  s). 
sS 
Clearly , Da  CG  D(hreg), where hreg is the set of regular points of h (i.e. not preserv ed 
by any reection), and D(hreg) denotes the algebra of dierential operators on hreg. 
Example 2.12. Let G = Z2, h = C. Then there is only one Dunkl operator up to scaling, 
and it equals to c D = x  (1  s), x 
where the operator s is given by the formula (sf)(x)= f(x). 
Remark 2.13. The Dunkl operators Da map the space of polynomials C[h] to itself. 
Prop osition 2.14. (i) For any x  h, one has 
[Da,x]=(a, x)  cs(a, s)(x, )s.s 
sS 
(ii) If g  G then gDag1 = Dga. 
Proof. (i) The proof follows immediately from the identity 
x  sx =1  s (x, )s. 2 s 
(ii) The identity is obvious from the invariance of the function c.  
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>2.7. Uniqueness of the operators Lj. 
Prop osition 2.21. The operators Lj are unique. 
Proof. Assume that we have two choices for Lj : Lj and L
j. Denote Lj  L
j by M. 
Assume M = 0. We have 
(i)	M is a dieren tial operator on h with rational coecien ts, of order smaller than dj 
and homogeneit y degree dj ; 
(ii) [M, H] = 0. 
Let M0 be the symbol of M. Then M0 is a polynomia l of p  h with coecien ts in C(h). 
We have, from (ii), 
{M0, p 2} =0, p  h, 
and from (i) we see that the coecien ts of M0 are not polynomial (as they have negat ive 
degree). 
However, we have the following lemma. 
Lemma 2.22. Let h be a nite dimensional vector space. Let  :(x, p)  (x, p) be a 
rational function on h  h which is a polynomial in p  h. Let f : h  C be a polynomial 
such that the dier entials df(p) for p  h span h (e.g., f(p)= p2). Supp ose that the 
Poisson bracket of f and  vanishes: {, f} =0. Then  is a polynomial. 
Proof. (R. Raj) Let Z  h be the pole divisor of . Let x0  h be a generic point in Z. Then 
1 is regular and vanishes at (x0, p) for generic p  h. Also from {1,f} = 0, we have 
1 vanishe s along the entire owline of the Hamiltonian ow dened by f and starting at 
x0. This owline is dened by the formula 
x(t)= x0 + tdf(p), p(t)= p, 
and it must be contained in the pole divisor of  near x0. This implies that df(p) must be 
in Tx0 Z for almost every, hence for every p  h. This is a contradiction with the assumption 
on f, which implies that in fact  has no poles.  
2.8. Classical Dunkl op erators and Olshanetsky-P erelomo v Hamiltonians. We con
tinue to use the notations in Section 2.4. 
Denition 2.23. The classical Olshanetsky-P erelomo v Hamiltonian corresp onding to W is 
the following classical Hamilton ian on hreg  h = T hreg: 
 c2(s,s)H0(x, p)= p 2  s
2(x) . 
sS s
Theorem 2.24 ([OP],[HO, He3, Op3, Op4],[He1]). The Hamiltonian H0 denes a classic al 
integrable system. Namely, there exist unique regular functions L0 on hreg h, wher e highest j 
terms in p are Pj , such that L0 are homo geneous of degree dj (under x  x, x  h, p j 
1p, p  h), and such that L0 = H0 and {L0 
j ,Lk0 } =0, j, k.1 
Proof. The proof is given in the next subsection.	  
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>i Example 2.5. If G = Sn, h = Cn1 (the space of vectors in Cn with zero sum of co
ordinates), then one can take Pi(p1,...,pn)= p i+1 + + pi+1 , i =1,...,n  1 (where  1 n 
pi = 0). 
2.3. Parabolic subgroups. Let G  GL(h) be a nite subgroup. 
Denition 2.6. A parab olic subgroup of G is the stabilizer Ga of a point a  h. 
Note that by Chev alleys theorem, a parab olic subgroup of a complex (resp ectively, real) 
reection group is itself a complex (resp ectively, real) reectio n group. 
Also, if W is a real reection group, then it can be shown that a subgroup W   W is 
parab olic if and only if it is conjugate to a subgroup generated by a subset of simple reections 
of W . In this case, the rank of W , i.e. the number of generating simple reections, equals 
the codimension of the space hW  . 
Example 2.7. Consider the Coxeter group of type E8. It has the Dynkin diagram: 
 
The parab olic subgroups will be Coxeter groups whose Dynkin diagrams are obtained by 
deleting vertices from the above graph. In particular, the maximal parab olic subgroups are 
D7,A7,A1  A6,A2  A1  A4,A4  A3,D5  A2,E6  A1,E7. 
Supp ose G  G is a parab olic subgroup, and b  h is such that Gb = G. In this case, 
we have a natura l G-invarian t decomp osition h = hG  (hG ), and b  hG . Thus we have 
a nonempt y open set hG of all a  hG for which Ga = G; this set is nonempt y because it reg 
contains b. We also have a G-invarian t decomp osition h = hG  (hG ), and we can dene 
the open set hG of all   hG for which G = G. It is clear that this set is nonempt y. Thisreg 
implies, in particular, that one can make an alternativ e denition of a parab olic subgroup 
of G as the stabilizer of a point in h. 
2.4. Olshanetsky-P erelomo v operators. Let s  GL(h) be a complex reection. Denote 
by s  h an eigen vector in h of s with nontrivial eigen value. 
Let W  O(h) be a real reection group and S W the set of reections. Clearly, W 
acts on S by conjugation. Let c : S C be a conjugation invarian t function. 
Denition 2.8. [OP] The quan tum Olshanetsky-P erelomov Hamiltonian attac hed to W is 
the second order dieren tial operator 
H := h  
sS (cscs+ 1)(s, 
2 
s s) , 
where h is the Laplace operator on h. 
Here we use the inner product on h which is dual to the inner product on h. 
Let us assume that h is an irreducible represen tation of W (i.e. W is an irreducible nite 
Coxeter group, and h is its reection represen tation.) In this case, we can take P1(p)= p2 . 
Theorem 2.9. The system dene d by the Olshanetsky-Per elomov operator H is completely 
integrable. Namely, there exist dier ential operators Lj on h with rational coecients and 
symb ols Pj , such that Lj are homo geneous (of degree dj ), L1 = H, and [Lj ,Lk]=0, j, k. 
7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Quantization of Calogero-Moser spaces</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-735-double-affine-hecke-algebras-in-representation-theory-combinatorics-geometry-and-mathematical-physics-fall-2009/resources/mit18_735f09_ch10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>10. Quantiza tion of Claoger o-Moser spaces
10.1. Quan tum momen t maps and quan tum Hamiltonian reduction. Now we would 
like to quan tize the notion of a momen t map. Let g be a Lie algebra, and A be an associativ e 
algebra equipp ed with a g-action, i.e. a Lie algebr a map  : g DerA. A quan tum momen t 
map for (A, ) is an associativ e algebra homomorphism  : U(g) A such that for any  
a  g, b  A one has [(a),b]= (a)b. 
The space of g-invarian ts Ag, i.e. elemen ts b  A such that [(a),b] = 0 for all a  g, is 
a subalgebra of A. Let J  A be the left ideal generated by (a), a  g. Then J is not 
a 2-sided ideal, but Jg := J  Ag is a 2-sided ideal in Ag. Indeed, let c  Ag, and b  Jg, 
b = bi(ai), bi  A, ai  g. Then bc = bi(ai)c = bic(ai)  Jg.i 
Thus, the algebra A//g := Ag/Jg is an associativ e algebra, which is called the quan tum 
Hamiltonian reduction of A with respect to the quan tum momen t map . 
10.2. The Levasseur-Staord theorem. In general, similarly to the classical case, it is 
rather dicult to compute the quan tum reduction A//g. For example, in this subsection 
we will describ e A//g in the case when A = D(g) is the algebra of dieren tial operators 
on a reductiv e Lie algebra g, and g acts on A through the adjoin t action on itself. This 
description is a very nontrivial result of Levasseur and Staord. 
Let h be a Cartan subalgebra of g, and W the Weyl group of (g, h). Let hreg denote the set 
of regular points in h, i.e. the complemen t of the reection hyperplanes. To describ e D(g)//g, 
we will construct a homomo rphism HC : D(g)g D(h)W , called the Harish-Chandra homo
morphism (as it was rst constructed by Harish-Chandra). Recall that we have the classical 
Harish-Chandra isomorphism  : C[g]g C[h]W , dened simply by restricting g-invarian t 
functions on g to the Cartan subalgebra h. Using this isomorphism, we can dene an action 
of D(g)g on C[h]W , which is clearly given by W -invarian t dieren tial operators. However, 
these operators will, in genera l, have poles on the reection hyperplanes. Thus we get a 
homomorphism HC : D(g)g D(hreg)W . 
The homomor phism HC is called the radial part homomorphism, as for example for 
g = su(2) it computes the radial parts of rotationally invarian t dieren tial operators on R3 
in spherical coordinate s. This homomorphism is not yet what we want, since it does not 
actually land in D(h)W (the radial parts have poles). 
Thus we dene the Harish-Chandra homomorp hism by twisting HC by the discriminan t 
(x)= (, x)(x  h, and  runs over positiv e roots of g):&gt;0
HC(D ) :=   HC(D)  1 D(hreg)W . 
Theorem 10.1. (i) (Harish-Chandr a, [HC]) For any reductive g, HC lands in D(h)W  
D(hreg)W . 
(ii) (Levasseur-Staor d [LS]) The homomorphism HC denes an isomorphism D(g)//g = 
D(h)W . 
Remark 10.2. (1) Part (i) of the theorem says that the poles magically disapp ear after 
conjugation by . 
(2) Both parts of this theorem are quite nontrivial. The rst part was proved by Harish-
Chandra using analytic metho ds, and the second part by Levasseur and Staord 
using the theory of D-modules. 
85</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>|
 
 In the case g = gln, Theorem 10.1 is a quan tum analog of Theorem 9.14. The remaining 
part of this subsection is devoted to the proof of Theorem 10.1 in this special case, using 
Theorem 9.14. 
We start the proof with the following proposition, valid for any reductiv e Lie algebr a. 
Prop osition 10.3. If D  (Sg)g is a dier ential operator with constant coecients, then 
HC(D ) is the W -invariant dier ential operator with constant coecients on h, obtaine d from 
D via the classic al Harish-Chandr a isomorphism  :(Sg)g (Sh)W . 
Proof. Without loss of generalit y, we may assume that g is simple. 
Lemma 10.4. Let D be the Laplacian g of g, corresponding to an invariant form. Then 
HC(D ) is the Laplacian h. 
Proof. Let us calculate HC(D). We have 
r
D = x2 
i +2 f e , 
i=1 &gt;0 
where xi is an orthonormal basis of h, and e,f are root elemen ts such that (e,f) = 1. 
Thus if F (x) is a g-invarian t function on g, then we get 
r 
(DF )|h = x2 
i (F |h)+2 (f e F )|h. 
i=1 &gt;0 
Now let x  h, and consider (f e F )(x). We have 
(f e F )(x)= st|s=t=0F (x + tf + se). 
On the other hand, we have 
Ad(e s(x )1e )(x + tf + se)= x + tf + ts(x)1h +  , 
where h =[e,f]. Hence, sts=t=0F (x +tf +se)= (x)1(h F )(x). This implie s that 
HC(D)F (x)=hF (x)+2 (x)1h F (x). 
&gt;0 
Now the statemen t of the Lemma reduces to the identity 1 h =h+2 &gt;0 (x)1h . 
This identity follows immediately from the identity h =0. To prove the latter, it suces 
to note that  is the lowest degree nonzero polynomial on h, which is antisymmetric under 
the action of W . The lemma is proved.  
Now let D be any elemen t of (Sg)g D(g)g of degree d (operator with constan t coe
cients). It is obvious that the leading order part of the operator HC(D) is the operator (D) 
with constan t coecien ts, whose symbol is just the restriction of the symbol of D from g 
to h. Our job is to show that in fact HC(D )= (D). To do so, denote by Y the dierence 
HC(D )  (D). Assume Y =0. By Lemma 10.4, the operator HC(D) comm utes with h. 
Therefore, so does Y . Also Y has homogeneit y degree d but order m  d  1. Let S(x, p) be 
the symbol of Y (x  h, p  h). Then S is a homogeneous funct ion of homoge neity degree 
d under the transformations x t1x, p tp, polynomial in p of degree m. From these 
properties of S it is clear that S is not a polynomial (its degree in x is m  d&lt; 0). On 
the other hand, since Y comm utes with h, the Poisson bracket of S with p2 is zero. Thus 
Prop osition 10.3 follows from Lemma 2.22.  
86</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Cherednik algebra B1,k for the symmetric group. Therefore, the following theorem comes as 
no surprize. 
Theorem 10.12 ([EG]). The algebr a Bk is isomorphic to the spheric al rational Cher ednik 
algebr a B1,k(Sn, Cn). 
Thus, quan tum Hamiltonian reduction provides a Lie-theoretic construction of the spher
ical rational Cherednik algebra for the symmetric group. A similar (but more complicated) 
Lie theoretic construction exists for symplectic reection algebras for wreath product groups 
dened in Examp le 8.5 (see [EGGO]). 
10.5. Notes. Our exposition in this section follows Section 4, Section 5 of [E4]. 
89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Now we continue the proof of Theor em 10.1. Consider the ltration on D(g) in which 
deg(g) = 1 deg(g) = 0 (the order ltration), and the associated graded map grHC : C[g  
g]g  C[h reg  h]W , which attac hes to every dieren tial operator the symbol of its radial 
part. It is easy to see that this map is just the restriction map to h  h  g  g, so it 
actually lands in C[h  h]W . 
Moreo ver, grHC is a map onto C[h  h]W . Indeed, grHC is a Poisson map, so the 
surjectivit y follows from the following Lemma. 
Lemma 10.5. C[h  h]W is gener ated as a Poisson algebr a by C[h]W and C[h]W , i.e. by 
functions fm = xim = p, m  1. m and f m
i 
Proof. We have {f ,fr} = mr x r1 p m1 . Thus the result follows from Corollary 9.13. m ii 
Let K0 be the kernel of grHC. Then by Theorem 9.14, K0 is the ideal of the commuting 
scheme Comm(g)/G. 
Now consid er the kernel K of the homomorphism HC. It is easy to see that K  Jg, 
so gr(K )  gr(J)g. On the other hand, since K0 is the ideal of the comm uting scheme, 
we clearly have gr(J)g  K0, and K0  grK. This implies that K0 = grK = gr(J)g, and 
K = Jg. 
It remain s to show that Im HC = D(h)W . Since grK = K0, we have grIm HC = C[hh]W . 
Therefore, to nish the proof of the Harish-Chandra and Levasseur-Staord theorems, it 
suces to prove the following proposition. 
Prop osition 10.6. Im HC D(h)W . 
Proof. We will use the following Lemma. 
Lemma 10.7 (N. Wallach, [Wa]). D(h)W is generated as an algebr a by W -invariant func
tions and W -invariant dier ential operators with constant coecients. 
Proof. The lemma follows by taking associated graded algebras from Lemma 10.5.  
Remark 10.8. Levasseur and Staord showed [LS] that this lemma is valid for any nite 
group W acting on a nite dimensional vector space h. However, the above proof does not 
apply , since, as explained in [Wa], Lemma 10.5 fails for many groups W , including Weyl 
groups of exceptional Lie algebras E6,E7,E8 (in fact it even fails for the cyclic group of 
order &gt; 2 acting on a 1-dime nsional space!). The general proof is more complicated and uses 
some results in noncomm utativ e algebra. 
Lemma 10.7 and Prop osition 10.3 imply Prop osition 10.6.  
Thus, Theorem 10.1 is proved. 
10.3. Corollaries of Theorem 10.1. Let gR be the compact form of g, and O a regular 
coadjoin t orbit in gConsider the map R. 
O : h  C,O(x)= 
O e(b,x)db, x  h, 
where db is the measure on the orbit coming from the Kirillo v-Kostan t symplectic structur e. 
87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.735 Double Affine Hecke Algebras in Representation Theory, Combinatorics, Geometry, 
and Mathematical Physics 
Fall 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Theorem 10.9 (Harish-Chandra formula). For a regular element x  h, we have 
O(x)= 1(x) (1)(w)e(w,x), 
wW 
wher e  is the interse ction of O with the dominant chamb er in the dual Cartan subalgebr a 
h
R, and (w) is the length of an element w  W .R  g
Proof. Take D  (Sg)g. Then (x) O is an eigenfunction of HC(D)= (D)  (Sh)W with 
eigen value O(D), where O(D) is the value of the invarian t polynomial D at the orbit O. 
Since the solutions of the equation (D) = O(D) have a basis e(w,x) where w  W , 
we have  
(x) O(x)= cw  e(w,x). 
wW 
Since it is antisymmetric, we have cw = c (1)(w), where c is a constan t. The fact that  
c = 1 can be shown by comparing the asymptotics of both sides as x  in the regular 
chamber (using the stationary phase appro ximation for the integral).  
From Theorem 10.9 and the Weyl Chara cter formula, we have the following corollary . 
Corollary 10.10 (Kirillo v character formula for nite dimensional represen tations, [Ki]). If 
 is a dominant integral weight, and L is the corresponding representation of G, then 
Tr L (e x)= (x) e(b,x)db,Tr (x) O+ 
wher e Tr (x) is the trigonometric version of (x), i.e. the Weyl denominator 
(e(x)/2  e(x)/2), and O denotes the coadjoint orbit passing through .&gt;0
10.4. The deformed Harish-Chandra homomorphism. Finally , we would like to ex
plain how to quan tize the Calogero-Moser space Cn, using the procedure of quantum Hamil
tonian reduction. 
Let g = gln, A = D(g) as above. Let k be a complex number, and Wk be the represen tation 
of sln on the space of functions of the form (x1  xn)kf(x1,...,xn), where f is a Lauren t 
polynomial of degree 0. We regard Wk as a g-mo dule by pulling it back to g under the 
natural projection g sln. Let Ik be the annihilator of Wk in U(g). The ideal Ik is the 
quan tum counterpart of the coadjoi nt orbit of matrices T such that T + 1 has rank 1. 
Let Bk = D(g)g/(D(g)(Ik))g where  : U(g) A is the quan tum momen tum map (the 
quan tum Hamiltonian reducti on with respect to the ideal Ik). Then Bk has a ltration 
induced from the order ltration of D(g)g. 
Let HCk : D(g)g  Bk be the natural homomorphism, and K(k) be the kernel of HCk. 
Theorem 10.11 (Etingof-Ginzburg, [EG]). (i) K(0) = K, B0 = D(h)W , HC0 = HC. 
(ii) grK(k) = Ker (grHCk)= K0 for all complex k. Thus, HCk is a at family of 
homomorphisms. 
(iii) The algebr a grBk is commutative and isomorphic to C[h  h]W as a Poisson algebr a. 
Because of this theorem, the homomorphism HCk is called the deformed Harish-Chandra 
homomorphism. 
Theorem 10.11 implies that Bk is a quan tization of the Calogero-Moser space Cn (with 
deformation parameter 1/k). But we already know one such quan tization -the spherical 
88</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Calogero-Moser spaces</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-735-double-affine-hecke-algebras-in-representation-theory-combinatorics-geometry-and-mathematical-physics-fall-2009/resources/mit18_735f09_ch09/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>9. Caloger o-Moser spaces
9.1. Hamiltonian reduction along an orbit. Let M be an ane algebraic variety and 
G a reductiv e algebraic group. Suppose M is Poisson and the action of G preserv es the 
Poisson structure. Let g be the Lie algeb ra of G and g the dual of g. Let  : M g be a 
momen t map for this action (we assume it exists). It induces a map  : Sg  C[M]. 
Let O be a closed coadjoin t orbit of G, IO be the ideal in Sg corresp onding to O, and let 
JO be the ideal in C[M] generated by (IO). Then JG is a Poisson ideal in C[M]G, and O 
A = C[M]G/JG is a Poisson algebra. O 
Geometrically , Spec(A) = 1(O)/G (categorical quotien t). It can also be written as 
1(z)/Gz, where z  O and Gz is the stabilizer of z in G. 
Denition 9.1. The scheme 1(O)/G is called the Hamiltonian reduction of M with respect 
to G along O. We will denote by R(M, G, O). 
The following proposition is standard. 
Prop osition 9.2. If M is a symple ctic variety and the action of G on 1(O) is free, then 
R(M, G, O) is a symple ctic variety, of dimension dim(M)  2 dim(G) + dim(O). 
9.2. The Calogero-Moser space. Let M = T Matn(C), and G = PGLn(C) (so g = 
sln(C)). Using the trace form we can identify g with g, and M with Matn(C)  Matn(C). 
Then a momen t map is given by the formula (X, Y )=[X, Y ], for X, Y  Matn(C). 
Let O be the orbit of the matrix diag(1, 1,..., 1,n  1), i.e. the set of traceless 
matrices T such that T + 1 has rank 1. 
Denition 9.3 (Kazhdan, Kostan t, Stern berg, [KKS]). The scheme Cn := R(M, G, O) is 
called the Calo gero-Moser space. 
Prop osition 9.4. The action of G on 1(O) is free, and thus (by Proposition 9.2) Cn is a 
smooth symple ctic variety (of dimension 2n). 
Proof. It suces to show that if X, Y are such that XY  YX + 1 has rank 1, then (X, Y ) 
is an irreducible set of matri ces. Indeed, in this case, by Schurs lemma, if B  GLn is such 
that BX = XB and BY = YB then B is a scalar, so the stabilizer of (X, Y ) in PGLn is 
trivial. 
To show this, assume that W =0 is an invarian t subspace of X, Y . In this case, the 
eigen values of [X, Y ] on W are a subcollection of the collection of n  1 copies of 1 and 
one copy of n  1. The sum of the elements of this subcollection must be zero, since it is the 
trace of [X, Y ] on W. But then the subcollection must be the entire collection, so W = Cn , 
as desired.  
Thus, Cn is the space of conjugacy classes of pairs of n  n matrices (X, Y ) such that the 
matrix XY  YX + 1 has rank 1. 
In fact, one also has the following more complicated theorem. 
Theorem 9.5 (G. Wilson, [Wi]). The Calo gero-Moser space is conne cted. 
We will give a proof of this theorem later, in Subsect ion 9.4. 
76</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>mrhas the form xi yi , i.e. coincides with the value of the corresp onding invarian t on the 
diagonal parts Xdiag,Ydiag of X and Y , which comm ute. The proposition is proved.  
We will also need the following proposition: 
Prop osition 9.11. The categoric al quotient {(X, Y )[X, Y ]=0}/PGLn is isomorphic to 
(Cn  Cn)/Sn, i.e. its function algebr a is C[x 1,...,xn|
,y1,...,yn]Sn . 
Proof. Restriction to diago nal matrices denes a homomorph ism 
 : O({(X, Y )|[X, Y ]=0}/PGLn)  C[x 1,...,xn,y1,...,yn]Sn . 
Since (as explained in the proof of Prop osition 9.9), any invarian t polynomial of entries of 
comm uting matrices is determined by its values on diagonal matrices, this map is injective. 
mrAlso, (Tr (XmY r)) = xi yi , where xi,yi are the eigen values of X and Y . 
Now we use the following well known theorem of H. Weyl (from his book Classical 
groups). 
Theorem 9.12. Let B be an algebr a over C. Then the algebr a SnB is gener ated by elements 
of the form 
b  1  1+1  b  1+  +1  1  b. 
Proof. Since SnB is linearly spanned by elemen ts of the form x  x, x  B, it suces 
to prove the theorem in the special case B = C[x]. In this case, the result is simply the fact 
that the ring of symmetric functions is generated by power sums, which is well known.  
]Sn mrCorollary 9.13. The ring C[x1,...,xn,y1,...,yn is gener ated by the polynomials xi yi 
for m, r  0, m + r&gt; 0. 
Proof. Apply Theorem 9.12 in the case B = C[x, y].  
Corollary 9.13 implies that  is surjectiv e. Prop osition 9.11 is proved.  
Now we are ready to prove Wilsons theorem. Let Cn(0)0 be the degenerati on of Cn(0), i.e. 
the subsc heme of C0 cut out by the equation (X ) = 0. According to Prop ositions 9.9 and n 
9.11, the reduced part (Cn(0)0)red is contained in the hypersurface in (Cn  Cn)/Sn cut out 
by the equation (xi  xj ) = 0. This hypersurface has dimension 2n  1, so we are done. i&lt;j 
9.5. The Gan-Ginzburg theorem. Let Comm(n) be the commuting scheme dened in 
T Matn = Matn  Matn by the equations [X, Y ] = 0, X, Y  Matn. Let G = PGLn, and 
consider the categorical quotien t Comm(n )/G (i.e., the Hamiltonian reduction 1(0)/G of 
T Matn by the action of G), whose algebra of regular functions is A = C[Comm(n)]G . 
It is not known whether the comm uting scheme Comm (n) is reduced (i.e. whether the 
corresp onding ideal is a radical ideal); this is a well known open problem. The underlying 
variety is irreducible (as was shown by Gerstenhab er [Ge1]), but very singular, and has a 
very complicated structure. However, we have the following result. 
Theorem 9.14 (Gan, Ginzburg, [GG]). Comm(n)/G is reduced, and isomorphic to C2n/Sn. 
Thus A = C[x 1,...,xn,y1,...,yn]Sn . The Poisson bracket on this algebr a is induc ed from 
the standar d symple ctic structur e on C2n . 
80</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Sketch of the proof. Look at the almost commuting variety Mn  gl gl Cn  (Cn) 
nn 
dened by 
Mn = {(X, Y, v, f)|[X, Y ]+ v  f =0}. 
Gan and Ginzbu rg proved the following result. 
Theorem 9.15. Mn is a complete interse ction. It has n +1 irreducible components denote d 
by Mi , labeled by i = dim CX, Y v. Also, Mn is generic ally reduced. n
Since Mn is generically reduced and is a complete intersectio n, by a standard result of 
comm utativ e algebra it is reduced. Thus C[Mn] has no nonze ro nilpotents. This implies 
C[Mn]G has no nonzero nilpotents. 
However, it is easy to show that the algebra C[Mn]G is isomorphic to the algebra of 
invarian t polynomials of entries of X and Y modulo the rank 1 relation 2[X, Y ]=0. By 
a scheme-theoret ic version of Prop osition 9.9 (proved in [EG]), the latter is isomorphic to 
A. This implies the theorem (the statemen t about Poisson structure s is checked directly in 
coordinates on the open part where X is regular semisimple) .  
9.6. The space Mc for Sn and the Calogero-Moser space. Let H0,c = H0,c[Sn,V ] be 
the symplectic reection algebra of the symmetric group Sn and space V = h  h, where 
h = Cn (i.e., the rational Cherednik algebra H0,c(Sn, h)). Let Mc = Spec B0,c[Sn,V ] be the 
Calogero-Moser space dened in Section 8.5. It is a sympl ectic variety for c = 0. 
Theorem 9.16. For c =0  the space Mc is isomorph ic to the Calo gero-Moser space Cn as a 
symple ctic variety. 
Proof. To prove the theorem, we will rst constru ct a map f : Mc , and then prove that Cn
f is an isomorphism. 
Without loss of generalit y, we may assume that c = 1. As we have shown before, the 
algebra H0,c is an Azuma ya algebra. Therefore, Mc can be regarded as the moduli space of 
irreducible represen tations of H0,c. 
Let E  Mc be an irreducible represen tation of H0,c. We have seen before that E has 
dimension n! and is isomorphic to the regular represen tation as a represen tation of Sn. Let 
Sn1  Sn be the subgroup which preserv es the elemen t 1. Then the space of invarian ts 
ESn1 has dimension n. On this space we have operators X, Y : ESn1 ESn1 obtained
by restriction of the operators x1,y1 on E to the subspace of invarian ts. We have 
n
[X, Y ]= T := s1i. 
i=2 
Let us now calculate the right hand side of this equation explicitly . Let e be the symmetrizer 
of Sn1. Let us realize the regular represen tation E of Sn as C[Sn] with action of Sn by 
left multiplication. Then v1 = e,v2 = es12,...,vn = es1n is a basis of ESn1 . The elemen t 
T comm utes with e, so we have  
Tvi = vj . 
j=i 
This means that T +1 has rank 1, and hence the pair (X, Y ) denes a point on the Calogero-
Moser space Cn. 8 
8Note that the pair (X, Y ) is well dened only up to conjugation, because the representation E is well 
dened only up to an isomorphism. 
81</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.735 Double Affine Hecke Algebras in Representation Theory, Combinatorics, Geometry, 
and Mathematical Physics 
Fall 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>We now set (X, Y )= f(E). It is clear that f : Mc is a regular map. So it remains to Cn 
show that f is an isomorphism. This is equiv alent to showing that the corresp onding map 
of function algebras f : O(Cn)  B0,c is an isomorphism. 
Let us calculate f and f more explicitly . To do so, consider the open set U in Mc consisting 
of represen tations in which xi xj acts invertibly . These are exactly the represen tations that 
are obtained by restricting represen tations of Sn C[x 1,...,xn,p1,...,pn,(x)1] using the 
classical Dunkl embedding. Thus represen tations E  U are of the form E = E, (,   Cn , 
and  has distinct coordinates), where E, is the space of complex valued functions on the 
orbit O,  C2n, with the following action of H0,c: 
 (sijF )(a, b)(xiF )(a, b)= aiF (a, b), (yiF )(a, b)= biF (a, b)+ . ai  ajj=i 
(the group Sn acts by permutations). 
Now let us consider the space ESn1 . A basis of this space is formed by characteristic , 
functions of Sn1-orbits on O,. Using the above presen tation, it is straightforw ard to 
calculate the matrices of the operator s X and Y in this basis: 
X = diag(1,...,n), 
and 
1 Yij = i if j = i, Yij = if j = i. i  j 
This shows that f induces an isomorphism f|U : U  Un, where Un is the subset of Cn 
consisting of pairs (X, Y ) for which X has distinct eigen values. 
From this presen tation, it is straigtforw ard that f(Tr (Xp)) = xp 
1 + + xp
n for every  
positiv e integer p. Also, f comm utes with the natural SL2(C)-action on Mc and Cn (by 
(X, Y )(aX + bY, cX + dY )), so we also get f(Tr (Y p)) = y1 p + + ynp , and   
1 p
mpmf(Tr (XpY )) = xi yixi . p +1 m=0 i 
Now, using the necklace bracket formula on Cn and the comm utation relations of H0,c, we 
nd, by a direct computation, that f preserv es Poisson bracket on the elemen ts Tr (Xp), 
Tr (XqY ). But these elemen ts are a local coordinate system near a generic point, so it follows 
that f is a Poisson map. Since the algebra B0,c is Poisson generated by xip and yip for 
all p, we get that f is a surjectiv e map. 
Also, f is injectiv e. Indeed, by Wilsons theorem the Calogero-Moser space is connected, 
and hence the algebra O(Cn) has no zero divisors, while Cn has the same dimension as Mc. 
This proves that f is an isomorphism, so f is an isomorphism.  
9.7. The Hilbert scheme Hilbn(C2) and the Calogero-Moser space. The Hilbert 
scheme Hilbn(C2) is dened to be 
Hilbn(C2)= { ideals I  C[x, y]|codimI = n} 
= {(E, v)|E is a C[x, y]-module of dimension n, v is a cyclic vector of E}. 
The second equal ity can be easily seen from the short exact sequence 
0 I C[x, y] E 0.  
82</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>formula 
(x1,...,xn,p1,...,pn)  (X, Y ), 
wher e X = diag(x1,...,xn), and Y = Y (x, p) := (yij ), 
1 yij = ,i = j, yii = pi. xi  xj 
In fact, we have a stronger result: 
Prop osition 9.7.  is an isomorphism of symple ctic varieties (wher e the cotangent bund le 
is equipp ed with the usual symple ctic structur e). 
For the proof of Prop osition 9.7, we will need the following general and importan t but 
easy theorem. 
Theorem 9.8 (The necklace bracket formula). Let a1,...,ar and b1,...,bs be either X or 
Y . Then on M we have 
{Tr (a1  ar), Tr (b1  bs)} =	 Tr(ai+1  ara1  ai1bj+1  bsb1  bj1)  
(i,j):ai=Y,bj =X 
Tr (ai+1  ara1  ai1bj+1  bsb1  bj1). 
(i,j):ai=X,bj =Y 
Proof of Proposition 9.7. Let ak = Tr(Xk), bk = Tr(XkY ). It is easy to check using the 
necklace bracket formula that on M we have 
{am,ak} =0, {bm,ak} = kam+k1, {bm,bk} =(k  m)bm+k1. 
On the other hand, ak = xik , bk = xikpi. Thus we see that 
{f, g} = {f, g}, 
where f, g are either ak or bk. But the functions ak,bk, k =0,...,n  1, form a local 
coordinate system near a generic point of Un, so we are done.  
Now let us write the Hamiltonian of the Calogero-Moser system in coordinates. It has the 
form 
 1 (9.1)	 H = Tr(Y (x, p)2)= pi 2  (xi  xj )2 . 
ii=j 
Thus the Calogero-Moser Hamiltonian describ es the motion of a system of n particles on the 
line with interaction potential 1/x2, which we consid ered in Section 2. 
Now we nally see the usefulness of the Hamiltonian reduction procedure. The point is 
that it is not clear at all from formula (9.1) why the Calogero-Moser Hamiltonian should be 
completely integrable. However, our reduction procedure implies the complete integrabilit y 
of H, and gives an explicit formula for the rst integrals: 7 
Hi = Tr(Y (x, p)i). 
Moreo ver, this procedure immediately gives us an explicit solution of the system. Namely , 
assume that x(t), p(t) is the solution with initial condition x(0), p(0). Let (X0,Y0)= 
7Thus, for type A we have two metho ds of proving the integrabilit y of the Calogero-Moser system -one 
using Dunkl operators and one using Ham iltonian reduction. 
78</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Theorem 9.22 (Nest-Tsygan, [NT]). If M is an ane symple ctic variety and A is a quan
tization of M, then 
HH(A[1],A[1]) =H(M, C(())) 
as an algebr a over C(()) . 
Now, we know that the algebra Bt,c is a quan tization of Cn. Therefore by above theorem , 
the cohomology algebra of Cn is the cohomology of Bt,c (for generic t). But Bt,c is Morita 
equiv alent to Ht,c, so this cohomology is the same as the Hochschild cohomology of Ht,c. 
However, the latter can be computed by using that Ht,c is given by generators and relations 
(by producing explicit represen tatives of cohomology classes and computing their product), 
which gives the result.  
9.9. Notes. Sections 9.19.6 follow Section 1, 2, 4 of [E4]; the parts about the Hilbert 
scheme and its relation to Calogero-Moser spaces follow the book [Na] (see also [GS]); the 
other parts follow the paper [EG]. 
84</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Let S(n)C2 = C2  C2 , where Sn acts by permutation. We have a natural map    /Sn
n times 
Hilbn(C2) S(n)C2 which sends every ideal I to its zero set (with multiplicities). This map 
is called the Hilbert-Chow map. 
Theorem 9.17 (Fogart y, [F]). (i) Hilbn(C2) is a smooth quasipr ojective variety. 
(ii) The Hilbert-Chow map Hilbn(C2) S(n)C2 is projective. It is a resolu tion of singu 
larities. 
Proof. Proof can be found in [Na].  
Now consider the Calogero-Moser space Cn dened in Section 9.2. 
Theorem 9.18 (see [Na]). The Hilbert Scheme Hilbn(C2) is C-die omorphic to Cn. 
Remark 9.19. More precisely there exists a family of algebraic varieties over A1, say Xt, 
t  A1, such that Xt is isomorphic to Cn if t = 0 and X0 is the Hilbert scheme; and also if we 
denote by Xt the deformation of C2n/Sn into the Calog ero-Moser space, then there exists 
a map ft : Xt  Xt, such that for t =0, ft is an isomorphism and f0 is the Hilbert-Cho w 
map. 
Remark 9.20. Consider the action of G = PGLn on T Matn. As we have discussed, the 
corresp onding momen t map is (X, Y )=[X, Y ], so 1(0) = {(X, Y )|[X, Y ]=0} is the 
comm uting variety. We can consider two kinds of quotien t 1(0)/G (i.e., of Hamiltonian 
reduction): 
(1) The categor ical quotien t, i.e., 
=(CnSpec(C[xij ,yij]/[X, Y ]=0)G  Cn)/Sn. 
It is a reduced (by Gan-Ginzburg Theore m 9.14), ane but singular variety. 
(2) The GIT quotien t, in which the stability condition is that there exists a cyclic vector 
for X, Y . This quotien t is Hilbn(C2), which is smooth but not ane. 
Both of these reductions are degenerations of the reduction along the orbit of matrices T 
such that T + 1 has rank 1, which yields the space Cn. This explains why Theorem 9.18 and 
the results mentioned in Remark 9.19 are natural to expect. 
9.8. The cohomology of Cn. We also have the following result describing the cohomology 
of Cn (and hence, by Theorem 9.18, of Hilbn(C2)). Dene the age ltration for the symmetric 
group Sn by setting 
age(transp osition) = 1. 
Then one can show that for any   Sn, age( ) = rank (1  )|reection represen tation. It is easy 
to see that 0  age  n1. Notice also that the age ltration can be dened for any Coxeter 
group. 
Theorem 9.21 (Lehn-Sorger, Vasserot). The c ohomolo gy ring H(Cn, C) lives in even de grees 
only and is isomorphic to gr(Center (C[Sn])) under the age ltration (with double d degrees). 
Proof. Let us sketch a noncomm utativ e-algeb raic proof of this theorem, given in [EG]. This 
proof is based on the following result. 
83</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>(x(0), p(0)). Then xi(t) are the eigen values of the matrix Xt := X0 +2tY0, and pi(t)= 
x
i(t)/2. 
9.4. Proof of Wilsons theorem. Let us now give a proof of Theorem 9.5. 
We have alrea dy shown that all comp onents of Cn are smooth and have dimension 2n. 
Also, we know that there is at least one comp onent (the closure of Un), and that the other 
comp onents, if they exist, do not contain pairs (X, Y ) in which X is regular semisimple . 
contained in the hypersurface (X) 
(X ) stands for the discriminan t of X (i.e., (X):= (xi  xj ), where xi are thei=j 
eigen values of X). 
Thus, to show that such additional comp onents dont in fact exist, it suces to show that 
the dimension of the subsc heme Cn(0) cut out in Cn by the equation (X)=0 is 2n  1. 
To do so, rst notice that the conditi on rank ([X, Y ] + 1) = 1 is equiv alent to the equa
tion 2([X, Y ] + 1) = 0; thus, the latter can be used as the equation denin g Cn inside 
T Matn/P GLn. 
0 (we use the ltrati on on O(Cn
0CThis means that these comp onents
 0, where
 are
 =
Dene C
:= Spec(grO(Cn)) to be the degeneration of Cn )
n 
dened by deg(X) = 0, deg(Y ) = 1). Then C0 is a closed subsc heme in the schemen 
out by the equations 2([X, Y ])=0 in T Matn
0 0 0 
nC C Ccut
n 
/PGLn. 
Let (
)red be the reduced part of Then (
)red coincides with the categorical quotien t .
n n
{(X, Y )|rank ([X, Y ])  1}/PGLn.
Our proof is based on the following proposition.
Prop osition 9.9. The categoric al quotient {(X, Y )|rank ([X, Y ])  1}/PGLn coincides with 
the categoric al quotient {(X, Y )|[X, Y ]=0}/PGLn. 
Proof. It is clear that {(X, Y )|[X, Y ]=0}/PGLn is contained in {(X, Y )|rank ([X, Y ]) 
1}/PGLn. For the proof of the opposite inclusion we need to show that any regular function 
on {(X, Y )|rank ([X, Y ])  1}/PGLn is completely determined by its values on the subvariety 
{(X, Y )|[X, Y ]=0}/PGLn, i.e. that any invarian t polynom ial on the set of pairs of matrices 
with comm utator of rank at most 1 is complet ely determined by its values on pairs of 
comm uting matrices. To this end, we need the following lemma from linear algebra. 
Lemma 9.10. If A, B are squar e matric es such that [A, B] has rank  1, then there exists 
a basis in which both A, B are upper triangular. 
Proof. Without loss of generalit y, we can assume ker A =0 (by replacing A with A   if 
needed) and that A = 0. It suc es to show that there exists a proper nonzero subspace 
invarian t under A, B; then the statemen t will follow by induction in dimension. 
Let C =[A, B] and supp ose rank C = 1 (since the case rank C = 0 is trivial). If ker A 
ker C, then ker A is B-invarian t: if Av = 0 then ABv = BAv + Cv = 0. Thus ker A is the 
required subspace. If ker A  ker C, then there exists a vector v such that Av = 0 but Cv = 0. 
So ABv = Cv =0. Thus ImC  ImA. So ImA is B-invarian t: BAv = ABv + Cv  ImA. 
So ImA is the required subspace. 
This proves the lemma.  
Now we are ready to prove Prop osition 9.9. By the fundamen tal theorem of invarian t 
theory , the ring of invarian ts of X and Y is generated by traces of words of X and Y : 
Tr(w(X, Y )). If X and Y are upper triangular with eigen values xi,yi, then any such trace 
79</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>9.3. The Calogero-Moser integrable system. Let M be a symplectic variety, and let 
H1,...,Hn be regular functions on M such that {Hi,Hj } = 0 and His are algebraically 
indep enden t everywhere. Assume that M carries a symplectic action of a reductiv e algebraic 
group G with momen t map  : M g, which preserv es the functions Hi, and let O be 
a coadj oint orbit of G. Assume that G acts freely on 1(O), and so the Calogero-Moser 
space R(M, G, O) is symplectic. The functions Hi descend to R(M, G, O). If they are still 
algebraically indep enden t and n = dim R(M, G, O)/2, then we get an integrable system on 
R(M, G, O). 
A vivid example of this is the Kazhdan-Kostan t-Stern berg construction of the Calogero-
Moser system. In this case M = T Matn(C) (regarded as the set of pairs of matrices (X, Y ) 
as in Section 9.2), with the usual symplectic form  = Tr (dY  dX). Let Hi = Tr(Y i), 
i =1,...,n. Let G = PGLn(C) act on M by conjugation, and let O be the coadjoin t 
orbit of G considered in Subsection 9.2. Then the system H1,...,Hn descends to a system 
of functions in involution on R(M, G, O), which is the Calogero-Moser space Cn. Since 
this space is 2n-dimensional, H1,...,Hn form an integrable system on Cn. It is called the 
(rational) Calo gero-Moser system . 
The Calogero-Moser ow is, by denition, the Hamiltonian ow on Cn dened by the 
Hamiltonian H = H2 = Tr(Y 2). Thus this ow is integrable, in the sense that it can be 
included in an integrable system. In particular, its solutions can be found in quadratures 
using the inductiv e procedure of reduction of order. However (as often happ ens with systems 
obtained by reduction), solutions can also be found by a much simple r procedure, since 
they can be found already on the non-reduced space M: indeed, on M the Calogero-
Moser ow is just the motion of a free particle in the space of matrices, so it has the form 
gt(X, Y )=(X +2Y t,Y ). The same formula is valid on Cn. In fact, we can use the same 
metho d to compute the ows corre sponding to all the Hamiltonians Hi = Tr(Y i), i  N: 
these ows are given by the formulas 
gt (i)(X, Y )=(X + iY i1t, Y ). 
Let us write the Calogero-Moser system explicitly in coordinates. To do so, we rst need 
to introduce local coordinates on the Calogero-Moser space Cn. 
To this end, let us restrict our attention to the open set Un which consists of Cn 
conjugacy classes of those pairs (X, Y ) for which the matrix X is diagonalizable, with distinct 
eigen values; by Wilsons Theorem 9.5, this open set is dense in Cn. 
A point P  Un may be represen ted by a pair (X, Y ) such that X = diag(x1,...,xn), 
xi = xj . In this case, the entries of T := XY  YX are (xi  xj )yij . In particular, the 
diagonal entries are zero. Since the matrix T + 1 has rank 1, its entries ij have the form 
aibj for some numbers ai,bj . On the other hand, ii = 1, so bj = a
j 1 and hence ij = aia
j 1 . 
By conjugating (X, Y ) by the matrix diag(a1,...,an), we can reduce to the situation when 
ai = 1, so ij = 1. Hence the matrix T has entries 1  ij (zeros on the diagonal, ones o 
the diagonal). Moreo ver, the represen tative of P with diagonal X and T as above is unique 
up to the action of the symmetric group Sn. Finally , we have (xi  xj )yij = 1 for i =j, so 
the entries of the matrix Y are yij =1/(xi  xj) if i =j. On the other hand, the diagonal 
entries yii of Y are unconstrained. Thus we have obtained the following result. 
Prop osition 9.6. Let Cn be the open set of (x1,...,xn)  Cn such that xi =xj for i =j.reg 
Then there exists an isomorphism of algebr aic varieties  : T (Cn /Sn) Un given by the reg
77</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Macdonald-Mehta integral</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-735-double-affine-hecke-algebras-in-representation-theory-combinatorics-geometry-and-mathematical-physics-fall-2009/resources/mit18_735f09_ch04/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Theorem 4.17. Consider the stratic ation of h with respect to stabilizers of points in W . 
Then the support supp (M) of any object M of Oc(W, h) in h is a union of strata of this 
stratic ation. 
This makes one wonder which strata occur in supp (Lc()), for given c and . In [VV], 
Varagnolo and Vasserot gave a partial answ er for  = C. Namely, they determined (for W 
being a Weyl group) when Lc(C) is nite dimensional, which is equiv alent to supp (Lc(C)) = 
0. For the proof (whic h is quite complicated), they used the geometry ane Springer bers. 
Here we will give a dieren t (and simpler) proof. In fact, we will prove a more general result. 
Recall that for any Coxeter group W , we have the Poincar e polynomial: 
r
PW (q)=  
q (w) =  1  qdi(W ) 
, where di(W ) are the degrees of W. 
wW i=1 1  q 
Lemma 4.18. If W   W is a parabolic subgroup of W , then PW is divisible by PW  . 
Proof. By Chev alleys theorem, C[h] is a free module over C[h]W and C[h]W  is a direct 
summand in this module. So C[h]W  is a projectiv e module, thus free (since it is graded). 
Hence, there exists a polynomial Q(q) such that we have 
Q(q)hC[h]W (q)= hC[h]W  (q), 
where hV (q) denotes the Hilbert series of a graded vector space V . Notice that we have 
1 hC[h]W (q)= ,sowehave PW (q)(1  q)r 
Q(q) 
PW (q) = 1 
PW  (q), i.e. Q(q) = PW (q)/PW  (q). 
 
Corollary 4.19. If m  2 then we have the following inequality: 
#{i|m divides di(W )} #{i|m divides di(W )}. 
Proof. This follows from Lemma 4.18 by looking at the roots of the polynomials PW and 
PW  .  
Our main result is the following theorem . 
Theorem 4.20. [E3] Let c  0. Then a  supp (Lc(C)) if and only if 
PW (e 2ic)=0. PWa 
We can obtain the following corollary easily . 
Corollary 4.21. (i) Lc(C) = Mc(C) if and only if c  Q&gt;0 and the denominator m of 
c divides di for some i; 
(ii) Lc(C) is nite dimensional if and only if PW (e2ic)=0, i.e., i PW  
#{i|m divides di(W )} &gt; #{i|m divides di(W )}. 
for any maximal parabolic subgroup W   W . 
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>4. The Macdonald-Meht a integral
4.1. Finite Coxeter groups and the Macdonald-Meh ta integral. Let W be a nite 
Coxeter group of rank r with real reection represen tation hR equipp ed with a Euclidean 
W -invarian t inner product (, ). Denote by h the complexication of hR. The reec tion 
hyperplanes subdivide hR into |W | chambers; let us pick one of them to be the dominan t 
chamber and call its interior D. For each reection h yperplane, pick the perpendicular v ector 
  hR with (, ) = 2 which has positiv e inner products with elemen ts of D, and call it 
the positiv e root corresp onding to this hyperplane. The walls of D are then dened by the 
equations (i,v) = 0, where i are simple roots. Denote by S the set of reections in W , 
and for a reection s S denote by s the corresp onding positiv e root. Let 
(x)= (s, x) 
sS 
be the corresp onding discriminan t polynomial. Let di,i =1,...,r, be the degrees of the 
generators of the algebra C[h]W . Note that W = i di.|| 
k Let H1,c(W, h) be the rational Cherednik algebra of W . Here we choose c = asa 
constan t function. Let Mc = Mc(C) be the polynomial represen tation of H1,c(W, h), and c 
be the contravarian t form on Mc dened in Section 3.12. We normalize it by the condition 
c(1, 1) = 1. 
Theorem 4.1. (i) (The Macdonald-Mehta integral) For Re (k)  0, one has 
 r (1 + kdi)(4.1) (2)r/2 
hR e(x,x)/2|(x)|2kdx = (1 + k) . 
i=1 
(ii) Let b(k) := c(, ). Then 
rdi1
b(k)= |W | (kdi + m). 
i=1 m=1 
For Weyl groups, this theorem was proved by E. Opdam [Op1]. The non-crystallographic 
cases were done by Opdam in [Op2] using a direct computation in the rank 2 case (reducing 
(4.1) to the beta integral by passing to polar coordinates), and a computer calculation by F. 
Garv an for H3 and H4. 
Example 4.2. In the case W = Sn, we have the following integral (the Mehta integral): 
 n
(2)(n1)/2 e(x,x)/2  
2kdx =  (1 + kd) . 
{xRn| P 
i xi=0}|xi  xj |(1 + k)i=j d=2 
In the next subsection, we give a uniform proof of Theorem 4.1 which is given in [E2]. We 
emphasize that many parts of this proof are borrowed from Opdams previous proof of this 
theorem. 
4.2. Proof of Theorem 4.1. 
Prop osition 4.3. The function b is a polynomial of degree at most |S|, and the roots of b 
are negative rational numb ers. 
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Since limx+(log ) = 0, (log F )  0, and  is periodic, we have (log )  0. Since n+1 
(log )dx = 0, we see that (log )  0. So we have (x)  1.  n 
In particular, we see from Corollary 4.8 and the multiplication formulas for the  function 
that part (ii) of Theorem 4.1 implies part (i). 
It remains to establish (ii). 
Prop osition 4.11. The polynomial b has degree exactly |S|. 
Proof. By Prop osition 4.3, b is a polynomial of degree at most |S|. To see that the degree is 
precisely |S|, let us make the change of variable x = k1/2y in the Macdonald-Meh ta integral 
and use the steep est descen t metho d. We nd that the leading term of the asymptot ics of 
log F (k) as k  + is |S|k log k. This together with the Stirling formula and Corollary 4.8 
implies the stateme nt.  
Prop osition 4.12. The function 
r 1  e2ikdj 
G(k) := F (k) 2ik 1  ej=1 
analytic ally continues to an entir e function of k. 
Proof. Let   D be an elemen t. Consider the real hyperplane Ct = it + hR, t&gt; 0. Then 
Ct does not intersect reection hyperplanes, so we have a continuous branc h of (x)2k on 
Ct which tends to the positiv e branc h in D as t 0. Then, it is easy to see that for any  
2ik(w)w  W , the limit of this branc h in the chamber w(D) will be e|(x)|2k, where (w) is 
the length of w. Therefore, by letting t = 0, we get 
1  
(2)r/2 e(x,x)/2(x)2kdx = F (k)( e 2ik(w)) 
Ct |W | wW 
(as this integral does not depend on t by Cauc hys theorem). But it is well known that 
2ik(w) r1  e2ikdj 
e = ,1  e2ik 
wW j=1 
([Hu], p.73), so  
(2)r/2|W | 
Ct e(x,x)/2(x)2kdx = G(k). 
Since Ct e(x,x)/2(x)2kdx is clearly an entire function, the statem ent is proved. 
Corollary 4.13. For every k0  [1, 0] the total multiplicity of all the roots of b of the 
form k0  p, p  Z+, equals the numb er of ways to represent k0 in the form m/di, m = 
1,...,di  1. In other words, the roots of b are ki,m = m/di  pi,m, 1  m  di  1, wher e 
pi,m  Z+. 
Proof. We have 
G(k  p)= F (k) r1  e2ikdj 
,b(k  1) b(k  p) j=1 1  e2ik  
29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Prop osition 4.26. 
supp (cW )= {a  hRFWa (c)=0} = {a  hRPW (e 2ic)=0} | FW |PWa 
= {a  hR|#{i|denominator of c divides di(W )}
=#{i|denominator of c divides di(Wa)}}. 
Proof. First note that the last equalit y follows from the product formula for the Poincar e 
polynomial, and the second equalit y from the Macdonald-Meh ta identity. Now let us prove 
the rst equalit y. 
Look at W near a  h. Equiv alently, we can consid er c 
(2)r/2
W (x + a)= FW (c) |(x + a)|2c
c 
with x near 0. We have 
W (x + a)= s(x + a)= (s(x)+ s(a)) 
sS sS 
= s(x) (s(x)+ s(a))  
sSWa sS\SWa 
= Wa (x) (x), 
where  is a nonvanishing function near a (since s(a)=0 if s/S Wa). 
So near a, we have 
W FWa Wa 2c 
c (x + a)= FW (c)  (x) ||,c 
and the last factor is well den ed since  is nonvanishing. Thus cW (x) is nonzero near a if 
and only if FWa (c) = 0 which nishes the proof.  FW 
Prop osition 4.27. For c  0, 
supp (cW ) = supp Lc(C)R, 
wher e the right hand side stands for the real points of the support. 
Proof. Let a/ supp Lc(C) and assume a  supp W . Then we can nd a P  Jc(C) = ker c c 
such that P (a) = 0. Pick a compactly supp orted test function    C(hR) such that P does c 
not vanish anywhere on supp , and W ,= 0 (this can be done since P (a) = 0 and W 
c c 
is nonzero near a). Then we have /P  S(hR). Thus from Lemma 4.25 (i) it follows that 
there exists a sequence of polynomials Pn such that 
Pn(x)ex2/2  P in S(hR), when n . 
So PPnex2/2   in S(hR), when n . 
But we have cW ,PPnex2/2 = c(P, Pn) = 0 which is a contradiction. This implies that 
supp cW  (supp Lc(C))R. 
To show the opposite inclu sion, let P be a polynomial on h which vanishes identically on 
supp W . By Lemma 4.25 (ii), there exists N such that W ,P N (x)Q (x)ex2/2 = 0. Thus, c c 
34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Prop osition 4.7. For Re (k)  0 we have 
(4.3) c(f, g)= F (k)1 f(x)g(x)dc(x) 
hR 
wher e 
dc(x) := e(x,x)/2|(x)|2kdx. 
Proof. It follows from Prop osition 4.6 that c is uniquely , up to scaling, determ ined by the 
condition that it is W -invarian t, and y= xa  ya. These properties are easy to check for the a 
right hand side of (4.3), using the fact that the action of ya is given by Dunkl operators.  
Now we can comp lete the proof of Prop osition 4.4. By Prop osition 4.7, we have 
F (k +1) = F (k)c(, ), 
so by (4.2) we have 
F (k +1) = F (k)b(k). 
Let 
b(k)= b0 (k + ki)ni .
We know that ki &gt; 0, and also b0 &gt; 0 (because the inner product 0 on real polynomials is 
positiv e denite). 
Corollary 4.8. We have ni  (k + ki)F (k)= bk 
0 . (ki)i 
Proof. Denote the right hand side by F(k) and let (k)= F (k)/F(k). Clearly , (0) = 1. 
Prop osition 4.4 implies that (k) is a 1-periodic positiv e function on [0, ). Also by the 
Cauc hy-Schwarz inequalit y, 
F (k)F (k)  F ((k + k)/2)2 , 
so log F (k) is convex for k  0. This implies that  = 1, since (log F(k))  0 as k 
+.  
Remark 4.9. The proof of this corollary is motiv ated by the standard proof of the following 
well known characterization of the  function. 
Prop osition 4.10. The  function is determine d by three properties: 
(i) (x) is positive on [1, +) and (1) = 1; 
(ii) (x +1) = x(x); 
(iii) log (x) is a convex function on [1, +). 
Proof. It is easy to see from the denition (x)= 0  tx1etdt that the  function has 
properties (i) and (ii); property (iii) follows from this denition and the Cauc hy-Schwarz 
inequalit y. 
Conversely, supp ose we have a function F (x) satisfying the above properties, then we have 
F (x)= (x)(x) for some 1-periodic functi on (x) with (x) &gt; 0. Thus, we have 
(log F ) = (log ) + (log ). 
28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.735 Double Affine Hecke Algebras in Representation Theory, Combinatorics, Geometry, 
and Mathematical Physics 
Fall 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>for any polynomial Q, c(P N ,Q) = 0, i.e. P N  Ker c. Thus, P |supp Lc(C) = 0. This implies 
the required inclusion, since supp cW is a union of strata.  
Theorem 4.20 follows from Prop osition 4.26 and Prop osition 4.27.  
4.4. Notes. Our exposition in Sections 4.1 and 4.2 follows the paper [E2]; Section 4.3 follows 
the paper [E3]. 
35</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Now plug in k = 1+ k0 and a large positiv e integer p. Since by Prop osition 4.12 the left 
hand side is regular, so must be the right hand side, which implies the claimed upper bound 
for the total multiplicit y, as F (1 + k0) &gt; 0. The fact that the bound is actually attained 
follows from the fact that the polynomial b has degree exactly |S| (Prop osition 4.11), and 
the fact that all roots of b are negativ e rational (Prop osition 4.3).  
It remains to show that in fact in Corollary 4.13, pi,m = 0 for all i, m; this would imply 
(ii) and hence (i). 
Prop osition 4.14. Identity (4.1) of Theorem 4.1 is satise d in C[k]/k2 . 
Proof. Indeed, we clearly have F (0) = 1. Next, a rank 1 computation gives F (0) = |S|, 
where  is the Euler constan t (i.e.  = limn+(1+ +1/n  log n)), while the deriv ative  
of the right hand side of (4.1) at zero equals to 
r
 (di  1). 
i=1 
But it is well known that 
r
(di  1) = |S|, 
i=1 
([Hu], p.62), which implies the result.  
Prop osition 4.15. Identity (4.1) of Theorem 4.1 is satise d in C[k]/k3 . 
Note that Prop osition 4.15 immediately implies (ii), and hence the whole theorem. Indeed, 
it yields that 
rdi1
(log F )(0) = (log )(m/di), 
i=1 m=1 
so by Corollary 4.13 
r rdi1 di1 
(log )(m/di + pi,m) = (log )(m/di), 
i=1 m=1 i=1 m=1 
which implies that pi,m = 0 since (log ) is strictly decreasing on [0, ). 
To prove Prop osition 4.15, we will need the following result about nite Coxeter groups. 
Let (W )=3|S|2  r (d2  1).i=1i 
Lemma 4.16. One has 
(4.4) (W )= (G), 
GPar2(W ) 
wher e Par 2(W ) is the set of parabolic subgroups of W of rank 2. 
Proof. Let 
r
Q(q)= |W | 11 
 
qq . di 
i=1 
30</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Remark 4.22. Varagnolo and Vasserot prove that Lc(C) is nite dimensional if and only if 
there exists a regular elliptic elemen t in W of order m. Case-b y-case inspection shows that 
this condition is equiv alent to the combinatorial condition of (2). Also, a uniform proof of 
this equiv alence is given in the appendix to [E3], written by S. Grieth. 
Example 4.23. For type An1, i.e., W = Sn, we get that Lc(C) is nite dimensional if and 
only if the denominator of c is n. This agrees with our previous results in type An1. 
Example 4.24. Supp ose W is the Coxeter group of type E7. Then we have the following 
list of maximal parab olic subgroups and the degrees (note that E7 itself is not a maximal 
parab olic). 
Subgroups E7 D6 A3  A2  A1 A6 
Degrees 2,6,8,10,12,14,18 2,4,6,6,8,10 2,3,4,2,3,2 2,3,4,5,6,7 
Subgroups A4  A2 E6 D5  A1 A5  A1 
Degrees 2,3,4,5,2,3 2,5,6,8,9,12 2,4,5,6,8,2 2,3,4,5,6,2 
So Lc(C) is nite dimensional if and only if the denominator of c is 2, 6, 14, 18. 
The rest of the subsection is dedicated to the proof of Theorem 4.20. First we recall some 
basic facts about the Schwartz space and temp ered distributions. 
Let S(Rn) be the set of Schwartz functions on Rn, i.e. 
S(Rn)= {f  C(Rn)|, , sup |x  f(x)| &lt; }. 
This space has a natural topology . 
A temp ered distributio n on Rn is a continuous linear functional on S(Rn). Let S(Rn) 
denote the space of temp ered distributio ns. 
We will use the following well known lemma. 
Lemma 4.25. (i) C[x]ex2/2  S(Rn) is a dense subsp ace. 
(ii)	Any temp ered distribution  has nite order, i.e., N = N() such that if f  S(Rn) 
satisfying f =df = =dN1f =0 on supp , then , f =0.  
Proof of Theorem 4.20. Recall that on Mc(C), we have the Gaussian form c from Section 
4.2. We have for Re (c)  0, 
(P, Q)= (2)r/2 
ex2/2(x)2cP (x)Q (x)dx, cFW (c) hR ||
where P, Q are polynomials and 
FW (k) = (2)r/2 ex2/2|(x)|2kdx 
hR 
is the Macdonald-Meh ta integral. 
Consider the distribu tion: 
cW = (2)r/2 
(x)2c . FW (c) ||
It is well-kno wn that this distribution is meromorphic in c (Bernsteins theorem). More over, 
since c(P, Q) is a polynomial in c for any P and Q, this distribution is in fact holomorphic 
in c  C. 
33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>It follows from Chev alleys theorem that
Q(q) = (1  q)r det(1  qw|h)1 . 
wW 
Let us subtract the terms for w = 1 and w S from both sides of this equation, divide both 
sides by (q  1)2, and set q = 1 (cf. [Hu], p.62, formula (21)). Let W2 be the set of elemen ts 
of W that can be written as a product of two dieren t reections. Then by a straigh tforw ard 
computation we get 
1  1 (W )= . 24 wW2 r  Tr h(w) 
In particular, this is true for rank 2 groups. The result follows, as any elemen t w  W2 
belongs to a unique parabolic subgroup Gw of rank 2 (nam ely, the stabilizer of a generic 
point hw, [Hu], p.22).  
Proof of Proposition 4.15. Now we are ready to prove the proposition. By Prop osition 4.14, 
it suces to show the coincidence of the second deriv atives of (4.1) at k = 0. The second 
deriv ative of the right hand side of (4.1) at zero is equal to 
2 r
6(d2  1) + 2|S|2 .i 
i=1 
On the other hand, we have 
F (0) = (2)r/2 e(x,x)/2 log 2(x) log 2(x)dx. 
,S hR 
Thus, from a rank 1 computation we see that our job is to establish the equalit y 
 r
(2)r/2  
e(x,x)/2 log 2(x) log 2
2(
(x
x)
)dx = 
6 2 
(  
(di 2  1)  3|S|2)=  
6 2 
(W ). 
=S hR i=1 
Since this equalit y holds in rank 2 (as in this case (4.1) reduces to the beta integral), in 
general it reduces to equation (4.4) (as for any  =   S, s and s are contained in a 
unique parab olic subgroup of W of rank 2). The proposition is proved.  
4.3. Application: the supp orts of Lc(C). In this subsection we will use the Macdonald-
Mehta integral to comput ation of the supp ort of the irreducible quotien t of the polynoamial 
represen tation of a rational Cherednik algebra (with equal parameters). We will follow the 
paper [E3]. 
First note that the vector space h has a stratication labeled by parab olic subgr oups of W . 
Indeed, for a parab olic subgroup W   W , let hW  be the set of points in h whose stabilizer reg 
is W . Then  
h = hW  ,reg 
W Par(W ) 
where Par(W ) is the set of parab olic subgroups in W . 
For a nitely generated module M over C[h], denote the supp ort of M by supp (M). 
The following theorem is proved in [Gi1], Section 6 and in [BE] with dieren t metho d. We 
will recall the proof from [BE] later. 
31</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Proof. Since  has degree |S|, it follows from the denition of b that it is a polynomial of 
degree  |S|. 
Supp ose that b(k) = 0 for some k  C. Then c(, P ) = 0 for any polynomi al P . Indeed, 
if there exists a P such that c(, P ) = 0, then there exists such a P which is antisymmetric 
of degree |S|. Then P must be a multiple of  which contradicts the equalit y c(, ) = 0. 
Thus, Mc is reducible and hence has a singular vector, i.e. a nonzero homogeneou s poly
nomial f of positiv e degree d living in an irreducible represen tation  of W killed by ya. 
Applying the element h = i xai yai + r/2+ ks to f, we get sS 
d ,k = m 
where m is the eigen value of the operator T := (1  s) on . But it is clear (by sS
computing the trace of T ) that m  0 and m  Q. This implies that any root of b is 
negativ e rational.  
Denote the Macdon ald-Meh ta integral by F (k). 
Prop osition 4.4. One has 
F (k +1) = b(k)F (k). 
Proof. Let F = i ya2 
i /2. Introduce the Gaussian inner product on Mc as follows: 
Denition 4.5. The Gaussian inner product c on Mc is given by the formula 
c(v, v)= c(exp(F)v, exp(F)v). 
This makes sense because the operator F is locally nilpotent on Mc. Note that  is a 
nonzero W -antisymmetric polynomial of the smallest possible degree, so ( ya2 
i ) = 0 and 
hence 
(4.2) c(, )= c(, )= b(k). 
For a  h, let xa  h  H1,c(W, h), ya  h  H1,c(W, h) be the corresp onding generators 
of the rational Cherednik algebra. 
Prop osition 4.6. Up to scaling, c is the unique W -invariant symmetric biline ar form on 
Mc satisfying the condition 
c((xa  ya)v, v)= c(v, yav),a  h. 
Proof. We have 
c((xa  ya)v, v)= c(exp(F)(xa  ya)v, exp(F)v)= c(xa exp(F)v, exp(F)v) 
= c(exp(F)v, ya exp(F)v)= c(exp(F)v, exp(F)yav)= c(v, yav). 
Let us now show uniqueness. If  is any W -invarian t symmetric bilinear form satisfying 
the condition of the Prop osition, then let (v, v)= (exp(F)v, exp(F)v). Then  is 
contravarian t, so its a multiple of c, hence  is a multiple of c.  
Now we will need the following known result (see [Du2], Theorem 3.10). 
27</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
