<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-638-drawings-numbers-five-centuries-of-digital-design-fall-2002/</course_url>
    <course_title>Drawings &amp; Numbers: Five Centuries of Digital Design</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Architecture </list>
      <list>Mathematics </list>
      <list>Fine Arts </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lecture 1: Introduction: Drawings, Numbers, and the Power of (Printed) Images (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-638-drawings-numbers-five-centuries-of-digital-design-fall-2002/resources/lecture_1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1-2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>far more compact and efficient way of coun ting as well a system that accounts for zero. 
Concurrently, makers of ephemeral materi als (playing cards, te xtiles and devotional 
materials) employ mass produced printed imag es for widespread distribution. In both 
cases, the humanists were slow to upgrade their software.  
  
The decimal notation is introduced to Eur ope by Simon Stevinus in 1585 but was not 
employed by such architects as Pallad io, Michelangelo, Vignola and Serlio. 
Michelangelo, for his other liberal talents, proves himself to be a very poor handler of 
numbers. All of these architects operated on a modular system in which, for instance, 
diameters of column are used as the measurem ent of the rest of the orders components. 
In fact no treatise tried to decimalize the or ders until a pathbreaking 1844 effort in the 
Ecole des Beaux Artes (of Belgium). While the importance of this decimalization of the 
orders did not prove to constitute one of the seminal moments of architectural history, 
one can observe a general rise in numer acy in architectural drawings in the 17th and 18th 
centuries. Numbers eventually gain supremacy as the favored bearers of information in 
architectural drawings. Dig ital communication is not new. Our current moment has 
experienced a case of much more of the sa me steady digitization, and at some point a 
change in scale is a change in nature, not me rely relation. A further aim of the course will 
be to ask what this dig ital future may look like. 
  
Printed images constitute a watershed moment in the history of architectural theory. The 
new process of xylography (the woodcut) can produce hundreds of reliab le copies from a 
single image before the origin al loses fidelity. While the t echnology crystallized in this 
particular form, other similar reproductive techno logies were extant at or before this time 
in the form of coins and seals of antiquity.  
  
&gt;1390-1430 Cenninis Libro dellArte contains a chapter on printing.  
  
&gt;1410 The tapestry of Sion, which was produced in Northern Italy, exhibits a repetitive 
printed pattern.    
  
&gt;1416-18 Devotional images in Flanders of the Madonna surrounded by saints still exist 
in several copies. 
  
&gt;1430s Archival evidence in Florence a nd Venice of printed playing cards. 
  
The curious route of the technology as it relates to the printed and illustrated architectural 
treatise can be observed from th e situation of Alberti. Albe rti lived in an environment 
where printed images were already pres ent and possibly conspicuous . His own 
architectural treatise De Re Aedificatoria , written in manuscript form around 1450 does 
not rely on the use of images, but instead takes great pride in verbal description of visual 
material. Alberti made only passing reference to printing with movabl e types late in his 
life, exhibiting a wait-and-s ee attitude. Images, whether printed from woodcuts or 
copied by an amanuensis, were not part  of Albertis program. Hand copying is 
untrustworthy and mechanical imaging is not imagined. Alberti did not immediately 
know of Gutenbergs almost co eval invention of the printi ng press with moveable type.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 1:  Introduction: Drawings, numbers, a nd the power of (printed) images. 
 
Transcribed by Chris Muskopf.  
 
  
Immediately we find the prof essor amending the title of the course to include an 
additional twenty centuries of the history of digital design than the students have signed 
on for.  
  
The course will take into account several t housand years and multiple circuits through a 
feedback loop in architectural history in order to trace the ideal of digital design. This 
feedback loop is important in the transmission of architectural ideas as a tradition--a body 
of knowledge that is passed across place and time. The feedback loop poses two 
questions; what can technology provide and wha t will be received by culture. It is 
important to note that there is  no universality or neutrality in the modes of transmission 
and these aspects come to influence the product.  As an example, consider the medium of 
black and white photography; the absence of  polychromatic transmission ostensibly 
makes the transmission of color much less im portant, even to the point of banishment 
into cultural oblivion. In a pub lic discipline such as architecture, there is generally no 
point in creating something no one will see. 
  
While medieval master masons served as both construction superv isor and architect on-
site and in real-time, Leon Battista Alberti first posited and theorized that architectural 
design and building site may exist many miles apart, and that architecture may--or 
should--be built by remote control. The examination of the watershed event of Alberti 
will receive many reprisals in the course. The course will also posit two hypotheses: 
  
1. We are in the process of moving from an analog past to a digital future. As an 
aside to this, we have witnessed a retreat from the original digital enthusiasm of 
the last few years, especially in accord ance with the rising and falling of world 
economic markets and indicators. What c ould reasonably be expected next is a 
where we went wrong period of self- doubt from the digital enthusiast camp. 
The professor prefers to see the long duration of digiter acy that is a slow upward 
curve beginning after the renaissance.  
  
2. The 16th century was dominated by printed imag es and it is in this time that the 
struggle between digital methods of design and geometric methods can be 
observed in an especially fruitful manner.  Architectural treati ses are evidence of a 
two-century battle betwee n drawings and numbers. 
  
  
The humanists of the 16th century were particularly devoted  to all things antique, and this 
manifest itself also in a strange way th rough the continued use of Roman numerals, 
which proved quite clumsy for computing. In fact, two advanced technologies of the time 
were overlooked by humanists and were instead the domain of the less refined circles. At 
this time, the merchant class can be obse rved using the Hindu-Ar abic number system, a</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Not only was the mechanical reproduction of words a novelty to the Florentine 
humanists, but also the prin ting of both words and images on the same page was even 
more remote. The first architectural books ar e printed in Rome with the publication of De 
Architectura  by Vitruvius. The first ar chitectural work with c ohabiting printed image and 
printed text debuts in Regens burg in 1486 in the manifestati on of Matthias von Roriczers 
Gothic quasi-treatise on how to build a spire. This timeline demonstrates that Alberti, 
modern as he was, produced an architectural  treatise without inte ntion to engage two 
potent technologies for disseminating his ideas:  the printed word and the printed image. 
To use the term media savvy before its time requires an introduction of Sebastiano 
Serlio into the discussion. He would arise as the first theorist  to write specifically for the 
medium of printing and mass reproduction.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lecture 4: Alberti&#8217;s Improbable Image-making Technologies (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-638-drawings-numbers-five-centuries-of-digital-design-fall-2002/resources/lecture_4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7-8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 4: Alberti's improbable image-making technologies. 
 
Transcribed by Kyle Steinfeld. 
  
 
Review:  
 
The ability to accurately transmit verbal info rmation in time in space marks the beginning 
of history. The ability to accu rately transmit visual information in time and space marks 
the beginning of the modern er a. The transmission of this information may be described 
as being either analog[ 1] or digital[2].   
 
The written alphabet can be seen as a code  or algorithm that insures the accurate 
reproduction of verbal information. It is digita l in that information is represented as a 
sequence of discrete symbols from a finite se t, and each copy made is essentially exactly 
like the original. The alphabet is a replacem ent for a less efficient analog system of 
transmitting verbal information: the spoken word.   
 
The oral system is an analog method for transm itting verbal information in that some part 
of the world, like an event, is recorded in an individuals memory which is more 
mobile in time and space than the event. Thes e two, the event and the record of it, occupy 
the same level of abstraction:  they are both in the world and can altered by the world.  
They are both analogs of each other. In th is system, each copy made will degrade the 
original data. 
 
It is perhaps this instance, this shift from or al to written systems that marks the beginning 
of history, that is the basis of the prevalen t assumption that digital forms of transmission 
are the inevitable evolution of the less efficient analog forms of transmission. A close 
examination of the details of a more recent shift that into the transmission of visual 
information, reveals a more complex relationship.   
 
 Before mechanical methods of reproduction we re developed, images were regarded as an 
unreliable method of storing and transmitting technical and scientific knowledge. This 
was due largely to the inhere nt unpredictability of analog methods of reproduction of the 
time. In effect, this positioned rhetoric as  the preferred means of transmission, while 
images were to be resorted to only by thos e without the ability to  describe their topic 
verbally. Still, the need for accurately repr oducing images did exist before a technology 
successfully fulfilled it (the analog prin ting press), and in the meantime many 
unsuccessful technologies were floating about: bo th analog and digital.  The inventions of 
Leon Battista Alberti make a good example. 
 
  
Albertis devices: 
 
In his treatise on sculpture, Alberti doesnt talk  about sculpture so mu ch as he describes a 
machine for making sculpture. Specifically, he describes a machine for making a precise</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>copy of the human body, consisting of a large disk and plumb-bob with which points on a 
live subject can be surveyed. Like Ptolemys point map of the world, the resulting map 
is simply a set of coordinates that can then be used to reproduce an image of the original 
object at another time, place, and scale. Clear ly, this meets the standard for a digital 
process (see footnote). 
 
Albertis first treatise on painting canonizes  central (perspectiv e) projection.  The 
techniques described here seem to me to be  less of a recording and transmission device, 
and more of an artistic techni que. Still, taken in the contex t of the later development of 
parallel projection and the implied position of the viewer to the space of the drawing and 
the idea of the infinite, it is worth a look. 
 
Albertis second chapter in hi s treatise on painting descri bes devices for representing 
non-geometric objects, such as landscapes and the human body. The primary method, 
which has recently been referred to as Alber tis Window, was to position a frame with 
a translucent paper inset between the oneself and the subject and simply trace the object 
through this veil. It has been  suggested that, because a gr id could be applied to the 
resulting image and thereby reproduced square by square as pixels, that this may 
constitute a digital form of  reproduction. However, in that  this method does not record 
and transmit in numbers but in the subjective lines and gestures of the user this is an 
obviously analog process. When seen in th e context of Albertis sometimes unwieldy 
image-making devices, however, it is easy to see why this technique has been 
characterized as digital-read y. Digitalization might in fa ct be seen as a logical 
development of it. 
 
 
 
 -------------------- ------------------------------------------------------------ 
 
[1] Analog is defined as rela ting to, or being a device in which data is represented by 
continuously variable, measurable, physical quan tities, such as leng th, width, voltage, or 
pressure. In an analog system, some physical quality of some part of the world, like an 
amount of light, is recorded in some other physical quality in a smaller, more mobile 
part of the world, like a photo-resistor. These two are at an equal level of abstraction, they are both a measurable part of the world, they are analogs of one another.  In an 
analog system, copies cannot be made wit hout degradation of the original data. 
 
[2] Digital is defined as relati ng to a device that can read, writ e, or store information that 
is represented in numerical form; or as a description of data which is stored or transmitted 
as a sequence of discrete symbols from a finite set, most commonly this means binary 
data represented using electro nic or electromagnetic signals. In a digital system, every 
copy of the original data is  exact, in fact the term original hardly applies.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lecture 3: Alberti and the (Untrustworthy) Power of Man-made Images (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-638-drawings-numbers-five-centuries-of-digital-design-fall-2002/resources/lecture_3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5-6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 3: Alberti and the (untrust worthy) power of man-made images. 
 
Transcribed by B. Alex Miller. 
 
 
When you need something done accurately  Please remove humans. 
The machine  and the media  of reproduction  the attempted removal of the human from 
the process of reproduction. 
 
Within the discussions surrounding Albertis pr oduction of his treatise  and his creation of 
a machine for reproducing the plan of the c ity of Rome in the middle 15th century, one 
consistent derivative theme that underlies portio ns of both developments is the desire for 
removal of subjective human interven tion on the modes of reproduction.   
 
In Albertis documented insistence on the removal of actual illustrations for his 
architectural treatise, the attempt was to summarily remove the subjective results of 
human intervention from the reproduction of this work. Because of written texts 
signifying status, the lack of fidelity inherent in physical human intervention has little 
effect on the true result of the texts m eaning. This is why Albertis request for the 
ablation of illustration is si gnificant:  it is the only input that would be completely 
dependent on physical input from a human. With  its removal, Alberti was trying to assure 
a certain level of fidelity that simply c ould not be maintained through physical human 
input. Alberti also tran sposed the physical pres ence of text to allow for the visualization 
of graphic form, thus eschewing its typical condition within the signi fying structures of 
actual words and phrases: Although this method of transposition of illustration was 
actually relying on the physical  production of the text, ther e was an already a culturally 
established graphic notion that allowed the adequate reproducti on of its graphic presence.  
In other words, Alberti was willing to depend on established social and cultural norms to 
regulate the reproduction of m eaning (words as signifiers)  and the very abstract 
reproduction of graphic composition. In both cases, the human was at least partially 
removed as a subjective contri butor to the reproduction.[1] 
 
Albertis Description of the C ity of Rome also removes the human as much as possible 
from the reproduction process. In this case, the machine devised by Alberti to allow the 
reproduction of the map of Rome (with its ou tput limited to the di gital spectrum of 
reproduction), attempts to remove the subjectivism of human inte rvention even more 
distinctly than the use of text. With the si mple introduction of a digital interface as a 
mode of reproduction, the machine discourages (or disallows in an ideal situation) any 
additional input or notations from the reproducer.  In this se nse, it can be said that the 
machine within Albertis reproductive process is forcing the appropriation of the human 
as a reproductive machine[2]: the human is, by design and intention, only used within a 
linear input to output sequence that transl ates digital information to a graphic 
composition of analog information (the comp leted map itself). The human-as-machine is 
the reproducing tool.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>accuracies in the construction of these classi cal building elements were principles that 
were bound digitally to the very descri ptions of the universe itself.   
 
[4] The human development of reproduction me thod is consistently steeped with this 
quest towards the removal of man from the process. With the advent of newer and faster 
processing capabilities, the overall removal of  man has become easier to accomplish, but 
the analysis of such methods has yielded cert ain production thresholds that illustrate the 
need for some human intervention. For more information on the removal of man and its 
relationship to methods of production please see Manual De Landas War in the Age of 
Intelligent Machines.   
 
[5] A question that could be asked: Was th ere a true objective understanding of the 
removal of man from these pr ocesses, or was it just a mo re abstract notion of higher 
fidelity that could only be reached  through digital methods?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The reference to Ptolemys composition of th e map of the world and its possible effects 
on Albertis processes of digital documentati on are also an interesting commentary on the 
removal of the human from the process of reproduction. The Renaissance cultivated a 
cultural necessity of accuracy: Embedded within the geometric constraints of built 
classical works were the very principles of the cosmos itself[3]. This is what began to 
demand the need for a higher order of fidelity  in reproduction. Ptolemys world map was 
crucial in reducing the factors that contribu te to accumulated error when reproducing an 
image with the reliance on the subjective human. Ptolemys insistence on the physical 
redrawing of the map based on the digital data every time reproduction was undertaken 
was again intentionally appropriating the human as a reproductive machine, thus 
removing the subjective human input[4].    
 
Even within the methods of drawing that we re being developed in the late 15th century; 
i.e., geometric perspective, the removal of man is an issue that permeates the very nature 
of input and output. The geometric perspective allows the removal of the cone of vision; 
the very cone of vision that has its origins in the eye of man. Wit hout the need for this 
cone, and the development of the idea of infi nity or vanishing point, man is not allowed 
to subjectively contribute to th e reproduction process. In f act, man is physically removed 
from the assembly that allows the reproduc tion of image through or  within a projection 
plane. Instead, with the constraint of geomet ry in the construction of three-dimensional 
space, man is once again appropriated only as a machine to record the graphical representation of this geometry. 
 
In all of these cases mentioned above, lim itations in technology would not allow the 
removal of the human from th e initial inputs of data. This , of course, has now changed 
with the methods of sensing and digital documentation becoming as conceptually 
rigorous as the methods of reproduction itself.  The implications of this human removal 
are quite varied, and could be discussed in length (especially in relationship to the 
humanist principles of th e Renaissance)[5].    
 
 
 
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 
 
[1] This could be a possible answer to the question, Why did Alberti resist the inclusion 
of illustration? as addressed in class: In  an underlying way, it was to remove the human 
from the act of reproduction. In this case, it could not be a complete  removal, but only a 
partial one based on the technical constr aints and social norms of the time. 
 
[2] The removal of human is achieved through a transposition of f unction or task. The 
subjective human is replaced by the human-as-machine. 
 
[3] It may be interesting to note that w ith the advent of calculus and descriptive 
mathematics, the universe itself could be c odified and structured completely through 
digital constraints and descriptions. The geometrical principles that would insure</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lecture 6: Image-making Technologies, Architecture, and Identical Replication (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-638-drawings-numbers-five-centuries-of-digital-design-fall-2002/resources/lecture_6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11-12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>compose the setting for a debate over the significance of replication in art. In 1832, 
Quatremere de Quincy wrote De LImitation  or On Imitation  on the problems of exact 
replication. He was among many who becam e nostalgic for the creative imitation of 
previous eras.  
 
Photographs heralded the transference of the physical environment. Replicas of buildings followed this change. In 1858 the bishop of Montreal had the idea to build a replica of St. Peters Basilica (for reasons that might have had to do with the weakening of Papal power in Rome and a widespread search for potential new homes). The bishop sent a team to take accurate measurements of St. Peters in order to reconstruct the 
building. Although a replica had never been attempted before, a complete survey of St. 
Peters had already been conducted and published (in 1620 and 1684). The surveying team from Montreal must have been aware of the earlier survey although it is unclear 
whether or not they used it. Regardless, the architects who reconstructed St. Peters in Montreal did not use photography but they may have been influenced by the idea, 
inherent to photography, of automated, identical reproducibility.  
 
There were many other examples of architectural imitation in the 19th century. By this 
time, the transplanted image of another city had been made publicly palatable by 
photography. In the 1840s, the city of Munich built an exact copy of a Florentine building, The Loggia Dei Lanzi, next to the Palazzo Vecchio. At the end of the 19
th 
century, Nashville Tennessee built two temporary structures to resemble the Parthenon and the Pyramids for the worlds fair. The original replicas had been made as temporary structures out of timber and plaster. They were subsequently removed but then rebuilt in the 1930s out of reinforced concrete.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 6: Image-Making Technologies, Ar chitecture, and Identical Replication.  
  
Transcribed by Yanni Loukissas. 
 
 
Review: 
 
We have learned from previous lectures that Leon Battista Alberti was on a quest for 
objectivity in the reproduction of artifacts. Alberti developed a series of improbable 
technologies to compensate for the unreliable way in which images were reproduced 
and distributed during the 15th century in Italy. We have also learned that printed images, 
the technology which would eventually resolve this problem, was available at the time when Alberti wrote his famous text. However, the idea that printed images could be applied towards serious tasks had not yet been accepted. 
 
A societys failure to fully accept a technology at the time of its invention has been 
dubbed postponed invention by the anthropologist Andre Leroi-Gourhan. Gourhan 
wrote that significant change often doesnt come about as the result of technology until that technology has been widely accepted by a wider cultural environment. This lecture addresses the impact of technologies for image reproduction, first printing and later photography, on architectural imitation in the West. 
 
In 1537, Sebastiano Serlio produced the first widely distributed architectural treatise since the mass adoption of book printing. Unlike Albertis book of one hundred year earlier, Serlios included drawings. Serlios images were drawn to scale and could have been precise enough to construct a building from. However, all of his drawings contain some perspectagle distortion. This suggests that images were not considered an objective means of communication. They were assumed to have a point of view and 
subjectivity. In addition, each image in Se rlios book is supplemented by a redundant 
textual description which includes dimensions. In Serlios book, the ability to accurately 
produce and distribute architectural drawings preceded a trust in the communicative power of drawing.  
 
In 1609, the Franciscan Friar, Bernardino Amico Da Gallipoli, conducted an extensive 
survey of monuments in the Holy Land using orthographic drawings (plan, section, 
elevation). However, buildings were rarely if ever imitated in their entirety until the 19th 
century. Architecture was often imitated at the scale of building components. It was not unusual for column capitols, column bases, and cornices from different historical examples to be combined in one new building. Sometimes, these parts were physically 
plundered from older buildings. In 1762, James Stuart and Nicholas Revett, two 
Englishmen, published the first book ever with accurate drawings of the antiques of Athens, Greece. James Stuart was later credited with building replicas of Athenian antiques in the gardens all over England. However, Stuarts replicas were not exact either. They were creative variations of examples included in his survey. 
 
Following the invention of photography, ideas about architectural imitation changed 
drastically. In the 19th century the visual environment was vastly influenced by ubiquitous 
mechanically reproduced images, either derived from handmade sketched or, more 
often, from photographic, ID EST machine-made, snapshots. Although architects were 
not yet explicitly using photography as a tool for design, this atmosphere helped</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lecture 7: On Some Semi-automatic Machines for the Drawing of the Architectural Orders Oddly Invented in the Seventeenth Century (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-638-drawings-numbers-five-centuries-of-digital-design-fall-2002/resources/lecture_7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13-14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>combustion engine to work properly over the passage of units of time (engine cycles), but 
its only true functioning capability comes from  its place within this cyclical sequence of 
mechanical movements; it is part of a repea ting narrative or tran sposition of movement 
that passes from one mechanical piece of machinery to the ne xt.  Its form derives solely 
in its physical crystallization of its porti on of a narrative. You can  retrieve the data 
embodied in the physical artifact of the cam , but only a portion of the overall functioning 
sequence can be derived, not the conclusion of  the entire sequence. The only meaningful 
data is retrieved at the end of  the sequence that is enacted by the moving physical parts of 
the machine. The sequence is what lends the machine its functionality. 
 
  
Similar to a narrative evolution, the machines for the creation / design of the orders were 
also functionally encapsulated by an implied passage of time. The process of state change 
implies that there is an original state that is  modified in some way; an algorithmic process 
does not necessarily require this original st ate to be changed. The entire result can be 
signified in some kind of resolved algorithm or  mathematical equation. This is in contrast 
to the state-changes that occur through the us e of the machines that are governed by the 
previous step in the process (in the case of  the machine-based process, the subsequent 
movements of each part of the machine define  each state change). The machine can not 
multi-process, or layer one movement on top of the other to collapse the sequence. One 
could look at the algorithmic condition (or at least its algorithmic state) in a much 
different manner. [1] 
 
  
 
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 
 
[1] The algorithm could be seen as a signifier of an entire result of calcula tion. Of course, 
one can also see this process as one of mathematical sequence (one that occurs within the 
step by step order of operation that goes into the calculation of the algorithm itself). The 
difference between this process and the mechan ical-narrative process is that the machines 
themselves do not allow themselves to be broken up into simultaneous actions (just because of simple physical and motion-relati ve constraints). An algorithm can, however, 
because it is an abstract colle ction of subsidiary and sometimes-autonomous calculations 
that need not be calculated one af ter the other in a linear sequence.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 7: On some semi-automatic machines for the drawing of the architectural orders 
oddly invented in the seventeenth century. 
 
Transcribed by B. Alex Miller. 
  
 
When you need something to transfer narrati ve motion from one state to another, please 
build a machine. 
The narrative-based state change of the transparent  geometric process and the fluidity of 
a machine built to replace this transparent  narrative. 
 
 
As the process of geometric construction is ca rried out that is nece ssary to proportionally 
design the orders according to  authors such as Serlio, a narrative is developed that 
prompts a movement from one proportional state to another: In the appropriate order of 
operation, the previous length of measure that is established for a portion of the column is 
subdivided into a particular fraction of that length of measure. Once this subdivision 
occurs, the original length has undergone a kind of state change that alters its reference 
from one portion of the column to another;  a consistent signifier of measurement is 
altered through a narr ative sequence of geometrical s ubdivision, changing its state of 
significance at the conclusion of each act of s ubdivision. In this case, the vehicle for this 
active state change is the seque ntial linearity of a narrative. 
 
  
In the late 16th and early 17th centuries, as algorithmic processes started to define the 
evolution of architectural design and pr oduction methodology, examples of mechanical 
constructs that took the place of the narra tive geometric sequence began to surface in 
order to compete. The artisans that were not  taught in the ways of algorithmic processes 
were forced to develop and attempt to us e these physical, mechanical constructs as 
replacements for these processes.   
 
In all of these machines designe d to recreate the orders, a stat e change similar to that of 
the textual / verbal narrative of Serlio  occurs, but it occurs through a physical 
embodiment of movement(s). Just as one can  almost picture an original length being 
subdivided over and over agai n to modify a signifier of measurement, the physical 
machines made this modification visible vi a expanding / folding armatures, and radial 
compositions of template punches. After one ar mature is moved to a particular location, 
the machine itself can be considered a frozen artifact that represents one of these phase 
changes, or narrative subdivisi ons. Both narrative-based processes are transparent, 
allowing the physical presence of each phase ch ange to be known or witnessed as they 
occur.   
 
  
The machines also embodied a type of physi cal memory, but a memory that was still 
rooted in the linear sequence of ordered opera tions. The cam of an automobile physically 
embodies a particular sequence of movement that is required to allow the internal</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lecture 8: Final Lecture (PDF)
Final Presentations</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-638-drawings-numbers-five-centuries-of-digital-design-fall-2002/resources/lecture_8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15-16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 8: Final Lecture.  
 
Transcribed by Yanni Loukissas. 
 
 
From the 15th to the 19th century, two mathematical systems for architectural design were in 
competition in Western Europe. The new system of numeracy allows architects to easily compare 
measurements and quantities. However, numerical  design requires a large amount of bookkeeping 
because it is difficult to memorize a long string of numeric symbols. Geometry was the tried and tested model. Geometrical constructions are inherently descriptive of the generative process. In contrast to numerical descriptions, this makes geometrical figures easily remembered and reconstructed. However, geometry is a propor tional system and therefore makes comparison 
between separate quantities impossible. 
  
The two systems seem to have an equal number of advantages and disadvantages. However, as 
we in the present already know, the numerical system prevailed. It is unclear what factors lead to 
its predominance. In this lecture, the prof essor outlines three possible reasons why numeracy 
might have appeared more favorable to architects than geometry. 
 
First, by the 15th century many other professions in Europe  were educated in the use of numbers. 
Merchants especially needed numbers to calculate interest rates. Some architects, being businessmen and entrepreneurs as well as artists nece ssarily had to learn the use of numbers in the 
daily practice of their trade to deal with merchants among others. There is recorded evidence that architects were more and more frequently asked to  calculate the cost of building. Early in the 
seventeenth century, French architectural treatises start to include instructions on the estimate of building costs.  
 
Second, architects increasing had to make survey s of existing site conditions prior to design. 
Additionally, the survey of ancient buildings or ruins was an essential part of the training of a 
classicist architect. Taking measurements is so mething that can only be  done with numbers.  
Third, printing made communication more image friendly. Images annotated with numbers are 
synchronic. This means that a lot of informa tion can be represented all at once. Geometrical 
descriptions are diachronic. They must be told  in sequence from beginning to end. A move 
towards images was a move towards synchronicity and towards numbers.  
  
 
The lectures that we have covered thus far are primarily concerned with the history of 
architectural theory. Unfortunately there is little evidence from the history of architectural 
practice. Very few examples of construction draw ings have been preserved. This remainder of 
this lecture will briefly survey the known history of drawing in architectural practice.  
We do not know when constructi on drawings were first adopted in the West. Until twenty years 
ago, only textual descriptions of ancient Greek and Roman buildings had been discovered. A few 
(perhaps seven) ancient drawings have been uncovered since. However, most of them are 
believed to be surveys. 
 
The next oldest building documents that we can refer to are some drawings from the late 
13th/early 14th century describing gothic windows or parts of gothic churches and the drawings 
attributed to Giottos workshop in 1334 for the Ca mpanile in Florence. Giottos drawings are also 
a conflation of survey and project documents.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Despite the lack of concrete evidence comi ng from actual practices at building sites, Leon 
Battista Albertis writings from the mid 15th century theorize that design should be expressed with 
drawings and three-dimensional models and left unchanged during the pr ocess of construction. 
There is evidence that this is i ndeed the design method that Alberti himself adopted, or at least 
favored, in some cases. 
 
In 1620 Martino Ferrabosco made a survey of St. Peters that is both proportionally correct and 
numerically dimensioned in a way that could be easily understood by todays engineers. This is 
the first concrete evidence of full adoption of  modern numeracy in construction documents 
including the precocious and somewhat puzzli ng adoption of a proportional scale of 1:100.  
 
Presently, digital encoding has followed the a dvance of numerical design and geometrical 
descriptions have all but disappeared. According to the professor, there are two predominant 
directions in which digital design may proceed  from here. One mode of digital design may 
involve nothing but a series of computational transformations based on available, industry-
standard software. As most software that is currently dominant is programmed using nineteenth 
century linear algebra and differential calculus, this could be perceived as the ultimate dominance of modern numeracy in design. As of yet, this mode of working remains a theoretical possibility. The other mode of digital age design is a retreat to gestural methods of design where the computer is positioned as a measuring and repli catory device for complex hand-made schemes. 
This second mode is best exemplified by the pant ograph (invented by a German Jesuit in 1631) or 
by the work of Frank Gehry. 
 
 
It remains to be seen how the computer will figure in to the future of architectural practice. At the 
end of the class, there was some disagreement, am ongst those present, as to whether digital means 
of encoding have ended the compe tition between numeracy and geometry.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lecture 2: The Primacy of the Word: Vitruvius and the Mystery of his Missing Images (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-638-drawings-numbers-five-centuries-of-digital-design-fall-2002/resources/lecture_2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3-4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 2: The Primacy of the Word: Vitruvius a nd the mystery of his missing images. 
 
Transcribed by Yanni Loukissas.  
  
  
This segment of the course will focus on the characteristics of handwritten 
manuscripts which deterred the use of images prior to the availability of printing. It will 
begin with a description of the materials us ed in the production of manuscripts and the 
methods used to make multiple copies of th em. It will cover the inherent problems which 
led to the primacy of writing over illustration, especially w ithin technical fields. In 
conclusion, it will show that these conditi ons prompted the two main writers of 
architectural theory, precedi ng the advent of print, to produce works that are almost 
exclusively text based. 
The previous lecture described the conditions surrounding the work of Leon 
Battista Alberti. Alberti was a Renaissance humanist who composed his treatise, De Re 
Aedificatoria , around 1452, just prior to  the adoption of the printing press in Italy. 
Although current publications of Albertis manuscript have been embellished with 
images, the original was devoid of diagrams  and illustrations. This lecture will introduce 
the work of the earlier writer, Vitruvius, who wrote the first know treatise on architecture.  
His manuscript was the only link to the ar chitectural knowledge of antiquity, which 
Renaissance scholars believed to be sacre d. For many years it was widely believed that 
Vitruviuss original ma nuscript contained illustrations. Ho wever, this lecture will suggest 
that Vitruvius may have also delib erately avoided the use of images. 
  
  
The Dominance of Text 
  
Parchment and papyrus were the two pr imary sheet materials used in the 
production of handwritten manuscripts. Parchment was made from animal skin; 
individual sheets of parchment were bound toge ther to form a codex. Papyrus, as the 
name suggests, was produced out of the pa pyrus plant. Manuscripts written on this 
material took the form of a long scroll instead of a compilation of pages. Before the 
widespread use of printing, manuscripts were no t expected to have a wide distribution.  
One could hope for 1,000 copies, at best. Th is was because copying texts manually was 
very labor intensive. When printed copies finally starte d to emerge the cost of a 
mechanical copy proved to be much cheaper than its manual equivalent. Manual copies 
were efficiently produced in scriptoria . In these workshops, manuscripts were often 
dictated to a large group of scribes simultaneously. This al lowed many duplicates to be 
produced at once. 
These conditions were primarily developed for the production of written 
documents and were extremely unfavorable for the distri bution of images. Neither 
papyrus nor parchment had physic al characteristics which aide d in the accurate transfer 
of images. They were not sufficiently transparent to allow tracing and other methods for 
direct transfer proved harmful to  the originals. The strategy of dictation used in scriptoria 
further inhibited the copying of images. Sin ce complex illustrations could not be dictated, 
it was up to one worker to transfer illustra tions from the original manuscript into each</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>new copy, one at a time. As a result, many copies remained unillustrated. Even when 
illustrators got around to producing copies, th e results were usually unsatisfactory.  
Illustrators were often pulled from the ra nks of normal scribes. Furthermore, the 
prevailing notion of illustrati on as a creative act gave illu strators license to make 
significant alterations. After all, before the invention of printing, each illustration was a 
unique work of art. As such, drawings were not frequently used in  the communication of 
technical or scientific information (e x. construction documents for a building, 
geographical maps, instructions, or scientific diagrams). A work of art was meant to be 
creative and did not demand fidelity. Copies  of illustrations were often altered by 
copyists in the interests of cr eative interpretation. As a result, there was no reliable way 
to duplicate and distribute illu strations for technical purposes. 
Illuminated manuscripts have been exte nsively studied by scholars (see Conrad 
Weitzman, Illustration in Rolls and Codex ). However, such artifacts were ill adapted to 
the transmission of scientific or technical information. These conditions resulted in a 
feedback loop which deterred the use of im ages altogether. Authors were aware that 
copies of their work would most likely be uni llustrated or illustrated unfaithfully. As a 
result, they avoided producing texts that  were reliant on accompanying images. One 
could only rely on the transmission of the simp lest geometrical shapes (ex. circle, square, 
triangle). In a sense, the fidelity of a copy c ould be expected to be in reverse proportion 
to the complexity of the illustrations. 
In Eastern cultures, the same separation between text and images did not exist.  
The alphabet was developed as a sound recorder in the west. W ith the use of this type of 
alphabet voices can be captured and transmitte d safely in time and space. Images cannot 
be transmitted as easily. As a result, the word took precedence over the image. Images copied before printing were almost always unf aithful. Therefore scientific and technical 
pursuits were dependent on non-visual means for recording information.   
  
  
The Treatise of Vitruvius 
  
Vitruvius wrote Ten Books on Architecture,  a general encyclopedia of the 
discipline, in approximately 30 B.C. In addi tion to architecture, it covers other topcis 
such as fortification, engineering, clock making, sundials, and military equipment.  
Vitruvius wrote on all that was known to him about architecture and its allied fields although oftentimes from the point of view of an architect practicing before his own time.  
Vitruviuss manuscript was ignored for centuri es even though there were many copies in 
existence. It was popularized again in the 15th century when humanists of the Italian 
Renaissance were trying to revive  the knowledge of antiquity.   
Vitruvius acknowledges in his own manuscrip t that his writing is difficult to 
understand. He notes that, as an architect, he is  not trained the art of  writing. Perhaps to 
make up for this, he refers to 9 or 11 expl anatory figures. However,  with a few and not 
significant exceptions, the supplementary draw ings have not been found in any copy of 
his manuscript. During the 16th century, scholars of Vitruviuss work became deeply 
interested in the whereabouts of the missi ng drawings. Several theories started to 
circulate under the premise that the drawings  provided some further key to unlocking the 
secrets of antiquity. Two of th e most prominent theories were as follows. 1. Someone has</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>found the images and is keeping them because  they contain secret knowledge 2. Vitruvius 
actually wrote two versions; one with imag es and one without because some people do 
not deserve to know the secrets of antiquity. 
These theories were supported by a common 16th century belief that there are 
several layers of knowledge in the world. The roots of this idea ca n be traced both to 
Christian and to classical sources. A ma nuscript was thought to hold more than one 
message. At the time, it was not uncommon for writers to hide in books, things that could 
not be said publicly. Some believed that only the initiat ed (or the predestined) could 
derive the true meaning of a text. 
An index of the images mentioned in Vitr uviuss treatise was constructed in the 
16th century by Guillaume Philandrier. Ironically, this index suggests that there may have 
been no original drawings in the manuscript. This is because the drawings that Vitruvius 
refers to are all simple geometrical shapes and can be easily unders tood or constructed by 
the reader. It appears that there was no necessity for Vitruvius to demonstrate these 
figures himself. It seems that Vitruvius, lik e Alberti, might have found it necessary to 
avoid illustrating his treatise. After all, he must have been well aware of the problems 
involved in the circulation of informati on that was not exclusively text-based.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
