<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/</course_url>
    <course_title>Ecology I: The Earth System</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Earth Science </list>
      <list>Biology </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ecosystem experiments/geoengineering</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourse Ware 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For informati on about citing these mate rials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/term s.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>be very difficult, if not impossible, to predict using reductionist modes of inquiry. What fundamental 
property of the Hubbard Brook ecosystem made this study possible? 
	What were the major changes in the chemical composition of the stream coming out of the clearcut 
watershed relative to the control? 
	What microbial processes played a key role in these changes? What strictly chemical processes? 
	Through what mechanisms can a cutover watershed become a source of atmospheric N2O? 
 What is cation exchange capacity and how does it relate to the effects of acid rain? 
Geoengineering and Ocean Fertilization 
	Humans are transforming the Earth on a global scale, eg. Increase in CO2 in our atmosphere, loss of 
nutrients in our soils, changes in the global water cycle, etc. Is this Geoengineering? Why or why 
not? 
	Why did John Martin suspect that iron was limiting phytoplankton growth in the equatorial Pacific? 
	Why did this suddenly make an ocean fertilization experiment feasible? Why didnt people think about 
this before? (think Redfield Ratios). 
	What biogeochemical cycles would be affected by large scale Ocean Fertilization?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1.018  7.30J 	 Handout 2009 
ECOSYSTEM EXPERIMENTS AND GEOENGINEERING 
READINGS: 
Textbook This lecture is based on very current ideas in Ecology and Earth System Science, and 
your textbook does not cover it. 
Articles: 
	The Economist 2008. Global Warming: A Changing Climate of Opinion? 
	Schiermeier, Quirin, 2007 Mixing the oceans proposed to reduce global warming. 
News@nature.com 
	Kintisch, Eli. 2007. Scientists say continued Warming Warrants Closer Look at Drastic Fixes. 
Science 2007 
	Likens, G. 2004 Some perspectives on long-term biogeochemical research from the Hubbard 
Brook Ecosysem Study. Ecology 85:2355-2362 
	Lovelock, J. 2008 A geophysiologists thoughts on geoengineering. Phil. Trans. Royal. Soc A/ 
doi10:1098/rsta.2008.0135 
	Carpenter et al 1995. Ecosystem Experiments. Science 
Audio: Lovelock on Science Friday 
FOOD FOR THOUGHT:
Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest
	The Hubbard Brook Study shows that ecosystem ecology and the study of biogeochemical cycles is 
an experimental science. One can do experiments with whole ecosystems and get answers that would</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>CI lecture: getting started with the term project</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec04/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>11
Your Introduction should consist of three parts, 
which:
Discusses the issues an d attributes of the problem addressed 
by the topic youve selected. 
Identify the problems implications ecologically and socially, 
etc. 
Provides a foundation for your reader to understand the problem through a discussion of the  literature. 
Reviews the origins and history of the concept of geogengineering, and summarize  a broad suite of proposed 
schemes  
Demonstrates themes, problems , negative side effects or 
other ideas common to these various strategies.
Provides an in-depth analysis of  the particular geoengineering
topic that youve selected.  
Discusses how it is supposed to work, providing technical details and diagrams if appropriate.   
Cites relevant literature to pr ovide the necessary details.  
_Describe the intended consequences of your geoengineering topic, i.e. what is it supposed to do and why?  1
22
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>14
Structure: Use Section Hierarchies to Clarify 
Structure, Use headings for major topics  
Executive Summary
Introduction
- Problem/Background
- Geoengineering overview- Description of specific scheme
Experimental Design
- Potential unintended consequences- Hypothesis- Description of Experiment
Conclusion/Recommendations
- Expected results- Conclusion- Recommendations</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
In scientific writing, formats vary considerably 
to serve different situations
Formal
ReportsJournal
ArticlesPresentationSlides</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9
The Term Paper consists of a series of five 
assignments, which will be completed in stages
1) Topic Submission... Due Lecture #3
2) Project Description. Due Lecture #73) Introduction.. Due Lecture #11
4) Experimental Design/Proposal.Due Lecture #15
5) Complete Final Paper. Due Lecture #22
* Oral Presentation:    (15% of term project grade)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>13
Your Conclusions and Recommendations 
should: 
Highlight the predicted results of your experiment 
and what these results might mean for your opinion regarding implementation of this and of other geoengineering strategies.   
Put your experiment in the context of dealing with the global problems as a whole.   
Include recommendations based on your research.1
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>27
Attention to the clarity of subjects and to logical             
connections helps the reader follow complex discussions
Global warming poses many potentia l risks to the Earths ecosystem and 
human existence. Not only are the natur al cycles, including the water and 
carbon cycle, thrown off balance, but effects such as the melting of polar 
icecaps may wipe out entire species . Other negative effects include 
changes in the geographical distribut ion of vegetation, and increased sea 
levels. Effects of global warming on the human population include difficulties 
sourcing energy, transportation, food, and water. Because of these effects,
there will be a change in health and infr astructure causing potential famine, 
and disease in many parts of the world (Wuebbles, 2001). The poorest parts 
of the world are at most risk of these effect s both because of their financial 
disadvantage and their rapid population increase. Thus, as the chemical 
imbalance of the atmosphere conti nues to cause global environmental 
changes, mankind may have to engineer radical methods to undo these 
anthropogenic effects . Geoengineering holds the possibility for such 
solutions, and for this reason has gained much public attention.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>16
The organization of a document is reflected in the 
headings, subheadings, and paragraphs, example:
Genetically Modified Trees Section Heading
A Geoengineering Scheme to Reverse Anthropogenic Environmental Changes
Geoengineering is an intended large-scale modification of the Earths systems to 
reverse human induced damage. Often fo cused on carbon emissions, geoeningeering
can also attempt to reverse sweeping human actions including deforestation, and 
pollution. The use of genetically modified tr ees (GM trees) for reforestation, addresses 
the repercussions of all of these actions. Benefits of GM trees include improved carbon sequestration, alternative energy, and bioremediation. Companies such as Arborgen
have begun to genetically modify trees for such purposes. There still, however, remains 
multiple side effects including mutations, undesired changes in the biogeochemical 
cycles, and biodiversity limitation. These uni ntended consequences have potential to out 
way the proposed benefits.
Mutations Subheads
Changes in the biogeochemical cycles
Biodiversity limitation</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>10
The final proposal includes all revised sections, 
and Conclusion &amp; Recommendations</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>12
Your Experimental Design should consist of 
three parts, which
Reviews the potential unintended consequences of 
implementation of the ge oengineering idea.   
Explains what might go wrong, how it might negatively impact 
the Earth System, etc.  
Provides a literature review of the relevant material.
Proposes a hypothesis regarding the testing of these 
unintended consequences.   Your  hypothesis should reflect 
your prediction of what your experiment will determine. 
Proposes the actual experimental design that youve 
developed to test the hypothesis  youve put forward regarding 
the unintended consequences of your geoengineering topic.
Includes technical details, diag rams, and experimental details 
(replicates, controls, etc.)    
This is the experiment you are proposing and whose funding 
will have to argue for in your pr esentation.  Your design must 
be scientifically reasonable an d this will require literature 
reviews.1
2
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>28
Beginning
EndingMiddleKnowing your Audience(s) for your 
Proposal is Crucial</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7The structure of a document is reflected in the 
headings, subheadings, and paragraphs</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Based on work by Michael 
AlleyMIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Keep it as simple as 
possible, yet no simpler.
Albert Einstein
Based on work by Michael 
AlleyHarlan Harlan Breindel, Lecturer
Program in Writing and Humanistic Studies
MIT 1.018/7.30J Fall 2009 Ecology I</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3
How well you communicate affects your career
Survey (Richard M. Davis) 
Successful engineers spent 25% of 
work week writing
Survey (Virginia Tech) 
Recruiters claim that engineers need more work on their writingSurvey (Wisconsin) 
Professional engineers found writing 
their most useful subject in college</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>24
Dont forget that Writing Is a Process
Good writing doesnt happen 
overnight; it requires planning, 
drafting, rereading, revising, and editing.
Learning and improvement 
requires self-review, peer-
review, subject-matter expert 
feedback, and practice .
There are no shortcuts ; practice 
makes perfect!http://www.thewriterswork shop.net/writing-2.jpg</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>26
Reread, revise your writing for 
clarity</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2
The fundamental purpose of scientific 
discourse is not the mere presentation of 
information and thought but rather its actual 
communication . It does not matter how 
pleased an author might be to have converted all the right data into sentences 
and paragraphs; it matters only whether a 
large majority of the reading audience accurately perceives what the author had in 
mind.
--George Gopen and Judith Swan
The Science of Scientific Writing</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8
Todays talk will overview the term project, 
consider structure, overview the Project 
Description</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>15
Outline/Structure for Experimental Design   
Section, example:
Experimental Testing of GM Trees Section Heading
Proposed testing mechanisms for intended and unintended 
consequences of implementation                            Introductory text
The usefulness of using GM trees as a Geoengineering solution remains uncertain. 
Both intended and unintended consequences of the project require further 
research and testing. We propose the follow ing experimentations to verify efficacy, 
and to test potential hazards. All experim ents are modeled after similarly formatted 
tests that have been either executed or proposed.
Proposed Hypotheses for Unin tended Consequence Testing
Large Scale Setup
Efficacy Testing- GM trees and Ca rbon Sequestration      
Testing Risk of Gene Flow-
Testing Effects of Mixed For ests- Changes in Resources and 
Biodiversity        Subheads/
Subsections</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>17
Writing your Project Description, a sample</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4
Scientists and engineers are called upon 
to communicate in many different situations
specific
technical
audiencesnon-technical
audiencesgeneral
technical
audiencesReports
Articles
Proposals
Web PagesConferences
Lectures
Meetings
Posters</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
The majority of your work is 
communicated in a variety of documents
What is a document?
Like most engineering projects, a document is 
an artifact that is designed and produced
 It is created  
 For specific purposes
 For specific audiences  For specific uses
 It is modular</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>22
For References use APA Format  Best, try 
Refworks, examples:
Journal article:
Fine, M. A., &amp; Kurdek, L. A. (1993). Reflections on determining 
authorship credit and authorship order on faculty-student 
collaborations. American Psychologist, 48, 1141-1147.
Book:
Nicol, A. A. M., &amp; Pexman, P. M. (1999). Presenting your findings: A 
practical guide for creating tables. Washington, DC: American 
Psychological Association.
Book chapter:
O'Neil, J. M., &amp; Egan, J. (1992). Men's and women's gender role 
journeys: Metaphor for healing, transition, and transformation. 
In B. R. Wainrib (Ed.), Gender issues across the life cycle (pp. 
107-123). New York: Springer.
Online document:
Author, A. A. (2000). Title of work.  Retrieved month day, year, from 
source (give URL)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>25
You choose the information, how it is 
presented, and how it is analyzed.
Objectivity is the basis of research, but effective 
communication of science requires some 
subjectivity on the part of the writer
-Amin Bredan &amp; Frans van Roy</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>29
NSF Seven Deadly Sins of Proposal Writing
1. Failure to focus on the problems/payoffs
2. No persuasive structure: poorly organized
3. No clear differentiation: competitive
analysis
4. Failure to offer a compelling value
proposition: potential impact
5. Key points buried: no highlights
6. Difficult to read: full of jargon, too long,
too technical
7. Credibility killers: misspellings, grammar
inconsistent format, etc.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>30
Use your Communications and Writing 
Resources
CI/WAC Lecturers
Harlan Breindel
Leslie Roldan
Mary Zoll
The Mayfield Handbook of Scientific and Technical Writing
Academic Integrity at the Massachusetts Institute of 
Technology: A Handbook for Students
The Science of Scientific Writing by Gopen &amp; Swan
The Writing Center</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>23
Use diagrams for explaining your 
experimental design</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Population growth</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourse Ware 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For informati on about citing these mate rials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/term s.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>SOME QUESTIONS TO THINK ABOUT 
 Is the human population in exponential growth? Why or why not? 
 Considering the growth of a microorganism, what is similar and different between 
growth in batch culture (Logistic growth) and a chemostat? 
 What are the assumptions of the Logistic Growth Model? 
 How do es age of first reproduction of females influence population growth rates? 
 What is the explicit definition of the Carrying Capacity of the Earth for humans? 
Why is it so difficult to estimate? 
 How is the ecological footprint of a person or country calculated? What is the 
ecological capacity of a country? 
LIFE TABLE TERMS AND EQUATIONS 
x	 = age 
nx	 = number of individuals surviving to age x 
lx	 = age-specific survivorship
= proportion of individuals surviving to age x
= nx /no
dx	 = number dying during the age interval x to x+1 
qx	 = age-specific per capita mortality rate
= proportion of individuals dying between age x and x + 1
= (lx  lx+1)/lx
= dx/nx
age class x = all the individuals between age x and x + 1 
ex	 = life expectancy of individuals of age x = Tx / nx 
Tx	 = total years to be lived by individuals of age x in the population 
! Lxx"#
= 
Lx	 = number of individuals alive on average during the age interval x to x+1 
= (nx + nx+1)/2 
bx= age-specific fecundity 
= average number of offspring produced per individual between ages x and x + 1 
Ro	= net replacement per generation 
=  (lxbx) 
r = intrinsic rate of increase 
exact solution:  (lxbxe rx)=1 
approx. solution: r  (ln Ro) / G 
where G = mean generation time
 { (x lx bx) } / Ro</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1.018  7.30J 2009 	 Handout 
Lectures 13,14 Population Growth: Exponential/Logistic, 
Chemostats, Life Tables, and Human Population Growth 
READINGS 
Text: Appendix A, p. 741-744; Appendix B pp. 762-766; Chapter 10: pp. 171  180;. 
Chapter 11: 181-193. 
Lecture Supplement 
Introduction to Chemostat Theory 
Chemostat Lecture Notes 
Articles: 
Smil, Vaclav (1999). How Many Billions To Go? Nature 401:429. 
Palumbi (2001). Humans as the Worlds Greatest Evolutionary Force. Science 293:1786-
1790. 
Cohen,J. (1995) Population growth and Earths human carrying capacity. Science 269:341 
Tilman et al (2002). Agricultural sustainability and intensive production practices. Nature 
418:671. 
Wackernagel et al (1999)	National natural capital accounting with the ecological footprint 
concept. Ecol. Econom. 29:375-390 
Further Reading 
Hindell, M. (1991) Some Life-History Parameters of a Declining population of southern 
elephant seals, Mirounga leonina. J. Anim. Ecol. 60: 119-134 
OUTLINE 
Exponential Growth Continuous growth in an unlimited environment 
Logistic Growth Growth with limits  Carrying Capacity 
Density Dependent Growth 
Life Tables and Demography Discrete generations and age distributions 
Chemostat Theory Growth in nutrient limited environments 
Human Population Growth Where have we come from and where are we going? 
Ecological Footprint Calculating Sustainability 
NOTE: The notation used in lecture may not always agree with that used in your text. This 
should not disturb you. If you understand the concepts with both sets of notation, then you 
really understand the material. 
STUDY GUIDE 
You should be able to solve problems that are similar to those covered in class, in the homework, and 
on the example quiz that will be available . You dont have to memorize all the formulas, but you should 
be familiar with them when you see them, and know which to use for what application. (Since there are 
so few of them, the safest thing to do is to internalize them. If you understand exponential growth, for 
example, you can derive the rest from here.)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction: what is ecology?</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec01/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1.018/7.30J Lecture 1-Introduction to Ecology 2009 
Readings 
 Smith and Smith Chapter 1. 
 Vernadskii The Biosphere 
 Carruthers Locusts in the Red Sea 
 Remmert Ecology: The Basic Concept Rowe Biological Fallacy: Life =Organisms (same document) 
 Redox Handout 
Evolution of Definitions of Ecology 
Ecology = from the Greek root OIKOS, at home, and OLOGY, the study of 
Haeckle (1870): By ecology we mean the body of knowledge concerning the economy of Nature -the
investigation of the total relations of the animal to its inorganic and organic environment.
Burdon-Sanderson (1890s): Elevated Ecology to one of the three natural divisions of Biology: Physiology -
Morphology -Ecology 
Elton (1927): Scientific natural history 
Andrewartha (1961): The scientific study of the distribution and abundance of organisms 
Odum (1963): The structure and function of Nature 
Our Definition: Ecology is the scientific study of the processes regulating the distribution and abundance of 
organisms and the interactions among them, and the study of how these organisms in turn mediate the 
transport and transformation of energy and matter in the biosphere (i.e., the study of the design of ecosystem 
structure and function). 
Beyond Fundamental Ecology 
Applied Ecology: Using ecological principles to maintain conditions necessary for the continuation of present day 
life on earth. 
Industrial Ecology: The design of the industrial infrastructure such that it consists of a series of interlocking 
"technological ecosystems" interfacing with global natural ecosystems. Industrial ecology takes the pattern and 
processes of natural ecosystems as a design for sustainability. It represents a shift in paradigm from conquering 
nature to becoming nature. 
Ecological Engineering: Unlike industrial ecology, the focus of Ecological Engineering is on the manipulation of 
natural ecosystems by humans for our purposes, using small amounts of supplemental energy to control systems 
in which the main energy drives are still coming from non-human sources. It is the design of new ecosystems for 
human purposes, using the self-organizing principles of natural ecosystems. 
[Note: The popular definition of ecological engineering is "the design of human society with its natural environment 
for the benefit of both.". What is the logical flaw in this definition?] 
Ecological Economics: Integrating ecology and economics in such a way that economic and environmental 
policies are reinforcing rather than mutually destructive. 
Urban ecology: For ecologists, urban ecology is the study of ecology in urban areas, specifically the relationships, 
interactions, types and numbers of species found in urban habitats. Also, the design of sustainable cities, urban 
design programs that incorporate political, infrastructure and economic considerations. 
Conservartion Biology: The application of diverse fields and disciplines to the conservation of biological diversity. 
Restoration Biology: Appllication of ecosystem ecology to the restoration of deteriorated landscapes in an 
attempt to bring it back to its original state as much as possible. Example, prarie grass.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>A chemical calm would overcome the Earth if life ceased to exist 
	Under the thermodynamic conditions of the biosphere, water is a powerful chemical agent but on a 
dead Earth, water is a compound of weak chemical activity? 
...there is no "original" state in nature, no nature-in-itself in the sense that a fixed set of characteristics holds true, like the law 
of gravity, always and everywhere. Nature resembles less a law than a story. And the story is not over. Thus to inquire of 
nature is to inquire of time, of circumstance and of contingency. What was natural three billion years ago--an empire of 
anaerobic bacteria--would strike most of us as decidedly unnatural today. 
Edwin Dobb
Cultivating Nature The Sciences Jan/Feb 1992 p. 45
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>series, new properties emerge. That is, one cannot explain all of the properties at one level from an 
understanding of the components at the one below. 
Emergence is the feedback between micro-and macro-level behaviors. The local dynamics of a set of interacting 
entities supports an emergent set of global dynamical structures which stabilize themselves by setting the 
boundary conditions within which the local dynamics operates. That is, these global structures can reach down to 
their own physical bases of support and fine tune them in the furtherance of their own global ends. Such LOCAL 
to GLOBAL back to LOCAL, inter-level feedback loops are essential to life, and are the key to understanding its 
origin, evolution and diversity. [Taylor, CE in Artificial Life II. 1991 Langton, CG, Taylor, C. Farmer. KD, eds. pp. 
371-408 Addison-Wesley]. 
Guide to Readings Why we chose them/Why they are important/ What to look for. 
Chapter 1 (Smith and Smith): This is an excellent overview of the field of Ecology, what kind of science it is,
how it is structured, how ecologists form and test hypotheses, and why it is important.
Redox Primer: Read in preparation for the next set of lectures and work through examples 
Remmert  Ecology: This is my favorite introduction to an Ecology Textbook. I think it captures the essence 
of ecology and should be read and understood before starting an Ecology course. Most important is the last
paragraph. We have to remember that the Earths ecosystems have not always been hospitable for humans,
and most likely will not be at some time in the future. We are but just a blip on the evolutionary landscape.
It will be a daunting task to sustain the Earths ecosystems in a way that will sustain human life on earth. Our 
understanding of Ecology will have to be a lot better than it is now.
Rowe  Biological Fallacy: Life Equals Organisms: This should get you thinking about what Life is. Its all 
perspective, and it is important for us to get out of our rigid view of life that is primarily dictated by our size 
relative to other living systems. Assume you could see energy and individual elements, and think about the 
how you would describe life if: 1) you sat on the inside of a cell and watched the energy and elements flow 
through metabolism, and 2) you sat on a space shuttle and watched the energy flow and element cycles of the 
Earth. What would be similar and different? 
Vernadski  The Biosphere (1926): Vernadski was a man ahead of his time, with brilliant insights into how the
Earth works. This was the first account of the Earth as an integrated living system, and preceeded modern
Ecology by decades. You will see that in Vernadskis view of the Earth, life forces shape the abiotic
components of the Earths crust.
Study Questions 
These example questions are designed to help you understand and think about lectures and readings. these are a 
guide only. you are not required to hand them in, nor do they necessarily include all of the major concepts covered 
in class and readings. 
	Give an example of the organism environment interaction being two way with regard to how organisms 
change planetary chemistry and physics. 
	What is the relationship between ecology and environmentalism? Where does Remmert see ecology fitting in 
to broader societal problems? 
	Why does Remmert call green plants the first great polluters of the environment? 
	Give an example of an ecosystem, and explain what the associated community would consist of. 
	The popular definition of ecological engineering is "the design of human society with its natural environment for 
the benefit of both." (Mitsch, 1988). What is the logical flaw in this definition?] 
	Rowes Biological Fallacy calls in to question using an organism-level perspective on life. Describe how 
energy flows would look different if you were a) inside a cell or b) in a space ship looking down on earth. 
Without prior knowledge, what would you call life? 
	What does Vernadsky mean by cosmic forces? What does he mean by the following statements? 
 The biosphere is the creation of the Sun 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Landscape Ecology: Landscape ecology is concerned with spatial patterns in the landscape and how they 
develop, with an emphasis on the role of disturbance, including human impacts (Smith and Smith). It is a 
relatively new branch of ecology, that employs Global Information Systems. The goal is to predict the responses 
of different organisms to changes in landscape, to ultimately facilitate ecosystem management. 
*** 
All these disciplines require an understanding of the "organizing principles" of ecosystems, i.e., their ecology. This 
involves the detailed study of the structure and function of ecosystems in their undisturbed state, and using their 
designs to: 
 determine the resilience of ecosystem functions to human activities. 
 design ecosystems which function in the service of human beings with minimal fossil energy input (ideally 
none) and minimal waste. 
 design the industrial infrastructure. 
 integrate the value of "goods and services" of natural ecosystems into the global economic system. 
What is "Sustainability"?: There are many definitions of this one, depending on your perspective. Heres 
ours: Sustainability is a property of a human society in which ecosystems (including humans) are managed such 
that the conditions supporting present day life on Earth can continue. 
Ecology and The Future of Biology 
However it is said, the future of biology lies not in the ongoing reduction of biology to molecular tidbits, but in 
studying biology in its essence; studying the organism and the environment as primary, not derived entities. 
Both, however, are facets of a single grand problem, the nature of biological organization. Such an emphasis 
brings to light an entirely different future for biology, one in which understanding the dynamic of the biosphere 
and the evolution and nature of cellular organization are central issues. 
Carl Woese 2006 
Levels of Studying Ecology 
Biosphere: The earths ecosystem interacting with the physical environment as a whole to maintain a steady 
state system intermediate in the flow of energy between the high energy input of the sun and the thermal sink 
of space (merges with atmosphere, lithosphere, hydrosphere). 
 
Biome: Large scale areas of similar vegetation and climatic characteristics. 
 
Ecosystem: Set of organisms and abiotic components connected by the exchange of matter and energy 
(forest, lake, coastal ocean). Or, the smallest units that can sustain life in isolation from all but atmospheric 
surroundings. 
 
Community: Interacting populations which significantly affect each others distributions and abundance
(intertidal, hot spring, wetland).
 
Population: Group of interacting and interbreeding organisms 
 
Cell/Organism  Organelle  Molecule  Atom 
Principle of Integrative Levels -Emergence 
Principle of hierarchical control: As components combine to produce larger functional wholes in hierarchical 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourse Ware 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For informati on about citing these mate rials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/term s.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Secondary productivity/food webs</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourse Ware 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For informati on about citing these mate rials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/term s.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>ENERGY FLOW, FOOD WEBS, AND EFFICIENCIES: 
 
 Pn = Productivity at trophic level n (net) 
Pn-1  = Productivity (net) of trophic level n-1 
Rn = Respiration at trophic level n 
Fn  = Faecal material produced at trophic 
level n (for microorganisms, this would 
be excreted organic carbon) 
In  = Amount ingested by trophic level n 
An  = Amount assimilated and available for 
metabolism 
Dn  = Fraction of P n-1 not consumed by 
trophic level n 
Bn = Biomass in trophic level n 
 
We can now define the following efficiencies (%)  
 
n-1 n I n/Pn-1 
 
      (sometimes called consumption efficiency) Trees Insects 1- 10% 
 Grass Animals 20% 
 Phytoplankton Zooplankton 20-40% 
 
 Herbivores   20-50%  Carnivores 80% 
 
 
 
 
 Tells you how much energy is lost in one trophic transfer in the grazing food chain 
 Some of this goes to the detritus food web, some goes to respiration 
 
King: Now, Hamlet, wheres Polonius? 
 2 Hamlet: At supper. 
King: At supper!  Where 
Hamlet: Not where he eats, but where he is eaten: a certain convocation of politic worms are een at him.  Your worm is your only 
emperor for diet: we fat all creatures else to fat us, and we fat ourselves for maggots: your fat king and lean beggar is but 
variable service; two dishes, but to one table: thats the end. 
King: Alas, alas! 
Hamlet: A man may fish with the worm that hath eat of a king, and eat of the fish that hath fed of that worm. 
King: What dost though mean by this? 
Hamlet: Nothing, but to show a king may go a progress through the guts of a beggar.  Hamlet , IV, II, 17-35  
King: Where is Polonius?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1.018/7.30J	  fall 2009 
Lecture 12  food webs and secondary productivity 
REA DINGS: 
Text: Ch 24, 491-503, p. 670-676 
Beddington, J. 1995 The Primary Requirements Nature 374: 213-214 (W) 
Pauly, D. and V. Christensen. 1995. Primary Production Required to Sustain Global Fisheries. Nature: 374: 
255-257 (W) 
Pauley, D. et al 2000.  Fishing Down Aquatic Food Webs. Am. Sci. 88: 46-51 
Optional and or Background for Lecture 
For background on stable isotopes: http://wwwrcamnl.wr.usgs.gov/isoig/res/funda.html 
Stapp et al. 1999. Stable isotopes reveal strong marine and El Nino effects on island food webs. Nature: 
401: 467  469. 
Peterson, B. et al. 1986. Sulfur and Carbon Isotopes as tracers of salt-marsh organic matter flow. Ecology. 
67:865 
It's a very odd thing 
As odd as can be 
That whatever Miss T eats 
Turns into Miss T. 
Walter De La Mare, 1913 
Outline: 
Secondary Production
Production Efficiencies
Assimilation Efficiencies
Food Chain Efficiencies
Grazing Food Webs vs. Decomposer Food Webs
Analysis of efficiencies in a marine ecosystem
STUDY GUIDE 
This lecture is designed to get you to think about the structure of food webs and how energy flows through an 
ecosystem...i.e. how one would construct an energy budget for an ecosystem if we could measure everything (which 
we can't, of course, except in model systems.). 
	Construct an energy flow diagram for both an organism and a food web. What are the similarities? Differences? 
	Could you measure energy flow through a food web? How might you try to do this? 
	How does the flow of energy through a carnivore differ from that of a herbivore? An endotherm vs. an ectotherm? 
	What does fish production in the sea have to do with the structure of food webs? 
	There are two hypotheses for why the average length of a food chain is 5. One is energy limitation. What is the 
other? Can you find any evidence for the second one in the literature? 
	Why is the world green? (see your textbook) 
	How might the biosphere be changed if all humans were vegetarians? If all animals were herbivores? 
	Some have argued that game ranching may give higher yields (secondary production) than that of livestock in 
the same area. What is the evidence for or against this (see your textbook)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Chemostats/life tables</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourse Ware 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For informati on about citing these mate rials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/term s.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1.018/7.30J                                                                                                                              
INTRODUCTION TO CHEMOSTAT THEORY 
The chemostat, independently developed by Monod (1950) and Novick and Szilard (1950), is a 
continuous culture device used to describe the growth characteristics of nutrient-limited 
microorganisms under steady state conditions. 
Consider a well-mixed vessel containing a culture of microorganisms.  Let v be the volume of the 
culture and let N be the cell density.  The flow rate , f, is the rate at which fresh medium is pumped 
into the culture and the rate at which the contents are removed, maintaining a constant volume, v, 
in the vessel.  f/v is the dilution rate of the cult ure, D.  All nutrients in the influent medium are in 
excess except one, the lim iting nutrient, which enters at a concentration S i.  The concentration of 
the limiting nutrient in the vessel is S, and the cells have a specific growth rate r. 
The rate of change of the cell density in the vessel can be written as 
dN
dt= rN  DN
 (1) 
which is the growth rate of the cells minus t he rate at which they are being washed out of the 
culture vessel.  In a steady state,  equation (1) is equal to zero, thus 
 (2) rN = DN
and 
 (3) r =D
That is, in steady state, the growth rate of the ce lls will be equal to the dilution rate of the culture.  
r and D have the unit time -1, which is the specific gr owth rate of the cells (you can think of it as 
cells per cell per day.) 
The rate of change of the concentration of the limiting nutrient in the vessel can be written 
dS/dt =  DSi - DS - rNQ (4) 
where Q is the cell quota, or the amount of limiti ng nutrient per cell.  In steady state, equation (4) 
equals zero, and 
 D(S i - S) = rNQ (5) 
which, since D = r, reduces to 
N = (S i - S) /Q (6) 
Thus, cell density in the culture is a function of  the cell quota and the concentration of the limiting 
nutrient in the culture vessel. 
   S.W. Chisholm</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Monod (1950) showed that the growth of bacteri a limited by a single substrate can be described 
by the equation 
r = rmax S/ (K s + S) (7) 
where r max is the maximum possible growth rate of a species and K s is the substrate 
concentration at r max/2.  Since D = r, equation (7) can be rewritten as 
S = Ks D/ (r max - D) (8) 
Combining equations (6) and (8) yields 
N = [S i - Ks D/rmax - D] / Q (9) 
Thus, in a system where Q is a constant, if K s, rmax, and Q are known for a given species, 
steady state values of N and S can be predicted fo r any dilution rate using equations (8) and (9). 
r = hr -1 specific growth rate of cells
N = cells ml -1 cell density
Si, S = g ml -1 influent, effluent dissolved conc entration of limiting nutrient 
Q = g cell -1 cell quota - amount of limiting nutrient in the cell  
Y = 1/Q cells g -1 yield coefficient 
D = day -1 = f/v dilution rate 
f = ml day -1 flow rate 
V = ml volume of culture 
Novick, A, and L. Szilard, 1950.  Experiments wi th the chemostat in spontaneous mutations of 
bacteria.  Proc. Nat. Ac ad. Sc i.  36:340-345. 
Monod, 1950.  La technique de culture c ontinue theorie et applications.  Annls . Inst. Pas teur, 
Paris,79:390-401. 
  2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Predation/symbiosis/mutualism</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourse Ware 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For informati on about citing these mate rials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/term s.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1.018/7.30J  fall 2009 
Ecology of the Earth System 
Lecture 16  Predator Prey Interactions 
Predation
Smith &amp; Smith Ch 1 5 p. 265-283 ( whole chapter ); Ch 16 p. 300-304
Gilg et al, Science 302:866 (2003); Hudson, Science 302:797 (perspective)
Turchin Nature 405:562 (2000)
REA DINGS FOR NEXT LECTURE:
Today : 
Predation 
terminology 
modeling predator -prey  interactions  Lotka Volttera and Rosenweig/McA rthur 
Functional response curv es 
laboratory  studies 
field studies 
Five general types of predation: 
 Herbivores (eat leaves, seeds, fruits -dont necessarily kill prey) 
 Carnivores (eat herbivores or other carnivores) 
 Cannibalisms 
 Parasitoids (host killed or eaten) 
 Parasites (live in or on hosts that provide them with nutrition) 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>How to be alive/thermodynamics of life</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec03/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Overview of Life on Earth 
The energy that drives all life processes is organized around oxidation/reduction reactions. 
Ultimately on Earth today, oxygenic photosynthesis, and energy from the sun, fuels the entire 
biosphere. Oxygenic photosynthesis produces (by the splitting of water as a reducing agent) 
one of the most powerful oxidants known  oxygen. The biosphere on the contemporary Earth 
runs largely on the carbon produced by CO2 fixation by oxygenic photosynthesis, and on the 
free energy difference between O2 and organic carbon, which heterotrophs use to fuel their 
metabolism. The autotrophs synthesize glucose using solar or chemical energy, which is 
broken down through respiration (either their own or that of the organisms that eat them) to 
provide the energy necessary for biological work. Redox reactions are central to all of these 
energy transformations, and the resulting flows of electrons manifest themselves, collectively, 
in the form of global biogeochemical cycles. The activities of bacteria keep these cycles 
moving. For example, the chemosynthetic bacteria oxidize many essential elements in the 
process of getting the energy required to reduce CO2. Certain anaerobic bacteria in turn 
reduce these compounds in the process of anaerobic respiration  i.e., they use them as an 
electron acceptor in the absence of oxygen. This keeps the element cycles cycling 
maintaining balanced amounts of oxidants and reductants necessary for diverse 
metabolic processes. This keeps the system from running down energetically. Stay 
tuned for section on Biogeochemical Cycles. 
Study  Questions: 
	What are the relative light, oxygen and sulfide levels in each layer of a Winogradsky column 
after it has gotten established and is in steady state? What types of organisms dominate 
each layer? What are the energy and carbon sources for each kind of organism? 
	What microbes form the base of this food web in hydrothermal vent ecosystems? Could 
this system persist in the absence of photsynthesis on the surface of the earth? Why or 
Why not? 
	What reaction does Ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase catalyze? Why has Rubisco 
been called the most important protein on Earth? 
	What is the difference between a chemoorganotroph and a chemolithotroph? Or between 
an autotroph and a heterotroph? Or between a chemotroph and a phototroph? 
	If a lake is covered in algae, how do anoxygenic photosynthetic bacteria, which live 
underneath the algae, manage to obtain sufficient light to carry out photosynthesis? 
	The article, Can deep bacteria live on nothing but rocks and water? is 10 years old. Can 
you find more recent research that provides more substantial evidence for this type of 
microbial metabolism? 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>chemicals in the environment, is what drives biogeochemical cycles in the biosphere. Their 
integrated activities balance oxidation and reduction reactions in the environment, and keep the 
system cycling between the oxidized and reduced forms of organic and inorganic materials. 
A. Autotrophs 
These self-nourishers typically get their energy from the sun (photoautotrophs), or from 
reduced inorganic compounds (chemoautotrophs a.k.a. chemolithotrophs). They get their 
carbon for growth and production of new cells from CO2. 
The energy generating reactions produces ATP and NADPH, which provide stored 
biochemical energy and reducing power forbiosynthesis and production of new cells. For 
oxygen -generating photosynthetic organisms (like plants and cyanobacteria), the light-requiring 
reaction that generates energy is known as the Hill, or light reaction. There are a number of 
different ways that organism can incorporate, or fix inorganic CO2 into organic material. In 
plants, the Calvin Cycle, is common biochemical pathway, and uses the stored energy and 
reducing power (ATP and NADPH) to convert CO2 to CH2O (sugar). 
1. Oxygenic Photosynthesis (produces O2) 
Who? Plants, cyanobacteria, eukaryotic algae 
C Source? CO 2 
Energy Source? Sunlight 
Electron Donor? H2O 
(the oxygen from the water used in photosynthesis, is what produces the O2 we breath !) 
Where? In aerobic, light conditions
 CO 2 + H 2O + h  CH 2O + O 2 
2. Anoxygenic Photosynthesis (doesnt produce O2) 
Who? Bacteria (e.g. Purple sulfur bacteria, green sulfur bacteria) 
C Source? CO 2 
Energy Source? Sunlight 
Electron Donor? H2S, H2, Fe2+ 
Where? In anaerobic, light conditions 
CO 2 +2 H 2S + h  CH 2O + 2 S + H 2O 
3. Chemosynthesis 
Who? Chemoautotrophic bacteria, aka chemolithoautotrophs (rock eaters) 
C Source? CO 2 
Energy Source? Reduced inorganic compounds (CH4, H2, NH4, H2S, Fe2+) 
Electron Donor? Reduced inorganic compounds 
Where? In microaerobic or anaerobic, dark conditions 
Sulfur oxidizing bacteria: H2S  S  SO42-
Methanotrophs: CH 4 (methane)  CO2
Nitrifying bacteria: NH 4+  NO2- NO3-
Iron oxidizing bacteria: Fe2+  Fe3+
*ATP = adenosine triphosphate. (ADP = adenosin e DI phosphate) 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>s
e
e
graentsmpcty.
reucng
gHeterotroph 
Fermentation 
Respiration (Quantities of compounds omitted for 
i li i ) glucos glucos 2 pyruvate lactate 
or 
CO2 + ethanol 
2 ADP + 2 Pi 2 ATP 2 NAD+ 2 NADH 
ATP NADH NAD+ 
pyruvate 
Krebs' 
Cycle 
CO2 NAD+ 
NADH 
NADH NAD+ e A 
B 
H+ -
di 
ADP+Pi ATP 
Type A B 
aerobic 
sulfate-O2 
SO4 2-H2O 
H2S or S  
 
d i denitrifyin NO3 -NO, N2,  
N2O, NH3 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Autotrophs, continued: (Quantities of compounds omitted for simplicity.) 
NADPH NADP + 
"Dark Reactions" 
(common to all)	CO2 glucose 
ATP 
Chemosynthesis 
(releases energy) ADP + P i 
D 
C e -
H+ gradient E 
F 
ADP + P i 
ATP 
e -
C D NADP + 
NADPH (requires energy) 
(requires energy) 
 
 
  
 
 Type
sulfur-oxidizing 
nitrifying C 
H2S 
H2S 
NH3,
NO2 -D 
S, SO 42-
S, SO 42-
NO3 -E 
O2 
NO3 -
O2 F 
H2O 
N2O 
H2O 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>APPENDIX
This is the same information given above, organized slightly differently &amp; in more detail 
Modes of Nutrition -Some basic definitions 
An organism needs a source of carbon, plus en ergy (ATP), plus reducing power (NADH).           
These may all come from the same source (e.g. glucose provides all three), or they may 
come from different sources: 
Where does the carbon come from? 
a) Organic molecules  heterotrophs
    b) Inorganic - mainly CO2 = autotrophs
Where does the energy come from?
                   a) Chemical reactions (redox reactions) - chemotrophs
                   b) Light - phototrophs 
What molecule is the electron donor? 
a) Organic molecules - organotro phs
               b) Inorganic (e.g., H2O, H2, Sulfur) - lithotrophs
What molecule is the electron acceptor ?
 a) O2 = aerobic respiration
 b) Oxidants other than O2 (SO4, NO3, FeIII) = anaerobic respiration 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1.018/7.30J  Fall 2009 
Ecology I: The Earth System 
REA DINGS: 
Textbook 
p. 43, 84  88; 673-674 
Luria. 1975. Overview of photosynthesis. 
Kaiser, J. 1995. Can deep bacteria live on nothing but rocks and water? Science. 270:377. 
Jannasch, H. Life at the sea floor. Nature. 1995 374:676-677 
Lovley, D. Bug juice harvesting electricity with microorganisms. 2006. Nat Rev. Microbiol. 4:497 
Jetten, M et al. Microbiology &amp; application of the anaerobic ammonium oxidation (anammox) process Curr Opin 
Biotechnol. 2001 Jun; 12(3):283-8. 
Lecture 3: How to be Alive
Carbon and energy transformations
Nature has put itself the problem of how to catch in flight light streaming to earth 
and to store the most elusive of all powers in rigid form. 
Mayer, 1842, discovered law of conservation of energy 
Summary 
energy inputs: 
solar 
chemical Carbon Metabolism 
O2 and CH2O 
Heterotrophs 
self-Autotrophs 
nourished from 
nourishers  others  
CO2 and H2O 
Organisms can be broadly  classified by  how they  obtain their energy  and carbon 
Living organisms can be generally categorized by their primary sources of carbon, reducing 
power (electrons), and energy. Typically whether these carbon, energy and electron sources 
are organic, or inorganic, guides the classification. The different types of metabolisms found in 
these diverse organisms, that differentially oxidize or reduce different organic and inorganic</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>s
graentAutotroph	 (Quantities of compounds omitted for simplicity.) 
"Dark Reactions" 
glucose (common to all)	CO2
ATP
Photosynthesis ADP + Pi NADP+NADPH 
LIGHT 
D 
C NADP+ 
NADPH e -
H+ 
di 
ADP + Pi ATP 
Type C D 
oxygenic H2O  O2 
(plant) 
anoxygenic H2S  S, SO4 2-
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------METABOLIC DIVERSITY of Energy Sources (Reductants) and Sinks (Oxidants) 
CHEMOLITHOAUTOTROPHS - Examples 
ANAEROBIC RESPIRERS - Examples 
Physiological groups of bacteria able to grow under anaerobic conditions using external 
electron acceptors for electron transportBacterial group Typical species Metabolic processElectron 
acceptorReduction products(s)
Denitrifiers
Sulfate reducers
Sulfur reducers
Methanogenic bacteria
Acetogenic bacteria
Succinogenic bacteria
Iron reducersPseudomonas 
denitrificans
Desulfovibrio vulgaris
Methanobacterium
thermoautotrophicumDesulfuromonas 
acetoxidans
Acetobacterium 
woodii
Wolinella 
succinogenes
Pseudomonas GS-15Nitrate respirationN2, N2O, 
NO2-
S2-
S2-
CH4
CH3-COOH
Succinate
Fe2+Fe3+SO42-
S0NO3-
FumarateCO2
CO2Sulfate respiration
Sulfur respiration
Carbonate respiration
Carbonate respiration
Fumarate respiration
Iron respiration
6 Groups of bacteria able to use inorganic electron donors for growth ("chemolithoautotrophs").Bacterial group Typical species Metabolic processElectron 
donorElectron 
acceptorCarbon 
sourceProduct
Hydrogen-oxidizing 
bacteria 
Carbon monoxide - 
oxidizing bacteria
Ammonium-oxidizing 
bacteria
Nitrite-oxidizing 
bacteria
Sulfur-oxidizing 
bacteria
Iron-oxidizing 
bacteria
Methanogenic 
bacteria
Acetogenic bacteriaAlcaligenes 
eutrophus
Pseudomonas 
carboxydovorans
Nitrosomonas 
europaea
Nitrobacter 
winogradskyi
Thiobacillus 
thiooxidans
Thiobacillus 
ferrooxidans
Methanobacterium 
thermoautotmphicum
Acetobacterium 
woodiiH2 oxidationH2 O2 CO2
CO2 CO2
CO2H2O
CO2
CO2
CO2
CO2
CO2O2
O2
O2
O2
O2
CO2
CO2H2
H2CO
NH4+
Fe2+Fe3+
CH4
CH3- 
COOHNO2-NO2-
NO3-
SO42- S, S2O32-CO oxidation
Ammonium oxidation
Nitrite oxidation
Sulfur oxidation
Iron oxidation
Methanogenesis
Acetogenesis
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>**NADPH = nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate 
B. Heterotrophs 
These organisms (nourished by others) get their energy and carbon by oxidizing (burning) 
reduced organic compounds, eg organic matter. ATP and NADH*** are produced, which can 
then be used elsfor biosynthesis, growth and the production of new cells. (***NADH = 
nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (chemically similar to NADPH, NADH is oxidized to facilitate 
ATP production, while NADPH is associated with biosynthesis). 
1. Aerobic respiration 
Who? Aerobic eukaryotes and prokaryotes 
C Source? CH 2O (sugars, amino acids, organic acids, other organic compounds) 
Energy Source? CH2O 
Electron Acceptor? O2 
Where? Aerobic conditions 
These reaction is essentially the reverse of the Calvin cycle. O2 is the final electron acceptor. 
Plants also carry out this reaction to get energy for their growth and metabolic processes. 
CH 2O + O 2  CO 2 + H 2O 
2. Fermentation 
Who? Eukaryotes and prokaryotes 
C Source? CH 2O 
Energy Source? CH2O 
Electron Acceptor? organic compounds (part of the energy source gets oxidized, the other 
part reduced) 
Where? Anaerobic conditions 
This is only the first part of respiration and results in partial breakdown of glucose. The 
products are organic acids or alcohols (e.g., lactic acid, ethanol, acetic acid) rather than CO2. 
3. Anaerobic respiration 
Who? Prokaryotes only 
C Source? CH 2O 
Energy Source? CH2O 
Electron Acceptor? Oxidized inorganic compounds (SO42-, Fe3+, NO3+, etc.) 
Where? Anaerobic conditions 
Very similar to aerobic respiration, except that O2 is not the final electron acceptor. Instead, 
another oxidized compound such as SO42-, NO3-, or CO2 is the final electron acceptor. 
Iron reducing bacteria: Fe3+  Fe2+
Denitrifying bacteria: NO 3- NO2-
NO 2- N2
Sulfate reducing bacteria: SO42- S  H2S
Methanogens: CO 2  CH4(methane)
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourse Ware 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For informati on about citing these mate rials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/term s.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Competition and the niche</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1.018/7.30J  fall 2009 
Ecology of the Earth System 
Competition and the Niche 
REA DINGS Tues and Thurs LECTUREs: 
Competition Smith/Smith Chapter 14, 242-263 + Lauer&amp;Spacie (zebra mussels) &amp; Byers readings 
Predation Smith/Smith Chapter 15 all + Turchin paper on lemmings 
Today :
Resource (exploitativ e) and interference competition
Lotka-Volterra equations
experimental ev idence for competition
the concept of niche
field ev idence of competition
Density -dependent population regulation Allelopathy (a form of interference competition) 
In song sparrows, reproductive success declines 
with increasing population density

Fewer fledged young per female 
 Lower juvenile survivorship over the winter 
dN1 = r1N1(K1  N1 12N2 )dt K1 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourse Ware 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For informati on about citing these mate rials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/term s.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Biogeochemical cycles</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec07/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourse Ware 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For informati on about citing these mate rials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/term s.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1.018/7.30J  fall 2009 
Ecology of the Earth System 
Readings : 
Lecture 7 Notes Biogeochemical cycles 
Readings: Smith&amp;Smith Chapter 25 514 -523 and Chapter 26 525 -537 (C cycle)
Galloway, et al. Transformation of the Nitrogen Cyc le: . Science 320, 889 (2008) 
Oki, et al. Global Hydrological Cycles and World Water Science 313, 1068 (2006) 
Filippelli, The Global Phosphorus Cycle: Past, Present, and Future . Elements, Vol. 4, pg. 89-95 
How much of an element or compound is present in a certain component of the biosphere?
What is the global amount, the reservoirs , the compounds  and their transformations ?
The movements between reservoirs are fluxes. How much of an element or compound 
moves from one reservoir per unit time?
1.Global geochemical cy cles are assessed in terms of fluxes and 
reserv oirs. Ty pical fluxes range &gt; teragrams (1012g) per y ear.
2. The different cy cles of the elements (P, S, N, C) v ary in terms of 
their major reserv oirs, rates of flux, and biological interaction.
3.Change in v alence (redox state) caused by  biological processes
greatly  influence elemental paths in sev eral biogeochemical cy cles.
4.Human activ ities are influencing the flux within some elemental cy cles 
on the same scales as all natural processes combined (P, N, S).</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Limiting factors and Redfield</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Behavior
(7,9)1.018/7.30J Fall 2009 
Ecology I: The Earth System 
Lecture 10Limiting Factors, and Redfield 
READINGS 
Smith and Smith 28-30; pp.54-56; Ch. 5, esp pp 81-83; 
Redfield, 1934: On The Proportions Of Organic Derivations In Sea Water. James Johnstone Memorial Volume, 
Liverpool University Press, Liverpool. 176-192 
Relevant information also in these articles, which were assigned for Lectures 4 and 5 
Falkowski: 2002. The Oceans Invisible Forest. Scientific American August 2002. p.38-45 
Chisholm, 1992 What Limits Phytoplankton Growth? Oceanus Magazine. 35:36-46 
Outline: 
I.	Limiting factors 
A.	Freshwater 
B.	Oceans 
II.	Redfield and the co-evolution of 
Chemistry and biology in seawater 
Redfield 
Alfred Redfield was one of the leading oceanographers of our time, and many of his contributions laid the 
foundations for modern oceanography. He was a physiologist who viewed the oceans as one would a living 
organism, with the global ocean circulation being analogous to the human bodys circulatory system. (The fact 
that the composition of blood and seawater is similar in many respects undoubtedly did not escape him). 
According to Redfield, the close relationship between the relative quantities of essential elements in seawater 
and living matter permits one to approach the biochemical cycle in the sea much the same way as the 
physiologist examines the metabolism of an individual organism. 
He further wrote, It appears that the relative quantities of nitrate and phosphate occurring in the oceans 
of the world are just those which are required for the composition of the animals and plants which live 
in the sea. That two compounds of such great importance in the synthesis of living matter are so 
exactly balanced in the marine environment, is a unique fact, and one which calls for some explanation, 
if it is not to be regarded as a mere coincidence. 
(1)	Do you think Redfields image of the sea as having a physiology is simply metaphorical? Or do you 
see direct parallels between the workings of your body and the workings of the sea? 
(2)	Redfield hypothesized that there must be a biochemical circulation which is different from, though 
dependent upon, the physical circulation of the water. What evidence led to this hypothesis? 
(3)	In formulating his hypothesis, Redfield engaged in an armchair experiment in which he took a liter of 
seawater from the deep ocean and returned it to the surface where it could be inoculated with 
phytoplankton and incubated in sunlight until the nutrients were exhausted, and equilibrate with the 
atmosphere. He then returned this liter of water to the deep ocean where degradative processes 
could go into operation. 
What questions did he ask of this experiment, and how did the answers illuminate his theory? 
Limiting Factors 
(1)	How would you design an experiment to determine which nutrient is limiting in a particular system? 
(2) What is the compensation depth in aquatic ecosystems? What is it a function of? 
(3) How does the depth of the thermocline affect productivity? 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourse Ware 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For informati on about citing these mate rials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/term s.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Primary productivity I and II</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/resources/mit1_018jf09_lec05/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5-6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2  
I.  Definitions 
 
biomass: total mass (or energy) of all living material (units: g C/m2  or  kJ/m2) 
gross primary productivity (GPP)  = rate of conversion of CO 2 to organic carbon per unit surface area 
  Units:  g C m-2 year-1, or kJ m-2 year-1 
gross primary production  has units of g C year-1 for a lake, forest, field, ecosystem, biome, etc. 
respiration by autotrophs (R A) = how much energy or carbon is used for plant metabolism 
net primary production (NPP) = GPP   RA  = how much energy or carbon is stored as biomass   
respiration by heterotrophs (R H) = how much energy or carbon is used for heterotroph metabolism 
net community production ( NCP ) = how much of GPP produced is not lost to respiration  
  = GPP   RA  RH   =  NPP   RH    
photosynthetic efficiency ( PE) = 100*(incident radiation converted to NPP)/(total incident radiation) 
 
n.b.  Were using energy and (reduced) carbon interchangeably.  Conversion:  39 kJ per g C  
 
 
 
II.  Residence times and Turnover times 
 
f = flux  (mass/area/time).    
M = mass (biomass/area) Mean residence time (MRT)  = M/f  
= (g/m
2) / (g/m2/year) = years 
Fractional turnover  (k) = 1 / MRT * 100  
= % turning over each year  ( or some appropriate time interval) 
Turnover Time   = 1/k 
P:B ratio  is the amount of biomass that gets replaced per unit time. 
 (Units of yr-1)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourse Ware 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
1.018J / 7.30J Ecology I: The Earth 
Fall 2009 
For informati on about citing these mate rials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/term s.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>-------------------- --------------------Some helpful unit conversions 
Tg (teragram) = 1012g 
Pg (petagram) = 1015g = 109 metric tons (mt) 
Metric ton = 106 g 
Gt (gigaton) = 1015g = 109 ton 
Study  Questions: 
Productivity 
1.	What is the difference between net and gross primary productivity? What is the difference between net 
community productivity and net primary productivity? How might you measure these differences in an 
aquatic or terrestrial ecosystem? 
2.	What factors can limit primary productivity in terrestrial ecosystems? How are these factors reflected in the 
global distribution of primary production? 
3.	What is the turnover time of a forest? How is it measured? 
4.	What is functionally similar about phytoplankton and trees? What is different? 
5.	What are the similarities and differences between the flow of energy and carbon in the open ocean and in a 
mature rain forest? 
6.	Why are phytoplankton so much more productive (on the basis of biomass) than land-based plants? 
7.	How might increases in atmospheric CO2 affect global productivity? 
8.	The following data are available for two forests. Fill in the missing values. Which forest is older? 
Gemstone Cerna 
Total biomass (kcal/m2)	 200,000 1,500,000 
Total photosynthesis (kcal/m2/yr)	 12,200 45,100 
Plant respiration (kcal/m2/yr)	 (i)__________ (ii)__________ 
New plant tissue created (kcal/m2/yr)	 7,500 13,200 
Heterotrophic respiration (kcal/m2/yr)	 4,600 13,180 
Net community production (kcal/m2/yr) (iii)__________ (iv)__________ 
C residence time	 (v) __________ (vi)__________ 
Fractional turnover	 (vii) __________ (viii) __________ 
9.	What are the challenges associated with using uptake of 14CO 2 to measure primary productivity? 
10. Approximately what is the contribution of marine ecosystems to global NPP? 
11. Explain why light tends to be more limiting in freshwater or coastal systems than in the open ocean. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 
1.018/7.30J                          Fall 2009 
Ecology I:  The Earth System 
 
Lecture s  5 and 6 - Primary Productivity   
 
  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
  
 
Behavior 
(7,9)   
  Smith and Smith  p42-50;  Ch 6, pp. 91-92;  Chapter 24, esp. pp 478- 490;  p. 632-640;  Ch 25, pp512-514;  Ch 
31, esp.  pp 666-667 
  Morton, O.  2007.   Introduction.   Eating the Sun:  How Plants Power the Planet 
  Chisholm,    1992  What Limits Phytoplankton Growth?  Oceanus Magazine. 35:36-46  
  Falkowski:   2002.  The Oceans Invisible Forest.   Scientific American   August 2002.  p.38-45  
Further Reading (optional, but may be helpful in study questions).  You can look these papers up at the library. 
  Nemani, RR et al.  2003 .  Climate-driven increases in global terrestrial net primary productivity from 1982 to 1999. 
Science.  300:1560 -1563 .   
  Field, C.B., M.J. Behrenfeld, J. T. Randerson, and P. Falkowski.   1998.  Primary Production of the Biosphere:  
Integrating Terrestrial and Oceanic Components.   Science. 281:237-240   
  Rojstaczer, S. Sterling, S.M. and N.J. Moore.  2001   Human Appropriation of Photosynthesis Products.  Science  
294: 2549-2553   
 
 
Outline: 
 
 Earths Metabolism emerges from cellular 
metabolism 
 Definitions  
 Residence times and turnover rate 
 Distribution of Productivity on Earth 
 
Terrestrial Productivity 
 Distribution 
 Measuring Terrestrial Productivity 
 What limits it? 
 
Aquatic Productivity 
 Who does it? 
 How do we measure it? 
 Dynamics of Lakes and oceans 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
  
 
 
 
  
 REA DINGS</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
