<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-452-economic-growth-fall-2016/</course_url>
    <course_title>Economic Growth</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Economics </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Developmental Economics </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Questions and Evidence (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-452-economic-growth-fall-2016/resources/mit14_452f16_lec1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Robustness 
The results are quite robust to a range of controls for other factors 
and trends. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 27 / 39 Courtesy of Daron Acemoglu, Suresh Naidu, Pascual Restrepo, and James A. Robinson. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Cross-Country Income Dierences
Cross-Country Income Dierences
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 Source unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see  https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
October 21, 2014. 2 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
The Eects of Democracy on Growth  
Democracy is a key aspect of political institutions of a society. 
Much controversy on its merits, and many popular writings and some 
economists emphasize its weaknesses and distortions (which are 
indeed many). Relatedly, the conventional wisdom appears to be That 
democracy is not good for economic growth and main fact be bad. 
Is this true? 
Let me share results from Acemoglu, Naidu, Restrepo and Robinson 
(2014) attempting to answer these questions. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 20 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
14.452 Economic Growth
Fall 2016
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Origins of Income Dierences and World Economic Growth 
Persistence of Prosperity  
DZAARGAUSAUT
BRBBEL
BENBOLBRA
B FA
BDICMRCAN
CPV
TCDCHL
CHNCOL
COMCOGCRI
CIVDNK
DOM
ECUEGYSLVGNQ
E THFINFRA
G AB
GMBGHAGRC
GTM
GIN
GNBHNDHKGI SL
INDIDNIRNIRL
I SRITA
JAMJPN
JOR
KENKOR
LSOLUX
M DG M WIM YS
MLIM US
M EX
M AR
MOZNPLNLD
NZL
NIC
NERNGANOR
PAKPAN
PRY
PER
PHLPRT
ROM
RWASENSGP
Z AFESP
LKASWECHE
SYR
TZATHA
TGOTTO
TUR
UGAG BRUSA
URY
VEN
ZMBZ WE.6
.7
.8
.9
1
1.1l ogGDPperworkerrelativetotheUSi n2000.6 .7 .8 .9 1
logGDPperworkerrelativetotheUSin1960
Figure: Log GDP per worker in 1960 and 2000. 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 10 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Semi-Parametric Estimates: Democratizations  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 29 / 39 Courtesy of Daron Acemoglu, 
Suresh Naidu, Pascual Restrepo, and James A. Robinson. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Cross-Country Income Dierences 
Cross-Country Income Dierences (continued) 
There are very large dierences in income per capita and output per 
worker across countries today. 
1960
1980
20000
.00005
.0001
.00015
.0002
.00025Densityofcoutries
0 10000 20000 30000 40000 50000
gdp
percapita
Figure: Distribution of PPP-adjusted GDP per capita. 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 3 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Cross-Country Income Dierences 
Cross-Country Income Dierences (continued)  
1960
1980
20000
.1
.2
.3
.4Densityofcoutries
6 8 10 12
loggdpperworker
Figure: Distribution of log GDP per worker (PPP-adjusted). 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 7 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Persistence, Reversal and Geography 
Reversal of Fortune in Urbanization  
.GDP per capita, PPP, in 1995
Urbanization in 15000 5 10 15 2078910
ARGAUS
BGDBLZ
BOLBRACAN
CHL
COL CRI
DOM DZAECU
EGYGTM
GUYHKG
HND
HTIIDN
INDJAM
LAOLKAMARMEXMYS
NICNZL
PAKPAN
PER
PHLPRYSGP
SLVTUNURYUSA
VEN
VNM
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 15 / 39  The Quarterly Journal of Economics. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from  our
Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Economic Growth and Income Dierences 
Economic Growth and Income Dierences  
Why is the United States richer in 1960 than other nations and able 
to grow at a steady pace thereafter? 
How did Singapore, South Korea and Botswana manage to grow at a 
relatively rapid pace for 40 years? 
Why did Spain grow relatively rapidly for about 20 years, but then 
slow down? Why did Brazil and Guatemala stagnate during the 
1980s? 
What is responsible for the disastrous growth performance of Nigeria? 
Central questions for understanding how the capitalist system works 
and the origins of economic growth. 
Central questions also for policy and welfare, since dierences in 
income related to living standards, consumption and health. 
Our rst task is to develop a coherent framework to investigate these 
questions and as a byproduct we will introduce the workhorse models 
of dynamic economic analysis and macroeconomics. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 9 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Inspecting the Residuals: The Case of Korea  
Figure: Red: Korean before democracy. Orange: Korea after democracy. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 25 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Semi-Parametric Estimates: Reversal in Democracy  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 30 / 39 Courtesy of Daron Acemoglu, 
Suresh Naidu, Pascual Restrepo, and James A. Robinson. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Instrumental Variables  
So far, the strategy for identifying the eect of democracy on future 
economic outcomes has been to condition on observables. 
Alternative is to use an instrumental-variables (IV) strategy exploiting 
a source of variation that is less likely to be contaminated with 
omitted variable biases. 
There is no perfect instrument for democracy, but a plausibly  
exogenous source of variation still provides useful estimates for  
triangulatingthe eect of democracy.  
Democracy spreads within (culturally homogeneous) areas,  
reminiscent of democratization waves.  
Here exploit regional democratization waves. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 31 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Institutions and Growth  
What about direct evidence of the eect of institutions of growth? 
Three types of evidence have been presented in the literature: 
1 
2 
3 Country-level evidence on the long-run eects of institutions, exploiting 
potentially exogenous sources of variation (e.g., Acemoglu, Johnson 
and Robinson, 2001). 
Within-country evidence on the long-run eects of institutional features 
that three across localities within a country (e.g., Dell, 2010). 
Growth regressions, focusing on shorter periods (such as decades or 
even shorter periods). 
Even though growth regressions are the most problematic from a 
variety of viewpoints (as we will discuss later), since they connect to 
some of the issues we will discuss in this course, I now provide 
evidence using a modied version of growth regressions. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 19 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Economic Growth and Income Dierences 
Economic Growth and Income Dierences  
SpainSouthKorea
IndiaBrazilUSA
Singapore
NigeriaGuatemalaUK
Botswana6
7
8
9
10l oggdppercapita
1960 1970 1980 1990 2000
year
Figure: The evolution of income per capita 1960-2000. 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 8 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
IV Estimates  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 34 / 39 Courtesy of Daron Acemoglu, Suresh Naidu, Pascual Restrepo, and James A. Robinson. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Challenges of Estimating the Eect of Democracy  
Measuring democracy create a dichotomous measure of democracy, 
minimizing measurement error. 
Not comparing apples and oranges models that country xed eects. 
Dynamics allow for mean reversion in income per capita exploiting 
our annual data. 
Sources of exogenous variation. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 21 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Persistence, Reversal and Geography 
Reversal of Fortune: Timing  
 The Quarterly Journal of Economics. All rights reserved.This content is excluded from our
Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 17 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Results: Importance of Dynamics Again  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 24 / 39 Courtesy of Daron Acemoglu, Suresh Naidu, Pascual Restrepo, and James A. Robinson. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Origins of Income Dierences and World Economic Growth 
Over Longer Periods Persistence and Divergence  
WesternOffshoots
WesternEurope
A f ricaLa tinAmer ic aAs ia6
7
8
9
10l oggdppercapi ta
1800 1850 1900 1950 2000
year
Figure: Evolution of GDP per capita 1820-2000. 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 11 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Importance of Dynamics 
Democratizations are more likely to happen when nondemocracies are 
having economic di culties: 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 22 / 39 Courtesy of Daron Acemoglu, 
Suresh Naidu, Pascual Restrepo, and James A. Robinson. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
The Nickell Bias  
The presence of the lagged dependent variable creates bias in panel 
estimates. But this potential bias turns out not to be important in 
this case. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 26 / 39  The Quarterly Journal of Economics.  All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For 
more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>October 21, 2014 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 1 /  39 
14.452 Economic Growth: Lecture 1 , Questions and 
Evidence
Daron  Acemoglu
MIT</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Method I: Panel Data  
Consider the following linear panel data model at annual frequency: 
p 
yct = Dct +  jyctj + c + t + ct .
j=1 
Here yct is the log of GDP per capita in country c at time t, and Dct 
is the dichotomous measure of democracy in country c in year t. 
In addition c denote a full set of country xed eects, the t denote 
a full set of year xed eects, and ct is the error term. 
Note that this specication has level on the RHS rather than growth 
(does that matter?) 
It also imposes that democracy does not have a permanent eect on 
growth (does this matter?). 
Crucially, none of the intermediating variables like education or  
investment are controlled for on the right-hand side.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 23 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Rest of the Course 
Rest of the Course 
In the rest of the course, we will introduce several workhorse models 
of economic growth used in macroeconomics and other elds more 
broadly (as well as some applications of techniques of dynamic 
economic analysis utilized even more widely). 
Three objectives: 
Build practice and skills in the analysis of dynamic economic models. 
Obtain intuition and insight about sources and causes of dierences in 
long run economic performance across countries. 
Start thinking about how to map some of these ideas to data. 
In the process, of the second goal, we will focus on proximate causes 
of economic growth (physical capital, human capital and technology), 
but useful to bear in mind that, especially in the context of the third 
goal, it is also important to investigate why these vary systematically 
across countries the question of fundamental causes. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 38 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Cross-Country Income Dierences 
Cross-Country Income Dierences (continued)  
1960
198020000
.1
.2
.3
.4Densityofcoutries
6 7 8 9 10 11
l
oggdppercapita
Figure: Estimates of the distribution of countries according to log GDP per capita 
(PPP-adjusted) in 1960, 1980 and 2000. 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 5 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Summary  
A range of dierent strategies yield positive and large eects of  
democracy on future GDP per capita, indicating roughly that a  
country that democratizes becomes 20-30% richer than it would  
otherwise be in the next 20 years.  
This eect does not appear to be related to other confounding eects 
or country-specic trends potentially impacting both democracy and 
growth. 
But important to control for GDP dynamics (and of course country 
xed eects). 
We will see later that many cross-country regressions do not do this, 
sometimes leading to unreliable or unstable results. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 37 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
First Stage  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 33 / 39 Courtesy of Daron Acemoglu, 
Suresh Naidu, Pascual Restrepo, and James A. Robinson. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence From Proximate to Fundamental Causes 
From Correlates to Fundamental Causes  
Correlates of economic growth, such as physical capital, human  
capital and technology, will be our rst topic of study.  
But these are only proximate causes of economic growth and  
economic success:  
why do certain societies fail to improve their technologies, invest more 
in physical capital, and accumulate more human capital? 
Return to Figure above to illustrate this point further: 
how did South Korea and Singapore manage to grow, while Nigeria 
failed to take advantage of the growth opportunities? 
If physical capital accumulation is so important, why did Nigeria not 
invest more in physical capital? 
If education is so important, why our education levels in Nigeria still so 
low and why is existing human capital not being used more eectively? 
The answer to these questions is related to the fundamental causes of 
economic growth. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 13 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Cross-Country Income Dierences 
Cross-Country Income Dierences (continued)  
Part of the spreading out of the distribution in the Figure is because 
of the increase in average incomes. 
More natural to look at the log of income per capita when growth is 
approximately proportional: 
when x (t) grows at a proportional rate, log x (t) grows linearly, 
if x1 (t) and x2 (t) both grow by 10%, x1 (t)  x2 (t) will also grow, 
while log x1 (t)  log x2 (t) will remain constant. 
The next Figure shows a similar pattern, but now the spreading-out is 
more limited. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 4 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Persistence, Reversal and Geography 
Reversal of Fortune in Population Density  
.GDP per capita, PPP, in 1995
Log Population Density in 1500-5 0 5678910
AGOARGAUS
BDIBEN
BFA BGDBHS
BLZ
BOLBRABRB
BWA
CAFCAN
CHL
CIVCMRCOGCOL
COMCPVCRI
DMADOM DZAECU
EGY
ERIGAB
GHAGIN
GMBGRD
GTM
GUYHKG
HND
HTIIDN
INDJAM
KENKNA
LAOLCA
LKA
LSOMAR
MDGMEX
MLIMOZMRT
MWIMYS
NAM
NERNGANIC
NPLNZL
PAKPAN
PER
PHLPRY
RWASDNSENSGP
SLESLVSURSWZ
TCDTGOTTO
TUN
TZAUGAURYUSA
VCTVEN
VNMZAF
ZARZMBZWE
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 16 / 39  The Quarterly Journal of Economics. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our
Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq- f air-use.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Persistence, Reversal and Geography 
Persistence and Reversal  
But is there persistence even if we go further? If yes, this might 
suggest there are important unchanging factors aecting growth at 
the country level (such as geography). 
If, on the other hand, this persistence breaks down during periods of 
fundamental institutional change, this would put the spotlight on 
institutions. 
How to approximate prosperity/GDP before national accounts? Some 
proxies: 
Urbanization: before industrial times only more prosperous places (and 
those with agricultural surplus) could support large urban areas. 
Population density: similar justication. 
Focusing on the sample of former colonies, we do in fact see a sharp 
reversal from before colonization to today. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 14 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Persistence, Reversal and Geography 
Reversal of Fortune: Role of Industrialization  
IndustrialProductionPerCapita,UKin1900=100
(fromBairoch)
050100150200250300350400
1750 1800 1830 1860 1880 1900 1913 1928 1953
US Australia Canada New Zealand Brazil M
exico India
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 18 / 39  The Quarterly Journal of Economics. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our
Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Cross-Country Income Dierences 
Cross-Country Income Dierences (continued)  
Theory is easier to map to data when we look at output (GDP) per 
worker. 
Moreover, key sources of dierence in economic performance across 
countries are national policies and institutions. 
The next Figure looks at the unweighted distribution of countries 
according to (PPP-adjusted) GDP per worker 
workers : total economically active population according to the 
denition of the International Labour Organization. 
Overall, two important facts:  
Large amount of inequality in income per capita and income per worker  
across countries.  
1 
2 Slight but noticeable increase in inequality across nations (though not 
necessarily across individuals in the entire world). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 6 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Origins of Income Dierences and World Economic Growth 
Growth in the Last 200 Years  
U SA
BritainSpain
GhanaBrazilChina
India6
7
8
9
10l oggdppercapi ta
1800 1850 1900 1950 2000
year
Figure: Evolution of income per capita in various countries. 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 12 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
IV Strategy  
Let Rc denote the geographic region of country c. 
Construct the set of countries 
'Ic = {c' : c = c, Rc ' = Rc , Dc 't0 = Dct0 }, countries in the same
region ith the same political history, i.e., Dc't0 = Dct0.  
Then construct the instrument  
1 Zct =  Dc 't .|Ic | c 'Ic 
Here, Zct is the jack-knifed average of democracy in a region  initial
regime cell, which leaves out the own-country observation. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 32 / 39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Mechanisms  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 35 / 39 Courtesy of Daron Acemoglu, 
Suresh Naidu, Pascual Restrepo, and James A. Robinson. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Mechanisms (continued)  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 36 / 39 Courtesy of Daron Acemoglu, Suresh Naidu, Pascual Restrepo, and James A. Robinson. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>Growth and Development: The Questions and Evidence Institutions and Growth 
Semi-Parametric Matching 
Relax linearity and allow for richer dynamics. 
More generally, and using the potential outcomes notation, the causal 
eect of a transition to democracy at time t on GDP s periods 
thereafter for countries that are democratizing is 
s ss = E (yct (1)  yct (0)|Dct = 1, Dct1 = 0) .
The challenge in estimating s is that countries that democratize may 
be dierent in terms of their potential outcomes than those that 
remain in nondemocracy. 
To overcome this problem, let us assume: 
Assumption 2 (selection on observables): 
yct s (d)Dct |Dct1 = 0, yct1, yct2, yct 3, yct4, t for all
yct1, . . . , yct4 , and for all c, t, and s  0. 
Estimation then uses inverse propensity score weighting and 
regression adjustment based on observables. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 1 October 21, 2014. 28 / 39</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Directed Technological Change and Applications (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-452-economic-growth-fall-2016/resources/mit14_452f16_lec12and13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12&#8211;13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Implications 
Implications II  
The framework also gives a potential interpretation for the dynamics 
of the college premium during the 1970s and 1980s. 
It is reasonable that the equilibrium skill bias of technologies, NH /NL, 
is a sluggish variable. 
Hence a rapid increase in the supply of skills would rst reduce the skill 
premium as the economy would be moving along a constant technology 
(constant NH /NL). 
After a while technology would start adjusting, and the economy would 
move back to the upward sloping relative demand curve, with a 
relatively sharp increase in the college premium. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 42 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Environment 
Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change III  
Dierences with baseline expanding product varieties model: 
1 
2 These are production functions for intermediate goods rather than the 
nal good. 
(5) and (6) use dierent types of machines dierent ranges [0, NL (t)] 
and [0, NH (t)]. 
All machines are supplied by monopolists that have a fully-enforced 
perpetual patent, at prices pLx (, t) for   [0, NL (t)] and pHx (, t) 
for   [0, NH (t)]. 
Once invented, each machine can be produced at the xed marginal 
cost  in terms of the nal good. 
Normalize to   1  . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 20 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>79</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Environmental Disaster 
Environmental Disaster  
An environmental disaster  occurs if St reaches 0 in nite time. 
Proposition 
Disaster. 
The laissez-faire equilibrium always leads to an environmental disaster. 
Proposition 
The role of policy. 
1  when the two inputs are strong substitutes ( &gt; 1/ (1  )) and S is 
su ciently high, a temporary clean research subsidy will prevent an 
environmental disaster; 
2 in contrast, when the two inputs are weak substitutes 
( &lt; 1/ (1  )), a temporary clean research subsidy cannot prevent 
an environmental disaster. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 80 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>56</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers Environment 
Equilibrium Relative Bias with Knowledge Spillovers II  
Intuitively, the additional increasing returns to scale coming from 
state dependence makes strong bias easier to obtain, because the 
induced technology eect is stronger. 
Note the elasticity of substitution between skilled and unskilled labor 
signicantly less than 2 may be su cient to generate strong 
equilibrium bias. 
How much lower than 2 the elasticity of substitution can be depends 
on the parameter . Unfortunately, this parameter is not easy to 
measure in practice. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 57 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>88</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
14.452 Economic Growth
Fall 2016
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>44</slideno>
          <text>Skillpremium
Long runrelative
demandforskills
ExogenousShiftin
RelativeSupplyInitialpremium
Short run
ResponseLong runpremium       Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Implications 
Implications V  
Figure: Dynamics of the skill premium in response to an increase in the relative 
supply of skills, with a downward-sloping endogenous-technology relative demand 
curve. 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 45 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>74</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Basic Model 
Model: Innovation  
At the beginning of every period scientists (of mass s = 1) work  
either to innovate in the clean or the dirty sector.  
Given sector choice, each randomly allocated to one machine in their 
target sector. 
Every scientist has a probability j of success (without congestion). 
if successful, proportional improvement in quality by  &gt; 0 and the 
scientist gets monopoly rights for one period, thus 
Ajit =(1 + ) Ajit1; 
if not successful, no improvement and monopoly rights in that machine 
randomly allocated to an entrepreneur who uses technology 
Ajit = Ajit1. 
simplifying assumption, mimicking structure in continuous time models. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 75 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Characterization of Equilibrium 
Equilibrium I 
Allocation. Time paths of 
 
t=0, [C (t) , X (t) , Z (t)]
[NL (t) , NH (t)]A 
t=0, h 
pLx (, t) , xL (, t) , VL (, t) t=0, and 
[0,NL (t)] 
[H (, t) , xH (, t) , VH (, t)] 
t=0, , and 
[0,NH (t)] 

[r (t) , wL (t) , wH (t)]t=0. 
Equilibrium. An allocation in which 
All existing research rms chooseA h px (, t) , xf (, t) t=0, for f = L, H to maximize prots, f [0,Nf (t)] 
is determined by free entry 0=t
=0, are consistent with market clearing, and 
[NL (t) , NH (t)]
[r (t) , wL (t) , wH (t)]
[C (t) , X (t) , Z (t)]=0 are consistent with consumer optimization. t
t
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 23 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>87</slideno>
          <text>Conclusions Conclusions 
Conclusions II  
The implications of the class of models studied for the empirical 
questions mentioned above stem from the weak equilibrium bias and 
strong equilibrium bias results. 
Technology should not be thought of as a black box. Prot incentives 
will play a major role in both the aggregate rate of technological 
progress and also in the biases of the technologies. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 88 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Basics and Denitions 
Equilibrium Bias  
Weak equilibrium bias of technology: an increase in H/L, induces 
technological change biased towards H. i.e., given (1): 
1 
 d (AH (t) /AL (t))  0,dH/L 
so AH (t) /AL (t) is biased towards the factor that has become more 
abundant. 
Strong equilibrium bias: an increase in H/L induces a su ciently 
large change in the bias so that the relative marginal product of H 
relative to that of L increases following the change in factor supplies: 
dMP H /MPL &gt; 0,dH/L 
The major dierence is whether the relative marginal product of the 
two factors are evaluated at the initial relative supplies (weak bias) or 
at the new relative supplies (strong bias). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 17 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Environment 
Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change I 
Framework: expanding varieties model with lab equipment 
specication of the innovation possibilities frontier (so none of the 
results here depend on technological externalities). 
Constant supply of L and H. 
Representative household with the standard CRRA preferences:
  1C (t) 1 exp (t) dt, (2) 
0 1   
Aggregate production function: 
 1 1 
  Y (t)= LYL (t)+ H YH (t) 1 , (3) 
where intermediate good YL (t) is L-intensive, YH (t) is H-intensive. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 18 / 89 
h i</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Directed Technological Change and Factor Prices 
Directed Technological Change and Factor Prices 
In BGP, there is a positive relationship between H/L and N  
H /N
only when  &gt; 1. 
But this does not mean that depending on  (or ), changes in factor 
supplies may induce technological changes that are biased in favor or 
against the factor that is becoming more abundant. 
Why?  
L 
 NH /NL refers to the ratio of factor-augmenting technologies, or to the 
 
 ratio of physical productivities. 
What matters for the bias of technology is the value of marginal 
 product of factors, aected by relative prices.  
The relationship between factor-augmenting and factor-biased  
technologies is reversed when  is less than 1.  
H /NL is relatively biased towards H, 
H /NL is relatively biased towards H.  
When  &gt; 1, an increase in N
while when  &lt; 1, a decrease in N
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 36 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>73</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Basic Model 
Model: Environmental Dynamics 
Production of dirty input depletes environmental stock S: 
S) . 
S (&lt; ): baseline (unpolluted) level St+1 = Ydt +(1 + ) St if S  (0, (41)  
Reecting at the upper bound
of environmental quality. 
Absorbing at the lower bound S = 0. 
 &gt; 0: rate of environmental regeneration (measures amount of 
pollution that can be absorbed without extreme adverse 
consequences) 
S is general quality of environment, inversely related to CO2  
concentration (what we do below for calibration).  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 74 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>83</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Environmental Disaster 
What If Technological Change Were Undirected? 
Compare with a model where scientists randomly allocated across 
sectors so as to ensure equal growth in the qualities of clean and dirty 
machines, thus gYd   d / (+ d ) &lt; d c c 
Proposition 
The role of directed technical change. 
When  &gt; 1/ (1  ): 
1 An environmental disaster under laissez-faire arises earlier with  
directed technical change than in the equivalent economy with  
undirected technical change.  
2 However, a temporary clean research subsidy can prevent an 
environmental disaster with directed technical change, but not in the 
equivalent economy with undirected technical change. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 84 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>72</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Basic Model 
Model: Consumption  
Constant mass 1 of innitely lived representative consumers with 
intertemporal utility: 
1 u (Ct , St )t 
t=0 (1 + )
where u increasing and concave, with 
u  lim u (C , S)= ; (C , S) = 0 
S 0 S 
 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 73 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>57</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers Evidence 
Evidence  
Hanlon (2014): evidence on factor-augmenting directed technological 
change and its impact on factor prices. 
Following the interruption to the British cotton textile industry caused 
by the US Civil War, the decrease in American cotton led to 
technological change directed to other types of cotton inputs. 
There was a urry of new patents related to cotton spinning. These 
appear to be directed at Indian cotton which was relatively abundant 
but harder to prepare for spinning than American cotton. 
This looks like factor-augmenting technological change directed 
towards the more abundant input. Consistent with theory if the 
elasticity of substitution &gt; 1, which Hanlon s estimates suggest. 
Hanlon also provides evidence of strong relative bias relative Indian 
cotton prices actually increased despite this input s relative 
abundance. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 58 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>69</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Climate Change and Endogenous Technological Change 
Why?  
Two sector model with clean and dirty inputs with two key  
externalities  
Environmental externality : production of dirty inputs creates  
environmental degradation.  
Researchers work to improve the technology depending on expected 
prots and build on the shoulders of giants in their own sector  . 
	 Knowledge externality : advances in dirty (clean) inputs make their 
future use more protable. 
Policy interventions can redirect technological change towards  
clean technologies.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 70 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>71</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Basic Model 
Model: Production  
Innite horizon in discrete time (suppress time dependence for now) 
Final good Y produced competitively with a clean intermediary input 
Yc , and a dirty input Yd 
   1 1 1 Y = Yc  + Y  
d 
Most of the analysis:  &gt; 1, the two inputs are substitute.  
For j {c, d}, input Yj produced with labor Lj and a continuum of  
machines xji :  
1 
= L1 A1 Yj xji dij ji 0 
Machines produced monopolistically using the nal good 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 72 / 89 
Z</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Basics and Denitions 
Factor-augmenting technological change 
Production side of the economy: 
Y (t)= F (L (t) , H (t) , A (t)) , 
where F /A &gt; 0. 
Technological change is L-augmenting if 
F (L, H, A) L F (L, H, A) . A A L 
Equivalent to: 
the production function taking the special form, F (AL, H). 
Harrod-neutral technological change when L corresponds to labor and 
H to capital. 
H-augmenting dened similarly, and corresponds to F (L, AH). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 12 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Importance 
Wage push and capital-biased technological change  
First phase. Late 1960s and early 1970s: unemployment and share of 
labor in national income increased rapidly continental European 
countries. 
Second phase. 1980s: unemployment continued to increase, but the 
labor share declined, even below its initial level. 
Blanchard (1997): 
Phase 1: wage-push by workers 
Phase 2: capital-biased technological changes. 
Is there a connection between capital-biased technological changes in 
European economies and the wage push preceding it? 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 6 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>63</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Labor-Augmenting Change 
Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change III  
To answer 1, note that what distinguishes capital from labor is the 
fact that it accumulates. 
The neoclassical growth model with technological change experiences 
continuous capital-deepening as K (t) /L increases. 
This implies that technological change should be more  
labor-augmenting than capital augmenting.  
Proposition	 In the baseline model of directed technological change with 
H (t)= K (t) as capital, if K (t) /L is increasing over time 
and  &lt; 1, then NL (t) /NK (t) will also increase over time. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 64 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>86</slideno>
          <text>Conclusions Conclusions 
Conclusions I  
The bias of technological change is potentially important for the 
distributional consequences of the introduction of new technologies 
(i.e., who will be the losers and winners?); important for political 
economy of growth. 
Models of directed technological change enable us to investigate a 
range of new questions: 
the sources of skill-biased technological change over the past 100 years, 
the causes of acceleration in skill-biased technological change during 
more recent decades, 
the causes of unskilled-biased technological developments during the 
19th century, 
the relationship between labor market institutions and the types of 
technologies that are developed and adopted, 
why technological change in neoclassical-type models may be largely 
labor-augmenting. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 87 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>65</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Labor-Augmenting Change 
Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change V  
However, one special case works: 
Proposition	 Consider the baseline model of directed technological change 
with the two factors corresponding to labor and capital. 
Suppose that the innovation possibilities frontier is given by 
the knowledge spillovers specication and extreme state 
dependence, i.e.,  = 1 and that capital accumulates 
according to (40). Then there exists a constant growth path 
allocation in which there is only labor-augmenting 
technological change, the interest rate is constant and 
consumption and output grow at constant rates. Moreover, 
there cannot be any other constant growth path allocations. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 66 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>61</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Labor-Augmenting Change 
Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change I 
Models of directed technological change create a natural reason for 
technology to be more labor augmenting than capital augmenting. 
Under most circumstances, the resulting equilibrium is not purely 
labor augmenting and as a result, a BGP fails to exist. 
But in one important special case, the model delivers long-run purely 
labor augmenting technological changes exactly as in the neoclassical 
growth model. 
Consider a two-factor model with H corresponding to capital, that is, 
H (t)= K (t). 
Assume that there is no depreciation of capital. 
Note that in this case the price of the second factor, K (t), is the 
same as the interest rate, r (t). 
Empirical evidence suggests  &lt; 1 and is also economically plausible. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 62 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Basics and Denitions 
Constant Elasticity of Substitution Production Function I 
CES production function case: 
   1 1 
  Y (t)= L (AL (t) L (t)) + H (AH (t) H (t)) 1 , 
where 
AL (t) and AH (t) are two separate technology terms. 
i s determine the importance of the two factors, L + H = 1. 
  (0, )=elasticity of substitution between the two factors. 
 = , perfect substitutes, linear production function is linear. 
 = 1, Cobb-Douglas, 
 = 0, no substitution, Leontie. 
 &gt; 1, gross substitutes, 
 &lt; 1, gross complements . 
Clearly, AL (t) is L-augmenting, while AH (t) is H-augmenting. 
Whether technological change that is L-augmenting (or  
H-augmenting) is L-biased or H-biased depends on .  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 14 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>s lm
l i ku i
 sem
egeage pr
l l ow
 of c yge 
pple
ul ol
. sC
el R
year
Relative Supply of College Skills and College Premium College wage premium  Rel. supply of college skills
39 49 59 69 79 89 96.3.4.5.6
0.2.4.6.8       Biased Technological Change Importance 
Skill-biased technological change  
Figure: 
Courtesy of Princeton U niversity Press . Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 4 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>55</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers Environment 
Equilibrium Relative Bias with Knowledge Spillovers I 
Proposition	 Consider the directed technological change model with 
knowledge spillovers and state dependence in the innovation 
possibilities frontier. Then there is always weak equilibrium 
(relative) bias in the sense that an increase in H/L always 
induces relatively H-biased technological change. 
Proposition	 Consider the directed technological change model with 
knowledge spillovers and state dependence in the innovation 
possibilities frontier. Then if 
 &gt; 2  , 
there is strong equilibrium (relative) bias in the sense that 
an increase in H/L raises the relative marginal product and 
the relative wage of the H factor compared to the L factor. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 56 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>48</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers Environment 
Directed Technological Change III  
State dependence adds another layer of increasing returns, this time 
not for the entire economy, but for specic technology lines. 
Free entry conditions: 
LNL (t)(1+)/2 NH (t)(1)/2 VL (t)  wS (t) (33) 
and LNL (t)(1+)/2 NH (t)(1)/2 VL (t)= wS (t) if SL (t) &gt; 0. 
and 
H NL (t)(1)/2 NH (t)(1+)/2 VH (t)  wS (t) (34) 
and H NL (t)(1)/2 NH (t)(1+)/2 VH (t)= wS (t) if SH (t) &gt; 0, 
where wS (t) denotes the wage of a scientist at time t. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 49 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Importance 
Importance of Biased Technological Change: more 
examples 
Balanced economic growth: 
Only possible when technological change is asymptotically 
Harrod-neutral, i.e., purely labor augmenting. 
Is there any reason to expect technological change to be endogenously 
labor augmenting? 
Globalization: 
Does it aect the types of technologies that are being developed and 
used? 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 7 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>82</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Environmental Disaster 
Cost of Intervention and Delay  
Concentrate on strong substitutability case ( &gt; 1/ (1  )) 
While Act catches up with Adt , growth is reduced. 
T : number of periods necessary for the economy under the policy 
intervention to reach the same level of output as it would have done 
within one period without intervention 
If intervention delayed, not only the environment gets further 
degraded, but also technology gap Adt1/Act1 increases, growth is 
reduced for a longer period. 
More generally, signicant welfare costs from delay (based on  
calibration).  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 83 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>59</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers Evidence 
Evidence: Changes in Spinning Patents  
Courtesy of W. Walker Hanlon. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 60 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>43</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Implications 
Implications IV  
If instead  &lt; 2, the long-run relative demand curve will be downward 
sloping, though again it will be shallower than the short-run relative 
demand curve. 
An increase in the relative supply of skills leads again to a decline in 
the college premium, and as technology starts adjusting the skill 
premium will increase. 
But it will end up below its initial level. To explain the larger increase 
in the college premium in the 1980s, in this case we would need some 
exogenous skill-biased technical change. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 44 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>53</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers Environment 
Transitional Dynamics with Knowledge Spillovers  
Transitional dynamics now more complicated because of the spillovers. 
The dynamic equilibrium path does not always tend to the BGP  
because of the additional increasing returns to scale:  
With a high degree of state dependence, when NH (0) is very high 
relative to NL (0), it may no longer be protable for rms to undertake 
further R&amp;D directed at labor-augmenting (L-augmenting) 
technologies. 
Whether this is so or not depends on a comparison of the degree of 
state dependence, , and the elasticity of substitution, . 
It can be shown that now stability requires  &lt; 1/. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 54 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Environment 
Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change V  
Normalize the price of the nal good at every instant to 1, which is 
equivalent to setting the ideal price index of the two intermediates 
equal to one, i.e., 
1 
1 1L  (pL (t)) + H  (pH (t))1 = 1 for all t, (10) 
where pL (t) is the price index of YL at time t and pH (t) is the price 
of YH . 
Denote factor prices by wL (t) and wH (t). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 22 / 89 
h i</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>60</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers Evidence 
Evidence: Changes in Input Prices  
Courtesy of W. Walker Hanlon. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 61 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Importance 
Skill-biased technological change  
Over the past 60 years, the U.S. relative supply of skills has increased, 
but: 
there has also been an increase in the college premium, and 
 1 
2 this increase accelerated in the late 1960s, and the skill premium 
increased very rapidly beginning in the late 1970s. 
Standard explanation: skill bias technical change, and an acceleration 
that coincided with the changes in the relative supply of skills. 
Important question: skill bias is endogenous, so, why has 
technological change become more skill biased in recent decades? 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 3 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>68</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Climate Change and Endogenous Technological Change 
Endogenous and Directed Technology  
Very dierent answers are possible. 
1 
2 
3 
4 Immediate and decisive intervention is necessary (in contrast to  
Nordhaus)  
Temporary intervention may be su cient (in contrast to Stern/Al Gore)  
Long-run growth costs may actually be very limited (in contrast to all  
of them).  
Two instruments not one necessary for optimal environmental  
regulation.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 69 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Basics and Denitions 
Factor-biased technological change 
Technological change change is L-biased, if: 
F (L,H ,A)/L F (L,H ,A)/H  0. 
Skillpremium
Relativesupply
ofskills
H/LSkill biasedtech.change
Relativedemand
forskills
Figure: The eect of H-biased technological change on relative demand and 
relative factor prices. 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 13 / 89 
A</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>62</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Labor-Augmenting Change 
Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change II  
Recall that when  &lt; 1 labor-augmenting technological change  
corresponds to capital-biased technological change.  
Hence the questions are: 
1 
2 Under what circumstances would the economy generate relatively  
capital-biased technological change?  
When will the equilibrium technology be su ciently capital biased that  
it corresponds to Harrod-neutral technological change?  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 63 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growt h Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 1 / 89  
14.452 Economic Growth: Lectures 12 and 13, Directed
Technological Change and Applications
Daron Acemoglu
MIT
December 8 and 13, 2016.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>70</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Climate Change and Endogenous Technological Change 
Why? (Continued) 
1 Immediate and decisive intervention is necessary (in contrast to  
Nordhaus)  
	 without intervention, innovation is directed towards dirty sectors; thus 
gap between clean and dirty technology widens; thus cost of 
intervention (reduced growth when clean technologies catch up with 
dirty ones) increases 
2 Temporary intervention may be su cient (in contrast to Stern/Al 
Gore), long-run growth costs limited (in contrast to all of them) 
 once government intervention has induced a technological lead in clean 
technologies, rms will spontaneously innovate in clean technologies (if 
clean and dirty inputs are su ciently substitutes). 
3	 Two instruments, not one:  
 optimal policy involves both a carbon tax and a subsidy to clean  
research to redirect innovation to green technologies  
	 too costly in terms of foregone short-run consumption to use carbon 
tax alone 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 71 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Transitional Dynamics 
Transitional Dynamics 
Dierently from the baseline endogenous technological change 
models, there are now transitional dynamics (because there are two 
state variables). 
Nevertheless, transitional dynamics simple and intuitive: 
Proposition	 Consider the directed technological change model described 
above. Starting with any NH (0) &gt; 0 and NL (0) &gt; 0, there 
exists a unique equilibrium path. If 
 NH (0) /NL (0) &lt; (NH /NL) as given by (27), then we have 
ZH (t) &gt; 0 and ZL (t)= 0 until 
NH (t) /NL (t)=(NH /NL) . If 
NH (0) /NL (0) &gt; (NH /NL) , then ZH (t)= 0 and 
ZL (t) &gt; 0 until NH (t) /NL (t)=(NH /NL ) . 
Summary: the dynamic equilibrium path always tends to the BGP and 
during transitional dynamics, there is only one type of innovation. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 35 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>64</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Labor-Augmenting Change 
Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change IV 
But the results are not easy to reconcile with purely-labor augmenting 
technological change. Suppose that capital accumulates at an 
exogenous rate, i.e., 
K (t) = sK &gt; 0.	 (40)K (t) 
Proposition	 Consider the baseline model of directed technological change 
with the knowledge spillovers specication and state 
dependence. Suppose that  &lt; 1 and capital accumulates 
according to (40). Then there exists no BGP. 
Intuitively, even though technological change is more labor 
augmenting than capital augmenting, there is still capital-augmenting 
technological change in equilibrium. 
Moreover it can be proved that in any asymptotic equilibrium, r (t) 
cannot be constant, thus consumption and output growth cannot be 
constant. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 65 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Importance 
Equilibrium Relative Bias in More Detail I  
Suppose the (inverse) relative demand curve: 
wH /wL = D (H/L, A) 
where wH /wL is the relative price of the factors and A is a technology 
term. 
A is H-biased if D is increasing in A, so that a higher A increases the 
relative demand for the H factor. 
D is always decreasing in H/L. 
Equilibrium bias: behavior of A as H/L changes, 
A (H/L) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 10 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Directed Technological Change and Factor Prices 
Discussion  
Analogous to Samuelson s LeChatelier principle : think of the 
endogenous-technology demand curve as adjusting the factors of 
production corresponding to technology. 
But, the eects here are caused by general equilibrium changes, not 
on partial equilibrium eects. 
Moreover ET2, which applies when  &gt; 2 holds, is upward-sloping. 
A complementary intuition: importance of non-rivalry of ideas: 
leads to an aggregate production function that exhibits increasing 
returns to scale (in all factors including technologies). 
the market size eect can create su ciently strong induced 
technological change to increase the relative marginal product and the 
relative price of the factor that has become more abundant. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 40 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>66</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Labor-Augmenting Change 
Stability  
The constant growth path allocation with purely labor augmenting 
technological change is globally stable if  &lt; 1. 
Intuition: 
If capital and labor were gross substitutes ( &gt; 1), the equilibrium 
would involve rapid accumulation of capital and capital-augmenting 
technological change, leading to an asymptotically increasing growth 
rate of consumption. 
When capital and labor are gross complements ( &lt; 1), capital 
accumulation would increase the price of labor and prots from 
labor-augmenting technologies and thus encourage further 
labor-augmenting technological change. 
 &lt; 1 forces the economy to strive towards a balanced allocation of 
eective capital and labor units. 
Since capital accumulates at a constant rate, a balanced allocation 
implies that the productivity of labor should increase faster, and the 
economy should converge to an equilibrium path with purely 
labor-augmenting technological progress. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 67 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Basics and Denitions 
Constant Elasticity of Substitution Production Function III  
Intuition for why, when  &lt; 1, H-augmenting technical change is 
L-biased: 
with gross complementarity ( &lt; 1), an increase in the productivity of 
H increases the demand for labor, L, by more than the demand for H, 
creating excess demand for labor. 
the marginal product of labor increases by more than the marginal 
product of H. 
Take case where   0 (Leontie): starting from a situation in which 
LAL (t) L (t)= H AH (t) H (t), a small increase in AH (t) will create 
an excess of the services of the H factor, and its price will fall to 0. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 16 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>Skillpremium
RelativeSupplyofSkillsCTconstant
technology
demandET1endogenous
technology
demandET2endogenous
technologydemand      Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Directed Technological Change and Factor Prices 
Relative Supply of Skills and Skill Premium  
Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 39 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>54</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers Environment 
Transitional Dynamics (Formally) 
Proposition Suppose that 
 &lt; 1/. 
Then, starting with any NH (0) &gt; 0 and NL (0) &gt; 0, there 
exists a unique equilibrium path. If 
 NH (0) /NL (0) &lt; (NH /NL) as given by (36), then we have 
ZH (t) &gt; 0 and ZL (t)= 0 until 
  NH (t) /NL (t)=(NH /NL) . NH (0) /NL (0) &lt; (NH /NL ) , 
then ZH (t)= 0 and ZL (t) &gt; 0 until 
 NH (t) /NL (t)=(NH /NL) . 
If 
 &gt; 1/, 
then starting with NH (0) /NL (0) &gt; (NH /NL )  , the 
economy tends to NH (t) /NL (t)   as t  , and 
starting with NH (0) /NL (0) &lt; (NH /NL)  , it tends to 
NH (t) /NL (t)  0 as t  . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 55 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Importance 
Equilibrium Relative Bias in More Detail II  
Weak equilibrium bias: 
A (H/L) is increasing (nondecreasing) in H/L. 
Strong equilibrium bias: 
A (H/L) is su ciently responsive to an increase in H/L that the total 
eect of the change in relative supply H/L is to increase wH /wL. 
i.e., let the endogenous-technology relative demand curve be 
wH /wL = D (H/L, A (H/L))  D(H/L) 
Strong equilibrium bias: Dincreasing in H/L. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 11 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Importance 
Unskill-biased technological change  
Late 18th and early 19th unskill-bias:  
First in rearms, then in clocks, pumps, locks, mechanical reapers,  
typewriters, sewing machines, and eventually in engines and bicycles,  
interchangeable parts technology proved superior and replaced the  
skilled artisans working with chisel and le. (Mokyr 1990, p. 137)  
Why was technological change unskilled-biased then and  
skilled-biased now?  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 5 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Characterization of Equilibrium 
Equilibrium II 
Maximization problem of producers in the two sectors: 
max pL (t) YL (t)  wL (t) L (11)
L,[xL (,t)][0,NL (t)] 
NL (t) x pL (, t) xL (, t) d, 
0 
and 
max pH (t) YH (t)  wH (t) H (12)
H ,[xH (,t)][0,NH (t)] 
NH (t) x pH (, t) xH (, t) d. 
0 
Note the presence of pL (t) and pH (t), since these sectors produce 
intermediate goods. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 24 / 89 
Z
Z</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>52</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers Environment 
Balanced Growth Path with Knowledge Spillovers  
Proposition	 Consider the directed technological change model with 
knowledge spillovers and state dependence in the innovation 
possibilities frontier. Suppose that 
(1)/2L H (NH /NL )(1  )	 S &lt; ,(1)H (NH /NL ) + L 
where NH /NL is given by (36). Then there exists a unique 
BGP equilibrium in which the relative technologies are given 
by (36), and consumption and output grow at the rate 
(1)/2LH (NH /NL ) g =	 S. (39)(1)H (NH /NL) + L 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 53 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Importance 
Directed Technological Change: Basic Arguments I  
Two factors of production, say L and H (unskilled and skilled  
workers).  
Two types of technologies that can complement either one or the 
other factor. 
Whenever the protability of H-augmenting technologies is greater 
than the L-augmenting technologies, more of the former type will be 
developed by prot-maximizing (research) rms. 
What determines the relative protability of developing dierent 
technologies? It is more protable to develop technologies... 
when the goods produced by these technologies command higher prices 
 1 
2 (price eect );  
that have a larger market (market size eect).  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 8 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Basics and Denitions 
Constant Elasticity of Substitution Production Function II 
Relative marginal product of the two factors: 
  1    1 
  MPH AH (t) H (t) =  , (1)MPL AL (t) L (t) 
where   H /L.  
substitution eect: the relative marginal product of H is decreasing in 
its relative abundance, H (t) /L (t). 
The eect of AH (t) on the relative marginal product: 
If  &gt; 1, an increase in AH (t) (relative to AL (t)) increases the 
relative marginal product of H. 
If  &lt; 1, an increase in AH (t) reduces the relative marginal product of 
H. 
If  = 1, Cobb-Douglas case, and neither a change in AH (t) nor in 
AL (t) is biased towards any of the factors. 
Note also that  is the elasticity of substitution between the two 
factors. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 15 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Biased Technological Change Importance 
Equilibrium Relative Bias  
Potentially counteracting eects, but the market size eect will be 
more powerful often. 
Under fairly general conditions: 
Weak Equilibrium (Relative) Bias: an increase in the relative supply of 
a factor always induces technological change that is biased in favor of 
this factor. 
Strong Equilibrium (Relative) Bias: if the elasticity of substitution 
between factors is su ciently large, an increase in the relative supply of 
a factor induces su ciently strong technological change biased towards 
itself that the endogenous-technology relative demand curve of the 
economy becomes upward-sloping. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 9 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Implications 
Implications I  
Recall we have the following stylized facts: 
Secular skill-biased technological change increasing the demand for 
skills throughout the 20th century. 
Possible acceleration in skill-biased technological change over the past 
25 years. 
A range of important technologies biased against skill workers during 
the 19th century. 
The current model gives us a way to think about these issues. 
The increase in the number of skilled workers should cause steady 
skill-biased technical change. 
Acceleration in the increase in the number of skilled workers should 
induce an acceleration in skill-biased technological change. 
Available evidence suggests that there were large increases in the 
number of unskilled workers during the late 18th and 19th centuries. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 41 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>58</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers Evidence 
Evidence: Changes in Quantities  
Courtesy of W. Walker Hanlon. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 59 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Characterization of Equilibrium 
Equilibrium IV  
Substituting into (13) and (14): 
1/ L xL (, t)= pL (t) for all  and all t,  
and  
1/ H xH (, t)= pH (t) for all  and all t. 
Since these quantities do not depend on the identity of the machine 
prots are also independent of the machine type: 
L (t)= pL (t)1/ L and H (t)= pH (t)1/ H. (15) 
Thus the values of monopolists only depend on which sector they are, 
VL (t) and VH (t). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 26 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Characterization of Equilibrium 
Equilibrium V  
Combining these with (5) and (6), derived production functions for 
the two intermediate goods: 
1   YL (t) = 1 
1   pL (t) NL (t) L 1 
 (16) 
and 
YH (t) = 1 pH (t) NH (t) H. 1 
 (17) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 27 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>84</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Optimal Environmental Regulation 
Optimal Environmental Regulation  
Proposition 
Optimal environmental regulation. 
A planner can implement the social optimum through a "carbon tax" on 
the use of the dirty input, a clean research subsidy and a subsidy for the 
use of all machines (all taxes/subsidies are nanced by lumpsum taxes). 
1 If  &gt; 1 and the discount rate  is su ciently small, then in nite 
time innovation ends up occurring only in the clean sector, the 
economy grows at rate and the optimal subsidy to clean research, c 
qt, is temporary. 
2 The optimal carbon tax, t, is temporary if  &gt; 1/ (1  ) but not if 
1 &lt;  &lt; 1/ (1  ). 
Interpretation: two instruments for two margins carbon tax for the 
intra-temporal one and research subsidies for the intertemporal one. 
But importantly, both are temporary. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 85 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>46</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers Environment 
Directed Technological Change with Knowledge Spillovers 
The lab equipment specication of the innovation possibilities does 
not allow for state dependence. 
Assume that R&amp;D is carried out by scientists and that there is a 
constant supply of scientists equal to S 
With only one sector, sustained endogenous growth requires N/N to 
be proportional to S. 
With two sectors, there is a variety of specications with dierent 
degrees of state dependence, because productivity in each sector can 
depend on the state of knowledge in both sectors. 
A exible formulation is 
NL (t)= LNL (t)(1+)/2 NH (t)(1)/2 SL (t) (31) 
and NH (t)= H NL (t)(1)/2 NH (t)(1+)/2 SH (t) , 
where   1.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 47 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Directed Technological Change Introduction 
Introduction  
Thus far have focused on a single type of technological change (e.g., 
Hicks-neutral). 
But, technological change is often not neutral:  
Benets some factors of production and some agents more than others.  
Distributional eects imply some groups will embrace new technologies  
and others oppose them.  
1 
2 Limiting to only one type of technological change obscures the 
competing eects that determine the nature of technological change. 
Directed technological change: endogenize the direction and bias of 
new technologies that are developed and adopted. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 2 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>80</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Environmental Disaster 
Sketch of Proof  
Look at eect of a temporary clean research subsidy 
Key role: redirecting technological change ; innovation can be 
redirected towards clean technology 
If  &gt; 1, then subsequent to an extended period of taxation, 
innovation will remain in clean technology 
Is this su cient to prevent an environmental disaster? 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 81 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Directed Technological Change and Factor Prices 
Weak Equilibrium (Relative) Bias Result  
Proposition	 Consider the directed technological change model described 
above. There is always weak equilibrium (relative) bias in 
the sense that an increase in H/L always induces relatively 
H-biased technological change. 
The results reect the strength of the market size eect: it always 
dominates the price eect. 
But it does not specify whether this induced eect will be strong 
enough to make the endogenous-technology relative demand curve for 
factors upward-sloping. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 37 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>45</slideno>
          <text>Baseline Model of Directed Technical Change Implications 
Implications VI  
Other remarks: 
Upward-sloping relative demand curves arise only when  &gt; 2. Most 
estimates put the elasticity of substitution between 1.4 and 2. One 
would like to understand whether  &gt; 2 is a feature of the specic 
model discussed here 
Results on induced technological change are not an artifact of the scale 
eect (exactly the same results apply when scale eects are removed, 
see below). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 46 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>85</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Optimal Environmental Regulation 
Carbon Tax 
Optimal carbon tax schedule is given by 
t+1 t = ,tpdt 
t is the marginal utility of a unit of consumption at time t 
t+1 is the shadow value of one unit of environmental quality at time 
t + 1, equal to the discounted marginal utility of environmental quality 
as of period t + 1. 
Why temporary? If  &gt; 1/ (1  ), dirty input production tends 
towards 0 and environmental quality St reaches S in nite time and 
thus t  0, carbon tax becomes null in nite time. 
Why two instruments? If gap between the two technologies is high, 
relying on carbon tax to redirect technical change would reduce too 
much consumption. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 86 / 89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>67</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Labor-Augmenting Technological Change Climate Change and Endogenous Technological Change 
Economic Analysis of Climate Change  
Existing economic analyses using computable general equilibrium 
models with exogenous technology (and climatological constraints; 
e.g., Nordhaus, 1994, 2002). 
Key issues: (1) economic costs and benets of environmental policy; 
(2) costs of delaying intervention (3) role of discounting and risk  
aversion.  
Various conclusions: 
1 
2 
3 Nordhaus approach: intervention should be limited and gradual; small  
long-run growth costs.  
Stern/Al Gore approach: intervention needs to be large, immediate  
and maintained permanently; large long-run growth costs.  
Greenpeace approach: only way to avoid disaster is zero growth.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 12 and 13 December 8 and 13, 2016. 68 / 89</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Neoclassical Endogenous Growth (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-452-economic-growth-fall-2016/resources/mit14_452f16_lec8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>The Two-Sector AK Model The Rebelo Model
The Two-Sector AK Model V
Euler equation (4) still holds, but interest rate has to be for
consumption-denominated loans ,rC(t).
I.e., the interest rate that measures how many units of consumption
good an individual will receive tomorrow by giving up one unit of
consumption today.
Relative price of consumption goods and investment goods is
changing over time, thus:
By giving up one dollar, the individual will buy 1 /pI(t)units of capital
goods.
This will have an instantaneous return of rI(t).
Individual will get back the one unit of capital, which has experienced a
change in its price of pI(t)/pI(t).
Finally, he will have to buy consumption goods, whose prices changed
bypC(t)/pC(t).
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 22 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 1 / 42
14.452 Economic Growth: Lecture 8, Neoclassical
Endogenous Growth
Daron Acemoglu
MIT
November 22, 2016.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>The Role of Policy
The Role of Policy III
Why then focus on standard neoclassical if AKmodel can generate
arbitrarily large dierences?
1AKmodel, with no diminishing returns and the share of capital in
national income asymptoting to 1, is not a good approximation to
reality.
2Relative stability of the world income distribution in the post-war era
makes it more attractive to focus on models in which there is a
stationary world income distribution.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 17 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
14.452 Economic Growth
 Fall 2016
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Growth with Externalities The Romer Model
Preferences and Technology II
Normalize the measure of nal good producers to 1, so market
clearing conditions:Z1
Ki(t)di=K(t)
0
andZ1
Li(t)di=L,
0
Lis the constant level of labor (supplied inelastically) in this economy.
Firms are competitive in all markets, thus all hire the same capital to
eective labor ratio, and
F(K(t),A(t)L)w(t)=L
F(K(t),A(t)L)R(t)= .K(t)
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 30 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>The Role of Policy
The Role of Policy II
In contrast to Solow, constants saving rate responds endogenously to
policy.
Since saving rate is constant, dierences in policies will lead to
permanent dierences in the rate of capital accumulation.
In the baseline neoclassical growth model even large dierences in
distortions could only have limited eects on dierences in income per
capita.
Here even small dierences in tcan have very large eects.
Consider two economies, with tax rates on capital income tand
t0&gt;t, and exactly the same otherwise.
For any t0&gt;t,
Y(t0,t)lim
t!Y(t,t)=0,
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 16 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>Growth with Externalities The Romer Model
Growth with Externalities I
Romer (1986): model the process of knowledge accumulation .
Di cult in the context of a competitive economy.
Solution: knowledge accumulation as a byproduct of capital
accumulation.
Technological spillovers: arguably crude, but captures that knowledge
is a largely non-rival good.
Non-rivalry does not imply knowledge is also non-excludable.
But some of the important characteristics of knowledge and its role
in the production process can be captured in a reduced-form way by
introducing technological spillovers.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 28 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Growth with Externalities The Romer Model
Preferences and Technology I
No population growth (we will see why this is important).
Production function with labor-augmenting knowledge (technology)
that satises Assumptions 1 and 2.
Instead of working with the aggregate production function, assume
that the production side of the economy consists of a set [0,1]of
rms.
The production function facing each rm i2[0,1]is
Yi(t)=F(Ki(t),A(t)Li(t)), (29)
Ki(t)andLi(t)are capital and labor rented by a rm i.
A(t)is not indexed by i, since it is technology common to all rms.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 29 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Equilibrium Characterization
Equilibrium Characterization VI
Since all markets are competitive, there is a representative household,
and there are no externalities, the competitive equilibrium will be
Pareto optimal.
Can be proved either using First Welfare Theorem type reasoning, or
by directly constructing the optimal growth solution.
Proposition Consider the above-described AKeconomy, with a
representative household with preferences given by (1), and
the production technology given by (6). Suppose that
condition (12) holds. Then, the unique competitive
equilibrium is Pareto optimal.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 14 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Growth with Externalities The Romer Model
Preferences and Technology III
Key assumption: rms take A(t)as given, but this stock of
technology (knowledge) advances endogenously for the economy as a
whole.
Lucas (1988) develops a similar model, but spillovers work through
human capital.
Extreme assumption of su ciently strong externalities such that A(t)
can grow continuously at the economy level. In particular,
A(t)=BK(t), (30)
Motivated by learning-by-doing. Alternatively, could be a function
of the cumulative output that the economy has produced up to now.
Substituting for (30) into (29) and using the fact that all rms are
functioning at the same capital-eective labor ratio, production
function of the representative rm:
Y(t)=F(K(t),BK(t)L).
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 31 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>Conclusions Conclusions
Conclusions I
Linearity of the models (most clearly visible in the AKmodel):
Removes transitional dynamics and leads to a more tractable
mathematical structure.
Essential feature of any model that will exhibit sustained economic
growth.
With strong concavity, especially consistent with the Inada, sustained
growth will not be possible.
But most models studied in this chapter do not feature technological
progress:
Debate about whether the observed total factor productivity growth is
partly a result of mismeasurement of inputs.
Could be that much of what we measure as technological progress is in
fact capital deepening, as in AKmodel and its variants.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 40 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>The Two-Sector AK Model The Rebelo Model
The Two-Sector AK Model I
Model before creates another factor of production that accumulates
linearly, so equilibrium is again equivalent to the one-sector AK
economy.
Thus, in some deep sense, the economies of both sections are
one-sector models.
Also, potentially blur key underlying characteristic driving growth.
What is important is not that production technology is AK, but that
theaccumulation technology is linear.
Preference and demographics are the same as in the model of the
previous section, (1)-(5) apply as before
No population growth, i.e., n=0, and Lis supplied inelastically.
Rather than a single good used for consumption and investment, now
two sectors.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 18 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>First-Generation Models of Endogenous Growth
Models so far: no sustained long-run growth; relatively little to say
about sources of technology dierences.
Models in which technology evolves as a result of rmsand workers
decisions are most attractive in this regard.
But sustained economic growth is possible in the neoclassical model
as well:
AKmodel before: relaxed Assumption 2 and prevented diminishing
returns to capital.
Capital accumulation could act as the engine of sustained economic
growth.
Neoclassical version of the AKmodel:
Very tractable and applications in many areas.
Shortcoming: capital is essentially the only factor of production,
asymptotically share of income accruing to it tends to 1.
Two-sector endogenous growth models behave very similarly to the
baseline AKmodel, but avoid this.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 2 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>The Two-Sector AK Model The Rebelo Model
The Two-Sector AK Model X
Dierent from the neoclassical growth model, there is continuous
capital deepening.
Capital grows at a faster rate than consumption and output. Whether
this is a realistic feature is debatable:
Kaldor facts include constant capital-output ratio as one of the
requirements of balanced growth.
For much of the 20th century, capital-output ratio has been constant,
but it has been increasing steadily over the past 30 years.
Part of the increase is because of relative price adjustments that have
only been performed in the recent past.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 27 / 42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>Conclusions Conclusions
Conclusions II
Important tension:
neoclassical growth model (or Solow growth model) have di culty in
generating very large income dierences
models here suer from the opposite problem.
Both a blessing and a curse: also predict an ever expanding world
distribution.
Issues to understand:
1Era of divergence is not the past 60 years, but the 19th century:
important to confront these models with historical data.
2Each country as an island approach is unlikely to be a good
approximation, much less so when we endogenize technology.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 8 November 22, 2016. 41 / 42</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Solow Model (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-452-economic-growth-fall-2016/resources/mit14_452f16_lec2and3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2&#8211;3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>54</slideno>
          <text>Transitional Dynamics in the Continuous Time Solow Model Dynamics in Continues Time
Simple Result in Figure
k(t)
f(k(t))k(t)
k(t)s (+g+n )k*0 k(t)
Figure: Dynamics of the capital-labor ratio in the basic Solow model.Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         55 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>80</slideno>
          <text>Solow Model with Technological Progress Solow Growth Model with Technological Progress
The Solow Growth Model with Technological Progress:
Continuous Time VI
Equation (37), emphasizes that now total savings, sf(k), are used for
replenishing the capital stock for three distinct reasons:
1depreciation at the rate d.
2population growth at the rate n, which reduces capital per worker.
3Harrod-neutral technological progress at the rate g.
Now replenishment of eective capital-labor ratio requires
investments to be equal to (d+g+n)k.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         81 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>60</slideno>
          <text>A First Look at Sustained Growth Sustained Growth
A First Look at Sustained Growth IV
Unattractive features:
1Knife-edge case, requires the production function to be ultimately
linear in the capital stock.
2Implies that as time goes by the share of national income accruing to
capital will increase towards 1.
3Technological progress seems to be a major (perhaps the most major)
factor in understanding the process of economic growth.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         61 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>62</slideno>
          <text>Solow Model with Technological Progress Balanced Growth
Balanced Growth II
Note capital share in national income is about 1/3, while the labor
share is about 2/3.
Ignoring land, not a major factor of production.
But in poor countries land is a major factor of production.
This pattern often makes economists choose AK1/3L2/3.
Main advantage from our point of view is that balanced growth is the
same as a steady-state in transformed variables
i.e., we will again have k=0, but the denition of kwill change.
But important to bear in mind that growth has many non-balanced
features.
e.g., the share of dierent sectors changes systematically.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         63 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>The Solow Model in Discrete Time Equilibrium
Non-Existence and Non-Uniqueness
(t+1)
k( t)45
sf(k(t))+(1 )k(t)
0k(t+1)
k( t)45sf(k(t))+(1 )k(t)
0k(t+1)
k( t)45
sf(k(t))+(1 )k(t)
0
Panel A PanelB PanelCk
Figure: Examples of nonexistence and nonuniqueness of interior steady states
when Assumptions 1 and 2 are not satised.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3Courtesy of Princeton University Press .   Used with permission.
November 1 and 3.         31 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
14.452 Economic Growth: Lectures 2 and 3
The Solow Growth Model
Daron Acemoglu
MIT
November 1 and 3.
November 1 and 3.         1 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>65</slideno>
          <text>Solow Model with Technological Progress Balanced Growth
Types of Neutral Technological Progress II
Could also have a vector valued index of technology
A(t)=(AH(t),AK(t),AL(t))and a production function
F[K(t),L(t),A(t)]=AH(t)F[AK(t)K(t),AL(t)L(t)],
Nests the constant elasticity of substitution production function
introduced in the Example above.
But even this is a restriction on the form of technological progress,
A(t)could modify the entire production function.
Balanced growth necessitates that all technological progress be labor
augmenting or Harrod-neutral.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         66 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>63</slideno>
          <text>Solow Model with Technological Progress Balanced Growth
Types of Neutral Technological Progress I
For some constant returns to scale function F:
Hicks-neutral technological progress :
F[K(t),L(t),A(t)]=A(t)F[K(t),L(t)],
Relabeling of the isoquants (without any change in their shape) of the
function F[K(t),L(t),A(t)]in the L-Kspace.
Solow-neutral technological progress,
F[K(t),L(t),A(t)]=F[A(t)K(t),L(t)].
Capital-augmenting progress: isoquants shifting with technological
progress in a way that they have constant slope at a given labor-output
ratio.
Harrod-neutral technological progress,
F[K(t),L(t),A(t)]=F[K(t),A(t)L(t)].
Increases output as if the economy had more labor: slope of the
isoquants are constant along rays with constant capital-output ratio.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         64 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>68</slideno>
          <text>Solow Model with Technological Progress Uzawa s Theorem
Implications of Uzawa s Theorem
Corollary Under the assumptions of Uzawa Theorem, after time t
technological progress can be represented as Harrod neutral
(purely labor augmenting).
Remarkable feature: stated and proved without any reference to
equilibrium behavior or market clearing.
Also, contrary to Uzawa s original theorem, not stated for a balanced
growth path but only for an asymptotic path with constant rates of
output, capital and consumption growth.
But, not as general as it seems;
the theorem gives only one representation.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         69 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>The Solow Model in Discrete Time Equilibrium
Equilibrium Without Population Growth and Technological
Progress IV
Alternative visual representation of the steady state: intersection
between dkand the function sf(k). Useful because:
1Depicts the levels of consumption and investment in a single gure.
2Emphasizes the steady-state equilibrium sets investment, sf(k), equal
to the amount of capital that needs to be replenished , dk.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         27 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>64</slideno>
          <text>Solow Model with Technological Progress Balanced Growth
Isoquants with Neutral Technological Progress
K
0 LYYK
0 LYY
0 LYYK
Figure: Hicks-neutral, Solow-neutral and Harrod-neutral shifts in isoquants.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         65 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Solow Growth Model Firm Optimization
Firm Optimization II
Since Fis dierentiable, rst-order necessary conditions imply:
w(t)=FL[K(t),L(t),A(t)], (2)
and
R(t)=FK[K(t),L(t),A(t)]. (3)
Note also that in (2) and (3), we used K(t)andL(t), the amount of
capital and labor used by rms.
In fact, solving for K(t)andL(t), we can derive the capital and labor
demands of rms in this economy at rental prices R(t)andw(t).
Thus we could have used Kd(t)instead of K(t), but this additional
notation is not necessary.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         11 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>85</slideno>
          <text>Conclusions
Conclusions
Simple and tractable framework, which allows us to discuss capital
accumulation and the implications of technological progress.
Solow model shows us that if there is no technological progress, and
as long as we are not in the AKworld, there will be no sustained
growth.
Generate per capita output growth, but only exogenously:
technological progress is a blackbox.
Capital accumulation: determined by the saving rate, the depreciation
rate and the rate of population growth. All are exogenous.
Need to dig deeper and understand what lies in these black boxes.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         86 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>The Solow Model in Discrete Time Equilibrium
Consumption and Investment in Steady State
output
k(t)f(k *)k(t)
f(k(t))
sf(k*)sf(k(t))consumption
investment
k* 0
Figure: Investment and consumption in the steady-state equilibrium.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3Courtesy of Princeton University Press .   Used with permission .
November 1 and 3.         28 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>86</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
14.452 Economic Growth
 Fall 2016
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Solow Growth Model Solow Growth Model
Solow Growth Model
Develop a simple framework for the proximate causes and the
mechanics of economic growth and cross-country income dierences.
Solow-Swan model named after Robert (Bob) Solow and Trevor
Swan, or simply the Solow model
Before Solow growth model, the most common approach to economic
growth built on the Harrod-Domar model.
Harrod-Domar mdel emphasized potential dysfunctional aspects of
growth: e.g, how growth could go hand-in-hand with increasing
unemployment.
Solow model demonstrated why the Harrod-Domar model was not an
attractive place to start.
At the center of the Solow growth model is the neoclassical aggregate
production function.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         2 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>71</slideno>
          <text>Solow Model with Technological Progress Uzawa s Theorem
Intuition for the Uzawa s Theorems
We assumed the economy features capital accumulation in the sense
thatgK&gt;0.
From the aggregate resource constraint, this is only possible if output
and capital grow at the same rate.
Either this growth rate is equal to nand there is no technological
change (i.e., proposition applies with g=0), or the economy exhibits
growth of per capita income and capital-labor ratio.
The latter case creates an asymmetry between capital and labor:
capital is accumulating faster than labor.
Constancy of growth requires technological change to make up for
this asymmetry
But this intuition does not provide a reason for why technology
should take labor-augmenting (Harrod-neutral) form.
But if technology did not take this form, an asymptotic path with
constant growth rates would not be possible.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         72 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Solow Growth Model Market Structure, Endowments and Market Clearing
Market Structure, Endowments and Market Clearing II
But Assumption 1 and competitive labor markets make sure that
wages have to be strictly positive.
Households also own the capital stock of the economy and rent it to
rms.
Denote the rental price of capital at time tbeR(t).
Capital market clearing condition:
Ks(t)=Kd(t)
Take householdsinitial holdings of capital, K(0), as given
P(t)is the price of the nal good at time t, normalize the price of
the nal good to 1 in all periods .
Build on an insight by Kenneth Arrow (Arrow, 1964) that it is
su cient to price securities (assets) that transfer one unit of
consumption from one date (or state of the world) to another.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         8 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>The Solow Model in Discrete Time Equilibrium
The Golden Rule
consumption
savingsrate(1s)f(k*gold)
s*gold 1 0
Figure: The golden rule level of savings rate, which maximizes steady-state
consumption.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission.
November 1 and 3.         34 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>51</slideno>
          <text>The Solow Model in Continuous Time Steady State in Continuous Time
Steady State With Population Growth
output
k(t)f(k*)
k*f(k(t))
sf(k*)sf(k(t))consumption
investment
0(+n)k(t )
Figure: Investment and consumption in the steady-state equilibrium with
population growth.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         52 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>72</slideno>
          <text>Solow Model with Technological Progress Uzawa s Theorem
Interpretation
Distressing result:
Balanced growth is only possible under a very stringent assumption.
Provides no reason why technological change should take this form.
But when technology is endogenous, intuition above also works to
make technology endogenously more labor-augmenting than capital
augmenting.
Not only requires labor augmenting asymptotically, i.e., along the
balanced growth path.
This is the pattern that certain classes of endogenous-technology
models will generate.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         73 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Solow Growth Model Households and Production
Households and Production II
Assume households save a constant exogenous fraction sof their
disposable income
Same assumption used in basic Keynesian models and in the
Harrod-Domar model; at odds with reality.
Assume all rms have access to the same production function:
economy admits a representative rm, with a representative (or
aggregate) production function.
Aggregate production function for the unique nal good is
Y(t)=F[K(t),L(t),A(t)] (1)
Assume capital is the same as the nal good of the economy, but
used in the production process of more goods.
A(t)is ashifter of the production function (1). Broad notion of
technology.
Major assumption: technology is free; it is publicly available as a
non-excludable, non-rival good.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         4 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>83</slideno>
          <text>Comparative Dynamics Comparative Dynamics
Comparative Dynamics in Figure
0k(t)
f(k(t))k(t)
k(t)sk*k(t)
k**
f(k(t))
k(t)s (+g+n )
(+g+n )
Figure: Dynamics following an increase in the savings rate from stos0. The solid
arrows show the dynamics for the initial steady state, while the dashed arrows
show the dynamics for the new steady state.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         84 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Transitional Dynamics in the Discrete Time Solow Model Transitional Dynamics
Transitional Dynamics
Equilibrium path: not simply steady state, but entire path of capital
stock, output, consumption and factor prices.
In engineering and physical sciences, equilibrium is point of rest of
dynamical system, thus the steady state equilibrium .
In economics, non-steady-state behavior also governed by optimizing
behavior of households and rms and market clearing.
Need to study the transitional dynamics of the equilibrium
dierence equation (12) starting from an arbitrary initial capital-labor
ratio k(0)&gt;0.
Key question: whether economy will tend to steady state and how it
will behave along the transition path.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         37 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>45</slideno>
          <text>Transitional Dynamics in the Discrete Time Solow Model Transitional Dynamics
Transitional Dynamics in Figure
Figure: Transitional dynamics  in the basic Solow model.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         46 / 87Courtesy of Princeton University Press.  Used with permission</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Solow Growth Model Firm Optimization
Firm Optimization III
Proposition Suppose Assumption 1 holds. Then in the equilibrium of the
Solow growth model, rms make no prots, and in particular,
Y(t)=w(t)L(t)+R(t)K(t).
Proof: Follows immediately from Euler Theorem for the case of
m=1, i.e., constant returns to scale.
Thus rms make no prots, so ownership of rms does not need to be
specied.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         12 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>61</slideno>
          <text>Solow Model with Technological Progress Balanced Growth
Balanced Growth I
Production function F[K(t),L(t),A(t)]is too general.
May not have balanced growth, i.e. a path of the economy consistent
with the Kaldor facts (Kaldor, 1963).
Kaldor facts:
while output per capita increases, the capital-output ratio, the interest
rate, and the distribution of income between capital and labor remain
roughly constant.
We know that the capital share of national income is not really
constant, and has been increasing over the last 30 years or so.
Nevertheless, its relative constancy for almost a century might be
an argument for sticking to Kaldor facts.
More importantly, balanced growth is a very simple starting point.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         62 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>74</slideno>
          <text>Solow Model with Technological Progress Uzawa s Theorem
Further Intuition
Suppose the production function takes the special form
F[AK(t)K(t),AL(t)L(t)].
The stronger theorem implies that factor shares will be constant.
Given constant returns to scale, this can only be the case when
AK(t)K(t)andAL(t)L(t)grow at the same rate.
The fact that the capital-output ratio is constant in steady state (or
the fact that capital accumulates) implies that K(t)must grow at
the same rate as AL(t)L(t).
Thus balanced growth can only be possible if AK(t)is asymptotically
constant.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         75 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Solow Growth Model Households and Production
Households and Production I
Closed economy, with a unique nal good.
Discrete time running to an innite horizon, time is indexed by
t=0,1,2, ....
Economy is inhabited by a large number of households, and for
now
households will not be optimizing.
This is the main dierence between the Solow model and the
neoclassical growth model.
To x ideas, assume all households are identical, so the economy
admits a representative household .
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         3 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>The Solow Model in Discrete Time Denition of Equilibrium
Denition of Equilibrium I
Solow model is a mixture of an old-style Keynesian model and a
modern dynamic macroeconomic model.
Households do not optimize, but rms still maximize and factor
markets clear.
Denition In the basic Solow model for a given sequence of
fL(t),A(t)gt=0and an initial capital stock K(0), an
equilibrium path is a sequence of capital stocks, output
levels, consumption levels, wages and rental rates
fK(t),Y(t),C(t),w(t),R(t)gt=0such that K(t)
satises (8), Y(t)is given by (1), C(t)is given by (7), and
w(t)andR(t)are given by (2) and (3).
Note an equilibrium is dened as an entire path of allocations and
prices: nota static object.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         18 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>56</slideno>
          <text>A First Look at Sustained Growth Sustained Growth
A First Look at Sustained Growth I
Cobb-Douglas already showed that when ais close to 1, adjustment
to steady-state level can be very slow.
Simplest model of sustained growth essentially takes a=1 in terms
of the Cobb-Douglas production function above.
Relax Assumptions 1 and 2 and suppose
F[K(t),L(t),A(t)]=AK(t), (28)
where A&gt;0 is a constant.
So-called AK model, and in its simplest form output does not even
depend on labor.
Results we would like to highlight apply with more general constant
returns to scale production functions,
F[K(t),L(t),A(t)]=AK(t)+BL(t), (29)
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3
November 1 and 3.         57 / 87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>The Solow Model in Discrete Time Equilibrium
Equilibrium Without Population Growth and Technological
Progress III
k(t+1)
k(t)45
k*
sf(k(t))+(1 )k(t)
k* 0
Figure: Unique steady state in the basic Solow model when f(0)=#&gt;0.Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 2-3Courtesy of Princeton University Press .   Used with permission .
November 1 and 3.         26 / 87</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Endogenous Technological Growth (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-452-economic-growth-fall-2016/resources/mit14_452f16_lec9and10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9&#8211;10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Policy in Models of Endogenous Technological Progress 
Growth with Knowledge Spillovers I  
In the lab equipment model, growth resulted from the use of nal 
output for R&amp;D. This is similar to the endogenous growth model of 
Rebelo (1991), since the accumulation equation is linear in 
accumulable factors. In equilibrium, output took a linear form in the 
stock of knowledge (new machines), thus a AN form instead of 
Rebelo s AK form. 
An alternative is to have scarce factors used in R&amp;D: we have  
scientists as the key creators of R&amp;D.  
With this alternative, there cannot be endogenous growth unless there 
are knowledge spillovers from past R&amp;D, making the scarce factors 
used in R&amp;D more and more productive over time. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 36 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>67</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Technological Spillovers and Diusion 
Diusion  
The basic facts about technology diusion are well established. 
The classic paper by Griliches on the hybrid corn still tells the basic 
picture: there is slow diusion of new technologies and the speed of 
diusion depends on various factors, most notably on market 
conditions, human capital and various measures of distance or 
similarity between innovators/early adopters and late adopters. 
Most likely because of information diusion across networks of 
agents. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 68 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>47</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Growth without Scale Eects 
Discussion I  
Growth without scale eects ? 
There are two senses in which there are still scale eects:  
A faster rate of population growth translates into a higher equilibrium  
 1 
2 growth rate.  
A larger population size leads to higher output per capita.  
Empirical evidence?  
Semi-endogenous growth models, because growth is determined 
only by population growth and technology, and does not respond to 
policies. 
Extensions to allow for the impact of policy and growth possible 
(though under somewhat restrictive assumptions). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 48 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Prot Maximization by Technology Monopolists II  
For future reference, the discounted value of prots can also be  
written in the alternative Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman form:  
r (t) V (, t)  V(, t) = (, t). (8) 
This equation shows that the discounted value of prots may change 
because of two reasons: 
1 
2 Prots change over time 
The market interest rate changes over time. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 12 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>68</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Technological Spillovers and Diusion 
Diusion (continued)  
 The Econometric Society. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 69 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>51</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Innovation Possibilities Frontier I  
Cumulative R&amp;D process. 
Z (, t) units of the nal good for research on machine line , quality 
q (, t) generate a ow rate 
Z (, t) /q (, t) 
of innovation. 
Note one unit of R&amp;D spending is proportionately less eective when 
applied to a more advanced machine. 
Free entry into research. 
The rm that makes an innovation has a perpetual patent. 
But other rms can undertake research based on the product invented 
by this rm. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 52 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
The Lab Equipment Model with Input Varieties  
All that is required for research is investment in equipment or in  
laboratories  
That is, new machines and ideas are created using the nal good. 
rather than the employment of skilled or unskilled workers or scientists. 
similar to Rebelo s AK economy. 
useful benchmark, since it minimizes the extent of spillovers and 
externalities. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 4 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>45</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Growth without Scale Eects 
Growth without Scale Eects II 
Dierentiating this condition with respect to time, we obtain 
N(t)LE (t)(  1) + = 0.N (t) LE (t) 
Since in BGP, the fraction of workers allocated to research is 
constant, we must have 
LE (t) /LE (t)= n 
Thus, 
N(t) n gN  = . (35)N (t) 1  
  g = g (36)C N
n = .1  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 46 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Pareto Optimal Allocations 
Social Planner Problem III  
The net output level (after investment costs are subtracted) is 
(1)/(1  )YS (t)= NS (t) L1   
=(1  )1/ NS (t) L, 
Therefore, the maximization problem of the social planner can be 
written as 
1  C (t) 1 max exp (t) dt 
0 1    
subject to  
N(t)=  (1  )1/N (t) L  C (t) .  
where (1  )1/NS (t) L is net output.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 27 / 93
Z</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>70</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Patents 
What Can Be Patented  
To be patented, an invention must be: 
Novel, 
Nonobvious, 
Adequately described or enabled (for one of ordinary skill in the art to 
make and use the invention), and 
Claimed by the inventor in clear and denite terms. 
Utility patents are provided for a novel, nonobvious and useful: 
Process, 
Machine, 
Article of manufacture, or 
Composition of matter. 
The Patent Act of 1790 was the rst federal patent statute of the 
United States, and set the length of a patent as 14 years. Since 1995, 
it is 20 years. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 71 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Demographics, Preferences, and Technology  
Innite-horizon economy, continuous time. 
Representative household with preferences:
  1C (t) 1 exp (t) dt. (1) 
0 1   
L =total (constant) population of workers. Labor supplied  
inelastically.  
Representative household owns a balanced portfolio of all the rms in 
the economy. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 5 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>66</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Pareto Optimality in Schumpeterian Growth  
This equilibrium is typically Pareto suboptimal. 
But now distortions more complex than the expanding varieties model. 
monopolists are not able to capture the entire social gain created by an 
innovation. 
Business stealing eect. 
The equilibrium rate of innovation and growth can be too high or too 
low because of the business stealing eect. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 67 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Growth without Scale Eects 
Growth without Scale Eects: Motivation 
The models so far feature a scale eect.  
A larger population L = higher interest rate and a higher growth
rate.  
Potentially problematic for three reasons:  
1 
2 Larger countries do not necessarily grow faster.  
The population of most nations has not been constant. If we have  
population growth as in the standard neoclassical growth model, e.g.,  
L (t)= exp (nt) L (0), these models would not feature balanced  
growth, rather, the growth rate of the economy would be increasing  
over time.  
3 In the data, the total amount of resources devoted to R&amp;D appears 
to increase steadily, but there is no associated increase in the 
aggregate growth rate. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 43/93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 1 / 93  
14.452 Economic Growth: Lectures 9 and 10,
Endogenous Technological Change
Daron Acemoglu
MIT
Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>79</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Estimating Technology Spillovers 
Technology Spillovers and Product Market Rivalry  
Almost all papers estimating technology spillovers are subject to the 
reection problem because the specication takes the form of 
regression of the rm s productivity/innovation on that of its 
neighbors . 
Few do much about it. 
Bloom, Schankerman and Van Reenen provide one attempt to deal 
with this problem. 
They start with an important observation: one needs to distinguish 
knowledge (technology) spillovers from product market rivalry, since 
rms like you to share knowledge are often also product market rivals. 
Knowledge spillovers are positive externalities while product market 
rivalry creates negative eects from (R&amp;D) investments of one rm 
on the prots and value of another, so at the very least the presence 
of these two interactions need to be taken together; ignoring one of 
them can confound the other. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 80 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>77</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Patents 
Patent Citations and Patent Value  
Considerable evidence suggests that patent value, and thus 
presumably patent quality, is correlated with patent citations, though 
there are many mitigating factors. 
For example: 
Trajtenberg (1990): Individual patent specic social value for 
Computed Tomography Scanners related to citations 
Hall, Jae and Trajtenberg (2005): Stock market value related to 
citations. 
Bessen (2008): Patent renewals (decision to pay the annual renewal 
fee) related to citations 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 78 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Expanding Variety Models 
Key Insights  
Innovation as generating new blueprints or ideas for production. 
Three important features (Romer):  
Ideas and technologies nonrival many rms can benet from the same  
idea.  
Increasing returns to scale constant returns to scale to capital, labor,  
1 
2 
3 material etc. and then ideas and blueprints are also produced. 
Costs of research and development paid as xed costs upfront. 
We must consider models of monopolistic competition, where rms 
that innovate become monopolists and make prots. 
Throughout use the Dixit-Stiglitz constant elasticity structure. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 3 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>81</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Empirical Strategy 
Empirical Measures  
For technological relatedness, they look at the average share of 
patents of each rm in each of the technology classes between 1970 
and 1999, with technology classes being constructed from the 426 
USPTO categories. 
Technological relatedness of two rms i and j is then given by the 
uncentered correlation between the share of patents in dierent 
technology classes of each rm (a measure originally suggested by 
Jae, 1986 ): 
'TiT 
Tech ij = -j , 
''TiT TjTi j 
where Ti is the vector of share of patents of rm i in dierent  
technology classes.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 82 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Policy in Models of Endogenous Technological Progress 
Innovation Possibilities Frontier I  
Innovation possibilities frontier in this case: 
N(t)= N (t) LR (t) (23) 
where LR (t) is labor allocated to R&amp;D at time t. 
The term N (t) on the right-hand side captures spillovers from the 
stock of existing ideas. 
Notice that (23) imposes that these spillovers are proportional or 
linear. This linearity will be the source of endogenous growth in the 
current model. 
In (23), LR (t) comes out of the regular labor force.The cost of 
workers to the research sector is given by the wage rate in nal good 
sector. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 37 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Policy in Models of Endogenous Technological Progress 
Summary of Equilibrium in the Model with Knowledge 
Spillovers 
Proposition	 Consider the above-described expanding input-variety model 
with knowledge spillovers and suppose that 
(1  ) (1  ) L &lt;  &lt; (1  ) LE  , (30)E 
where L is the number of workers employed in production in E 
BGP, given by (29).Then there exists a unique balanced 
growth path in which technology, output and consumption 
grow at the same rate, g &gt; 0, given by (28) starting from 
any initial level of technology stock N (0) &gt; 0. 
As in the lab equipment model, the equilibrium allocation is Pareto 
suboptimal. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 42 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Pareto Optimal Allocations 
Social Planner Problem IV  
In this problem, N (t) is the state variable, and C (t) is the control 
variable. The current-value Hamiltonian is: 
C (t)1  1H(N, C , )= 1    
1/+ (t) (1  ) N (t) L  C (t). 
The conditions for a candidate Pareto optimal allocation are: 
HC (N, C , )= C (t)  (t)= 0 
1/HN (N, C , )=  (t)  (1  ) L 
=  (t)  (t) 
lim [exp (t)  (t) N (t)] = 0. 
t 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 28 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>88</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Empirical Strategy 
Regressions on Patents (citation weighted)  
 The Econometric Society. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 89 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Characterization of Equilibrium IV  
Equilibrium wages: 
w (t) =  
1   N (t) . (13) 
Free entry 
V (, t) 
(V (, t)  1) Z (, t)  1, Z (, t)  0 and 
= 0, for all  and t, (14) 
where V (, t) is given by (7). 
For relevant parameter values with positive entry and economic 
growth: 
V (, t) = 1. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 16 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Balanced Growth Path II  
Let us next suppose that the (free entry) condition (14) holds as an 
equality, in which case we also have 
L = 1 r  
This equation pins down the steady-state interest rate, r , as:  
  r = L 
The consumer Euler equation, (15), then implies that the rate of  
growth of consumption must be given by  
C(t) 1 g = = ( r  ). (18)CC (t)  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 20 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>90</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Empirical Strategy 
Summary of Empirical Findings  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 91 / 93  The Econometric Society. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Common
s license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>64</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Summary of Balanced Growth Path  
Proposition	 Consider the model of Schumpeterian growth described 
above. Suppose that 
L   L &gt;  &gt; (1  ) 1 . (57) 
 +(  1)
Then, there exists a unique balanced growth path in which 
average quality of machines, output and consumption grow 
at rate g given by (56). The rate of innovation is 
g / (  1). 
Also, as in the expanding input for IT model, there are 
no transitional dynamics. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 65 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>52</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Innovation Possibilities Frontier II  
Once a machine of quality q (, t) has been invented, any quantity 
can be produced at the marginal cost q (, t). 
New entrants undertake the R&amp;D and innovation: 
The incumbent has weaker incentives to innovate, since it would be 
replacing its own machine, and thus destroying the prots that it is 
already making (Arrow s replacement eect ). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 53 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Policy in Models of Endogenous Technological Progress 
Characterization of Equilibrium III 
Using these observations together with the free entry condition, we 
obtain: 
LE (t)  N (t) = N (t) . (27)r  1  
Hence the BGP equilibrium interest rate must be 
 r =(1  ) LE  ,
where L = L  LR  . The fact that the number of workers inE 
production must be constant in BGP follows from (27). 
Now using the Euler equation of the representative household, (15), 
for all t: 
C(t) 1= ((1  ) LE  ) (28)C (t) 
 g .
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 40 /93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>73</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Patents 
Some Examples: Apple s Touchscreen  
Item is in the public domain.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 74 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>74</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Patents 
Some Examples: Apple s Touchscreen (continued)  
Item is in the public domain.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 75 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Policy in Models of Endogenous Technological Progress 
Characterization of Equilibrium I 
Most of equilibrium characterization very similar. 
Labor market clearing: 
LR (t)+ LE (t)  L.
Aggregate output of the economy:  
1 Y (t)= N (t) LE (t) , (24)1   
and prots of monopolists from selling their machines is 
 (t)= LE (t) . (25) 
The net present discounted value of a monopolist (for a blueprint ) 
is still given by V (, t) as in (7) or (8), with the ow prots given by 
(25). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 38/93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>92</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
14.452 Economic Growth
 Fall 2016
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>62</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Balanced Growth Path III  

To solve for the BGP equilibrium, we need a nal equation relating g 
to z . From (44)  
Y(t) Q(t)  = . Y (t) Q (t) 
Note that in an interval of time t, z (t) t sectors experience one 
innovation, and this will increase their productivity by . 
The measure of sectors experiencing more than one innovation within 
this time interval is o (t) i.e., it is second-order in t, so that 
as t  0, o(t)/t  0. 
Therefore, we have 
Q (t + t)= Q (t) z (t) t +(1  z (t) t) Q (t)+ o (t) . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 63 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>78</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Patents 
Patent Citations and Spillovers  
Another prima fascia evidence in favor of the idea that innovation 
creates knowledge spillovers is that most patents cite other patents, 
indicating that they are building on them. 
However, this is not conclusive, since the citation may be done purely 
for bureaucratic reasons and after the fact (and in fact, many of the 
citations are added by patent examiners). 
If so, we would not know exactly how much building on the  
shoulders of giants there is.  
Nevertheless, this would be an interesting source of data to exploit for 
this purpose. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 79 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Policy in Models of Endogenous Technological Progress 
Characterization of Equilibrium II  
The free entry condition is no longer the same. Instead, (23) implies: 
N (t) V (, t)= w (t) , (26) 
where N (t) is on the left-hand side because it parameterizes the 
productivity of an R&amp;D worker, while the ow cost of undertaking 
research is hiring workers for R&amp;D, thus is equal to the wage rate 
w (t). 
The equilibrium wage rate must be the same as before: 
w (t)= N (t) / (1  )
Balanced growth again requires that the interest rate must be 
constant at some level r . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 39/93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>86</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Empirical Strategy 
Regressions for Market Value (Tobin s Q)  
 The Econometric Society. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 87 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>46</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Growth without Scale Eects 
Summary of Equilibrium without Scale Eects 
Proposition	 In the above-described expanding input-variety model with 
limited knowledge spillovers as given by (32), starting from 
any initial level of technology stock N (0) &gt; 0, there exists a 
unique balanced growth path in which, technology and 
consumption per capita grow at the rate gN as given by (35), 
and output grows at rate gN + n. 
Sustained equilibrium growth of per capita income is possible with 
growing population. 
Instead of the linear (proportional) spillovers, only a limited amount 
of spillovers. 
Without population growth, these spillovers would aect the level of 
output, but not su cient to sustain long-run growth. 
Population growth increases the market size for new technologies 
steadily and generates growth from these limited spillovers. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 47 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>44</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Growth without Scale Eects 
Growth without Scale Eects I  
Aggregate output and prots are given by (24) and (25) as in the 
previous section. An equilibrium is also dened similarly. 
Focus on the BGP. Free entry with equality: 
N (t)LE (t)= w (t) . (34)r  n
As before, the equilibrium wage is determined by the production side, 
(13), as 
w (t)= N (t) / (1  ) .
Thus, 
N (t)1 (1  ) LE (t) = 1.r  n
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 45 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Policy in Models of Endogenous Technological Progress 
The Eects of Competition I  
Recall that the monopoly price is: 
x  p= .1   
Imagine, instead, that a fringe of competitive rms can copy the  
innovation of any monopolist.  
But instead of a marginal cost , the fringe has marginal cost of  
with  &gt; 1. 
If  &gt; 1/ (1  ), no threat from the fringe. 
If  &lt; 1/ (1  ), the fringe would forced the monopolist to set a 
limit price , 
xp= . (22) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 34 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>55</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Monopoly Prots  
Prot-maximizing monopoly:  
px (, t | q)= q (, t) . (42)  
Combining with (40) 
x (, t | q)= L. (43) 
Thus, ow prots of monopolist: 
 (, t | q)= q (, t) L. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 56 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>59</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Denition of Equilibrium  
V (, t | q), is nonstochastic: either q is not the highest quality in 
this machine line and V (, t | q) is equal to 0, or it is given by (47). 
An equilibrium can then be represented as time paths of 
t[C (t) , X (t) , Z (t)]
[Q (t)] =0 that satisfy (37), (??), (50), 
=0 consistent with (45), (47) and  
=0 and [V (, t | q)]t [0,1],t
(48), 
 
[0,1],t=0 given by (42) and (43), and [px (, t | q) , x (, t)]
[r (t) , w (t)]=0 that are consistent with (46) and (49)  
t
Balanced Growth Path dened similarly to before (constant growth of 
output, constant interest rate). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 60 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Pareto Optimal Allocations 
Social Planner Problem I  
Monopolistic competition implies that the competitive equilibrium is 
not necessarily Pareto optimal. The model exhibits a version of the 
aggregate demand externalities : 
1 
2 There is a markup over the marginal cost of production of inputs. 
The number of inputs produced at any point in time may not be 
optimal. 
The rst ine ciency is familiar from models of static monopoly, while 
the second emerges from the fact that in this economy the set of 
traded (Arrow-Debreu) commodities is endogenously determined. 
This relates to the issue of endogenously incomplete markets (there is 
no way to purchase an input that is not supplied in equilibrium). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 25 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>69</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Patents 
Patents  
A very useful source of data on the quantity, quality and nature of 
innovation comes from patents data. 
A signicant fraction of new innovations are patented to protect the 
property rights of the inventor. 
USPTO denes a patent as: 
A patent is a property right granted by the Government of 
the United States of America to an inventor to exclude others 
from making, using, oering for sale, or selling the invention 
throughout the United States or importing the invention into the 
United States for a limited time in exchange for public disclosure 
of the invention when the patent is granted. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 70 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Policy in Models of Endogenous Technological Progress 
Policies 
What kind of policies can increase equilibrium growth rate? 
1 Subsidies to Research: the government can increase the growth rate 
of the economy, and this can be a Pareto improvement if taxation is 
not distortionary and there can be appropriate redistribution of 
resources so that all parties benet. 
2 Subsidies to Capital Inputs: ine ciencies also arise from the fact that 
the decentralized economy is not using as many units of the 
machines/capital inputs (because of the monopoly markup); so 
subsidies to capital inputs given to nal good producers would also 
increase the growth rate. 
But note, the same policies can also be used to distort allocations. 
When we look at a the cross-section of countries, taxes on research 
and capital inputs more common than subsidies. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 33 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Characterization of Equilibrium II  
Since (6) denes isoelastic demands, the solution to the maximization 
problem of any monopolist   [0, N (t)] involves setting the same
price in every period: 
px (, t) = for all  and t. (9)1  
Normalize   (1  ), so that
xpx (, t) = p= 1 for all  and t. 
Prot-maximization also implies that each monopolist rents out the 
same quantity of machines in every period, equal to 
x (, t)= L for all  and t. (10) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 14 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>49</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Preferences and Technology I  
Continuous time. 
Representative household with standard CRRA preferences. 
Constant population L; labor supplied inelastically. 
Resource constraint: 
C (t)+ X (t)+ Z (t)  Y (t) , (37) 
Normalize the measure of inputs to 1, and denote each machine line 
by   [0, 1]. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 50 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>60</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Balanced Growth Path I  

In BGP, consumption grows at the constant rate gC , that must be the 
same rate as output growth, g . 

From (49), r (t)= r for all t. 
If there is positive growth in BGP, there must be research at least in 
some sectors. 
Since prots and R&amp;D costs are proportional to quality, whenever the 
free entry condition (48) holds as equality for one machine type, it 
will hold as equality for all of them. 
Thus, 
q (, t)V (, t | q)= . (51) 
 Moreover, if it holds between t and t + t, V (, t | q)= 0, because 
the right-hand side of equation (51) is constant over time q (, t) 
refers to the quality of the machine supplied by the incumbent, which 
does not change. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 61 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Characterization of Equilibrium I 
An allocation in this economy is dened by time paths of: 
consumption levels, aggregate spending on machines, and aggregate 
R&amp;D expenditure [C (t) , X (t) , Z (t)]t=0, 

available machine types, [N (t)]t=0,
prices and quantities of each machine and the net present discounted 
value of prots from that machine, 
x (, t), x (, t) , V (, t)][p=0, and N (t),t
 
t=0.
 interest rates and wage rates, [r (t) , w (t)]
An equilibrium is an allocation in which 
all research rms choose [px (, t) , x (, t)] 
[0,N (t)],t=0 to maximize
prots, 
[N (t)]=0 is determined by free entry, 

[r (t) , w (t)]=0, are consistent with market clearing, and 
=0 are consistent with consumer optimization. t 
t
[C (t) , X (t) , Z (t)]t
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 13 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>65</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Transitional Dynamics  
Proposition	 In the model of Schumpeterian growth described above, 
starting with any average quality of machines Q (0) &gt; 0, 
there are no transitional dynamics and the equilibrium path 
always involves constant growth at the rate g given by (56). 
Note only the average quality of machines, Q (t), matters for the 
allocation of resources. 
Moreover, the incentives to undertake research are identical for two 
machine types  and  ', with dierent quality levels q (, t) and 
q ( ' , t) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 66 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>80</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Empirical Strategy 
Empirical Strategy  
Bloom, Schankerman and Van Reenen estimate models related to 
these predictions on Compustat matched to the patents citation data. 
There are two major challenges:  
Constructing equivalents of technology neighbors and product market  
 1 
2 rivals.  
Worrying about the reection problem.  
They are successful in the rst, less so in the second. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 81 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>61</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Balanced Growth Path II  
Since R&amp;D for each machine type has the same productivity, constant 
in BGP: 
 z (, t)= z (t)= z 
Then (47) implies 
q (, t) LV (, t | q)= . (52)r  + z  

Note the eective discount rate is r  + z . 
Combining this with (51): 
  r + z = L. (53) 
  
From the fact that g = g and (49), g =(r  ) /, or C 
  r = g + . (54) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 62 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>91</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Conclusions 
Conclusions  
Knowledge spillovers are an important form of externality. Though 
they are not necessary for endogenous technological change, it is 
plausible that they are quite sizable. 
A variety of diverse evidence is consistent with the importance of 
these spillovers, but not always based on solid inference. 
Patent data and patent citation data can be used to investigate this 
question, as well as more generally as a very useful source of data in 
empirical work on innovation and technological change. 
Estimates of the spillovers that attempt to deal with major 
endogeneity issues and also spillovers taking place through product 
market competition suggest that knowledge spillovers are present and 
perhaps quite large. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 92 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Transitional Dynamics I  
There are no transitional dynamics in this model. 
Substituting for prots in the value function for each monopolist, this 
gives 
r (t) V (, t)  V(, t) = L.
The key observation is that positive growth at any point implies that 
V (, t) = 1 for all t. In other words, if V (, t ' ) = 1 for some t ' , 
then V (, t) = 1 for all t. 
Now dierentiating V (, t) = 1 with respect to time yields 
 V (, t) = 0, which is only consistent with r (t)= r for all t, thus 
r (t)= L for all t. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 23 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Characterization of Equilibrium III 
Monopoly prots: 
 (, t)= L for all  and t. (11) 
Substituting (6) and the machine prices into (2) yields: 
1Y (t)= N (t) L. (12)1  
Even though the aggregate production function exhibits constant 
returns to scale from the viewpoint of nal good rms (which take 
N (t) as given), there are increasing returns to scale for the entire 
economy; 
An increase in N (t) raises the productivity of labor and when N (t) 
increases at a constant rate so will output per capita. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 15 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Transitional Dynamics II  
Proposition	 Suppose that condition (20) holds. In the above-described 
lab equipment expanding input-variety model, with initial 
technology stock N (0) &gt; 0, there is a unique equilibrium 
path in which technology, output and consumption always 
grow at the rate g as in (19). 
While the microfoundations here are very dierent from the 
neoclassical AK economy, the mathematical structure is very similar 
to the AK model (as most clearly illustrated by the derived equation 
for output, (12)). 
Consequently, as in the AK model, the economy always grows at a 
constant rate. 
But the economics is very dierent. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 24 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>83</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Empirical Strategy 
Empirical Measures (continued)  
Measures of product market rivalry are created similarly, by using the 
vector of sales of each rm in dierent four digit industries. Denoting 
these vectors by Si , this is 
'SiS
SICij = j , -' 'SiS S jSi j 
and they also dene 
SpillSIC it =  SICij  Kjt . 
j H=i 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 84 / 93 q</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>82</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Empirical Strategy 
Empirical Measures (continued)  
For technological relatedness, they also construct similar measures 
based on the Mahalanobis distance, which relaxes the assumption 
that knowledge spillovers are within technology classes and instead 
assumes that they are proportional to the likelihood of co-location of 
patents from dierent technology classes within rms. 
Their measure of spillover for rm i in year t is then: 
SpillTech it =  Tech ij  Kjt ,
Hj =i  
where Kjt is the R&amp;D stock of rm j at time t, obtained from their 
past R&amp;D investments. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 83 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>57</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Characterization of Equilibrium II  
Value function for monopolist of variety  of quality q (, t) at time t: 
r (t) V (, t | q)  V(, t | q) = (, t | q)  z(, t | q)V (, t | q), 
(47) 
where: 
z(, t | q)=rate at which new innovations occur in sector  at time t, 
(, t | q)=ow of prots. 
Last term captures the essence of Schumpeterian growth: 
when innovation occurs, the monopolist loses its monopoly position  
and is replaced by the producer of the higher-quality machine.  
From then on, it receives zero prots, and thus has zero value.  
Because of Arrow s replacement eect, an entrant undertakes the  
innovation, thus z(, t | q) is the ow rate at which the incumbent will  
be replaced.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 58 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>76</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Patents 
Patent Citations  
What makes patents a particularly useful source of data for measuring 
and modeling innovation is the data on patent citations. 
We know essentially the entire universe of patent citations. 
For example, between 1975 and 1990, a patent led with the USPTO 
received about 8 cites (with a maximum of 631 cites) from other 
patents in the same time window. Only about 13-14% of this is self 
citation. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 77 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Demographics, Preferences, and Technology II  
Final good producers are competitive. 
The resource constraint of the economy at time t is 
C (t)+ X (t)+ Z (t)  Y (t) , (3) 
where X (t) is investment on inputs at time t and Z (t) is  
expenditure on R&amp;D at time t.  
Once the blueprint of a particular input is invented, the research rm 
can create one unit of that machine at marginal cost equal to  &gt; 0 
units of the nal good. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 7 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>72</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Patents 
Some Examples: Watt s Steam Engine (continued)  
Except is in the public domain.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 73 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Policy in Models of Endogenous Technological Progress 
Characterization of Equilibrium IV  
To complete the characterization of the BGP equilibrium, we need to 
determine LE  . In BGP, (23) implies that the rate of technological 
progress satises 
N(t) = L =  (L  LE  )N (t) R 
This implies that the BGP level of employment is 
L + L = . (29)E (1  )  + 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 41/ 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>56</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Characterization of Equilibrium I  
Substituting (43) into (39): 
1Y (t)= Q (t) L, (44)1  
where 1 
Q (t)= q(, t)d (45) 
0 
Equilibrium wage rate: 
w (t)= Q (t) . (46)1  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 57 / 93 
Z</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>43</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Growth without Scale Eects 
Knowledge Spillovers Model with two Dierences  
1 Dierences: 
Population growth at exponential rate n, L(t)= nL (t). 
Representative household, also growing at the rate n, with preferences: 
1  C (t) 1exp ( (  n) t) dt, (31)
0 1  
2 R&amp;D sector only admits limited knowledge spillovers and (23) is 
replaced by 
N(t)= N (t) LR (t) (32) 
where  &lt; 1 and LR (t) is labor allocated to R&amp;D activities at time t. 
Labor market clearing requires 
LE (t)+ LR (t)= L (t) , (33) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 44 / 93 
Z</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Pareto Optimal Allocations 
Social Planner Problem V  
It can be veried easily that the current-value Hamiltonian of the 
social planner is (strictly) concave, thus these conditions are also 
su cient for an optimal solution. 
Combining these conditions: 
CS (t) 1 1/ =  (1  ) L   . (21)CS (t) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 29 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>89</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Empirical Strategy 
Regression on R&amp;D (ln(R&amp;D divided by sales))  
 The Econometric Society. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 90 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>63</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Balanced Growth Path IV  
Now subtracting Q (t) from both sides, dividing by t and taking the  
limit as t  0, we obtain 
Q (t) = (  1) z (t) Q (t) . 
Therefore, 
g  = (  1) z  . (55) 
Now combining (53)-(55),  we obtain: 
g  = L   
 + (  1)1 . (56) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 64 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>53</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Equilibrium  
Allocation: time paths of  
consumption levels, aggregate spending on machines, and aggregate 
R&amp;D expenditure [C (t) , X (t) , Z (t)]t=0,  

machine qualities [q (, t)][0,1],t=0, 
prices and quantities of each machine and the net present discounted 
value of prots from that machine, 
 xV| | [(t )(t)(t )]    p qx q , , ,, , 
interest rates and wage rates, [()()] t t r w, 
=0, and [0,1],t
 
t=0. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 54 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Balanced Growth Path III 
Note the current-value Hamiltonian for the consumer s maximization 
problem is concave, thus this condition, together with the 
transversality condition, characterizes the optimal consumption plans 
of the consumer. 
In BGP, consumption grows at the same rate as total output 
  g = gC . 
Therefore, given r , the long-run growth rate of the economy is: 
1 g =(L  ) (19) 
Suppose that  
L &gt;  and (1  ) L &lt; , (20)  
which will ensure that g &gt; 0 and that the transversality condition is 
satised. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 21 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Expanding Variety Models 
Introduction  
The key to understanding technology is that R&amp;D and technology 
adoption are purposeful activities. 
This lecture, focus on technological change and R&amp;D. 
The simplest models of endogenous technological change are those in 
which R&amp;D expands the variety of inputs or machines used in 
production (Romer, 1990). 
Models with expanding input varieties: 
research will lead to the creation of new varieties of inputs (machines) 
and a greater variety of inputs will increase the division of labor 
process innovation . 
Alternative: product innovation (Grossman and Helpman (1991a,b)): 
invention of new goods, 
because of love-for-variety, real incomes increase 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 2 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>84</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Empirical Strategy 
Example  
Are these measures distinct?  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 85 / 93  The Econometric Society. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Innovation Possibilities Frontier and Patents II  
A rm that invents a new machine variety v is the sole supplier of 
that type of machine, and sets a prot-maximizing price of px (, t) at 
time t to maximize prots. 
Since machines depreciate after use, px (, t) can also be interpreted 
as a rental price or the user cost of this machine. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 9 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Demographics, Preferences, and Technology I  
Unique consumption good, produced with aggregate production  
function:   N (t) 
Y (t)= 1 x(, t)1dL , (2)1   0  
where  
N (t)=number of varieties of inputs (machines) at time t, 
x (, t)=amount of input (machine) type  used at time t. 
The x s depreciate fully after use. 
They can be interpreted as generic inputs, intermediate goods,  
machines, or capital.  
Thus machines are not additional state variables. 
For given N (t), which nal good producers take as given, (2) exhibits 
constant returns to scale. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 6 / 93 
Z</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>48</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Schumpeterian Growth 
Schumpeterian Growth  
Alternative: quality improvements (over existing technologies or  
products).  
Similar to vertical dierentiation rather than horizontal dierentiation. 
But more important dierence is that now new technologies replace 
old ones. 
Creative destruction : when a higher-quality machine is invented it will 
replace (destroy ) the previous vintage of machines. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 49 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Balanced Growth Path IV  
Proposition	 Suppose that condition (20) holds. Then, in the 
above-described lab equipment expanding input variety 
model, there exists a unique balanced growth path in which 
technology, output and consumption all grow at the same 
rate, g , given by (19).. 
An important feature of this class models is the presence of the scale 
eect : the larger is L, the greater is the growth rate. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 22 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Pareto Optimal Allocations 
Comparison of Equilibrium and Pareto Optimum  
The comparison to the growth rate in the decentralized equilibrium, 
(19), boils down to that of 
1/(1  )  to , 
The socially-planned economy will always grow faster than the  
decentralized economythe former is always greater since  
1/(1  )&gt;1 by virtue of the fact that   (0, 1).
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 30 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Balanced Growth Path I  
A balanced growth path (BGP) requires that consumption grows at a 
constant rate, say gC . This is only possible from (15) if 
 r (t)= r for all t 
Since prots at each date are given by (11) and since the interest rate 
is constant, V(t)= 0 and 
LV  = . (17)r  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 19 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Pareto Optimal Allocations 
Comparison  
Why is the equilibrium growing more slowly than the optimum  
allocation?  
Because the social planner values innovation more 
The social planner is able to use the machines more intensively after 
innovation, pecuniary externality resulting from the monopoly 
markups. 
Other models of endogenous technological progress we will study in 
this lecture incorporate technological spillovers and thus generate 
ine ciencies both because of the pecuniary externality isolated here 
and because of the standard technological spillovers. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 32 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>85</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Empirical Strategy 
Regression Specications 
Then, their main empirical specications regress rm value divided by 
assets (Tobin s average Q), future citation-weighted patents, R&amp;D 
and productivity on SpillTech and SpillSIC as well as controls and own 
R&amp;D stock 
Their models include rm xed eects and also sometimes instrument 
for R&amp;D using tax credits (as a function of the state and industry of 
the rm). 
While one may argue about whether it is instrumented to valid or not 
(though likely not...), it would not solve the endogeneity problems 
unless one also instrumented the spillover variables properly (see 
Acemoglu and Angrist, 2000, for the econometric point in the context 
of human capital externalities). 
Here the same tax credit variable used as instrument for spillovers. 
Though in principle potentially valid, it still raises a variety of issues 
(in particular, correlation in the instrument between rms located in 
the same area) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 86 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Equilibrium and Balanced Growth Path I  
We can now dene an equilibrium more formally as time paths  
=0, such that (3), (??), (15), (16) and t
[C (t) , X (t) , Z (t) , N (t)]
(14) are satised;
[px (, t) , x (, t)] 
=0 that satisfy (9) and (10),N (t),t
=0 such that (13) and (15) hold. t
[r (t) , w (t)]
We dene a balanced growth path (BGP) as an equilibrium path 
where C (t) , X (t) , Z (t) and N (t) grow at a constant rate. Such an 
equilibrium can alternatively be referred to as a steady state , since 
it is a steady state in transformed variables. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 18 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>71</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Patents 
Some Examples: Watt s Steam Engine  
Except is in the public domain.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 72 / 93 
..... D. 1769 .... ... N' 913. 
WJ.Tn !lPEGfFlCATrOJ&lt;. 
Tg.ilL :ro "IIG.1r ullU UIB:rn; flUt.l. 00lU, L h ... 
w .... "''''_.'' $--'10" ll ...... t._~ . 
"'!'O"'" II" _f.t ... , lI!o,Ioot.o "'" o...-r Iloo ThW.",. 1110 '-1'&gt;000, -"'.to.. a_, So .. ~ r:o-. lid ..... boorio, &lt;10&gt;0 &lt;100 FIr .. 
 "",,, , .. ,....,."' .... ""' ...... " &gt;Go ,.;j ltlo,joo,,', ........ ,; ..... 
.,.,..  .., _ tloo .... J_ W .. , Ilio......., .... _ ... _ ..... 
~ .... ..-,. ..... I ..... .., J._ w." ,.,..t.... _ 
.... "' .... "  M .... "-" "';.\I. t,.;'C , .. , .... ~ ,.... ....... 
..,.... .... _. "'_. """ ..... &lt;10",",", ........ " II .. NojooOfJ 
10 I&lt;lor-.tG_, _ ..... E.rr_'" n-;oioo ... W ........ T .... 
... ",,"wlc' __ T ............... II .. "'j 'r', Col .... p,,. .... _ .. ,." .. , ...... .,.. ......... -.............. ,'-".,.." ... 
......... .,..1 ... .-"'_,""_~"-' ,,_.,.... _ r, ... _ ....... J_W""",. ......... .-.. , ........ _" 
" .......... )" r if ; .. "''''' ...... "tIooWol 1._ .... _ 
'" lib )f .... ' n". c..,.,,, {10. OJ _. ,,", "r . r . __ ...... 
.... _ooftloo odd ....... r-~ .. '" ...!'o, ....... ~ ~ ........ _ .. ""'"... )f ..... _ .... __ 
.... , ko.I. __ .. ,,~ .,.,.... . 
.. """nOTlfYI," "/o 'r __ ,..""',. .. _ ...... pu-
_~""MloIOI_ I .......... J ..... w ...... -,._ .... "'"</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change The Lab Equipment Model 
Innovation Possibilities Frontier and Patents I  
Innovation possibilities frontier : 
N(t)= Z (t) , (4) 
where  &gt; 0, and the economy starts with some N (0) &gt; 0. 
There is free entry into research: any individual or rm can spend one 
unit of the nal good at time t in order to generate a ow rate  of 
the blueprints of new machines. 
The rm that discovers these blueprints receives a fully-enforced  
perpetual patent on this machine.  
There is no aggregate uncertainty in the innovation process. 
There will be uncertainty at the level of the individual rm, but with 
many dierent research labs undertaking such expenditure, at the 
aggregate level, equation (4) holds deterministically. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 8 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>75</slideno>
          <text>Endogenous Technological Change Patents 
Some Examples: Apple s Touchscreen (continued)  
Item is in the public domain.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 76 / 93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>87</slideno>
          <text>http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/  
        
    Endogenous Technological Change Empirical Strategy 
Regressions for Productivity  
Creative
Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. The Econ ometric Society. 
All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 9 and 10 Nov. 29 and Dec. 1, 2016. 88 / 93</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Neoclassical Growth (PDF - 1.2MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-452-economic-growth-fall-2016/resources/mit14_452f16_lec5and6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5&#8211;6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Representative Firm Representative Firm 
The Representative Firm II 
Why such a dierence between representative household and  
representative rm assumptions? Income eects.  
Changes in prices create income eects, which aect dierent 
households dierently. 
No income eects in producer theory, so the representative rm 
assumption is without loss of any generality. 
Does not mean that heterogeneity among rms is uninteresting or 
unimportant. 
Many models of endogenous technology feature productivity 
dierences across rms, and rmsattempts to increase their 
productivity relative to others will often be an engine of economic 
growth. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        14 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>53</slideno>
          <text>Steady-State Equilibrium Steady State 
Steady-State Equilibrium III 
Given k, steady-state consumption level: 
 c = f (k )  (n + )k ,	 (24) 
Given Assumption 4', a steady state where the capital-labor ratio and 
thus output are constant necessarily satises the transversality 
condition. 
Proposition	 In the neoclassical growth model described above, with 
Assumptions 1, 2, assumptions on utility above and 
Assumption 4', the steady-state equilibrium capital-labor 
ratio, k, is uniquely determined by (23) and is independent 
of the utility function. The steady-state consumption per 
capita, c , is given by (24).  
Comparative statics again straightforward. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        54 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Neoclassical Growth Model Environment 
Preferences, Technology and Demographics IV 
Per capita production function f ()  
Y (t) y (t)  L (t)(  K (t) = F , 1L (t) 
 f (k (t)) , 
where, as before, 
K (t)k (t)  . (10)L (t) 
Competitive factor markets then imply: 
R (t) = FK [K (t), L(t)] = f ' (k(t)). (11) 
and 
w (t) = FL[K (t), L(t)] = f (k (t))  k (t) f ' (k(t)). (12) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        36 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Welfare Theorems 
Welfare Theorems XII 
Notice: 
if instead if we had a nite commodity space, say with K commodities, 
'then the hypothesis that 0  Xi for each i  H and x, x  Xi with 
T such that u  i (x) &gt; u
all T i (x i (x [T ]) &gt; ui (x ' ), there exists' [T ]) for u
T and all i  H (and also that there exists Tsuch that if 
for all T  Tand all f  F ) would be 
T T  y  Yf , then y [T ]  Yf 
satised automatically, by taking = K . = 
Condition not imposed in Second Welfare Theorem in economies with a 
nite number of commodities. 
In dynamic economies, its role is changes in allocations at very far in 
the future should not have a large eect. 
The conditions for the Second Welfare Theorem are more di cult to 
satisfy than those for the First. 
Also the more important of the two theorems: stronger results that 
any Pareto optimal allocation can be decentralized. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        31 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Welfare Theorems 
Welfare Theorems I  
There should be a close connection between Pareto optima and  
competitive equilibria.  
Start with models that have a nite number of consumers, so H is 
nite. 
However, allow an innite number of commodities. 
Results here have analogs for economies with a continuum of  
commodities, but focus on countable number of commodities.     
i iLet commodities be indexed by j  N and x x be the jj =0   
consumption bundle of household i, and i i
j be its 
j =0 
endowment bundle. 
Assume feasible xs must belong to some consumption set Xi  R i +. 
Most relevant interpretation for us is that at each date j = 0, 1, ..., 
each individual consumes a nite dimensional vector of products. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        15 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>54</slideno>
          <text>Steady-State Equilibrium Steady State 
Steady-State Equilibrium IV 
Instead of the saving rate, it is now the discount factor that aects 
the rate of capital accumulation. 
Loosely, lower discount rate implies greater patience and thus greater 
savings. 
Without technological progress, the steady-state saving rate can be 
computed as 
k 
 s = . (25)f (k) 
Rate of population growth has no impact on the steady state 
capital-labor ratio, which contrasts with the basic Solow model. 
result depends on the way in which intertemporal discounting takes 
place. 

k and thus c do not depend on the instantaneous utility function 
u (). 
form of the utility function only aects the transitional dynamics 
not true when there is technological change,. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        55 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>Characterization of Equilibrium Household Maximization 
Household Maximization I 
Maximize (9) subject to (13) and (16).  
First ignore (16) and set up the current-value Hamiltonian: 
H(a, c, )= u (c (t)) +  (t) [w (t)+(r (t)  n) a (t)  c (t)] , 
Maximum Principle  candidate solution 
Hc (a, c, )= u ' (c (t))   (t)= 0 
Ha (a, c, )=  (t) (r (t)  n) 
= (t)+(  n)  (t) 
lim [exp ( (  n) t)  (t) a (t)] = 0. 
t 
and the transition equation (13).  
Notice transversality condition is written in terms of the current-value 
costate variable. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        43 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>57</slideno>
          <text>Dynamics Transitional Dynamics 
Transitional Dynamics III  
c(t)
kgold 0k(t)
k(0)c(0)
c(0)c(t)=0
k(t)=0
k*c(0)c*
k
Figure: Transitional dynamics in the baseline neoclassical growth model 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        58 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>Neoclassical Growth Model Environment 
Preferences, Technology and Demographics VI  
With uncertainty, households would have a portfolio choice between 
K (t) and riskless bonds. 
With incomplete markets, bonds allow households to smooth  
idiosyncratic shocks. But for now no need.  
Thus, market clearing  
a (t)= k (t) . 
No uncertainty depreciation rate of  implies  
r (t)= R (t)  . (14)  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        38 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>44</slideno>
          <text>Characterization of Equilibrium Household Maximization 
Household Maximization III 
Dierentiate with respect to time and divide by  (t),  
u '' (c (t)) c (t) c(t) (t)  = . u ' (c (t)) c (t)  (t) 
Substituting into (18) gives  
c(t) 1  = (r (t)  ) (20)c (t) u (c(t)) 
where 
u '' (c (t)) c (t)u (c (t))   (21)u ' (c (t)) 
is the elasticity of the marginal utility u ' (c(t)) or the inverse of the 
intertemporal elasticity of substitution. 
Consumption will grow over time when the discount rate is less than 
the rate of return on assets. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        45 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>Neoclassical Growth Model Environment 
The No Ponzi Game Condition  
Innite-horizon no Ponzi game condition is: 
  t 
lim a (t) exp (r (s)  n) ds 0. (15)
t 0 
Transversality condition ensures individual would never want to have 
positive wealth asymptotically, so no Ponzi game condition can be 
strengthened to (though not necessary in general): 
  t 
lim a (t) exp (r (s)  n) ds= 0. (16)
t 0 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
Z
Z
November 10 and 15, 2016.        40 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>82</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Comparative Dynamics 
Comparative Dynamics II 
Figure: drawn assuming change is unanticipated and occurs at some 
date T . 
At T , curve corresponding to c /c = 0 shifts to the right and laws of 
motion represented by the phase diagram change. 

Following the decline c is above the stable arm of the new dynamical 
system: consumption must drop immediately 
Then consumption slowly increases along the stable arm 
Overall level of normalized consumption will necessarily increase, since 
the intersection between the curve for c /c = 0 and for k/k = 0 will 
necessarily be to the left side of kgold . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        83 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Representative Household A Partial Positive Result 
Gorman Aggregation  
  
Recall an indirect utility function for household i, vip, yi, species 
(ordinal) utility as a function of the price vector p =(p1, ..., pN ) and 
household s income yi .  
vip, yi: homogeneous of degree 0 in p and y. 
Theorem	 (Gorman s Aggregation Theorem) Consider an economy 
with a nite number N &lt;  of commodities and a set H of 
households. Suppose that the preferences of household i  H 
can be represented by an indirect utility function of the form 
  i i	 iv p , y	= ai (p)+ b (p) y, (2) 
then these preferences can be aggregated and represented by 
those of a representative household, with indirect utility 
 
v (p, y )= ai (p) di + b (p) y, 
i H  
where y  yi di is aggregate income. i H 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        9 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Neoclassical Growth Model Environment 
Preferences, Technology and Demographics III 
Utility of u (c (t)) per household member at time t, total of 
L (t) u (c (t)) = exp (nt) u (c (t)). 
With discount at rate of exp (t), obtain (9). 
'ASSUMPTION 4 . 
 &gt; n. 
Ensures that in the model without growth, discounted utility is nite 
(otherwise innite utility and not well behaved equilibrium). Will 
strengthen it in model with growth. 
Start model without any technological progress. 
Factor and product markets are competitive. 
Production possibilities set of the economy is represented by 
Y (t)= F [K (t) , L (t)] , 
Standard constant returns to scale and Inada assumptions still hold. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        35 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction Preliminaries 
Time Separable Preferences  
Standard assumptions on preference orderings so that they can be 
represented by utility functions. 
In addition, time separable preferences: each household i has an 
instantaneous (Bernoulli) utility function (or felicity function): 
ui (ci (t)) , 
ui : R+ R is increasing and concave and ci (t) is the consumption 
of household i. 
Note instantaneous utility function is not specifying a complete 
preference ordering over all commodities here consumption levels in 
all dates. 
Instead, household i preferences at time t = 0 are obtained by  
combining this with exponential discounting.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        4 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction Preliminaries 
Innite Horizon and the Representative Household 
Given by the von Neumann-Morgenstern expected utility function 
T 
Ei 
0  t
i ui (ci (t)) , (1) 
t=0 
where i  (0, 1) is the discount factor of household i, where T &lt;  
or T = , corresponding to nite planning horizon (e.g., with 
overlapping generations) or innite planning horizon. 
The second is often assumed because the standard approach in 
macroeconomics is to impose the existence of a representative 
household costs of this to be discussed below. 
Exponential discounting and time separability also ensure 
time-consistent behavior. 
TA solution {x (t)}=0 (possibly with T = ) is time consistent if:t
T
whenever {x (t)}=0 is an optimal solution starting at time t = 0,t
T{x (t)} is an optimal solution to the continuation dynamic t=t' 
optimization problem starting from time t = t' [0, T ]. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        5 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>74</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Technological Change XI 
Proposition	 Consider the neoclassical growth model with labor 
augmenting technological progress at the rate g and 
preferences given by (30).  Suppose that Assumptions 1, 2, 
assumptions on utility above hold and   n &gt; (1  ) g. 
Then there exists a unique balanced growth path with a 
normalized capital to eective labor ratio of k, given by 
(33),  and output per capita and consumption per capita 
grow at the rate g. 
Steady-state capital-labor ratio no longer independent of preferences, 
depends on . 
Positive growth in output per capita, and thus in consumption per 
capita. 
With upward-sloping consumption prole, willingness to substitute 
consumption today for consumption tomorrow determines 
accumulation and thus equilibrium eective capital-labor ratio. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        75 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Representative Household A Partial Positive Result 
Importance of Gorman Preferences  
Gorman Preferences limit the extent of income eects and enables 
the aggregation of individual behavior. 
Integral is Lebesgue integral, so when H is a nite or countable set, 
iyi di is indeed equivalent to the summation i H y.i H 
Stated for an economy with a nite number of commodities, but can 
be generalized for innite or even a continuum of commodities. 
Note all we require is there exists a monotonic transformation of the 
indirect utility function that takes the form in (2) as long as no 
uncertainty. 
Contains some commonly-used preferences in macroeconomics. 
Gorman preferences also imply the existence of a normative 
representative household, i.e., a representative household such that 
if it prefers an allocation to another, then the former allocation 
Pareto dominates the latter. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
R
November 10 and 15, 2016.        11 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>43</slideno>
          <text>Characterization of Equilibrium Household Maximization 
Household Maximization II  
For any  (t) &gt; 0, H(a, c, ) is a concave function of (a, c) and 
strictly concave in c. 
The rst necessary condition implies  (t) &gt; 0 for all t. 
Therefore, Su cient Conditions imply that the candidate solution
 is 
an optimum (is it unique?) 
Rearrange the second condition: 
 (t) 
 (t) =  (r (t)  ) , (18) 
First necessary condition implies, 
u ' (c (t)) =  (t) . (19) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        44 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>88</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change A Quantitative Evaluation 
A Quantitative Evaluation VI 
Parallels discussion of the Mankiw-Romer-Weil approach: 
dierences in income per capita unlikely to be accounted for by 
dierences in capital per worker alone. 
need sizable dierences in the e ciency with which these factors are 
used, absent in this model. 
But many economists have tried (and still try) to use versions of the 
neoclassical model to go further. 
Motivation is simple: if instead of using  = 2/3, we take  = 1/3 
Y ()  82  64.Y ( ' ) 
Thus if there is a way of increasing the responsiveness of capital or 
other factors to distortions, predicted dierences across countries can 
be made much larger. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        89 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Welfare Theorems 
Welfare Theorems X  
 Theorem	 (First Welfare Theorem II) Suppose that (x , y , p ) is a 
competitive equilibrium of the economy 
E  (H, F , u, , Y, X, ) with H countably innite. Assume 
that all households are locally non-satiated and that 
	    p    = i H j  
=0 pj i
j &lt; . Then (x , y , p ) is Pareto 
optimal. 
Proof: 
Same as before but now local non-satiation does not guarantee 
summations are nite (5), since we sum over an innite number of 
households. 
But since endowments are nite, the assumption that 
i H  
=0 pj ji &lt;  ensures that the sums in (5) are indeed nite. j 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        27 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>56</slideno>
          <text>Dynamics Transitional Dynamics 
Transitional Dynamics II  
Appropriate notion of saddle-path stability: 
consumption level (or equivalently ) is the control variable, and c (0) 
(or  (0)) is free: has to adjust to satisfy transversality condition 
since c (0) or  (0) can jump to any value, need that there exists a 
one-dimensional manifold tending to the steady state (stable arm). 
If there were more than one path equilibrium would be indeterminate. 
Economic forces are such that indeed there will be a one-dimensional 
manifold of stable solutions tending to the unique steady state. 
See Figure. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        57 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>89</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change A Quantitative Evaluation 
A Quantitative Evaluation VII  
To have a model in which  = 1/3, must have additional 
accumulated factors, while still keeping the share of labor income in 
national product roughly around 2/3. 
E.g., include human capital, but human capital dierences appear to 
be insu cient to explain much of the income per capita dierences 
across countries. 
Or introduce other types of capital or perhaps technology that  
responds to distortions in the same way as capital.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        90 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Welfare Theorems 
Proof of First Welfare Theorem IV  
However, by market clearing of xi (Denition above, part 1), we have 
i i f xj =  j +  yj , 
i H i H f F 

Therefore, by multiplying both sides by p and exploiting (6), 
 i  i fp   xj  p   j +  yj 
i H i H f F 
 f   p   ji +  yj , 
i H f F 
Contradicts (5), establishing that any competitive equilibrium 
allocation (x , y ) is Pareto optimal. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
 !
 !
November 10 and 15, 2016.        25 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Representative Firm Representative Firm 
The Representative Firm I  
While not all economies would admit a representative household,  
standard assumptions (in particular no production externalities and  
competitive markets) are su cient to ensure a representative rm.  
Theorem	 (The Representative Firm Theorem) Consider a 
competitive production economy with N  N{+}
commodities and a countable set F of rms, each with a 
convex production possibilities set Yf  RN . Let p  RN be + 
the price vector in this economy and denote the set of prot 
maximizing net supplies of rm f  F by Yf (p)  Yf (so 
f	 f fthat for any y  Yf (p), we have p  y  p  yfor all 
fy Yf ). Then there exists a representative rm with 
production possibilities set Y  RN and set of prot 
maximizing net supplies Y(p) such that for any p  RN 
+, 
fy  Y(p) if and only if y (p)= f F yfor some 
fy  Yf (p) for each f  F. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        13 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>68</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Technological Change V  
Given the restriction that balanced growth is only possible with a  
constant elasticity of intertemporal substitution, start with  
c (t )1 1 if   1 and   0u (c (t)) = 1 ,
ln c(t) if  = 1 
Elasticity of marginal utility of consumption, u , is given by . 
When  = 0, these represent linear preferences, when  = 1, we have 
log preferences, and as   , innitely risk-averse, and innitely 
unwilling to substitute consumption over time. 
Assume that the economy admits a representative household with 
CRRA preferences 
1  c(t) 1 exp ((  n)t) dt, (30) 
0 1   
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 (
6=
Z
November 10 and 15, 2016.        69 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>59</slideno>
          <text>Dynamics Transitional Dynamics 
Global Stability Analysis  
Alternative argument: 
if c (0) started below it, say c '' (0), consumption would reach zero, 
thus capital would accumulate continuously until the maximum level of 
capital (reached with zero consumption) k&gt; kgold . This would violate 
the transversality condition. Can be established that transversality 
condition necessary in this case, thus such paths can be ruled out. 
if c (0) started above this stable arm, say at c ' (0), the capital stock 
would reach 0 in nite time, while consumption would remain positive. 
But this would violate feasibility (a little care is necessary with this 
argument, since necessary conditions do not apply at the boundary). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        60 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction Introduction 
Foundations of Neoclassical Growth  
Solow model: constant saving rate. 
Ramsey or Cass-Koopmans model: diers from the Solow model only 
because it explicitly models the consumer side and endogenizes 
savings. This model species the preference orderings of individuals 
and derives their decisions from these preferences. It also 
Enables better understanding of the factors that aect savings 
decisions. 
Enables to discuss the optimality of equilibria 
Claries whether the (competitive) equilibria of growth models can be 
improved upon . 
Beyond its use as a basic growth model, also a workhorse for many 
areas of macroeconomics. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        2 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>67</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Example: CRRA Utility I 
Recall the Arrow-Pratt coe cient of relative risk aversion for a 
twice-continuously dierentiable concave utility function U (c) is 
U'' (c) c R =  .U' (c) 
Constant relative risk aversion (CRRA) utility function satises the 
property that R is constant. 
Integrating both sides of the previous equation, setting R to a 
constant, implies that the family of CRRA utility functions is given by 
 
1 1 cif  = 1 and   0U (c)= 1 ,ln c if  = 1 
with the coe cient of relative risk aversion given by . 
CRRA utility functions are useful precisely because they imply 
constant intertemporal elasticity of substitution. 
Details: see recitation. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        68 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>63</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Technological Change and the Neoclassical Model 
Extend the production function to: 
Y (t)= F [K (t) , A (t) L (t)] , (28) 
where  
A (t)= exp (gt) A (0) .  
A consequence of Uzawa Theorem.: (28) imposes purely  
labor-augmenting Harrod-neutral technological change.  
Continue to adopt all usual assumptions, and Assumption 4' will be 
strengthened further in order to ensure nite discounted utility in the 
presence of sustained economic growth. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        64 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
14.452 Economic Growth: Lectures 5 and 6, Neoclassical
Growth
Daron Acemoglu
MIT
November 10 and 15, 2016.
November 10 and 15, 2016.        1 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Representative Household Representative Household 
Representative Household IV  
That excess demands come from optimizing behavior of households 
puts no restrictions on the form of these demands. 
E.g., x (p) does not necessarily possess a negative-semi-denite 
Jacobian or satisfy the weak axiom of revealed preference 
(requirements of demands generated by individual households). 
Hence without imposing further structure, impossible to derive 
specic x (p) s from the maximization behavior of a single household. 
Severe warning against the use of the representative household  
assumption.  
Partly an outcome of very strong income eects: 
special but approximately realistic preference functions, and restrictions 
on distribution of income rule out arbitrary aggregate excess demand 
functions. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        8 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>91</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
14.452 Economic Growth
Fall 2016
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>76</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Technological Change XII  
Steady-state eective capital-labor ratio, k, is determined 
endogenously, but steady-state growth rate of the economy is given 
exogenously and equal to g. 
Proposition	 Consider the neoclassical growth model with labor 
augmenting technological progress at the rate g and 
preferences given by (30).  Suppose that Assumptions 1, 2, 
assumptions on utility above hold and   n &gt; (1  ) g. 
Then there exists a unique equilibrium path of normalized 
capital and consumption, (k (t) , c (t)) converging to the 
unique steady-state (k , c ) with k given by (33).  
Moreover, if k (0) &lt; k, then k (t)  k and c (t)  c , 
whereas if k (0) &gt; k, then c (t)  k and c (t)  c . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        77 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction Preliminaries 
Preliminaries  
Consider an economy consisting of a unit measure of innitely-lived 
households.  
I.e., an uncountable number of households: e.g., the set of households  
H could be represented by the unit interval [0, 1].  
Emphasize that each household is innitesimal and will have no eect 
on aggregates.  
Can alternatively think of H as a countable set of the form  
H = {1, 2, ..., M} with M = , without any loss of generality.  
Advantage of unit measure: averages and aggregates are the same 
Simpler to have H as a nite set in the form {1, 2, ..., M} with M 
large but nite. 
Acceptable for many models, but with overlapping generations require 
the set of households to be innite. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        3 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>48</slideno>
          <text>Optimal Growth Optimal Growth 
Optimal Growth I  
In an economy that admits a representative household, optimal 
growth involves maximization of utility of representative household 
subject to technology and feasibility constraints: 
 
max  exp ( (  n) t) u (c (t)) dt, 
[k (t),c (t)] 0t=0 
subject to 
k (t)= f (k (t))  (n + )k (t)  c (t) ,  
and k (0) &gt; 0.  
Versions of the First and Second Welfare Theorems for economies 
with a continuum of commodities: solution to this problem should be 
the same as the equilibrium growth problem. 
But straightforward to show the equivalence of the two problems. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
Z
November 10 and 15, 2016.        49 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>52</slideno>
          <text>Steady-State Equilibrium Steady State 
Steady-State Equilibrium II  
c(t)
kgold 0k(t)
k(0)c(0)
c(0)c(t)=0
k(t)=0
k*c(0)c*
k
Figure: Steady state in the baseline neoclassical growth model 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        53 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>72</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Technological Change IX 
Since in steady state c (t) must remain constant:  
r (t)=  + g  
or 
f ' (k )=  +  + g, (33) 
Pins down the steady-state value of the normalized capital ratio k 
uniquely. 
Normalized consumption level is then given by 
 c = f (k )  (n + g + ) k , (34) 
Per capita consumption grows at the rate g. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        73 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Welfare Theorems 
Welfare Theorems VIII  
 Theorem	 (First Welfare Theorem I) Suppose that (x , y , p ) is a 
competitive equilibrium of economy 
E  (H, F , u, , Y, X, ) with H nite. Assume that all 
households are locally non-satiated. Then (x , y ) is Pareto 
optimal. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        21 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Welfare Theorems 
Welfare Theorems XIII  
Immediate corollary is an existence result: a competitive equilibrium 
must exist. 
Motivates many to look for the set of Pareto optimal allocations  
instead of explicitly characterizing competitive equilibria.  
Real power of the Theorem in dynamic macro models comes when we 
combine it with models that admit a representative household. 
Enables us to characterize the optimal growth allocation that 
maximizes the utility of the representative household and assert that 
this will correspond to a competitive equilibrium. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        32 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>65</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Technological Change III  
Dene balanced growth as a pattern of growth consistent with the 
Kaldor facts of constant capital-output ratio and capital share in 
national income. 
These two observations together also imply that the rental rate of 
return on capital, R (t), has to be constant, which, from (14),  implies 
that r (t) has to be constant. 
Again refer to an equilibrium path that satises these conditions as a 
balanced growth path (BGP). 
Balanced growth also requires that consumption and output grow at a 
constant rate. Euler equation 
c(t) 1 = (r (t)  ) . c (t) u (c (t)) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        66 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>70</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Technological Change VII 
Instead dene 
C (t)c (t)  A (t) L (t) 
c(t) .A (t) 
This normalized consumption level will remain constant along the 
BGP: 
 
c(t) c(t)  gc (t) c(t) 
1 = (r (t)    g ) .  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        71 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>Neoclassical Growth Model Environment 
The Budget Constraint  
The dierential equation 
a(t)=(r (t)  n) a (t)+ w (t)  c (t) 
is a ow constraint 
Not su cient as a proper budget constraint unless we impose a lower 
bound on assets. 
Three options:  
Lower bound on assets such as a (t)  0 for all t 
 1 
2 
3 Natural debt limit.  
No Ponzi Game Condition.  
The last two equivalent as long of the natural debt limit is specied 
properly. Let us focus on the latter. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 1
2
3
November 10 and 15, 2016.        39 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>83</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Comparative Dynamics 
Comparative Dynamics III  
c(t)
kgold 0k(t)
k*c(t)=0
k(t)=0
k**c**
c*
k
Figure: The dynamic response of capital and consumption to a decline in capital 
taxation from  to  ' &lt; . 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        84 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Neoclassical Growth Model Environment 
Preferences, Technology and Demographics II 
All members of the household supply their labor inelastically. 
Objective function of each household at t = 0: 
 
U (0)  exp ( (  n) t) u (c (t)) dt, (9) 
0 
where c (t)=consumption per capita at t, and =subjective discount 
rate, and eective discount rate is   n. 
Continues time analogue of  
=0 t
i ui (ci (t)).t
Objective function (9) embeds: 
Household is fully altruistic towards all of its future members, and 
makes allocations of consumption (among household members) 
cooperatively. 
Strict concavity of u () 
Thus each household member will have an equal consumption 
C (t)c (t)  L (t) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
Z
November 10 and 15, 2016.        34 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>62</slideno>
          <text>Dynamics Transitional Dynamics 
Neoclassical Growth Model in Discrete Time  
Economically, nothing is dierent in discrete time. 
Mathematically, a few details need to be sorted out. 
Sometimes discrete time will be more convenient to work with, and 
sometimes continuous time. 
See recitation for details of the discrete time model. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        63 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>75</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Transitional Dynamics with Technological Change  
c(t)
kgold 0k(t)
k(0)c(0)
c(0)c(t)=0
k(t)=0
k*c(0)c*
k
Figure: Transitional dynamics in the neoclassical growth model with technological 
change. 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        76 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Neoclassical Growth Model Environment 
Preferences, Technology and Demographics I 
Innite-horizon, continuous time. 
Representative household with instantaneous utility function 
u (c (t)) , (7) 
Assumption u (c) is strictly increasing, concave, twice continuously 
'dierentiable with derivatives u and u '', and satises the 
following Inada type assumptions: 
lim u ' (c)=  and lim u ' (c)= 0. 
c 0 c  
Suppose representative household represents set of identical  
households (normalized to 1).  
Each household has an instantaneous utility function given by (7).  
L (0)= 1 and  
L (t)= exp (nt) . (8)  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        33 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>.  
  
  Welfare Theorems 
Proof of First Welfare Theorem III 
Now summing over (3) and (4), we have 
 i  i if  p   x&gt; p   +  fy , (5) 
i H i H f F 
	 f  = p 	  i +  y , 
i H f F 
Second line uses the fact that the summations are nite, can change  
the order of summation, and that by denition of shares i H i = 1 f 
for all f . 

Finally, since y is prot-maximizing at prices p , we have that 
 f   f f fp   y p   yfor any y with y Yf for all f  F 
f F f F f F 
(6) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
 !
 !
n o
November 10 and 15, 2016.        24 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>61</slideno>
          <text>Dynamics Transitional Dynamics 
Local Stability Analysis II 
From (23),  f ' (k)   = , so the eigenvalues of this two-equation 
system are given by the values of  that solve the following quadratic 
form: 
  n   1 
det c f '' (k  ) = 0.0  u (c ) 
f '' (k) /u (c Since c ) &lt; 0, there are two real eigenvalues, one 
negative and one positive. 
Thus local analysis also leads to the same conclusion, but can only 
establish local stability. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
 !
November 10 and 15, 2016.        62 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>78</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change The Role of Policy 
The Role of Policy I  
Growth of per capita consumption and output per worker (per capita) 
are determined exogenously. 
But level of income, depends on 1/, , , n, and naturally the form 
of f (). 
Proximate causes of dierences in income per capita: here explain 
those dierences only in terms of preference and technology 
parameters. 
Link between proximate and potential fundamental causes: 
e.g. intertemporal elasticity of substitution and the discount rate can 
be as related to cultural or geographic factors. 
But an explanation for cross-country and over-time dierences in 
economic growth based on dierences or changes in preferences is 
unlikely to be satisfactory. 
More appealing: link incentives to accumulate physical capital (and 
human capital and technology) to the institutional environment. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        79 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>66</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Technological Change IV  
If r (t)  r , then c(t) /c (t)  gc is only possible if  
u (c (t))  u , i.e., if the elasticity of marginal utility of  
consumption, which determines the intertemporal elasticity of  
substitution, is asymptotically constant.  
Thus balanced growth is only consistent with utility functions that 
have asymptotically constant elasticity of marginal utility of 
consumption, so that the way that individuals substitute consumption 
today vs. consumption tomorrow does not change with the level of 
consumption (i.e., as the economy grows). 
Proposition	 Balanced growth in the neoclassical model requires that 
asymptotically (as t  ) all technological change is purely 
labor augmenting and the elasticity of intertemporal 
substitution, u (c (t)), tends to a constant u . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        67 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>77</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Example: CRRA and Cobb-Douglas  
One solvable case: CRRA (or even better log) preferences and 
Cobb-Douglas production function, given by 
F (K , AL)= K  (AL)1, so that 
f (k)= k . 
See recitation. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        78 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>69</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Technological Change 
Technological Change VI  
c(t)  C (t) /L (t) is per capita consumption. 
Refer to this model, with labor-augmenting technological change and 
CRRA preference as given by (30) as the canonical model 
Euler equation takes the simpler form: 
 
c(t) 1 =(r (t)  ) . (31)c(t)  
Steady-state equilibrium rst: since with technological progress there 
will be growth in per capita income, c(t) will grow. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        70 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>90</slideno>
          <text>Conclusions 
Conclusions  
Major contribution: open the black box of capital accumulation by 
specifying the preferences of consumers. 
Also by specifying individual preferences we can explicitly compare  
equilibrium and optimal growth.  
Paves the way for further analysis of capital accumulation, human  
capital and endogenous technological progress.  
Did our study of the neoclassical growth model generate new insights 
about the sources of cross-country income dierences and economic 
growth relative to the Solow growth model? Largely no. 
This model, by itself, does not enable us to answer questions about 
the fundamental causes of economic growth. 
But it claries the nature of the economic decisions so that we are in 
a better position to ask such questions. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        91 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Representative Household Representative Household 
Representative Household II  
If instead households are not identical but assume can model as if 
demand side generated by the optimization decision of a 
representative household: 
More realistic, but:  
The representative household will have positive, but not always a  
normative meaning.  
Models with heterogeneity: often not lead to behavior that can be  
represented as if generated by a representative household.  
1 
2 
Theorem	 (Debreu-Mantel-Sonnenschein Theorem) Let  &gt; 0 be a 
scalar and N &lt;  be a positive integer. Consider a set of  	 e'prices P =pRN : pj /pj '  for all j and jand any +
continuous function x : P  RN that satises WalrasLaw + 
and is homogeneous of degree 0. Then there exists an 
exchange economy with N commodities and H &lt;  
households, where the aggregate demand is given by x (p) 
over the set P. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 1
2
November 10 and 15, 2016.        7 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>87</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change A Quantitative Evaluation 
A Quantitative Evaluation V 
For dierences in  s across countries there is no obvious answer: 
popular approach: obtain estimates of  from the relative price of 
investment goods (as compared to consumption goods) 
data from the Penn World tables suggest there is a large amount of 
variation in the relative price of investment goods. 
E.g., countries with the highest relative price of investment goods 
have relative prices almost eight times as high as countries with the 
lowest relative price. 
Plausible value for  from the labor share in national income is 
 = 2/3, so equation (39) implies: 
Y ()  81/2  3.Y ( ' ) 
Thus, even very large dierences in taxes or distortions are unlikely to 
account for the large dierences in income per capita that we observe. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        88 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Welfare Theorems 
Welfare Theorems IX  
Proof of the First Welfare Theorem based on two intuitive ideas. 
If another allocation Pareto dominates the competitive equilibrium, 
then it must be non-aordable in the competitive equilibrium. 
1 
2 Prot-maximization implies that any competitive equilibrium already 
contains the maximal set of aordable allocations. 
Note it makes no convexity assumption. 
Also highlights the importance of the feature that the relevant sums 
exist and are nite. 
Otherwise, the last step would lead to the conclusion that  &lt;  . 
That these sums exist followed from two assumptions: niteness of 
the number of individuals and non-satiation. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 1
2
November 10 and 15, 2016.        26 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Representative Household Representative Household 
Challenges to the Representative Household  
An economy admits a representative household if preference side can 
be represented as if a single household made the aggregate 
consumption and saving decisions subject to a single budget 
constraint. 
This description concerning a representative household is purely  
positive  
Stronger notion of normative representative household: if we can 
also use the utility function of the representative household for welfare 
comparisons. 
Simplest case that will lead to the existence of a representative  
household: suppose each household is identical.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        6 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>51</slideno>
          <text>Steady-State Equilibrium Steady State 
Steady-State Equilibrium I 
Steady-state equilibrium is dened as an equilibrium path in which 
capital-labor ratio, consumption and output are constant, thus: 
c(t)= 0. 
From (22),  as long as f (k) &gt; 0, irrespective of the exact utility 
function, we must have a capital-labor ratio k such that 
f ' (k )=  + . (23) 
Pins down the steady-state capital-labor ratio only as a function of 
the production function, the discount rate and the depreciation rate. 
Modied golden rule: level of the capital stock that does not 
maximize steady-state consumption, because earlier consumption is 
preferred to later consumption. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        52 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>85</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change A Quantitative Evaluation 
A Quantitative Evaluation II 
The accumulation equation is 
Kj = Ij  Kj . 
The only dierence across countries is in the budget constraint for the 
representative household, 
(1 + j ) Ij + Cj  Yj , (38) 
j is the tax on investment: varies across countries because of policies 
or dierences in institutions/property rights enforcement. 
1 + j is also the relative price of investment goods (relative to 
consumption goods): one unit of consumption goods can only be 
transformed into 1/ (1 + j ) units of investment goods. 
The right-hand side variable of (38) is still Yj : assumes that j Ij is 
wasted, rather than simply redistributed to some other agents. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        86 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>58</slideno>
          <text>Dynamics Transitional Dynamics 
Transitional Dynamics: Su ciency 
Why is the stable arm unique? 
Proposition	 In the neoclassical growth model described above, with 
Assumptions 1, 2, assumptions on utility above and 
Assumption 4', there exists a unique equilibrium path 
starting from any k (0) &gt; 0 and converging to the unique 
steady-state (k , c ) with k given by (23).  Moreover, if 
k (0) &lt; k, then k (t)  k and c (t)  c , whereas if 
k (0) &gt; k, then k (t)  k and c (t)  c . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 Three dierent (complementary) lines of analysis
1Su ciency Theorem
2Global Stability Analysis
3Local Stability Analysis
Su ciency Theorem : solution starting in c(0)and limiting to the
steady state satises the necessary and su cient conditions, and thus
unique solution to household problem and unique equilibrium.1
2
3
November 10 and 15, 2016.        59 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Neoclassical Growth Model Environment 
Preferences, Technology and Demographics V 
Denote asset holdings of the representative household at time t by 
A (t). Then, 
A (t)= r (t) A (t)+ w (t) L (t)  c (t) L (t) 
r (t) is the risk-free market ow rate of return on assets, and 
w (t) L (t) is the ow of labor income earnings of the household. 
Dening per capita assets as 
A (t)a (t)  ,L (t) 
we obtain: 
a(t)=(r (t)  n) a (t)+ w (t)  c (t) . (13) 
Household assets can consist of capital stock, K (t), which they rent 
to rms and government bonds, B (t). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        37 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>84</slideno>
          <text>Hjis the exogenously given stock of eective labor (human capital). 
Y K1AHTechnological Change A Quantitative Evaluation 
A Quantitative Evaluation I  
Does the neoclassical growth model help us understand/account for 
cross-country growth or income dierences? Not growth dierences, 
since all countries have the same growth rate. What about income 
dierences? 
Consider a world consisting of a collection J of closed neoclassical 
economies (with the caveats of ignoring technological, trade and 
nancial linkages across countries 
Each country j  J admits a representative household with identical 
preferences and no population growth, 
C 1  1jexp (t) dt. (36) 
0 1   
Equation (36) imposes that all countries have the same discount rate 
. 
All countries also have access to the same production technology  
given by the Cobb-Douglas production function  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
j 
Z
Hjis the exogenously given stock of eective labor (human capital).
November 10 and 15, 2016.        85 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>Characterization of Equilibrium Denition of Equilibrium 
Denition of Equilibrium 
Denition	 A competitive equilibrium of the Ramsey economy consists 
of paths [C (t) , K (t) , w (t) , R (t)] 
=0, such that the t
representative household maximizes its utility given initial 
capital stock K (0) and the time path of prices 
[w (t) , R (t)] 
=0, and all markets clear. t
Notice refers to the entire path of quantities and prices, not just 
steady-state equilibrium. 
Denition	 A competitive equilibrium of the Ramsey economy consists 
of paths [c (t) , k (t) , w (t) , R (t)] 
=0, such that the t
representative household maximizes (9) subject to (13) and 
(15) given initial capital-labor ratio k (0), factor prices 
[w (t) , R (t)] 
=0 as in (11) and (12),  and the rate of return t
on assets r (t) given by (14).  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        42 / 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>81</slideno>
          <text>Technological Change Comparative Dynamics 
Comparative Dynamics I 
Comparative statics: changes in steady state in response to changes 
in parameters. 
Comparative dynamics look at how the entire equilibrium path of 
variables changes in response to a change in policy or parameters. 
Look at the eect of a change in tax on capital (or discount rate ) 
Consider the neoclassical growth in steady state (k , c ). 
Tax declines to  ' &lt; . 
From Propositions above, after the change there exists a unique 
steady state equilibrium that is saddle path stable.  
). 
 Let this steady state be denoted by (k , c  
&lt; , k &gt; k 
Since  ' while the equilibrium growth rate will remain 
unchanged. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lectures 5 and 6 
November 10 and 15, 2016.        82 / 92</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Overlapping Generations (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-452-economic-growth-fall-2016/resources/mit14_452f16_lec7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>43</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Unfunded Social Security 
Unfunded Social Security II  
Only s (t) rather than s (t) plus d (t) as in the funded  
scheme goes into capital accumulation.  
It is possible that s (t) will change in order to compensate, but such 
an osetting change does not typically take place. 
Thus unfunded Social Security reduces capital accumulation. 
Discouraging capital accumulation can have negative consequences 
for growth and welfare. 
In fact, empirical evidence suggests that there are many societies in 
which the level of capital accumulation is suboptimally low. 
But here reducing aggregate savings may be good when the economy 
exhibits dynamic ine ciency. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 44 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>46</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
14.452 Economic Growth
 Fall 2016
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Special Cases 
Restrictions on Utility and Production Functions I  
Suppose that the utility functions take the familiar CRRA form: 
  1 1 c1 (t) 1 c2 (t + 1) 1U (t)= +  , (10)1   1  
where  &gt; 0 and   (0, 1). 
Technology is Cobb-Douglas, 
f (k)= k 
The rest of the environment is as described above. 
The CRRA utility simplies the rst-order condition for consumer 
optimization,  
c2 (t + 1) 1/ =(R (t + 1)) . c1 (t) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 18 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>Canonical OLG Model Canonical Model 
Canonical Model IV  
Proposition	 In the canonical overlapping generations model with log 
preferences and Cobb-Douglas technology, there exists a 
unique steady state, with capital-labor ratio k given by 
(20).  Starting with any k (0)  (0, k), equilibrium dynamics 
are such that k (t)  k, and starting with any k' (0) &gt; k , 
equilibrium dynamics involve k (t)  k . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 28 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Fully Funded Social Security 
Fully Funded Social Security III 
Proposition	 Consider a fully funded Social Security system in the  
above-described environment whereby the government  
collects d (t) from young individuals at date t.  
1 Suppose that s (t)  0 for all t. If given the feasible 
 sequence {d (t)}=0 of Social Security payments, the t utility-maximizing sequence of savings {s (t)}=0 ist
such that s (t) &gt; 0 for all t, then the set of competitive 
equilibria without Social Security are the set of 
competitive equilibria with Social Security. 
2 Without the constraint s (t)  0, given any feasible 
 sequence {d (t)}=0 of Social Security payments, the t 
set of competitive equilibria without Social Security are 
the set of competitive equilibria with Social Security. 
Moreover, even when there is the restriction that s (t)  0, a funded 
Social Security program cannot lead to the Pareto improvement. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 42 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Special Cases 
Restrictions on Utility and Production Functions VI  
Proposition	 In the overlapping-generations model with two-period lived 
households, Cobb-Douglas technology and CRRA 
preferences, there exists a unique steady-state equilibrium 
with the capital-labor ratio k given by (15),  this 
steady-state equilibrium is globally stable for all k (0) &gt; 0. 
In this particular (well-behaved) case, equilibrium dynamics are very 
similar to the basic Solow model 
Figure shows that convergence to the unique steady-state  
capital-labor ratio, k, is monotonic.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 23 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Overaccumulation and Pareto Optimality 
Overaccumulation V  
Now if k &gt; kgold , then c /k &lt; 0: reducing savings can increase 
(total) consumption for everybody. 
More specically, consider the following variation starting from steady 
state at time T : change next period s capital stock by k, where 
k &gt; 0, and from then on, we immediately move to a new steady 
state (clearly feasible) with the following consumption changes: 
c (T )=(1 + n) k &gt; 0 
c (t)=  f ' (k k)  (1 + n) k for all t &gt; T 
The rst expression reects the direct increase in consumption due to 
the decrease in savings. 
In addition, since k &gt; kgold , for small enough k,  
f ' (k k)  (1 + n) &lt; 0, thus c (t) &gt; 0 for all t  T .  
The increase in consumption for each generation can be allocated  
equally during the two periods of their lives, thus necessarily  
increasing the utility of all generations.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 34 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Consumption Decisions 
Consumption Decisions I  
Savings by an individual of generation t, s (t), is determined as a 
solution to 
max 
c1 (t),c2 (t+1),s(t) u (c1 (t)) + u (c2 (t + 1)) 
subject to 
c1 (t) + s (t)  w (t) 
and 
c2 (t + 1)  R (t + 1) s (t) , 
Old individuals rent their savings of time t as capital to rms at time 
t + 1, and receive gross rate of return R (t + 1)= 1 + r (t + 1) 
Second constraint incorporates notion that individuals only spend 
money on their own end of life consumption (no altruism or bequest 
motive). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 12 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Growth with Overlapping Generations Problems of Innity 
Problems of Innity I  
Static economy with countably innite number of households, i  N 
Countably innite number of commodities, j  N. 
All households behave competitively (alternatively, there are M  
households of each type, M is a large number).  
Household i has preferences: 
ui = cii + ci 
i +1, 
icj denotes the consumption of the jth type of commodity by  
household i.  
Endowment vector  of the economy: each household has one unit 
endowment of the commodity with the same index as its index. 
Choose the price of the rst commodity as the numeraire, i.e., p0 = 1. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 3 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Growth with Overlapping Generations Problems of Innity 
Proof of Proposition 
Consider the following reallocation of : endowment of household 
i  1 is given to household i  1. 
At the new endowment vector ~ = 0 has one unit of good , household i  
j = 0 and one unit of good j = 1.  
Other households i have one unit of good i + 1. 
At the price vector p, household 0 has a budget set 
c00 + c1  2,1 
0 0thus chooses c= c= 1.0 1 
All other households have budget sets given by 
cii + cii 
+1  1, 
Thus it is optimal for each household i &gt; 0 to consume one unit of 
the good ci 
i +1 
Thus xis a competitive equilibrium. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 8 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Overaccumulation and Pareto Optimality 
Dynamic Ine ciency 
However, issues of dynamic and e ciency are still present. 
In particular, competitive equilibrium is Pareto suboptimal when 
k &gt; kgold , since reducing saving can increase consumption for every 
generation, where kgold is dened as 
f ' (kgold )= 1 + n. 
In steady state 
1 f (k )  (1 + n)k = c1 +(1 + n)c2 
  c , 
First line follows by national income accounting, and second denes 
 c . Therefore 
 c 
k = f ' (k )  (1 + n) &lt; 0 i k &gt; kgold . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 32 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Consumption Decisions 
Consumption Decisions III  
s : R2  R is strictly increasing in its rst argument and may be + 
increasing or decreasing in its second argument. 
Total savings in the economy will be equal to 
S (t)= s (t) L (t) , 
L (t) denotes the size of generation t, who are saving for time t + 1. 
Since capital depreciates fully after use and all new savings are  
invested in capital,  
K (t + 1)= L (t) s (w (t) , R (t + 1)) . (7) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 14 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Consumption Decisions 
Consumption Decisions II  
No need to introduce s (t)  0, since negative savings would violate 
second-period budget constraint (given c2 (t + 1)  0). 
Since u () is strictly increasing, both constraints will hold as  
equalities.  
Thus rst-order condition for a maximum can be written in the  
familiar form of the consumption Euler equation,  
u ' (c1 (t)) = R (t + 1) u ' (c2 (t + 1)) . (5) 
Problem of each individual is strictly concave, so this Euler equation 
is su cient. 
Solving for consumption and thus for savings, 
s (t)= s (w (t) , R (t + 1)) , (6) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 13 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Overaccumulation and Pareto Optimality 
Overaccumulation IV  
consumption
savings rate(1s)f(k*gold)
s*gold 1 0
Figure: The golden rule level of savings rate, which maximizes steady-state 
consumption. 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 33 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>44</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Unfunded Social Security 
Unfunded Social Security III 
Proposition	 Consider the above-described overlapping generations 
economy and suppose that the decentralized competitive 
equilibrium is dynamically ine cient. Then there exists a 
feasible sequence of unfunded Social Security payments 
{d (t)}=0 which will lead to a competitive equilibrium t
starting from any date t that Pareto dominates the 
competitive equilibrium without Social Security. 
Similar to way in which the Pareto optimal allocation was 
decentralized in the example economy above. 
Social Security is transferring resources from future generations to 
initial old generation. 
But with no dynamic ine ciency, any transfer of resources (and any 
unfunded Social Security program) would make some future 
generation worse-o. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 45 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Overaccumulation and Pareto Optimality 
Overaccumulation II  

 
Substituting from (1), this implies: 
t
S (u (c1 (t)) + u (c2 (t + 1))) 
t=0 
subject to the resource constraint 
F (K (t) , L (t)) = K (t + 1)+ L (t) c1 (t)+ L (t  1) c2 (t) . 
Dividing this by L (t) and using (2),  
c2 (t) f (k (t)) = (1 + n) k (t + 1)+ c1 (t)+ .1 + n 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 30 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Canonical OLG Model Canonical Model 
45
k*
k* k(0) k(0) 0k(t+1)
k(t)
Figure: Equilibrium dynamics in the canonical overlapping generations model. 
Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission .
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 27 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 1 / 47 
14.452 Economic Growth: Lecture 7, Overlapping
Generations
Daron Acemoglu
MIT
November 15, 2016.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Growth with Overlapping Generations Problems of Innity 
Problems of Innity III  
However, this competitive equilibrium is not Pareto optimal. Consider 
alternative allocation, x: 
Household i = 0 consumes its own endowment and that of household 1. 
All other households, indexed i &gt; 0, consume the endowment of than 
neighboring household, i + 1. 
All households with i &gt; 0 are as well o as in the competitive 
equilibrium (p, x). 
Individual i = 0 is strictly better-o. 
Proposition	 In the above-described economy, the competitive equilibrium 
at (p, x) is not Pareto optimal. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 5 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Growth with Overlapping Generations Growth with Overlapping Generations 
Growth with Overlapping Generations  
In many situations, the assumption of a representative household is 
not appropriate because 
1 
2 households do not have an innite planning horizon  
new households arrive (or are born) over time.  
New economic interactions: decisions made by older generations 
will aect the prices faced by younger generations . 
Overlapping generations models 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 Capture potential interaction of dierent generations of individuals in  
the marketplace;  
Provide tractable alternative to innite-horizon representative agent  
models;  
Some key implications dierent from neoclassical growth model;  
Dynamics in some special cases quite similar to Solow model rather  
than the neoclassical model;  
Generate new insights about the role of national debt and Social  
Security in the economy.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 2 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Environment 
Demographics, Preferences and Technology I  
Exponential population growth,  
L (t)=(1 + n)tL (0) . (2)  
Production side same as before: competitive rms, constant returns to 
scale aggregate production function, satisfying Assumptions 1 and 2: 
Y (t)= F (K (t) , L (t)) . 
Factor markets are competitive. 
Individuals can only work in the rst period and supply one unit of 
labor inelastically, earning w (t). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 10 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Equilibrium 
Equilibrium II 
Now substituting for R (t + 1) and w (t) from (3) and (4), 
s (f (k (t))  k (t) f ' (k (t)) , f ' (k (t + 1))) k (t + 1)= (8)1 + n 
This is the fundamental law of motion of the overlapping generations 
economy. 
A steady state is given by a solution to this equation such that 
k (t + 1)= k (t)= k, i.e., 
s (f (k)  kf ' (k) , f ' (k)) k = (9)1 + n 
Since the savings function s (, ) can take any form, the dierence 
equation (8) can lead to quite complicated dynamics, and multiple 
steady states are possible. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 16 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Special Cases 
Restrictions on Utility and Production Functions IV 
Equation (8) implies 
s(t)k (t + 1)= (13)(1 + n) 
w (t) =(1 + n) (t + 1) , 
Or more explicitly, 
f (k (t))  k (t) f ' (k (t)) k (t + 1)= (14)(1)/(1 + n)[1 + 1/f ' (k(t + 1)) ] 
The steady state then involves a solution to the following implicit 
equation: 
f (k)  kf ' (k)k = . 
(1 + n)[1 + 1/f '(k)(1)/ ] 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 21 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Fully Funded Social Security 
Fully Funded Social Security II 
No longer the case that individuals will always choose s (t) &gt; 0. 
As long as s (t) is free, whatever {d (t)}=0, the competitive t
equilibrium applies.  
When s (t)  0 is imposed as a constraint, competitive equilibrium  
 applies if given {d (t)}=0, privately-optimal {s (t)}=0 is such that t t
s (t) &gt; 0 for all t. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 41 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Growth with Overlapping Generations Problems of Innity 
Problems of Innity V  

Second Welfare Theorem did not assume  
=0 pj j &lt; .j 
Instead, it used convexity of preferences, consumption sets and 
production possibilities sets. 
This exchange economy has convex preferences and convex  
consumption sets:  
Pareto optima must be decentralizable by some redistribution of 
endowments. 
Proposition	 In the above-described economy, there exists a reallocation 
of the endowment vector  to ~, and an associated 
competitive equilibrium (p, x) that is Pareto optimal where x
is as described above, and pis such that pj = 1 for all j  N. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 7 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Growth with Overlapping Generations Problems of Innity 
Problems of Innity IV  
Source of the problem must be related to the innite number of  
commodities.  
Extended version of the First Welfare Theorem covers innite number 
of commodities, but only assuming  
j =0 pj j &lt;  (written with the 
aggregate endowment j ). 

Here theonly endowment is labor, and thus p = 1 for all j  N, so jthat j  
=0 pj j =  (why?). 
This abstract economy is isomorphic to the baseline overlapping 
generations model. 
The Pareto suboptimality in this economy will be the source of  
potential ine ciencies in overlapping generations model.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 6 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Canonical OLG Model Canonical Model 
Canonical Model II  
Consumption Euler equation:  
c2 (t + 1)  = R (t + 1)c1 (t) 
Savings should satisfy the equation 
 s (t)= w (t) , (19)1 +  
Constant saving rate, equal to / (1 + ), out of labor income for 
each individual. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 25 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Role of Social Security 
Role of Social Security in Capital Accumulation 
Social Security as a way of dealing with overaccumulation 
Fully-funded system: young make contributions to the Social Security 
system and their contributions are paid back to them in their old age. 
Unfunded system or a pay-as-you-go: transfers from the young  
directly go to the current old.  
Pay-as-you-go (unfunded) Social Security discourages aggregate  
savings.  
With dynamic ine ciency, discouraging savings may lead to a Pareto 
improvement. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 39 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Fully Funded Social Security 
Fully Funded Social Security I 
Government at date t raises some amount d (t) from the young, 
funds are invested in capital stock, and pays workers when old 
R (t + 1) d (t). 
Thus individual maximization problem is, 
max 
c1 (t),c2 (t+1),s(t) u (c1 (t)) + u (c2 (t + 1)) 
subject to 
c1 (t) + s (t) + d (t)  w (t) 
and 
c2 (t + 1)  R (t + 1) (s (t) + d (t)) , 
for a given choice of d (t) by the government. 
Notice that now the total amount invested in capital accumulation is 
s (t)+ d (t)=(1 + n) k (t + 1). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 40 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Overaccumulation and Pareto Optimality 
Interpretation  
Intuition for dynamic ine ciency: 
Individuals who live at time t face prices determined by the capital 
stock with which they are working. 
Pecuniary externality from the actions of previous generations aecting 
welfare of current generation. 
Pecuniary externalities typically second-order and do not matter for 
welfare. 
But not when an innite stream of newborn agents joining the 
economy are aected. 
It is possible to rearrange in a way that these pecuniary externalities 
can be exploited. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 37 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Overaccumulation and Pareto Optimality 
Overaccumulation III  
Social planner s maximization problem then implies the following 
rst-order necessary condition: 
u ' (c1 (t)) = f ' (k (t + 1)) u ' (c2 (t + 1)) . 
Since R (t + 1)= f ' (k (t + 1)), this is identical to (5). 
Not surprising: allocate consumption of a given individual in exactly 
the same way as the individual himself would do. 
No market failures in the over-time allocation of consumption at 
given prices. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 31 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Unfunded Social Security 
Unfunded Social Security I  
Government collects d (t) from the young at time t and distributes to 
the current old with per capita transfer b (t)=(1 + n) d (t) 
Individual maximization problem becomes 
max 
c1 (t),c2 (t+1),s(t) u (c1 (t)) + u (c2 (t + 1)) 
subject to 
c1 (t) + s (t) + d (t)  w (t) 
and 
c2 (t + 1)  R (t + 1) s (t)+(1 + n) d (t + 1) , 
for a given feasible sequence of Social Security payment levels 
{d (t)}t=0. 
Rate of return on Social Security payments is n rather than 
r (t + 1)= R (t + 1)  1, because unfunded Social Security is a pure 
transfer system. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 43 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Growth with Overlapping Generations Problems of Innity 
Problems of Innity II  
Proposition	 In the above-described economy, the price vector psuch that 
pj = 1 for all j  N is a competitive equilibrium price vector 
and induces an equilibrium with no trade, denoted by x. 
Proof: 
At p, each household has income equal to 1. 
Therefore, the budget constraint of household i can be written as 
cii + cii 
+1  1. 
This implies that consuming own endowment is optimal for each 
household, 
Thus pand no trade, x, constitute a competitive equilibrium. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 4 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Equilibrium 
Equilibrium I 
Denition	 A competitive equilibrium can be represented by a sequence 
of aggregate capital stocks, individual consumption and 
factor prices, 
{K (t) , c1 (t) , c2 (t) , R (t) , w (t)}=0, such that the factor tprice sequence {R (t) , w (t)}=0 is given by (3) and (4), tindividual consumption decisions {c1 (t) , c2 (t)}=0 are t
given by (5) and (6), and the aggregate capital stock, 
{K (t)}=0, evolves according to (7). t
Steady-state equilibrium dened as usual: an equilibrium in which 
k  K /L is constant. 
To characterize the equilibrium, divide (7) by  
L(t + 1) = (1 + n) L (t),  
s (w (t) , R (t + 1)) k (t + 1)=	 .1 + n 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 15 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>45</slideno>
          <text>Conclusions Conclusions 
Conclusions 
Overlapping generations of the more realistic than innity-lived 
representative agents. 
Models with overlapping generations fall outside the scope of the 
First Welfare Theorem: 
they were partly motivated by the possibility of Pareto suboptimal 
allocations. 
Equilibria may be dynamically ine cient and feature 
overaccumulation: unfunded Social Security can ameliorate the 
problem. 
Declining path of labor income important for overaccumulation, and 
what matters is not nite horizons but arrival of new individuals. 
Overaccumulation and Pareto suboptimality: pecuniary externalities 
created on individuals that are not yet in the marketplace. 
Not overemhasize dynamic ine ciency: major question of economic 
growth is why so many countries have so little capital. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 46 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Overaccumulation and Pareto Optimality 
Further Intuition  
Complementary intuition: 
Dynamic ine ciency arises from overaccumulation. 
Results from current young generation needs to save for old age. 
However, the more they save, the lower is the rate of return and may 
encourage to save even more. 
Eect on future rate of return to capital is a pecuniary externality on 
next generation 
If alternative ways of providing consumption to individuals in old age 
were introduced, overaccumulation could be ameliorated. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 38 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Overaccumulation and Pareto Optimality 
Pareto Optimality and Suboptimality in the OLG Model  
Proposition	 In the baseline overlapping-generations economy, the 
competitive equilibrium is not necessarily Pareto optimal. 
More specically, whenever r &lt; n and the economy is 
dynamically ine cient, it is possible to reduce the capital 
stock starting from the competitive steady state and increase 
the consumption level of all generations. 
Pareto ine ciency of the competitive equilibrium is the other side of 
the coin of dynamic ine ciency. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 36 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Special Cases 
Restrictions on Utility and Production Functions V  
Now using the Cobb-Douglas formula, steady state is the solution to 
the equation 
    (1)/(1 + n)1 + 1/(k )1= (1  )(k )1 . (15) 
For simplicity, dene R (k)1 as the marginal product of  
capital in steady-state, in which case, (15) can be rewritten as  
  1   (1)/(1 + n)1 + 1/ (R ) = R . (16) 
Steady-state value of R, and thus k, can now be determined from 
equation (16),  which always has a unique solution. 
To investigate the stability, substitute for the Cobb-Douglas  
production function in (14)  
(1  ) k (t)k (t + 1)= . (17)(1)/(1 + n)[1 + 1/ (k(t + 1)1) ] 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 22 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Canonical OLG Model Canonical Model 
Canonical Model I  
Even the model with CRRA utility and Cobb-Douglas production  
function is relatively messy.  
Many of the applications use log preferences ( = 1). 
Income and substitution eects exactly cancel each othe: changes in 
the interest rate (and thus in the capital-labor ratio of the economy) 
have no eect on the saving rate. 
Structure of the equilibrium is essentially identical to the basic Solow 
model. 
Utility of the household and generation t is, 
U (t)= log c1 (t)+  log c2 (t + 1) , (18) 
  (0, 1) (even though   1 could be allowed). 
Again f (k)= k . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 24 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Overaccumulation and Pareto Optimality 
Overaccumulation I  
Compare the overlapping-generations equilibrium to the choice of a 
social planner wishing to maximize a weighted average of all 
generationsutilities. 
Suppose that the social planner maximizes 
t 
SU (t) 
t=0 
S is the discount factor of the social planner, which reects how she 
values the utilities of dierent generations. 
 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 29 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Special Cases 
Restrictions on Utility and Production Functions III 
The impact of factor prices on savings is summarized by the following 
and derivatives:  
s (t) 1  sw  =  (0, 1) ,w (t)  (t + 1)  s (t) 1   1/ s (t)sR  = (R (t + 1)) . R (t + 1)   (t + 1) 
Since  (t + 1) &gt; 1, we also have that 0 &lt; sw &lt; 1. 
Moreover, in this case sR &gt; 0 if  &lt; 1, sR &lt; 0 if  &gt; 1, and sR = 0 if 
 = 1. 
Reects counteracting inuences of income and substitution eects. 
The substitution eects wins out when  &lt; 1, and loses out when 
 &gt; 1. 
Case of  = 1 (log preferences) is of special importance, as the 
income and substitution eects cancel out exactly. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 20 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Special Cases 
Restrictions on Utility and Production Functions II 
This Euler equation can be alternatively expressed in terms of savings 
as 
 1 s (t)R (t + 1)= (w (t)  s (t)) , (11) 
Gives the following equation for the saving rate: 
w (t)s (t) =  (t + 1) , (12) 
where 
(1)/ (t + 1)  [1 + 1/R (t + 1) ] &gt; 1, 
Ensures that savings are always less than earnings. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 19 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Environment 
The Baseline Overlapping Generations Model  
Time is discrete and runs to innity. 
Each individual lives for two periods. 
Individuals born at time t live for dates t and t + 1. 
Assume a general (separable) utility function for individuals born at 
date t, 
U (t)= u (c1 (t)) + u (c2 (t + 1)) , (1) 
u : R+  R satises the usual Assumptions on utility. 
c1 (t): consumption of the individual born at t when young (at date 
t). 
c2 (t + 1): consumption when old (at date t + 1). 
  (0, 1) is the discount factor. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 9 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Environment 
Demographics, Preferences and Technology II  
Assume that  = 1. 
k  K /L, f (k)  F (k, 1), and the (gross) rate of return to saving, 
which equals the rental rate of capital, is 
1 + r (t) = R (t)= f ' (k (t)) , (3) 
As usual, the wage rate is  
w (t)= f (k (t))  k (t) f ' (k (t)) . (4)  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 11 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Overaccumulation and Policy Overaccumulation and Pareto Optimality 
Overaccumulation VI  
If k &gt; kgold , the economy is referred to as dynamically ine cient it 
involves overaccumulation. 
Another way of expressing dynamic ine ciency is that 
 r &lt; n, 
Recall in innite-horizon Ramsey economy, transversality condition 
required that r &gt; g + n. 
Dynamic ine ciency arises because of the heterogeneity inherent in 
the overlapping generations model, which removes the transversality 
condition. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 35 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>The Baseline OLG Model Equilibrium 
Equilibrium III  
Possible patterns: 
k(t)k(t+1)
k2*k3*k4*k1* 045
k5*
Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 17 / 47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Canonical OLG Model Canonical Model 
Canonical Model III 
Combining this with the capital accumulation equation (8), 
s(t)k (t + 1)= (1 + n) 
w (t) = (1 + n)(1 + ) 
 (1  ) [k(t)]=(1 + n)(1 + ) , 
Second line uses (19) and last uses that, given competitive factor 
markets, w (t)=(1  ) [k(t)]. 
There exists a unique steady state with 
  1  (1  ) 1 
k = . (20)(1 + n)(1 + )
Equilibrium dynamics are identical to those of the basic Solow model 
and monotonically converge to k . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 7 November 15, 2016. 26 / 47</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Technology Diffusion, Trade, and World Growth (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-452-economic-growth-fall-2016/resources/mit14_452f16_lec11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Technology Diusion and Endogenous Growth
Technology Diusion: Endogenous World Growth Rate I
More satisfactory to derive the world growth rate from the technology
adoption and R&amp;D activities of each country.
Modeling di culties:
Degree of interaction among countries is now greater.
More care needed so that the world economy grows at a constant
endogenous rate, while there are still forces that ensure relatively
similar growth rates across countries. Modeling choice:
Countries grow at permanently dierent long run rates, e.g. to
approximate long-run growth dierences of the past 200 or 500 years
Countries grow at similar rates, e.g. like the past 60 years or so.
Since long-run dierences emerge straightforwardly in many models,
focus here on forces that will keep countries growing at similar rates.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        13 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Productivity Dierences and Technology
Review: Productivity and Technology Dierences within
Narrow Sectors I
Longitudinal micro-data studies (often for manufacturing): even
within a narrow sector there are signicant and persistent productivity
dierences across plants.
Little consensus on the causes.
Correlation between plant productivity and plant or rm size, various
measures of technology (in particular IT technology), capital intensity,
the skill level of the workforce.
But these correlations cannot be taken to be causal.
But technology dierences appear to be an important factor.
A key determinant seems to be the skill level of the workforce, though
adoption of new technology does not typically lead to a signicant
change in employment structure.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        4 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Technology Diusion and Endogenous Growth
Technology Diusion: Endogenous World Growth Rate II
Replace the world growth equation (4) with:
1N(t)=J
JNj(t). (6)
j=1
N(t)is no longer the world technology frontier : it represents
average technology in the world, so Nj(t)&gt;N(t)for at least some j.
Disadvantage of the formulation: contribution of each country to the
world technology is the same. But qualitative results here do not
depend on this.
Main result: pattern of cross-country growth will be similar to that in
the previous model, but the growth rate of the world economy, g, will
be endogenous, resulting from the investments in technologies made
by rms in each country.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        14 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Technology Diusion and Endogenous Growth
Basics IV
Intermediates produced competitively.
In each country one unit of capital produces one unit of any of the
intermediates that the country is capable of producing.
Free entry to the production of intermediates.
Hence prices of all intermediates
pj(t)=rj(t), (12)
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        24 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Introduction
Introduction II
Technology adoption involves many challenging features:
1Even within a single country, we observe considerable dierences in the
technologies used by dierent rms.
2It is di cult to explain how in the globalized world some countries may
fail to import and use technologies.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        3 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Technology Diusion and Endogenous Growth
Basics I
Jof small countries, j=1, ..., J.
Continuum of intermediate products n2[0,N].
Two nal products used for consumption and investment.
Free trade in intermediate goods and no trade in nal products or
assets (rule out international borrowing and lending).
Each country has constant population normalized to 1.
Country jwill be dened by (mj,rj,zj),vary across countries but
constant over time:
m: indicator of how advanced the technology of the country is,
r: rate of time preference, and
z: measure the eect of policies and institutions on the incentives to
invest.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        21 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Technology Diusion and Endogenous Growth
Discussion of Proposition: Steady State Equilibrium II
Consider special case mj=mfor all jandjhas lower zjandrjthan
the rest of the world.
Then (24) implies jwill tend to accumulate more capital than others.
But (25) implies this cannot go on forever and j, being richer than the
world average, will have a lower rate of return on capital.
This will compensate the greater incentive to accumulate and
accumulation in jconverges back to the rate of the world.
Each country is smallrelative to the world, but has market power in
the goods that it supplies.
Hence when a country accumulates faster it will face worsening terms
of trades .
This will reduce the income of the country that is accumulating faster.
Dynamic eects: (12) shows it also experiences a decline in the rate of
return the capital and in the interest rate, that slows down its rate of
capital accumulation.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        38 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Technology Diusion and Endogenous Growth
Basics III
Armington preferences or technology: Nintermediates partitioned
such that each intermediate can only be produced by one country.
While each country is small in import markets, it will aect its own
terms of trades by the amount of the goods it exports.
Denoting the measure of goods produced by country jbymj:
J
mj=N. (11)
j=1
A higher level of mjimplies country jhas the technology to produce a
larger variety of intermediates.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        23 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>Conclusions Conclusions
Main Lessons I
1We can make considerable progress in understanding technology and
productivity dierences across nations by positing a slow process of
technology transfer across countries, where technology in the less
advanced economies catches up only slowly to the frontier.
2An important aspect of models of international technology diusion is
that it necessitates an analysis of the world equilibrium, not simply
the equilibrium of each country on its own.
3An important element of models of technology diusion is that they
create a built-in advantage for countries (or rms) that are relatively
behind, which ensures that dierences between poor and rich nations
will be in terms of income level not growth rates.
4Similar issues, arise because of trade interactions. Ricardian trade
leads to similar dynamics to those obtained from ecological
interdependencies.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        41 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
14.452 Economic Growth: Lecture 11, Technology
Diusion, Trade and World Growth
Daron Acemoglu
MIT
December 6, 2016.
December 6, 2016.        1 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Productivity Dierences and Technology
Review: Productivity and Technology Dierences within
Narrow Sectors II
Productivity dierences appear to be related to the entry of new and
more productive plants and the exit of less productive plants (recall
Schumpeterian models).
But entry and exit account for only about 25% of average TFP
growth, with the remaining accounted for by continuing plants.
Thus models in which rms continually invest in technology and
productivity are important for understanding dierences across rms
and plants and also across countries.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        5 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Technology Diusion and Endogenous Growth
Discussion of Proposition: Steady State Equilibrium IV
Equation (29) shows similar implications, except that:
1the role of the labor-augmenting technologies is played by the
technological capabilities of the country, which determine the range of
goods in which it has a comparative advantage;
2the role of the saving rate is played by the discount rate rjand the
policy parameter aecting the distortions on the production of
investment goods, zj;
3instead of the share of capital in national income, the elasticity of
substitution between intermediates and the degree of trade openness
aects how spread out the world income distribution is.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        40 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Technology Diusion and Endogenous Growth
Trade, Specialization and the World Income Distribution
Similar interdependences because of trade.
Model based on Acemoglu and Ventura (2001). Ricardian features:
each country will specialize in subset of available goods and aect
their prices.
Hence each country s terms of trade will be endogenous and depend
on the rate at which it accumulates capital.
Model can allow for dierences in discount (and saving) rates and has
richer comparative static results.
Also now exhibit endogenous growth, determined by the investment
decisions of all countries.
International trade (without any technological spillovers) will create
su cient interactions to ensure a common long-run growth rate.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        20 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Technology Diusion and Endogenous Growth
Remarks
1Taking the world growth rate given, the structure of the equilibrium is
very similar to that beore.
2The same model now gives us an endogenous growth rate for the
world economy. Growth for each country appears exogenous , but
the growth rate of the world economy is endogenous.
3Technological progress and economic growth are the outcome of
investments by all countries in the world, but there are su ciently
powerful forces in the world economy through technological spillovers
that pull relatively backward countries towards the world average,
ensuring equal long-run growth rates for all countries in the long run.
4Equal growth rates are still consistent with large level dierences
across countries.
5Several simplifying assumptions: same discount rates and focus on
steady-state equilibriua (transitional dynamics are now more
complicated, since the block recursiveness of the dynamical system
is lost).
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        19 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Introduction
Introduction I
In the models thus far each country is treated as an island ; its
technology is either exogenous or endogenously generated within its
boundaries.
A framework in which frontier technologies are produced in advanced
economies and then copied or adopted by follower countries
provides a better approximation.
Thus, should not only focus on dierential rates of endogenous
technology generation but on technology adoption ande cient
technology use .
Exogenous growth models have this feature, but technology is
exogenous. Decisions in these models only concern investment in
physical capital. In reality, technological advances at the world level
are not manna from heaven .
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        2 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>International Linkages Technology Diusion and Endogenous Growth
Steady State Equilibrium III
Higher njimplies that country jis technologically more advanced and
thus richer
Thus (5) shows that countries with higher hjand lower zj, will be
more advanced and richer.
A country with a greater labor force will also be richer (scale eect):
more demand for machines, making R&amp;D more protable.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        11 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>Conclusions Conclusions
Main Lessons II
5More realistic and richer trade models lead to a more complex
dynamics.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 11
December 6, 2016.        42 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
14.452 Economic Growth
 Fall 2016
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Solow Growth Model and the Data (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-452-economic-growth-fall-2016/resources/mit14_452f16_lec4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>Conclusions Conclusions 
Conclusions 
Message is somewhat mixed. 
On the positive side, despite its simplicity, the Solow model has enough 
substance that we can take it to data in various dierent forms, 
including TFP accounting, regression analysis and calibration. 
On the negative side, however, no single approach is entirely 
convincing. 
Complete agreement is not possible, but safe to say that consensus 
favors the interpretation that cross-country dierences in income per 
capita cannot be understood solely on the basis of dierences in 
physical and human capital 
Dierences in TFP are not necessarily due to technology in the 
narrow sense. 
It is also useful and important to think about fundamental causes , 
what lies behind the factors taken as given either Solow model. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 42 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Calibrating Productivity Dierences 
Calibrating Productivity Dierences IV  
ARGAUS
AUTBEL
BENB GDB OLBRABRB
B WA
CAFCANCHE
CHL
CHN
C MRC OG
C OLCRICYPDNK
D OMECU
E GYESPF IN
FJIF RAG BR
G HA
GMBG RC
G TMG UY
HKG
HNDHUN
I DNI NDI RL
I RNI SLI SR
I TA
J AM
J ORJ PN
KENK OR
L KA
L SOM EX
M LI
MOZM US
MWIM YS
NERN ICNLDN OR
NPLNZL
PAKPANPER
PHL
PNGPRT
PRY
R WASENS GP
SLESLVS WE
SYR
T GOT HA
TTO
T UNT UR
U GAURYUSA
VEN
ZAFZ MB
Z WE457
8
9
10
11P redictedloggdpperworker1980
7 8 9 10 11
loggdpperw orker1980ARGAUS
AUT
BDIBEL
BENB GDB OLBRABRB
B WA
CAFCANCHE
CHL
CHN
C MRC OG
C OLCRICYPDNK
D OM
E GYESPF IN
FJIF RAG BRG ER
GMBG RC
G TMG UYHKG
HNDHUN
I DN I NDI RL
I RNI SL I SR
I TA
J AMJ ORJ PN
KENK OR
L KA
L SOM EX
M LI
MOZM RTM US
MWIM YS
N ICNLDN OR
NPLNZL
PAKPANPER
PHL
PNGPRT
PRY
SENS GP
SLESLVS WE
SYR
T GOT HA
TTO
T UNT UR
U GAURYUSA
VEN
ZAFZ MB
Z WE457
8
9
10
11P redictedloggdpperworker1990
7 8 9 10 11
loggdpperw orker1990ARGAUSAUTBEL
BENB GDB OLBRABRBCANCHE
CHL
CHN
C MRC OGC OLCRIDNK
D OMDZAECU
E GYESPF IN
F RA
G BRG ER
G HA
GMBG RC
G TMHKG
HNDHUN
I DN
I NDI RL
I RNI SLI SR
I TA
J AMJ ORJ PN
KENK OR
L KAL SOM EX
M LI
MOZM US
MWIM YS
NERN ICNLDN OR
NPLNZL
PAKPANPER
PHL
PRT
PRY
R WASENSLVS WE
SYR
T GOT HA
TTO
T UNT UR
U GAURYUSA
VENZAF
Z MB Z WE457
8
9
10
11P redictedloggdpperworker2000
7 8 9 10 11 12
loggdpperw orker2000
Figure: Calibrated technology levels relative to the US technology (from the  
Solow growth model with human capital) versus log GDP per worker, 1980, 1990  
and 2000.  
Courtesy of Princeton University Press . Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 35 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Growth Regressions 
Solow Model and Growth Regressions V  
Latter source, convergence: 
Negative impact of the gap between current level and steady-state level 
of output per capita on rate of capital accumulation (recall 
0 &lt; f (k) &lt; 1). 
The lower is y (t) relative to y  (t), hence the lower is k (t) relative to 
k, the greater is f (k) /k, and this leads to faster growth in the 
eective capital-labor ratio. 
Speed of convergence in (12), measured by the term  
(1  f (k)) ( + g + n), depends on:  
 + g + n : determines rate at which eective capital-labor ratio needs  
to be replenished.  
f (k) : when f (k) is high, we are close to a  
linear AK  production function, convergence should be slow.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 28 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Challenges to Callibration 
From Correlates to Fundamental Causes  
In this lecture, the focus has been on proximate causes importance 
of human capital, physical capital and technology. 
Let us now return to the list of potential fundamental causes  
discussed  in the rst lecture:  
luck (or multiple equilibria)  
geographic dierences  
institutional dierences  
cultural dierences  
Do we need to worry about the relationship between these  
fundamental causes and the correlates of growth? In what way?  
Where is theory useful?  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 41 / 43 1
2
3
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Calibrating Productivity Dierences 
Calibrating Productivity Dierences V  
ARG
AUSAUTBEL
BENB GDB OLBRA
BRB
B WA
CAFCANCHE
CHL
CHNC MR
C OGC OL
CRI
CYPDNK
D OM
ECUE GYESP
F IN
FJIF RA
G BR
G HAGMBG RCG TM
G UYHKG
HND
HUN
I DN
I NDI RL
I RNI SL
I SRI TA
J AMJ OR
J PN
KENK OR
L KA
L SOM EX
M LIMOZM US
MWIM YS
NERN ICNLD
N OR
NPLNZL
PAKPAN
PER
PHLPNGPRT
PRY
R WA
SENS GP
SLESLV
S WE
SYR
T GO
T HATTOT UN
T UR
U GAURYUSA
VENZAF
Z MBZWE0
.5
1
1.5Predictedrelativetechnology
7 8 9 10 11
loggdpperw orker1980ARGAUSAUT
BDIBEL
BENB GDB OLBRABRB
B WA
CAFCANCHE
CHL
CHNC MR
C OGC OL
CRICYPDNK
D OME GYESP
F IN
FJIF RA
G BR
G ER
GMBG RCG TM
G UYHKG
HNDHUN
I DN
I NDI RL
I RNI SL
I SRI TA
J AMJ ORJ PN
KENK OR
L KA
L SOM EX
M LIMOZ
M RTM US
MWIM YS
N ICNLD
N OR
NPLNZL
PAKPAN
PER
PHLPNGPRT
PRY
SENS GP
SLESLVS WE
SYR
T GOT HATTOT UN
T UR
U GAURYUSA
VENZAF
Z MBZWE0
.5
1
1.5Predictedrelativetechnology
7 8 9 10 11
loggdpperw orker1990ARGAUSAUTBEL
BENB GD
B OLBRABRB
CAN
CHE
CHL
CHNC MR
C OGC OL
CRIDNK
D OM
DZA
ECUE GYESP
F INF RA
G BR
G ER
G HAGMBG RCG TMHKG
HNDHUN
I DN I NDI RL
I RNI SL
I SRI TA
J AMJ ORJ PN
KENK OR
L KA
L SOM EX
M LIMOZM US
MWIM YS
NERN ICNLD
N OR
NPLNZL
PAK
PAN
PERPHLPRT
PRY
R WASENSLVS WE
SYR
T GOT HATTOT UN
T UR
U GAURYUSA
VENZAF
Z MBZWE0
.5
1
1.5Predictedrelativetechnology
7 8 9 10 11 12
loggdpperw orker2000
Figure: Calibrated technology levels relative to the US technology (from the  
Solow growth model with human capital) versus log GDP per worker, 1980, 1990  
and 2000.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 36 / 43  Courtesy of Princeton University Press.  Used with permission</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis A World of Augmented Solow Economies 
A World of Augmented Solow Economies I  
Mankiw, Romer and Weil (1992) used regression analysis to take the 
augmented Solow model, with human capital, to data. 
Use the Cobb-Douglas model and envisage a world consisting of  
j = 1, ..., N countries.  
Each country is an island : countries do not interact (perhaps  
except for sharing some common technology growth).  
Country j = 1, ..., N has the aggregate production function: 
1Yj (t)= Kj (t) Hj (t) (Aj (t) Lj (t)) . 
Nests the basic Solow model without human capital when  = 0. 
Countries dier in terms of their saving rates, sk ,j and sh,j , population 
growth rates, nj , and technology growth rates Aj (t) /Aj (t)= gj . 
Dene kj  Kj /AjLj and hj  Hj /AjLj . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 10 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Growth Regressions 
Solow Model and Growth Regressions II  
Dierentiating (9) with respect to time and dividing both sides by 
y (t),  
y (t) k (t)  = g + f (k (t)) , (11)y (t) k (t) 
where 
f (k (t)) k (t)f (k (t))   (0, 1)f (k (t))  
is the elasticity of the f () function.  
f (k (t)) is between 0 and 1 follows from Assumption 1. For example, 
with Cobb-Douglas f (k (t)) = , but generally a function of k (t). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 25 / 43 
0</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Mapping the Model to Data Growth Accounting 
Growth Accounting IV 
Moreover, 
K (t)+ K (t + 1)K ,t,t+1  2 
L (t)+ L (t + 1)and L,t,t+1  2 
Equation (4) would be a fairly good approximation to (3) when the 
dierence between t and t + 1 is small and the capital-labor ratio 
does not change much during this time interval. 
Solow s (1957) applied this framework to US data: a large part of the 
growth was due to technological progress. 
From early days, however, a number of pitfalls were recognized. 
Moses Abramovitz (1956): dubbed the xterm the measure of our 
ignorance . 
If we mismeasure gL and gK we will arrive at inated estimates of x. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 6 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 1 / 43
14.452 Economic Growth: Lecture 4, The Solow Growth
Model and the Data
Daron Acemoglu
MIT
November 8, 2016.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Mapping the Model to Data Growth Accounting 
Interpreting the Results  
Reasons for mismeasurement: 
what matters is not labor hours, but eective labor hours 
important though di cult to make adjustments for changes in the 
human capital of workers. 
measurement of capital inputs: 
in the theoretical model, capital corresponds to the nal good used as 
input to produce more goods. 
in practice, capital is machinery, need assumptions about how relative 
prices of machinery change over time. 
typical assumption was to use capital expenditures but if machines 
become cheaper would severely underestimate gK 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 9 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis A World of Augmented Solow Economies 
A World of Augmented Solow Economies IV  
Even with all of these assumptions, (6) can still not be estimated 
consistently. 
lnAj is unobserved (at least to the econometrician) and thus will be 
captured by the error term. 
Most reasonable models would suggest ln
Aj  s should be correlated 
with investment rates. 
Thus an estimation of (6) would lead to omitted variable bias and 
inconsistent estimates. 
Implicitly, MRW make another crucial assumption, the orthogonal 
technology assumption: 
Aj = jA, with j orthogonal to all other variables. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 14 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis A World of Augmented Solow Economies 
Cross-Country Income Dierences: Regressions IV  
If these regression results are reliable, they give a big boost to the 
augmented Solow model. 
Adjusted R2 suggests that three quarters of income per capita 
dierences across countries can be explained by dierences in their 
physical and human capital investment. 
Immediate implication is technology (TFP) dierences have a 
somewhat limited role. 
But this conclusion should not be accepted without further  
investigation.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 19 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Challenges to Regression Analyses 
Challenges to Regression Analyses I  
Technology dierences across countries are not orthogonal to 
all other variables. 
Aj is correlated with measures of s
Aj will be those that have  h kand s for two reasons.  j j 
1 
2 omitted variable bias: societies with high
invested more in technology for various reasons; same reasons likely to 
induce greater investment in physical and human capital as well. 
reverse causality : complementarity between technology and physical or 
Aj will nd it more human capital imply that countries with high
benecial to increase their stock of human and physical capital. 
In terms of (7), implies that key right-hand side variables are 
correlated with the error term, j . 
OLS estimates of  and  and R2 are biased upwards. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 20 / 43 1
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Mapping the Model to Data Growth Accounting 
Growth Accounting II 
Denote growth rates of output, capital stock and labor by g  Y/Y , 
gK  K/K and gL  L/L. 
Dene the contribution of technology to growth as 
 FAA A x  Y A 
Recall with competitive factor markets, w = FL and R = FK . 
Dene factor shares as K  RK /Y and L  wL/Y . 
Putting all these together, (1) the fundamental growth accounting 
equation 
x = g  K gK  LgL. (2) 
Gives estimate of contribution of technological progress, Total Factor 
Productivity (TFP) or Multi Factor Productivity as 
x(t)= g (t)  K (t) gK (t)  L (t) gL (t) . (3) 
All terms on right-hand side are estimates obtained with a range of 
assumptions from national accounts and other data sources.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 4 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis A World of Augmented Solow Economies 
Cross-Country Income Dierences: Regressions III  
Their estimates for / (1  ), implies that  must be around 2/3, 
but should be around 1/3. 
The most natural reason for the high implied values of  is that j is 
correlated with ln (sk ,j ), either because: 
1	 the orthogonal technology assumption is not a good approximation to 
reality or   
2 there are also human capital dierences correlated with lnsk,j. 
Mankiw, Romer and Weil favor the second interpretation and  
estimate the augmented model,  
 ln yj
 = cst + ln (sk,j )  ln (n+ g + ) (7)1     1     j k 
  + ln (sh,j )  ln (nj + g + h )+ j .1     1     	
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 17 / 43 1
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Mapping the Model to Data Growth Accounting 
Growth Accounting I  
Aggregate production function in its general form: 
Y (t)= F [K (t) , L (t) , A (t)] . 
Combined with competitive factor markets, gives Solow (1957) 
growth accounting framework. 
Continuous-time economy and dierentiate the aggregate production 
function with respect to time. 
Dropping time dependence, 
   Y FAA A FKK K FLL L = + + . (1)Y Y A YK Y L
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 3 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis A World of Augmented Solow Economies 
A World of Augmented Solow Economies II 
Focus on a world in which each country is in their steady state 
Assuming that human capital also has depreciation, at the rate h , 
and it is accumulated with the saving rate sh , steady state values for 
country j would be (to be derived in recitation): 
   1 1   1 sk,j sh,jk =j nj + gj + k nj + gj + h
   1   1 1 sk,j sh,jh 
j = . nj + gj + k nj + gj + h
Consequently: 
Y (t) y (t)  (5)j L (t) 
      
1 1 sk ,j sh,j= Aj (t) . nj + gj + k nj + gj + h
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 11 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis A World of Augmented Solow Economies 
Estimates of the Augmented Solow Model 
MRW Updated data 
1985 1985 2000 
ln(sk ) .69 .65 .96 
(.13) (.11) (.13) 
ln(n + g + ) -1.73 -1.02 -1.06 
(.41) (.45) (.33) 
ln(sh ) .66 .47 .70 
(.07) (.07) (.13) 
Adj R2 .78 .65 .60 
Implied  .30 .31 .36 
Implied  .28 .22 .26 
No. of observations 98 98 107 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 18 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Growth Regressions 
Solow Model and Growth Regressions I  
Another popular approach of taking the Solow model to data: growth 
regressions, following Barro (1991). 
Return to basic Solow model with constant population growth and 
labor-augmenting technological change in continuous time: 
y (t) = A (t) f (k (t)) , (9) 
and 
k (t) 
k (t) = sf (k (t)) 
k (t)    g  n, (10) 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 24 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Growth Regressions 
Solow Model and Growth Regressions VII 
If countries dier according to characteristics, then perhaps 
gi,t,t1 = bi 0 + b1 log yi ,t1 + i ,t , (14) 
Now the constant term, bi 0, is country specic, and can be, for 
example, modeled as 
= Xi,t +i + ui,t , 
where i denotes country xed eects. 
In this case, focus is on conditional convergence, i.e., on whether 
b1 &lt; 0. 
This equation can be estimated using panel data methods as in the 
rst lecture, but much care is necessary. 
Xi ,t should not include channels (such as education and investment); 
lots of biases and causality denitely not guaranteed. If these 
problems exist for the model is not specied properly, b1 will not be 
estimated consistently. bi 0 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 31 / 43 
0</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Challenges to Regression Analyses 
Challenges to Regression Analyses III  
Take Mincer regressions of the form: 
ln wi = Xi   + Si , (8) 
Microeconometrics literature suggests that  is between 0.06 and 
0.10. 
Can deduce how much richer a country with 12 if we assume: 
1 That the micro-level relationship as captured by (8) applies identically 
to all countries.  
2 That there are no human capital externalities .  
Then: a country with 12 more years of average schooling should have 
between exp (0.10  12) c 3.3 and exp (0.06  12) c 2.05 times the 
stock of human capital of a county with fewer years of schooling. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 22 / 43 1
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Growth Regressions 
Solow Model and Growth Regressions IV  
Dene y  (t)  A (t) f (k); refer to y  (t) as the steady-state level 
of output per capita even though it is not constant. 
First-order Taylor expansions of log y (t) with respect to log k (t) 
around log k (t): 
log y (t)  log y  (t) c f (k ) (log k (t)  log k ) . 
Combining this with the previous equation, convergence equation : 
y (t) c g  (1  f (k )) ( + g + n) (log y (t)  log y  (t)) . (12)y (t) 
Two sources of growth in Solow model: g, the rate of technological 
progress, and convergence . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 27 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Growth Regressions 
Example: Cobb-Douglas Production Function 
Consider Cobb-Douglas production function 
1Y (t)= A (t) K (t) L (t). 
Then (12) becomes 
y (t) c g  (1  ) ( + g + n) (log y (t)  log y  (t)) . y (t) 
Focus on advanced economies for a back of the envelope calculation: 
g c 0.02 for approximately 2% per year output per capita growth, 
n c 0.01 for approximately 1% population growth and 
 c 0.05 for about 5% per year depreciation. 
Share of capital in national income is about 1/3, so  c 1/3. 
Thus convergence coe cient would be around 0.054 (c 0.67  0.08), 
which is very rapid relative to what some authors estimate from 
cross-country regressions. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 29 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Mapping the Model to Data Growth Accounting 
Growth Accounting III 
In continuous time, equation (3) is exact. 
With discrete time, potential problem in using (3): over the time 
horizon factor shares can change. 
Use beginning-of-period or end-of-period values of K and L? 
Either might lead to seriously biased estimates. 
Best way of avoiding such biases is to use as high-frequency data as 
possible. 
Typically use factor shares calculated as the average of the beginning 
and end of period values. 
In discrete time, the analog of equation (3) becomes 
xt,t+1 = gt,t+1  K ,t,t+1gK ,t,t+1  L,t,t+1gL,t,t+1, (4) 
gt,t+1 is the growth rate of output between t and t + 1; other growth 
rates dened analogously. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 5 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis A World of Augmented Solow Economies 
Cross-Country Income Dierences: Regressions II 
Estimates of the Basic Solow Model 
MRW Updated data 
1985 1985 2000 
ln(sk ) 1.42 1.01 1.22 
(.14) (.11) (.13) 
ln(n + g + ) -1.97 -1.12 -1.31 
(.56) (.55) (.36) 
Adj R2 .59 .49 .49 
Implied  .59 .50 .55 
No. of observations 98 98 107 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 16 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Growth Regressions 
Solow Model and Growth Regressions VI 
Using (12), we can obtain a growth regression similar to those 
estimated by Barro (1991). 
Using discrete time approximations, equation (12) yields: 
gi,t,t1 = b0 + b1 log yi ,t1 + i ,t , (13) 
where i ,t is a stochastic term capturing all omitted inuences. 
If such an equation is estimated in the sample of core OECD 
countries, b1 is indeed estimated to be negative. But for the whole 
world, no evidence for a negative b1. If anything, b1 would be 
positive, i.e., there is no evidence of world-wide convergence, 
Barro and Sala-i-Martin refer to this as unconditional convergence. 
But this might be too demanding: 
requires income gap between two countries to decline, irrespective of 
what types of technological opportunities, policies and institutions 
these countries have. If countries do dier, Solow model would not 
predict that they should converge in income level. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 30 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Mapping the Model to Data Growth Accounting 
Growth Accounting Results 
Example from Barro and Sala-i-Martin s textbook 
Courtesy of The MIT Press. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 7 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Calibrating Productivity Dierences 
Calibrating Productivity Dierences II  
Let the rate of return to acquiring the Sth year of schooling be  (S). 
A better estimate of the stock of human capital can be constructed as 
Hj =  exp { (S) S} Lj (S) 
S 
Lj (S) now refers to the total employment of workers with S years of 
schooling in country j. 
Series for Kj can be constructed from Summers-Heston dataset using 
investment data and the perpetual inventory method. 
Kj (t + 1)=(1  ) Kj (t)+ Ij (t) , 
Assume, following Hall and Jones that  = 0.06. 
With same arguments as before, choose a value of 1/3 for . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 33 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Calibrating Productivity Dierences 
Calibrating Productivity Dierences VI  
The following features are noteworthy: 
Dierences in physical and human capital still matter a lot.  
However, dierently from the regression analysis, this exercise also  
shows signicant technology (productivity) dierences .  
Same pattern visible in the next three gures for the estimates of the  
technology dierences, Aj /AUS , against log GDP per capita in the  
corresponding year.  
Also interesting is the pattern that the empirical t of the neoclassical 
growth model seems to deteriorate over time. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 37 / 43 1
2
3
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
14.452 Economic Growth
 Fall 2016
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis A World of Augmented Solow Economies 
Cross-Country Income Dierences: Regressions I  
MRW rst estimate equation (6) without the human capital term for 
the cross-sectional sample of non-oil producing countries 
 ln yj = constant + ln (sk,j )  ln (nj + g + k )+ j .1   1   
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 15 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Challenges to Regression Analyses 
Challenges to Regression Analyses II  
 is too large relative to what we should expect on the basis of 
microeconometric evidence. 
The working age population enrolled in school ranges from 0.4% to 
over 12% in the sample of countries. 
Predicted log dierence in incomes between these two countries is 
 (ln 12  ln (0.4)) = 0.66  (ln 12  ln (0.4))  2.24.1     
Thus a country with schooling investment of over 12 should be about 
exp (2.24)  1  8.5 times richer than one with investment of around 
0.4. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 21 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis A World of Augmented Solow Economies 
A World of Augmented Solow Economies II  

Here y (t) stands for output per capita of country j along the j 
balanced growth path. 
Note if gj  s are not equal across countries, income per capita will 
diverge. 
Mankiw, Romer and Weil (1992) make the following assumption: 
 Aj (t)= Aj exp (gt) . 

 Countries dier according to technology level, (initial level Aj ) but 
they share the same common technology growth rate, g. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 12 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Challenges to Callibration 
Challenges to Callibration III  
Levels-accounting faces two challenges. 
1 
2 Data on capital and labor shares across countries are not widely 
available. Almost all exercises use the Cobb-Douglas approach (i.e., a 
constant value of K equal to 1/3). 
The dierences in factor proportions, e.g., dierences in Kj /Hj , across 
countries are large. An equation like (16) is a good approximation 
when we consider small (innitesimal) changes. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 40 / 43 1
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Challenges to Callibration 
Challenges to Callibration I  
In addition to the standard assumptions of competitive factor  
markets, we had to assume :  
no human capital externalities, a Cobb-Douglas production function, 
and a range of approximations to measure cross-country dierences in 
the stocks of physical and human capital. 
The calibration approach is in fact a close cousin of the  
growth-accounting exercise (sometimes referred to as levels  
accounting ).  
Imagine that the production function that applies to all countries in 
the world is 
F (Kj , Hj , Aj ) , 
Assume countries dier according to their physical and human capital 
as well as technology but not according to F . 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 38 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Mapping the Model to Data Introduction 
Solow Growth Model and the Data  
Use Solow model or extensions to interpret both economic growth 
over time and cross-country output dierences. 
Focus on proximate causes of economic growth. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 2 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Mapping the Model to Data Growth Accounting 
Growth Accounting Results (continued)  
Courtesy of The MIT Press. Used with permission.
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 8 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Calibrating Productivity Dierences 
Calibrating Productivity Dierences I  
Suppose each country has access to the Cobb-Douglas aggregate  
production function:  
1Yj = Kj  (AjHj ) , (15) 
Each worker in country j has Sj years of schooling. 
Then using the Mincer equation (8) ignoring the other covariates and 
taking exponents, Hj can be estimated as 
Hj = exp (Sj ) Lj , 
Does not take into account dierences in other human capital  
factors, such as experience.  
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 32 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Challenges to Callibration 
Challenges to Callibration II  
Rank countries in descending order according to their physical capital 
to human capital ratios, Kj /Hj Then 
xj ,j +1 = gj,j +1  K ,j,j +1gK ,j,j +1  Lj,j +1gH ,j,j +1, (16) 
where: 
gj,j +1: proportional dierence in output between countries j and j + 1, 
gK ,j,j +1: proportional dierence in capital stock between these 
countries and 
gH ,j ,j +1: proportional dierence in human capital stocks. 
K ,j,j +1 and Lj,j +1: average capital and labor shares between the two 
countries. 
The estimate xj,j +1 is then the proportional TFP dierence between 
the two countries. 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 39 / 43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Regression Analysis Challenges to Regression Analyses 
Challenges to Regression Analyses IV  
Thus holding other factors constant, this country should be about 2-3 
times as rich as the country with zero years of average schooling. 
Much less than the 8.5 fold dierence implied by the  
Mankiw-Romer-Weil analysis.  
Thus  in MRW is too high relative to the estimates implied by the 
microeconometric evidence and thus likely upwardly biased. 
Overestimation of  is, in turn, most likely related to correlation 
between the error term j and the key right-hand side regressors in 
(7). 
Daron Acemoglu (MIT) Economic Growth Lecture 4 November 8, 2016. 23 / 43</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
