<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/</course_url>
    <course_title>Ethnic and National Identity</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Anthropology </list>
      <list>Ethnography </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ethnic Identity I</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_2_ethn_id_i/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7
 D. 	 Non-scholarly, everyd ay meanings of ethnic 
1. 	 Ethnic usually refers to a perspective the majority applies to minority 
others 
2. 	 It refers to a relationship
 a. 	 It will often be a term connoting inferiority 
   b .	 DISCUSS: Can WASPs (White Anglo-Saxon Protestants in the US) be ethnic? 
E. To study the meaning of a word we al so have to compare it to related words 
1. 	 Our syllabus is organized this way 
2. 	 Eriksen organizes his book the same way 
3. 	 Eriksen compares ethnicity and race 
a. 	 One notion: that ethnicity refe rs more to group identification, and 
race is more oriented to th e categorization of them 
b. 	 But they both tend to stress common descent among the members 
4. 	 The relationship between ethnicity and nationality is equally complicated
 a. 	 Nationalism: holds that politic al boundaries should be coterminous 
with cultural boundaries 
5. 	 Social class 
a. 	 In general there are 2 kinds of relationship between social class 
and ethnicity: 1) 	 An ethnic group may or may not be internally ranked 
contain more than one social class 
2) 	 And there may be a high correlation between ethnicity and 
class in a given society: this often happens 
    3 )	 DISCUSS: examples? 
VI. 	 The China example 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>2: ETHNIC IDENTI
TY I 
Read: Gladney 1-24 
 Nagel 3-13  Eriksen 1-22 
I. 	 Ethnicity as a topic of study 
A. 	 Were studying it partly because interest in ethnic and national identity has surged
 1. 	 Scholarship on it has increased 
2. 	 The topic is certainly much more im portant in the world than 15 years ago 
B. 	 As Eriksen points out, many people felt that ethnicity and nationalism were 
incompatible with modernity and would disappear 1. 	 An image of all of us becoming a global village ruled by a body like the 
UN (what was it called in Star Wars?) 
II. 	 Why didnt ethnic and nationa l loyalties continue to diminish, as everyone predicted? 
A. 	 Most present-day conflict invol ves ethnic groups one way or another 
1. 	 In 1991: 35 of the 37 major armed c onflicts were internal and most of 
them could plausibly be de scribed as ethnic conflicts 
a. 	 Some conflicts are non- violent (Quebecois independence 
movement) 
III.	 Explanations: 
A. 	 Structural factor 1 : Colonialism 
1. 	 Breakup of colonial holdings during the 20
th century
 a. 	 Newly independent nations tend to be culturally diverse 
b. 	 Examples of Papua New Guinea; India, all sub-Saharan African 
countries 
c. 	 The colonial powers deliberately created colonies that divided up 
the territories belonging to pre- existing social/c ultural groups 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9 
b. 	 To get people to throw off the yoke of the Qing empire (who were 
Manchu) 
2. 	 Real Chinese were Han; the Manchu and others were foreigners, occupiers 
a. 	 Suns scheme proposed 5 pe oples of China: Han, Man (Manchu), 
Meng (Mongolian), Zang (Tibetan) and Hui (all Muslims, now the 
Uygur, Kazakh, Hui, etc.) 
3. 	 Similar to Eriksens point about et hnicity always being a relationship, we 
see Suns concern to create minoritie s as part of an overall scheme to 
create a majoritya unified Chinese nation 
4. 	 One people, one history 
E. 	 Quite successful: got all so rts of people to think that  Chinese and Han are the 
same 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
c. 	 Many countries now contain migrants who arrived relatively 
recently  
1) 	 Laotians in Texas; Hm ong in California and Minnesota, 
Turks and Pakistanis in Germany and Scandinavia 
    2 )	 DISCUSS: other examples? 
d. 	 And ethnic conflict sometimes results 
D. 	 Structural factor 4 : end of the Cold War 
1. Breakup of the Soviet Union and its satellite countries (E. Europe) 
a. 	 New countries emerged, with new assertions of national identity 
2. 	 Many socialist states had seen  ethnic loyalties as regressive 
a. 	 Ethnic, religious activities were repressed 
b. 	 Examples: Yugoslavia; the Sovi et Union itself; China; Ethiopia; 
Tanzania (there are no distinct ethnic groups in socialist Cuba) 
3. 	 Ethnic conflict followed 
E. 	 Structural factor 5: Glob alizing processes, transnationalism 
1. 	 Western Europe: the formation of  the European Union resulted in less 
power for the nation-state 
2. 	 Also, regions within European countries have become more autonomous 
3. 	 Spaces have opened up in which to assert ethnicity 
4. 	 Examples: Wales, Ireland, Scotla nd in Great Britain, many others 
5. 	 Spain is another example: regions like Catalonia, the Basque region, have 
become much stronger a. 	 Like the Soviet Union, during the regime of dictator Franco, Spain 
repressed nationa list mobilizing 
b. 	 Regional identity is strong there, and in other parts of Europe 
6. 	 Theres a movement in northern It aly to secede from the rest of the 
country 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
d. 	 A divide and conquer strategy 
1) Look at a political ma p of Africa (showing the countries) 
a) Then look at a map of tribes and kingdoms 
2) Theres no congruenceon purpose 3) Indonesia is the best current examplean archipelago 
(collection of islands) that s highly culturally diverse 
2. 	 Empire
 a. 	 The European colonial powersGreat Britain, France, Germany, 
Italy, the Netherlandswere building empires 
b. 	 Empires by definition are multicultural 
1) Theyre made up of diverse conquered peoples 
c. 	 Empire-builders have  cared about bu ilding a strong state
 1) But theyve not been interested in building a strong nation 
a) In the sense of a citizenry that sees itself as one 
people, one culture, one language, etc. 
b) 	 In fact, empires have worked against colonized 
peoples being able to fost er nationalist sentiment 
d. 	 This is why so many newly independent countries have found it 
extremely difficult to unify the populations within their borders 
1) 	 Example 1: a very blood y civil war in Nigeria in 1967-68: 
Biafrans wanted to secede 
2) 	 Example 2: Sun Yat Sens quest for building a nation (in 
Gladney) a) 	 He wanted China to cast off the yoke of external 
colonialismthe British empire 
b) 	 And unite against the ruling Manchus, also an 
empire 
e. 	 So, Empires are states , but they arent nations 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
IV. 	 Conclusion: ethnic identity has become more important, more salient, more significant to 
the holders of the identity themselves 
A. 	 People are claiming their identity in ways they didnt before 
1. 	 Nagels book explores Native Americans working to reve rse the previous 
trajectory of assimilation 
2. 	 Other indigenous peoples reveal a similar story 
a. 	 In some cases there was too much repression earlier, and people 
hid or denied their identity 1) El Salvador
1 is an example 
3. 	 Of course the earlier pattern of dimi nished identification with ones ethnic 
group continues to occur a. 	 What sociologist Mary Wate rs calls symbolic  ethnicities and 
optional ethnicities
2 
1) 	 Example of someone with an Italian last name, but thats 
pretty much it 
B. 	 There are several theories as to w hy many people who earlier werent interested 
have become interested in their ethnic roots 1. 	 One explanation thats been offered:  theres more anxiety, fear of cultural 
standardization, McDonaldization of the world a. 	 This is one explanati on Eriksen (and many others) offers 
b. 	 Well search for answers throughout the course 
   c .	 DISCUSS: examples you can think of? 
V. 	 Methodology: how to study the various mean ings of concepts like ethnicity, ethnic? 
A. First: look at history of the meaning of the word: for example, ethnic 
1 See Tilley VQ. 2002. New help or new hegemony? the tran snational indigenous peoples movement and Being 
Indian in El Salvador. J. Lat. Amer. Stud.  34(3):525-554. 
2 Mary Waters, Optional Ethnicities: For Whites Only? pp. 430-38 in Andersen and Collins, eds., Race, Class and 
Gender , 4th edition.Wadsworth 2001. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
1) 	 The fact that several empires were quite successful for a 
considerable amount of time de monstrates that they did not 
need to be a nation 
   f .	 DISCUSS: was the U.S. ever an empire? 
3. Other kinds of ethnic conflict also  stem from history of colonization 
a. 	 Religious conflict in Ireland 
1) Ireland was the first British colonyprior to establishing 
the 13 American colonies 
2) Ireland is still living out that colonial legacy today 
b. 	 The same for Indonesiahorrific religious conflict has occurred in 
that country 
B. 	 Structural factor 2: how post-colonial states have been reconfigured 
1. 	 The populations that were tribes,  aboriginals, etc. in the colony, are 
now considered ethnic minorities 
2. 	 Post-colonial states have tried to  assimilate, or at least control these 
internal populations that ar e distinct in some respect 
a. 	 These populations usually resist 
1) 	 Example: the Kurds resisting the states of Iran, Iraq, and 
Turkey 
2) 	 Gladney mentions that th e Chinese state is very concerned 
about members of its nationalit ies in regions near Chinas 
bordersfears of separatism 
C. 	 Structural factor 3 :  an increase in  the number of people located in diasporas 
(away from their homeland) 1. 	 Why move to other countries? Several reasons: 
a. 	 Because of capitalisms need for cheap labor 
b. 	 Refugees fleeing violence 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
1. 	 An earlier meaning was heathen or pagan 
2. 	 The term subsequently was used to refer to racial characteristics (in the 
mid-nineteenth century) 
3. 	 Then it came to be a polite term  (in the US) for Jews, Italians, Irish 
populations the majority considered to be inferior:  
a. 	 Ethnics 
B. 	 Second: look at current meanings, both scholarly and general  
C. 	 Scholarly meanings: 
1. 	 Ethnicity refers to classificat ions of people and to relationships 
a. 	 Two (or more) groups must be in contact with each otherethnic 
groups do not exist as isolates 
b. 	 And must entertain ideas of members of one group being culturally 
different from the other 
2. 	 Scholarship often encounters pr oblems in classification and analysis 
3. 	 Gladney asks, who are the Chinese?  Who are the Hui? 
4. 	 Many scholars conclude that self -ascription is the best definition 
   a .	 NOTE: Dont worry about difficult terms you find in your reading 
(e.g., emic category of ascription) 
b. 	 The self-ascription approach pa ys attention to groups that consider 
themselves as  
1) Culturally distinctive
 2) Employ metaphoric or fictive kinship 
3) Have myths of common origin 
4) Encourage endogamy (marriage within the group) 
c. 	 Yet self-definition can produce problems 1) 	 For example, a census taker will often want other kinds of 
evidence 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
A. 	 China has usually been seen as  huge homogeneous, monocultural nation 
1. 	 It has had long history of  empire-building (and falling) 
2. 	 Heavily affected by European colonialism (although never formally a 
European colony) 
B. 	 Gladney asks specifically, what does it mean to be Hui in the Chinese nation-
state? 
1. 	 He discusses a new feeling in China, a revalorization of something 
a. 	 A revalorization of ancestral and ethnic ties 
b. 	 A politics of ethnic and cultural difference within China proper 
c. 	 Official minorities in China be gan to strongly asse rt their identities 
d. 	 And groups within the so-calle d Han majority began to rediscover, 
reinvent, and reassert their ethnic differences 
2. 	 Especially in the south, there is a newfound interest in the southern Chu 
kingdom a. 	 Many museumsearly Chu now  seen by some as essential to 
Chinese culture, said to be less important northern dynasties 
b. 	 Note the use of archaeology fo r present-day political interests  
   c .	 DISCUSS: other examples of archaeology being used for this 
purpose? 
C. 	 Chinas nationalities 
1. 	 There are 56 official nationalities,  but there are near ly 350 other groups 
who have applied 
2. 	 These latter groups are regarded as ethnically different but dont fit into 
any of the official categories recognized by the state 
D. 	 Gladney briefly discusses how th e state created the majority Han 
1. 	 Sun Yat-Sen saw familism and clanism in the China of his day but he saw 
no real nationalism 
a. 	 His project was to create it 
8</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction to the Study of Ethnic and National Identity: The Stakes, and Why the Stakes Are So High</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_1_intro_crs/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
32 Ethiopian Jews who moved to Israel: Falashi: black Jews 
33 They experienced racism, people had difficulty accepting them as truly Jewish 
34 Children of black/Jewish parents will say they felt they had to choose an identitythey 
werent allowed to be both 
35 Like the Asian lesbian butch, these difficulties reveal stereotypes; what combinations of 
identity components are permitted and which ones are not 
36 By the way, its OK to speculate in this class, you just have to make sure you tell us that 
youre speculating 
37 Its OK to talk about stereotypes, if you make it clear that this is what youre doing 
38 Then we move to language, culture and ethnicity 
39 We next look at current trends in scholarship on ethnic and national identity 
40 Transnationalism, globalization are stressed more 
41 Culture recovery movementsheritage initiatives 
42 An example is the Celtic revival in England, Scotland, Ireland, even in Brittany 
43 DISCUSS : other examples you can think of? 
44 We consider culture as commodity: issues surrounding appropriating culture, fears 
about losing culture, enriching culture, recovering culture, selling culture 
45 We move on to rights movements, which are concerned with ensuring rights of all 
kinds 
46 Both the foundational assumptions of human rights, civil rights 
47 Out of the liberal philosophical tradition 
48 And the notion of collective and culturespecific rights 
49 Then we move to identity politics, New Social Movements 
50 Mobilizing around identity components 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
51 Examples: gender, indigeneity 
52 Religious mobilizing has been going on for a long time 
53 And transnationalismdiasporas, migration, refugees, globalizations effects 
54 Students will present their third papers at the end of the course 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity
Fall 2011 
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>INTRODUCTION TO COURSE 
1	 Housekeeping 
a.	 Send around piece of paper; each of you should include: 
i.	 Name 
ii.	 email 
iii.	 year 
iv.	 major 
v.	 previous anthropology or sociology courses? 
vi.	 why taking the course? 
b.	 All readings (except for books) will be posted 
i.	 Supplemental readings (related resources) are usually from the mass 
media 
ii.	 If newspaper articles are posted for a particular class, they are optional 
readingonly the scholarly pieces are required 
iii.	 Keep the supplemental readings (related resources) in mind as a resource 
when youre deciding on a paper topic 
2 Nature of the course 
a.	 CIH and HASSD course 
b.	 HASSDs are being phased out 
c.	 CIH: improve communication skills, especially writing 
d. The syllabus contains the specifics of the CIH component of the course 
3 Course requirements 
a.	 No prerequisites 
b.	 Strong discussion component 
c.	 Basic format is 1 hour lecture,  hour discussion 
d.	 Lectures themselves are very interactive 
e.   Study questions for the readings, designed to help guide class discussions, are on 
       the course webpage 
f.	 Youll be asked to answer these in class at random 
g.	 Youll be asked to bring discussion questions 
h.	 Youll be asked to work in groups and present your findings 
i. Written assignments are fairly easy 
4 Reading 
a. As it says on the syllabus, you must do the reading 
5 Reader responses 
a.	 Consisting of a few sentences, a paragraph, nothing you cant do in 5 minutes, after 
doing the readings 
b.	 Ive found these to be quite useful: students come much more prepared to discuss 
the reading 
c.	 They must be reactions to the readingnot about the lectures, not your random 
thoughts about ethnicity not a synopsis of the reading 
d.	 Reader Responses can be about any of the reading for that week 
e.	 Theyre not graded 
f.	 They are required 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
6 We will see five video/DVDs 
7 Intellectual Thrust of Course 
a.	 Ethnic identity: well begin with a short overview (Eriksen) on ethnicity snd begin 
Gladneyan easy bookas well as begin Nagel 
b.	 Note that some reading of a more theoretical, introductory nature will come later 
c.	 The syllabus may look like too much reading; it isnt 
d.	 Vast majority of readings are ethnography based rather than theoretical 
e.	 Introduce you to the wide range of societies out there 
f.	 We then begin to explore the anthropological perspective on national identity 
g.	 Have to first ask what nationalism is 
i.	 For example, is nation the same as country? 
h.	 What is national identity? How does it differ from ethnic identity? 
i.	 Note: throughout the course, the purpose of questions like this is not to 
discover the BEST definition of ethnic identity or nationalism 
ii.	 In this respect, this course is not like your chemistry class, or other science 
and engineering courses 
iii.	 The purpose of these questions is to get you to think about these concepts 
systematically and comprehensively 
iv.	 To explore the various meanings of the terms we use (all of them have 
several meanings) 
v.	 To better understand the political, historical, social context of the meanings 
vi.	 And become familiar with the idea that various meanings can coexist, each 
one making a contribution to an analysis 
vii.	 The several meanings of a term are useful for different kinds of scholarly 
and political goals 
i.	 DISCUSS : how can you have a discussion in a course if all the words have several 
meanings and theres no best meaning? 
i.	 By everyone agreeing that there are several meanings 
ii.	 And understanding these several meanings to some extent 
iii.	 And everyone agreeing on a particular meaning for purposes of discussion 
that day 
iv.	 We then move to some concepts related to ethnic and national identity 
v.	 Colonialism, empire, state, culture 
vi.	 For example, is state the same as nation? 
vii.	 And discuss how to define culture 
j.	 DISCUSS : your definition of culture? 
i.	 Then well look at ethnic conflict 
ii.	 There are two main kinds: 
1.	 Conflict between ethnic groups 
2.	 And conflict between a state and an ethnic group within its 
boarders 
iii.	 Gladney and Nagel address ethnic/state conflict 
iv.	 In some ways ethnic conflict permeates the course 
v.	 Because it constantly calls attention to itself in our lives 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
16 An example: Kath Weston found that for many people, in the U.S. Asian lesbians could 
not be butch1 
17 DISCUSS : what does butch mean? 
18 Weston says that the construction of Asian women at present is such that an Asian 
lesbian trying to act working class, for example, by becoming a mechanic, look as 
masculine as possible, will encounter more problems than will an African American 
woman 
19 An Asian lesbian who wants to be butch will have to work harder to overcome the 
stereotype of petite, docile, oriental blossom, a femininity thats seen to inhere in 
Asian females 
20 We will read about another example: de la Cadenas essay titled Women are more 
Indian, about Andean Indians in Peru 
21 While it is useful to separate out these identity components during analysis 
22 After all, this is what analysis is 
23 Keep in mind that we can only isolate them during examination; no one is ever only a 
man, only an AfricanAmerican, only an Italian 
24 G. Sexuality 
25 Same thing: we will read about how sexuality is raced, ethnicized, classed 
26 H. Religion 
27 We will pay particular attention to connections between religion and ethnic/national 
identityactual connections, or connections made in peoples minds 
28 Islam: the Gladney book 
29 DISCUSS : Jewishness: religion, ethnicity, racestereotypes about Jewish bodies? 
30 He doesnt look Jewish 
31 Jokes were made about AfricanAmerican movie actor Sammy Davis converting to 
Judaism not looking Jewish 
1 Weston, Kath, 1996. Render Me, Gender Me: Lesbians Talk Sex, Class, Color, Nation, Studmuffins New York: 
Columbia University Press. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
vi.	 In the newspapers, TV and because a fundamental premise in the social 
sciences holds: 
1.	 That you learn more about a subject 
2.	 By examining examples of malfunction, breakdown, toorapid 
change 
vii.	 Youll learn less when studying cases where things are going well 
1.	 For example: do you want to know about marriage in the 17th 
century New England? 
2.	 Then study divorce in 17th century New England 
viii. We then look at the concept of race 
1.	 Which, like culture, informs ethnic and national identity 
ix.	 We look at notions about biology 
1.	 Note that biology is a Western concept 
2.	 If were looking at societies crossculturally 
3.	 Trying to understand their notions of race 
4.	 We have to first work to understand their notions about the 
materiality of the body 
5.	 What they understand to be inheritance from one person to 
another 
6.	 How they see physical relatedness between persons 
k.	 DISCUSS: Think about folk biology concepts you know about 
i.	 For example, blood. Race is one of those concepts that has many 
meanings which have changed over time 
8	 We will work to understand their history 
9	 Nation, race had very different meanings earlier in the West 
10 Gender 
11 An important lesson in this course is that one identity component (class, gender, 
nationality, sexual orientation) 
12 Is always linked to the othersit never stands in isolation in the real world 
13 These identity components always cooccur in individuals identity 
14 Some pairs are seen by members of a given culture to always or usually cooccur 
15 Concepts about race are gendered, etc. 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ethnic Conflict II</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_11_el_mal/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
13. Nagel says that we tend to see Native Am ericans as rooted. Discuss, referring to 
Malkkis points. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Study Questions on Eller 143-193 (Kurds); Malkki 
1. 	 According to Eller, three conditions must  be m
et before a group can be considered 
a nation. What are they? (p. 144) 
2. 	 Eller cites another scholar, Izady, w ho states that Kurdish society remains 
heterogeneous in almost all those aspects th at normally form the basis of an ethnic 
identity (in Eller, p. 144). What are these? How do the Kurds compare to the 
Hui in this respect?
 3. 	 Eller says that some of the most trad itional characteristics of Kurdish society are 
the biggest impediments to being able to  build themselves as a nation. What are 
these? 
4. 	 List the ways Kurdish nationalism differ s from the vast majority of nationalist 
movements. 
5. 	 Describe two examples of the Kurds manipulating the govern ments of countries 
that contain Kurdish populations. Describe two examples where the Kurds were 
used as pawns by these states.
 6. 	 On p. 163 Eller says that in a certain sense the Kurdish trib al organization of 
today is a product of the state systems that overarched Kurdish society. How 
so? Compare to the case of the Hui. 
7. 	 Iraq, unlike Iran, has very little nationalist ideology. What are some of the 
consequences for the Kurds liv ing in these two countries? 
8. 	 Of all the interests at work in Kurdistan, however, the most enduring and pernicious is geopolitics. (p. 164). Give two examples. 
9. 	 What does Malkki mean by National Geographic? 
10. 	 How rooted in land/territory/soil is our concept of cu lture? Give three examples 
of extremely rooted culture. And thr ee examples of what we might call 
unrooted culture. 
11. 	 Describe the differences between the cam p Hutu refugees and those of the town. 
What do the two groupsand the differences between themtell us about culture? About nation ? About ethnicity? 
12. 	 Malkki makes a couple of points that are potentially upsetting to activists. Why, 
do you think, would they be upset? 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ethnic Identity, State, and Sexuality</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_16_nag_dev/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
16. 	 What role did the eugenics m ovement play in these colonies? 
17. 	 Discuss the changes in ideology accompanyi ng the flipflop from a pro-concubinage policy 
to a policy that advocated bringing European women to the colonies. 
18. 	 Describe how the Singapore government ch aracterized graduate babies (Heng &amp; 
Devan). 
19. 	 Why was the Prime Minister so  concerned about this issue? 
20. 	 What were the ethnic stereotypes of Singapores Indi an/Malay citizen? 
21. 	 The argument was made that the four Asian tigers (Japan, South Korea, Taiwan and 
Singapore) succeeded economically because of  their Confucian-based cultures, their 
communitarian value system, etc.  Defend this argument.  Critique it. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>QUESTIONS ON NAGEL (Sex and Nationalism), STOLER, 

 HENG AND DEVAN  
1. 	 Nagel speaks of a moral economy  of nationalism (p. 146).  Discuss. 
2. 	 Describe Durkheims theory  concerning ways in which devian ce (rule-breaking) are in fact 
useful  for society. 
3. 	 What is the colonial gaze?  List three characteristics typical of the colonial sexual script 
assigned to colonized (native) men. 
4. 	 Describe the role of sexuality  in the Sepoy War in India in 1857. 
5. 	 Describe the most frequently occurring policies aimed at mixed-race children developed by 
colonial administrations. 
6. 	 What is orientalism?  Nagel speaks of an internal orientalism directed at certain 
categories of women (p. 159).  Compare the Chinese exampl e of internal orientalism 
discussed in the article by Schein that we re ad earlier in the term  to U.S. examples. 
7. 	 List the most co mmon ways nationalism is masculini zed.  Nagel says that nationalist 
politics is a major venue for accomplishi ng masculinity (p. 160).  Discuss. 
8. 	 In what ways did Europe an womens experiences (in Dutc h, French, and British colonies) 
of the cleavages of racial dominance and inte rnal social distinctions differ from mens 
(Stoler)? 
9. 	 Characterize the dilemma faced by colonials when they tried to de termine who was white 
and who was native. 
10. 	 Why was sex the most  discussed subject in  colonial literature, according to Stoler? 
11. 	 What points does Stoler  make regarding Saids concept of Orientalism? 
12. 	 Why did the Dutch Ea st Indies Compa ny initially promote extramarital relations and legal 
unions between low-ranking employ ees and imported slave women? 
13. 	 How does this system of concubinage make the distinctions in co lonial societies more 
problematic, more difficult to uphold? 
14. 	 Discuss the images of European women found in colonial literature. 
15. 	 What kinds of empirical ev idence support the assumptions in this literature about women 
and men, colonial and native? 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Religion, Ethnicity, the Nation</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_17_rel_nat/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17 RELIGION, ETHNICITY, TH
E NATION 
Read: Aihwa Ong, 1990. State versus Islam: Malay families, womens bodies, and the 
body politic in Malaysia 
  Kimberly Arkin, 2009. Rhinestone aesth etics and religious essence: Looking 
Jewish in Paris. American Ethnologist  36(4): 722-734. (8) 
I. 	 Introduction: anthropolog ical views about religion 
A. Religion is seen as part of culture, a component of a partic ular cultural system 
1. 	 In some conceptualizations of culture, each culture has a religion 
2. 	 For example, E. E. Evan s-Pritchard wrote an ethnography, The Nuer  about 
people in southern Sudan 
a. Followed it with the book Nuer Religion 
3. 	 Similarly, in the U.S. Southwest,  the Navajo people speak the Navajo 
language and practice th e Navajo religion 
a. 	 Its difficult to imagine what  Navajo religion could be if someone 
who doesnt speak Navajo beli eved in it and practiced it 
B. 	 But for the most part religions are linke d to culture (in the sense of a culture), 
nation, and ethnicity in mo re complicated fashion 
1. 	 Example of world religions 
2. 	 They are shared by many culture s, no matter how you define culture 
a. 	 Islam in Nigeria is very  different from Islam in Indonesia 
3. 	 To be successful such major religions must have a core set of meanings, 
symbols and practices that adapt fairly easily to different cultural contexts 
a. 	 Faint echoes of the original culture will remain 
b. 	 Because all world religions began in a single culture 
c. 	 There will be premises, assumptions, and sometimes language 
from the original culture 
1)	 The Hui are an example: Arabic loan words, calligraphy 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
2. 	 Example: among Iroquois in New Yo rk state and Canada, the Handsome 
Lake revitalization movement 
3. 	 As is the Ghost Dance adopted by Plains Indians in the 19
th century 
4. 	 DISCUSS: other examples? a. 	 Nation of Islam in the US (optional reading) 
5. 	 Some new religions are short-lived 
C. 	 Another kind of new religion: 
1. 	 Is a blend of two or more old religions 
2. 	 This kind is called a syncretistic religion 
a. 	 Comes about through for ces of creolization, amalgamation, 
assimilation
   b .	 Santera  in this country 
1) Combination of Yoruba and Spanish Catholicism 2) With concomitant associations with certain Hispanic 
groups 
   c .	 Voudoun in Haiti another example 1) Combination of West African and French Catholicism 
2) Now serves as a symbol of the Haitian people
 d. 	 Similar religions in other countries have different names: 
Macumba, Candombl in Brazil 
D. 	 Religions that claim to be rational
 1. 	 Scientology 
2. 	 Rational, secular states that s ee religious practice as old-fashioned, not 
modern a. 	 Illustrated in the optional article by Malarney on Viet Nam 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3
 1. 	 Greek or Russian Orthodox 
a. 	 Roman Catholic is complicat ed because this Church has been so 
concerned with proselytizing, and has been successful 
2. 	 But the phrases Irish Catholic, Irish wake a. 	 The image evoked is very different from the image of an Italian 
(Catholic) wake or a Polish (Catholic) one 
b. 	 All are Catholic 
c. 	 And anyone can become a Catholic 
3. 	 Tibet is perhaps the best exam ple of one-culture -one-religion model 
fashioned out of a world religion (Buddhism)
 a. 	 Tibetan Buddhism 
1) Illustrates a very str ong imbrication of religion, culture, and 
political structures 
2) 	 Tibet comes close to being a theocracy (the Dalai Lama is 
seen to be both the religious and political leader) 
a) Although other relig ions are represented there 
E. 	 Some world religions are seen  to belong to certain populations 
1. 	 Even though they are practiced in many countries 
2. 	 Judaism: Arkins discov ery of the notion of the  tte juive  
a. 	 Even though the aggregate of  people who self-identify as Jews 
shows enormous physical variation 
b. 	 Example: Sammy Davis, an African-American entertainer in the 
US
 1) 	 Converted to Judaism 
2) 	 It was seen as oddthere  were jokes about his not looking 
Jewish 
c. 	 Ethiopian Jews who migrated  to IsraelFalashiare seen as 
odd as well 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
2. 	 The model obviously doesnt work for religions 
3. 	 Even though a religion may appear  to be fairly straightforwardly linked to 
a nationality and a localitya culture 
a. 	 Above example of Tibetan religion 
b. 	 But if we were to study Ti betan history we would have to 
understand the spread of Buddhism 
c. 	 Look at the fame of the current Dalai Lama; what he represents, 
who his followers are. What produced this? 1) 	 He visited MIT in 2003 ; conference with a panel of 
scientists 
2) 	 His international fame has everything to do with 
geopolitical politicsCh inas hegemony, Tibetan 
resistance, Western support of  the resistance (in some 
quarters), international human rights movement 
C. 	 Despite obstacles, studying the relations hip between religion, nation and ethnicity 
(and, sometimes, race) is crucial 
1. 	 Even though it is so varied and complex 
2. 	 Because this relationship so often is extremely important 
III.	 Notion of ethnicity and nationality as  relationships goes for religion as well 
A. 	 How a given religion is born, how it evolves 
1. 	 Depends on its relationship with ot her religions it is in contact with 
2. 	 As well as the relationships between the cultures and societies of its 
adherents and non-adherents 
B. 	 The Hui see themselves as Muslim in  some fashion (even the ones who are not 
practicing Muslims) 
1. 	 And part of their nationality ident ity connects them to Arabia/Persia via 
their religious beliefs a. 	 An identity that in this re spect is not-China, in the sense of not-
Han 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
b. 	 Certainly they are Chinese citizens 
c. 	 But its more complicated, and certainly has changed over time 
2. 	 DISCUSS: provide an example of an ethnic ity or nationality that doesnt 
evoke religion at all 
C. 	 Another example: the relationship be tween colonized people and the colonizers 
1. 	 Colonial powers have greatly in fluenced, over time, the nature of the 
religion(s) practiced in their colonies 
a. 	 Tibetan religion and nationali sm changed as a result of occupation 
by PRC 
1) Here local religi on is a sign of resistance 
2) This happens often 
2. 	 Religions may be introduced by colonizers 
a. 	 Conversion may be coerced 1) The Inca empire, when it overtook other societies 2) African slaves in the U.S. and Caribbean 
b. 	 Or voluntarily adopted (Christi anity in Africa, Islam in many parts 
of the world) 
D. 	 Transnational movement affects religious observance 
1. 	 Buddhist Koreans converted to Chri stianity in substantial numbers when 
they immigrated to U.S. and Canada 
IV. 	 New religions A. Of interest to us because they are so important in ethnic, national processes 
1. 	 All new religions draw on al ready existing religious components 
symbolism, ritual, etc. 
B. New religions may spring up in resp onse to changes, pressures, oppression 
1. 	 Example: Christianity: ancient Is rael was a colony of Imperial Rome 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9
 b. 	 They promote the philosophies/i deologies that undergird them as 
replacements for religion 
c. 	 The cult of Mao Tse Tung in China 
E. Another type are religions that claim to be reviving old, extinct religions 
1. 	 Wicca (witchcraft) in the U.S. and England
 a. 	 No major association with  a current ethnic group, but do link 
themselves to a persecuted group in the past: Druids 
2. 	 Are syncretistic 
V. 	 Forces behind religious change 
A. Are quite often powerfully linked to  nation, ethnicity and related topics 
1. 	 They appear as responses to cr isis, or to felt needs not being met 
2. 	 Changes are threatening, and th e old religion cannot account for them 
3. 	 Fundamentalist movements 
a. 	 Can, but usually dont, produce radical change 
b. 	 The Iranian revolution is an example of radical change connected 
to fundamentalism 
4. 	 DISCUSS: other less sweeping exampl es of fundamentalism?
 a. 	 Revitalization: the Islami c revival movement described by Ong 
B. 	 As a religion grows and becomes estab lished, it will become associated with the 
society that mainstreams it 
1. 	 May not be an entire nation-state, however 
2. 	 Can be the source of a great deal of conflict 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
b. 	 Female genital cutting in areas of northern and central Africa 
c. 	 Such inscriptions serve many purposes 
1) 	 Constantly remind the person they are members of a moral 
communitythey cant do what they like with their bodies 
2) 	 And are emblems: make the person easier to identify as a 
member of X culture; practitioner of X religion
    3 )	 DISCUSS:  does this sound like Nagels definition of ethnic 
identity? 
4) 	 These body inscriptions can  be seen as reminders, internal 
and external 
F. 	 And some religions are found in many parts of the globe, but, like Hinduism, are 
not world religions 
1. 	 Roma (Gypsy) beliefs form part of what makes them distinct 
2. 	 We can say the same for the Hutterites, an Anabaptist sect in Canada and 
the U.S. 
a. 	 Anabaptists broke away from mainstream Protestant religions in 
Europe 
b. 	 Were persecuted; came to  New World (like other persecuted 
religious minoritiesth e Puritans, Quakers) 
1) 	 But Anabaptists chose to remain apart; some continued to 
speak German; the Hutterites live in huge communal farms 
c. 	 Because of missionization, Anabaptists (e.g., Mennonites) are 
found in places like Nicaragua and Paraguay 
II. 	 The relationship between re ligion and ethnic and national identity 
A. 	 Cross-culturally and over time this is  an extremely varied and complicated matter 
B. 	 If your notion of culture follows a cookie- cutter model, if you see cultures as little 
islands, bounded, unchanging, internally homogeneous 
1. Youll have a lot of trouble when you look at the real world  
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
d. 	 Traces of early Judaism in present-day Jewish and Christian 
religions? 1) 	 The lists approved-of prac tices and beliefs in the Bible that 
are no longer acceptable is extensive 
2) 	 Polygyny, stoning to death, slaves, witches 
4. Another influence: concepts and practices from cultural systems that 
existed in between  the original cultural context and the present 
a. 	 Many Orthodox Jewish pract ices actually stem from Central 
European communities practices from the last few centuries
 1) 	 Clothing; shaving the brides head at marriage and donning 
a wig 
2) 	 Arkin mentions the growth of ultra-orthodox Jewish 
observance that includes the wigs and dark suits of 
Eastern European shtetls (p. 726) 
5. 	 There will be stronger connections between the culture that existed at the 
beginning of the religion a nd the present-day culture if its in the same 
location 
a. 	 Islam and Judaism in the Middle East 
b. 	 Both religions developed in  pastoralist (herding as well as 
agriculture), arid societies; these subsistence modes are reflected in 
many ways in texts (e.g., metaphors) and practices 
   c .	 DISCUSS: examples in Christianity? 
C. 	 Missionaries, of course, proselytiz ing a religion, encounter difficulties when 
working among members of a very different culture 
1. 	 The elderly nun interviewed in the video Stolen Generations says that 
earlier she hadnt known that in fact  God was in the Aborigines long 
before the whites came to Australia a. 	 One must have a very ecumeni cal and abstract notion of God to be 
able to believe this 
D. 	 Local variants of world religions can resemble the one-culture-one-religion model 
a bit more 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4
 d. 	 There is an association made between religion, culture, and 
looking Jewish1 
e. 	 Notions of Jewishness as raced can be quite pronounced among 
some categories of Jews 
f. 	 So there will be rulings, for instance, about organ transplants 
g. 	 The optional Kahn reading comes from book on the employment 
of new reproductive technologies in Israel2
 1) 	 Fascinating study of the centrality of reproduction in 
Judaism and Jewish culture 
2) 	 The state makes such treatments available to all Israelis, 
even unmarried secular women 
h. 	 Compare to he doesnt look Catholic 
    1 ) DISCUSS:  what would that mean? 
2) Are you surprised when you see photographs of African 
Catholic bishops and cardinals? 
3. 	 A very different example: young Americans who followed South Asian 
gurus 
a. 	 In the 1970s 
b. 	 Hare Krishna, Rajneesh 
c. 	 Evoked laughter because thei r bodies didnt seem to belong in the 
saffron-colored robes, and th eir shaved heads looked odd 
d. 	 Hinduism, although practiced in many countries 
1) Is quite linked to In dia; not really a world religion 
4. 	 Additional point: many religions alter the body by inscribing religious 
symbols onto it a. 	 Circumcision of Jewish and Muslim males 
1 See Sander Gilman, 1991.  The Jews Body . New York: Routledge. 
2 Kahn, Susan Martha, 2000. Reproducing Jews:  A Cultural Account of Assisted Conception in Israel . Durham: 
Duke University Press. 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ethnic Identity II</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_3_ethn_id_ii/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3
   b .	 DISCUSS:  ways the Hui do not fit into the 4 Stalinist criteria for 
a minority 
4. 	Gladney shows the ways that stat e policies lie behind why the Hui are so 
difficult to define as an ethnic group 
5. 	The state created, invented the cate gory (came up with a legal definition of 
who and who is not a member) 
6. 	Then lumped all Muslims that did not belong to the 9 recognized Muslim 
nationalities into one nationality 
7. 	Hui became basically a default term for groups of Muslims who do not 
have a language of their own 
8. 	We have here a good example of ethnicity as a PROCESS 
III.	 Six ways to analyze ethnic processes1 
A. 	First: evolutionary perspective 
1. 	Sees ethnic groups to be from a pre-modern time 
2. 	Sees ethnicity to be a kind of vestigial feature char acteristic of more 
traditional societies 
3. 	In mid-century U.S. everyone saw ethnicity as incompatible with 
modernity 
4. 	Both the political Right (who subscr ibed to assimilationist models) and 
Left (who employed class models ) predicted its disappearance 
a. 	The Right saw ethnic groups as eventually joining the mainstream 
societyin US, Canada, Europe 
1) 	The melting pot idea 
b. 	The Left saw class solida rity eventually replacing ethnic 
identification and loyalties 
5. 	Clearly, the incompatible with modernity perspective doesnt work, 
never did 
1 These analytic approaches are not mutually exclusive. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
2. 	Nagels notion of ethnic choice refers  to an individual choosing to keep or 
discard an ethnicity
 a. 	This feature, operating over time, explains the varying rates of 
official membership for Native Americans
 3. 	She makes a distinction between rational choice and nonrational choice 
a. 	I dont care for this characterization 
1) 	This terminology comes from a subfield of political science 
called Rational Choice Theory 
b. 	It sets up an either/or, and ranked opposition, whereas in fact such 
choices are often a little of both2
 c. 	Nonrational is  a put-down kind of word 
1) 	Implies that rationa l is a good strategy, understandable, 
the correct choice because it serves the individuals 
interests
 2) 	And implies that nonra tional is due to other reasons 
emotion influencing the choice, for example
 4. 	The idea she discusses is OK: choosing an identity based on a perceived 
advantage in the form of some kind of material or power gain is rational 
a. 	As opposed to. some other kind of motive having to do with 
symbolic meaning, feelings, so ciability, recreational, etc. 
b. 	Lots of the multiculturalis t activities so popular today are 
motivated more by emotions than perceived material gainbut emotions serving as motives are not examples of nonrational in the sense of irrational 
c. 	Ethnic symbols can elic it powerful emotional responses 
d. 	People attend ethnic festivals, take classes in a Celtic language, 
etc., for these reasonsand feeling emotions is not irrational 
5. 	So the notion of instrumentalist motives is useful 
2 See Sonia Alvarez, Evelina Dagnino, Arturo Escobar, 1998.  Introduction: The cultural and the political in Latin 
American social movements.  In Alvarez, Dagnino and Escobar, eds., Cultures of politics, politics of Cultures: Re-
visioning Latin American social movements . Boulder: Westview: 1-32. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
 1) 	Using Arabic or Pe rsian numbers to decide among 
themselves what the price will be, then announcing it to 
Han buyers 
   c .	 
DISCUSS:  ways your speech serves to mark your individual 
portfolio of identities (set  of identity components) 
1) 	In what contexts? What kinds of people have to be present 
for you to perform in this way? 
2. 	Ritual behavior can be seen as a kind of language that serves as an 
emblem of, and a method for, enacting, performing, ethnic and religious identity
   a .	 
DISCUSS : examples of Hui ritual that do this? 
b. 	Dietary restrictions; ritual bathing 
c. 	Gladneys example of the man who refused to drink from a cup of tea Gladney offered because it might  still be contaminated from a 
pork eaters use 
d. 	This man was a Communist , self-avowed atheistalthough he 
went to mosque services 
   e .	 
DISCUSS : a basic powerfulness, ev en horror, related to 
defilement and impurity (p. 28) 
D. 	Fourth: ethnicity as dialectic 
1. 	The Bai, the Tibetans, the Hainan ese Muslims, Cantonese, Shanghainese, 
Fujianese non-Mandarin speakers them selves claim membership in the 
same Hui ethnic group as other Hui in China 
a. Despite linguistic dive rsity and multicultural background 
2. 	This is called ethnogenesis: 
a. 	The birth of, the origin of, a new form of ethnic identity; or, in a 
weaker sense (Nagel), cultural revival 
b. 	Prior to state recognition, th e Hui recognized one another as fellow 
Muslims 1) 	But not as members of the same minzu (nationality) 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3 ETHNI
C IDENTITY II 
Read: 	Gladney 25-54  Nagel: 19-33 
Difficult words encountered in reading: 
Cadre: authorized organizers in a political party or state agency 
Madrassah: Islamic school 
Ethnonym: name of an ethnos/ethnic group Sufism: an Islamic movement, adherent s are located in numerous countries 
Acculturation: movement toward the dominant culture Pogrom: campaign of extermination of local me mbers of an ethnic group , usually referring to 
European Jews 
Hegemonic: will be discussed in the coursepertains to power
 I. 	Ethnicity: what is it and how do we analyze it? 
A. 	Review: weve established that: 
1. 	Ethnicity is best seen  in terms of relationship 
2. 	Ethnicity has to do with cl assification of groups of humans 
B. 	Today well consider ethnicity seen as a process 
1. 	Nagel introduces lots of terms re lated to seeing ethnicity in this way 
C.	 The benefits of this approach: 
1. 	History is brought back in 
2. 	Change is allowed in the analysis 
3. 	People arent seen as ob jectsas Xs throughout time 
a. 	Ethnicity is about classifications of hu mans, but theres a lot more 
to it than that 
b. 	The classifications are dynamictheir meaning changes 
1) The populations that the terms refer to change 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
a. 	It explains some of the ways people move into and out of ethnic 
categories 
b. 	But only some of it 
6.	 There are many examples of challenges to identity choices and the claims 
based on those self-identifications 
a. 	University committees deciding which minorities are 
underrepresentedit happens here 
b. 	Often the challenge is based on assumptions that a person or group 
has chosen to claim an ethnic identity because of perceived gains to be made in so doing 
   c .	 
DISCUSS : some examples? 
d. 	We will read an article by de la Cadena discussing how Quechua 
women in Peru are said to be m ore Indian, more purely Indian 
than Quechua men 
    1 )	 DISCUSS : other examples distinguishing degree of 
belonging by gender? 
F. 	The sixth perspective analyzes ethnic ity as non-choice: a cl assification ascribed 
by the mainstream society 
1. 	We have returned to the state and its interests 
a. 	Examples of state concern about ethnicity: 1) Census 2) Security to the point of internmentwell see a video 
about U.S. internment of Japanese and Japanese-American 
citizens during WW II 
3) Security and economic protectionism: immigration policies 
4) Using ethnicity to dete rmine political acce ss and eligibility
    5 ) 
DISCUSS : examples in the U.S.?  Other countries? 
2. 	The state and other authorities (e.g., religious institutions) may place 
external limits on choice 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9
   a .	 
DISCUSS : examples? 
b. 	The Hui are an example 
c. 	African Americans
 d. 	Ethnic ghettoes 
e. 	Ethnic cleansing (deportation, forced displacement) 
f. 	Killing, pogroms
 g. 	Required ethnic markers 
1) Yellow star of David 
2) Stamping an identity card 
3.	 The ethnic group itself might place inte rnal limits on choice (e.g., options 
for behavior) 
a.	 Dont be a traitor to your group 
    1 ) DISCUSS : examples you can think of? 
2) Dont be a sell-out 
3) Dont be a self-hating Jew 
b. 	Such pressures can be strong, to the point of put someone in 
danger in times of great conflict 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
6. 	Wont explain the Hui, the Ha n, not, even, Native American peoples 
7. 	Cannot answer the question of w hy there has been such a strong ethnic 
resurgence in the U.S. and Europe, Chinaand many other places 
8. 	Clearly we cannot analyze ethnicity  as only a matter of blood (ancestry) 
and soil (territory) 
a. 	Its often characterized this way, and with justification 
b. 	But theres always more to it 
B. 	The second approach: Adaptation 
1. 	Sees ethnic change as  processes of adaptation 
2. 	The Hui provide examples 
a. 	They adapted the Chinese language 
1) 	For example, Gladneys discussion of etymology (origins) 
of the 2 Chinese terms for pure and truth 
b. Adapt their Islamic beliefs  and practices to Confucianism 
c. Include Buddhist architec tural features in their mosques
   d . 
DISCUSS:  other examples of Hui adaptation? 
C. 	Third approach: ethnicity seen as performance 
1. 	For example, a language can serve as emblem of ethnic membership, and 
speaking it permits enactments of ethnic identity a. 	The Huis use of the term s pure and true is an example 
1) These words help the Hui perform, instantiate, their identity 2) These words stand as symbols, emblems that communicate 
ethnic membership to insiders and outsiders alike 
b. 	Gladneys example of Hui ma rket men recognizing one another by 
listening to their speech 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2
 2) 	As does the authoritativ e individual or institution that 
determines which classifications  are the correct, official 
ones 
II. 	Two perspectives can be taken: 
A. 	First perspective: analyze the position of an individual 
1. 	Nagels point that ethnic identity  lies at the inters ection of individual 
ethnic self-definition (w ho I am) and collective ethnic attribution (who 
they say I am) 
a. 	A dialectic between internal identification and external ascription 
B. 	Second perspective involves analyzing the group as a wholefrom its point of 
view and from an external point of view 
1. 	Ethnic identity in this perspectiv e lies at the inters ection of ethnic group 
self-definition (who we say we are) and non-group ethnic attribution (who 
they say we are) 
C. 	Notice the different thrusts of the 2 authors we read for today with respect to this 
point 
1. Nagels perspective is more  individualistic than Gladneys 
D. 	The Hui case suggests we  need a third perspective 
1. 	One that analyzes the state itself
 2. 	And investigates its formulations  of ethnic policies,  the rationales for 
them, the history, etc. 
a. 	And then analyzes why in many cases the state doesnt subscribe 
to its own policies/formulations  
b. 	Bureaucracies are never comple tely rational, coherent, internally 
logical 1) 	They have histories, cultures, power dynamics 
3. 	The state was not using its own crit eria when it classified the Hui into a 
single ethnic groupand this  is not a small matter 
a. 	The Hui were included in th e group of nationalities (minorities) 
initially recognized by the state 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
 2) 	Earlier, their ethnic consciousness was localized, it was not 
China-wide 
c. 	State recognition brough t all Hui closer together 
1) Through dialogue with state policy and local traditions
 2) Examples: pan-Hui interaction, and mandatory Hui 
schools 
3. 	We have a dialectical  relationship here 
a. 	Gladneys point about th e Han looking down on Hui as dirty, 
immoral 
b. 	Whereas the Hui look down on Han because the Hui see 
themselves as more pure and true 
c. 	The same thing happens with Gypsies, also known as Roma (self-
name) 
1) 	Are often considered dirty by mainstream society 
2) 	But Roma consider them selves purer and cleaner than non-
Roma 
a) 	Distinct ways of seeing the body as polluting and 
engaging in rituals of pu rification that non-Roma 
dont performso non-Roma are dirty 
E. 	The fifth perspective: ethnicity seen as choice 
1. 	Nagels discussion of  multilayered ethnicity 
a. 	This analytic perspective counteracts the thingness of most 
notions of ethnic groups 
   b .	 An Indian. A Jew. A Chinese person. Lati nos, HispanicsAfrican 
AmericansAsians 
c. 	While these ascriptions are real, they will definitively categorize an 
individual, a group, only fr om the distant outside 
d. 	This thingness invariably dissolves the closer we getmultiple 
identities, layers of identity components 
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Culture Recovery</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_19_nag/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Study Questions 
Nagel 83-105 and 113-141 

1. 	 Discuss some of the problems with the concept of race as used by the U.S. Census 
Bureau. 
2. 	 Nagel says that the Census Bureaus formul as and categories suggest that there is a role 
played by the politics of race and et hnicity in the census.  Discuss.
 3. 	 Nagel speaks of the discrepancy between race and ancestry.  Discuss.
 4. 	 What impressions did you have of the U.S. censuss figures on race prior to reading this 
chapter in Nagel?  In what ways are these figures important (what kinds of cultural, 
political work do these statistics do)? 
5. 	 Researchers have concluded that most Af rican Americans marked black/Negro. (p. 
87) What is the issue here? 
6. 	 Nagel quotes Forbes as estimating that the American Indian population is vastly 
undercounted. For example, an additional seven  to eight million persons classified as 
Spanish are of Native American ancestry.  (p. 89) What is Forbes definition of 
American Indian? What is yours? 
7. 	 Spanish-speaking Caribbean countries produce populations seen to be  white (Hispanics 
are assigned to the white category).  Wh at happens to French speakers, English 
speakers and Dutch speakers who migrate fr om the Caribbean to the U.S.? (p. 89) 
8. 	 What is hypodescent? What is bl ood quantum? Why, according to Forbes, are 
researchers always finding Blacks and always losing Indians? (p. 91) 
9. 	 Explain the 700 percent increase in  Native Americans between 1900 and 1990.  
10. 	 Why do 7.1 million Americans claim Indian  ancestry but only 1.36 million Americans 
list their race as Indian? 
11. 	 Briefly describe Nagels characterization of those Americans who appear to have changed their ethnic identifica tion from non-Indian to Indian. 
12. 	 Describe the emergence of Red Power activis m. What, according to Nagel, contributed to 
its appearance and growth? 
13. 	 What indicators of assimila tion were present during the 20
th century? (p. 114) 
14. 	 Nagel speaks of a paradoxthat assimilation processes set into motion and fueled 
American Indian ethnic renewal. Explain. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
15. 	 What was the Indian New Deal legislat ion of 1934 (IRA)? What kind of politics did it 
emerge out of? What was the policy known as  termination (1946-1960)? What kind of 
politics lay behind th is legislation? 
16. 	 Describe the changes in American Indian  communities that resulted from WW II. 
17. 	 Describe Indian re newal in urban areas. 
18. 	 Describe the social and political cont ext of The Civil Rights Era. (p. 122) 
19. 	 How was the Bureau of Indian Affa irs undermined during the 1970s and 1980s? 
20. 	 Was the occupation of Alcatraz Island a success or a failure? 
21. 	 A mother on a reservation came to refer to her son as My son, th e Indian. What does 
this phrase allude to ? Why is it funny? 
22. 	 Describe supratribal Indian id entity. In what ways is this a new identity, a new ethnic 
group? In what ways not? 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Human Rights, Collective Rights</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_21_mes_nag/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
15. 	 Describe the atmosphere created by the poli tics of civil rights in the 1960s. List three 
themes (p. 223). 
16. 	 Nagel mentions The White Mans Burden (p. 224). What kind of burden is this? 
17. 	 Compare the relationship between federally recognized Indian tr ibes and unrecognized 
tribes seeking recogni tion, to the relationship between various Hui communities and the 
Chinese state. Similarities? Differences? 
18. 	 What are your criteria for determin ing who is really an Indianhas the right  to be 
considered indigenous? Defend your criteria. 
19. 	 Should people who self-identify as Indian but who are not enrolled members of a tribe 
qualify for jobs intended for Indians?  Discuss. 
20. 	 Compare the Red Power and Black Power movements (p. 247). 
21. 	 Discuss the differences in how rights were conceived in the two movements. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Study Questions 
Messer, Nagel 213-228, 234-248 

1. 	 Why did the American Anthropological Asso ciation object to the Universal Declaration 
of Human Rights? 
2. 	 Provide two examples of variation in the wayhuman rights is conceptualized. 
3. 	 What are human rights? Civil rights? What are r ights? What rights do people have, in 
your opinion? 
4. 	 Name some Non-Governmental Organizations (NGOs) concerned with rights. 
5. 	 Describe the evolution of human rights discourse from its beginning to the present. Why 
did this discourse begin when it did? What  issues became more prominent during the 
1970s? (Messer, p. 323) 
6. 	 What kinds of development projects have resulted in protes ts about disregard of human 
rights, according to Messer? 
7. 	 What should be the aims of international development? What impedes international 
development projects full observance of their target communities human rights? 
8. 	 Describe the difference between a universal  language of human ri ghts and and a language 
of culture-specific rights. 
9. 	 What is cultural relativism? Discuss Wh ite Shamans and Plastic Medicine Men with 
respect to this difference. 
10. 	 Discuss the issue of indigenous intellectu al property rights (Me sser p. 331). What kinds 
of rights are threatened? Incl ude White Shamans and Plas tic Medicine Men in your 
discussion. 
11. 	 Nagel says that throughout U.S. history fe deral Indian policy ha s shifted between two 
essentially contradictor y goals. What are they? 
12. 	 I have utterly no patience w ith those who think more about Indian culture than they do 
about Indians (p. 214). Place this statements within an ideological framework. Within a 
human rights framework. 
13. 	 Nagel lists four factors contri buting to the reversal of fede ral termination policy (p. 220). 
What were these? 
14. 	 Nagel discusses Tarrows notion of prote st spread (p. 221). Describe and illustrate. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ethnic Conflict I</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_10_may_el_r/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Study Questions on Maybury-Lewi
s 81-103 (Genocide)  
and Eller 195-241 (Rwanda and Burundi) 
1. 	 Compare what Eller says about the shifting na ture of the categorical  designations Hutu 
and Tutsi to Gladneys anal ysis of the category Hui. 
2. 	 Describe the role played by European racial aesthetics and racism in the received wisdom 
regarding differences between  the Hutu and the Tutsi. 
3. 	 Compare and contrast the Rwandan genocide with the Third Reichs final solution. 
4. 	 What did you know about the categories H utu and Tutsi prior to reading Maybury-
Lewiss and Ellers essays? Wh at did you know about the genocide in Rwanda? In what 
ways did these essays change your understanding of the situation? 
5. 	 Discuss the ethnogenesis of the Hutu and Tutsi categories as et hnic groups. What did 
these categories mean prior to colonizatio n? How did colonization change them? What 
happened to them following independence, in  particular what were the effects of 
instituting democratic rule? 
6. 	 On p. 83, Maybury-Lewis discusses indirect rule (also see p. 212 of Eller). What does 
this mean? 
7. 	 What conclusions can we draw from the Rwanda and Burundi cases about the likelihood 
of ethnic conflict becoming seriously vi olent, to the point of genocide? 
8. 	 Describe the arguments made by Tutsi for why they should rule Rwanda (Eller, p. 226). 
Describe those made by Hutu. 
9. 	 Eller says that Hutu and Tutsi were achieved  statuses almost as much as they were 
ascribed  ones (p. 202). What do these terms mean ? How did an individual or a family 
achieve one or the other status? 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Culture: Definitions</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_9_cul_def/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
1) 	The worlds cultures were seen to live in distinct 
geographical territories 
a) Culture made places out of spaces 
2) 	Although some members might have left: for example, 
overseas Chinese 
b. 	An isomorphism of place and culture  was assumed 
3. 	What are the problems we encount er if we link cu lture with place? 
a. 	The Hue: how does a space achieve a distinctive identity as a 
Hue place? 
b. 	What is the real England, and what relationship does it have to a 
particular bounded place? 1) 	By the end of the 20
th century England is more an imagined 
state of being or moral loca tion than an actual place 
c. Related problematic concepts: native land, homeland, real 
American, American culture (America is a place) 
4. 	This definition (a culture) also highlights the fact that culture, like ethnicity, is relational : it exists because there is something not-it: it can be 
compared to something 
a. 	This is the idea behind saying its a difference of culture 
b. 	We can say MIT culture and people know were talking about 
MIT, as opposed to Harvard or BU culture 
c. 	This relational feature is especially important to keep in mind 
1) 	First, because of the importance of inter-cultural (inter -
ethnic, inter-national, etc.) relations in the real world 
a) Ethnic conflict, for instance 
2) 	Second, because understanding that a culture always exists 
in relation to other cultures often allows  us to uncover sites 
of powerasymmetrical re lations involving dominance 
and subordination, etc. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
1. 	A member of a culture might even be aware that part of their culture is not 
in their best interests 
a. 	But they might very well  keep on doing/thinking/believing 
whatever it is 
2. 	What role does individual human agency play? 
3. 	We arent automatons 
4. 	But neither are we free agents alwa ys able to know whats in our best 
interest and freely carry it out a. 	Were not Little monads guided solely by internal reasons 
(Bourdieu and Wacquant
1) 
5. 	Nagel puts the difference this way: 
a. 	Culture as structure (a sy stem that defines and shapes human 
thought and action) 
b. 	And cultural construction (a process by which culture is defined 
and shaped by human thought and action) 
6. 	DISCUSS: something you continue to do even though you know its not 
in your best interest? 
a. 	Is this entrenched cultural habit or neurosis? 
1 Pierre Bourdieu and Loic Wacquant, 1992. An Invitation to Reflexive Sociology . Chicago: University of Chicago 
Press: 135. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>9 CULTURE: DEFINITIONS 
Read: 	Eriksen, The social organisation of cultural distin ctiveness, 43-69  
Nagel, Constructing culture, 43- 54; Deconstructing ethnicity, 60-72 
Richard Handler, 1985. On having a cultu re: nationalism and the preservation of 
Quebecs patrimoine 
Definitions 
A. 	As is the case for most of our ot her analytic terms, culture is polysemic 
1. 	It has multiple, related meanings 
a. 	Think of the various concepts  of culture offered in the pieces by 
Eriksen, Nagel, and Handler 
2. 	Related to the culture in agricu lture; also, think of  culturing microbes 
in a petri dish a. 	The piece well read by Mal kki later on discusses agricultural 
metaphors, for example, a cultu re is rooted in a place 
b. 	Nagel says that one image of Native Americans is that theyre 
rooted.
  3 .	  DISCUSS:  Your definition of culture? 
a. 	Connections between ear lier meaning and your definition? 
B. 	One definition: culture is be liefs and practices  shared by a group 
1. 	Very common definition 
a. 	Culture is clearly not the idiosyncratic beliefs and behavior 
peculiar to one person 
2. 	Nagel (p. 43): Those ideational and material aspects of social life 
language, religion, ceremony, myth, belief,  values.are the substance of a 
people. 
3. 	DISCUSS:  possible problems with this definition? 
a. 	First, like nation and et hnicity, what/who are the people who 
share this culture is difficult to specify 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
b. 	Not self-evident, even though you may think it is 
c. 	Second, all cultural system s to some degree depend on their 
members not sharing the same knowledge or beliefs 
1) 	For example, even in very small-scale, seemingly 
homogeneous societies 
a)	 Men and women will not share the same cultural 
knowledgeand this non-sharing will be built in, 
not accidental 
2) 	In modern societies 
a) 	The management, foreman, and workers in a factory 
will not share the same understandings of the institution they all work in 
b) 	This non-sharing also is built inits necessary for 
the proper function of the factory 
     c )	 DISCUSS: MIT examples 
4. 	Definition cant hand le change very well 
a.	 All those examples in Eriksen of  people leaving one culture for 
another (Fur, Bagara in Da rfur, studied by Haaland) 
5. 	Nor can it handle complex ethnic intera ctions, in which all actors share the 
rules for interaction, even though th ey belong to different cultures 
C. 	Another definition: high culture : literature, ballet, opera, poetry: Culture 
D. 	Another: the notion of a culture: Eskimo culture, Polynesian culture, African-
American culture, Norwegian culture 
1. 	Note that only one of these exam ples of culture is coterminous with a 
nation-state 
2. 	But three are located in spaceth e exception is African-American culture 
a. 	Anthropologists (and others) traditionally saw several kinds of 
divisions between cultures 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
d. 	Nagel, Handler and other authors weve read (e.g., Harrison) illustrate the important role power differentials can play
 1) 	And how important it is to analyze the images one culture 
has of another 
2) 	The native art markets mentioned by Nagel, and the 
tourism 
E. 	Another idea of culture: as adaptation 
1. 	This concept of culture-as-adaptati on seeks to explain why culture exists 
in the first place and why it changes
 2. 	Helps us understand the cultural evolution that has occurred during homo 
sapiens history on the planet 
3. 	Previous lecture mentioni ng different subsistence modes 
Hunting/gathering, horticulture, nomadic pastoralis ts, agrarian states 
a. 	These are adaptations cultural adaptationsto a specific 
environment 
1) 	Interactions between environment and culture that are adaptive enough to allo w the group to survive 
a) 	Technology is an aspect  of culture in this definition 
b) 	Such cultural evolu tion brought us to our glorious 
position at presentwe are able to live in many environments, some of them quite inhospitable 
c) 	And weve gained enough power over the 
environment to turn it into a cinder 
2) 	The emergence of a technology that permitted 
horticultureproducing (growing) ones food rather than gathering it 
a) 	Is an example of cultural evolution 
b) 	We can see it as adaptive because it allowed more 
food to be produced, allowed a more secure food supply, etc. 
4. Keep in mind when using this culture-as-adaptation definition: 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
a. 	That whats good for a group as a wholewhat enhances its 
probability of survivaldoesnt al ways mean good for all of the 
individuals w ithin the group 
b. 	Theres a constant te nsion, as a matter of fact 
c. 	Poor people dont benefit from  being members of a given culture 
the way rich people do 
1) 	Example: producing food introduces a much higher 
possibility of plagues of insects, famines, etc., than is the 
case for hunter-gatherer-foragers 
2) 	People will starve ev en though food is available because 
certain cultural understandi ngs and power relations 
withhold it from them 
5. 	Remember: adaptive is always a relative term: Adaptive for what? For 
whom? Over what time span? In  what kind of environment? 
6. 	DISCUSS:  Other examples of authorized cu ltural practices not in the best 
interest of certain sectors or individuals? 
a. 	Mandated suicide
 1) 	Kamikaze pilots 
b. Although we say that mandated suicide is unfortunate for the 
individual; perhaps we say it shouldnt have to happen 
1) This probably isnt the viewpoint of the individual 
c. 	Other examples of cultural practices arguably not in the best 
interest of the individual practitioners? 1) 	Fasting, going to th e wilderness and eating honey and 
locusts, Plains Indians participating in the Sun Dance, 
breast implants, foot bindi ng, high heels, infibulation, 
botox injections 
     a )	 T a t o o i n g ? 
2) 	People outside the culture will probably see these practices, 
and the ideology supporting them, as unhealthy, unnecessary, morally wrong, etc. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
3) People inside the culture will defend them 
7. 	When using this definition remember that cultures are never perfectly 
adaptive and adapted 
a. 	And that a given culture may in fact be very maladaptive at a 
particular point in time due to changing conditions, ecological or 
social 
8. 	Nagels book has many examples of the adaptability of culture 
a. 	A given case might illustrate the process of assimilation, or show a 
successful way to resist  assimilation pressures 
F. 	Another definition of cult ure: that which is taught 
1. 	Not simply that which is learned 
a. 	Many animals learn all sorts of things, but we wouldnt say they 
have culture 
b. 	A child will learn that fire is hot and painful, but this lesson is not 
provided by the childs culture if the learning comes from touching 
the stove flame and being burned 
2. 	The notion of culture-as-teaching conveys the idea of intentional 
transmission 
a. 	But we can argue that a lot of  culture is not deliberately taught 
3. 	In fact, much of the culture one  learns is embodied, and learned half-
consciously or unconsciously 
a. 	This is Bourdieus notion of habitus, described by Nagel, also 
mentioned by Eriksen 
b. 	A set of assumptions, disposit ions, and orientat ions that shape 
human thought and action, visions of  the possible, the perceived 
choices 
c. 	This is why if youve learned one culture, its hard to adjust to a 
new one 
G. 	The question of Free Will 
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Race III</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_14_omi_win/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>QUESTIONS ON OMI &amp; WINANT, AND HI
LL
 1. 	 Omi and Winant state that  race is now a preeminently political phenomenon (p. 126).  
Discuss. Do you agree? 
2. 	 Omi and Winant argue that race has no fixed meaning.  Do you agree? Why do they 
say this?   
3. 	 What is hegemony (Omi and Winant, p. 127) ?  How can this concept help us understand 
racialization and racism?   
4. 	 Discuss Omi and Winants notion of racial projects.  What makes some racial projects 
racist and others not? Give an example of each.
 5. 	 Hill also talks about projects (pp 20-21) .  Compare to Omi and Winants use of the 
word. 
6. 	 Were the members of the association of bl ack social workers who maintained that black 
children should only be adopted by black  parents racist?  Defend your position.
 7. 	 What is an ideologue ?  Give one example. 
8. 	 Is affirmative action an example of reverse racism?  De fend your position. 
9. 	 Omi and Winant differentiate between ideolo gical and structural causes of racism (p. 134 
and previous discussion). Describe both concepts. 
10. 	 What is the distinction between racial awareness and racial essentialism (Omi and Winant 
p. 131)?  What is essentialism?  Give 3 exampl es of essentialism not related to race (if 
you can, from our readings). 
11. 	 Omi and Winant state (p. 130) that Bob Bl auner has found that some non-white students 
maintain that blacks cannot be racist.  Defend this position using these students 
argument.  Critique it.  
12. 	 Describe Omi and Winants racial formati on theory.  Link it to racial project. 
13. 	 Use the concept of hegemony to discuss Hills essay. 
14. 	 How do Omi and Winant differ from cl assic Marxist understandings of racism? 
15. 	 If someone perpetuates racism but is unawa re of doing so, under what circumstances are 
they racist?  Under what circumstances are th ey not be racists?  Provide an example of 
both. Gold stars if you can do this using examples from Hill. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
16. 	 What are the differences between the biologi cal dimensions of se x/gender and those of 
race?  How does racism resemble sexism? 
17. 	 Why is the average household net worth of Afri can Americans less than one-tenth of 
White households (Hill p. 3)? 
18. 	 What does Jim Crow refer to? 
19. 	 How can a sociopolitical phenomenon have bi ological effects?  Provide 3 examples. 
20. 	 What is black exceptionalism (Hill, p. 16)? 
21. 	 Describe Foucaults use of  discourse (Hill, p. 19). 
22. 	 Give 5 examples of white privilege .  Try to come up with unobvious ones. 
23. 	 Counter-intuitively, the ten most racially segreg ated cities in the U.S. are in the North and 
the ten most racially integrated  cities are in the South.  Ha ving read Hill, discuss what 
produced these patterns. 
24. 	 Give 3 examples of actions that perpetuate racism yet are neither intentionally nor 
unconsciously racist. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Nation and Nationalism II</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_5_nat_n_nat/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
2. 	Each nation is the product of partic ular, localized, or re gional historical 
conjunctures 
3. 	Its not like classifying bird s or lizards, where you can work out a priori 
criteria 
4. 	The criteria themselves are fuzzy, shifting and ambiguous (language, 
ethnicity) 
5. 	Hobsbawm:
 a. 	Defining a nation by its member s consciousness of belonging to it 
b. 	Is tautological (a circul ar argument), and provides only an a 
posteriori  (afterwards) guide to what a nation is 
6. But, Hobsbawm says that an initial working assumption might be: 
a. 	Any sufficiently large body of people whose members regard 
themselves as members of a nation 
7. 	DISCUSS: Exceptions?
 a. 	Israel? 
1) Is Israel a Jew ish state?  If so, why? 
2) Is Israel a Jew ish nation?  If so, why? 
b. 	Other examples? 
1) 	Gladney: if Tibet we re a free state, there would be 
similarities in how that stat e and its citizens would be 
conceptualizedTibetanwould be close to a nation-state 
II. 	History of the concept of nation 
A. Root meaning of word: naissance, or igin, descent (ancient French dictionary) 
1. 	Nacin was an aggregate of the inhabitants of a territory 
2. 	Could be a provin ce, a country, a kingdom 
a. Was used when speaking of foreigners 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
1. 	There was no historical precedent whatever for the formation of Yugoslavia 
2. 	No one questioned existing states multinationalityin Britain, France, 
Spain 
a. What these minority people felt wasnt considered important 
1) 	And many individuals be longing to these groups did favor 
unification 
b. 	Many felt they were better offbigger is better 
1) 	How, it was asked, could the Slovenes possibly manage by 
themselves? 
3. 	Evolutionary ideology was very strong: these small groups, languages, 
were seen to be doomed as civilization progressed 
   a .	 DISCUSS: examples of doomed European languages you know about that didnt die out? 
b. 	The evolution to larger units  was seen as following natural law 
inevitable
 c. 	Society was to evolve from family and tribe to a nation-state 
d. 	From the local to the regional,  the national and eventually global 
1) 	Familiar idea that at the next phase in human evolution, ethnic and national barriers  will melt and dissolve 
2) 	Attempts to construc t artificial wo rld languages (e.g., 
Esperanto) are an example 
4. 	Folklorization processes of cultures and languages 
a. 	Campaigns to preserve the dialects 
b. 	A new idea that contradicted th e notion that these variants should 
be eliminated, in order to fost er national unity through a single 
standardized language 1) 	Spaces opened up for thick Irish and Scottish accents on the 
stageso long as safely reduced to appendages 
(Hobsbawm) 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9 
2) Songs in Neapolitan became positively valorized
 c. 	Folk museums were built; anth ropologists were hired to recover 
oral traditions, etc. 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>5 and 6 NATION AND NATIONALISM I, II 
Read: Read: Eriksen, 2002. Nationalism. In Eriksen, Ethnicity and Nationalism: 
Anthropological Perspectives  (3
rd ed.). London: Pluto Press: 117-146 
Simon Harrison, 1999. Identity as a scarce resource.  Social Anthropology  7 (3), 
239-251 
I. 	Nation as linked to a state is a NEW idea 
A. 	The modern sense of the word is no older than the 18th century 
1. 	The word and related words have been around 
2. 	DISCUSS: other meanings? a. 	What does Indian nation, Cherokee Nation suggest to you? 
b. Can we say American nation?  Why or why not? 
c United Nations, Wealth of Nations? 
1) 	Could the UN just as easily be United Countries?  Or 
United States? (except that ones taken) 
B. 	Nations, in the sense of  nation-states are also new 
1. 	Nation, state, country, nation-state 
2. 	DISCUSS: provide examples of actual na tion-statesstates that contain 
only one nation, one people a. 	There really arent many 
b.	 Dominican Republic (unusual for Caribbean) and Oceania 
c. 	Japan almost qualifies (non-Japanese: Ainu, Koreans) 
C. 	How can we define nation? 
1. 	One author, Eric Hobsbawm, says we cant characterize nation-states 
using an a priori (established beforehand), objective set of distinctions 
that allows us to distinguis h a nation from other entities 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
 a. 	Contends that this developm ent is intricately tied to colonial 
activity in the rest of the world 
3. 	It is clear that nation ideology was closely linked to the development of 
modern states 
4. 	A great deal of literature is concerned with this issue2 
B. 	Empires did not see the need for a single people 
1. 	In fact, they exploited these differences: worked to increase divisions 
between subjects 
a. 	For example, the idea of ethnic soldieringbring in soldiers 
from a different ethnicity/count ry to reduce the likelihood of 
alliances between civilians and military 
b. 	At times rulers used soldiers belonging to an ethnic group that was 
the traditional enemies of the population 
C. 	The idea emerged that strong states need citizens who th ink alike and share 
identity in various ways 1. 	Notion of the right to rule conf erred by divinity wa s losing legitimacy 
a. 	All states claim a monopoly on use of legitimate force 
b. 	But is very costly if force is the main way of maintaining rule 
2. 	Citizens of a state ideally would embrace one language, one heritage, one 
religion, etc., and so would agree to being ruled a. 	Loyalties to other groups came to be seen to compete with loyalty 
to the nation-state (family, religion) 
b. 	Familiar idea? 
    1 ) DISCUSS: current examples? 
3. 	During the 19
th century many subject populations made the argument that 
a people need to be sovereign 
4. 	Newly recognized states legiti macy was based on concept of nation 
2 See Benedict Anderson, 1983. Imagined Communities: Reflections on the origin and spread of nationalism . 
London, Verso.  Ernest Gellner, 1983.  Nations and Nationalism. Oxford: Basil Blackwell. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
3. 	Words for homelandones ow n place, township, land of birth:  patria, 
tierra
 a. 	Territory of originpays natal  (Old French) 
B. 	Meanings in the languages th at used some form of nation: 
1. 	German: foreigner (a loan word, contrasted with volk) 
2. 	Territory of origin 
3. 	Common descent groupethnicity 
4. 	Speaking the same language 
5. 	We could consider Castile, in Spai n to be one of the earliest European 
kingdoms approximating the nation-state idea 
a. 	A bounded territory, a political unit, inhabitants s poke the Castilian 
language and shared the no tion of being Castilian 
C. 	In the 19
th century in Europe, nation and na tionalism developed in stages: 
1. 	Originally seen as something purel y cultural, literary and folkloric, not 
political 
2. 	A body of pioneers and militants began promoting the national idea in 
several countriesthey were urban elites 
3. 	Then nationalist programs start to acquire mass support 
D. 	This process sometimes occurs 
1. 	Before the creation of a na tional state: Ireland 
2.	 Sometimes afterwards: We have ma de Italy, now we have to make 
Italians
 3. 	Sometimes never 
   a .	 DISCUSS: Third World examples of #3? 
E. 	The meaning changed over the 19th century to include notion of a political body 
1. 	Earlier: simply the people; later,  the idea that this unit of people should 
have a government 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
III.	 Eighteenth century ideas about the people 
A. American and French revolutions: ideas about one nation and one state 
1. 	American colonists were disti nguished from King George and his 
supporters neither by ethnicity nor language 
2. 	At that time, many of the modern me anings of nation simply didnt exist 
a. 	Ethnicity, common la nguage, religion, territory 
b. 	A common history, historical me mories shared by those seeking to 
establish themselves as a separate state 
3. 	American goal: overthrow colonial  oppressor, be independent of England 
4. 	French: overthrow rgime and th e entire fixed hierarchy of royalty, 
nobility, clergy (Catholic Church), and replacing it with Liberty, 
Brotherhood, Equality 
B. 	Always present: the element of citizenship and mass participation 
1.	 And desire to be a national state 
2. 	French revolutionaries called one another citizen 
IV. 	In the nineteenth century: 
A. The principle of nationality gained  ground: its primary meaning was political 
1. 	A people should constitute a state 
B. 	Eric Hobsbawm1 discusses major arguments that took place about the necessary 
preconditions 
1. 	Had to be viable (c ulturally, economically, size) 
2. 	Many arguments were made about size throughout the 19th century 
a. 	Ridiculous that Belgium and Portugal be states 
   b .	 DISCUSS: examples of very small states today?  Problems? 
1 Eric Hobsbawm, Introduction.  Nation as Novelty.  Pp. 1-45 in Nations and Nationalism since 1780: Programme, 
myth, reality .  Cambridge, 1990. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
3. 	After World War I, the princip le of nationality appeared in peace 
treaties 
a. 	Produced a Europe of 26 states  (27 if we add Irish Free State) 
b. 	None of these were then, nor are now, nation-states  (i.e., a single 
people) 1) 	A recent study of regionalist movements in W. Europe 
alone counts 42 of them 
4. 	Notion of self-determination 
a. 	Yes the idea was present in independence movements (Latin 
America) during the century 
1) 	Except for Haitis in 1804, which no one accepted, really
 b. 	Empire was still very  much present in Europe 
c. 	The notion of each people needing to be independent and 
sovereign evolved during the late 19
th and early 20th century 
C. 	But how to establish criteria for a people? 
1. The French people did not all speak French, by any means 
a.	 The requirement that they speak French became a characteristic of French state-building 
b.	 Eriksen: speaking Breton was forbidden 
   b .	 DISCUSS:  other examples of imposition of a state language? 
V. 	Ideology of state = nation = people continued to develop 
A. 	Why this evolution from empires? 
1. 	DISCUSS: examples of empires 
a. 	British, French, Hapsburg, Ottoman 
2. 	An optional reading for next Mondays (Oct. 3) class by Segal and 
Handler 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
a. Belgium, Serbia, Greece, Romania, Bulgaria 
5. Changes in the economic system also supported the shift 
a. 	Each territorially circumscri bed state tended to pursue mercantilist 
policies as a unified whole 
b. 	Extra-territorial, transnational units played a larger role  
1) Both prior to the nation-building period and currently 
2) Earlier: Hanseatic Leag ue in Northern Europe is an 
example3
    3 )	 DISCUSS: present-day extra-territorial, transnational 
units? 
a) International markets, international trade 
agreements, European Union 
c. Note that empires we re still very much present 
1) 	But they were colonial empires 
2) 	Note that various populations in Europe continued to feel 
they were under colonial rule 
3) 	June 28, 1914 Archduke Franz Ferdinand, Austro-
Hungarian assassinated by a Bosn ian nationalist, in effect 
beginning WWI 
VI. 	How Nationalism was employed 
A. 	Nationalist moveme nts gained in strength 
1. 	National unification or expansion 
a. 	Germany, Italy, Greeks 1) 	At the moment of Italys unification, 2 % of the 
population spoke Italian 
B. 	Hobsbawm points out that the c oncept of nation was manipulated 
3 An alliance of trading guilds existing from the Middle Ages to the Early Modern period (from the 13th to 17th 
centuries) that monopolized trade in the Baltic and some parts of the North Sea. 
7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Language and Culture, Ethnicity, Race</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_18_lang_ethn/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
1. 	 Depends on the politicsand languag e politics can be volatile, stubborn 
and, at times, very bloody 
2. 	Why? 
a. 	 Symbolic claims tend to be absolute 
b. 	 If you identify your fortunes with those of your language, if you 
see the status of your language to reflect your own sense of dignity and self-reflect 
c. 	 Its difficult to find a compromise 
D. 	 Language links political claims to ownership 
1. With psychological demands fo r the affirmation of group worth 
E. 	 In 1964 a young man in the S. Indian city  of Tiruchirapalli set himself afire while 
shouting Death to Hindi!  May Tamil flourish! 
1. 	 Nine others committed suicide over the same issue the next year 
2. 	 A researcher examining these instances of violence
8: 
a. 	 Shows that its not just  linguistic nationalism European-style 
b. 	She documents how devotional practices to the language are seen 
as devotion to the embodiment of a languageMother Tamil 
c. 	 Devotees say the practice date s from antiquity, but the devotion in 
fact began in the late 19th century
 d. 	Reaction to the colonial govern ments linguistic literature that 
classed Sanskrit as the classi cal language of the Aryans 
e. 	 And Tamil as a vernacul ar language of the Dravidians 
F. 	 Like ethnic claims in general, language claims are ma de in a moral, categorical 
manner 
1. 	 The problem is that in a multilingu al state there has to be a language 
policy 
8 Sumathi Ramaswamy, Passions of the Tongue: Language Devotion in Tamil India, 1891-1970 . Berkeley: U 
California Press, 1977. 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
1. 	 We dont have many of the problems other countries have 
2. 	 What problems do we have? 
a. 	Arguments about bilingual education 
1) Legislation that prohib its the use of Spanish in schools 
2) Official English legislation 
a) Speak American 
3) Nonstandard English spoken by some African Americans 
b. 	Hills 1999 article and 2008 book discuss ethnoracial domination 
via speech of White English speakers and Spanish speakers 
perceived as non-white or not-quite-white 
B. 	 Other examples of linguistic repression in the US? 
1. 	Native American children were forbidden to use their language in 
boarding school 
2. 	 Immigrant children forbidden to speak to each other in German, Italian, 
etc., in school, even if  they were siblings 
C. 	The class site contains a ne wspaper article on English and French in 
Quebec6; things have softened, bilingualism is growing 
1. 	 Use of the one or the other languag e isnt a political st atement nearly as 
much as it used to be 
a. The Handler article you read on Quebec 
2. 	 A lot of people resented the very stringent legislation th at required French 
for EVERYTHING, required the French  word to appear before the 
English
 a. 	Even imported merchandise ha d to have French (we see it on many 
packages here) 
   b .	 DISCUSS: good thing?  Bad thing? 
6 Krauss, Clifford, 2003.  Quebec seeking to end its old cultural divide: Getting along in English and en Franais. 
New York Times  April 13. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
7. 	 Think of men and women speaking in lower-class registers in the USA 
the men retain their masculinity, th e women come across as vulgar, 
assertive, crude, etc. 
8. 	 The Hill chapter makes this point using the double negative feature of 
working-class speech (p. 37) 
B. 	Jane Hill3 studies the correlation between languages and classethnic/race 
prejudice of a very subtle kind 
1. 	 Shows how nuanced and subtle some of this majority linguistic dominance 
can be 
2. 	 We tend to see Mock Spanish as funny, harmlessif you cant appreciate it, youre too PC (politically correct) 
a. 	No way, Jos 
b. 	 But she suggests that it enacts dominance every time its used
 3. 	DISCUSS: examples? a. 	The Big Enchilada 
b. 	Remember: just because a raci st joke is funny doesnt cancel out 
the fact that it is racist 
III.	 Language  as Symbol of Identity 
A.	 Example: Gender 1. 	 Quite often when two languages or two dialects of the same language are 
in contact and theres friction, it will be about class as well as ethnic issues 
2.	 Asymmetric power relations, different economic options 
3. 	 These identities will also be gendered and often classed 
4. 	 De la Cadenas Women are more Indian, the article on Peru 
a.	 As a rule, indigenous women are more likely to be monolingual;  
3Jane Hill, 1999.  Language, ra ce, and white public space.  American Anthropologist  100 (3): 680-689. Also, 2008, 
The Everyday Language of White Racism . Malden, MA: Wiley-Blackwell. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9 
2. 	 What language will be used in Parliame nt, in official letters, on road signs, 
etc.? 
a. 	When driving around Wales and Scotland in the 1990s one could 
see road signs in English crossed out and Welsh or Scottish Celtic 
spray-painted in 
3. So its easy for some groups to see a language policy as domination 
G. 	Language issues are symbolically capable  of weaving together claims to exclude 
others with claims to sh ore up uncertain group worth 
1. 	 Clearly much is at stake 
2. 	 Policy choices have consequences for careers, for social-class mobility, 
bureaucratic effectiveness 
3. 	 A groups language being given offici al status may aid the performance of 
its members 
H. 	Also, there will be struggles over the suitability of a given language 
1. 	 Measured by comparison to European language 
2. 	 The appropriateness of a given language is contested 
3. 	 Northern Sudan dismisses the contribution of the Southern tongues to human culture 
4. 	 Tamils Dravidian heritage seen as rich 
5. 	 Bengali heritage seen as rich 
6. 	 It can be galling for those who c onsider their language to have a rich 
tradition to have to trade what is in their eyes a richer linguistic heritage 
for a poorer one 
7. 	 One reason English plays such an impor tant role in India, despite its status 
as the language of th e colonial oppressors 
8. 	Multilingual states usua lly have to perpetuate the colonial language as the 
interethnic link 
a. 	Thereby preserving the advantag es of the advanced, most educated 
group 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
 b. 	Speech would still enact, would still instantiate the differences and 
the power asymmetry  
c. 	As does non-verbal behavior 
    1 ) DISCUSS: examples? 
IV. 	 Linguistic nationalism: Language as symbol of the nation 
A. Nation-building in Europe linked nation with culture with language 
1. 	 Eriksens example of the campaign to turn Norway into a nation-state 
a. 	 The language Nynorsk was created because the Norwegian being 
spoken was seen by nationalists as  too polluted by Danish (who 
controlled the territory that turned into Norway) 
1) Ivar Aasens led the effort 
b. 	 In addition, the goal of having a truly unifying, democratic national 
language led the linguist  who created it to gather lexicon (words) 
and grammatical constructions from all over Norway 
2. 	Esperanto is also an invented language composed of several languages 
a. 	But Esperanto intended to overcome nationalism as well as 
improve communication 
B. 	 Linguistic problems arising in other European countries due to nation-building 
projects 1. 	Basque regions,
5 Wales, Scotland, Catalonia (in Spain), many other places 
2. 	Ireland 
3. 	The Linke article a. 	 Because of Nazism, racialized nationalism is problematic in 
Germany, so a shift is made to languagewhich can be seen to represent other domains of Germanness 
V. 	 Post-colonial problems and langua ge nationalism outside of Europe 
A. In the U.S., because the dominant  language, English, is VERY dominant  
5 Jacqueline Urla, 1993.  Contesting modernities: Language standardization and the production of an ancient modern 
Basque culture.  Critique of Anthropology  13 (2): 101-118. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>18 LANGUAGE, CULTURE, ETHNICITY 
Read: 
Rodolfo Stavenhagen, L
anguage and social identity 
Peter Whiteley, Do language rights serv e indigenous interests?  Some Hopi and 
other queries 
Uli Linke, There is a land where everyt hing is pure: Linguistic nationalism and 
identity politics in Germany 
Jane Hill, 2008. Language in  white racism: An overview.  
I. 	Introduction 
A. 	Language plays many roles in additi on to being a channel to communicate 
referential meaning 
1. A given language is often seen  to represent non-linguistic qualities 
a. 	For example, Italian is  musical, just like the Italians 
   b .	 DISCUSS: other examples? 
2. 	 Sometimes the language is seen as being the cause, not just a symbol, of 
these non-linguistic characteristics1
 a. 	Classic example: arguing that, in contrast to English, where we say 
time runs, 1) 	 In Spanish they say time walks, which produces in 
Spanish-speakers a more laid-back notion of time 
2) 	The supposed maana (tomorrow) attitude 
(procrastination, lack of the work ethic, procrastination) 
b. 	This notion is thoroughly discre dited todaythe re lationship is not 
so simple, and the maana idea simply an ethnoracial slur 
c. 	 These are called linguistic ideologies (Hill, p. 31) 
B. 	In addition to the referential messages being sent, speakers communicate other 
ones 1. 	 Speech indexes (points to) identit y, it sends messages about identity 
1 This is known as a strong version of the Sapir-Whorf hypothesis.  See Benjamin Lee Whorf, 1956.  Language, 
Thought, and Reality.  Selected Writings of Benjamin Lee Whorf. John B. Carroll, ed.  New York: Wiley. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2
 a. 	Sometimes such messages ar e sent totally unconsciously on the 
part of the speaker 
    1 )	 DISCUSS: Examples? 
II.	 Speech and ethnic, national, and racial identity 
A.	 Example: gender and class 
1. 	 A study in Norwich, England2 of attitudes toward speaking proper 
English 
2. 	 Men rated themselves as speaking a more lower-class version of English 
than they really did 
3. 	 But women rated themselves as sp eaking a higher-class version than they 
actually did a. 	Linguists made the evaluations 
4. 	 An association was being made between masculinity, social class, male 
solidarity, and work ing-class culture 
a. 	 The men wanted to see them selves as regular guys who didnt 
put on airs, or who were wimpy 
b. 	 Upper-class British men and their accents are seen as effeminate twits 
1)	 The British comedy group Monty Python enacts this 
perceived characteristic 
5. 	 The Norfolk women aspired to speaking properly as a marker of their 
class position and ambitions for their children 
a. 	The working-class men ag reed with this, supported it 
    1 ) T h e i r w i v e s should  speak better 
2) Their wives are the one s to teach the children, to know 
about manners, etc. 
6. 	 In general, femininity require s refined, grammatically correct, soft 
speechcoincides with middle-class speech styles 
2 See Peter Trudgill, 1974.  Language and sex.  In Sociolinguistics: An Introduction to Language and Society . 
Harmondsworth: Pelican: 78-99. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
3. 	 40 years of turbulence, marches, etc. 
a. 	Its origin was colonial domination; continuing resentment 
b. 	 British seizing Quebec province from the French and English 
speakers dominating ever since 
4. 	 The article points out that separatist politics has been bad for business 
a. 	 There has been flight of English-speaking individuals and firms 
5. Fear of assimilation on the part of French speakers has eased 
6. Attitudes of those English-speakers who remained have changed 
a. 	Its cool to be bilingual 
VI. 	The language situation in states that have gained independence more recently:  
A. 	Vast majority are plural w ith respect to ethnicity and language7
 B. 	Example of Malay language 
1. 	 Sign in Kuala Lumpur in Mala ysia: Glorify the National Language 
a. 	 Suggests that it has been denigrated 
2. 	 Malayness was a relatively new idea 
a. 	Earlier, peoples identity was rooted in a region and that regions 
language(s), rather than rooted  in the territory that became 
Malaysia upon independence 
3. 	 But the nation-building project 
a. 	Requires the Malay language to represent Malays (the people) in 
opposition to Chinese and Indians 
b. 	Remember Ongs article? 
c. 	Note that here those in power, who make up the majority are not 
dominant economically 
C. 	 What do such linguistic ally plural states do? 
7 This section follows Donald Horowitz, 1985.  Ethnic Groups in Conflict . Berkeley: U Cal. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>10 
9. 	 Or the opposite claim will be made : we need to catch up, therefore the 
state should help by giving our  language official status 
10. 	Language institutes are created to: 
a. 	Enrich the language 
b. 	 Cultivate the intellectuals who work in it (and employ them) 
c. 	Directly related to middle-cl ass job and promotion prospects in the 
civil service 
I. 	 Often minorities want an official policy of multilingualism
 1. 	Chinese in Malaysia 
2. 	 Bengali as an alternative official language 
3. 	Berbers in Algeria 
4. 	 Tamils in Sri Lanka 
J. 	 The campaign for linguistic parity is a transparent code fo r establishing greater 
equality more generally 
K. 	Language standardizatio n will bring more conflict 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
1) Stavenhagen points this out as well 
b. 	 We discussed how this is often seen as appropriate, because 
women are seen as safeguarding th e language of their specifically 
indigenous identity 
B.	 Languages, like other concepts we have discussed 
1.	 Should be seen in terms of relations hips between people (both individuals 
and groups) performed, enacted through speech 
2. 	 It is not the linguistic attribut e being noticed and commented on thats 
important in itself, whats important  is the group that speaks the language, 
and the differences between groups that make the attribute important.4 
C. 	 Fredrik Barth (remember the discussion in Eriksen?) says that in addition to 
looking at the content of ethnic differences 1. 	It is always was important  to examine boundaries and boundary 
maintenance 
2. 	 Especially true in politicized situ ations involving more than one language 
3. 	 Which is why thinking that language differences create  ethnic tension and 
conflict, because people dont understand one another, is way too simple 
4. 	 The idea that language differencesinability to understand one another, 
misunderstandingproduce c onflict, is very old 
a. 	 In the Old Testament: the story of Babylonthe beginning of 
failing to understand one anothers speech seen as the beginning of all misunderstandings 
1) 	Whats occurring is that  understand the other is being 
conflated with comprehends the language being spoken 
b. 	 Whereas in fact there are many additional ways of 
misunderstanding apart from not understanding speech 
5. 	 Corollary idea: Esperanto-like gl obal languages will solve these problems 
a. 	 Again, way too simple: if everyone spoke English, ethnoracial and 
social class misunderstanding a nd conflict would not disappear 
4 Donald Horowitz, 1985.  Ethnic Groups in Conflict . Berkeley: University of California Press: 50. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ethnic Identity, Nationalism and Gender</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_15_ethn_nat/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
c. 	 The ideology justifies this w ith the mythologized actions of one of 
their sex 
d. 	 Zavella says that male dominance and the double standard are 
rationalized in the cultural polemics of macho/chingn  and 
virgin/whore
 e. 	 Ideology of machismo : men are jealous, unfaithful, possessive 
f. 	 Theme of conquestdeflowering virgins, etc. 
g. 	 With women needing to continua lly prove their purity, for they all 
bear the mark of that original betrayal 
h. 	 Do you see how Zavellas argument links the ideologythe 
symbolic levelwith on-the-ground gendered relations?
 1) 	 Providing justifications for the power asymmetries? 
E. 	 The very frequent theme of sleepin g with the enemy is gendered and sexed 
1. 	 Its always women: co llaborators, sluts, traitors
 2. 	 Frantz Fanons book The Wretched of the Earth6 
a. 	 Assigns a vastly different role  to Algerian women in the struggle 
against French colonialism 
b. 	 Women should remain veiled: the veil is a sign of resistance to the 
oppressor who wants to unveil them
    1 ) A r a p e t h e m e
 2) Rape symbolizes violation, conquest
 3) But what if the woman accepts being unveiled?
 a) Ideology says shes a traitor in a way a man cannot 
betray 
     b) Seen as buying into the colonialists ideology 
6 Fanon, Frantz, 1968 (1961 in French). The Wretched of the Earth. New York: Grove Press. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
 b. 	 Or should they repres ent the traditio nal culture? 
c. 	 During the Black protests in the U.S. in the 1960s and 1970s 
d. 	 One leader, Stokley Carmich ael, said the proper position of women 
in the movement was supine 
1) This means lying on their backs 
e. 	 Another leader, Eldridge Cleav er, said womens proper role in the 
Black movement was to be a good wife and mother and raise a 
new generation of warriors wholl continue the fight 
f. 	 Elicited a great deal of discussion 
g. 	 Also theres a debate in the Native American movement: women 
portrayed as needing to be tr aditionalbearers of culture 
D. 	 Another example: Mexico 
1. 	 The very powerful symbol of la Malinche: 
   a.	 A national allegory of Mexi co involving race, ethnicity, conquest, 
gender, and sexuality 
b. 	 La Malinche was conquistador  Cortezs translator and concubine 
c. 	 She is seen to personify the cultural connection between the act of 
sexual intercourse ( chingar ) and conquest, violation 
d. 	 She is also seen  to represent the devalua tion of women by men who 
are shamed for being mestizossons of Spanish fathers and socially 
denigrated Indian mothers 
e. 	 And to have betrayed her people
 2. 	 Present-day gendered Mexican/Chicana identity 
a. 	 Patricia Zavella5 says that the ideology re quires women to submit to 
repression of their sexuality 
b. 	 Embedded in Catholic-based discourse, institutions, and everyday 
practices 
5 Zavella, Patricia 1997.  Playing with fire: The gende red construction of Chicana/Mexicana sexuality.  In Roger 
N. Lancaster &amp; Micaela di Leonardo, eds., The Gender Sexuality Reader: Culture, History, Political Economy. New 
York: Routledge: 392-410. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3
 d. 	 Greece 
1) Highest abortion rate in Europe (Russias is higher) 
a) Unlike Romania under Ceausescu, contraception 
and abortion readily available 
2) Studied by several scholars4
 3) Decision-making by both men and women was complicated 
by state policies and propaganda regarding the need to 
increase the number of Greeks
 a) Perceive Turkey to be a threat 
b) And Slavs to the north: the highly conflictive issue 
of Macedonia as Greek pr ovince and as a country 
e. Pro-Russian policies in the USSR continue today 
1) 	 Officials had been quite concerned that in the near future 
ethnic Russians would be a minority 
3. 	 Note that states always have a stake in demographics 
a. 	 For example, Japan is worri ed about a too-high proportion of older 
people 
1) 	 Not enough workers in the future 
2) 	 Not enough stay-at-home wives to take care  of increasing 
numbers of elderly family members 
b. 	 Chinas one-child policy: a c oncern with too many people, period 
4. 	 But in this class were concerne d with a specific kind of state policy 
regarding demographics a. 	 How to produce more of the right stuff and less of the wrong 
stuff in terms of specific categories of people 1) 	 With respect to nationality, ethnicity, race 
4 Alexandra Halkias, 1998.  Give birt h for Greece!  Abortion and nation in lette rs to the editor of the mainstream 
Greek press.  Journal of Modern Greek Studies 16, no. 1: 111-138; also see Heather Paxson, 2004.  Making Modern 
Mothers: Ethics and Family Planning in Urban Greece .  Berkeley: University of California Press. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
c. 	 De la Cadena speaks of cultural mestizaje 
1) 	 And documents how women are indeed symbolically 
more Indianin several negative senses 
d. 	 What culturalideological, symbolicprocesses keep women in 
that inferior position?
 1) Familiar notions about inferioritywomen linked to 
children
 2) Weak 
3) Seen to not really work 
4) Idea that if they were to  try to do real work, theyd do it 
poorly, fall ill, and damage  their reproductive system 
5) If they went to the city, theyd be subject to sexual 
predation and assault 
6) Less likely to be in pr ocess of losing their indigenous 
identity 
7) 	 So, not only are they more Indian 
a) More of them are, in fact, Indian 
C. 	 In many other systems women are exp ected to maintain the ethnic difference 
1. 	 But the gender inequality is sometimes less apparent, more easily argued 
away 
2. 	 The Smith piece: in Guatemala i ndigenous women will wear traditional 
dress (even when in the U.S.) in situations where men wont 
a. 	 And are far more likely to be monolingual 
b. 	 Celebrated as Maya mothers, etc. 
3. 	 In the U.S. and Canada: lots of debates within activist ethnoracial 
communities about the proper role of women 
a. 	 Should they organize demonstr ations, write leaflets, sign petitions, 
etc., just like the men? 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
1) 	 Mississippi appendectomies performed on rural black 
women
 2) 	 Were in fact sterilizationsoutright deception 
2. 	 And the opposite: attempts to increase births of members of the right 
nationality/ ethnic group/ race 
a. 	 Piece by Heng and Devan well read for the next class is about 
Singapore governments pro-natalist state policies directed at 
Chinese women, but not Malays or South Asians 
b. 	 Romania under Ceausescu , the last socialist dictator2
 1) 	 Wanted to increase birth rate 
2) 	 Contraception and abortion were basically not available 
a) 	 Like all E. Eur opean socialist countries, both 
women and men were expected to hold full-time jobs; state services to help families with infants and small children inadequate 
3) 	 Consequently many unwanted infants were left as 
foundlings to be raised in state orphanages 
4) 	 Horrible conditions; worse was their being given 
transfusions of HIV-infected  blood to strengthen them 
c. 	 Israel
3
 1) 	 There are more fertility c linics per capita in Israel than in 
any other country in the world;  worlds highest per capita 
rate of in-vitro fertilization procedures 
2) 	 Fertility treatments are fully subsidized by Israeli national 
health insurance 
3) 	 Available to all women, regardless of marital status 
4) 	 Gideon Levys Haaretz article about state pro-natalism 
2 See Gail Kligman, 1998.  The Politics of Duplicity: Controlling Reproduction in Ceausescus Romania. Berkeley: 
University of California Press. 
3 See Susan Martha Kahn, 2000. Reproducing Jews: A cultural account of assisted conception in Israel . Durham: 
Duke University Press. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Jean: get more images for the last part  of this lecture, it was too short 
15 ETHNIC IDENTITY, NATIONALISM, AND GENDER 
Read: De la Cadena, Marisol, 1995, Women are more Indian: Ethnicity and gender in a 
community near Cuzco 
Smith, Carol, 1996.  Race, class, gender ideology in Guatemala: modern and anti-modern 
forms 
I. 	 Introduction 
A 	 We have noted in class several times th at class /ethnicity /race /nation /gender 
/sexuality intersect, are imbricatedconjoined, interact with and constrain one 
another1
 B. 	 Nationality is gendered 
C. 	 Ethnicity is gendered 
1. 	 De la Cadenas case in Peru: i ndividuals construct or contest their 
ascribed ethnicity within specific social contexts of power and domination based on class and gender inequalities (p. 331) 
2. 	 Recall the reading by Schein: The Consumption of color and the politics 
of white skin in post-Mao China 
3. 	 DISCUSS: other examples of gendered nation or gendered ethnicity you 
can think of? 
II. 	 Gendering occurs at two levels: on- the-ground situations, and symbolically 
A. 	 On-the-ground refers to how people actually live; their op tions, constraints, 
their material reality 
1. 	 Example:  limiting reproduction 
a. 	 Example of Slovenian progr am to promote sterilizing Gypsy 
women 
b. 	 Attempt to limit births of the wrong nationali ty/ ethnic group 
c. 	 Or the wrong race 
1 Smith, p. 51. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity
Fall 2011 
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
2) 	 We dont focus on attempts to limit reproduction in the 
wrong social class 
a) 	 But ethnicity and race usually correlate with social 
class
 b) 	 Heng and Devans piece youll read for next Mon. 
shows that ethnicity in Singapore is classed 
c) 	 But clearly Singapore s policy is mostly intended to 
result in more ethnic Chinese, not increase numbers of upper and middle class members 
B. 	 Second kind of gendering: symbolic 
1. 	 What De la Cadena terms peoples mental reality 
2. 	 The ideology says theres a fixed bi polar system that assigns people to one 
and only one category 
a. 	 But theres also a fluid, pr otean, and contingent process by which 
people attach ethnic labels to themselves or others (p. 331) 
b. 	 This benefits men 
3. 	 What is the material reality of Chitapampa? 
4. 	 Peru went through a land reformredistribution of land 
a. 	 Such that the original distin ction between whites (those that had 
land) and indios (those w ho didnt), no longer applied 
b. 	 But the classification remained 
1) Evolved into a cultural onea set of symbols 
     a ) DISCUSS: what is a symbol? 
2) 	 Dress, language, certain skills
 3) 	 Racism does exist in Peru a) In the sense of colorism
 b) But most people are mestizos 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ethnicity, state, Nation</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_7_ethn_may/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
2. 	All scholars mention the ro le played by industrialization 
3. 	An article by Segal and Handler3 argues that the rise of nationalism in 
Europe and the Americas must be seen in the larger context of 
colonization
 a. 	They insist that analyses of nationalism must look at the entire 
global picture 
b. 	They provide a critique of Euro-centric views of the development 
of nationalism 
c. 	They argue that all analyses of nationalism have to examine the political economy of colonialism and the role of racial ideologies in justifying it 
d. 	For instance, they argue that we cannot look at British nationalisms evolution  
1) 	Without looking at Ireland as  a colony; at Br itains Atlantic 
coast colonies; at the British West Indies
 4. 	Also, various authors, in addition to Segal and Handler, argue that much 
of the theoretical characterization of nationalism does not fit the nation-
building processes that take place in former colonies 
a. 	For example, Eriksens example of Trinidad: its nationalism is 
built, not on autochthonous, indigenous people and their culture, 
nor on ancient folkways being re-discovered 
1) 	But built on forging a nation out of two immigrant 
populations: African and E. Indian 
2) 	Nationalism consequently looks very different in countries 
like Trinidad
    3 )	 
DISCUSS:  Eriksens discussion of the changing ethnic 
formation of East Indians and Blacks in Trinidad? 
5. 	A new kind of nationalist ideology is  required if former colonies are to 
successfully develop into nation-states 
a. 	If they are to be capable of creating cohesion and loyalties 
3 Daniel Segal and Richard Handler, 1992. How European is nationalism? Social Analysis  32: 1-15. 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
B. 	Characteristics of nationalism1: 
1. 	Is primarily a principle that holds that the political and national unit should 
be congruent 
2. 	Nation is not primary nor an unchanging social entity.is historically 
grounded, the nation-state meaning emerged fairly recently 
a. 	Although nationalist sentimen t may contend that a people (a 
nation) have lived a long time in the same place 
3. 	Nations are not natural, God-given, etc. 
a. 	This is why nationalists are so interested in what historians are up 
to 1) 	Example of anthropologist Anastasia Karakasidous 
research on Greek Macedonians speaking a Balkan 
language
2 
2) 	She was denounced by the Greek Parliament, and received 
death threats from Greek nationalists living in New York city
 b. 	Simon Harrison discusses Greek  feelings about use of the word 
Macedonia 
4. 	Nationalism sometimes takes pree xisting cultures and turns them into 
nations 
a. 	Sometimes invents them 
b. 	Often obliterates pre-existing cultures 
   c .	 DISCUSS: Examples from Eriksen? 
   d .	 DISCUSS: China and nationalism in Gladney 
5. 	Nationalism comes before nati ons. Nations do not make states and 
nationalisms, but the other way around. 
6. 	Nationalism emerges only at a point of intersection of politics, technology 
and social transformation 
1 Hobsbawm agrees with Gellner (1983) in the list that follows. 
2 Karakasidou, Anastasia N., 1997. Fields of Wheat, Hills of Blood: Passages to Nationhood in Greek Macedonia, 
1870-1990 . Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
5. 	More familiar to us: feudal agrari an states in Europe during the Middle 
Ages 
6. 	These states were not integrated nationally 
a. 	Their subjects were locally integrated, under the rule of a member 
of the nobility who collected tribute
 b. 	Socialization and social c ontrol were largely handled locally 
c. 	Armies tended to be profe ssional, without the ideology of moral 
duty of all to fight for ones country that we find in nations 
7. 	Compared with modern nation-states these earlier dynastic states: 
a. 	Placed few demands on the majority of their citizens 
1) Note: oppression, exploitation could be brutal 
a) Building Egyptian, Mayan pyramids 
2) 	But few demands on them as citizensnot much state 
bureaucracy
 b. 	No nation-building was need ed because the boundaries were 
always shifting 
1) 	No sense of a need to have populations w ithin the borders 
share a culture, language 
2) 	The subject populations ju st needed to be loyal to the 
rulers,
     a )	 P a y t a x e s 
b) 	Consent to be conscripted as labor (e.g., road-
building), etc. or for military
 c. 	Pre-modern dynastic kingdoms in Europe werent French or British as they are understood today 
1) 	Inhabitants were subjects to a monarch, not citizens 
III.	 Modern Period 
A. 	Ethnic identity formation and boundary maintenance increase 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4
 2) 	With their interaction structured around: a) Kinship networks and face-to-face interaction
 c. 	Tribal is an anthr opological classification, although a 
problematic one 
d. 	Pre-modern, small-scale soci eties: three type s of subsistence 
modes 1) Hunter-gatherers
 2) Horticulturalists
 a) Gardeners: subsiste nce mode lackin g the plow and 
draft animals 
b) Note that horticultu ralist societies can in fact be 
very largesome African  kingdoms, for example
 3) Nomadic pastoralists 
2. 	Contrast with the grea t pre-modern dynastic states 
a. 	Which were characterize d by the fourth subsistence mode, 
agrarian: plow and draft animals 
b. 	The fertile crescent: Babylonia, etc. were agrarian 
3. 	Some pre-modern stat es were horticulturalist 
a. 	New World (Aztec, Maya, Inca) 
4. 	In general these great ancient st ates developed where water was scarce 
(exception: Maya) a. 	One hypothesis (overly simple) argues that civilizations developed 
in arid zones 1) 	Because there was a need to organize to develop the 
technology that allowed for optimal water distribution 
b. 	As well as develop a socio-pol itical organization that ensured an 
appropriate distribution 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
1. 	Ethnic identities tend to attain thei r greatest importance in situations of  
a. 	Flux, potential ambiguity 
b. 	Change 
c. 	Resource competition
 d. 	Threats against boundaries 
B. 	Ethnic identity formation and attention to boundary maintenance are found in 
societies undergoing modernization: 1. 	Industrializing 
2. 	The scale increases: a large numbe r of people might participate in the 
same economic system 
3. 	Pre-modern ideologies were base d in kinship, feudalism and religion  
a. 	In industrial capitalism contex t, these were no longer capable of 
organizing people efficiently 
4. 	Eriksen provides a number of examples from Africa showing how ethnic 
formation changes, adapts 
IV. 	Nationalism and ethnicity A. 	Note that isms refer to sets  of beliefs, theories, ideologies 
1. 	
DISCUSS : meaning of ideology? 
2. 	Two mainoften interre latedmeanings for ideology 
a. 	First, a pejorative meaning: a given ideology is in fact an illusion, a 
set of false ideas 
b. 	Second meaning: the set of ideas  that arise from a definite social 
class or group 
B. 	Definitions of the ideology of nationalism? 
1. 	Gellner: a political principle which holds that the political and the national 
unit should be congruent 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>7 ETHNICITY, STATE, NATION 
Read: Eriksen, Ethnic identity and ideolo gy: 70-94; Ethnicity in history: 95-115. 
  David Maybury-Lewis,  Ethnic groups:  47-79 
I. 	Summary of nationalism 
A. 	Role of liberal ideology? 
1. 	Belief in social, cultural, polit ical evolution: notion of progress 
2. 	Liberal ideology is the underpinning of familiar slogans like the French 
Revolutions liberty, e quality, fraternity  
   a .	 DISCUSS: how does the U.S. Declaration of Independence put it? 
b. 	Remember: this revolution was mainly one of liberation from 
colonial power, fight for sovereignty 
c. 	Nationalism arrived later 
3. 	But dont equate this meaning of liberal with its current meaning of 
progressive on the political left 
a. 	Maybury-Lewis speaks of the liberal state , which was the model 
for nation-building in Europe and liberated colonies 
1)	 Self-determination, republic, democratic, people are 
citizens, not subjects of a monarch,  
b. 	For example, nationalists may want ethnic cleansing (very un -
liberal)
 1) 	Despite being politically liberal in some ways 
a) E.g., anticlerical (anti-religious) 
c. 	Another example: nation alism and eugenic reasoning may go 
together 1) 	Idea of strengthening the nation, and so may be against 
birth control, abortion 
2)	 Nicolae Ceaucescu of Romania under the Soviets  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
a. 	Particular stage of technological and economic development 
b. 	Standard languages cannot emerge before printing; need for mass 
literacy, mass schooling 
C. 	So, nations are dual phenomena 
1. 	Constructed by political forces 
2.	 But any analysis must include John St uart Millss notion of desire (see 
Eriksen chapter) 
a. 	The role of ordinary peoples assumptions, hopes, needs, longings 
and interests in the process 
b. 	By no means do nationalist activists always accurately represent 
these feelings 
    1 ) DISCUSS: Examples you can think of? 
2) Chechnya: activists drew on the repression they suffered 
under the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia 
3) Who knows what the majority  of Chechnyans felt, or feel at 
present? 
4) It is difficult for a researcher to get at these feelings 
II.	 Pre-modern compared to modern states: brief history 
A. 	Pre-modern period 
1. 	Tribes 
   a .	 
DISCUSS : What do you think of when you hear this word? 
    1 )  O t h e r 
 2) Exotic 
3) Examples from the movies? 
b. 	Tribal societies have classically been seen as: 
1) Small-scale (not large populations) 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
a. 	But, asks Eriksen, what is the national unit? 
2. 	Another: the belief that ethnic bound aries should not cut across political 
ones 
3. 	Nationalism holds that the poli tical organization s hould be ethnic in 
character in that it represents the in terests of a particular ethnic group 
4. 	Another definition: ethnic ideologies that hold that their group should 
dominate a state 
C. 	Benedict Andersons characteri zation of nationalism: it posits an imagined 
community 
1.	 Imagined  because members of nations will never know the vast majority 
of their fellow members; community  because the ideology holds that 
members share a culture 
2. 	The same goes for large ethni c groups: they are imagined ethnic 
communities 
3. 	Whats special to the nationalist ima gined community is that it is seen to 
be embedded in the state 
4. 	The national state is imagined by its members as both inherently limited 
and sovereign 
5. 	The ideology holds that member s loyalty and attachment should be 
directed towards the state and the legislative system 
D. 	So, nationalism is an ideology about culture and power 
1. 	Self-conscious culture 
a. 	By now we understand that nation-building requ ires talk about 
culture
 2. 	Nationalism reifies  cultureDISCUSS
 a. 	Enables people to talk about their culture as though it were a thing, 
a constant 
E. 	Additional discussion of theories about the causes of the rise of nationalism 
1. 	All scholars mention the role played by modernization 
7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Transnationalism, Globalization and Culture</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_23_trans_glo/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
 2. 	 New, differential  citizenship rights
 3. 	 Particularly restrictive citizenship procedures were developed in the Baltic 
states
 4. 	 Disenfranchising large numb ers of the resident Russians 
5. 	 In Estonias 1992 elections, nearly 40% were forbidden to vote, most of them Russians 
a. 	 Estonian citizens were de fined by native Estonian language and 
descent 
6. 	 We can call this Constitutional nationalism 
a. 	 A nationalism that privileg es members of one ethnonation over 
others 
D. 	 Croatian independence in 1992 fulf illed a one-thousand-year-old dream 
1. 	 Recuperation, revivals, festivals,  etc., Croatian icons, monuments, folk 
songs 
E. 	 An estimated half of all Croats live outside the homeland 
1. 	 Diaspora Croats desired a free Croatia, but independence has created 
conditions for the emergence and exacerbation of the often fraught 
relationships within and between groups 
2. 	 Desire for the homeland is not neces sarily coterminous with the desire to 
return to it 
3. 	 Not much scholarship has been done on the roles of homeland peoples 
a. 	 And how they change as a result of interaction with diasporic 
peoples 
4. 	 Remember point made earlier in seme ster that ethnicity is a relationship? 
5. 	 Clearly everywhere diasporas cons truct notions of homelands in ways 
often very different from homelanders constructions 
a. 	 This leads to ambivalence and tensions 
F. 	 History: Croats immigrated to Cana da earlier in century for economic reasons 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2
 4. 	 Employment in professions regularly associated with women 
5. 	 Being associated with domestic rather than public spheres 
6. 	 Cross-dressing 
7. 	 Engaging in sexual relations with straight men 
C. 	 The Miss Galaxy beauty pageant in Tonga 
1. 	 Is the antithesis of the traditional Miss Heilala pageant 
a. 	 Which involves real women performing Tonganness 
b. 	 With speech, body postures 
c. 	 Tongans will return from New Zealand, Australia, California to 
participate in the Miss Heilala pageant 1) 	 But they are likely to be judged as poor  dancers, not 
proficient in spoken Tongan 
d. 	 In the Miss Heilala contest, locality is supposed to triumph over 
cosmopolitanism, transnationalism, the industrial world 
2. 	 Contrasts between the two pageants: a. 	 Miss Galaxy is carnivalesque (as opposed to the seriousat times 
tediousMiss Heilala) 
b. 	 Miss Galaxy is for fun 
c. 	 Miss Galaxy characterized by a camp sensibility 1) Is an event of outstanding exoticism 
d. 	 Nonlocal clothing, language, names, mannerisms, performances 
nonlocal gender itself
 e. 	 Examples of nonlocality: 1) Contestants appear in national costumes 2) Miss Rarotonga, Miss Switzerland, Miss South America 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
2. 	 Many said yes, we should valorize Croatian culture and heritage 
3. 	 But a large number of critics inside and outside disapproved of the 
direction of post independence politi cal, economic and social processes 
K. 	 Initial euphoria at  Croatian independence 
1. 	 But soon the nationalist policies a nd practices of Pr esident Tudjmans 
regime were criticized
 a. Many believed it to be autocratic and corrupt 
L. 	 Tudjmans support came from diaspora Croats 
1. 	 Many were and continue to be strongly nationalist 
a. 	 Diaspora Croats (more recent emigrants) represent sentiments and 
qualities valorized by nati onalist elites at home 
2. 	 An illustration of Verderys cita tion of Andersons politics without 
accountability 
a. 	 migrs and refugees who contribute funds to violent nationalist 
organizations in their home countries while living peacefully in a 
suburb or Paris or Montreal3 
M. 	 Diaspora Croats participation 
1. 	 Vote in federal electionsCroatia is a multi-sited nation-state that is 
maintained through transnational means 
a. 	 Diaspora Croats were po litically and economically involved 
2. 	 They were interested in promoti ng the reproduction of images depicting a 
romantic and idealized social, cultural, and political landscape 
3. 	 But these diasporic Croats nationali st sentiments were resented by many 
homelanders 
4. 	 Who did not share the ethnonational vision of Croatia 
5. 	 Regional differences hardened, and came to be defined in cultural terms 
3 Verdery, p. 293 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4
 4. 	 DISCUSS: differences between these stereotypes and the situation 
described by Marisol de la Ca dena for Peruvian Indians? 
5. 	 An extra ingredient: the complicated  identity of the Fakaleiti with respect 
to gender, class, and translocality 
D. 	 What are the Fakaleiti hoping for? 
1. 	 These men are socially marginalized in many wayseconomically, 
socially 
2. 	 The link-up to international glam our provides a (temporary) escape route 
from local dynamics of so cial exclusion and poverty 
3. 	 Temporarily they can try to c onstitute selves that foreground their 
superiority over, and autonomy  from, the rest of society 
a. 	 Cant actually travel 
4. 	 Performing/subscribing to nonlocality provides symbolic resources 
5. 	 Enables them to claim that they ar e exempt from local morality and forms 
of exchange that marginalize a nd degrade them (like marriage) 
6. 	 Many of them idealize the West 
a. 	 See it as a source of desirabl e marriage partners, financial security, 
etc. 
b. 	 A source of partners who will take care of them, rather than their 
having to financially take care of  their Tongan boyfriends (who are 
straight Tongan men)
 c. 	 Obviously a fantasy, not the reality of what the West offers 
7. 	 They reject hormones to increase feminine appearance 
8. 	 As elsewhere in the Pacific, they reject gay identity 
a. 	 God made man and woman, they say 
9. 	 They scorn what they see as the foregrounding of sexuality in Western gay 
identity (e.g., gay pride parades) 
E. Conclusion: 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>23 TRANS
NATIONALISM, GLOBALIZATION AND CULTURE 
Read: Katherine Verdery, 1998. Transnat ionalism, nationalism, citizenship, and 
property: Eastern Europe since 1989 
Eriksen, 2002. Identity politics, culture and rights 143-161; The non-ethnic: 162
178. In Eriksen, Ethnicity and Nationalism: Anthropological Perspectives 
(2nd ed.). London: Pluto Press (34) 
I. 	 Today well look at two very different cas e studies illustrating globalization processes 
A. 	 Analysis of transnationalism  and ethnonational identity in Tonga 
B. 	 Analysis of Croatia and the Canadian  Croatian diaspora to illustrate some of 
Verderys points 
C. 	 Wednesdays lecture will be more theoretical 
II.	 Transgenderism is widespread in Tonga and elsewhere in the S. Pacific1
 A. 	 Traditional patterns of cross-dressingnot brand new 
1. 	 Beauty contests with prizes are held 
2. 	 In Tonga: a yearly Miss Galaxy pageant 
a. Seems to be a display of transgendered glamour 
b. But equally the contest is a show of translocality 
1) 	 Modernity and hybridity are performed; cosmopolitanism, 
migration, non-local values, symbols, languages, body 
practices, etc 
c.	 Translocality is opposed to Locality  (here meaning Tonganness) 
B. 	 The stereotype of local transgendered men, called Fakaleiti, is: 
1. 	 Feminine comportment 
2. 	 Greater affinity with women than men 
3. 	 Being responsible for domestic work in the home 
1 Information from Niko Besnier, Transgenderism, locality  and the Miss Galaxy B eauty Pageant in Tonga.  
American Ethnologist 29. 3: 534-566, 2002. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
1. 	 Some authors say that globalization brings challenges to the received order 
a. 	 Modernity, etc. 
2. 	 But although we see the fakale iti temporarily enacting a glamorous 
translocality
 a. 	 We also see them rejecti ng Western gay and lesbian identities 
3. 	 The modern, the West are reconfigured, and local meanings are 
worked into the meanings that arrive from elsewhere
 4. 	 Globalizing homogenization and heterogenizationhere they occur 
simultaneously, which is most often the case 
III.	 The Croatian case2 
A. 	 Croatia: following the 1989 colla pse of communism and Yugoslavia 
1. 	 Verdery: political parties ha d no recognizable political platforms 
2. 	 The democratic process was very unfamiliar, to say the least 
3. 	 Rejection of communism, an opening for discourses relating to pre-Soviet 
era 
B. 	 National symbols proved so potent th at no political group co uld entirely avoid 
them 
1. 	 Nationalism was turned into pol itical capital, and it increasedwhich 
surprised everyone 
2. 	 Rewriting of constitutions began 
3. 	 In socialist-era constitutions, al l socialist citizens had been on equal 
footing 
4. 	 This system of civil status coll apsedambitious politicians manipulated 
the very definition of citizenship 
C. 	 Verderys discussion of Latv ia, Estonia, Croatia, Slovenia 
1. Nationalities were turned into majorities and minorities 
2 Information from Daphne Winland, The politics of desire and disdain: Croatian identity between home and 
homeland American Ethnologist  29. 3: 693-718, 2002. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
1. 	 Endured hardships there, were the targ et of stereotypes of  racial inferiority 
(applied to all E. Europeans) 
2. 	 The early ones had leftist leanings 
3. 	 They labeled the Croats who came to Canada after World War II as war 
criminals
 4. 	 Ustasethe Croatian fascist separatist organization during WW II 
committed atrocities 
5. 	 These later arrivals resented the earlier left-leaning ones 
a. 	 Saw them as nave about communism 
G. 	 Tensions within Croatia  played out in Canada too 
H. 	 Canadian states policy of official multiculturalism 
1. 	 Point weve encountered oftenthe  state wields power, influences the 
nature of ethnicity 
2. 	 Croatian heritage language progr ams, music and folklore groups 
flourished 
3. 	 They had to play the politics of  recognition according to terms set by the 
Canadian state 
4. 	 Foregrounding ethnocultural traditions as  part of the Croatian contribution 
to the (cultural) fabric of Canadian society 
I. 	 Over the years Toronto Croats had seen themselves as a victim diaspora 
1. 	 Saw their countrymen Croats in communist Yugoslavia as their oppressed brethren 
2. 	 Independence brought changes 
a. 	 To already unstable and ambiva lent bases of loyalty, affiliation and 
identity 
J. 	 Homeland Croats had endured enor mous upheavals sociopolitical, economic, 
personal nature 1. 	 Needed to come to terms with the transition from communism and come 
to see themselves as citizens 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3
 3) 	 Contestants are emulating beauty pageants everyone 
watches on TV 
4) 	 Their names: Lady Amyl and, Suzie from Sosefo, Priscilla 
Pressland, Aisa De Lorenzo, Aodushi Kiroshoto 
a) Chosen for exotic sounds 
5) 	 Background music: William Tell Overture, etc. 
6) 	 Language: supposed to speak English as much as possible 
7) 	 Fakaleiti are in general expected to speak English more 
readily than nontransgendered men 
8) 	 Fakaleiti are seen as self-assured and brash, shameless 
(even though many are self-effacing) 
f. Clearly, the stereotypes depict the Miss Galaxy contestants as oriented toward modernity, the West, transnationalism 
3. 	 The interplay of gender and mode rnity revealed in this contest: 
a. 	 In general in Tonga, speaking English has feminine undertones 
1) Competes with a code of traditionalism 
b. 	 Because in general a language  of modernity is associated with 
womens aspirations for upward mobility and emancipation from the strictures of tradition 
c. 	 Familiar notions that girls study harder, and women more talkative by nature 
d. 	 So, all men who speak too much English do so at the risk of 
compromising their masculinity 
e. 	 Tongans born overseas are awkward in performing Tongan 
maleness 
1) 	 They are often branded as fakaleiti-like regardless of lack 
of effeminacy 
f. 	 In general, the use of E nglish indexes (points to) a deficient 
Tonganness, masculinity 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9
 a. 	 People held very firmly fixed notions of regional identity 
impervious to change 
b. 	 The snob from Zagreb, etc. 
c. 	 Some nationalists said that some Croats could never be good 
Croats 
1) If theyre unpatriotic,  if they dont valorize the Croatian 
past, then theyre bad 
2) Are said to be Yugonostalgic 3) Are called Yugo-zombies 
d. Those targeted tended to be intellectuals and journalists
 N. 	 Conclusions: 
1. 	 Verderys point: diaspora and homeland relations and identities are 
mutually constituted
 2. 	 The classic modernist logic that diaspora patterns of identification 
function to undermine the cultural and te rritorial goals and political vision 
of the nation-state 
a. 	 Is wrong 
3. 	 One must study the impact of diaspora-homeland relations on identity 
formation 
a. 	 Examine the local in relation to transnational connections 
4. 	 Keeping in mind that the homeland dimension is more than just the object 
of diaspora imaginings 
a. Rather, its a crucial site of diaspora identity politics 
5. 	 Diaspora and homeland relations must be analyzed in their historical 
specificity 
9</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The State: Hegemony and Push-back</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_24_abu_el/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Questions on Abu El-Haj and Erikse n 147-173 (Minorities and the State) 
1. 	 On p. 166 Abu El-Haj describes rumors to th e effect that an arch aeologist was m
urdered 
because he had found something that unde rmined their entire historiography of 
ancient Jerusalem. Under what circumstances  can archaeological findings hypothetically 
pose this kind of subversive threat, if any?
 2. 	 What were your reactions to reading an ar ticle about Jerusalem archaeology written by 
someone named Nadia Abu El-Haj?  Would you have read the essay any differently had 
it been authored by someone named, say, Jeff Goldblum? 
3. 	 Abu El-Haj makes some pretty sweeping cl aims for the role of archaeology in nation-
building. Which points do you agree with? Disagree with? 
4. 	 Think of a hypothetical case in another count ry where archaeology mi ght be as important 
as Abu El-Haj says it is for Israel. 
5. 	 Provide two cases involving competing nationalist narratives a bout the pastfrom the 
course readings or your own experienceand discuss them. 
6. 	 In her essay Abu El-Hajs po litical and moral position is evid ent. To what degree, in your 
opinion, does this affect the impact of th e evidence she provides and her arguments? 
7. 	 Abu El-Haj states that her larger concern is to examine 
...the workings of science in proces ses of cultural production, examining the 
practices and context through which fo rms and embodiments of knowledge can 
fashion national imaginations, realize col onial projects, and become the terms and 
the signs through which struggles fo r the present are waged. (p. 167)  
Do you see archaeology as sc ience? List all the ways you can think of that archaeology 
can be involved in colonial or nationalis t projects. Provide examples from course 
materials.
 8. 	 Describe Abu El-Hajs evidence for the claims she makes about Israeli archaeologists 
selective excavation techniques and decisionstheir privilegi ng of certain archaeological 
traditions.
 9. 	 I want to understand how knowledge is power, how it actually helps to change the 
reality we encounter (p. 169). Provide two ex amples, from this essay or other source. 
10. 	 On p. 169 Abu El-Haj writes of the nati onalist mythology Do you agree with her use 
of this word? What does mythology mean here? 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
11. 	 What other countries have a monumental na tional past (p. 171) that  is available through 
archaeological sites and objects (material culture)? 
12. 	 Abu El-Haj discusses some peoples assumptions that archaeologists would naturally  be 
nationalistic in their interests a nd practices (p. 174). Discuss. 
13. 	 What is the appropriate relations hip one should have to ones  own archaeological past? 
(p. 174) 
14. 	 Compare the planning of the new Jewish Quarter to Handlers discussion of lawmakers 
decision-making about how to recons truct a section of Old Quebec. 
15. 	 List the ways states have dealt wi th their minorities. (Eriksen pp. 149-150) 
16. 	 Discuss the way modernization is producing an ethnicization of the world. (p. 151) 
17. 	 Discuss minority elites. (p. 150) 
18. 	 Why, do you think, is indigenous such a c ontested term? (p. 152). Provide a definition 
that works for you. 
19. 	 Compare Eriksens discussion of Sami political organizing with the essay by Laura 
Graham we read for Nov. 28. 
20. 	 Eriksen says that in many cases certain  aspects of modernisation are required for 
identity maintenance to be successful. (p. 154) What  are these? 
21. 	 Eriksen speaks of the reification of culture, culture as a thing. (p. 155-156) What does 
this mean? What does non-reified culture  look like? Bring in Nagel if you can. 
22. 	 Leaders of a dominated group must master the cultural codes of the dominant group in 
order to present their case efficiently. ( p. 156) Compare Eriksen to Laura Graham with 
respect to this issue. 
23. 	 Whats the distinction between tr adition and traditionalism? (p. 158) 
24. 	 What are the political and moral dangers associated with an analytical emphasis on 
cultural differences be tween groups? (p. 165) 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>New Social Movements</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_22_war_jack/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Study Questions 
On Warren  and Jackson
 1. 	 How do W&amp;J define essentialism (p. 8)? Pr ovide an example of strategic essentialism 
you disagree with (from our r eadingsNagel provides someor from another source). 
Provide an example you sympathize with. 
2. 	 What is second-order indexicality (p. 9) and why should we care about it? Provide two 
examples. 
3. 	 What do W&amp;J have to say about authentici ty? What does the word mean to you? List 
the ways a group of people might be describe d by critics as havi ng an inauthentic 
culture. Argue in favor of such critiques. Argue against them. 
4. 	 Provide two examples of interactions between the indi genous movement and state and 
supra-state processes that have produced changes in the movement. 
5. 	 What are the three meanings of sel f-representation men tioned by W&amp;J (p. 12)? 
6. 	 List four themes in W&amp;J that we  have already discussed in class. 
7. 	 W&amp;J refer to the ironies of multiculturalism and power. What do they mean?  Be 
prepared to discu ss 2 such ironies.
 8. 	 What is neoliberalism?
 9. 	 Describe neocolonialism. 
10. 	 On p. 28 W&amp;J say that rather than see cu lture as a distinct set of discourses and 
practices all too often cont rasted with, say political economywe should understand it as 
a dimension of all institutions, a set of material practices  which constitute meanings, 
values and subjectivities. 
What is political economy? How is it ofte n seen to contrast with culture? How 
could culture be a dimension of politi cal economy? How could political economy 
be a dimension of culture? 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Race I</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_12_race_i/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
3. 	 Example of untranslatabililty of white into Spanish in Colombia 
a. 	 Blacks in the Vaups where I did my fieldwork (on the equator and 
on the border between Brazil and Colombia) 
b. 	 Were called blancos (whites) 
c. 	 The important divide there was between blancos and indgenas 
(Indians) 
d. 	 To us, white signals skin co lor; clearly in the Vaups its Spanish 
translation signaled non-Indian, a nd not from here, rather than 
skin color 
4. 	 Brazilian use of white (Portuguese: branco) is also quite different from 
English 
5. 	 Different meanings of whit e at different moments in history 
a. 	 Jews, Irish, Syrians were not white earlier in U.S. history 
B. 	 Should we conclude that all these cl assificatory schemes are wrong and only ours 
is correct? 
VI. 	 Differences in racial clas sification systems around the world 
A. 	 Constitute another set of evidence for a social constructionist explanation of race
 1. 	 Like ours, these classi fications derive from the t ype of colonial enterprise 
and sets of social relations that  were established in each region 
a. 	 Gandhi was called a nigger 
2. 	 Look at the TV news: you will see Afghanis, Pakistanis, etc. who are 
darker than many African Americans 
3. 	 The populations on opposite coasts of the Red Sea look completely alike, 
yet the African ones are classified as black and the Middle Eastern ones 
classified as white (if one is us ing a threefold classification system) 
4. 	 DISCUSS:  any other examples? 
5. 	 In North America: category bla ck supposedly includes anyone with a 
known drop of black blood 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
2) 	 One high school had a race war on its hands when white 
girls decided to dress black 
b. 	 Sometimes traits described as ethnic are in fact being posited as 
racial, but the speaker doesnt want to appear racist 
B 	 Second underlying premise: Europeans are superior 
C. 	 Third premise: race can be scientifically  studied (note: only a few scientists today 
believe this) 1. 	 By taking careful measurements 
a. 	 A good book by Harvard genetici st Stephen Jay Gould discusses 
this premise: The Mismeasure of Man 
2. They carefully measured hair color and texture, eye color and shape, 
thickness of lips, breadth of th e nose, body stature, skin color 
a. 	 Next week we will see a video with an example of such 
scientific research projects
    1 )	 Stolen Generations
   b .	 DISCUSS: other examples you know about? 
D. 	 Problems: 
1. 	 First: depending on who was doing the categorizing, some racial 
typologies had hundreds of categories wh ile others had as few as three 
a. 	 The familiar Mongoloid, Caucasoid, Negroid
 2. 	 Second: external traits traditionall y used to classify and identify races 
were found to not correlate well with other physical and bi ological traits 
a. 	 Which are often useful ma rkers of populations (e.g., the Diego 
factor in blood type) 
3. 	 Third: the various schemes differ depending on the traits on which they 
are based 
a. 	 All the following derive, in part, from genetic inheritance 
b. 	 Skin color 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12: RACE I 
Read: 
Wade, Defining Race, 1-15; Existing A pproaches to Race, 16-36; Historicising 
Racialized Natures, 37-68 
I. 	 Conceptions of race1 
A. 	 Race is a social fact 
1. 	 Wade emphasizes that when studyi ng the history of race, one always 
needs to unpack the terms 
2. 	 For example, an earlier notion about racial type: 
3. 	 Saw it as something not directly observable 
4. 	 But rather, seen to be an underl ying essence, subject to all kinds of 
variation in its obser vable manifestations 
5. 	 DISCUSS: to what extent is this notion the opposite of current notions 
about race? 
B. 	 We must pay careful atten tion to how such notions change 
1. 	 Wade discusses various notions  about how a changing environment 
creates fixed qualities
 a. 	 Contradiction 
b. 	 E.g., God created humanity, but sometime in the remote past the 
races were established 
c. 	 Some people believed in polygenesis: distinct origins of the races 
2. 	 He cites Young: 
a. 	 The question is whether the old essentialising categories of 
cultural identity, or race, were really  so essentialised, or have been 
retrospectively constructed as more  fixed than they were.  When 
we look at the texts of racial theo ry, we find that they are in fact 
contradictory, disruptive a nd already deconstructed. 
C. 	 Earlier meanings of race incl uded seeing it in terms of lineage 
1 The first part of this lecture follows Wades exposition of race. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7
 a. 	 Nagel discusses how different this is from how one is assigned to 
the category Indian, or Native American 
6. 	 Whereas in Latin America racial classifications take the form of a 
continuum of racial categories 
a. 	 Often it is only people who look quite African in appearance who 
will be identified as black 
b. 	 Other people are classed by a variety of terms denoting a position 
in between 
c. 	 A Puerto Rican or Cuban ma y not be classed as black in their 
country, but might be in the U.S. 
1) 	 Not to say racism doesnt exist in Puerto Rico or Cuba (just 
ask any dark-skinned Puerto Rican or Cuban) a) 	 But the system there is colorism, not our binary 
classification system 
b) 	 Colorism exists in the U.S., too 
d. 	 Brazil: the phrase money whitens 
e. 	 Also in Brazil  A sua branqueza , your whiteness, may be said 
as a way of buttering someone up 1) 	 Both notions sound silly in English 
f. 	 Someone poor who has light skin in Brazil will be perceived  and 
classified as darker than a comparably colored person who is rich 1) 	 All kinds of studies have been done establishing this 
7. 	 In the U.S., race and class are co rrelated, but racial classification isnt 
changed by class a. 	 People do pass, of coursea one-drop rule makes this quite 
possible 
b. 	 And colorism results in lighter -skinned people being more likely to 
be higher socioeconomically 
c. 	 But in Brazil colorism processes are labeled, are very explicit 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
1. 	 All the descendants of a given set of ancestors were members of a 
common stock 
a. 	 E.g., the race of Abraham 
D. 	 The meaning changed so that by the nine teenth-century the c oncept of race was a 
system for classifying types 
1. 	 Humans were divided into a limite d number of permanent racial types, 
sometimes seen as having distinct origins 
2. 	 Static, relatively unchangingaltho ugh keep in mind Wades point about 
internal contradictions challe nging this notion of fixity 
II. 	 Today: A. 	 A typical definition of race: an inte rbreeding population whose members share a 
greater number of traits w ith one another than they do with people outside the 
group (Ferraro) 1. 	 The notion of unambiguous categories based on distinct sets of biological 
attributes and inferred distinct descents 
2. 	 Note that establishing a boundary using this definition would be very 
difficult 
III.	 Underlying premises of th e social construct of race: 
A. 	 First: biology determines behavior 
1. 	 Many earlier racial schemes included tr aits we no longer consider to be 
physically inheriteddegene racy, laziness, poverty 
a. 	 Note Wades discussion of ear lier racial classifications that 
allow for environmental influence, effects of culture 
2. Cultural, moral, aesthetic traits were included as racial traits 
a. 	 This continues, in a sense,  today: Wades points about cultural 
racism 
1) 	 Good exercise: list all the racial traits that turn out to be 
cultural 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
B. 	 Clearly, when used to refer to categori es of people, black, no matter what the 
language, has no simple univers ally applicable referent 
1. 	 How could it be possible to create an objective concept thats applicable 
everywhere? 
2. 	 Impossible 
a. 	 No matter what the term inology is (e.g., Negroidsounds 
scientific, but simply derives from Spanish for black) 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
1. 	 They correspond to the geographica l encounters of Europeans in their 
colonial histories 
2. 	 It is specific combinations  of skin color, hair type  and facial features that 
have been worked into racial signifiers 
D. 	 Phenotype cannot be independent of history 
1. 	 Because only certain phenotypical va riations become racial categories  
a. 	 The ones that count do so because they have emerged through 
history 
2. 	 This is why height doesnt work as a race 
a. 	 Height is importantand  is a source of discrimination 
1) 	 Why Randy Newmans ironic song Short People evoked 
such outragehe was on to something that people didnt want to acknowledge 
b. 	 But height doesnt do what the social fact of race doesit 
cant 
   c .	 DISCUSS: what worksocial, cultural, political, economic does race do? 
E. 	 Conclusions: Racial classifications  cannot be understood to be social 
constructions elaborated on the basis of phenotypical variation 
1. 	 Because they do this using the par ticular aspects of phenotypical variation 
that were worked into vita l signifiers of difference  
2. 	 During European coloni al encounters with others 
3. 	 The study of race is part of  that history, not outside it 
V. 	 EXERCISE : before reading further, do this exer cise with the current most prominent 
signifier of race, skin color 
A. 	 Take out a piece of paper and list all the ways skin color alone doesnt work 
is not successful at this task 1. 	 S. Asians skin color darker than many African-Americans 
2. 	 Many African-Americans would be considered white in Nigeria 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
c. 	 Body staturewould produce very different racial categories 
d. 	 Hair color 
e. 	 Blood type 
f. 	 Earlobe structure 
4. 	 Fourth: variations occur not only within, but between breeding populations 
a. 	 Much more variation within a given race than between races (if 
your number of races is small) 
5. 	 Our reactions to the idea of usi ng some of these characteristics (using 
height: silly) demonstrate that  races are social constructions 
   a .	 DISCUSS:  Why not height? 
   b .	 DISCUSS: those who have read Huxleys Brave New World: how 
do the categories of people differ? 
IV. 	 Race is a social construction, but wh at kind?  Here is Wades argument 
A. 	 The notion that races exist w ith definable physical characteristics 
1. 	 And that some races are superior to others
 2. 	 Is the result of par ticular historical processes 
a. 	 Colonization by European powers 
B. 	 We cant even assume there is such  a thing as the brut e fact of phenotypical 
variation 
1. 	 We cant stop at recognizing that races dont exist as objective biological 
entities 
2. 	 And then reconstruct an objective basis for recognizing racial 
distinctions by grounding them in phenotype 
3. 	 This glosses over the problem that  the apparently natural fact of 
phenotypical variation is its elf socially constructed 
C. 	 Physical differences th at have become cues for ra cial distinctions are quite 
particular ones 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>State, Nation, Culture</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_9_cul_def/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
1) 	The worlds cultures were seen to live in distinct 
geographical territories 
a) Culture made places out of spaces 
2) 	Although some members might have left: for example, 
overseas Chinese 
b. 	An isomorphism of place and culture  was assumed 
3. 	What are the problems we encount er if we link cu lture with place? 
a. 	The Hue: how does a space achieve a distinctive identity as a 
Hue place? 
b. 	What is the real England, and what relationship does it have to a 
particular bounded place? 1) 	By the end of the 20
th century England is more an imagined 
state of being or moral loca tion than an actual place 
c. Related problematic concepts: native land, homeland, real 
American, American culture (America is a place) 
4. 	This definition (a culture) also highlights the fact that culture, like ethnicity, is relational : it exists because there is something not-it: it can be 
compared to something 
a. 	This is the idea behind saying its a difference of culture 
b. 	We can say MIT culture and people know were talking about 
MIT, as opposed to Harvard or BU culture 
c. 	This relational feature is especially important to keep in mind 
1) 	First, because of the importance of inter-cultural (inter -
ethnic, inter-national, etc.) relations in the real world 
a) Ethnic conflict, for instance 
2) 	Second, because understanding that a culture always exists 
in relation to other cultures often allows  us to uncover sites 
of powerasymmetrical re lations involving dominance 
and subordination, etc. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
1. 	A member of a culture might even be aware that part of their culture is not 
in their best interests 
a. 	But they might very well  keep on doing/thinking/believing 
whatever it is 
2. 	What role does individual human agency play? 
3. 	We arent automatons 
4. 	But neither are we free agents alwa ys able to know whats in our best 
interest and freely carry it out a. 	Were not Little monads guided solely by internal reasons 
(Bourdieu and Wacquant
1) 
5. 	Nagel puts the difference this way: 
a. 	Culture as structure (a sy stem that defines and shapes human 
thought and action) 
b. 	And cultural construction (a process by which culture is defined 
and shaped by human thought and action) 
6. 	DISCUSS: something you continue to do even though you know its not 
in your best interest? 
a. 	Is this entrenched cultural habit or neurosis? 
1 Pierre Bourdieu and Loic Wacquant, 1992. An Invitation to Reflexive Sociology . Chicago: University of Chicago 
Press: 135. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>9 CULTURE: DEFINITIONS 
Read: 	Eriksen, The social organisation of cultural distin ctiveness, 43-69  
Nagel, Constructing culture, 43- 54; Deconstructing ethnicity, 60-72 
Richard Handler, 1985. On having a cultu re: nationalism and the preservation of 
Quebecs patrimoine 
Definitions 
A. 	As is the case for most of our ot her analytic terms, culture is polysemic 
1. 	It has multiple, related meanings 
a. 	Think of the various concepts  of culture offered in the pieces by 
Eriksen, Nagel, and Handler 
2. 	Related to the culture in agricu lture; also, think of  culturing microbes 
in a petri dish a. 	The piece well read by Mal kki later on discusses agricultural 
metaphors, for example, a cultu re is rooted in a place 
b. 	Nagel says that one image of Native Americans is that theyre 
rooted.
  3 .	  DISCUSS:  Your definition of culture? 
a. 	Connections between ear lier meaning and your definition? 
B. 	One definition: culture is be liefs and practices  shared by a group 
1. 	Very common definition 
a. 	Culture is clearly not the idiosyncratic beliefs and behavior 
peculiar to one person 
2. 	Nagel (p. 43): Those ideational and material aspects of social life 
language, religion, ceremony, myth, belief,  values.are the substance of a 
people. 
3. 	DISCUSS:  possible problems with this definition? 
a. 	First, like nation and et hnicity, what/who are the people who 
share this culture is difficult to specify 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
b. 	Not self-evident, even though you may think it is 
c. 	Second, all cultural system s to some degree depend on their 
members not sharing the same knowledge or beliefs 
1) 	For example, even in very small-scale, seemingly 
homogeneous societies 
a)	 Men and women will not share the same cultural 
knowledgeand this non-sharing will be built in, 
not accidental 
2) 	In modern societies 
a) 	The management, foreman, and workers in a factory 
will not share the same understandings of the institution they all work in 
b) 	This non-sharing also is built inits necessary for 
the proper function of the factory 
     c )	 DISCUSS: MIT examples 
4. 	Definition cant hand le change very well 
a.	 All those examples in Eriksen of  people leaving one culture for 
another (Fur, Bagara in Da rfur, studied by Haaland) 
5. 	Nor can it handle complex ethnic intera ctions, in which all actors share the 
rules for interaction, even though th ey belong to different cultures 
C. 	Another definition: high culture : literature, ballet, opera, poetry: Culture 
D. 	Another: the notion of a culture: Eskimo culture, Polynesian culture, African-
American culture, Norwegian culture 
1. 	Note that only one of these exam ples of culture is coterminous with a 
nation-state 
2. 	But three are located in spaceth e exception is African-American culture 
a. 	Anthropologists (and others) traditionally saw several kinds of 
divisions between cultures 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
d. 	Nagel, Handler and other authors weve read (e.g., Harrison) illustrate the important role power differentials can play
 1) 	And how important it is to analyze the images one culture 
has of another 
2) 	The native art markets mentioned by Nagel, and the 
tourism 
E. 	Another idea of culture: as adaptation 
1. 	This concept of culture-as-adaptati on seeks to explain why culture exists 
in the first place and why it changes
 2. 	Helps us understand the cultural evolution that has occurred during homo 
sapiens history on the planet 
3. 	Previous lecture mentioni ng different subsistence modes 
Hunting/gathering, horticulture, nomadic pastoralis ts, agrarian states 
a. 	These are adaptations cultural adaptationsto a specific 
environment 
1) 	Interactions between environment and culture that are adaptive enough to allo w the group to survive 
a) 	Technology is an aspect  of culture in this definition 
b) 	Such cultural evolu tion brought us to our glorious 
position at presentwe are able to live in many environments, some of them quite inhospitable 
c) 	And weve gained enough power over the 
environment to turn it into a cinder 
2) 	The emergence of a technology that permitted 
horticultureproducing (growing) ones food rather than gathering it 
a) 	Is an example of cultural evolution 
b) 	We can see it as adaptive because it allowed more 
food to be produced, allowed a more secure food supply, etc. 
4. Keep in mind when using this culture-as-adaptation definition: 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
a. 	That whats good for a group as a wholewhat enhances its 
probability of survivaldoesnt al ways mean good for all of the 
individuals w ithin the group 
b. 	Theres a constant te nsion, as a matter of fact 
c. 	Poor people dont benefit from  being members of a given culture 
the way rich people do 
1) 	Example: producing food introduces a much higher 
possibility of plagues of insects, famines, etc., than is the 
case for hunter-gatherer-foragers 
2) 	People will starve ev en though food is available because 
certain cultural understandi ngs and power relations 
withhold it from them 
5. 	Remember: adaptive is always a relative term: Adaptive for what? For 
whom? Over what time span? In  what kind of environment? 
6. 	DISCUSS:  Other examples of authorized cu ltural practices not in the best 
interest of certain sectors or individuals? 
a. 	Mandated suicide
 1) 	Kamikaze pilots 
b. Although we say that mandated suicide is unfortunate for the 
individual; perhaps we say it shouldnt have to happen 
1) This probably isnt the viewpoint of the individual 
c. 	Other examples of cultural practices arguably not in the best 
interest of the individual practitioners? 1) 	Fasting, going to th e wilderness and eating honey and 
locusts, Plains Indians participating in the Sun Dance, 
breast implants, foot bindi ng, high heels, infibulation, 
botox injections 
     a )	 T a t o o i n g ? 
2) 	People outside the culture will probably see these practices, 
and the ideology supporting them, as unhealthy, unnecessary, morally wrong, etc. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 
3) People inside the culture will defend them 
7. 	When using this definition remember that cultures are never perfectly 
adaptive and adapted 
a. 	And that a given culture may in fact be very maladaptive at a 
particular point in time due to changing conditions, ecological or 
social 
8. 	Nagels book has many examples of the adaptability of culture 
a. 	A given case might illustrate the process of assimilation, or show a 
successful way to resist  assimilation pressures 
F. 	Another definition of cult ure: that which is taught 
1. 	Not simply that which is learned 
a. 	Many animals learn all sorts of things, but we wouldnt say they 
have culture 
b. 	A child will learn that fire is hot and painful, but this lesson is not 
provided by the childs culture if the learning comes from touching 
the stove flame and being burned 
2. 	The notion of culture-as-teaching conveys the idea of intentional 
transmission 
a. 	But we can argue that a lot of  culture is not deliberately taught 
3. 	In fact, much of the culture one  learns is embodied, and learned half-
consciously or unconsciously 
a. 	This is Bourdieus notion of habitus, described by Nagel, also 
mentioned by Eriksen 
b. 	A set of assumptions, disposit ions, and orientat ions that shape 
human thought and action, visions of  the possible, the perceived 
choices 
c. 	This is why if youve learned one culture, its hard to adjust to a 
new one 
G. 	The question of Free Will 
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ethnic Identity III: The Hui</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_4_ethn_id/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7
 b. 	Hui say Han are better at agriculture 
1) The Han say the cra fty Hui are better at trade 
2) Gladneys example of Han feeling cheated by Hui in 
marketplaces: larcenous Hui 
c. 	But Hui say they like engaging in small business as an expression of their ethnoreligious heritage 
1) 	Their ancestors were traders 
D. 	The role played by the state 
1. 	China originally adopted a trait list model of minority nationalities 
derived from the Soviets 
2. 	Earlier, China established campaigns that promoted nationality unity 
and discouraged local nationality chauvinism a. 	An emphasis on secularism; a re pression of minoritie s, particularly 
religious ones 
b. 	Policies sought to make a clear division between religion and 
ethnicity 
c. 	Yes there was recognition of localized nationalities 
3. 	Motivation behind these policies: 
a. 	Afraid of powerful effect of ethnoreligious loyalties 
b. 	Muslims in Western China 
1) State came up with the id ea of creating a plurality of Turkic 
ethnicities
 2) This strategy would help prevent pan-Turkic unification 
3) A divide and conquer strategy 
4. 	Shifts in state policies  
a. 	Recognition of Hui as one of the 56 minzus  (nationality, minority) 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
B. 	A descent-based definition of  ethnicity is quite widespread: 
1. 	Ethnic identity is based on the idea of descentthe idea, factual or fictive, 
of belonging to a group of people de scended from ancestors who differ 
from the ancestors of the others the group interacts with 
a. 	Blood and soil as  core of ethnic identity 
1) Descent and territory
 2) Does not apply to every case 
2. 	The blood component of the definition draws on  
a. 	Descent from an ancestor in common 
b. 	The groups relationship with th e descendants of other ancestors 
c. 	Who are members of other et hnic groups: remember, ethnicity is 
always a relationship 
3. 	What happens if a person doesnt affirm his or her ancestry? 
a. 	Is the identity still retained?  Or lost? 
b. 	What if the person doesn t know about th ese ancestors? 
4. 	Midwest Italians seen to be less Italian than New York ones  
a. 	Because they dont know enough about the region of Italy their 
family comes from
 5. 	
DISCUSS:  How do you think of an American with an Italian last name? 
a. 	Italian-American? 
b. 	Or someone of Italian descent 
c. 	What is the difference in meaning? 
d. 	What are your criter ia for deciding which label? 
6. 	Whats the difference between 
a. 	A Native American 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4
 1) 	And a person with I ndian blood, someone of indigenous 
descent 
b. 	Can you suggest methods to dis tinguish, to identify who belongs in 
which category? 
7. The Hui in Chendai see their otherness to be etched in stone 
a. 	Records, historical artif acts, 200 pieces from gravestones, 
mosques, etc. 
b. 	Even though these Huis practi ces toward their ancestors resemble 
Han ancestral worship, they are sure  they are Hui, because of the 
records
   c .	 
DISCUSS : would descendants of these ancestors still be Hui if 
they didnt know  their ancestry? 
III.	 Religion as criterion for ethnicity 
A. 	For the Hui, religion is very much tied in with their Hui-ness, but in complicated 
ways 
1. 	What Gladney calls ethnoreligious 
2. 	We see a resurgence of religion among some groups of Hui 
3. 	Hui made a variety of Islam their own a. 	A form of Sufism, but not conne cted to Sufi ins titutions elsewhere 
4. 	For example, womens mosques ar e found in China, nowhere else in 
Muslim world 
5. 	
DISCUSS : when can we say we have et hnoreligious ritu al, etc., as 
opposed to just religious ritual? 
6. 	Other evidence of  Hui ethnoreligiosity? 
   a .	 P u r i t y (qing) 
b. 	Dietary restrictions 
c. 	The small wash 5 times a day and big wash every Friday 
IV. 	Religion, ethnicity and nationalism 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
1. 	In English we use the metaphor of blood to talk about descentties 
between parents and childrenor used to; now its genes 
a. 	On p. 126 a man who eats pork and who married a Han woman 
says his son is 100% Hui, my sons blood is Hui 
1) 	He also says that childre n of Hui-Han marriages are just as 
Hui as other Hui children 
2) 	Gladney said this response was unusual in the PRC 
(Peoples Republic of China) 
   b .	 
DISCUSS : How would you classify this mans son, and other 
offspring of intermarried c ouples?  100% Hui?  50% Hui? 
1) 	What about a Hu i woman marrying a Han man? 
    2 )	 DISCUSS : How does your notion of bloodkin 
relatednessresemble this mans?  Not resemble? 
2. 	A highly recommended movie: Rab bit-proof Fence; rent it if you can 
a. 	Based on a true story of 3 si sters in rural Australia whose father 
was white and mother was Aboriginal 
b. 	They were forcibly taken from their maternal relatives and put in a school with other mixed-race children 
c. 	They kept escaping and going home
 d. 	This policy derived from the notion at the time that children of 
Aboriginals and whites (almost always the father was white) could racially improve if ra ised in white society
 e. 	Australian government in  2008 apologized to its Aboriginal 
citizens, especially this Stolen Generation 
f. 	We will see a documentary about the policy
 3. 	
DISCUSS:  Whats the parallel with Gladneys example? 
4. 	Notions about relatedness can be gendered 
a. 	Interesting idea Gladney disc usses, of tainted blood passed down 
from female to female 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
A. 	First kind: ethnic nationalism expressed in the form of a religion that opposes the 
state 
1. 	Examples? 
a. 	Fundamentalists in Iraq opposing the imposition of (a variety of) 
democracythey are against es tablishing a secular state
 2. Immigrants to this country  fleeing religious persecution  
a. 	The Pilgrims, the Quakers, the Shakers 
b. 	I mentioned the Anabaptists: Amish, Mennonites, Hutterites 1) 	Their religion was paci fist, which was seen as anti -
government, unpatriotic 
3. 	Hui 
a. 	The modern Chinese state is anti-religion 1) Although not nearly so strongly as earlier
1 
b. 	Islam is not the traditional religion of the majorityHan 
Confucianism is 
B. 	Second kind: religion-based ethno- nationalism allied with the state 
1. 	Iran and Islam: Shia Muslims 
a. 	There are religious minorities  in Iran, some of them persecuted 
b. 	Jews, Bahai, Sunni Muslims 
2. 	Ireland and Northern Ireland a. 	Atheists may support various Catholic institutions because of the 
link between Catholicism, Irish  history, and nationalism,  
2) 	In particular that the colonizers from England were 
Protestant 
a) 	The Anglo-Irish were the aristocracy in Ireland 
1 See issues of Chinas Ethnic Groups , published quarterly by the China Association of Advanced Knowledge 
Promotion in Ethnic Regions, Beijing, set up with the approval of Chinese authority. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>4 ETHNIC IDENTITY III 
Read: Gladney 57-132 
I. 	Folk (non-scholarly) models of ethnicity, ethnic relatedness 
A. Level of relationality determines how ethnicity is defined in actual situations 1. 	I am Indian as compared to Paki stanis, Sinhalese (citizens of Sri Lanka) 
2. 	I am Gujarati as compared to  Indians living in other regions 
3. 	I am Jain as compared to Hindus or Muslims 
4. 	An example from Nagel: 
Thus, an American Indian might be a mixed-blood on the reservation, 
from Pine Ridge when speaking to someone from another reservation an 
Oglala Sioux or Lakota when asked about tribal affiliation, or an 
American Indian when interact ing with non-Indians. (p. 21) 
B. 	
DISCUSS:  does this level of relationality  model work for race?  Gender? 
C. 	Does it work for Hui? 
1. 	Gladneys book is about the construction of an ethnic category, Hui, at 
the state level  and the consequences at the local level 
2. 	Previously the term de signated a religious identity 
3. 	Previously the Hui themselves co nsidered only those Hui in the same 
region of the country to belong to the same group 
4.	 In the Na homestead, those Hui share an ethnoreligious identity 
5. 	DISCUSS : any other examples of ethnore ligious identity you can think 
of? 
a. 	African-American Muslims? 
II. 	Folk notions about physical relatedness 
A. 	Race and ancestry 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
 b) 	An Anglo-Irish woman, whose family migrated in 
the 17
th century  
c) 	Talked with us about the Irish, clearly not 
identifying with them
 3. 	Confucianism in China 
a. 	Overseas Chinese subscribing to Confucian principles and 
traditions, celebrating holidays 
b. 	Even overseas Chinese who are Christian 
4. DISCUSS : other examples of congrue nce of state and religion? 
5. If religious leaders constitute the government, its called a theocracy 
C. 	The present-day Hui 
1. 	Ethnic cultural markers that reveal a complicated merging with religion
 2. 	Certain recurring texts that ar e of interest to urban Hui,  
a. 	Including legends of origin, aspects of qing zhen  lifestyle, religious 
holidays, traditional specializations and handicrafts, martial arts 
practices, and the organi zation of social space 
3. 	Pork avoidance 
   a .	 DISCUSS:  how does this differ from Muslim states where no one 
eats pork? 
b. 	Hui in Fujian ancestral rites: similar to their Han neighbors, but the 
rites are for Muslim ancestors
 1) 	Cant offer the ancestors  pork, although descendants eat it 
c. 	Avoid even saying the word pig 
    1 )	 DISCUSS : examples of taboos on specific words serving 
as ethnic markers? 
4. 	Hui ethnic division of labor seems very secular: 
a. 	Aquaculture: razor clams in Fujian 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
b. 	Hui had to learn to accept other Hui throughout the country as 
members of the same minzu 
c. 	Hui in Fujian had to wait for a long time for recognition; they didnt fit the trait list criteria 
1) 	But they argued that they had assimilated to mainstream 
China because they had been forced tothey were forbidden to practice Islam 
2) 	Forbidden to speak Arabic or Persian 
d. 	Present-day advantages to being Hui 
1) 1979 reforms 2) Hui prosperity with factories and restaurants due to 
favorable government policies 
3) The government approved and funded 2 Islamic schools 
4) Hui can have more children than local Han 
e. 	Why? 
1) 	Chinese state wants foreign exchange and so promotes 
Muslim tourism 
8</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Nation and Nationalism I</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_5_nat_n_nat/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
2. 	Each nation is the product of partic ular, localized, or re gional historical 
conjunctures 
3. 	Its not like classifying bird s or lizards, where you can work out a priori 
criteria 
4. 	The criteria themselves are fuzzy, shifting and ambiguous (language, 
ethnicity) 
5. 	Hobsbawm:
 a. 	Defining a nation by its member s consciousness of belonging to it 
b. 	Is tautological (a circul ar argument), and provides only an a 
posteriori  (afterwards) guide to what a nation is 
6. But, Hobsbawm says that an initial working assumption might be: 
a. 	Any sufficiently large body of people whose members regard 
themselves as members of a nation 
7. 	DISCUSS: Exceptions?
 a. 	Israel? 
1) Is Israel a Jew ish state?  If so, why? 
2) Is Israel a Jew ish nation?  If so, why? 
b. 	Other examples? 
1) 	Gladney: if Tibet we re a free state, there would be 
similarities in how that stat e and its citizens would be 
conceptualizedTibetanwould be close to a nation-state 
II. 	History of the concept of nation 
A. Root meaning of word: naissance, or igin, descent (ancient French dictionary) 
1. 	Nacin was an aggregate of the inhabitants of a territory 
2. 	Could be a provin ce, a country, a kingdom 
a. Was used when speaking of foreigners 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
1. 	There was no historical precedent whatever for the formation of Yugoslavia 
2. 	No one questioned existing states multinationalityin Britain, France, 
Spain 
a. What these minority people felt wasnt considered important 
1) 	And many individuals be longing to these groups did favor 
unification 
b. 	Many felt they were better offbigger is better 
1) 	How, it was asked, could the Slovenes possibly manage by 
themselves? 
3. 	Evolutionary ideology was very strong: these small groups, languages, 
were seen to be doomed as civilization progressed 
   a .	 DISCUSS: examples of doomed European languages you know about that didnt die out? 
b. 	The evolution to larger units  was seen as following natural law 
inevitable
 c. 	Society was to evolve from family and tribe to a nation-state 
d. 	From the local to the regional,  the national and eventually global 
1) 	Familiar idea that at the next phase in human evolution, ethnic and national barriers  will melt and dissolve 
2) 	Attempts to construc t artificial wo rld languages (e.g., 
Esperanto) are an example 
4. 	Folklorization processes of cultures and languages 
a. 	Campaigns to preserve the dialects 
b. 	A new idea that contradicted th e notion that these variants should 
be eliminated, in order to fost er national unity through a single 
standardized language 1) 	Spaces opened up for thick Irish and Scottish accents on the 
stageso long as safely reduced to appendages 
(Hobsbawm) 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9 
2) Songs in Neapolitan became positively valorized
 c. 	Folk museums were built; anth ropologists were hired to recover 
oral traditions, etc. 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>5 and 6 NATION AND NATIONALISM I, II 
Read: Read: Eriksen, 2002. Nationalism. In Eriksen, Ethnicity and Nationalism: 
Anthropological Perspectives  (3
rd ed.). London: Pluto Press: 117-146 
Simon Harrison, 1999. Identity as a scarce resource.  Social Anthropology  7 (3), 
239-251 
I. 	Nation as linked to a state is a NEW idea 
A. 	The modern sense of the word is no older than the 18th century 
1. 	The word and related words have been around 
2. 	DISCUSS: other meanings? a. 	What does Indian nation, Cherokee Nation suggest to you? 
b. Can we say American nation?  Why or why not? 
c United Nations, Wealth of Nations? 
1) 	Could the UN just as easily be United Countries?  Or 
United States? (except that ones taken) 
B. 	Nations, in the sense of  nation-states are also new 
1. 	Nation, state, country, nation-state 
2. 	DISCUSS: provide examples of actual na tion-statesstates that contain 
only one nation, one people a. 	There really arent many 
b.	 Dominican Republic (unusual for Caribbean) and Oceania 
c. 	Japan almost qualifies (non-Japanese: Ainu, Koreans) 
C. 	How can we define nation? 
1. 	One author, Eric Hobsbawm, says we cant characterize nation-states 
using an a priori (established beforehand), objective set of distinctions 
that allows us to distinguis h a nation from other entities 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
 a. 	Contends that this developm ent is intricately tied to colonial 
activity in the rest of the world 
3. 	It is clear that nation ideology was closely linked to the development of 
modern states 
4. 	A great deal of literature is concerned with this issue2 
B. 	Empires did not see the need for a single people 
1. 	In fact, they exploited these differences: worked to increase divisions 
between subjects 
a. 	For example, the idea of ethnic soldieringbring in soldiers 
from a different ethnicity/count ry to reduce the likelihood of 
alliances between civilians and military 
b. 	At times rulers used soldiers belonging to an ethnic group that was 
the traditional enemies of the population 
C. 	The idea emerged that strong states need citizens who th ink alike and share 
identity in various ways 1. 	Notion of the right to rule conf erred by divinity wa s losing legitimacy 
a. 	All states claim a monopoly on use of legitimate force 
b. 	But is very costly if force is the main way of maintaining rule 
2. 	Citizens of a state ideally would embrace one language, one heritage, one 
religion, etc., and so would agree to being ruled a. 	Loyalties to other groups came to be seen to compete with loyalty 
to the nation-state (family, religion) 
b. 	Familiar idea? 
    1 ) DISCUSS: current examples? 
3. 	During the 19
th century many subject populations made the argument that 
a people need to be sovereign 
4. 	Newly recognized states legiti macy was based on concept of nation 
2 See Benedict Anderson, 1983. Imagined Communities: Reflections on the origin and spread of nationalism . 
London, Verso.  Ernest Gellner, 1983.  Nations and Nationalism. Oxford: Basil Blackwell. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
3. 	Words for homelandones ow n place, township, land of birth:  patria, 
tierra
 a. 	Territory of originpays natal  (Old French) 
B. 	Meanings in the languages th at used some form of nation: 
1. 	German: foreigner (a loan word, contrasted with volk) 
2. 	Territory of origin 
3. 	Common descent groupethnicity 
4. 	Speaking the same language 
5. 	We could consider Castile, in Spai n to be one of the earliest European 
kingdoms approximating the nation-state idea 
a. 	A bounded territory, a political unit, inhabitants s poke the Castilian 
language and shared the no tion of being Castilian 
C. 	In the 19
th century in Europe, nation and na tionalism developed in stages: 
1. 	Originally seen as something purel y cultural, literary and folkloric, not 
political 
2. 	A body of pioneers and militants began promoting the national idea in 
several countriesthey were urban elites 
3. 	Then nationalist programs start to acquire mass support 
D. 	This process sometimes occurs 
1. 	Before the creation of a na tional state: Ireland 
2.	 Sometimes afterwards: We have ma de Italy, now we have to make 
Italians
 3. 	Sometimes never 
   a .	 DISCUSS: Third World examples of #3? 
E. 	The meaning changed over the 19th century to include notion of a political body 
1. 	Earlier: simply the people; later,  the idea that this unit of people should 
have a government 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
III.	 Eighteenth century ideas about the people 
A. American and French revolutions: ideas about one nation and one state 
1. 	American colonists were disti nguished from King George and his 
supporters neither by ethnicity nor language 
2. 	At that time, many of the modern me anings of nation simply didnt exist 
a. 	Ethnicity, common la nguage, religion, territory 
b. 	A common history, historical me mories shared by those seeking to 
establish themselves as a separate state 
3. 	American goal: overthrow colonial  oppressor, be independent of England 
4. 	French: overthrow rgime and th e entire fixed hierarchy of royalty, 
nobility, clergy (Catholic Church), and replacing it with Liberty, 
Brotherhood, Equality 
B. 	Always present: the element of citizenship and mass participation 
1.	 And desire to be a national state 
2. 	French revolutionaries called one another citizen 
IV. 	In the nineteenth century: 
A. The principle of nationality gained  ground: its primary meaning was political 
1. 	A people should constitute a state 
B. 	Eric Hobsbawm1 discusses major arguments that took place about the necessary 
preconditions 
1. 	Had to be viable (c ulturally, economically, size) 
2. 	Many arguments were made about size throughout the 19th century 
a. 	Ridiculous that Belgium and Portugal be states 
   b .	 DISCUSS: examples of very small states today?  Problems? 
1 Eric Hobsbawm, Introduction.  Nation as Novelty.  Pp. 1-45 in Nations and Nationalism since 1780: Programme, 
myth, reality .  Cambridge, 1990. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 
3. 	After World War I, the princip le of nationality appeared in peace 
treaties 
a. 	Produced a Europe of 26 states  (27 if we add Irish Free State) 
b. 	None of these were then, nor are now, nation-states  (i.e., a single 
people) 1) 	A recent study of regionalist movements in W. Europe 
alone counts 42 of them 
4. 	Notion of self-determination 
a. 	Yes the idea was present in independence movements (Latin 
America) during the century 
1) 	Except for Haitis in 1804, which no one accepted, really
 b. 	Empire was still very  much present in Europe 
c. 	The notion of each people needing to be independent and 
sovereign evolved during the late 19
th and early 20th century 
C. 	But how to establish criteria for a people? 
1. The French people did not all speak French, by any means 
a.	 The requirement that they speak French became a characteristic of French state-building 
b.	 Eriksen: speaking Breton was forbidden 
   b .	 DISCUSS:  other examples of imposition of a state language? 
V. 	Ideology of state = nation = people continued to develop 
A. 	Why this evolution from empires? 
1. 	DISCUSS: examples of empires 
a. 	British, French, Hapsburg, Ottoman 
2. 	An optional reading for next Mondays (Oct. 3) class by Segal and 
Handler 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
a. Belgium, Serbia, Greece, Romania, Bulgaria 
5. Changes in the economic system also supported the shift 
a. 	Each territorially circumscri bed state tended to pursue mercantilist 
policies as a unified whole 
b. 	Extra-territorial, transnational units played a larger role  
1) Both prior to the nation-building period and currently 
2) Earlier: Hanseatic Leag ue in Northern Europe is an 
example3
    3 )	 DISCUSS: present-day extra-territorial, transnational 
units? 
a) International markets, international trade 
agreements, European Union 
c. Note that empires we re still very much present 
1) 	But they were colonial empires 
2) 	Note that various populations in Europe continued to feel 
they were under colonial rule 
3) 	June 28, 1914 Archduke Franz Ferdinand, Austro-
Hungarian assassinated by a Bosn ian nationalist, in effect 
beginning WWI 
VI. 	How Nationalism was employed 
A. 	Nationalist moveme nts gained in strength 
1. 	National unification or expansion 
a. 	Germany, Italy, Greeks 1) 	At the moment of Italys unification, 2 % of the 
population spoke Italian 
B. 	Hobsbawm points out that the c oncept of nation was manipulated 
3 An alliance of trading guilds existing from the Middle Ages to the Early Modern period (from the 13th to 17th 
centuries) that monopolized trade in the Baltic and some parts of the North Sea. 
7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Race II</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-226-ethnic-and-national-identity-fall-2011/resources/mit21a_226f11_13_race_ii/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3
 d. A racial cue resulti ng from European colonization 
F. 	 Wade is generalizing about racialization in the West, but always when you look at 
specific cases there will be difference, elaborations 
1. 	 Colorism (Latin America) vs. categorical (U.S., apartheid South Africa)  
2. 	 Differences in language 
3. 	 Spanish Raza not the same mean ing as raceand both are polysemic 
4. 	 Examples of difference 
a. 	 A saying in Brazilian  Portuguese: money whitens, 
b. 	 Or A sua branqueza your whiteness in Portuguese 
c. 	 Both sound silly to us
 d. 	 In Brazil, someone poor with  light skin will be perceived and 
classified as darker 
1)	 Might be true here 
IV. 	 Race in Japan1: a contrast with our system 
A. 	 In 1986 former Prime Minister Nakas one contrasted his countrys supposed 
homogeneity with the ethnically mixed U.S. 1. 	 Said the homogeneity was responsib le for Japans success in international 
business 
2. 	 The statement created an international furor 
B. 	 As a major industrial state, Ja pan is indeed relatively homogeneous 
1 Discussion of race in Japa n follows C. Ko ttak, 1996. Mirror for Humanity: A Concise Introduction to Cultural 
Anthropology .  New York: McGraw-Hill, Inc.: 61-65; and Barb ara Hall, BurakuminThe Untouchable Caste of 
Japan, 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>13: Race II 
Read: 	 Wade: Genetics and Kinship: The Interpen etration of Nature and Culture, 69-96; Race, 
Nature and Culture, 97-111; Embod ying Racialised Natures, 112-122 
I. Review: Race, racialization, racism A. 	 Race is a so
cial fact, not a biological one 
1. 	 A social construction 
2. 	 A very powerful social fact 
B. 	 Even if were not interested in the hi story of a concept, how its meanings evolved 
1. 	 Learning about it can help us get some distance from the terms current, 
taken-for-granted meaning and be able to analyze it 
C. 	 Wade provides a very thorough discussi on of race, its links  to nature (how 
reproduction was understood, notions about heredity, environmental influences) 
and culture 1. 	 In particular the surprising variety of theories, both scholarly and in the 
general public 
II. 	 Todays meaning of racecomponents  
A. 	 Biology determines behavior (at least in part) 
B. 	 Europeans are superior 
C. 	 Race can be scientifically studied 
III.	 A social construction, but what kind? 
A.	 Wades discussion of what kind of construction: 1. 	 The modern idea that races exist, with definable physical characteristics, 
with some superior to others  a. 	 Is the result of par ticular historical processes: 
b. 	 Colonization by European powers 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
 b. 	 Japanese racial classifications  include notions of  what people like 
Burakumin or Koreans smell like 
1) 	 But note the built-in contradictions similar to Wades 
points about racial classifi cations being both fixed and 
flexible 
2) 	 These differences sometimes will be attributed by Japanese 
themselves to non-genetic fact ors like diet and level of 
cleanliness
 3) 	 Not some relatively immutable and long-standing 
separation between the races
 c. 	 Discrimination mainly seems to stem from the association with 
ancestors and their perceived difference 
4. 	 Present-day differences 
a. 	 Some job niches still hold (e.g., leather work, and Burakumin are 
more likely to do manual work) 
b. 	 Systematic ostracism accounts for some estimates that 70% of 
Yakuza (Japanese mafia) are Burakumin 
c. 	 Live mainly in Western Japan 
d. 	 1974 Ministry of Health a nd Welfare forbade the practice of 
showing family registry details, restricted access 
e. 	 But in 2 years nine lists from the registers were secretly sold at 
high prices to large companies and major banks 
1) So they could identify  them, reject job applications 
f. 	 No Burakumin are found in high government office: most are 
engaged in garbage colle ction and similar jobs 
g. 	 Google Earth caused an upr oar by overlaying old maps that 
highlighted Burakumin neighborhoods 
h. 	 If Burakumin attend schools with majority Japanese, they will face 
discrimination 
1) Some people will refuse to eat with them 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
1. 	 Most Japanese have strongly held opinions about Japanese being one race, 
one people 
2. 	 Linguistically, too (although some dialects of Japanese are mutually unintelligible) 
3. 	 Only 4%-10% of Japanese are minorities (sources differ) 
a. 	 Burakumin are the largest minority 
4. 	 Assimilation of minorities happens, but has been discouraged
 C. 	 The minorities: 
1. 	 Aboriginal Ainu in the north 
2. 	 Annexed Okinawans 
3. 	 Immigrant nationalities, mostly Koreans 
4. 	 Outcaste Burakumin (who, unlike Koreans, are citizens) 
a. 	 They number 2-4 million (sources vary) 
D. 	 Burakumin 
1. 	 History 
a. 	 Present-day Burakumins ancestors were outcasts 
1) Who did unclean jobsani mal slaughter, disposal of dead 
2) Similar to Indias Untouchables 
3) Association with impure materials, death, made them 
ritually impure
 4) Polluting to others 
5) Residentially segregat ed, official lineage books made it 
impossible to escape from the identity 
b. 	 Their origins are from a tiere d system of stratification (Tokugawa 
period[1603-1868]) 
1) 4 ranks: warrior, farmer, artisan and merchant 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 
2. 	 70,000 to 200,000 women were forced to serve as comfort women, 
prostitutes for military forces 
3. 	 Most had been repatriated to a divided Korea by 1952 
4. 	 Those who remained were denied citizenship 
5. 	 Koreans qualify for citizenship if re sident for 3 years and one parent was 
born in Japan 
a. 	 Some qualify for citizensh ip but choose not to take it 
b. 	 Resentful of earlier and continuing discrimination 
c. 	 And many maintain strong ethnic ties, ofte n residentially 
6. 	 If they do become citizens 
a. 	 They are strongly encouraged to take a Japanese name 
b. 	 A kind of semi-occult assimilati on that helps maintain the ideology 
of Japanese homogeneity 
VI. 	 The valued group is the majority pure Japanese 
A. 	 Strong feelings about same blood 
1. Example: a caption under a photo of a Japanese-American: a. 	 She was born in Japan but ra ised in Hawaii. Her nationality is 
American but no foreign blood flows in her veins
2
 2. Children of mixed marriages ma y not get the same racial label 
a. 	 But they are still stigmatized 
b. 	 As are Japanese who spend a long time away from Japan 1) When they return, a process of reintegration must take 
place 
2) Children are sent to special schools
3 
2 Jennifer Robertson, Koreans in Japan.  Paper presented at U Michigan Dept. of Anthropology Jan. 1992.  Cited in Kottak. 
3 See Merry White, 1988. The Japanese Educational Challenge: A Commitment to Children . New York: Free Press, 1987, and 
Tokyo: Kodansha. Also in Japanese: Shueisha, 1992. 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21A.226 Ethnic and National Identity 
Fall 2011 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
 2) 	 And outcasts: a)	 Eta (Great Filth), earlier name for Burakumin 
b) 	 And the Hinin (not humancriminals and survivors 
of suicide)
 3) Not human, not in th e census, but yes registered by 
government 
4) Not human, didnt have to pay taxes 
5) Life of 7 Etas was equal to that of one human being 
6) Had to wear 5x4 rect angular pieces of cloth identifying 
themselves as Eta 
c. 	 Meiji Restoration (1868-1912) emancipated them, recognized their 
humanness 
1) 	 But, although registers merged, Burakumin were called 
new commoners 
d. 	 1926 Emperor Showa called them Dowa, same people 
1) Burakumin prefer Buraku 
2. 	 Are physically and genetically in distinguishable from other Japanese 
a. 	 But are seen to be racially different 
3. 	 Present-day notions about the content of difference 
a. 	 Virtually indistinguisha ble appearance, culture, religion
 1) Sometimes slight speech differences 
2) But mainly known through residence and family last name 
a) 	 Originally had no family names, then were named 
after their dwelling sites
 b) Kristi Yamaguchimeans mouth of mountain 
c) Shes thought to be Buraku 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9 
B. 	 Again, built-in contradictionsthe idiom of pure blood, which presumably 
remains in the body no matter what 1. 	 Japanese race 
C. 	 Another idiom: a notion of c ontamination from foreign influence 
1. 	 That must be cleansed, eliminated 
a. 	 Not permanently impure 
2. 	 Remind you of Wade? 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
B. 	 If race is a social construction, we can t assume that races dont exist as objective 
biological entities BUT ARE grounded in phenotype 
1. 	 The natural fact of phenotypical variation is in itself socially constructed 
2. 	 Not just any physical differences, only some have become cues for racial 
distinctions 
a. 	 These cues correspond to the geographical encounters of 
Europeans in their colonial histories
 3. 	 Specific combinations of skin color, hair type a nd facial features that have 
been worked into racial signifiers 
4. 	 Only certain phenotypical variations become racial categories a. 	 Those that have emerged through history 
C. 	 Particular aspects of phenotypical variation that have been worked into visual 
signifiers of difference 1.	 Vital signifiers of difference 
2. 	 Worked into for a reasonthey work; they help achieve certain goals: 
social, cultural, political, economic 
D. 	 Could height serve as a racial signifier? 
1. 	 It could, but it hasnt 
2. 	 Height IS a signifier , just not a racial one 
a. 	 Could it be a racial cue, somewhere? Sure.  
b. 	 It is in Brave New World 
E. 	 Other phenotypical variations, more lo cally, have served as racial signifiers 
1. 	 My example of body hair a. 	 In the U.S., body hair means certain things 
b. 	 Unwanted in women 
c. 	 In Colombia, at least earlier, it racially signified European descent, 
and was desirable 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 
i. 	 Many of them pass as a majority Japanese person 
1) As do some blacks in the U.S. 
j. 	 But if they marry a non Bu raku Japanese and are discovered, a 
divorce might take place 
1) 	 Many Japanese hire marriage mediators to check out the 
family histories of prospective spouses 
a) 	 Looking especially for Burakumin 
5. 	 Many outsiders dont know about Burakumin, many Japanese know very 
little 
a. Embarrassing if it comes up in conversation 
6. 	 The discriminationattitudinal and in stitutionalis strikingly similar to 
what blacks face in U.S. a. 	 Even though there is no clear phenotypic difference 
b. 	 Now in Japan, like the U.S., the discrimination is de facto  rather 
than de jure 
7. 	 In response to Burakumin political mobilization: a. 	 Japan has dismantled the lega l structure of discrimination against 
them 
b. 	 And worked to improve conditions in their racially segregated 
neighborhoods ( buraku) 
1) 	 Poor sanitation, housing, etc. 
2) 	 For example, a Sports Day for Burakumin children was 
established
 V. 	 Koreans in Japan 
A. 	 During WW II more than 2 million Koreans were in Japan 
1. 	 Recruited to replace Japanese farm workers 
7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <videos>
      <video>
        <video_url/>
        <video_title/>
        <transcript>
          <slice>
            <text_slice/>
            <time_slice/>
          </slice>
        </transcript>
      </video>
    </videos>
  </lectures>
</doc>
