<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/</course_url>
    <course_title>Ethnicity and Race in World Politics</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Political Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>A Framework for Analysis of Ethnopolitical Mobilization</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/l_08/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Seven internal factors make  genocides happen (in book): 
o	Elites rely on repression to remain in power. 
o	Typically seen in authoritarian states. 
o	Elites use power to award groups deferentially. Elite manipulation. 
o	Exclusionary ideologywe re the best.  Youre an animal or sub-human.  
o	Elites are part of an ethnic minority. 
o	Country has recently undergone poli tical upheaval and instability.  
o	State has weak political and economic  links with other states, thereby 
making it easier for elites to shun international norms on human rights. 
-3-</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523: Ethnicity and Race in World Politics-Fall 2005 
Prof. M. Nobles 
Lecture 8: A Framework for Anal ysis of Ethnopolitical Mobilization 
	Essay topics out today 
	Read thru preamble of Iraq constitu tion that will be voted on Oct. 15th 
o	Sunnis, Shiites, and Kurds voted on a legislative council that drafted the 
constitution. 
o	Sunnis are boycotting the constitution de spite participating in the drafting. 
o	Sunnis claim that their dema nds werent taken seriously. 
o	Constitution states that Islam is official religion 
o	No law may be passed that  contradicts the religion 
o	Student: legislation according to Islam could be a concern 
o	Iraqis are equal under the law without discrimination against race, color, 
etc. 
o	Student: how are they going to set up powers?  Will it be like Iran?  Not 
sure if there will be a fourth branch of government. 
o	Student: Women dont have rights in Ar ab culture.  Its going to take a 
while to make changes to society while staying in the confines of the 
interpretation of the Quran. 
o	Student: Saudi Arabia furthest right of all Arab countries in terms of 
patriarchal attitudes.  Iraq not as far as Saudi Arabia. 
o	Student: Iraq cant be expected to tolerate different sexual orientations 
because its still an issue here in the U.S. and Iraq definitely isnt at the 
same point as the U.S. 
o	Brazil has a comprehensive constitution that lists every imaginable right 
but it is not always enforced. There are limits to what a constitution can 
do. 
o	Student: South after the Supreme Cour t decision to desegregate, however 
continued to segregate because it wasnt enforced.  Will that happen in 
Iraq? 
o	Why is Sunni non-participation/boycotting bad? 
 Student: a lot of the violence against the U.S. forces comes from Sunnis or forces hired by the Sunnis. 
	Sunnis are experiencing status reversal.  Enjoyed being on top 
politically. Were associated  with the ruling regime. 
 They do not want to be a permanent minority. 
 Do not want to be violently attacked. 
 Many Sunnis are moderate, but they cant control the fighters, who 
will likely not be on board poli tically with the new Iraqi. 
 How much is there a cen tral control of power? 
o	Students need to follow current developments in Iraq.  
-1-</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>o	Why is it important to students? (student responses) 
 Students are draft age 
 No support in the military for it. 
 Financially it affects our future. 
 Have friends fighting in Iraq 
 Souring U.S. relations with Europe.  Important for economic 
reasons. Could affect pocket book indirectly. 
 Draft still possible 
 Recruitment is low. 
o	Why are Europeans against the U.S. involvement with Iraq 
 Student: Things were better  economically under Saddam. 
 Had guaranteed source of oil prior to war 
 Destabilizing of the region 
 Violating international law 
 Student: French disbelieve the U.S. justification of war and 
anything U.S. government says. 
 Student: In all fairness, the Europeans were the original 
imperialists. 
 Student: Feel like everyone  has been lied to.   
o	Student: Hurricane Katrina revealed wea knesses in the U.S.  Its weakened 
in its claims because life in the U.S. isnt so wonderful and who is the U.S. 
to force democracy on everyone else. 
	Ethnopolitical mobilization 
o	Thinking about why people organize  around ethnicity, modernization 
theory viewed ethnicity has vestiges of the past.  Once people got better 
jobs, cities urbanized, class identiti es would become more important. 
Ethnic politics will disappear once class identity replaces ethnic identity.  
o	Politics would be more pluralistic and competitive. Elections wont look 
like a census. 
o	The predictions of moderniz ation theory didnt happen.  
o	Ethnic politics can still be seen in: 
 Developed economies (U.S., western Europe.) 
 Developing countries (becoming more prosperous, yet ethnic 
politics persists).  
	Modernization theory failed. Why? Two competing explanations:  
o	One instrumental reason, people use ethni c identity to get what they want.  
Want rights, territory, economic advantages.  Helps them mobilize a base. 
OR 
o	Ethnic identities are primordial.  Deep  cultural and psychological needs.  
Ethnic conflict occurs sometimes when  their identities are threatened.  
Ethnic politics will persist as long as people view themselves in terms of 
ethnicity. 
-2-</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Emergence of International Human Rights&#160;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/o_l4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14-15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523 / Lecture Notes 
 
 
From Jack Donnelly, International Human Rights
 
 
THE EMERGENCE OF INTERNATIONAL HUMAN RIGHTS 
 
I. Main Issues: 
 
A. State Sovereignty vs. Intervention: In the 19th and early 20th 
centuries, violation of human rights of a countrys nationals 
were not considered a matter of diplomatic concern. One important exception: International Opposition to Slavery. 
Congress of Vienna in 1815  Major powers recognized an 
obligation to abolish the slave trade.  
 
B. W.W.II constitutes an important turning point. Specifically,  
   The Holocaust. 
 
A. How was the International Human Rights Regime created? 
 
1. Nuremberg War Crimes Trials (1945-1946). Nazis were 
prosecuted under the then novel charge of Crimes Against 
Humanity. 
2. The United Nations  Its preamble for its Charter 
specifically mentions Human Rights. The UN has been the 
main international institution dedicated to elaborating international human rights standards. 
3. December 10, 1948  UN General Assembly unanimously adopted the Universal Declaration of Human Rights. 
4. Advent of the Cold War  Flagrant disregard of Human 
Rights by both the U.S, and Soviet Union.  
 
B. Decolonization and the entry of African and Asian countries into the UN. Greater progress made on the ratification of a H.R. 
treaty.  December 1966  - International Human Rights Covenants were finally completed. 
 
1, International Covenant on Economic, Social, and Cultural Rights. 
2. International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights 
3. Universal Declaration of Rights. 
 
All three together comprise the International Bill of Human Rights.  Existence of international covenants does not mean that they are being implemented. 
 
C. In the 1970s, UN began to put monitoring mechanisms into place, through the passage of resolutions. Also in the 1970s, the rise 
of international NGOs. HR Committee within the UN established 
in 1976. 
 
F.  HR are only as important as the sovereign states view and treat them.  (States can make them a part of its foreign policy. For example, President Carter in the late 1970s.)  
 
G. What are the Strengths and Weaknesses of NGOs? 
 
1. Strengths  Organizational independence; Lobby for change; Publicity and persuasion. 
2. Weaknesses  Non-binding; Credibility can be severely 
damaged if found to be dealing in inaccurate information. 
Their currency is accurate (and neglected) information.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>H. 1980s and 1990s  The deepening of International HR norms and 
issues as legitimate concerns of states and the international 
community such that now Humanitarian intervention is seen as a legitimate and sometimes preferred option. (UN peace keeping 
forces, care for refugees.) 
 
General Timeline: The emergence of International Human Norms (1940s) ---
 Cold War and Convenants (1950 and 1960s) ------  Monitoring in  
1970s ---   Further growth and Institutionalization (1980s) ------  
Continuity and Change in the Post-Cold War Era (1990s  Present)  
 
II.  Theories of Human Rights: 
 
The nature of HR  Universal rights possessed by every human being. They 
are equal rights in that every human being has them equally and may 
claim them irrespective of which country s/he lives. HR are moral rights as well in that they presume a shared notion of a good life and 
acceptable behavior. They typically do not include the right to murder, 
flat out, as a HR. 
 
Rights as entitlements  They are exercised and typically trump all competing claims.  Rights holders versus duty bearers. Human rights provide a moral standard of national political legitimacy. 
 
Human Rights based on some notion of human nature. But whats that? Most broadly, a moral account of human possibility.  
 
Marxists :  Human nature is the result of historical processes and esp. 
class struggle. 
 
Radical Behaviorists : Human nature is the result of social conditioning.  
 
Utilitarianism   Principle of utility  Greatest happiness principle 
requires us to act so as to maximize the balance of pleasure over pain. 
 
Moral and political theories that stress particularity are likely to be at odds with theories of universality. 
 
Kants categorical imperative: The duty to treat people as ends, never as means only. This imperative is categorical, without exception. A list of human rights can be seen as a political specification of what it 
means to treat all human beings as ends.  
 
In the end, although there may appear to be a political consensus, there is no philosophical consensus about human rights.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>International Humanitarian Intervention: Bosnia vs. Darfur, Sudan and Rwanda</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/l_20/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20-23</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>o	Serbia 
 Kosovo was an autonomous region of Serbia. 
o	Croatia 
o	Slovenia 
o	Bosnia-Herzegovina 
o	Macedonia 
o	Montenegro 
	What does a federal system do? 
Potentially keeps the peace. 
Allows for a certain amount of autonomy. 
o	U.S. is a federal system. 
o	You have more devolution of power a nd give substantial amount of power 
to the states. 
	While there were still separate ethnic id entities,  they were superseded by the 
national Yugoslavia identity. 
o	Which is underscored by the communism ideals. 
	Kosovo 
o	Under Tito, it was set up where Ko sovo had veto power over what was 
going on in Serbia. This was an admi nistrative  and political problem.  
There was an ethnic Albanian majority in Kosovo. 
o	Kosovo has some of the most sacred sites of the Serbs 
o	Serbs never liked that Albanian demographic domination. 
o	About 80% of Kosovo is Albanian. 
o	Albania is right next to Kosovo. 
o	Although ethnically identified with Albania,  Albanians Kosovars 
wouldnt necessarily want to be forced  out of Kosovo and into Albania.  
 Similar to Turks in Germany 
 Kurds in Iraq. 
	Yugoslavia began to have tensions within  the arrangement that were manifested 
in economic performance and political influence 
 Some of the republics were doing better than others. 
With the absence of an overriding ideology, communism  wilted. 
International community responded how to the war?
o	They werent pleased with the possi ble disintegration of Yugoslavia. 
o	Once you have international recognition, 
	Although these republics had ethnic major ities, the minority population was pretty 
large. 
	Which group had the most at stake in 
o	Muslims because they didnt have anywhere to go. 
o	Serbians back to Serbia, Croats back to Croatia. 
War ended in 1985, the Dayton accords ha ve been settled. What could the 
international community have done differently? 
2 of 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523: Ethnicity and Race in World Politics-Fall 2005 
Prof. M. Nobles 
Lecture 20: International Humanitarian Intervention: Bosnia vs. Darfur, Sudan and 
Rwanda 
Yugoslavia 
	Ethnic war not seen since WWII 
	What happened caught the world largely unaware. 
	In hindsight, the world looks back and can  see the indicators leading up to the 
conflict. 
Brief history of Yugoslavia 
	Map of Yugoslavia has changed over the years 
	Country was created after WWII the bounda ries of which consisted of three 
different boundaries 
1.	Previously independent states  of Serbia and Montenegro 
2.	Former Austro-Hungarian territories of Slovenia, Istria,  Dalmatia, 
Croatia-Slavonia, a nd Bosnia-Herzegovina 
3.	Macedonia (taken from the Ottoman Empire), 
	All groups were living fairly  peacefully prior to WWII  
	What would the state response be to ethnic political divisions? 
o	Mostly separate the groups a nd create six equal republics  
o	Complex power sharing solution 
 Similar to what they have in Northern Ireland. 
 Acknowledge that divisions among the people exist and decide on 
power sharing. 
	Trying to avert violence 
	Set up institutions that may appear less than democratic (a lot of 
emphasis on elite cooperation) in order to ensure peace. 
o	Student: Some sort of democratic ro ute.  Encourage leaders to sit down 
and talk. 
o	Student: International intervention 
 No fly zone 
 Demilitarized zones 
o	Student: Containment.  Let the groups fight it out and make sure that it 
doesnt spill over into other countries. 
o	Some sort of assimilation policy.  Get the actual groups to get along. 
o	Student: Treat the groups the same. 
o	Student: setup incentive program.  Like  countries trying to get into the 
E.U. using it as a carrot. 
	Student: was there a dominant group? 
o	Serbia was pretty dominant. 
	Communist rule. Every gr oup was largely separated ac ross the country with the 
exception of Bosnia-Herzegovina, where all three groups (Serbs, Muslims, Croats 
co-existed).  
	Republics comprising the former Yugos lavia, within a federal system. 
1 of 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Sources of Discontent: The Intersections of Race and Class&#160;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/o_l09/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9-10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523 / Lecture Notes 
 
 
From: William Julius Wilson, When Work Disappears: The World of the 
Urban Poor   
 
 
I. What are ghettos? What are inner-cities? They can be identified 
by a census tract, where where at least 40% of the residents are 
defined as poor, using federal standards.  
 
  A. Why is there such concentration? Because working people  
  and people with some means have moved out. 
b. The existence of hypersegregation among urban blacks - a 
result of de jure racial segregation and its legacy. 
c.Wilson argues, however, that the history of racial 
segregation cannot fully explain the concentration of 
poverty. He argues instead that some attention has to be 
paid to rapid depopulation as people left.  
  
II. The main problem today is joblessness and a new urban poverty, which Wilson describes as neighborhoods in which a substantial majority of individual adults are either unemployed or  
Have dropped out of the labor force altogether. It is important to stress here that there are plenty of poor neighborhoods where people work, but which are still poor, in some sense. Yet, the 
new urban poverty is characterized by substantial joblessness. 
 
III. In the past, greater class integration w/in black communities, resulted in neighborhoods w/ higher levels of social 
organization: Meaning: 
  a. The prevalence, strength, and interdependence of social 
  networks. 
  b. The extent of collective supervision that the residents 
exercise and the personal responsibility that they assume in 
neighborhood affairs. 
c. The rate of resident participation in voluntary and 
formal organizations and informal networks. 
 
 1. When social organization is poor low, 
 there are observable adverse effects on neighborhood 
 life. 
 2. Development of community norms that can facilitate 
negative behaviors. Clear connection between 
joblessness and violent crime. 
 
 
 
 IV. The Disappearance of Jobs 
  A. Decline of Manufacturing: Good jobs, with good wages, 
  which required a high school education and skills. These 
  jobs also offered job mobility within the industry, thereby 
  fostering stability. 
  B. With the decline of manufacturing, growth of the service 
economy, which pays less, offers less security, and 
sometimes requires more skills, or at least, another skill  
set. For little education and experience, these are the jobs. Yet, these jobs are typically associated with women. Known as pink collar jobs.  
C. The internationalization of the low-skill labor market. Flight of factories to countries where there is cheap and often non-unionized labor. 
C. In short, industrial restructuring has taken its toll on Americans, especially American males. (The losers in this</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Men have multiple partners and multiple children.  
F. General distrust of marriage as an institution, since the 
norms of marriage clash with the norms that many men possess. 
(High value on freedom and autonomy.)  
G. End result: A high tolerance for single parenthood.  
 
IX: The Meaning and Significance of Race  Employers and Inner-
City Workers. 
 
 A. Negative employer perceptions about their qualifications 
and work ethic are higher for black Americans than for any 
other group.  
  1. p. 113  Discuss the employers remarks. Also page 
 118 for table of employer observations on job 
attainment or retention. 
   a. Many employers see it as a class thing. 
   b. Weak to non-existent Work ethic 
   c. Moral character (or lack thereof) 
   d. Cultural predispositions 
   e. Neighborhood Milieu 
   f. Poor education 
 B. Significant Gender Gap  More positive attitudes towards 
black females than black males.  
 C. If these negative attitudes exist, what are the 
consequences? 
1. Employers will advertise in more local papers as opposed to city dailies, thereby restricting the 
applicant pool. 
2. Jobs will be advertised by word of mouth. 
3. A screening out process begins before a black applicant enters the room. Assessment of individuals is lost. 
4. Non-recruitment at black urban high schools. 
D. What are the attitudes of black workers, esp. black males? 
1. Knowledge that employers possess negative attitudes towards them.   
  2. Black males (versus Mexican males) more hostile to  
 low-paying jobs, less flexible in assignments and less 
willing to work hard for low wages. Sense of being a victim of discrimination. Also, a sense of honor and 
pride.  
 
X. What are the solutions? 
 
 A. Analogies to the U.S. experience  The experiences of 
unskilled immigrant workers, who were recruited to work and are now being laid off. Joblessness there, like here, is 
being created by changes in the global economy. 
 
 B. Yet, the U.S. is different  An absence of comprehensive 
public programs to promote the social rights of Americans. Anti-poverty programs have been limited and fragmented. 
Social citizenship rights in the U.S. are less developed and 
less intertwined with rights of political and civil citizenship.  For example, most housing programs designed to 
promote home ownership have been directed at the middle and 
working classes, not the poor.  Similarly, medical care is not considered a basic collective good. 
 
 C. A huge problem or difficulty in addressing poverty in the 
U.S. is how the discussion is itself framed: individual 
responsibility vs. the collective/structural circumstance.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>In the U.S., the economic origins and social significance of 
poverty and welfare are minimized. 
 
 D. The growth or increase of tensions b/ween blacks and 
other minorities (mostly immigrants) how live in 
neighborhoods that border black ghettos (e.g. Latinos) or 
who work in black ghettos (e.g. Koreans). Negative stereotypes and different views towards poverty and how to 
get out of it. 
 
 E. Affirmative Action policies have had the effect of 
benefiting those in the position to take advantage of it. 
These policies, on the whole, did not open up vast avenues of opportunities for the masses of black people. 
 
 F. Wilson recommends race neutral policies: Programs that 
increase employment opportunities and job skills training, 
improve public education, promote better child and health 
care, and reduce neighborhood crime and drug abuse  would, despite being race-neutral, disproportionately benefit the 
most disadvantaged segments of the population, especially 
poor minorities. 
 
 G. Wilson proposes two long-term solutions in an effort to 
address the issues of generating good jobs and combating the growing wage inequality among workers: 1) the relationship 
b/ween employment and education and family support systems, 
and 2) in the metropolitan context, the relationship b/ween the cities and suburbs. (p.208). 
 H. Wilson also suggests WPA-style jobs, aimed at broad segments of the U.S. population. 
 
1. Long-term solutions: Development of a system of national performance standards in public schools, 
family policies to reinforce the learning system in 
the schools, a national system of school-to-work transition, and ways to promote city-suburban 
integration and cooperation. 
2. Short-term solutions: Development of job 
information and placement centers and subsidized car 
pools in the ghetto to the creation of WPA-style jobs. 
 
 
XI.  Wilsons punchline: It is really more about class, than race.  The 
problems about which we are concerned, and appear to be borne in greater proportion by black people, cannot be solved by race-specific policies 
only. As Wilson sees them, such programs have real limitations insofar 
as they supposedly only benefit the better off (rather than the truly disadvantaged). They are also limited because of their limited political 
viability.  Wilson seems to think that class-specific policies have 
stronger political legs.  Is he right?  What on the American political landscape supports his view?  By contrast, Lani Guiner and Gerald Torres 
argue the opposite: That race is a useful way of forging class alliances.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>restructuring have been and will continue to be persons w/ 
lower levels of education. 
D. The reactions of these workers? They often drop-out of the labor force.  
 
 
 V. The New Jobs: What are they and where are they? There is now 
an evident mismatch between the suburban location of 
employment and urban workers. 
A. The few manufacturing jobs that remain are now in the 
suburbs. Difficult to get out there. 
B. Many service jobs are also out in the suburbs.  
 
 
VI. What other Factors have contributed to the creation of 
ghettos?  
   
1. Federal Government Policy : Government withheld mortgage capital, thereby making it difficult for urban residents to  
purchase their homes. FHA redlined black neighborhoods, by 
not underwriting mortgage loans  seen as high risks. 
2. Growth of suburbs, with different revenue streams.  
3. Lack of government efforts to combat racial discrimination in housing markets helped lead to the 
construction of massive public housing projects were heavily minority and poor.  
4. Crisis of Public Education funding. Poor neighborhoods tend to have poor and under-resourced schools. 
 
 
 VII. Ghetto-Related Behavior and the Structure of Opportunity: 
 
A. Without sufficient opportunities to join the formal labor market, ghetto residents join informal labor markets or are only loosely connected to formal labor markets through odd 
jobs, etc. This situation engenders: 
 1. A certain hopelessness and negative feelings. 
 2. Observable gender gap? Girls tend to stick w/ 
 things and boys head to the streets. 
 3. Attractiveness of Drug-Dealing and other  
 illicit activities.   
 4. Social isolation of adults  no mutual support 
 networks either for the neighborhood or for finding 
out about jobs. Lack of persons within the neighborhood with resources. 
 5. Increase in street- crime. 
 6. Absence of work-related behaviors and norms   
 everything from punctuality, sense of responsibility,  
speech patterns, dress codes and suitable public  
behaviors. 
  
 VIII. The Fading Inter-City Family 
 
  A. Decrease in marriage-rates: Men dont have jobs. 
B. A rise in children born of a mother who has never and may 
not ever be married. Among black women, higher educated 
women are more likely to marry than less educated women (The 
opposite of white women.) 
C. Many kids being raised by single mothers.  
D. In policy circles, it is often asserted that welfare has 
helped to foster single-parenthood.  Wilson argues that it is joblessness instead. 
E. On the whole, Wilsons respondents (the women) possess 
quite negative views of black men as husbands and fathers.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Government Responses to Ethnopolitical Demands and Group Disadvantage</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/o_l11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11-12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>5. The more violence is used by political authorities, the 
greater the likelihood that challengers will respond with 
violence. 
a. The more extreme force is used, the less likely the 
chances for open rebellion.  
6. The greater their external support, the greater the chances groups will use violent means to challenge authorities. 
7. The greater the international status accorded to a state, the less it is likely that its challengers are externally supported. 
 
C. Seven Concepts of a Variable Character: 
 
 1. Discrimination (Economic and Political) 
 2. Group Identity (Strength of) 
 3. Ethnopolitical leadership and group cohesion  degree of 
 cohesion b/ween leadership and followers. 
4. Type of Political Regime (e.g. Democratic, Authoritarian, etc.) 
  5. Severity of force used by Govt 
  6. Degree of External Support 
  7. Level of International political and economic status.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523 / Lecture Notes 
 
A THEORETICAL FRAMEWORK FOR ANALYSIS OF ETHNOPOLITICAL MOBILIZATION 
 
 
I. Approaches to Explaining Ethnopolitical Conflict 
 
A. Modernization theory predicted that ethnic identities 
would disappear. Why? Class identities or an overriding 
national identity would eventually subsume other identities. However, ethnic identities persisted in both developed and 
developing countries. 
 
B. With the evident failure of modernization theory to 
explain ethnic conflict, scholars have developed theories to 
explain why groups mobilize, sometimes, violently, sometimes not. 
 1. Instrumental reasons  To pursue clear aims: gain   
 rights, territory, goods, etc. Pursuit of ethnic and  
 political interests. 
2. Primordial  conflict has deep cultural and psychological sources. Defense of ethnic identity 
 
C. These two reasons are not mutually exclusive. Also, the instrumental approach tends to focus on the role of group elites. 
 
D. Non-violent and Violent Conflicts are different than genocides. Authors identify 5 internal factors, that, in 
combination, make genocides and politicides possible. 
 
 1. Persisting cleavages exist among ethnic groups 
 2. Elites have a history of relying on repression to  
 maintain power. 
3. Elites use their power to reward groups differentially for their loyalty 
4. The society has recently experienced a political 
upheaval, for example, a revolution or defeat in war. 
5. Exclusionary ideologies arise that identify target 
groups as expendable. 
 
 
 
 
 
II.  Seven Hypotheses for explaining Ethnopolitical Mobilization: 
  
 
 1. The greater the discrimination they experience, the more  
 likely they are to organize for action. 
 2. The more strongly a person identifies w/ an ethnic group  
that is subject to discrimination, the more likely he or she is to be motivated into action. 
a. The greater the number of traits common to a group, the stronger the group identity. 
 3. Group cohesion increases to the extent that groups are  
regionally concentrated, share many common traits and grievances over long periods of time, and have widely accepted autocratic leadership. 
4. The more democratic the political environment, the more likely ethnopolitical groups will be to voice opposition 
nonviolently.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Review Class - Lessons Learned and Looking Forward</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/l_25/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>25-26</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Should the indigenous groups be protected and saved? 
	Is it an utopian vision to sa ve these groups? Or is it the morally right thing to do? 
	Student: it sets a bad precedent. Were  more powerful than you and your culture 
doesnt matter.  Social dominance. 
	A dominant idea has been that there woul d be a gradual transition and that they 
will eventual disappear. 
Is the interest in their lands recent? 
	Theres always been interest, but its intensified recently. 
Student: You dont lose culture  of the tribe when you intr oduce some level of technology 
into the area. Well, logging is obviously out of the question, but maybe they could bring 
in Pharmaceutical companies in a regulated way. 
How open do you think Brazilians are in general to the indigenous population? 
	Student: its a far-fetched idea to think the indigenous  people moving to Rio or 
another large town. If it s a border town, theres going to be some skepticism 
coming from Brazilians. 
	Student: there is already antagonism be tween the two groups .  I dont think it 
would end well. 
	In the article, they were called wild  Indians by Brazilians who were quoted. 
	There is not a positive attitude a bout the indigenous  population among many 
Brazilians. 
How are Native Americans viewed now? 
	Student: if you asked a child, they w ould probably think Indians dont exist 
anymore. 
	Student: still have Indians in the Central Coast.  Student taught that white people 
abused the Indians. 
2 of 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523: Ethnicity and Race in World Politics-Fall 2005 
Prof. M. Nobles 
Lecture 25: Wrapping Up 
Article on indigenous people in Brazil 
	Indigenous groups living in Brazils Amazon forest. 
	Trying to remain autonomous, against developer, rancher, and government 
encroachment. 
How has the world dealt with indigenous people? 
	Student: Typically pretty bad. Impose policies and social movements ostracize 
the indigenous groups. Seen in the US and Australia. 
	US: sovereignty largely ignored. Trail of Tears, Andrew Jacksons policies 
decidedly displaced Native Americans.  Set up Oklahoma as a reservation to put 
Indians forced west from Georgia. 
	Student: very antagonistic relationship.  Conditions on the reservations today is 
poor, health conditions poor, access to education isnt very good.  Theyre trying 
to make it separate but equal, but its of course inherently unequal. 
	Student: European diseases  were initially brought over and killed many Native 
Americans. 
	Assimilation as a forced policy occurr ed in the US, New Zealand, Canada. 
	Removed children from the home, placed them in Indian schools and supposedly 
civilized the children. 
 Children werent allowed to speak their native languages. 
What would be the arguments for such policies? 
 Student: Everyone is on the same page 
What are the arguments agains t what happened in the US? 
	Student: Its essentially et hnic cleansing.  Forced them to assimilate, but we lied 
to them. 
	Student: How can you preach about civil liberties, etc. but take it away from the 
indigenous population. In ternally hypocritical. 
Brazil is going through something similar, althou gh at a very different point in time.   
	Pharmaceutical industry is interested in  exploiting the resources in the Amazon. 
	Conservationists want to preserve the Amazon. 
	Loggers are interest ed in the trees 
	Aboriginal groups want to continue  to exercise self-determination. 
	There are many competing interests.  
Where does the Brazilian govern ment fit in all of this? 
	FUNDAI: Department of Indian Affairs wasnt very friendly for a long time. 
	The new head person is friendlier and mo re open to Aboriginal peoples. Sees 
himself as their protector. 
1 of 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>International Dimensions of National Ethnopolitical Conflicts</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/o_l13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523 / Lecture Notes  
 
INTERNATIONAL DIMENSIONS OF NATIONAL ETHNOPOLITICAL CONFLICTS 
 
 
I. International Theories of the State System: 
  
A. According to IR theory, the world is an anarchic place, 
composed of nation-states, with supra- national organizations, 
such as the EC (regionally based) and internationally based (UN). 
 
B. Highly cohesive groups that have organized politically and obtained external support have a good chance of attaining some 
of their objectives. 
 
C. This outside support is, in turn, dependent upon the sympathies of international actors and the legitimacy of their demands.  
 
- For example, if the government recognizes the groups demands, then legitimacy is increased. 
 
 
Also, it is important to note that while there is a connection between these levels of analysis, which are in some sense mutually reinforcing, 
not all levels are equally influential on the other.  For example, individual preferences would have few global implications. However, 
global occurrences are very likely to affect individual preferences. For 
example, global warming, pollution, and overpopulation have all affected personal preferences and behaviors. 
 
II. What are the forms of outside support? 
 
A. Rhetorical Support  Public pronouncements, Powerful symbolism, 
B. Provision of supplies and Monies  Guns, etc. 
C. Training of Combatants 
D. Aggressive Intervention on behalf of the ethnic group.  
 
 
III. Factors / Variables that account for an Ethnic Groups Success or Failure: 
 
A. Extent of External Support : The greater their external support,  
The greater the chances that groups will use violent means to challenge authorities. (e.g. Miskito Indians and Contra War). 
 
B. International Status of the Regime : The greater the 
international status accorded to a state, the less likely that 
its challengers will be externally supported. (African-
Americans in the U.S., Turks in Germany in contrast to Kurds in Iraq).</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rethinking Ethnicity and Race</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/o_l02/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2-3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The threshold of statistical significance is arbitrary.  The 
probability of reaching significance for a given distance 
increases steadily with the number of individuals and genes 
tested.3   
 
 
III. A HISTORICAL CASE: BLUMENBACHS BLUNDER 
A. Blumenbach, one of the greatest and most honored scientists of 
the Enlightenment, developed taxonomy of the human races.  
1. His final taxonomy of 1795 divided all humans into five 
groups, defined by both by geography and appearance  in his 
order, the Caucasian variety, for the light-skinned people 
of Europe and adjacent parts of Asia and Africa; the Mongolian variety, for most other inhabitants of Asia, 
including China and Japan, the Ethiopian variety, for the 
dark-skinned people of Africa; the American variety, for most native populations of the New World; and the Malay 
variety, for the Polynesians and Melanesians of the Pacific 
and the Aborigines of Australia.
4
2. Blumenbach taxonomy was based largely on an earlier one 
created by Carolus Linnaeus (Systema Naturae) in 1758.  
However, the Linnaeus taxonomy had 4 races, while 
Blumenbachs had five. According to Gould, this slight 
alteration had huge ramifications. 
B.  The most significant difference is that Blumenbach introduced 
a notion of hierarchy, according to Gould. The idea of races 
provided by Linnaeus corresponded to the conventional cartography 
of the day.   
1. Blumenbachs alteration changed the axis of races from 
conventional cartography to another axis that included 
hierarchy although B was one of the more progressive thinkers of his time on the idea of race. He, for example, 
believed in the unity of the human species. He also believed 
in the relative superficiality of racial variation. 
C.  Nonetheless, Blumenbachs taxonomy also singled out a 
particular group as closest to the created ideal and then 
characterized all groups by relative degrees of departure from this archetypal standard. He ended up with a system that placed a 
single race at the pinnacle, then envisioned two symmetrical lines 
of departure away from this ideal toward greater and greater degeneration.
5  Beauty was the criterion that Blumenbach used to 
make his judgments re: degeneration. 
 
 
 
 
The key point is that race, as it has been widely and historically 
deployed, has not been limited to physical appearance.  Values are 
assigned and evaluations made about an individuals moral character, intelligence, and temperament, based upon membership in one group or 
another. 
 
                                                           
3 Luigi Luca Cavalli-Sforza, Genes, Peoples, and Languages , (Berkeley: 
University of California Press, 2000), p.5. 
4 Stephen Jay Gould, The Geometer of Race, Discover , November 1994, 
p.66. 
5 Ibid, p.69.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523 / Lecture Notes 
 
 
RETHINKING ETHNICITY AND RACE 
 
 
I. HOW HAVE RACIAL AND ETHNIC IDENTITIES BEEN UNDERSTOOD AND USED? 
A. Variously used by different professionals. Author James Shreeve 
provides an example from the forensic sciences . Age, sex, stature, 
and race are the cardinal points of a preliminary forensic report, 
the cornerstones that support the reconstruction 
of a specific human identity.1  But of the four, race is  
most subject to interpretation and contestation.  
 
1. Medical anthropologists  and other medical professionals  
use the term race to organize data and to analyze such data. There are studies, then, that purport to show differences in 
susceptibility to disease between races. [But what are these 
data really showing? For example, the high incidence of high blood pressure among African-Americans or high alcoholism 
rates among Native-Americans? 
 
Arent these data really telling us as much about socio-economic 
status and environmental conditions as about a purported racial 
susceptibility? 
 
 
II. WHAT IS RACE? 
 A. General Consensus that we are all members of the same species: 
 Homo sapiens.  
1. Shreeve offers this rough definition: race is the part of ones -persons variation on the theme of humanity 
created by the interplay of geography and inheritance. 
B.  Historically, anthropologists viewed concepts of races as 
fixed types, each of which was pure and distinct. [As such, a 
person of any given race would be taken as representative of 
that race, since each race had its own characteristics. Think of Linnaeus and Blumenbach.] 
1. The idea of cluster of physical characteristics and bushel- basket scheme still exist when we think about the shared physical characteristics that generally, but not 
completely, correlate to geography.  
2. The straightforward biological fact of human variation 
is that there are no traits that are inherently, inevitably 
associated with one another. Morphological features do vary 
from region to region, but they do so independently, not in packaged sets.
2  
C. But is it silly, as one biological anthropologist has argued, to suggest, that there are no races? 
D. There are human morphological (structure, form) differences and 
similarities, to be sure, but is race the right word to use? 
E. According to a study conducted by geneticist Richard Lewontin 
of Harvard, approximately 6% of human variation can be attributed 
to race.  
F. Heres a more recent attempt to define race provided by a 
leading researcher in the Human Genome Project , Luigi Luca 
Cavalli-Sforza:  A race is a group of individuals that we can recognize as biologically different from others.  To be scientifically recognized, the differences between a population 
that we would like to call a race and neighboring populations must 
be statistically significant according to some defined criteria.  
                                                           
1 James Shreeve, Terms of Estrangement, Discover , November 1994, p.57. 
2 Ibid, p.58.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Are Human Rights Universal?: Women&#8217;s Rights versus Cultural Practices&#160;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/o_l16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16-18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523 /  Lecture Notes 
 
ARE HUMAN RIGHTS UNIVERSAL? WOMENS RIGHTS VERSUS CULTURAL PRACTICES 
 
 
I. Susan Okin asks the question of whether multiculturalism is good for 
womens rights?  She largely judges that it is not. She argues that persons who endorse the moral and equality of men and women should be 
skeptical. 
 
 A. What is Feminism? What is Multiculturalism? 
 
1. Feminism  Women should not be disadvantaged b/c of their 
sex; that they should be recognized as having human dignity 
equal to that of men; that they should have the opportunity 
to live as fulfilling and as freely chosen lives as men can. 
 
2. Multiculturalism  the claim made within liberal democracies that minority cultures or ways of life are not sufficiently protected by the practice of ensuring the 
individual rights of their members. Therefore, special group 
rights should also protect the group. 
 
B. Okin argues that most cultures are suffused with ideologies and practices regarding gender. As importantly, most of these ideologies and practices disadvantage women.  Moreover, within 
these cultures the more powerful men are better positioned to 
determine and articulate the groups beliefs, practices, and interests.  
Therefore , protecting a given culture with group 
rights usually means disadvantaging some portion of the individual members within the group. Why has this simple critique been ignored?  Two reasons, according to Okin. 
 
1. They tend to treat cultural groups as monoliths. They pay more attention to differences 
between groups than within 
them. They ignore the gendered dimensions of the minority cultures. 
2. Advocates of group rights pay little or no attention to 
the private sphere, preferring instead to argue that culture 
is important in shaping what people come to regard as a good life.  The actual content of the culture is not 
deeply probed. But this is the main problem for Okin.  
 
C.   Cultures and Traditions are Sexist and Patriarchal: The 
content of culture matters, since much of it concerns the private 
sphere, where ideas and practices are deeply gendered as they typically revolve around reproduction, marriage, and family life. 
Within many cultures (mostly non-Western), women are denied basic 
liberties regarding reproductive and marriage choices. It is not only then those women are denied these basic choices, but as 
importantly (and linked), such authority and power over those 
decisions are given to men. 
 
1. Examples: Female Genital Operations; Polygamy; Rape laws where men are exonerated of charges if they marry or just offer to marry the victim for the purposes of family 
honor.  
 
D. According to Okin, western cultures are less sexist and patriarchal. More emphasis is placed on womens physical 
attractiveness and domesticity is still highly valued. Women are subjected to sexual violence. Women are most often engaged in 
unpaid work and are, many times, disadvantaged in marriages, esp.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>around divorce time.  Yet, women do enjoy the same basic freedoms 
as men and are subject to the same protections of the law.  
 
E. Where legal cases have arisen in Western liberal democracies, the courts have had to weigh the claims of individual women 
members against the cultural defenses, usually offered by the 
male defendants. The problem with these cultural defenses is that they: 1) resonate w/ past sexism of American law (i.e. the 
passion defense over adultery or a woman, who did not resist rape, 
thereby consented or a woman provoked a rape.) 2) These defenses disadvantage immigrant women in U.S. courts, by denying the 
protections of US law, by applying it unfairly. (Why should an 
immigrant man receive a reduced sentence for rape just b/c hes from a different culture?) 
 
F. The Liberal defense for group rights: According to Will Kymlicka, individuals require the self-esteem that group cultures 
can provide.  A minority culture requires special protections, 
lest it be swept up within the majority culture  thereby denying minority group members the opportunity to live their lives as they 
see fit. Yet, Kymlicka argues that such minority cultures should 
only be protected if they are themselves liberal, meaning that they are  sufficiently mindful of individual autonomy.  
 
Why must the minority cultures be liberal? B/c we are concerned with cultural membership precisely to preserve choice (meaningful 
cultural choices for minority group members). Thus, a minority 
group that denies individual choice violates this basic principle.  
 
G. All of  this leads Okin to ask whether certain of these cultures ought to be preserved. Maybe they should be extinct  if we take individual rights of women and girls into account.  
 
F.  A Solution?  Okin ends by arguing that group rights are only acceptable if: 
 1) The private sphere of the culture is subject to scrutiny. 
 2) The voices of all group members are heard  women and the least advantaged  not just men and the powerful when negotiating 
group rights.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Human Rights and Foreign Policy: Should Outsiders Assist the Ethnic/Racial Groups of Another Country?</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/l_19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Read: PRINCIPLES FOR MILITARY INTERVENTION , the Responsibility to 
Protect. 
o	Student: Hurricane Katrina would have justified interven tion based on this 
definition. 
o	Student: what does the U.N. have to  gain from creating such broad 
abilities? 
o	The U.N. has no power and it can only  implore the country to stop the 
human rights abuses, but its ulti mately left up to the country. 
o	Student: what would you consider a significant loss of life?  You could 
rationalize not considering intervention of the Hussein regime because the 
atrocities may not have added up to a significant loss of life. 
o	Student: it seems to me that it gives the U.N. a lot of leeway to use as 
justification to do what they want. 
o	Student: it seems counterproductive to  protecting human rights.  It 
quantifies the number that must be lost  but the idea of hu man rights is that 
if its violated its violated. Not quantified. 
o	Student: Theres something morally wrong to saying significant loss of 
life and assigning value to a particular number of lives. 
	What about the ethnic cleansing portion of the document 
o	How does a person who is the product of rape ethnically identify 
himself/herself when the mother wa s raped by an ethnically superior 
man? 
	It has something to do with the larger political concept. 
	You want demographic superi ority and you solve that by 
saying the child belongs to the superior group. 
	Serbs for instance didnt like the Bosnians, but raped 
Bosnian women in order to change the ethnic balance. 
	Unless the kids are removed from the mother, they will not 
adopt the identity of the rapist. 
	This is a common strategy in  war and ethnic cleansing. 
	There are some precautionary principles in the document. 
o	Intervention should be a last resort. 
o	The country must be intervening to halt or avert human suffering. 
	Why would you want reasonable prospect s of success for an intervention? 
o	Student: the idea that you could make it worse.  
	Whats going on in the Sudan today? 
o	Arabs in the north at war with Christians in the south. 
o	In Darfur, Northern Arabs who are Mu slim are against the black Africans 
who are also Muslim. 
o	The government hasnt done anything about these militias, mostly because the government are supporting them. 
o	There had been a war going on for th e past 20 years in southern Sudan. 
o	They reached a peace agreement last year; the head of the southern 
liberation forces was made the vice president in the Sudanese government 
to show that they were united. 
-2-</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>o	Somalia syndrome: promoting isolationist  principles because of the fallout 
in Somalia. 
How do we think about U.S. interests in humanitarian intervention? 
	Some would say that human rights dont even come close to describing the 
motives for intervention. 
	If thats the case, why do we bother at  all with human rights intervention? 
o	Student: It sounds so much better to say that were going for human rights.  
It cuts down on the disgust. 
o	Student: if the U.S. aids countries fo r humanitarian efforts, it could be 
seen as increasing credibility and legitimacy of government. 
o	Student: its an ideal because were not there.  The fact that its out there 
and its what we eventually want to  be.  It could potentially do good. 
o	We can say that for smaller countries, theyre able to put human rights at 
the center of their policies. 
o	The world is a better place with human rights even if they are ignored or 
disregarded. 
o	Leaders do have to acknowledge them and maybe thats the best we can 
hope for. 
o	Even though dictators, et c violate human rights, the dictators know that 
they are violating human rights and could potentially be subject to some 
kind of intervention. 
-4-</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>o	There was a lot of international pressure for both sides to settle this 
conflict. 
o	The VP was killed in a plane crash 
o	In the West (Darfur), theres a conf lict between Arabs and Blacks (both 
Muslim) 
o	Its very complicated, and it appears to be Arab vs. Black, but there are other elements  to the conflict as well. 
o	People have been using rape as a war tool. 
o People from the Darfur re gion have escaped to Chad. 
There are many places around the world with sign ificant levels of vi olence, but no one is 
calling for an intervention. 
	The Sudan is one of these. 
 The Russians and Chechnya. 
International laws say one thing about humanitarian intervention, but how does the 
national foreign policy of other countries compare to the U.S.? 
	Different countries respond differently. 
	Donnelly discusses Like minded countries 
o	Which countries? What do thei r foreign policies look like? 
 There are a few smaller western European countries 
	Norway 
	Netherlands 
	Human rights matters enormously. 
	Use development assistance 
	Fashion foreign policy that communicates that to the 
recipient country that human rights is important and helps 
them with the development of these ideas 
	Actively use foreign policy to promote these ideas within 
recipient countries 
	U.S. and Great Britain 
o	Student: Norway and Netherlands have the luxury of spending their 
money and foreign policy to advance smaller nation because they enjoy 
the security provided by a larg er country like the U.S.  
Is it that humanitarian efforts have boiled down to a smoke screen for ulterior motives? 
	Student: I think the world lik es to hear discussions a bout that, but its unlikely 
coming from the U.S.  In the Middle East, people were killed to maintain his 
power. In Egypt, they exported people for torture and the government is chasing 
after those people and shooting them.  Instead of invading were giving them 
foreign aid. 
	Would Somalia have satisfied that clai m?  Going in for humanitarian reasons? 
o	Student: there was significant oil, not in Somalia, but in the sea.  Americans had holdings and foreign i nvestment in the area and stood to 
lose a lot. 
o	Most Americans saw Somalia as a purely humanitarian effort 
o	It became a bigger deal and 18 soldiers were killed. 
o	The operation went poorly and Amer icans immediately asked why the 
government was intervening c onsidering the blood shed. 
-3-</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523: Ethnicity and Race in World Politics-Fall 2005 
Prof. M. Nobles 
Lecture 19: Human Rights and Foreign Policy: Should Outsiders Assist 
the Ethnic/Racial Groups of Another Country? 
Last week we spoke about multiculturalism  and upholding womens rights.  The focus 
shifts to the international arena and hu manitarian intervention.  Again you have 
competing values of whether and when to intervene. 
What does the international community think ab out intervention and what is the status of 
international law? 
	The international community ha snt come to a consensus 
	Its an easy question, but a difficult answer. 
	The block against intervention is the no tion of sovereignty and respecting that 
idea. 
	The idea is that the international system is built on states, which are built on 
sovereignty. Its very important. 
	There isnt a grand international govern ment. Theres a hope that governments 
dont mistreat their own populations. 
	Historically, there was very little rec ourse for groups within a given country.  
Certain views on intervention changed af ter WWII and the creation of the U.N. 
	Intervention is allowed for now. 
	Its something that states use sparingly. 
	Ch. 7 of the U.N. allows for intervention. 
	Article 34 empowers Security Council to investigate security problems within and 
between states. 
A government can invite another government to help.  Thats not seen as an intervention. 
What is the basis for humanitarian intervention? 
	Its vexing b/c of the iron law of sovereignty, on the one hand,  and the 
international community is interested in protecting basic human rights, on the 
other. You have to balance the two commitments. 
What is an example where an intervention leads to occupation? 
 Cyprus. 
An intervention on humanitarian grounds can sometimes be viewed as an occupation. 
Any response is viewed as meddling and is au tomatically discredited.  In the absence of 
any consensus for intervention (when you should intervene, how long, how you would 
intervene, etc.) in internati onal law, then we shouldnt have any kind of intervention. 
The Responsibility to Protect was written  in response to what happened in Rwanda, 
Bosnia, and Somalia.  The U.N. wanted to co me up with a rationale for why they didnt 
intervene and under what conditions it could intervene. 
-1-</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ethnic and Racial Identities in Comparative Perspective&#160;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/o_l04/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>ETHNIC AND RACIAL IDENTITIES IN COMPARATIVE PERSPECTIVE 
 
 
I. Gans  Symbolic Ethnicity  Using the experiences of white ethnic 
groups in the U.S., Gans argues that by the 3rd generation, white ethnics 
adapt a symbolic ethnicity. It is one of convenience and of little cost 
(economic or social). It does not organize life in any meaningful way. 
a. What about white identity? What identity do these ethnic groups hold on to? 
b. What distinguishes these groups from non-white ethnic 
groups? 
c. Gans argues that prior theorists were wrong. There is no  
straight line to assimilation, but rather than some ethnicity is retained. 
d. Assimilation into American-ness which is implicitly 
white. 
 
 
II.  Kim  Racial Triangulation Between Whites, Blacks, and Asians. 
Where Gans says nothing about whiteness as a powerful supra-identity 
into which European ethnics entered, Kims article is based upon the idea of white dominance and manipulation. That is, whites manipulate and 
occupy a field of racial positions, where they play Asians and Blacks 
off against one another, while degrading both. 
a. Kim judges this idea of racial triangulation to be have 
been successful politically. 
b. Civic Ostracism  Never fully American, always foreign in 
some way. 
c. Asians as the Model Minority vis--vis Blacks. 
 
III. Horowitz  Ethnic Identities are best thought of as familial 
arrangements. Ethnic identities and affiliations in Asia and Africa are 
stronger than in the West where there are cross-cutting cleavages. In Asia and Africa, societies are typically divided along one ethnic 
cleavage.  
a. Ethnicity is a kinship connection, although it is best 
thought of as existing along a continuum, from birth to 
choice. 
b. Yet Horowitz also claims that it permeates all of civic 
life and interactions. 
 
 
Ethnic affiliations exist along a continuum of ways in which people 
organize and categorize themselves. 
 
Voluntary Membership --------------------------&gt; Membership by Birth 
 
Often times, these two extremes are not mutually exclusive, although 
they would appear to be. For example, voluntary social clubs often times 
decide membership based on ones origins. Both principles of membership 
 birth and choice  are capable of accommodating fictive elements. 
 
Definition of Ethnicity: Extended Kinship (terms such as brother, cousins, etc. are employed). The ethnic tie is simultaneously suffused with overtones of familial duty and laden with depths of familial 
emotion.  
 
 
Uses of Ethnicity (or EI as function): 
1. Assists transition from rural to urban areas. 
2. Marriage choices are constrained and presented. 
3. All types of transactions outside of the home are facilitated by 
ethnic ties.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Processes of Ethnic Fusion and Fission: 
 
Whether one or the other of these occurs depends on the political 
context. 
1. Under colonialism  The establishing of colonial boundaries (both 
territorial, administrative, and social) can result in either subgroup 
amalgamation or aggregation/dis-aggregation. 
 
Changes in ethnic boundaries and the appearance of organized efforts can produce corresponding changes in culture: 
1. Myths of common ancestry emerge or disappear 
2. Music and other cultural practices reflect the new ethnic order of either aggregation or dis-aggregation. 
3. Similarly the case with literature and folklore.  
 
The Utility of Ethnic Affiliations: 
 
1. They help in the negotiation of social and business transactions. 
2. Emotional support and meaning producing. 
 
Ethnicity and the Modern State: 
 
1. Electoral Politics  Ethnic Parties 
2. Can liberalism (individualism) work or be meaningful in highly divided societies. 
 
Ethnicity and Class: 
 
1. Ethnic affiliations  Should they be viewed as just another way for 
economic and political elites to advance their own individual and class 
interests under the guise of the group.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>What are the Political Dimensions of Ethnicity and Race?&#160;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/o_l05/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5-7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523 / Lecture Notes 
 
 
ETHNIC AND RACIAL IDENTITIES IN COMPARATIVE PERSPECTIVE 
 
 
I.  From Ethnic Conflict in World Politics   Gurr and Harff 
 
Chapter One: Ethnic Conflict and the Changing World Order 
 
A.  Contemporary Examples of Ethnopolitical Conflict  What are 
the desired outcomes of Ethnopolitical mobilization? 
1.Autonomy or Independence: Sometimes autonomy can be an end 
in itself or it can be seen as a means to the end of  
  Independence. What is desired is informed, in part, by  
  existing constraints and opportunities. 
   a. East Timor  Autonomy, maybe independence 
   b. South Africa  Independence 
   c. Indigenous populations in the US, Canada, and  
   Australia, 
 
2. Civil Wars  When groups within an existing or disintegrating country fight violently to obtain their 
desired ends. 
   a. Ethnic cleansing is a common tactic of conflict. 
   b. Genocide is an extreme form of warfare. 
  
c. Revolution  Complete overthrow of political system. 
Usually has a strong political ideological component, but 
ethnic dimensions are usually present at well, even if not up front. 
 
 B. Defining and Mapping the World of Ethnic Groups. 
  1. Identity groups is Gurrs preferred term. 
a. Fighting against Discrimination (Economic and 
Political) 
   b. Nationalists  Want their own State 
   c. Protracted Communal Conflicts (Northern Ireland,  
   Southern Sudan, etc.) 
d. Sometimes, Pan groups have developed to fight for 
a common cause, if not against a common foe. (Pan-Arab, 
Pan-Indigenous, Pan-African) 
 
 C.  The Timing of Ethnic Conflicts 
  1. The End of Colonialism  The beginning of wars as 
  countries won independence and had to redistribute  
  political, economic, and public goods. The conflicts either  
happened in societies where there was a clear majority/ 
minority (e.g. India, Nigeria, Rwanda) or in Angola, where groups were more evenly distributed.  
2. The End of the Cold War  With the ending of proxy regimes that had the backing of the U.S. or USSR, state 
power decreases, and war begins. Example: USSR, Ethiopia, 
Angola, Former Yugoslavia. 
3. Some ethnic conflicts are neither directly connected to the end of Colonialism or the Cold War, but have more to do 
w/ the political ambitions/greed of domestic political 
elites. 
 
 
Chapter Two: The World of Ethnopolitical Groups 
 
A. The World Historical Background to Contemporary Ethnic Conflicts</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>1. Stratified Societies  Stratified along ethnic lines in  
 post-colonial world. Ethnic groups that were privileged  
under colonialism usually attempt to maintain their 
privileges upon independence. 
 a. New World Slavery 
 b. Removal/ Extermination of Indigenous Populations 
In short, colonialism, slavery, and conquest have all left their  
imprint on contemporary politics, in that the stratification that 
 continues to see has deep historical roots. 
 
B. The Types of Groups and their Grievances: (These groups are not 
always mutually exclusive.  
1. Ethnonationalists  We Want Our Own State (Basques in 
Spain) 
 2. Indigenous Groups  We Want Our Land and Autonomy Back 
3. Communal Contenders  Political aim is to share power in the central govt of modern states.  
4. Ethnoclasses  are ethnically or culturally distinct minorities who occupy distinct social strata and have specialized economic roles in the societies in which they 
now live. Most ethnoclasses in advanced industrial societies 
are composed of descendants of slaves or immigrants who were brought in to do the hard and menial work the dominant 
groups would not perform (e.g. Lebanese in Africa, Turks in 
Germany, etc.)  
5. Sometimes, the relationships b/ween indigenous groups and 
ethnoclasses can overlap. For example,  Indians in Fiji.  
6. Visible Minorities  People who can not easily fit in. 
For example, Somali in Norway and the Netherlands. 
7. Dominant Minorities  Tutsi in Burundi, White Afrikaaners 
of South Africa. 
8. Politically Active Religious Minorities  
 C.  Matching the Types with the Cases 
1. Ethnonationalists  Their demands pose the greatest dilemma for states and the international system; they are 
the source of some of the most deadly and protracted 
conflicts of the last 50 years. (The Kurds in Iraq). 
2. Communal Contenders- Groups seek a place in the existing 
states. (The Chinese in Malaysia). 
3. Ethnoclasses  Turks in Germany. Usually, their demands 
and actions are not a major threat to regional or 
international security, but they are a matter of political 
concern, both nationally and internationally. 
4.Indigenous groups  The Miskito of Nicaragua. They demand 
autonomy, based on their claims as the original inhabitants 
or owners of the land.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ethnic Minority Rights, Human Rights, and Sovereignty</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/17-523-ethnicity-and-race-in-world-politics-fall-2005/resources/l_24/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17.523: Ethnicity and Race in World Politics-Fall 2005 
Prof. M. Nobles 
Lecture 24: Ethnic Minority Right s, Human Rights, and Sovereignty 
Article passed out: Schneider, Peter.  The new Berlin Wall. New York Times. December 
4, 2005. 
What were the students reactions  to the video? Student Views: 
	When the conflict was going on, the Hutus were being stopped by the UN 
forces and white people with weapons. It seemed like they didnt want to hurt 
people other than Tutsi. 
	The concept of their cultural obedience is  to whom?  Government authority? 
Whether its Hutu or Tutsi. 
	There was a certain amount of deception.  People told to go to churches were 
unaware that the Priests had betrayed them.  
	The RPF was more disciplined and directed than the Hutu forces. 
	It took a long time for the RPF to reach the government. 
	There was a small distribution of forces  for the RPF and they were able to 
defeat the Hutu.   
	One of the most disturbing things was that the Hutu killers would be so drunk 
and not realize when people were dead. They went around shooting dead 
bodies because they didnt know 
	How do you try these people?  Is  there a double jeopardy concept? 
o The leaders were tried by international court in Tanzania. 
o	The national courts handled the less powerful leaders. 
o	The biggest problem is that they  dont have enough resources. 
o	The prisons are very full. 
o	Theyre not being tried at a proper rate. 
o	Tanzania was chosen largely because of its proximity. Also, a certain 
amount of Tutsi exiles reside in Tanzania. 
	Was it the Saddams power as a person that allowed him to order people 
around? 
o	Thats a hard question to an swer.  Men who have exerted 
extraordinary power for terrible ends.  What made Hitler Hitler? 
o	Theres no easy answer as to whether its him or his power. 
o	Its a combination of both. 
o	Certain personality traits combined  with opportunity produced Hussein 
as a leader of Iraq. 
	Certain US officials were  asked whether it was genocide dodged the question. 
In last class, we talked about how to punish.  Helen Cobbans article addresses this. 
	She raises the issue of Mozambique a nd how you might have reconciliation in 
a country that has experi enced a lot of violence. 
	What is the Mozambique system for prosecuting? 
1 of 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The fighting has sent over 100,000 people into exile and killed at least 75,000 
people. 
What does each side want? 
	Darfur liberation army wants a better re distribution of government funds and  
	Also wants government to stop as sisting Arabs in the war.  
	Why hasnt the government responded with force against militias. 
o	There are competing explanations: 
 Idea of straight racism. 
 Central government refuses to respond to another groups 
demands.   
	If they respond, the government will have to respond to 
any other group. Public funds are not well distributed 
among regions or ethnic groups.  
3 of 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>o	People are brought back into the community because the evil that was 
in their community was just that.  Mozambicans claimed that evil that 
committed those acts, not the people. 
o	Theyre not saying that atrocities didnt happen, but offenders had to 
offer an account of what they had done. 
	When did the conflict in Mozambique end? 
o	Early 1990s 
	Mozambique tried to integrate the offenders back into society. Made them do 
community service if they claimed that evil possessed them. 
Genocide today?  Darfur, Sudan 
	Received independence in 1956 from Britain. 
	There is a north-south divide. 
	Capitol, Khartoum is in the north. 
	War was waged in 1955-1972, between North and South. 
	It picked back up in 1975. 
	Why were the evangelicals in Midla nd Texas interested in the Sudan? 
o There were Christians in the S udan who were being persecuted. 
	They pushed the Bush administration into resolving the conflict. 
	Bush responds to their pressure by appointing former Senator Danforth who 
led the American efforts to bring pea ce to the southern Sudanese crisis. 
	Southern Sudanese liberation armys head is John Garang. 
	He agrees to be vice president in Khartoum. 
	He is then killed in an airplane accident 
	The peace agreement  still appears to be  holding up, even after his death.  
 The years of fighting have been disastrous for the south.  
As the Samantha Powers article paints it,  as do a number of observers, there seems to 
have been a delicate balance between Arab nomadic herders and African Farmers.  As 
long as the balance was in sh ape, they werent at war. 
	What was that balance and what threw it off? 
o	Both groups were expanding and needed more land. 
o	Land became scarce partly because of drought. 
	How do the Arabs survive? 
o	Theyre herdsmen. 
	The central government in Khartoum ignor ed the signs of the brewing tension. 
	In the late 1990s, there were hundreds of fights. 
	The government saw what was going on, but didnt know what to do and didnt do enough. 
	Sudanese liberation army sensed the br ewing problems and the fact that the 
government wouldnt do anything. 
	All top jobs were going to the Arabs from the North. 
	As a result, the Darfur liberation army was formed. 
	Wanted to get the worlds attention. 
	Arab militias use rape as a war tool. 
2 of 3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
