<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/</course_url>
    <course_title>Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Chemistry </list>
      <list>Earth Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Atmospheric Photochemistry and Air Pollution I (PDF - 1.7MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/resources/mit12_335f14_lecture1_1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Measuring [NOx](= [NO] + [NO2]) &amp; [NO2] 
(2B Technologies Model 401 NO2 Converter)  
Air stream (containing both NO and NO2 ) passes through a molybdenum 
catalytic converter which converts NO2 into NO prior to the air entering the NO 
Monitor.  
 
Thus the NO Monitor gives a measurement of [NOx].  
 
Then [NO2] = [NOx]  [NO] where [NO] is value obtained by NO Monitor 
without using the Converter 
 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Measuring CO: Teledyne 300E Carbon Monoxide Analyzer 
(similar to the 360E CO2 Analyzer)  
Beer-Lambert Law 
Calibration:   Zero/Span 
 
Zero and Span gases should match chemical composition of sample  
 
Span gas with concentration ~80% of full measurement range 
 
Traceable to NIST standard -Band pass filter at 4.7m with 
14 m pathway 
-GFC wheel with CO to cancel  
interfering gases  
(H2O, CO2, N2O, CH4)  
-Low CO cannot be accurately  
measured with high 
concentrations  
of interfering gases 
 
6II0exp[[CO]COcell]
I[CO]ln[0]/(COcell)
I
 Teledyne Technologies Incorporated . All rights reserved. This content
is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For  
more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Measuring O3: Ozone Calibration Source, contd 
 
Scrubs ozone from ambient air to produce zero 
air and air with ozone mixing ratios 30-1000 
ppb, up to 10 concentration steps 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Benefits: portable &amp; source of ozone with same 
humidity, P, etc as air to be measured 
 
Factory calibrated against NIST-traceable 
ozone standard 
  
O3 concentration depends upon:  
     -lamp intensity  
     -O2 concentration (P and T)  
     -sample time in cell (cell volume and  flow rate) 
Courtesy of 2B Technologies, Inc. Used with permission.
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Global Warming Art. Some rights reserved. License: CC BY-SA. This content is excluded from our
Creative Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
3Gas absorption and scattering</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
12.335 / 12.835 Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry
Fall  2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Measuring Aerosols: DustTrak Model 8520-1 
Continuous sample stream illuminated with laser light at 780 nm 
Smallest detectable particle 0.1m  
Light scattering in all directions, focusing lens and photo-detector at 90
 degrees 
Fixed sensing volume 
Can choose 1.0m, 2.5m, and 10m inlet nozzles  *Optics kept clean by 
surrounding aerosol stream in 
a sheath of filtered air* 
 TSI Incorporated. All rights reserved. This content is excluded
from our Creative Commons license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>BEERS _LAW
I=photon  flux(photons /m2)
x=photon  pathlength  from  source  (m) (total  path=2.5m)
[i]=gas concentration  (molecule /m3)Measuring CO2: TELEDYNE Model 360E  
Gas Filter Correlation (GFC) Optical Analyzer 
IR SOURCE IS  
HOT FILAMENT (4.3 m) 
 Teledyne Technologies Incorporated . All rights reserved. This content
is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more  information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
4
I(x)I(0)exp([i]x)
absorbtion  cross  section at 4.3m (m2/molecule )</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Measuring CO2: Teledyne Model 360E Analyzer, contd.  
[GDC should be GFC] 
[CO should be CO2] 
5
 Teledyne Technologies Incorporated . All rights reserved.  This content is excluded from  our
Creative Commons license. For more  information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Measuring NO: Nitric Oxide Monitor  
(2B Technologies Model 400) 
NO + O3  NO2 + O2 + chemi-luminescence*   
*Alternative chemi-luminescence analyzer: Detects the small amount 
of light produced. Higher sensitivity &amp; faster response time but requires 
more frequent calibration - Stoichiometric reaction 
- Adequate concentration of O3 added to the sample stream 
- Decrease in the concentration of O3 is measured by absolute UV absorption         
(as in the Ozone Monitor, 254nm) 
 
Beer-Lambert Law 
Ftotal/(Ftotal - Fozone)  is dilution correction factor ( F = flow rate) molecules/cm3 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Beer-Lambert Law
Solenoid valves switch in unison to alternately send ozone-scrubbed air and 
unscrubbed air through the two absorption cells.  
The intensity of light passing through ozonescrubbed air ( Io) is measured in Cell 1 
while the intensity of light pass through unscrubbed air (I) is measured in Cell 2. 
Every 2 seconds, the solenoid valves switch, changing which cell receives ozone-
scrubbed air and which cell receives unscrubbed air.  The 2 values are averaged. 
Measuring O3: Dual Beam Ozone Monitor, contd.  
Courtesy of 2B Technologies, Inc. Used with permission.
8II0exp[[O3]ozonecell]
 I[O3]ln[0]/(ozonecell)I</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>ATMOSPHERIC 
PHOTOCHEMISTRY and 
AIR POLLUTION  
Field Campaign on Top of 
Bldg. 54 
 On the top of the building 
you will measure 
ultraviolet radiation 
(UV), CO, O3, NO, NO2, 
CO2, wind speed (u), 
temperature (T) and 
aerosols (1, 2.5, and 
10m diameter filters) 
(we will use aerosols as 
tracers of nearby 
combustion). 
 Image courtesy of Christine Daniloff/MIT. Used with permission.
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>RONALD PRINN &amp; MARIA ZAWADOWICZ 
 SEPTEMBER  9, 2014   
TOPIC 1  
ATMOSPHERIC PHOTOCHEMISTRY and 
AIR POLLUTION 
 
Field Project &amp; Instrumentation: 
 CO, O3, NO, NO2, CO2, aerosols, UV 
 
  12.335/12.835 EXPERIMENTAL ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY, FALL 2014 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Measuring O3: Ozone Calibration Source, contd. 
    O2 + h  O + O 
2 [O + O2 + M]  2 [O3 + M] 
 
    3 O2 + hv  2 O3 
Low pressure mercury lamp photolyzes oxygen at 185 nm 
(monitored by photodiode) Uses same chemistry that 
produces ozone in the 
stratosphere 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Measuring Aerosols: DustTrak, contd. 
4m is internationally accepted as 
the 50 percent cut-off size for 
respirable aerosol diameter. 
Particles larger than 4 m impact 
onto the surfaces of the upper 
respiratory tract and cannot reach 
the lungs. 
 
10mm Nylon Dorr-Oliver 
Cyclone (2) included with the 
aerosol monitor can be used to 
discriminate between the 
respirable fraction and other 
portions of the ambient aerosol.  
 
Particle-laden air sample swirls inside the Cyclone  body. Larger (higher mass) 
particles cannot follow the air stream and become trapped, while smaller 
particles stay in the air stream and pass through. When using the Cyclone , you 
can assume that all particles smaller than the cut-off size pass through and all 
larger particles become trapped in the grit pot. 
17 TSI Incorporated. All rights reserved. This content is excluded
from our Creative Commons license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Measuring Aerosols: DustTrak, contd. 
Mie light scattering theory 
Scattered light by aerosols dependent upon: 
 Particle size parameter [ratio of circumference (D) to laser wavelength ()]  
 Index of refraction of aerosol material 
 Aerosol light absorption properties ( = abs/(abs+scat) 
 
Collected light  Total scattered light  Aerosol mass concentration   
 
Calibration and Zeroing  
Internal calibration constant relates this linear response.  Determined from the ratio of 
voltage response to the known mass concentration of a test aerosol (ISO 12103-1, A1 
Arizona Test Dust) that has a wide size distribution representative of a variety of 
ambient aerosols 
Optional recalibration for each specific aerosol type 
Zero calibration daily with zero inlet filter  
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Measuring NO: Nitric Oxide 
Monitor, contd. 
Reference cell to correct for ambient O3 
Adequate reaction time 3.5 - 4.5s 
 
Light intensities measured for: 
Sample air and reference 
NO scrubbed sample air and reference 
 
Ozone production by low pressure mercury 
lamp at 185nm to photolyze O2 (same as 
Ozone Calibration Source) 
Corrections for incomplete reaction and dilution 
by added ozonized air 
Courtesy of 2B Technologies, Inc. Used with permission.
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Measuring O3: Ozone Calibration Source 
(2B Technologies Model 306) 
In principle, the 
measurement of ozone 
by UV absorbance 
requires no external 
calibration; it is an 
absolute method.  
 
However, non-linearity 
of the photodiode 
response and 
electronics can result in 
a small measurement 
error (Model 306 versus 
standard). Therefore, 
each instrument is 
compared with a NIST-
traceable standard 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Beer-Lambert Law
Ozone has an absorption maximum at 254 nm, coincident with the principal 
emission wavelength of a low-pressure mercury lamp 
 
Only potential interferences from organic compounds in highly polluted air 
Measuring O3: 2B Technologies Model 205 
Dual Beam Ozone Monitor 
Courtesy of 2B Technologies, Inc. Used with permission.
7II0 3 ozonecell
I[O3]ln[0]/(ozonecell)exp[[O] ]
I</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>CO{{&lt; sub &#8220;2&#8221; &gt;}} and Climate Change (PDF - 4.2MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/resources/mit12_335f14_lecture2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12&#8211;17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Basic of Infrared spectrum (diatomic molecule)
8
677

P branch R-branch
12
0
1 10
* Each molecule (and each vibrational mode) has characteristic absorption pattern because the center of the 
band corresponds to vibrational frequency, which depends upon force constant (strong bond) has high frequency and reduced mass (proportional to sqrt(k/)) and spacing between lines goes with rotation constant (bond length and reduced mass). 
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>Low spectral resolution (0.4 cm-1) high P (760 torr) 
High spectral resolution (0.004 cm-1), high P (760 torr) 
High spectral resolution (0.004 cm-1), low P (76 torr)Quick overview of the HITRAN database
28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Compact/inexpensive NDIR detector 
Cost: $ 60-200 
Light source: Incandescent Lamp Detector: Thermopile 4.25m0.1m (HW) IR lter 15 cm pathlength (gold coated cell) hydrophobic lter to avoid liquid H
2O 
!
Repeatability 20 ppm Accuracy 30 ppm
http://www.co2meter.com/collections/co2-sensors
Portable CO 2 meter/data 
logger in a bird house CO2 Meter. All rights reserved. This content is excluded
from our Creative Commons license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Aerodyne Tunable QC Laser 
Spectroscopy 
!
Path Length, 76 m Cell Volume, 500 mL Precision    0.05 ppm Quantum Cascade Laser at 4.2 m (4.6 m for N
2O) 
Pressure at &lt;30 mbar
 15  
      
 
         Figure 2. 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>ENERGY BALANCE IN THE CLIMATE SYSTEM
ESSENCE 
OF THE  
GREEN- 
HOUSE 
EFFECT
32
Trenberth, Kevin E., John T. Fasullo, et al. "Earth's Global Energy Budget ." Bulletin of the American
Meteorological Society  90 (2009): 31123.  American Meteorological Society. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Project 2  
Why is CO 2 a Powerful Green House Gas? 
FTIR (Thermo is5)
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Meteorology data 1
http://www.wunderground.comWeather Underground
http://www.wunderground.com/weatherstation/WXDailyHistory.asp?
ID=KMACAMBR9For Green Building Roof
You can download comma delimited le for each day 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Figure 7.3. The global carbon cycle for the 1990s, showing the main annual fluxes in GtC yr 1: pre-industrial natural fluxes in black and anthropogenic fluxes in red 
(modified from Sarmiento and Gruber, 2006, with changes in pool sizes from Sabine et al., 2004a). The net terrestrial loss of 39 GtC is inferred from cumulative 
fossil fuel emissions minus atmospheric increase minus ocean storage. The loss of 140 GtC from the vegetation, soil and detritus compartment represents the cumulative emissions from land use change (Houghton, 2003), and requires a terrestrial biosphere sink of 101 GtC (in Sabine et al., given only as ranges of 140 to 80 GtC and 61 to 141 GtC, respectively; other uncertainties given in their Table 1). Net anthropogenic exchanges with the atmosphere are from Column 5 AR4 in Table 7.1 . Gross fluxes generally have uncertainties of more than 20% but fractional amounts have been retained to achieve overall balance when including The Global Carbon Cycle for the 1990s
estimates in fractions of GtC yr 1 for riverine transport, weathering, deep ocean burial, etc. GPP is annual gross (terrestrial) primary production. Atmospheric carbon 
content and all cumulative fluxes since 1750 are as of end 1994. American Institute of Physics. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
Source: Sarmiento, Jorge L., and Nicolas Gruber. " Sinks for Anthropogenetic Carbon ." 2002.
35</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Incoming Solar Radiation and Absorption by the 
Atmospheric Constituents
Solar irradiance spectrum above atmosphere and at surface Robert A. Rohde . Some rights reserved. License: CC BY-SA. This content is excluded from our
Creative Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Incoming Solar 
Radiation
Radiation from Earth 
Surface
bending
asyn. stretch
 source unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see  http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
30</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Ro-vibrational transition of 15 m CO 2 bending band
Low spectral resolution (0.4 cm-1) high P (760 torr) 
High spectral resolution (0.004 cm-1), high P (760 torr) 
High spectral resolution (0.004 cm-1), low P (76 torr)
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>thermal IR, the lifetimes tend to range from a few milli -
seconds to a few tenths of a second. In contrast, the typicaltime between collisions for, say, a nitrogen-dominated atmos-phere at a pressure of 10
4Pa and temperature of 250 K is well
under 107s. Therefore, the energy of the photon will almost
always be assimilated by collisions into the general energypool of the matter and establish a new MaxwellBoltzmanndistribution at a slightly higher temperature. That is how radiation heats matter in the LTE limit.
According to the equipartition principle, molecular col-
lisions maintain an equilibrium distribution of molecules inhigher vibrational and rotational states. Many molecules oc-cupy those higher-energy states, so even though the lifetimeof the excited states is long, over a moderately small stretchof time a large number of molecules will decay by emittingphotons. If that radiation escapes without being reabsorbed,the higher-energy states are depopulated and the system isthrown out of thermodynamic equilibrium. Molecular colli-sions repopulate the states and establish a new thermo -dynamic equilibrium at a slightly cooler temperature. That is how thermal emission of radiation cools matter in the LTE limit.
Now consider a column of atmosphere sliced into thin
horizontal slabs, each of which has matter in LTE. ThermalIR does not significantly scatter off atmospheric molecules or
the strongly absorbing materials such as those that make upEarths water and ice clouds. In the absence of scattering, eachdirection is decoupled from the others, and the linearity ofthe electromagnetic interactions means that each frequencycan also be considered in isolation. If a radiation flux distri-bution I
in a given propagation direction impinges on a
slab from below, a fraction awill be absorbed, with a1 by
assumption. The slab may be too thin to emit like a black-body. Without loss of generality, though, one can write theemission in the form e
B(,T); here e1 is the emissivity of
the slab (see figure 1). Both aand eare proportional to the
number of absorberemitter molecules in the slab.
The most fundamental relation underpinning radiative
transfer in the LTE limit is Kirchhoffs law, which states thata
=e. Gustav Kirchhoff first formulated the law as an em -
pirical description of his pioneering experiments on the in-teraction of radiation with matter, which led directly to theconcept of blackbody radiation. It can be derived as a conse-quence of the second law of thermodynamics by requiring,as Kirchhoff did, that radiative transfer act to relax matter ina closed system toward an isothermal state. If Kirchhoffs lawwere violated, isolated isothermal matter could sponta-neously generate temperature inhomogeneities through interaction with the internal radiation field.
Given Kirchhoffs law, the change in the flux distribution
across a slab is I
=e[I+B(,T)], assuming e1. The
 radiation decays exponentially with rate e, but it is resup-
plied by a source eB. The stable equilibrium solution to 
the flux-change iteration is I=B(,T), which implies that
within a sufficiently extensive isothermal region the solutionis the Planck function appropriate to a blackbody. The recov-ery of blackbody radiation in that limit is one of the chief im-plications of Kirchhoffs law, and it applies separately foreach frequency. 
In the limit of infinitesimal slabs, the iteration reduces to
a linear first-order ordinary differential equation for I
. Or, as
illustrated in figure 1, one can sum the contributions from eachlayer, suitably attenuated by absorption in the intervening lay-ers. The resulting radiative transfer equations entered 20th-century science through the work of Karl Schwarzschild (ofblack hole fame) and Edward Milne, who were interested inastrophysical applications; Simon Poisson published a nearlyidentical formulation of radiative transfer
3in 1835, but his
equations languished for nearly 100 years without application.
Spectroscopy of greenhouse gases
Because of its numerous uses throughout science and tech-nology, gaseous spectroscopy is a highly developed subject.The application of gaseous spectroscopy to atmospheric con-stituents began with John Tyndall, who discovered in 1863that most of the IR opacity of Earths atmosphere was attrib-utable to two minor constituentsCO
2and water vapor. All
spectral absorption lines acquire a finite width by virtue of anumber of processes that allow a molecule to absorb a photoneven if the energy is slightly detuned from that of an exacttransition. For reasonably dense atmospheres, the most im-portant of those processes is collisional broadening, whichborrows some kinetic energy from recent collisions to makeup the difference between the absorbed photons energy anda transition. 
Databases of spectral-line properties lie at the founda-
tions of all calculations of IR radiative transfer in gases. TheHITRAN database,
4culled from thousands of meticulously
cross- validated, published spectroscopic studies, providesline properties for 39 molecules; it has been extensively usedT3
T2
T1
Tg(1 )aI  ,3
BT(, )geB T (, ) 3 ,3
eB T (, ) 2 ,2
eB T (, ) 1 ,1
Figure 1. Three isothermal layers model the atmosphere
in this illustration of upward-moving electromagnetic radia-
tion with frequency . The radiation, assumed not to scatter,
propagates at an angle with respect to the vertical and
emerges from layer 3, the topmost atmospheric slice. Theground below the atmosphere emits as an ideal blackbody,characterized by the Planck function B. Each layer, at its
own temperature T, emits with its own emissivity e
and, by
Kirchhoffs law, absorbs a proportion a=eof the incident
radiation. The radiation flux distribution incident on layer 3
is I. It is the sum of the thermal emission from the ground,
layer 1, and layer 2, attenuated by absorption in the inter-vening layers 1 and 2. Squiggly arrows indicate thermalemission; straight arrows indica te transmitted radiation.
34 January 2011    Physics Today www.physicstoday.org This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to  IP:
18.7.29.240 On: Tue, 02 Sep 2014 11:37:51Why isnt atmosphere 
totally black at 15 um?
Pierrehumbert, 2011, Physics Today
31 American Institute of Physics. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see  http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
Source: Pierrehumbert, Raymond T. " Infrared Radiation and Planetary Temperature ."
Physics Today  64, no. 1 (2011): 33-38.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Lab-2: Green Building CO 2 data
data co2_full_record.mat
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Project 1 
How do we monitor CO 2?
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Infrared spectra for H 2O, CO 2, CH 4 and CO 
H2O ! H2O!
bend stretch
http://vplapps.astro.washington.edu/
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Molecular vibration
Three Fundamental 
Vibrational Frequency of CO 2Infrared-inactive
1: symmetric stretch 
1345.4 cm-1 (7.43 m)
3: asymmetric stretch m)2-1: bending 2349.5 cm  (4.26 661.7 cm-1 (15.1 m)
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Instrument resolution, and pressure broadening
Low spectral resolution (0.4 cm-1) high P (760 torr) 
High spectral resolution (0.004 cm-1), high P (760 torr) 
High spectral resolution (0.004 cm-1), low P (76 torr)
27</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Ref: IPCC 4th Assessment, Summary for Policymakers, Feb. 2, 2007ATMOSPHERIC COMPOSITION &amp; RADIATIVE FORCING: 
TRENDS OVER THE LAST 20,000 YEARS 
The concentrations and radiative 
forcing by (a) carbon dioxide (CO
2), (b) methane (CH4), (c) 
nitrous oxide (N2O) and (d) the 
rate of change in their combined radiative forcing over the last 20,000 years reconstructed from Antarctic and Greenland ice and firn data (symbols) and direct atmospheric measurements (panels a,b,c, red lines). The grey bars show the reconstructed ranges of natural variability for the past 650,000 years. The rate of change in radiative forcing (panel d, black line) has been computed from spline fits to the concentration data. The negative rate of change in forcing around 1600 shown in the higher-resolution inset in panel d results from a CO
2 decrease of about 10 
ppm in the ice core record.
3
Climate Change 2007: The Physical Science Basis. Working Group I Contribution to the Fourth Assessment
Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, Figure 8 Cambridge University Press.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.335/12.835, FALL 2014 
CO2 &amp; CLIMATE CHANGE, Lecture 1-1,  
!
Shuhei Ono
Agenda of the day
Observation since 1970
Earth Energy Budget. Why is CO 2 a powerful green house gas?
Global Carbon Cycles. Where all the CO 2 goes, and how.
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Mauna Loa (19oN)
Baring Head, NZ (41oS)Alert, Canada
Cape Grim
Mauna Loa Emission
 
Panel (a) shows CO2 mole fractions (monthly averages) measured by continuous analyser over the period 1970 to 2004 for Mauna Loa (19oN 
red)  and Baring Head (41oS blue) . Due to the larger amount of terrestrial biosphere in the Northern hemisphere, seasonal cycles in CO2 are 
larger there than in the Southern hemisphere. In the lower right of the panel, atmospheric oxygen measurements (permeg) are shown from 
Alert, Canada (pink) and Cape Grim  (41oS cyan) . 
Panel (b) shows the annual global CO12 emissions from fossil-fuel burning and cement manufactur 
e Gt C yr (black) through to 2002. Data from 
the CDIAC website . Preliminary emissions data for 2003 and 2004 of 7.0 and 7.2 Gt C yr1 respectively are added derived from BP Statistical 
Review of World Energy 2005 website  Annual averages of 13C/12C (permil) measured in atmospheric CO2 at Mauna Loa from 1981 to 2002 (red) 
are also shown.CAUSES OF 
SEASONAL &amp; 
INTERANNUAL 
VARIATIONS IN 
THE  CO2 CYCLE?    
Ref: IPCC 4th 
Assessment, WG1, 2007TOPIC 1    
CO2 &amp; 
CLIMATE
 {Note :R=10x(R(sample )1)R(standard )
x=2(percent );3(permil);6( permeg )}
 IPCC. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons
license. For more information, see  http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Instrument to measure IR absorption
2. Dispersive Infrared Analyzer
Michelson  Interferometer used for FTIR
1. Non-Dispersive Infrared Analyzer (NDIR)
Diffraction Grating Spectrometer
3. Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy
Diffraction Grating
Dispersive Prism source unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see  http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
 Kkmurray . Some rights reserved. L
icense: CC BY-SA. This content is
exclud e
d from our Creative Commons license. For more information,
 see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
 source unknown. All rights reserved.
 This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see  http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>CO 2 source
Boston Generating Station
Car: 9 kg CO 2/gallon, I drive 14 miles per 
day making 2.5 kg CO 2/day @ 50mpgPeople: 2k food cal diet per day 
Free Energy Gain from Glucose = 2870 kJ/mol glucose (makes 6 CO
2), I get 770 g CO 2 per day 
how many people are in the box? Google. All rights reserved. This content is excluded  from
our Creative Commons  license. For more information,
see htt
p://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
Photograph by  I
FCAR ; in the public domain.
 Business Wire . All rights reserved. This content is excluded
from our Creative Commons license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
Courtesy of William Warby  on flickr. License: CC BY.
Courtesy of katsrcool  on flickr. License: CC BY.
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Teledyne CO2 Carbon Dioxide Analyzer (NDIR)Model 360E Instruction Manual Optional Hardware and Software 
05232 Rev B3 47 The O 2 concentration range is 0-100% (user selectable) with 0.1% precision and accuracy and is available to be 
output via the instruments analog output channel A3 (See Section 6.13.4). 
The temperature of the O 2 sensor is maintained at a constant 50 C by means of a PID loop and can be viewed 
on the front panel as test function O2 TEMP.   
The O 2 sensor assembly itself does no t have any serviceable parts and is enclosed in an insulated canister. 
5.6.1.3. Pneumatic Operation of the O 2 Sensor 
x P n e u m a t i c a l l y ,  t h e  O 2 sensor is connected to the bypass m anifold and draws a flow of about 120 
cm/min in addition to the normal sample flow rate and is separately controlled with its own critical flow 
orifice.  Figure 5-8 shows the internal pneumatics of  the M360E with the O2 Sensor installed.     
 
Figure 5-3:     M360E  Internal Pneumatics with O 2 Sensor Option 65 
From Teledyne 360E Instruction Manual Teledyne Technologies Incorporated. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our
Creative Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR)
Michelson interferometer
 Fourier transform
Image  is in the public domain. source unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see  http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>NDIR CO 2 meter; we will use this to set up 2nd 
observatory
Portable CO 2 meter/data 
logger in a bird house
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Explore different ways to measure CO2
FTIR (Thermo is5)
Aerodyne Research 
Tunable Infrared Laser Direct Absorption Spectroscopy
K033 from CO2meter.com
Gas Chromatography Shimadzu GC-2014
Teledyne 360E
 source unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see  http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
 source unknown. All rights reserved. This content is
excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more
information, see  http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ . CO2 Meter. All rights reserved. This content i s
e
xcluded from our Creative Commons license. For more
information, see  http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Exercise last week
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>23
CO2 cross section from FTIR</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Project 3 
What is the fate of CO 2? 
34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Earth Simulator 2
37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>403Carbon Cycle, CO 2, and Climate
Fate of CO 2!
in different time scales
Sarmiento&amp;Gruber(2006)
36This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see Figure 10.2.3.  Time series  figures of carbon dioxide from book: Sarmiento,
J. L., and N. Gruber. Ocean Biogeochemical Cycles . Princeton University, 2006.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Infrared Spectrum of CO 2
3: asymmetric stretch 
2349.5 cm-1 (4.26 m)
High resolution spectrum 
showing individual rotation lines
 source unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see  http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
12.335 / 12.835 Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry
Fall  2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Course Introduction (PDF - 2.1MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/resources/mit12_335f14_lecture_intro/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>THIS IS A HANDS-ON COURSE 
NOW LET S GO SEE THE LABS!  
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>CO 2 &amp; Climate Change 
Part 1: Flux Chamber and  
Portable CO 2 Sensor 
1-1) Flux chamber 
experiments to 
quantify CO 2 
source/sink flux 
from 
soil/grass/tree 
1-2) Deploy portable 
CO 2 sensors to 
examine local 
CO 2 hot spots. Flux Chamber 
Portable CO 2 meter/data 
logger Section 2    
CO2 &amp; 
CLIMATE 
 IPCC. All rights reserved. This content is excluded
from our Creative Commons  license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Explore different ways to measure CO2 
FTIR (Thermo is5) 
Aerodyne Research 
Tunable Infrared Laser Direct Absorption Spectroscopy 
T eledyne 360E
K033 from CO2meter.com 
Gas Chromatography 
Shimadzu GC- 2014  source unknown. All right
s reserved. This content is excluded
from our Creative Commons license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
 source unknown. All rights reserved. This content is
excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more
information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ . CO2 Met
er. All rights reserved.
This content is excluded from our
Creative Commons license. For more
information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/
help/faq-fair-use/.
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>12.335 /12.835  Experimental Atmos pheric Chemistry: Additional Grading Policies 
 
 
Laboratory reports 
Lab reports are due at the start of the class after the presentations are completed. This will allow you t o 
incorpora te comments from the presentations into your l ab report. We caution that you s hould start the 
report well before the presentation da y, if you wait until afterward as may not have sufficient time to 
finish. Com ments/grades on lab reports are returned approxi mately one  week later. Students will revise 
the first lab report based on t he comments to earn ba ck partial credit by the resubmission due  date, 
which is 1 week after the lab reports are returned. Late lab reports are penalized by making the 
maximum possible grade be a declining fraction of fu ll credit. Lab reports have a maximum of 75% 
credit if turned in a day late and 50% credit when turned in two days late. Lab reports turned in more 
than two days late will have a maximum grade of 25% . This policy is also in effect for the resubmitted 
reports after the resubmission due  date. The report MUST  be resubmitted for CI-M credit. 
Furthermore, if the first report is not resubmitted an additional 25% will be subtracted from the original 
grade (e. g. an original grade of 90% will instead become 65%). 
 
Presentations and Participation 
Presentations will be submitted to the TAs via email before the start of the (first) presentation class. 
This will allow the TAs to have presentation on t he course computer for that class. Absence will only 
be excused with a doctors note or ot her similar doc umentation (s ee below). In onl y this case students 
will be given the opport unity to make up the presentation in a future class. Presentations represent 
20% of the final grade. 
Students will show up for all presentations regardless of if they are presenting. During each 
presentation you w ill be expected to participate by a sking que stions of your pe ers. You w ill also return 
a feedback report on the presentations the next day of class. Participation in class and pr esentations 
represents 10%  of the final grade. 
 
Field Trips and Lab oratory Work 
Students must make all field trips and show up for all laboratory e xperiments. If the TA can manage, a 
make-up field trip or l aboratory a ppointment can be offered but this should not  be expected.  
 
Statement on Group Work 
You w ill be working in groups  during laboratory a nd field experiments and are free to collaborate on 
the measurements and ot her group w ork that will form the basis of your i ndividual presentations and 
reports. However, all the slides in your pre sentations and all the text and gra phs in your re ports should 
be your ow n work. Copy ing another persons assignment text, data or figures will not be tolerated 
and will result in a lower grade. All work s hould be fully referenced. For a general discussion of  
academic integrity at MIT, please see http://web.mit.edu/academicintegrity/. 
 
Special Circumstances 
The penalties described above  can be forgiven unde r special circumstances (for example, personal 
reasons, health reasons, etc.) if the student provi des documentation from Student Services, a doctor or 
another reputable source.  
 
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
12.335 / 12.835 Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry
Fall  2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.335/12.835 
FALL 2014 
COURSE 
OVERVIEW  
9-4-14 
Experiment al Atmospheric Chemis try 
Fall 2014  
12.335 (U)  
12.835 (G ) 
Tu/Th 1:30-3:00 
Profs. Ron Prinn &amp; Shuhei  Ono and Dr. Kari n Ardon-Dryer 
TAs: Sarves h
 Gari mella and Mari a Zawadowi cz 
Introduction to the atmospher ic chemistry 
involved in climate change , air pollution 
and biogeochemical  cycl es using a 
combination of hand s-on laboratory , field 
studies , and simple computer mod els. 
Lectur es will be accompanied by field trips 
to colle ct air samples for the analysis of 
gases, aerosols and clouds by the studen ts. 
FIRST CLASS: THURSDAY SEPTEMBE R 4 
Prereq.: 5.111 or 5.1 12, or pe rmission of instructor 2 -4-6 Credit 
(U and G)  
This course satisifes the Communica tion Intensive in the Major 
(CI-M) requireme nt for Course 12 majors in Area 2 
(Atmosphe res, Oceans and Climate) 
Image courtesy of Laura Kelsey Meredith.
Used with permission.
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Summary of the  chemistry  in the troposphere important in air 
pollution and climate. VOCs (not shown) are similar to CH4 in their 
reactions with OH, but they form acids, aldehydes and ketones in 
addition to CO.  
   Decreasing NOx 
   decreases O3 
 and OH 
    
Decreasing OH 
   increases CH4 
  
   Decreasing CO 
increases OH 
and decreases O3      
Decreasing O3 
   decreases OH 
   
  
  
 
 
  
 We will 
measure 
all these 
air 
pollutants 
in the lab 
and field 
Section 1    
Atmospheric 
Chemistry &amp; 
Air Pollution 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9
Average Rain Drop
Size: 2 mmAverage Cloud Droplet
Size: .02 mmAverage Condensation
Nucleus
Size: .0002 mm
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Section 3    
Aerosols &amp; 
Clouds 
Image courtesy of Pacific Northwest National Laboratory .
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>CO 2 &amp; Climate Change 
Part 2: CO 2 Cycle in Urban Environments 
Air Intake 
MIT Green Building (~95 m) 
2-1) Examine the main controls of CO 2 in 
the urban environment from CO 2 
measurements from air taken from the 
roof of the Green Building. e.g., diurnal 
cycles (amplitude, phase), pollution 
plume events.  
2-2) Learn how to construct a simple box 
model 
CO 2 mixing ratio data for July 4-9th  source unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded
from our Creative Commons l i
cense. For more information, see
http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use /.
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Aerosol and Clouds I (PDF - 2.8MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/resources/mit12_335f14_lecture3_1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19&#8211;20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Mineral Dust 
Pruppacher and Klett 
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page: http://www.microlabgallery.com/gallery/
Coal%20Dust%20668-99%20N%20Side%20100X%202.aspx .
Image courtesy of NASA . 
http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Saltation-mechanics.gif
31This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://41.media.tumblr.com/tumblr_lui4qyZPB-
t1r1qmaso1_500.jpg .
Range of wind speed and grain size in which saltation
of quartz grains can occur in the atmosphere.
Wind Too Violent250(Grains enter into suspension)
200)-1ec sSaltation Possiblem 150(c y elocit
100V Friction 
50
Wind Too Feeble
0
0.05 0.10 0.15 0.20
Grain Diameter (cm)
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>From Oberdrster et al. (2005) courtesy of Eben Cross Why Study Aerosols? : Health Effects 
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.tesa-clean -air.com/imedia/084/180
2084,dim:437x380,mode:exact.jpg.
These image
s hav
e been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see Figure 8 on Page 829 of the PDF file: http://www.ncbi.
nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC 1257642/pdf/ehp 0113- 000823.pdf .
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Dust storm approaching Stratford, Texas Dust bowl surveying in Texas 
Image ID: theb 1365 , Historic C&amp;GS Collection 
Location: Stratford, Texas 
Photo Date: April 18, 1935  
Credit: NOAA George E. Marsh Album  Why Care 2: Precipitation: Too little or too much 
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://41.media.tumblr.com/tumblr_lui4qyZPBt1r1qmaso1_ 500.jpg .Thi
s image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://syn500.com/wp -
content/uploads/2015/
02/hail-damage- car-repair-estimate.jpg .
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://agrozon a.
bg/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/bii01s17j.jpg .
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Why Care 3: dust effect on coral reef and Amazon rainforest 
Nutrients to the rain forest 
Disease for coral reef Image courtesy of USGS.
Image courtesy of USGS.Public domain via wikimedia  commons.
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Internally mixed aerosol 
 Externally mixed aerosol. Internally vs Externally  
Single phase Multiple phases 
Most solid aerosol particles : 
(a) not single-phase (i.e. not externally mixed) 
(b) irregularly shaped rather than spherical 
(c) do not have coreshell configurations 
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use /.This image has been removed due
to copyright restrictions.
Please see Figure 7a on page: http ://dz
umenvis.nic.
in/Climate%20Change/pdf/Airborne%20minerals
%20and%20related%20aerosol.pdf.
37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
12.335 / 12.835 Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry
Fall  2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Aerosol Terminology 
 Aerosol  
A colloid of fine solid particles or liquid  droplets, in a gas 
Aerosol Measurement - Principles, Techniques, and Applications 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>The Next 6 Weeks 
Month  Date Day  Topic  Where 
Oct  6 Thu Lecture 1 : Aerosols  517 
Nov 13 Thu Lab 1: Aerosols  1311 
Nov 18 Tue Lecture 2: Clouds  517 
Nov 20 Thu Lab 2: Clouds  1311 
Nov 25 Tue Lecture 3 : Atmospheric Particles and Clouds  517 
Dec 2 Tue Lab 3: The Atmosphere  1311 
Dec 4 Thu Lecture 4 : Odds &amp; Ends + "Feedback" 517 
Dec 9 Tue Aerosol/Cloud Presentations 517 
Dec 12 Fri Reports Due (by 9am)  Online or -1413  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Sandstone portal Figure on Herten Castle in Ruhr district of Germany,  
Sculpted 1702 . 
Acid Rain 
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page: http://facultylounge.whfreeman.
com/files/images/figure_16_22_02.preview.jpg .
Public domain via wikimedia commons.
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page: ht
tp
s://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.
com/236x/d6/a7/5b/d6a75bb14eb29336f702d644b1317b40.jpg .
35</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Why Study Aerosols ? : Climate 
 IPCC. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons
license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 4 
Month Date Day  Topic Where 
Nov 6 Thu Lecture 1 : Aerosols 517 
Nov 13 Thu Lab 1: Aerosols 1311 
Nov 18 Tue Lecture 2: Clouds 517 
Nov 20 Thu Lab 2: Clouds 1311 
Nov 25 Tue Lecture 3 : Atmospheric Particles and Clouds 517 
Dec 2 Tue Lab 3: The Atmosphere 1311 
Dec 4 Thu Lecture 4 : Odds &amp; Ends + "Feedback" 517 
Dec 9 Tue Aerosol/Cloud Presentations 517 
Dec 12 Fri Reports Due (by 9am) Online or - 1413 
Weather Modification  Ice in clouds  Geoengineering 
This image has been removed due This image has been removed dueThis image has been removed dueto copyright restrictions. to copyright restrictions.to copyright restrictions.Please see Figure 7a on page: http://www. Please see http://www.newscientist.com/Please see http://www.onislam.net/english/asktitangroup.com/wp-content/uploads/ data/images/archive/ 2697/ 26973601 .jpg.oimedia/onislamen/ 1119_local_seeding-2015/01/rogginh-img1.jpg .standalone-prod_affiliate-361.jpg .
Ice in clouds
 Geoengineering 
Geoengineering 
40</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>28This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions. Please see: Figure 4 on
page http://elements.geoscienceworld.org/content/6/4/215/F5.expansion.html</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Aerosol sizes 
12
0.0001 0.001 0.01 0.1 1 10 100 1000
Sizes of Different AerosolsPollen
Mold Spores
House Dust Mite Allergens
Bacteria
Cat Allergens
Viruses
Heavy Dust
Settling Dust
Suspended Atmosperic Dust
Cement Dust
Fly Ash
Oil Smoke
Smog
Tobacco Smoke
Gaseous ContaminationSoot
0.001 0.01 0.1 1 10 100 1000Cloud particles
Human hair
Dust stormsBeach sand
BacteriaViruses
Sea salt
Smoke from fires
SmogContaminants Biological t s u D  f Types o ntaminantsCo iculate art P lecules Mo Gas 
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Nitrogen oxides :  
 Nitric oxide (NO)  
  Nitrogen dioxide (NO2)  
SO2 + H2O --&gt; H2SO3 
SO3 + H2O --&gt; H2SO4 NO2 + OH --&gt; HNO3 
Nitric Acid - HNO3  http://janison.cyriljackson.wa.edu.au/Janison/Science/Chem3A3B/WestOne/Chem3A/content/008_environm
ental_processes/page_08.htm Sulfur oxides :  
 Sulfur dioxide (SO2)  
 Sulfur trioxide (SO3)  
Sulfuric Acid - H2SO4  This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page:
http://www.scienceclarified.com/images/uesc_ 07_img 0396.jpg .This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page: http://janison.cyriljackson.
wa.edu.au/Janison/Science/Chem3A3B/WestOne/Chem3A/
content/ 008_environmental_processes/media/cc8 _g015.jpg .
34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry 
 (12.335/12.835) 
 
Section 3, Lecture 1: 
Aerosols and Clouds  
 
Karin Ardon-Dryer &amp; Sarvesh Garimella 
 
Thursday, Nov 6, 2014 
 
 
http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/Features/Aerosols/     Image courtesy of NASA.  
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Biological Aerosol 
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page:
http://sciencenetlinks.com/media/filer/ 2011/ 10/24/fungi.jpg.
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page: https://s-media-
cache-ak 0.pinimg.
com/200x150/01/7d/8e/017d8e 94f96f27972c 21ca35bb 566a52.jpg .
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Today 
1.Our schedule 
 
2.The standard stuff (what you can expect from us, what we expect from you) 
 
3.Definitions 
 
4.Why you should care about aerosols and clouds : radiative effects, health, 
precipitation 
 
5.Where do aerosols come from? 
 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>Lab 1 Objectives (Nov 13): 
1.Learn how aerosol number and size are measured in the lab and field. 
 
2.Measure aerosols during your everyday activities. When are you being 
exposed? 
 
3.Long-term measurements with an eye on sources (e.g. urban, clean and 
maritime) 
1.Backtrajectories  where did that air come from? 
39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>From the book: Physics and Dynamics of Clouds and Precipitation Four stages to produce sea salt 
particles: 
(a) First, when a bubble rises to the top of 
the surface, its cap becomes a very thin 
film.  
(b) which eventually ruptures to form 
numerous mini-droplets that fly into the 
air.  
(c) Some of these film droplets eventually 
evaporate to leave dry sea salt particles 
that may be carried up higher by winds. 
At the same time, the water in the 
remnant bubble creates a jet due to the 
buildup of pressure at the bottom of the 
bubble. As the jet rises,  instability 
grows such that the jet breaks into a 
few droplets that also fly into the air.  
(d) These jet drops are usually larger than 
the film drops. Some of these  droplets 
are then carried by winds to higher 
layers and evaporate to become  dry sea 
salt particles. 
  Sea Salt - bubble burst mechanism 
29
Film drains and thins
Air
Ocean waterJet drop
Film
fragments
CapillarywavesUnstable jet
New bubbleFilm fragments
Flow down sides of cavity(A) (C)
(B) (D)
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>Broken Hill Dust Storm Australia 
This video has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9gCRq0xKk14 .
41</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Today 
1.Our schedule 
 
2.The standard stuff (what you can expect from us, what we expect from you) 
 
3.Definitions 
 
4.Why you should care about aerosols and clouds : radiative effects, health, 
precipitation 
 
5.Where do aerosols come from? 
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>1. Physics and chemistry of clouds  * 
Dennis Lamb, Johannes Verlinde. 
Shelf Location Hayden Library - Stacks | QC921.6.D95 L36 2011 
Published Cambridge ; New York : Cambridge University Press, 2011. 
ISBN    9780521899109 (hardback) 
  
2. Microphysics of clouds and precipitation, 2nd Edition  * 
Hans R. Pruppacher and James D. Klett. 
Shelf Location   Hayden Library - Stacks | QC921.5.P78 1997 
Published   Dordrecht ; Boston : Kluwer Academic Publishers, 1997. 
ISBN    0792342119 (alk. paper) 
  
3. Atmospheric chemistry and physics : from air pollution to climate change, 2nd Edition  * 
John H. Seinfeld, Spyros N. Pandis. 
Shelf Location   Barker Library - Reserve Stacks | QC879.6.S45 2006  
Published    Hoboken, N.J. : Wiley, c2006. 
ISBN    0471720178 (cloth) 
  
4. A short course in cloud physics, 3rd Edition  
R.R. Rogers and M.K. Yau 
Shelf Location   Hayden Library - Stacks | QC921.5.R63 1989 
Published    Oxford ; New York : Pergamon Press, 1989. 
ISBN    0080348645 
  Important Textbooks physically and  e-vailable*  
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Who We Are 
Dr. Karin Ardon-Dryer 
  
Communication Resources 
Jane Connor 
  
Teaching Assistant:  
Sarvesh Garimella 
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>The total annual global production of aerosol particles appears to be: 
 2500  4000 10Tg/year.  Aerosol     Natural  (N) or 
Anthropogenic  (A)     Annual flux 
(10 Tg/year)  
 Sea spray    N 1000-1500 
Dust   N,A 100-750 
Forest Fires    N,A 35-100 
V olcanic  N 50 
(highly variable)  
Meteors    N 1 
Combustion  A 50 
Condensation N,A 1500 Origins of aerosol particles: 
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>A Little About Myself  
Image courtesy of NASA.
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see:
http://www.ynetnews.com/PicServer2/ 20122005/ 720
846/DS_wa.jpg.
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Sources of Aerosols: 
This image is part of the one at http://www.ems.psu.edu/~lno/Meteo 437/Aerosol.jpg.
 owner unknown (haven't found yet). All rights reserved. This content is  excluded from our
Creative Commons license. For more information, see  http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Nucleation mode: 0.001- 0.01 m  
Aitkin mode: 0.01 - 0.1 m 
Soot, sulfuric acid and organics 
Accumulation mode: 0.1 -1 m 
Ammonium sulfate and ammonium nitrate, organics and smoke  
from biomass burning or other fires. 
Coarse mode: &gt; 1 m 
Mineral dust, sea salt and pollen. Fine mode Aerosol Size Classes: 
Anthropogenic 
Natural  
This image is part of the one at
http://capita.wustl.edu/AerosolIntegration/specialtopics/Integration/Capter4
Drafts/Figs/Fig1GenSizeDV000614.gif .
 owner unknown (haven't found yet). All rights reserved.This content is 
excluded from our Creative Commons  license. For more information, see
http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Aerosol Size Classes: 
This image is from http://capita.wustl.edu/AerosolIntegration/specialtopics/
Integration/Capter4Drafts/Figs/Fig1GenSizeDV 000614.gif.
 owner unknown (haven't fo
und yet). All rights reserved. This content is
excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see
http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.Public domain via wikipedia .
27</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Soot &amp; Black Carbon (BC) 
http://www.sites.mech.ubc.ca/~rogak/research/aerosol.html 
Coville et al 2011  Public domain via wikimedia commons.This image has been removed due
to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page: http://s3.ezlocal.com/img/
p/2011/4c4586f3-72b6 -4596-a7bc-3031a6ffe283.png .This image has been removed due to copyright
restrictions.
Please see the imag
e on page: http://img.timeinc.net/
time/daily/2009/0911/360_black_carbon_1109.jpg .
" 
Image courtesy of Steven Rogak , University
of British Columbia. Used with permission.This image has been removed due
to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page: http://www.scielo.
org.za/img/revistas/sajs/v10
7n3-4/a10fig
11.jpg .
36</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Primary atmospheric aerosols are particulates that directly emitted 
into the atmosphere  
Secondary atmospheric aerosols are particulates that formed in the 
atmosphere by gas-to -particles conversion processes Sources of Aerosols: 
Category Examples Type 
Coarse 
Coarse 
Coarse Sea salt 
Soil dust 
V olcanic dust Natural  - Primary 
Fine 
Fine and coarse 
Fine Sulfate from biogenic gases and volcanic SO2 
Nitrate from NOx 
Organic matter from biogenic sources Natural  - Secondary 
Fine and Coarse 
Fine 
Fine Industrial dust 
Soot 
Biomass burning Anthropogenic  -Primary 
Fine 
Fine 
Fine Sulfate from SO2 
Nitrate from NOx 
Organic from
 anthropogenic sources Anthropogenic  -Secondary 
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Category Examples Type 
Coarse 
Coarse 
Coarse Sea salt 
Soil dust 
V olcanic dust Natural  - Primary 
Fine 
Fine and coarse 
Fine Sulfate from biogenic gases and volcanic SO2 
Nitrate from NOx  
Organic matter from biogenic sources Natural  - Secondary 
Fine and Coarse 
Fine 
Fine Industrial dust 
Soot 
Biomass burning Anthropogenic  -Primary 
Fine 
Fine 
Fine 
 Sulfate from SO2 
Nitrate from NOx  
Organic from anthropogenic sources
 Anthropogenic  -Secondary 
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>Sources and sinks of Aerosols: 
This image is from http://www.ems.psu.edu/~lno/Meteo 437/Aerosol.jpg .
 owner unknown (haven't found yet). All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our
Creative Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
38</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>The global mean radiative forcing of the climate system 
IPCC  - Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change   IPCC. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons
license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use /.
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Primary Volcanic Emissions 
Image courtesy of USGS.SO2 
http://www.hko.gov.hk/blog/en/archives/00000107.htm 
Volcanic Ash From 1989  
Mt. Redoubt Eruption, Alaska  Image courtesy of USGS.
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page: http://www.hko.gov.hk/blog/en/img/ 20110829 _fig2e.jpg .
33Image courtesy of NASA.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Murphy et al. JGR 2009 Why Study Aerosols ? : Climate 
19
Year
Strat. + Trop. O3 N2O CH4CO2Solar HalocarbonsCumulative Energy Budget for the Earth since 1950
1950 1960 1970 1980 1990 20001500
1000
500
0Cumulative Forcing (1021J)
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Mode Sizes 
25
TABLE: Comparison of Ambient Fine and Coarse Particles
Coarse Particles Fine Particles
Atmospheric Lifetime Minutes to days Days to weeks
Composition Resuspended dust Sulfate
Coal and oil fly ash Nitrate
Crustal element (Si, Al, Ti, Fe) oxides Ammonium
CaCO3, NaCl Hydrogen ion
Pollen, mold, spores Elemental carbon (EC)
Plant, animal debris Organic compounds
Tire wear debris Water
Metals (Pb, Cd, V, Ni, Cu, Zn, Mn, Fe,etc.)
Formation Pathways Mechanical Disruption Chemical reactions
Suspension of dusts NucleationCondensationCoagulationCloud/ Fog Processing
Solubility Largely insoluble and non-hygroscopic Largely soluble, hygroscopic
Sources Resuspension of industrial dust and soil Combustion (coal, oil, gasoline, diesel,
Suspension of soil (farming, mining, wood)
unpaved roads) Gas-to-particle conversion of NO
3, SO3,
Biological sources VOCs
Construction/demolition Smelters, mills, etc.
Ocean spray
Travel Distance &lt; to 10s of km 100s to 1000s of km
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Sea Salt - bubble burst mechanism 
Pruppacher and Klett 
30
Mason (1957)Blanchard (1963, Max)
Mason (1954)
3% NaCl Solution (Day, 1964)
Filtered Ocean Water (Day, 1964)
Bubble Diameter (mm)0.11361030601003006001000
0.0 1.0 2.0 3.0 4.0Number of Droplets Per Bubble
Mean number of droplets resulting from the disintegration of
an air bubble cap in salt water as a function of equivalentdiameter of the air bubble.Film drains and thins
Air
Ocean waterJet drop
Film
fragments
CapillarywavesUnstable jet
New bubbleFilm fragments
Flow down sides of cavity(A) (C)
(B) (D)
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>PM10 particles with a diameter less than 10 microns  
PM2.5  particles with a diameter less than 2.5 microns  
1 m=10-6 m  Aerosol sizes 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Section Overview 
 
(what you should expect from us) 
 
 
This section will provide tools for understanding:  
 
(1) Basic physics and chemistry of aerosols and cloud droplets 
 
(2) The interaction of particles with water vapor including phase changes and droplet 
formation 
 
(3) Basic operations of common measurements techniques including CPC, DMA, 
OPS and CCN  (acronyms defined next time!). Keep in mind this youll be working 
with ~$ 200,000 of equipment: take a moment to  consider care and the opportunity! 
 
 
  
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Grading 
(what I expect from you) 
Lab reports 
This lab report is due at 9am December 12 (few days after the presentations are completed). 
Send to me via email or bring it to my office . Late policy in effect per Grading Policy. 
 
Presentations and Participation  
Pres
entations will be submitted to Sarvesh via email before the start of the December 9 class.   
Students are expected to show  up for all presentations regardless of if you are presenting. 
During each presentation you will be expected to participate by asking questions of your 
peers. You will also return a feedback report on the presentations the next day of class.  
 
Laboratory Work 
Students are expected to show  up for all laboratory experiments. You will also have 
possession of a DustTrak for a one week period.  
 
Special Circumstances 
The penalties described in the Grading Policy can be forgiven under special circumstances 
(for example, personal reasons, health reasons, etc.) if the student provides documentation 
from Student Services, a doctor or another reputable source.  
 
*I expect reports / presentations to be individual efforts. Collaboration is acceptable but 
copies and plagiarism will NOT be tolerated* 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Why Care 1: Health Effects 
Combination of meteorology (cold air / increase heating and temperature inversion) 
Particles reached 14,000 g/m (280x current US standard average and ~100x times peak 
allowable)  
Visibility &lt; 1 m (!) 
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Smog The Great Smog  London, 1952 
4000 deaths within 2 weeks,  
12000 estimated total  N. T. Stobbs . Some rights reserved. License: CC BY-SA. This
content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For
more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
These images have been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the images No. 1 and No. 6 on page:
http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/ 2013/12/05/11-incredible-
pictures-from-the-great
-smog-of -1952_n_ 4389546.html.
140100200300400500600700800900Smoke (micrograms per cubic metre)
Deaths per day/sulphur dioxide (ppb)10001100
0400
Date, December 19528001200160020002400280032003600
Deaths Sulphur Dioxide Smoke40004400
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Properties of aerosol important to atmospheric 
processes: 
 Number concentration 
 Mass 
 Size distribution 
 Chemical composition 
 Aerodynamic property 
 Optical properties 
26</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Atmospheric Photochemistry and Air Pollution III (PDF - 1.7MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/resources/mit12_335f14_lecture1_3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>The spatial 
grid 
We divide the earth s 
atmosphere into a 
finite number of boxes 
(grid cells).  
 
Assume that each 
variable has the same 
value throughout the 
box. 
 
Write a budget for each 
each box, defining the 
changes within the 
box, and the flows 
between the boxes. 
 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>AEROSOL PHYSICAL RATE EXPRESSIONS IN MODELS  
dNk
dt=Rate of change of aerosol number density 
            (with size between k and k+dk) 
         = Emission (surface and in situ)
         + Condensation of precursor gases 
         +
 Complete evaporation of water from cloud droplets
         + Coagulation of smaller aerosols
         + Fragmentation of larger aerosols
         Sedimentation (net into &amp; out of layer) 
         -  Coagulation with any other aerosols
         -  Coalescence (into water droplets)
         -  Fragmentation by collisions with other aerosols
         -
  Deposition (all surfaces)
         -  Rainout (to surface)
         -  "Activation" to form cloud droplets
5
dNcoagkdtcoagN*N
dNcoalk**
dtcoalN N
dNdepvdtdepN
dNrain Ndtrain
etc.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>INCORPORATING METEOROLOGY IN THE BOX MODEL  
 
1. USE THE u MEASUREMENTS TO ALIGN THE MODEL x AXIS AND USE IN THE        
BOX MODEL ADVECTION TERMS. 
2. USE THE T &amp; u MEASUREMENTS TO CALCULATE A RICHARDSON NUMBER TO 
HELP CHOOSE SUITABLE texchange  VALUES.  
3. USE TEMPERATURE SOUNDINGS OR HAZE LAYER HEIGHT TO ESTIMATE Z T OP OF BOUNDARY LAYER 
 Cory Cripe . Some rights reserved. License: CC BY-NC
3.0. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons  license. For more information, see
http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.. 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Summary of gaseous chemical rate expressions for 
production and loss of species i including surface 
sources and sinks: 
 
(1) Ji[i] where Ji can be derived from UV 
measurements 
 
(1) kij[i][j] where kij is given 
 
(1) lijm[i][j][m] where lijm is given 
 
(2) surface  = wdep[i] where wdep is given 
 
(1) surface  either given or estimated from model-
measurement comparison  i emissions   i sink 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>[Note Expect NOx  &gt; NO] [Note Expect O3  &gt; 40ppb ] 
N 
 
W 
 
S 
 
E 
 
N 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
12.335 / 12.835 Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry
Fall  2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>TRANSPORT,
CHEMISTRY AND 
RADIATION 
 COMPONENTS 
IN COMPLEX 3D 
MODELS 
11Interactions Between Air Pollution and Climate
UV
N2O
CFCs
LightningStratosphere
O(1D) OHNO
HO 2
OHOH
BC
H2O CH 4 CO SO 2OHO2UV
CO 2 CO 2O2NO 2
O2
Hydrosphere Biosphere &amp; Human ActivityHNO 3
Primary &amp; Secondary PollutantsGreenhouse Gases Reactive Free Radical/Atom
Less Reactive Radicals
Reflective Aerosols Absorbing Aerosols (BC)O3
H2SO 4COMPONENTS OF ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY MODELS
DYNAMICAL EQUATIONS
MASS CONTINUITY EQUATION
MOMENTUM EQUATIONS
THERMODYNAMIC EQUATION
CHEMICAL
CONTINUITY EQUATIONS
RADIATION
EQUATIONSWinds , Eddy diffusion coefficients
Temperature
 Rates 
   forHeatingRates for ChemistryConcentrations
(O3, etc.)
ForUnpredictedgreen housegases usescenarios orextra polations
For Source gases use predictions,extra polationsor scenarios  U.V Fluxes For photodissociation 
rates{
{ [i]
t= Pi - Li -    . ( [ i ] V )~
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>PM - WIND (DIRECTION, SPEED) CORRELATIONS N 
 
W 
 
S 
 
E 
 
N USE i-
PHONE 
COMPAS
S TO 
INTEPRET 
RE BLDG 
54  
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>INTERSPECIES (CO-PM) CORRELATIONS 
[Note Expect PM10 &gt; PM2.5 &gt; PM1] 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>TOPIC 1  
ATMOSPHERIC PHOTOCHEMISTRY and  
AIR POLLUTION  
 
MODELING GASES AND AEROSOLS 
 12.335/12.835 EXPERIMENTAL ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY, FALL 2014 
RONALD PRINN &amp; MARIA ZAWADOWICZ 
 SEPTEMBER 30, 2014  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>PROGNOSTIC  (CONTINUITY) EQUATIONS TAKE 
ACCOUNT OF PROGNOSTIC CHEMISTRY AND 
TRANSPORT BY WINDS 
The local change 
 (rate of accumulation) 
ofi in the boxActual production  
or destruction of  i 
within the box Change in [i] due to loss to downstream 
boxes or arrival from an upstream  
box (called advection or convection) 
HYBRID[i]d[i] []chemu[i]v[i]w[i]t
 CHEMICAL KINETIC EQUATIONS 
(1)Use prognostic equations, (d[i]/dt)  = P - L) for long lived chemistry i i
species like [O ] (=[O] + [O ]) and [NO ](=[NO + [NO ]) x 3 x 2
(2)Use diagnostic (steady state) equations, P  = L for short lived i i
species like O, NO, H and HO  to provide the ratios  [O]/[O ], 2 3
[NO ]/[NO], [HO ]/[H] and [H]/[OH]  2 2
(3)Assume [HO ] = [H] + [OH] + [HO ] ~ [HO ] is given x 2 2
(4)Use observed values for [CO] 
(5)Use lowest observed [NO ] and [O ] as boundary conditions for x 3
NO and Ox x 
7dtxyz</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>A SIMPLE PHOTOCHEMICAL BOX MODEL  
to simulate time-varying concentrations of trace gases and 
aerosols using the PROGNOSTIC CONTINUITY EQUATION 
8
d[i]boxuPiLi[i]upwind[i]box([i]top[i]box)/
dt Xexchange(surface surface
i,emissionsi,sink)/Z</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>GASEOUS CHEMICAL RATE EXPRESSIONS IN MODELS  
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>[Note Expect NOx  &gt; NO] [Note Expect O3  &gt; 40ppb ] 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>CO - WIND (DIRECTION, SPEED) CORRELATIONS USE i-
PHONE 
COMPAS
S TO 
INTEPRET 
RE BLDG 
54  N 
 
W 
 
S 
 
E 
 
N 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>DIAGNOSTIC  EQUATIONS  ASSUME A PHOTOCHEMICAL STEADY 
STATE (PSSA) 
Recall PSSA equations ignore influence of meteorology so valid only when wind speed u ~ 0 
 
In PSSA: rate of loss (Li) = rate of production (Pi) 
e. g. for the ozone chemical reaction set including NOx and HOx chemistry: 
 
(1) NO + O3 -&gt; NO2 + O2  
(2) NO2 + hv -&gt; NO + O 
(3) O + O2 + M -&gt; O3 + M 
(4) O3 + hv -&gt; O2 + O 
(5) NO2 + OH + M -&gt; HNO3 + M 
(6) OH + CO -&gt; H + CO2 
(7) H + O2 + M -&gt; HO2 + M 
(8) HO2 + NO -&gt; OH + NO2 
 
We have for NO, HO2, H and O concentrations: 
 
k1[O3][NO] + k8[HO2][NO] = J2[NO2] 
i.e. [NO2]/[NO] = (k1[O3] + k8[HO2])/J2 
 
k8[HO2][NO] = l7[H][O2][M]  
i.e. [HO2] /[H] = l7[O2][M]/(k8[NO])  
 
l7[H][O2][M]= k6[CO][OH] 
i.e. [H]/[OH] = k6[CO]/(l7[O2][M]) 
 
 l3[O][O2][ M]= J2[NO2] + J4[O3] 
i.e. [O]/[O3] = (J2[NO2]/[O3] + J4)/(l3[O2][M]) 
 
Recall the PSSA analytical solution when we consider NOx but not HOx chemistry: 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Aerosol and Clouds II (PDF - 2.3MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/resources/mit12_335f14_lecture3_2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21&#8211;22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Today : Cloud Droplet Formation 
RH &amp; Saruration 
 
Liquid water from 0  100% RH 
 
RH of 100% + 
 
Kelvin Khler curve 
 
Cloud droplets 
 
CCN counter 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Insoluble Components 
Most atmospheric particles contain both water-soluble and water-
insoluble substances (dust, elemental carbon, etc.). 
The effect of the insoluble material is to 
increase in absolute terms the solute 
effect. Physically, the insoluble material 
is responsible for part of the droplet 
volume, displacing the equivalent water. 
Therefore, for the same overall droplet 
diameter, the solution concentration will 
be higher and the solute effect more 
significant. 
Khler curves for a particle consisting of various combinations of (NH4)2SO4 and insoluble material  
 
We see that the smaller the water-soluble fraction the higher the supersaturation needed 
for activation of the same particle, and the lower the critical diameter. 
Seinfeld and Pandis, 2006 This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure 17.8  of the book Atmospheric Chemistry and
Physics: From Air Pollution to Climate Change.  Wiley-Interscience,
2006. ISBN: 9780471720188.
30</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>There are a lot of molecule in the air in supersaturation, 
in order to create a  drop the molecule need to become  
attached to each other  
Water vapor molecules Homogeneous Nucleation  
Embryonic droplet of radius R 
Growth of the pure water embryo depend on the difference 
between es and e  
e &lt; es              decay (vapor moves away from the drop) 
e &gt; es      growth (vapor moves toward the drop) 
When the pure water embryo drop radius is  e = es 
The droplet is just large enough to be stable 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>Until now we only create small cloud drop 
43
This image has been removed due to copyright
restrictions. Please see the first image on page:http://conveccion.at.fcen.uba.ar/practicas/
NUBES.pdf .
This image has been removed due to copyright
restrictions. Please see: https://gnightearth.
files.wordpress.com/2014/06/slide0001_
image060.jpg.cities
cities
r - radius in microns
n - number per literV - terminal velocity in centimeters per secondComparative sizes, concentrations, and terminal fall velocities
of some of the particles included in cloud and precipitation processes
Conventional borderline
between cloud drops
and raindrops
r = 100
v = 70
Typical raindrop r = 1000, n = 1, V = 650Large cloud dropr = 50n = 10
3
V = 27 Typical condensation nucleusr = 0.1n = 10
6
V = 0.0001
Typical cloud dropr = 10n = 10
6
V = 1cities
citiesKEYSr - radius in micronsn - number per literV - terminal velocity in centimeters per secondComparative sizes, concentrations, and terminal fall velocities
of some of the particles included in cloud and precipitation processes
Conventional borderline
between cloud drops
and raindrops
r = 100
v = 70
Typical raindrop r = 1000, n = 1, V = 650
Comparative sizes, concentrations, and terminal fall velocities
of some of the particles included in cloud and precipitation processes
Large cloud dropr = 50n = 10
3
V = 27
 Typical condensation nucleusr = 0.1n = 10
6
V = 0.0001
Typical cloud dropr = 10n = 10
6
V = 1KEYS
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>43</slideno>
          <text>As result of the raising air and cooling 
the droplets are going through: 
1.Evaporation 
2.Gravity 
3. Condensation 
4. Collision-coalescence 
44
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the first image on page: http://conveccion.
at.fcen.uba.ar/practicas/NUBES.pdf.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>How Do We Measure CCN? 
Moore and Nenes AST 2009 Initial size is selected with a 
DMA  
 
Supersaturation due to T 
gradient used for activation This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see  Figure 1 on page:  http://www.tandfonline.com/
doi/full/10.1080/02786820903289780.
36</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>The saturation ratio for a solution droplet must still be 
given by this relation since we must require the droplet to 
be in equilibrium with the vapor 
(cm)   10 3 . 3 5 
T A   - Ms  molecular weight r- drop radius 
ms- masses of salt For sea salt 
im ) (cm     3 . 4 3 
s s 
M B  A=2 /wRvT B=(3imsMw)/(4Msw)  
i = Vant Hoff factor 
= exp

3 
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Insoluble Components 
Seinfeld and Pandis, 2006 The smaller the mthe higher the supersaturation needed for 
activation of the same particle size These images have been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure s 17.8 and 17.9 of the book Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics: From
Air Pollution to Climate Change.  Wiley-Interscience, 2006. ISBN: 9780471720188.
31</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>CCN - (Cloud Condensation Nuclei) 
Aerosol that consider as a good candidate for condensation nuclei are: 
 Hygroscopic aerosol. 
 Bigger Aerosol with a critical radius can nucleate at low 
supersaturation (according to  Khler curve)  
Hygroscopic aerosol can be larger than 
~ 0.01 m  in order to nucleate. 
http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/Features/GlobalClouds/The ability of a given particle to serve as a nucleus for water droplet 
formation will depend on its: 
Size 
Chemical composition 
 Local supersaturation 
Image courtesy of NASA.
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Cloud drop 
Khler curve with GCCN 
GCCN
 
  
area 
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>Hudson_and Yum 2001 This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure 5 on page, http://olympic.atmos.colostate.
edu/AT 620/papers/Hudson_and_Yum.pdf .This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure s 17.4 of the book Atmospheric Chemistry and
Physics: From Air Pollution to Climate Change . Wiley-Interscience,
2006. ISBN: 9780471720188 .
39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>The relative humidity of an air-water 
 mixture defined as the ratio of :  Relative Humidity ~ Saturation 
e - vapor pressure of environment 
es - vapor pressure of saturated environment e es 
e es 
= 1 saturated e es &gt; 1 supersaturated e es &lt; 1 sub-saturated 
4
When evaporation = Condensation
RH = 100%
If RH &lt;100% water/cloud will evaporate If RH &gt;100% water/cloud will condenseEvaporation
rateEvaporationrateNo water vapor
Flat water
surface coveredSaturated AirEvaporation
WaterCondensation
Pure H 2OCondensation
rateCondensation
rate
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>Account for Composition - k -Khler equations  
Petters and Kreidenweis ACP 2008 PK07 proposed a hygroscopicity parameter   that 
is defined through its effect on the water activity 
of the solution: 
The saturation ratio, S, over an aqueous solution 
droplet can be calculated from 
where aw is the activity of water in solution, w  is 
the density  of water,  Mw  is the molecular  weight  
of water,  s/a is the surface  tension  of the 
solution/air  interface,  R is the universal  gas 
constant,  T is temperature, and D is the diameter  
of the droplet .  
where Vs is the volume of the dry particulate 
matter (both soluble and insoluble) and Vw is 
the volume of the water. where A=8.69251 106 s/a /T is a 
constant  that is evaluated  at s/a 
=0.072 Jm2 and T =298.15K (PK07) 
40</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Mass of dissolved 
salt [gr]  rsalt[
m ] r*[
m ] S*[%] 
10-16 0.0223  0.19 0.42 
10-15 0.0479  0.61 0.13 
10-14 0.103  1.9 0.042  
10-13 0.223  6.1 0.013  
10-12 0.479  19 0.0042  
 r*     , S*       as dry particle diameter (or mass) increases 
r*     , S*       as dry solute molecular weight increases 
29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>For a water molecule in the salt solution which is inside a water 
drop just like before: 
e - vapor pressure of water vapor above a solution. 
es vapor pressure above a plane surface of pure water. 
f - mole fraction of water in the solution. 
moles water is: (4/3r3 m)/M0  
ims/M moles salt is: m = mass of salt in solution 
M = molecular weight of the salt 
M0 = molecular weight of water 
i = Vant Hoff factor 
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>DRH is material specific 
DRH changes with T per Clausius-Clapyeron relation  
ERH is not predictable but follows nucleation theory 
Seinfeld and Pandis, 2006 Deliquescence and Efflorescence  
(NH4)2SO4  Ammonium sulfate  
Diameter change of (NH4)2SO4, NH4HSO4, and H2SO4 particles as a function of
relative humidity. Dp0 is the diameter of the particle at 0% RH.00.81.01.21.41.61.82.02.22.4
(NH4)2SO4Dp /Dp0
5 10 15 20 25 30 35 40 45 50 55 60 65
Relative Humidity, %70 75 80 85 90 95 100
7
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>Historically, one counted aerosol and determined number activated as 
a function of s (atmospheric supersaturation, %).  
 
Relationship:  CCN (s) = c sk 
CCN(s) - particles cm- 3  
s - supersaturation expressed as a percentage 
C - constant c corresponds to the CCN(1%), the 
particles active at 1 % supersaturation. 
10 100 1000 10000 
0 0.5 1 1.5 2 
Supersaturation (%) Activity Spectrum (cm-3) 
N(marine) N(continental) Nc = C sk 
Marine:     C= 150 
                  k= 0.6 
Continental:         C= 1500  
                  k= 1.1 Number of aerosol going to nucleation 
maritime: C=10-300 cm-3     
  k=0.3-1.0 
Continental: C=200-1000 cm-3     
  k=0.2-2.0 
38</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Bigger particle are more effective than small ones, but their concentration in the cloud is lower 
Seinfeld and Pandis, 2006 This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure 17.5 of the book Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics: From Air
Pollution to Climate Change . Wiley-Interscience, 2006.  ISBN: 9780471720188.
27</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
Content 6 oz water
6/6 x 100 = 100% 6/9 x 100 = 67% 6/12 x 100 = 50% 9/12 x 100 = 75%9 oz glass 12 oz glass 12 oz glass6 oz water 6 oz water 9 oz water
Relative Humidity6 oz glass Capacity
20oC Temperature
AirCapacityH
2O Vapor Content
Relative Humidity1 kg
At 20oC=14 grams
7 grams
7/14=50%10oC
1 kg
At 10oC=7 grams
7 grams
7/7=100%0oC
1 kg
At 0oC=3.5 grams
3.5 grams
3.5/3.5=100%(A) Initial Condition (B) Cooled to 10oC (C) Cooled to 0oC0oC
1 kg Air3.5 g 
H2O liquid3.5 g H
2O vapor10oC
1 kg Air7 g H
2O vapor20oC
1 kg Air7 g H
2O vaporLow Medium HighTemperature
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Heterogeneous Nucleation  
In this section we will examine the production of 
small water droplets nucleated with the aid of a 
foreign particle.  
 
Since nucleation takes place with something in 
addition to pure water vapor, the nucleation process 
is called heterogeneous . 
http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/Features/GlobalClouds/Image courtesy of NASA.
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Statistical thermodynamic 
calculations show that 
Saturation ratio must be 
300-600% for one 
homogeneous nucleation 
event per cm3 per second 
in the natural atmosphere. 
Homogeneous Nucleation  
Since Saturation ratio rarely 
exceeds 1-2%,  
 Homogeneous nucleation is never consistently achieved.  
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>Seinfeld and Pandis, 2006 SS vs. Critical Diameter 
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure 17.6 of the book Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics: From Air
Pollution to Climate Change . Wiley-Interscience, 2006. ISBN: 9780471720188.
28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry 
 (12.335/12.835) 
 
Section 3, Lecture 2: 
 
 
Karin Ardon-Dryer &amp; Sarvesh Garimella 
 
Tuesday, Nov 18, 2014 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Approaching 100% 
Heating reduces RH, cooling increases RH 
(day/night variation and concept of dew point and frost point) 
 
Parcel rise of fall (adiabatic) results in condensation or evaporation  This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.harding.edu/lmurray/ 113_files/html/d2_earth% 20revised/img037 .jpg.
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Haze and cloud drop -Khler curves  
Drop below the critical radius called haze particle 
Drop above the critical radius called clouds drop their aerosol are 
activated aerosol  haze Khler curve 
Cloud drop 
activated 
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
25</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Haze or Deliquesced -&gt; Droplet 
10
r - radius in microns
n - number per literV - terminal velocity in centimeters per secondComparative sizes, concentrations, and terminal fall velocities
of some of the particles included in cloud and precipitation processes
Conventional borderline
between cloud drops
and raindrops
r = 100
v = 70
Typical raindrop r = 1000, n = 1, V = 650
Comparative sizes, concentrations, and terminal fall velocities
of some of the particles included in cloud and precipitation processes
Large cloud dropr = 50n = 10
3
V = 27
 Typical condensation nucleusr = 0.1n = 10
6
V = 0.0001
Typical cloud dropr = 10n = 10
6
V = 1KEYS
Figures by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Seinfeld and Pandis, 2006 Deliquescence and Efflorescence  
8
TABLE: Deliquescence Relative Humidities
of Electrolyte Solutions at 298 K
DRH (%) Salt
NaCl 75.3 + 0.1
NaHSO4 52.0
NaNO3 74.3 + 0.4
Na2SO4 84.2 + 0.4
NH4Cl 80.0
NH4HSO4 40.0
(NH4)3H(SO4)2 69.0
NH4NO3 61.8
(NH4)2SO4 79.9 + 0.5
KCl 84.2 + 0.3
Source: Tang (1980) and Tang and Munkelwitz (1993).TABLE: Efflorescence Relative Humidity
at 298 K
ERH (%) Salt
NaCl 43 + 3
NaNO3 Not Observed
Na2SO4 56 + 1
NH4Cl 45
NH4HSO4 Not Observed
(NH4)H(SO4)2 35
NH4NO3 Not Observed
(NH4)2SO4 35 + 2
KCl 59
Source: Martin (2000).
Figures by MIT OpenCourseWare. Figures by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>RH (Relative Humidity)= s  100%  
Supersaturation = S= ( s + 1) es - saturation vapor pressure over a plane surface of pure water. er -Vapor pressure Saturation rate as a function of the drop size 
 =
= 1+

3 
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>CCN Use in Models 
n(Dp) - number distribution of the aerosol population 
Ds - activation diameter for s%  s upersaturation of these particles 
fs(Dp) - fraction of the aerosol particles of diameter Dp that are activated at s% CCN Use in Models 
Seinfeld and Pandis, 2006 This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure s 17.16 of the book Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics: From
Air Pollution to Climate Change . Wiley-Interscience, 2006. ISBN: 9780471720188.
37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Heterogeneous Nucleation 
Collection of water molecules on a foreign substance 
Creation of clouds droplets 
Homogeneous Nucleation  
Drop of pure water forms from vapour 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>A term used to describe the amount of water vapor 
that exists in a gaseous mixture of air and water vapor. Relative Humidity ~ Saturation 
The relative humidity of an air-water mixture 
defined as the ratio of : 
 Relative Humidity (RH) =  X 100%
 Actual Vapor Density 
 --------(amount of -------m---oisture----- in --ai---r) ---
 Saturation Vapor Density
 (amount in saturated air) 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Deliquescence &amp; Efflorescence of  two Component Systems 
Seinfeld and Pandis, 2006 Two (or more) components 
More favorable state is solution 
sooner when a second component is 
added (regardless of the DRH) 
DRH  
NaCl  (Sodium chloride )  75.3% 
KCI (potassium chloride)  84.2% 
Mixed-salt particle  72.7 %  
ERH  
NaCl  (Sodium chloride )  43% 
KCI (potassium chloride)  59%  
Hygroscopic growth and evaporation of a mixed-salt particle
composed initially of 66% mass KCl and 34% mass NaCl.
Particle Mass/Dry Particle Mass
Relative Humidity, %KCl/NaCl
01234567
60 65 70 7580 85 90 95
Crystallization Deliquescence
9
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Kelvins equation for critical radius for initial droplet 
to survive, strongly dependent on supersaturation 

sL vvl
c
eeT RR
ln2

Rv- gas constant (8.314472 JK-1mol-1) 
LV - surface tension between the liquid-vapor phases (0.076Jm2) T- temperature L- liquid density  Rc- critical radius 
e - vapor pressure of environment 
es - vapor pressure of saturated environment Homogeneous Nucleation  
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Solution Effect (Raoults Law) 
Seinfeld and Pandis, 2006 
The vapor pressure of water over NaCl and (NH4)2 SO4 solutions is shown in Figure 17.3. Also shown is the ideal solution behavior. 
Note that because NaCl dissociates into two ions, the number of equivalents in solution is twice the number of moles of NaCl. For 
(NH4)2 SO4, the number of ion
s in solution is three times the number of dissolved salt moles. In calculating the number of moles in 
solution, ns, a dissociated molecule that has dissociated into i ions is treated as i molecules, whereas an undissociated molecule is 
counted only once. A similar diagram is given in Figure 17.4, using now the concentration of salt as the independent variable. Solutes 
that dissociate (e.g., salts) reduce the vapor pressure of water more than do solutes that do not dissociate, and this reduction 
depends strongly on the type of salt. 
  John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use /.
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>rc, Sc Khler curves  
rc = (3b/a)1/2 Sc = 1+(4 a3/[27b]) 
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Smaller pure drop need higher supersaturation, and less  
molecules in order to grow. Homogeneous Nucleation  
16
TABLE: Radii and Number of Molecules in Droplets of
Pure Water in Equilibrium with the Vapor at 0 
Number of Molecules
nCritical Radius
rc (m)Saturation Ratio
S
10 5.221 X 10-420
5 7.468 X 10-458
4 8.671 X 10-491
3 1.094 X 10-3183
2 1.734 X 10-3730
1.5 2.964 X 10-33.645 X 103
1.10 1.261 X 10-22.807 X 105
1.01 1.208 X 10-12.468 X 108
1  
Figures by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Kelvin Khler curve 
Drop Radius ( m) Saturation Ration S* 
Sa Sb S 
r* ra rb r 
A drop at point a (r=ra, S=Sa). Let 
the Supersaturation   to increases to 
Sb, the drop will grow to radius rb. 
If the Supersaturation drops again, 
the drop will get smaller.  
But if the Supersaturation will 
increase to the critical 
Supersaturation   condition (r=r*, 
S=S*) the drop will grow to a 
critical radius.  
From now on the drop will 
continue growing spontaneously 
(by diffusion), even if the 
Supersaturation decrease. a b 
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Saturation above a pure water droplet of a know 
radius is: 
LV - surface tension of water molecules T- temperature 
e - vapor pressure of environment 
es - vapor pressure of saturated environment (water molecules)  
nL - number of water molecules/unit volume in the liquid phase r- embryo drop radius 
k- Boltzmann constant   Homogeneous Nucleation  

= 2
 
 e/es&lt; 1 sub-saturated      e/es&gt; 1 super-saturated 
e &lt; es      decay (vapor moves away from the drop) 
e &gt; es     growth (vapor moves toward the drop) 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Cloud Condensation Nucleus Counter (CCNC) 
The CCN Counter is a continuous-flow thermal-
gradient diffusion chamber for measuring 
aerosols that can act as cloud condensation 
nuclei.  
http://acd.ucar.edu/~jimsmith/POP/instruments_files/CCNc.htmhttp://www.dropletmeasurement.com/This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.dropletmeasurement.com/
sites/default/files/pictures/Products/CCN/CCN.png .
 James Smith, UCAR. All rights reserved. This content is
excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more
information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>46</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
12.335 / 12.835 Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry
Fall  2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>45</slideno>
          <text>46</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Deliquescence and Efflorescence  
Deliquescence (DRH) - process by which a substance absorbs moisture from the 
atmosphere until it dissolves in the absorbed water and forms a solution. 
Efflorescence (ERH) -  spontaneous loss of water by a hydrated salt, which 
occurs when the aqueous vapor pressure of the salt is greater than the partial 
pressure of the water vapour in the air.  
1.0 1.5 2.0 
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
6Increasing RH
Solid Particle Liquid Particle
Deliquescence
Decreasing RH
Solid Particle Liquid Particle
Efflorescence
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Cloud Condensation Nucleus Counter (CCNC) 
Water vapor is saturated at the column wall at 
all points.  
Diffusing heat originates at Point A, while 
diffusing mass originates at Point B.  
The actual partial water pressure of water vapor 
at C equals the partial pressure of water vapor 
at B.  
However , the temperature at C is lower than at 
B, meaning there is more water vapor than 
thermodynamically allowed.  
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded
from our Creative Commons license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use /.
35 James Smith, UCAR. All rights reserved. This content is
excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more
information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>Petters and Kreidenweis ACP 2008 k -Khler equations  
Lower k indicate on less  
hygroscopic or less CCN activity This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure 2 on page, http://www.atmos-chem-phys.net/
7/1961/ 2007/acp -7-1961- 2007.pdf .
41</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>Garimella et al. 2014 ACP This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure 5 on page, http://www.atmos-chem-phys.net/
14/6003/ 2014/acp -14-6003- 2014.pdf .
42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>If we plot the saturation with r for a given salt type and salt mass, we 
obtain a set of curves known as the Khler curves. 
r* = (3b/a)1/2 
S* = 1+(4 a3/[27b]) 
Kelvin Khler curve 
Kelvin curve 
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>44</slideno>
          <text>In order for the Collision  
Coalescence process to be 
effective, a minimum 20 m drop 
is needed. From this size the drop 
can collect smaller drops .  
For 30 m drop collision is the main growing 
process.
  
Larger particles sweep out smaller cloud droplets. 1 mm drop is a product of 100,000 
Collisions and Coalescences  Collision-coalescence 
45
 
cities
cities
r - radius in microns
n - number per literV - terminal velocity in centimeters per secondComparative sizes, concentrations, and terminal fall velocities
of some of the particles included in cloud and precipitation processes
Conventional borderline
between cloud drops
and raindrops
r = 100
v = 70
Typical raindrop r = 1000, n = 1, V = 650
Comparative sizes, concentrations, and terminal fall velocities
of some of the particles included in cloud and precipitation processes
Large cloud dropr = 50n = 10
3
V = 27
 Typical condensation nucleusr = 0.1n = 10
6
V = 0.0001
Typical cloud dropr = 10n = 10
6
V = 1KEYS
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Aerosol and Clouds IV (PDF - 2.9MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/resources/mit12_335f14_lecture3_4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>25</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>1. Precipitation Enhancement- Warm -cloud seeding    
Hygroscopic seeding  - GCCN (Ammonium  Nitrate,  Sodium  chloride)  are 
released  into a cloud. These  particles  grow  until they are large  enough  to 
cause  precipitation  to form . Usually  done  on individual  clouds . 
Kraft paper mill in South Africa 
Mather, 1991 
Hygroscopic seeding for maritime cloud will have no effect, since coalescence is already 
very efficient in such clouds.  
From Wassana Wongrat From Wassana Wongrat Experiments in S. Africa, Mexico and Thailand, hygroscopic 
seeding seems promising under specific circumstances. Though 
promising, it is not well understood (National Research Council , 2003). Reisin et al. (1996) and Cooper et al. (1997) This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
 Wassana Wongrat. All rights
reserved. This content is excluded
from our Creative Commons license.
For more information, see
http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use /.
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>3. Hurricane Modification 
The general strategy is to reduce 
the intensity of the storm by 
seeding the outside the eye wall. 
This will lead to form a new eye 
wall that would surround
 the 
existing eye wall
 and therefore 
reduce the intensity of the 
hurricane.  
Project Cirrus  
(1947) 
Project STORMFURY 
 (1962  1983 )  
This image has been removed due to
copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.toptenz.net/wp-
content/uploads/ 2016/ 01/madscience1.jpg .
This image is in the public domain,
http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Project
_Stormfury_crew.jpg.This image is in the public domain,
http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Project_
stormfury_h ypothesis.gif.
31</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>5. Cloud Dissipation  
it never rains during the May Day parade  
2008 Olympics open ceremony in Beijing, no rain by 
breaking up clouds headed towards Beijing and forcing 
them to drop rain on outlying areas instead. Russian government spent 64 million rubles ($ 20 million) to dissipate 
clouds in Moscow in preparation for Moscows birthday celebration.  
CO2 (in the form of dry ice), liquid nitrogen 
and a powdered cement reagent called 
cement m-500 . 
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/china/images/attachement/jpg/s
ite1/20120522 /180373d 2873011262c 8609.jpg.This image has been removed due to
copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://s3.amazonaws.com/
rapgenius/Victory-day-parade-Russia.jpg.This image has been removed due
to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://media-3.web.
britannica.com/eb-media/ 23/
4823- 004-94C 25E04.jpg .
This image has been remov e
d due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://o
lympi
cs.sporting99.com/pics/national-stadium.jpg.
35</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Charles M. Hatfield ( 1876-1958 ) The Moisture Accelerator - The Rainmaker 
Images courtesy of Washington Secretary of State, from
http://blogs.sos.wa.gov/library/index.php/2012/11/a-rainmaker-meets-his-match- in-ephrata.This image has been removed due
to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http s://
www.johnfry.com/
Media /PhotoSanDiego 036.jpg.
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Church bells and Hail cannons 
Hail cannon market at 3rd  International Congress on Hail 
Shooting, Lyon 1901 (Changon and Ivens, 1981). Albert Stiger 1896 
Austrian winegrower During the Middle Ages, people in Europe 
used to ring church bells and fire cannons 
to try to prevent hail, and the subsequent 
damage to crops.  
Public domain via wikimedia  commons.
This image has been removed due
to copyright restrictions.
Please see:http://www.cyberphysics.
co.uk/graphics/diagrams/db_scale.gif .This image has bee n
 removed due
to copyright restrictions.
Please see:http://photos.demandstudios.
com/getty/article/ 171/22/92824551 _XS.jpg.
This image has b e
en  removed due
to copyright restrictions.
Please see:http://static.
neatorama.
com/images/ 2007- 07/hail-cannon.jpg .This image has b e
en 
removed d
ue
to copy ri
ght restrictions.
Please see:http://www.popsci.com
/scitech/article/ 2004- 11/october-1919.
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
12.335/12.835 Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry
Fall  2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Low concentration of ice crystals  
Can we increase it artificially and produce more rain? 
Assumption : Ice will grow faster than water drops, leading 
to more efficient rain formation. Cold-cloud seeding- Static seeding  
Optimal for Cumulus &amp; Winter Orographic clouds 
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.
17Optimal for Cumulus &amp; Winter Orographic clouds Cloud at Seeding Time After Seeding
Freezing LevelIce
Water</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>1. Precipitation Enhancement  
Precipitation Enhancement -  seeking to increase rainfall amount  
a. Static Seeding - Alter the 
microphysical properties of clouds   by 
adding  ice crystals  (AgI  or dry ice)  
b. Dynamic Seeding - Attempt to 
modify  the air motion in clouds. 
enhancing  vertical air currents  and 
thereby  vertically process more  water  
through  the clouds  
Adding hygroscopic  material  (GCCN  e.g. Salt, Ammonium  Nitrate,  Sodium  
chloride)  to obtain  the intended  result  of Static  or Dynamic . 1.Glaciated seeding-  
warm cloud seeding cold cloud seeding 
2.Hygroscopic Seeding-  This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://s.hswstatic.com/gif/control-weather.gif.
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Spain 
Canada  
Belgium  
Italy These images have been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see:http://www2.ljworld.com/photos/ 2008/sep/ 23/155789/
and http://realneo.us/content/hail-cannon .France  
Austria 
Tibet 
Australia 
New Zealand  
The Netherlands
United States is  
 There is neither a scientific bas
nor a credible hypothesis to 
support the use of cannons (WMO, 2001).  Hail cannons People who do not know history are doomed to repeat it (Wieringa and Holleman,  2006) Hail Suppression  
Hail cannons or ionization devices, 
have no physical basis and are not 
recommended for Hail suppression 
(WMO, 2007).  This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.hailcannon.com .
These images have been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://cloud-seeding.eu/images/slides/generators/ground_generator
_start.jpg and http://cloud-seeding.eu/documents_pic/ 88/small-rocket-big.jpg .
29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>1)Precipitation Enhancement  
2)Hail Suppression  
3)Hurricane Modification 
4)Fog Dissipation  
5)Cloud Dissipation Artificial Weather Modification  Goals: 
https://www2.ucar.edu/news/weather-modification-multimedia-gallery  
150 weather modification programs 
operating in 37 countries worldwide  
25
 University Corporation for Atmospheric Research. All
rights reserved. This content is excluded from our 
Creative Commons license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Rain enhancement by cloud ionization  
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.meteo-systems.com.
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://climateviewer.com/wp-content/uploads/
2014/ 03/desert-rain-110104c-02.jpg .
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://sindicatum.com/meteosystems/photo-
gallery/#!prettyPhoto[pp_gal]/2/ .
According to WMO report weather-modification technologies such 
as "ionization methods" had no sound scientific basis and "should 
be treated with suspicion" 
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.335/12.835  Special Topics : 
Aerosol and Cloud Section 
Special Topic : 
Weather Modification 
Thursday, Dec 4, 2014  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>On Nov 13, 1946, Shaeffer dropped 1.4 kg of dry ice (solid CO2) pellets 
from an airplane into a supercooled stratus cloud at 14,000ft (-20C), 
flying in a race-track pattern near Schenectady, New York.  
And snow fell! 
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.globalresearch.ca/articlePictures/ 11%20romy-ny-dry-ice-seeding- 1946.jpg .
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Deliberate human intervention to 
influence atmospheric processes 
that constitute the weather.  
 Weather Modification:
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>1946 Vincent Schaefer  discovered by 
accident that supercooled water can be 
transformed into ice using dry ice (solid 
CO2); 
1947 Bernard Vonnegut  while working for 
the General Electric Corporation in New York 
found that silver iodide (AgI) aerosols were 
excellent ice-nuclei. 
Houghton, 1985  
Irving Langmuir (top left), Bernard V onnegut (top right) and 
Vince Schaefer. 
J. Appl. Phys. 18, 593 (1947 ) This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://files.gereports.com/wp-content/uploads/
2011/12/NB10460-Cloud-seeding-Langm.jpg .
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>WMO - World Meteorological  Organization  Quantify weather modification experiments 
1)The experiments have to be randomized  and evaluated by 
statistical methods . 
2) Success has to be judged on the basis of the rain obtained at 
the ground. 
3)Statistical success of an experiment has to be supported by 
physical insights and understanding . 
4) Success has to be repeated in other areas of the world 
(transferability). WMO criteria for  
successful experiments 
National Academy of Science, 2003 : Last comprehensive report on weather 
modification (http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=10829)
 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Vapor pressure above water is higher than the vapor pressure above ice, 
this mean that more water molecules will be around the water drop. 
Due to the fact that the Ice crystal is supersaturated and the 
water drop is just saturated, the ice crystal will grow on the 
account of the water drop growth.   sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use /.
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Summary 
1)Precipitation Enhancement  
2)Hail Suppression  
3)Hurricane Modification 
4)Fog Dissipation  
5)Cloud Dissipation Artificial Weather Modification  Goals: 
This image is in the public domain,
http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Project_
stormfury_hypothesis.gif.
37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>1)Precipitation Enhancement  
2)Hail Suppression  
3)Hurricane Modification 
4)Fog Dissipation  
5)Cloud Dissipation Artificial Weather Modification  Goals: 
Cloud Seeding - Act of adding foreign objects to change the type and amount 
of precipitation that a cloud will release .  
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Examples for Cold-cloud seeding- Static seeding  
Project Cirrus  - The five year experiment was born in February of 1947 at Fort 
Monmouth, New Jersey. It was a joint effort of the Army, Navy, Air Force, and GE   
Cloud seeding did not always produce the expected results  
Israel Rain Enhancement Experiments 
                 Israel I 1961- 1968 
                 Israel II 1969-1975 
                 Israel III 1975-1994 
Re-analysis of the cloud seeding experiment and operations in 
Israel shows that seeding has not produced the expected  
enhancement in rainfall. seeding had little or no effect on total 
precipitation on the ground. 
Levin et al. 2010 This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://cfile3.uf.tistory.com/image/132585484F1633312A3E11 .
This image has been removed
due to copyright restrictions.
Please see Figure 1 on page,
http://www.tau.ac.il/~zevlev/pub
_files/Levin-Halfon-Alpert-cloud-
seeding-in -Israel-2010-AtmRes.pdf .
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Snomax Snow Inducer is an ice-nucleating protein derived 
from the naturally occurring bacteria, Pseudomonas 
syringae.  Seeding with Snomax 
http://www.snomax.com/ 
http://www.snomax.com/english/environment
.html This image has been removed due to
copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.snomax.ch/Bilder/Bearb
eitet/Snomax%20Sack_Berg.jpg .
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.snomax.com/files/snowmax_11.jpg .
This image has been remov
ed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.snomax.com/files/snomax_1.jpg .
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>1)Precipitation Enhancement  
2)Hail Suppression  
3)Hurricane Modification 
4)Fog Dissipation  
5)Cloud Dissipation Artificial Weather Modification  Goals: 
30</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>4. Fog Dissipation  
Salt Lake City  
Heathrow Airport  
Heathrow, 2006 . About 350 
flights cancelled (50 %) 
during Christmas holiday. 
40,000 people affected 
Tenerife, 1977 
Collision in heavy fog 
583 people killed. 
Seeding from the ground  
Mainly with dry ice This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://pandawhale.com/post/ 11343/fog-before-
amp-after .This image has been removed due to
copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://newsimg.bbc.co.uk/media/
images/ 42379000/jpg/_ 42379441_ba_getty.jpg .This image has been removed due to
copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://img.deseretnews.com/images/
article/midres/ 325701/ 325701.jpg .
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger/ 2067/
3930/ 400/Imagem2.0.png .
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see Figures 9 and 10. Vardiman, L, E. D . Figgins , and H.  S. Appleman , 1971:
Operational D issipation
 of Supercooled Fog using L iquid Propane. Journal of Applied
Meteorology and Climatology  10: 51525.
34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Bergeron-Findeisen Process 
Ice particles grow at the expense of water droplets 
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions. Please see:
http://www.atmos.washington.edu/~hakim/ 101/snowflakes/ahrens_ 0522.jpg .
 R. Pitter. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons
license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>According the American Meteorological Society (AMS): 
The efficacy of projects intended to mitigate the severity of 
hailstorms remains indeterminate .  
Statistical assessments of certain operational projects indicate 
successful reduction of crop hail damage.  
Scientific  establishment of cause and effect are incomplete. 
Results of various operational and experimental projects provide a 
range of outcomes. Some suggest decreases  in hailfall (reduction 
of 20-50%), while others have produced inconclusive results, and 
some suggest increases .  2. Hail Suppression  
Our understanding of hailstorms is not yet sufficient to allow 
confident prediction of the effects of seeding individual storms, and 
the most appropriate seeding methodology has not been determined.  
28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>2. Hail Suppression  
Major hail risk area in Europe (Berz and Siebert, 2000) 
www2.ucar.edu This image has been removed
due to copyright restrictions.
 MetEd  of the University Corporation for Atmospheric
Research. All rights reserved. This content is excluded
from ourCreative Commons license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>1)Precipitation Enhancement  
2)Hail Suppression  
3)Hurricane Modification 
4)Fog Dissipation  
5)Cloud Dissipation Artificial Weather Modification  Goals: 
https://www2.ucar.edu/news/weather-modification-multimedia-gallery  
150 weather modification programs 
operating in 37 countries worldwide  
 University Corporation for Atmospheric Research. All
rights reserved. This content is excluded from our 
Creative Commons license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>The main difference between the static and dynamic 
seeding is in the amounts of seeding material that 
introduced into clouds. 
dynamic mode 
 static mode 
1 - 10 IC/L 
 100 - 1000 IC/L 
seeding target at 
temperatures warmer 
than - 15C 
200-1000g of  AgI in flares dropped 
directly into the high supercooled liquid 
water content updrafts of cumuli. Over Seeding  
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Not all clouds may be amenable to seeding and there exists a 
certain window of opportunity. 
Clouds are relatively cold-based and 
continental  type.  
Clouds top temperatures approximately 
-10  to -20 C. 
limited to the time when significant 
amounts of supercooled liquid water is 
available for growth by riming of the 
seeded produced ice crystals .  
Not all clouds may be amenable to seeding and there exists a 
Not all clouds may be amenable to seeding and there exists a 
Not all clouds may be amenable to seeding and there exists a 
 
window of opportunity : 
For the static seeding concept this opportunity appears to be limited to: 
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Hurricane Modification  does it work? 
Since a hurricane's destructive potential increases rapidly as 
its strongest winds become stronger, a reduction as small as 
10% would have been worthwhile.  
There is no generally accepted conceptual model  for modifying 
tropical disturbances.  
Hurricane modification experiments of the 1950s and 1960s were 
inconclusive .  
No sound physical hypotheses exist for the modification of tornadoes, 
or of damaging winds in general, and no scientific experimentation 
has been conducted.  
 
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Broad scale seeding  -Seeding below cloud base along a 
predetermined line. Often ground generators are used. 
 
Target seeding  -Seeding individual clouds based on their 
development stage. Cannons or airplanes are often used. Definitions for cloud seeding 
From Wassana Wongrat This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the third and fourth images at the left hand side
on page, http://english.sina.com/china/p/ 2011/0521/ 374338.html .
 Wassana Wongrat. All rights reserved.
This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use /.
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>United Nations Environment Programmed website cloud-seeding airplane 
measurement and monitoring plane 
communications plane for experimental and monitoring purposes 
aircraft maintenance  
hanger facilities 
meteorological radar  
air sounding equipment 
computer system and data analysis software 
rain gauge network and automatic weather stations 
suitable cloud formations.  Operation and Maintenance 
Costs - The cost of water produced is about $1.50 /m3/season/ha (United Nations, 1985).  
This cost is made up of scientific equipment and hardware costs; flying costs for cloud seeding (capital 
and operational, including maintenance or hire charges); salaries for scientists and pilots; the cost of 
seeding agents and flares; and, software
 costs (for experimental and monitoring purposes). This is an expensive technology to operate, requiring sophi
sticated equipment, control and 
monitoring procedures, and materials, including: 
Estimated $ 1 billion spent 
world-wide per year on 
some type of modification 
36</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Even a well designed statistical experiment will not be accepted 
by scientific community as being credible unless that experiment 
is supported by physical evidence: 
1.Seeding material actually entered the cloud. 
2.Seeded cloud exhibit broader droplet spectra than unseeded 
clouds. 
3.Seeded cloud have higher drop concentrations than 
unseeded clouds. 
4.Large amount of rainfall actually reach  the ground. 
Cotton and Pielke, 2007 Quantify weather modification experiments 
Both physical and statistical evaluations 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>1)Precipitation Enhancement  
2)Hail Suppression  
3)Hurricane Modification 
4)Fog Dissipation  
5)Cloud Dissipation Artificial Weather Modification  Goals: 
33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Graupel     Diameter &lt; 5mm 
Hail           Diameter &gt; 5mm 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Graupe &amp; Hail Snow Rain 
Riming = Accretion Aggregation 
This image has been removed due
to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.ems.psu.
edu/~lno/Meteo 437/Riming.jpg .
 MetEd  of the University Corporation for Atmospheric Research. All rights reserved. This
content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see
http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions. It's about how to measure hail.
Please see: http://www.cocorahs.org/Media/images/hailpad_large_md.jpg .
38</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>2. Hail Suppression  
The idea is to reduce the average size of 
the hailstones and to increases the 
number of small ice particles competing 
for the available supercooled droplets. Over seeding  
Switzerland project Grossversuch IV ( 1977-1981)   
research groups from Switzerland, Italy and France 
The main result is that there 
is no statistically significant 
difference between seeded 
and unseeded hail cells.  
This image has been removed due to
copyright restrictions.
Please see:  http://users.telenet.be/kareldewaele/
hagelkanon/deel3_clip_image 008.gif .
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded  
from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
27</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>- Dynamic Seeding 
The focus of the  of cloud seeding is to
enhance the vertical air currents in clouds and thereby 
vertically process more water through the clouds resulting in
increased precipitation.  
Over Seeding 
Dynamic Seeding steps 
1. Supercooled liquid water converted 
into ice particles  
2. Releasing latent heat 
3.  Increasing buoyancy and motivate 
Cloud updrafts.  
4. Cloud grow larger  
5. Process more water vapor 
6. Yield more precipitation 
20</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Atmospheric Photochemistry and Air Pollution II (PDF - 1.3MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/resources/mit12_335f14_lecture1_2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>HOWEVER, IN 
POLLUTED AIR 
THERE ARE 
MULTIPLE 
SOURCES OF OH 
DEPENDING ON 
TIME OF DAY 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Examining the chemistry and physics of air pollution, we see 
that air pollution regulations affect climate by increasing CH4 
(warming), decreasing H2SO4 aerosols (warming), decreasing O3 
(cooling) and decreasing black carbon aerosols (cooling).    
   Regulating NOx 
   decreases O3 
 and OH 
    
Decreasing OH 
   increases CH4 
  
   Regulating CO 
increases OH 
and decreases O3      
Decreasing O3 
   decreases OH 
  
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>TOPIC 1  
ATMOSPHERIC PHOTOCHEMISTRY and 
AIR POLLUTION 
 
INTRODUCTION TO THE CHEMISTRY OF AIR 
POLLUTION  
  12.335/12.835 EXPERIMENTAL ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY, FALL 2014 
RONALD PRINN &amp; MARIA ZAWADOWICZ 
 SEPTEMBER 23, 2014  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>a[O3]2 + b[O3] + c = 0 OZONE CYCLE &amp; PHOTOCHEMICAL STEADY STATE APPROXIMATION (PSSA) 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
12.335 / 12.835 Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry
Fall  2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>USA TROPOSPHERIC COLUMN OZONE BY SEASON  
(Satellite observations in DOBSON UNITS = 2.7 x 1016 molecules/cm2) 
Image courtesy of Fishman, J., A.  E. Wozniak, and J.  K. Creilson.
From Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics  3 (2003): 893907.
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>As we will discuss in a later lecture, human health is 
affected by exposure to ozone expressed here as a 
function of the AOT40 Index (AOT40 = hourly ozone 
exposure above 40 ppb in units of ppb.hr/mo.)  
NOTE: (8000 ppb.hr/mo 
divided by (31x24) hr/mo 
=10.75ppb) 
 Benjamin Felzer , Lehigh University. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our
Creative Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>BECAUSE OZONE PRODUCTION TAKES TIME, 
TRANSPORT PLAYS AN IMPORTANT ROLE IN 
DETERMINING EXPOSURE LEVELS 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>TYPICAL 
URBAN 
AEROSOL 
NUMBER (N) 
DENSITY (nn), &amp; 
SURFACE AREA 
(S) &amp; VOLUME 
(V) WEIGHTED 
DENSITIES (nS, 
nV), AS 
FUNCTIONS OF 
PARTICLE 
DIAMETER (Dp) 
TYPICAL 
URBAN 
AEROSOL 
COMPOSITION, 
ORIGIN 
(primary,  
secondary, 
either ) &amp; 
SHAPE Sulfates [H2SO4 (aq), NH4)2SO4 (aq, s)] 
Black Carbon [C) (s)] 
Organic Carbon [CxHyOz (l, s)] 
Dust [Silicates (s), Clays (s), Pollens (s)] 
Nitrates [HNO3 (aq), NH4NO3 ) (aq, s)] 
Chlorides [NaCl (aq, s)] 
Mixtures[(H2SO4 on BC, OC, dust] 
Spheres (liquids) 
Crystals (ice, salts, minerals)  
Dendriform (snow, soot) 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>The hydroxyl free radical 
(OH) is the major oxidizing 
chemical in the global 
atmosphere  
It annually removes about 3.7 billion 
metric tons (Pg) of trace gases (CO, CH4, 
higher hydrocarbons, hydro-halocarbons, 
NOx, SOx, etc.) from the atmosphere. . 
 
With a lifetime of only about 1 second it is 
possible to measure locally, but not 
possible to measure directly at regional to 
global scales. 
 
Use measurements of the industrial 
chemical CH3CCl3, whose emissions are 
are known and whose major sink is OH, to 
indirectly estimate large scale OH 
variations. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>FIGURES: Aerosol optical depth, 
aer, at 0.55 m (color bar) as 
determined by the MODIS 
satellite instrument for the 
January to March 2001 mean 
(top panel) and for August to 
October 2001 mean (bottom 
panel). The top panel also 
shows the location of AERONET 
sites (white squares) that have 
been operated (not necessary 
continuously) since 1996. The 
bottom panel also shows the 
location of different aerosol 
lidar networks (red = EARLINET, 
orange = ADNET, black = 
MPLNET). (Ref: IPCC AR4 WG1, 
Chap. 2, Fig. 2.11, 2007) ATMOSPHERIC 
AEROSOLS 
 
DEFINITION: ALL SUSPENDED 
LIQUID, SOLID &amp; MIXED 
LIQUID-SOLID PARTICLES IN 
AIR EXCEPT WATER DROPLETS 
&amp; ICE CRYSTALS 
e.g. BLACK CARBON, SULFATE, 
ETC. 
A
T
A
T
A
T
A
T
A
T
M
M
M
M
M
OSPHERIC
A
E
E
EROSOLS
D
E
F
I
N
I
T
I
O
O
O
O
O
O
N:ALLSUSPENDED
L
I
Q
U
I
D
D
D
D
D
D
,
,
SOLID&amp;MIXED
L
I
Q
U
I
D
-
S
O
O
O
O
O
O
OLIDPAPAPAAPAPARTICLESIN
A
I
R
E
X
C
C
C
E
P
P
P
P
TWAAATATATATATERDROPLETS
&amp;
I
C
C
C
C
CECRYRYRYRYRYYSYSYSSYSYSTATATAATATALS
e
.
g
.
B
L
A
C
K
K
K
K
CARBON,SULFAFAFAAFAFATATATATATE,
ETC.
 IPCC. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons
license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>M</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/resources/test-1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Atmospheric Photochemistry and Air Pollution IV (PDF - 1.3MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/resources/mit12_335f14_lecture1_4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9&#8211;10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>OZONE MONITORING 
 NETWORK  IN NEW ENGLAND 
High concentrations of ozone near ground 
level can be harmful to people, animals, 
crops, and other materials. Ozone can 
irritate your respiratory system, causing you to start coughing, feel an irritation in your throat and/or experience an uncomfortable sensation in your chest. Ozone can aggravate asthma, and can inflame and damage cells that line your lungs. Ozone may also aggravate chronic 
lung diseases such as emphysema and 
bronchitis and reduce the immune system's ability to fight off bacterial infections in the respiratory system. Lastly, 
ozone may cause permanent lung 
damage. These effects can be worse in children and exercising adults 
Image courtesy of EPA .10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>NATIONAL 
AMBIENT 
AIR QUALITY 
STANDARDS 
(NAAQS) 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>O3 at BOSTON - LONG ISLAND STATION (Operating 1999 to Present)  
Year Total  
Days 
&gt; 
0.084  1st 
High 
(ppm)  Date 2nd 
High 
(ppm)  Date 3rd 
High 
(ppm)  Date 4th 
High 
(ppm)  Date MAP 
1999  4 0.102 July 
16 0.100 June 
240.089 June 1  0.087 May 31* 2000 0 0.084 June 
10 0.073 June 1  0.072 Aug 9  0.070 June 2  2001  9 0.111 June 
20 0.107 June 
19 0.100  Aug 2  0.094 July 
24 2002 10 0.126 Aug 
130.117 Aug 
14 0.102 July 3 0.102 Sept 9* 2003  1 0.102 June 
270.083 June 
25 0.078 June 
26 0.078 July 4  2004 1 0.094 June 8  0.081 July 
220.080 July 
23 0.079 July 
30 2005  5 0.095 June 
250.091 June 
26 0.089  Aug 
11 0.086 June 
24 2006 0 0.083 June 
22 0.083 July 2  0.083 July 
18 0.079 July 1 2007 0 0.082 Sept 
25 0.080 April 
230.076 Sept 
260.073 Aug 3  
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>REGIONAL OZONE HEALTH ALERTS IN NEW ENGLAND 
 BASED ON THE MONITORING NETWORK. Human health is 
affected by exposure to ozone expressed as a function of the 
AOT40 Index (AOT40 = hourly ozone exposure above 40 ppb in 
units of ppb.hr/mo; see earlier lecture for USA AOT40 map)  
Image courtesy of EPA.
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Benefit of Policy is avoided 
health costs due to the 
policy.  
Remaining Cost of Pollution 
decreases due to lower 
pollution levels,  but is offset 
by increases due to rising 
income and population. 
Welfare is a measure of total 
consumption of goods and 
services. 
14Change in Welfare
Benefits of air pollution regulation and costs of remaining pollution.$ billions 1997 USD
Year1975050100150250350450
1980 1985 1990 1995 2000 2005200300400
Cost of PollutionBenefit of Policy
Welfare
(a) Benefits (b) Costs by Pollutant
$ billions USD
Year1975050100150250350
1980 1985 1990 1995 2000200300
$ billions USD
Year1975050100150
1980 1985 1990 1995 2000200
O3 PMFigure by MIT OpenCourseWare.
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
12.335 / 12.835 Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry
Fall  2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Oxides of Nitrogen  The oxides of most concern are nitric oxide (NO) and nitrogen dioxide 
(NO2). The latter is more damaging to health, due to the toxic nature of this gas. NO 
is emitted to the atmosphere as a primary pollutant, from traffic and power stations, and is 
oxidized to nitrogen dioxide following dispersal. Health effects of exposure to NO2 include 
shortness of breath and chest pains. The effects of NO include changes to lung function at high 
concentrations. 
Carbon Monoxide  Carbon monoxide combines with hemoglobin, the oxygen carrying 
component of the blood stream, to form carboxy-hemoglobin (COHb) which can be life-
threatening in high doses. The effects of CO pollution are more damaging to pregnant women 
and their fetus. Research into smoking during pregnancy shows that concentrations within the 
blood stream of unborn infants is as high as 12%, causing retardation of the unborn child's 
growth and mental development. 
Lead  Lead is still a serious air pollutant especially to those living near to areas of dense traffic 
in cities where leaded fuel is still used or to coal-fired power plants. Damage to the central 
nervous system, kidneys and brain can result when levels in the blood reach 
concentrations of 800 mg/liter. Much of the concern regarding pollution from lead centers 
around its effects on child health. Children exhibit vulnerability to the toxic effects of lead at 
much lower concentrations than for adults. There is a strong link between high lead exposures 
and impaired intelligence. 
Sulfur dioxide  The health effects of sulfur dioxide include heart disease and bronchitis. SO2 
emissions have been significantly reduced through legislative measures in developed countries. 
Asthmatics are especially sensitive for whom concentrations above 125 ppb may result in a fall 
in lung function. Tightness in the chest and coughing may also result at levels approaching 400 
ppb. At levels above 400 ppb the lung function of asthmatics may be impaired to the 
extent that medical help is required. Sulfur dioxide pollution is more harmful when 
particulate and other pollution concentrations are also high (the synergistic effect).  
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Air Pollution Economic Effects 
(Yang et al, Report 113, MIT Joint Program on the Science &amp; Policy of Global Change: 
http://globalchange.mit.edu ) 
Approach 
Extensive data set on epidemiological effects of air 
pollution exposure 
Resultant illness, death, demand for medical services 
Lost labor, leisure, diversion of resources to medical and 
health services introduced into MIT economic model 
Results based on historical pollution levels  
evaluated US benefit of air pollution regulation, and 
remaining burden of air pollution (1975-2000) 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>TOPIC 1  
ATMOSPHERIC PHOTOCHEMISTRY and  
AIR POLLUTION 
 
AIR POLLUTION: HUMAN HEALTH, 
REGULATION, MONITORING &amp; COSTS 
 12.335/12.835 EXPERIMENTAL ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY, FALL 2014 
RONALD PRINN &amp; MARIA ZAWADOWICZ 
 OCTOBER 2, 2014  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Volatile Organic Compounds (VOCs) 
Some VOCs are directly harmful, including: Benzene which may increase susceptibility to 
leukemia,  if exposure is maintained over a period of time; Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons  
(PAH) some of which can cause cancer (there are several hundred different forms of PAH, and 
sources can be both natural and man-made); Dioxins,  whose sources include manufacturing of 
organic compounds as well as the incineration of wastes and various other combustion 
processes involving chlorinated compounds, and which has health effects due to inhalation 
and ingestion (e.g. dioxins entering the food chain from soils); 1,3 Butadiene , for which  there is 
an apparent correlation between exposure and a higher risk of cancer, and which is produced 
from manufacturing of synthetic rubbers, gasoline-driven vehicles and cigarette smoke. 
General Air Quality Problems 
Air quality indoors Many different compounds are contained in tobacco smoke, including carbon 
monoxide, ammonia, dioxins and PAH; the latter two are thought to be carcinogenic. Other 
sources of indoor pollution include particulates from mineral fibers as well as household dust. 
Dust in buildings is known to cause problems including fatigue and nausea. One of the most 
pressing concerns with indoor air pollution is with carbon monoxide built up from gas, oil or 
wood fired appliances. Open gas flames and fire places also produce BC. 
Asthma and air pollution  There has been a steady rise in the number of reported asthma cases 
since the 1970s,  and air pollution problems are believed to be a significant (but not sole) 
contributor to the rise. High concentrations of nitrogen dioxide, sulfur dioxide, ozone and 
particulates (especially PM10) can all trigger breathing difficulties in asthmatics. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>The spatial 
grid 
We divide the earth s 
atmosphere into a 
finite number of boxes 
(grid cells).  
 
Assume that each 
variable has the same 
value throughout the 
box. 
 
Write a budget for each 
each box, defining the 
changes within the 
box, and the flows 
between the boxes. 
Figure  Henderson-Sellers: A Climate 
Modeling Primer.  John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>TRANSPORT,
CHEMISTRY AND RADIATION  COMPONENTS IN COMPLEX 3D 
MODELS 
3Interactions Between Air Pollution and Climate
UV
N2O
CFCs
LightningStratosphere
O(1D) OHNO
HO 2
OHOH
BC
H2O CH 4 CO SO 2OHO2UV
CO 2 CO 2O2NO 2
O2
Hydrosphere Biosphere &amp; Human ActivityHNO 3
Primary &amp; Secondary PollutantsGreenhouse Gases Reactive Free Radical/Atom
Less Reactive Radicals
Reflective Aerosols Absorbing Aerosols (BC)O3
H2SO 4COMPONENTS OF ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY MODELS
DYNAMICAL EQUATIONS
MASS CONTINUITY EQUATION
MOMENTUM EQUATIONS
THERMODYNAMIC EQUATION
CHEMICAL
CONTINUITY EQUATIONS
RADIATION
EQUATIONSWinds , Eddy diffusion coefficients
Temperature
 Rates 
   forHeatingRates for ChemistryConcentrations
(O3, etc.)
ForUnpredictedgreen housegases usescenarios orextra polations
For Source gases use predictions,extra polationsor scenarios  U.V Fluxes For photodissociation 
rates{
{ [i]
t= Pi - Li -    . ( [ i ] V )~
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>INCORPORATING METEOROLOGY IN THE BOX MODEL  
 
1. USE THE u MEASUREMENTS TO ALIGN THE MODEL x AXIS AND USE IN THE        
BOX MODEL ADVECTION TERMS. 
2. USE THE T &amp; u MEASUREMENTS TO CALCULATE A RICHARDSON NUMBER TO 
HELP CHOOSE SUITABLE texchange  VALUES (e.g. unstable~1 hour, neutral~6 hours, 
stable~12 hours).  
3. USE TEMPERATURE SOUNDINGS OR HAZE LAYER HEIGHT TO ESTIMATE Z TOP OF BOUNDARY LAYER 
 Cory Cripe . Some rights reserved. License: CC BY-NC 3.0.
This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license.
For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Air Pollution and Human Health 
(Reference: Adapted from http://www.air-quality.org.uk/18.php) 
Introduction  Pollution-related health problems result from primary pollutants such as sulfur 
dioxide, nitrogen dioxide, and some particulates, and secondary pollutants like ozone and 
particulates produced from primary gas-phase pollutants.  
Particulates  The extent to which particulates are considered harmful depends largely on their 
composition. Sea salt, for example, is believed to have a positive effect on health. Man-made 
sources of particulates, however, are rarely harmless. In towns and cities, these are 
extensively from diesel vehicle exhausts. The effects of man-made particulate emissions are 
considered detrimental due to their composition, containing mainly unburned fuel oil and 
polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) that are known to be carcinogenic  among 
laboratory animals. Particulates may originate from many other sources including cement 
manufacturing processes, incineration and power generation, so  localized particulate pollution 
is common. The sizes of particles are important when assessing their effects on health. PM2.5 
and PM10 as well as total suspended particulates are routinely monitored. This is due to the 
fact that particles of less than 2.5- 10 micro-meters ( mm)  in diameter can penetrate 
deep into the lung and cause more damage,  as opposed to larger particles that may be 
filtered out through the airways' natural mechanisms. 
Ozone Ozone is created by the action of sunlight on CO, volatile organic compounds (VOCs) 
and nitrogen oxides over 1-3 day time periods. This results in ozone being widely dispersed 
as a pollutant, and can form in greater concentrations in rural areas. As ozone concentrations 
are particularly dependant on sunlight, episodes are always likely to develop following 
sustained periods of warmth and calm weather. Ozone is a toxic gas that can bring 
irreversible damage to the respiratory tract and lung tissue if delivered in high 
quantities. Levels during air pollution episodes range up to 100-250 ppb (0.1-0. 25 
ppm). At these concentrations ozone impairs lung function and causes irritation to 
the respiratory tract. Asthmatics are especially affected. 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Aerosol and Clouds III (PDF - 3.0MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-335-experimental-atmospheric-chemistry-fall-2014/resources/mit12_335f14_lecture3_3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23&#8211;24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Single Particle Mass Spectrometry 
Particle 
Inlet 
Particle 
Sizing 
Particle 
Composition + -
+ - 
2/ tzmIntensity 
2/ tzmIntensity start 0 
200100 300
sstop 0 
200100 300
s0 
200100 300
s
Courtesy of D. Gross 
PALMS  
Particle Analysis by Laser Mass Spectrometry  
Image courtesy of Deborah Gross. Used with permission.7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Cziczo et al. 2013 This images has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see Figure 2 on page:  http://www.sciencemag.org/content/ 340/6138/ 1320.full .
30</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Remainder of Today 
Seinfeld and Pandis This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure 2.15 of the book Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics:
From Air Pollution to Climate Change . ISBN: 9780471720188.
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Free Tropospheric 
K. Froyd, unpublished 
Biomass Burning   
Sulfate-Organic
mixtures  dominate in 
UTLS 
Mineral Dust : 10-30%  
 Little Sea Salt  in UT 
Meteoric  particles in 
stratosphere 
Acidic sulfate  mainly in 
stratosphere Tropopause  
Number Fraction m)  (k tude Alti
Image courtesy of Karl Froyd. Used with permission.
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Clouds 
Lamb and Verlinde 
 or Ice d Col P - M arm W
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons licen se. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Stratiform 
  High-Level Clouds  
  Mid-Level Clouds 
  Low-Level Clouds Clouds Classification 
Convective 
Clouds with Vertical Development  
Stratiform 
 Convective 
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded
from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see
http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use /.
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Supersaturation (With Respect to Ice) 
Temperature (C)  0 -50 1.0 1.6 
Droplets and 
Ice Crystals ~ -38 C 
Droplet  
Activation 
Contact 
Freezing 
Deliquescence 
Homogeneous 
Freezing 
Freezing 
Freezing 
Ice 
Only 
Figure 3. Aerosol and Ice Condensation 
Freezing 
Condensation 
Condensation 
Deliquescence Deliquesced 
Aerosol and 
Ice 
Deposition 
Freezing Heterogeneously Formed Clouds: 
-Few but large ice crystals -Shorter lifetime due to crystal size -Clouds possible at lower altitude (higher T, lower RH) Homogeneously Formed Clouds 
- Almost all particles nucleate ice - Many small ice crystals 
- Longer lifetime 
- Higher altitude clouds 
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry 
 (12.335/12.835) 
 
Section 3, Lecture 3: 
 
 
Karin Ardon-Dryer &amp; Sarvesh Garimella 
 
Tuesday, Nov 25, 2014 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Analysis of Cloud Residuals  
Single particle size and composition (0.2  3 mm) 
Offline  SEM + EDS 
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see Figure 1 on page: http://www.sciencemag.org/content/340/6138/1320.full.
Size, morphology, and composition 
Online - PALMS 
detect a particle &amp; meas size 
focus particles vaporize &amp; ionize 
 + + Time- of-flight + MS +   193 analyze ions 
nm 
Size and composition 
29Cziczo et al. 2013 
29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Clouds with high concentrations of cloud drops 
are referred to as continental  clouds. These are 
more often found  over land.  
Clouds with low concentrations of cloud drops 
are called maritime clouds and they are often 
found  in clean regions and over water. 
Continental and Maritime clouds 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
Continental  clouds 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
 clean regions and over water. 
Maritime clouds 
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Sulfate-
Organic  
Biomass Burning  
Mineral 
Dust &amp; 
Metallic  Sea Salt  Unclassified  
EC 
Cziczo et al. 2013 This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see Figure 1 on page:
http://www.sciencemag.org/content/ 340/6138/ 1320.full .
31</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Influential Results 
Zhang et al. GRL2007 This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://eloquentscience.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/img_global.jpg .
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Troposphere Tropopau
se 
Cloud anvil winds  Mirisa56 . Some rights reserved. License: 
CC BY-SA. This content is
excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page:
http://teachertech.rice.edu/Participants/louviere/Images/profile.gif.
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excluded
from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see
http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use /.
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>A Few Words About ALL Clouds 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Murphy et al. JGR 2006 This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see  Figure 6 on page: https://cloud1.arc.nasa.gov/
intex-na/publications/articles/2006JD007340.pdf .
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>0C  0C  0C  
Mixed Phase cloud  Glaciated cloud
Warm cloud Water drop 
Ice crystal  
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Contrail clouds 
Ship track 
Mammatus clouds  
 Orographic clouds Classification of Clouds  
Other Cloud Types:   Temperatures 
By their shape and heights 
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Aerosol Composition Before 1994 
 So, whats the problem(s) 
here? 
 
Courtesy / adapted from J. 
Jimenez 
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Thermal Desorption  
Aerosol Mass Spectrometer  
https://www.tropos.de/en/research/projects-infrastructures-technology/technology-at-tropos/chemical-analytics/
aerosol-mass-spectrometry-techniques/This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://cires1.colorado.edu/jimenez/amsanimation.gif .
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.airmonitor.cn/upload/editorfiles/
2008.12.3_13.43.7_7015.JPG .This image has been removed due to cop
yright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.tropos.de/fileadmin/_processed_/
csm_Aerosol_chemicalKK_20131212_c10452182e.jpg.
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Today 
Atmospheric Particles 
 
Atmospheric Clouds 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>0.0010.010.1110ion current (mA)
220 210 200 190 180 170 160 150 140 130 120 110 10090 80 70 60 50 40 30 20 100
m/zC+
C2+
SO+CO+
Pb+NO+
C3+
HSO3+ HSO2+
H3SO4+
0.0010.010.1110ion current (mA)
220 210 200 190 180 170 160 150 140 130 120 110 10090 80 70 60 50 40 30 20 100
m/zApr 07  16:06
8.5 km  237 K
Da = 1.3 m
C+Na+
SO+Al+
Fe+
Ca+
Ba+Cu+
Li+K+
Pb+Rb+Mineral Dust particle 
Sulfate-Organic particle 
adapted from D. Cziczo 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>What Forms Clouds? 
Seinfeld and Pandis, 2006 This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure 2.15 of the book Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics:
From Air Pollution to Climate Change. ISBN: 9780471720188.This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Figure 17.6 of the book Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics:
From Air Pollution to Climate Change . ISBN: 9780471720188.
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Cloud Development 
Clouds form as air rises, 
expands and cools 
Most clouds form by: 
a. Surface heating and 
    free convection 
b. . Lifting of air over 
topography 
c. Widespread air lifting 
due to surface convergence 
d. Lifting along weather   
fronts 
 
http://www.sir-ray.com/cloudformation2.jpg 
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excludedfrom our Creative Commons license. For more information, seehttp://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Aerosol Abundance 
Unless otherwise specified figures from Seinfeld and Pandis This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: Table 2.20 of the book Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics:
From Air Pollution to Climate Change . ISBN: 9780471720188.
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Higher Temperature, Lower Humidity Lower Temperature, Higher Humidity 
Condensation Nucleus 
(Grey = Soluble 
or Insoluble) 
(Black = Solid) Droplet 
Ice Crystal 
Heterogeneous Droplet Activation : ~101%RH 
Heterogeneous Ice Nucleation : ~ 120% RH 
Ice Nucleus (IN)  ode
Contact Freezing M on i t a e l Nuc
Deposition Freezing 
Homogeneous Ice Nucleation: ~ 160% RH 
Homogeneous Freezing Nucleus (HFN) Particles take up water Homogeneous Nucleation : 
~400% RH! 
25</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
12.335 / 12.835 Experimental Atmospheric Chemistry
Fall  2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page: http://scied.ucar.edu/webweather/clouds/cloud-types.
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Cloud Measurement 
DMT, Boulder, CO Cloud Imaging Probe (CIP)  
Passive Cavity Aerosol Spectrometer Probe 
(PCASP-100X)  This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the "Cloud Droplet Probe" image on page:
ht
tp://dev.dropletmeasurement.com/products/airborne .Cloud Droplet Probe (CDP-2) 
This image has been removed due to copyright restri cti
ons.
Please see the "Cloud Imaging Probe" image on page:
http://dev.dropletmeasurement .
com/p
roducts/airborne .
This image has been removed due to
copyright restrictions.
Please see the "Ultra-High Sensitivity Aerosol
Spectrometer" image on page: http://dev.
dropletmeasurement.com/products/airborne .
This image has been  removed due
to copyright rest ri
ctions.
Please see the "Passive Cavity Aerosol" image
on page: http://dev.dropletmeasurement.
com/products/airborne .
27</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>PCVI - Pumped Counter flow Virtual Impactor  
add pump 
Fluid flow velocity characteristics during passage through the PCVI 
Kulkarni et al AST 2011 This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see Figure 3 on page:
http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/ 02786826.2010.539291 .
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see Figure 4 on page:
http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/02786826.2010.539291 .
28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Drop freezing technique 
Cold metal plate  CCD  
Camer
a 
130 drops  
(1l; 0.8mm diameter)  
33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Influential Results 
Murphy et al. Science 1998 
9
0.3
0.2
0.1
0.0
0.30.4
0.2
0.1
0.0
0 20 40 60 80 100 1200 20 40 60 80 100 120O-
S-HSO 4-
HSO 3-
SO3-SO4-
H34SO4- OH-
OH-C2-
CHO2-
C2H2O-
O-H-C2H5CO2-
CH3CO2- SO4- 79Br- 35Cl-A
B19980507 #6672
19 km: 31oN
q=437 K
19980501 #1120
14.6 km: 22oN
q=360 KDetector Signal (mA) Detector Signal (mA)
Ion mass/chargeCN- &amp; C2H2-
SO3-
HSO3-HSO4-
l-CH2OHSO3-
H34SO4-La
Ac Th Pa UCe Pr Nd Pm Sm Eu Gd Tb Dy Ho Er Tm Yb LuH
Li Be
Na Mg
K
Rb
Cs
FrBa
RaSrCa Sc Ti V Cr Mn Fe Co Ni Cu Zn Ga Ge As Se Br
Ru Rh Pd Ag Cd In Sn Sb Te ITc
Re Os Ir Pt Au Hg Tl Pb Bi Po AtMo
WNb
Ta HfZr Ymost many common some rare maybe
He
Ne B C N O F
Al Si P S Cl Ar
Kr
Xe
Rn
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Contrails Other Cloud Types 
Image courtesy of NASA.Image 
cou
rtesy of NASA.
http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Sfc.contrail.1.26.01.JPG.
 Aviationstirling . Some rights reserved. License:
CC BY-SA. This content is excluded from our
Creative Commo
ns 
license. For more information,
see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
 
This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page: http://www.rainb
owskill.
com/wp-content/uploads/ 2009/07/a132.jpg .This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page: https://s-media-cache-
ak0.pinimg.com/736x/76/e3/63/76e363ed61675f5de64f68a
1608197ad.jpg.
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>0 1 Parallel plates 
Ice on walls 
Ice saturation 
Linear temp and vapor gradient 
Nonlinear saturation ratio 
Detector Clausius-Clayperon Relation 
Sarvesh Garimella PhD work 
Making Clouds in the lab 
Spectrometer for Ice Nuclei (SPIN) 
Commercially available from DMT, Boulder, CO Based on Zurich Ice Nucleation Chamber (Stetzer. Lohmann) 
This image has been removed due
to copyright restrictions.Please see: http://www.dropletmeasurement.com/
sites/default/files/pictures/Products/SPIN/SPIN_2.gif .
 sources unknown. All rights reserved. This content is excludedfrom our Creative Commons license. For more information, seehttp://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ .
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Cloud Formation Basics 
"The Atmosphere", Lutgens and 
Tarbuck, 10th Edition Reference Texts 
on Reserve in EPSc Library: 
"Understanding Our Atmospheric 
Environment", Neiburger et al. 
"Meteorology Today", Ahrens 
http://epsc.wustl.edu/courses/epsc 105a/, 
W. H. Smith 
 http://jennyse7en.blogspot.com/This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see: http://www.harding.edu/lmurray/113_files/html/d2_earth%20revised/img037.jpg .
14</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
