<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/2-627-fundamentals-of-photovoltaics-fall-2013/</course_url>
    <course_title>Fundamentals of Photovoltaics</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Physics </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          Background Assessment Quiz
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/2-627-fundamentals-of-photovoltaics-fall-2013/resources/mit2_627f13_lec1_survey/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>0</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
2.627 / 2.626 Fundamentals of Photovoltaics
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 
  
2.627/2.626 Background Assessment Quiz 
 
My background in solar energy (research, industry, business, hobbies) can be 
summarized as follows:  
 
 
I can basically describe how a solar cell operates  
o True 
o False 
 
I can explain what a semiconductor bandgap is to a layperson 
o True 
o False 
 
I can sketch out a pn-junction on a band diagram 
o True 
o False 
 
I can explain the difference between a nanostructured PV device, an thin film PV 
device, and a crystalline silicon wafer-based PV device  
o True 
o False 
 
You are given a .csv file containing a set of numbers (e.g., one hundred rows and 
two columns), describing an x-y function. You are asked to perform a numerical 
integration of this data. What tool(s) can you use to perform the integration?  
o MATLAB 
o Excel 
o Mathematica 
o C++</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
 o Other _________________ 
 
As output from lab, you are given a .csv file containing a set of numbers 
describing an x-y function, e.g., one hundred rows and two columns. You would 
like to perform a numerical integration of this data. What tool(s) can you use to 
perform the integration?  
o MATLAB 
o Excel 
o Mathematica 
o C++ 
o Other ______________________ 
 
 
My home academic department is _______________________ 
 
 
Degree Program (e.g., B.S., S.M., Ph.D., MBA)  ________________ 
 
Number of years in program ______________ 
I describe my core skill set to others as: physicist / chemist / materials scientist / 
mechanical engineer / civil engineer / political scientist / business person / 
other   
 
 
Aside from lecture, I am also interested in (check all that apply):  
o Hands-on lab-based solar cell projects 
o Field trips to solar installations, companies 
o Guest lectures from PV experts in industry and academia 
o Other __________________________________  
 
 For a class project, I am most excited about (check all that apply)  
o Working closely with a PV company, to help address a problem or identify 
an opportunity 
o Preparing a technology prospectus on an emerging PV technology 
o A self-designed project (pls elaborate below)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
 o Other: ______________________________________ 
 
List (up to) three of your desired learning objectives for this course  
 
 
Anything else we should know? (Add your name here if you'd like us to get in 
touch with you  otherwise, this survey is anonymous.)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          Lecture 7: In-class Problems on PN Junction Band Formation and Ideal Diode Equation
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/2-627-fundamentals-of-photovoltaics-fall-2013/resources/mit2_627f13_lec07_prob/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Question #3 
a. Solve for the minority charge carrier concentrations in the quasi-neutral 
regions as a function of position under dark (i.e. non-illuminated) conditions. 
 
b. Solve for the subsequent current density in the quasi-neutral regions as a 
function of position.   
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Question #2 
a. Given the pn junction energy band diagram above, show that anywhere 
within the space-charge region, the following condition holds 
 
       
  (   ) 
 
b. From the above expression, show that at      , the minority charge 
carrier concentration is  
 
  (   )    
     (   ) 
 
and likewise at     , the minority charge carrier concentration is  
 
  (  )    
     (   ) 
 
c. Show that the difference between biased and unbiased charge carrier 
concentrations at the space-charge region edges are 
 
   (   )    
  [   (   )  ] 
 
and 
 
   (  )    
  [   (   )  ] 
 
respectively.   
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
2.627 / 2.626 Fundamentals of Photovoltaics
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>2.626 / 2.627: Fundamentals of Photovoltaics 
In-class Problem Set, Fall 2013 (9/26) 
Prof. Tonio Buonassisi 
 
Please note :  These should be done analytically.     
 
 
Question #1  
 
Current density and electric field in the quasi-neutral regions.  
Fr
om the conditions of quasi-neutrality and surface recombination, show that 
the resulting electric field in the quasi-neutral regions is zero and, subsequently, 
that all current density in the quasi-neutral regions is diffusional in nature, given 
that the pn junction is operating in the low injection limit.   Note:  Current density at 
the surfaces of the quasi-neutral regions can be expressed as  
  (        )    ( )   
where      and       for holes and electrons, respectively.   
 
 
 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
