<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/</course_url>
    <course_title>Good Food: Ethics and Politics of Food</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>Ethics </list>
      <list>The Developing World </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Oppression (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec07/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7: Justice and Oppression</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 2/27/17 
are therefor e inferior . Ethnocentris m mean s an inabilit y  t o appreciat e other s whos e cultur e may 
include a d ifferent racial group, ethnic g r oup, religion, morality, language, political system, 
ec
onomi c syste m, etc. It also mean s  a n inabilit y to see a commo n humanit y and huma n condition 
facing a l l w omen a nd m en in a l l cultures  and societies  beneath th e su rface v a riations  in social a nd 
cultural traditions. 
FROM: http://www.webref.org/sociology/e/ethnocentrism.htm. 
Both individuals and institutions can be ethnocentric. 
5.Systematic Violence  What makes violence a face of oppression is less the particular acts
themselves, though these are often utterly horrible, than the social context surrounding them, which
makes them possible and even acceptable. What makes violence a phenomenon of soci al injustice, and
not merely an individual moral wrong, is its systematic character, its existence as a social practice. (13)
Violence is systemic because directed at members of groups simply because they are members of that
group.The oppression of vio lence consists not only in direct victimization, but in the daily 
knowledgethat they are liable to violation solely on account of their group identity. (13) This threat 
deprives people of freedom and dignity. 
These different faces of oppression can aff ect members of different groups (races, genders) differently, 
and combine to result in what is sometimes called intersectional oppression. 
Haslanger 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 2/27/17 
1. Oppression is objective. It is not a subjective feeling of being trapped. Whether one is
systematically disadvantag ed by a structure is something that can be empirically established.
2. Oppression is structural and systematic. Although individuals may be involved in enforcing and
perpetuating the structure, the oppressing force is the unjust structure. Members of subord inated
groups may also enforce and perpetuate oppressive structures that disadvantage themselves.
3. One is subject to oppression by virtue of ones membership in a group. Oppression involves two
groups in relation to a structure: the subordinated and the privileged. The privileged are those
who (unjustly) benefit from the structure; the subordinated are those who (unjustly) bear the costs.
4. Oppression occurs or is most problematic when ones membership in the subordinated group is
either non -voluntary, o r a central member of ones identity, so exit from the group is not a
reasonable option.
IV. Faces of Oppression (Young 1990)
1.Exploitation : Exploitation occurs through a steady process of the transfer of the results of the
labor of one social group to benefit another.  The injustice of class division does not consist only in the
distributive fact that some people have great wealth while mo st people have little. Exploitation enacts a
structure relation between social groups. Social rules about what work is, who does what for whom, how
work is compensated, and the social process by which the results of work are appropriated operate to
enact relations of power and inequality. (6)
Examples: gender exploitation: transfer of the fruits of material labor to men and transfer of nurturing and 
sexual energies to men. (7) 
Racially specific exploitation: Wherever there is racism, there is the assumption, more or less enforced, that 
members of the oppressed racial groups are or ought to be servants of those, or some of those, in the 
privileged group. (7 -8) 
2.Marginalization : Marginalization occurs when a whole category of people is expelled from useful
participation in social life and thus potentially subjected to severe material deprivation and even
extermination.(9) Marginals are people the system of labor cannot or will not use. (8)
Examples: The elderly, the poor, the disabled. The ha rm of marginalization is not just the material 
deprivation experienced, but also the fact that marginals are prevented from [exercising] capacities in 
socially defined and recognized ways. (9) 
3.Powerlessness  The powerless are those who lack authorit y or power even in this mediated sense,
those over whom power is exercised without their exercising it; the powerless are situated so that they
must take orders and rarely have the right to give them. Powerlessness also designates a position in the
divisi on of labor and the concomitant social position that allows person little opportunities to develop and
exercise skills. The powerless have little or no work autonomy, exercise little creativity or judgment in
their work, have no technical expertise or aut hority, express themselves awkwardly, especially in public or
bureaucratic settings, and do not command respect. (10)
Examples: Non -professionals are powerless relative to professionals. 
4.Cultural Imperialism  To experience cultural imperialism means to experience how the
dominant meanings of a society render the particular perspective of ones own group invisible at the same
time as they stereotype ones group and mark it out as the Other. (12)
Examples: Androcentrism. Heteronormativity. Cisgenderis m. Marginalization in the US of native 
Spanish -speakers and Latino culture. Note also ethnocentrism : 
An attitude that one's own culture, society, or group is inherently superior to all others. Judging 
other cultures by your own cultural standards and sin ce, of course, other cultures are different, they 
Haslanger	 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 2/27/17 
Oppression 
I.Injustice
Plausibly, justice and injustice come in different forms. One form of justice, for example, is distributive. If
we agree to share a pizza, we each pay half (assume we are the same size and are equally hungry), and yet
you take 9/10 of the pie and leave me one slice, that is unfair. Such unfairness, especially when it is
expanded to a broader social context, seems unjust. Another form of justice is criminal justice. If you and
I commit the same crime, but after trials at which we are both found guilty you are sentenced for 1 year in
prison and Im sentenced to 5 years in prison, thats unfair. Another form of injustice is oppression. What
is oppression and how does it differ from other sorts of injustice?
II.Structures and Power
Historically, the notion of oppression has been associated with the idea of dictators and tyrants. The
model of power underlying this is one in which individuals hold power over others and exercise that
power unjustly. Oppression in this sense (let s call it individual oppression , though it may be a group rather
than an individual who is the dominant force) may still occur found in many domains, from
governments to families but it is now generally recognized not to be the only form of oppression.
Another form of oppression occurs in structures and institutions, and so reasonably is called structural 
oppression. The power at issue in structural oppression is not held by an individual but is diffused in a 
system. Consider, for example, a democratic sy stem in which majority rules. In such a system there is no 
tyrant dominating others, nevertheless the majority hold power and can make decisions that benefit them 
and disadvantage the minority. Power is circulated in even seemingly trivial matters, e.g., the design and 
distribution of restroom facilities. 
Marilyn Frye offers a characterization of the phenomenon of oppression in terms of a cage: 
The experience of oppressed people is that the living of ones life is confined and shaped by forces 
and barri er which are not accidental or occasional and hence avoidable, but are systematically 
related to each other in such a way as to catch one between and among them and restrict or 
penalize motion in any direction. It is the experience of being caged in: all avenues, in every 
direction, are blocked or booby trapped. ( Frye 1983, 4) 
Although Frye emphasizes the idea that when one is oppressed, all of ones options are blocked and one is 
trapped , this is not necessarily the case.  Whats at issue in oppression is that by virtue of ones membership 
in a particular group one is subject to a set of structures that cause unjust subordination. The birdcage analogy is 
useful to see how structures rather than individuals may be to blame for ones subordination, it is 
important not to be misled by the analogy. 
III. Group membership
Oppression is structural, and it applies to individuals by virtue of their membership in groups. Is there a
way to make this clearer? It is helpful to view societies as very complicated sets of relations between
people. There are professors and students, landlords and tenants, employers and employees, bus drivers
and riders, etc. Such relationships a part of an economy, which exists within a social -political structure.
For example, without a background system of private property there could be no landlords and tenants;
without institutions of higher learning there could be no professors and students. The nature of such
relationships is defined by laws, institutional rules, and social norms . Oppression occurs when the
relations constituting a social system or part of a social system are unjust and where exit from the
relations is either impossible, or extremely costly for the individual in the subordinate position. To take an
extreme examp le, slavery is oppressive because the relation between slave and master is unjust and slaves
have little or no option for exit. Sweatshops are oppressive because the relation between owners and
laborers is unjust (the laborers are being exploited), and th e laborers have no reasonable economic
alternatives for supporting themselves and their families.
So what can we say about oppression? 
Haslanger 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Industrial Plant Agriculture: Weighing Values? (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec20/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22: Industrial Plant Agriculture</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 May 1, 2017 
Industrial Pla nt Agriculture: Weighing Values? 
1. Terms and Questions 
As 
the textbook suggests, the  current state of industrial plant agriculture (IPA) involve s: 
	 Large farms that mainly raise monocultures using methods of h ighly mechanized production; 
	 Substantial reliance on synthetic herbicides, fungicides, pesticides, fertilizer, and large irrigation 
syst
ems; 
	 Embrace of increasing number of GMOs; 
	 Long -distance transportation of yield and trade in relatively unregulated global marketplace, i.e., 
un
der neo-liberal policies. 
Note that industrial plant agriculture may involve more or less of each factor, e.g., plausibly one would sti
ll have industrial agriculture without the use of GMOs, or where the global marketplace was highly 
regulated. So we might wa nt to distinguish: actual IPA, and ideal IPA. In considering ideal IPA, 
however, we should bear in mind what is actually feasible in the world as it currently exists. 
Here are some questions: 
1) Is actual IPA morally required as t he primary mode of agricu ltural production? 
2) Is actual IPA morally permissible as t he primary mode of agricultural production? 
3) Is it morally permissible to include actual IPA as part of a global system of food production? 
4) What would ide al IPA look like?  Would ideal IPA be morally required/permissible? 
Lets begin by brainstorming some of the morally relevant factors answering these questions. To s tart 
(lets elaborate each , considering both +/ -): 
	 Global hunger/famine 
	 Environmental degradation /sus tainability 
	 Health impacts of s ynthetic pesticides (etc.) 
	 Economic justice 
	 Well -being of future generations (im posing risks) 
	 Regulatory interventions and state responsibilities, e.g., for education, solving coordination 
probl
ems. 
	 Human rights to procreate, to engage in local cul tural practices and traditions, etc. 
As the textbook introduction to the issues makes clear, there are both emp irical questions and normative 
questions to consider. But even if we cant completely settle the empirical questions, we should also 
consider the risks involved. 
2. Future Generations and the Identity Problem 
A major challenge in weighing the factors at stake is how to take risk into account, i.e., how to make a mor
al decision under conditions of substantial uncertainty. Another is how to consider the impact on 
future generations.  Lets consider the latter in a b it more detail by exploring the non -identity problem.  It 
is usually introduced with a version of this example: 
Pregnancy Choice: A couple is deciding whether or not to conceive a child. The doctor tells them that, 
due t
o a medication the woman is currently taking, if they conceive now, the child will suffer a medical 
condition that will sometimes cause a mild discomfort and a premature death at 40. However, if she stops taking the medicati on and waits a month for it to clear her system before conceiving, she will conceive a 
healthy child who can be expected to live an average lifespan. Either way, the childs life will (as a whole) be a life worth living.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food May 1, 2017 
What should she do? Most people s ay t hat she should wait a month. Why? 
Note, however, that if the woman had waited a month before conceiving, she would have conceived a 
dif
ferent child. In other words, the unhealthy child would not have existed if the woman had waited 
another month to co nceive. So, the two alternatives for the unhealthy child are either (a) a good life that is 
cut short, or (b) no life at all. Surely a good life that is cut short is better than no life at all. So, it seems that 
the woman has not harmed the unhealthy chi ld by deciding not to wait a month before conceiving. 
Notice that a similar argument can be developed regarding environmental degradation (see FES, p . 423).1 
Let Depletion be a set of policies that makes our lives better in the present but at the cost o f making 
the lives of future people significantly worse. (423) 
1. Depletion does not make future generations worse off than they otherwise would have been. 
2. An act harms someone if and only if it causes them to be worse off than they otherwise would hav e 
been. 
3. Therefore, depletion does not harm future generations. 
4. Depletion benefits presently existing people, and harms no one. 
5. Any action that harms no one, and benefits some, is not wrong. 
6. Therefore, depletion is not wrong. 
Notice the co nflicting principles that seem to be at issue here: 
A. An act can be wrong only if it makes someone (presently existing, or someone in the future) worse off. 
B. Making it the case that someones life is not ideal, but is still better than not exi sting at all, is not a way 
of harming them or making them worse off. 
C. In some cases we do wrong, even if we dont make someone worse off. More generally, some possible 
sce
narios are morally worse than others, even though there is no one for whom tha t scenario is worse. 
Which principle (A, B, C) would you reject? 
1 See also the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy article on the Non -Identity Problem, and Chad Vances handout 
here: http://rintintin.colorado.edu/~vancecd/phil3140/nonid.pdf</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
  
  
  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
  
  
  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Food and Social Meaning (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec09/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9: Food and Identity</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 3/6/17 
skills than those who dont, have their time constrained in differen t ways, and find support and 
companionship amongst those who have similar responsibilities. 
3.Why food?
1.Why does food carry such significance?
a.[Claude Levi -Straus s] has proposed that the place of eating and drinking in myths and
rituals provides the medium whereby people may express their conviction that they are
civilized and human, rather than savage and animal. (Murcott 1982, 204; see also p.
209) Is this a helpful analysis?
Raw 
Rotten 
 Cooked 
b.How does food help us draw boundaries between us and them? What kinds of
boundaries, e.g., ethnic, class, gender?
2.Do food ch oi ces provide a way to express your identity ?  What aspects of your identity? Would it
be difficult for you to give up certain foods? Does social meaning play a role in that at all? Would
it be difficult for you to give up certain practices or tra ditions involving food?
3.In what contexts do we expect others to modify their social practices involving food to conform to
a cer t
ain 
understanding of what is good, proper, healthy, fitting with their/your identity, etc?
4.Individual and social meaning s: eth i cal questions?
What something means to you, to an ind ividual, may not always correspond to its social meaning.
Consider the Budapest cab example. Sometimes we are ignorant of the social meaning. Sometimes wedont care about the social meaning. Sometimes the social meaning and personal meaning exist happily
together.
Questions to consider: 
1.How do w 
e determine what the meaning of someones (including our own) action is?
2.When are you morally responsible for symbolic meanings (insults, encouragement, etc) you didnt
inten d
?
3.Wha
t is our responsibility for the material consequences (intended or not) of our actions?
4.How are social meanings changed?
Refe r
ences:
 
Lessi g
, Lawrence. 1995. The Regulation of Social Meaning. The Uni v ersity of Chicago Law Review 62(3):
 
943-1045.
Levi-Strauss, Claude. 1975. The Raw and the Cooked. New York: Harper and Row.
Haslanger 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 3/6/17 
Food and Social Meaning 
1.Social meanings
Foods themselves can be seen to convey a range of cultural meanings; [they] communicate
information in terms not only of occasion but also social status, ethnicity and wealth. These meanings,
however, are not inherent in foodstuffs. They depend on the social context in which the items are
found.  (Murcott 1982, 203)
The preparation and consumption of food provides, moreover, a material means for expressing the
more abs
tract significance of social systems and cu ltural values. It may be argued that what people are
prepared to take inside their bodies reflects their social identities, and their membership of socialgroups. To view eating habits as 
a matter of culture is to understand that they are a product of code s of conduct and the
structure of social relationships of the society in which they occur. (Murcott 1982, 204)
Food, then, has both a material and a symbolic significance. (Murcott 1982, 204  my ita l ics)
Lets start with obvious cases in which something has me a ning: language and conventional signs. Written 
language is a set of marks, but what the marks mean depends on the context, e.g., what does fin mean? In English it means an appendage on a fish; in French it means end. A flat red octagonal shap e means 
stop in many cultures.  When we learn the meaning, we learn, and typically internalize, a set of apt responses. In the case of conventions, the learning is often explicit. But we also learn many meanings 
implicitly. 
Social meanings are not just a matte r 
 of intention. 
Seatbelts in a Budapest cab. Because most cabs in Budapest are quite small, most passengers sit in the 
front seat. Until about two years ago, if you tried to put on a seatbelt in the front seat of a cab, the 
driver would try to dis suade you. If you nonetheless insisted and buckled your belt, your action would 
have an important effect: To wear a seatbelt was to insult the driver. That insult is a social meaning. 
(Lessig 1995, 952) 
2.Symbolic significance and material significance
We use objects, our bodies, our clothing, our children to convey messages all the time. Symbo l ic significance
is a matter of what is expressed based on the conventions, codes, social meanings, in the context.  Not
everything conveys meanings, and not all meanings are easily recognized. And they are not fixed or
stable: they can be contested, changed, etc. Semiotics is the study of such symbolic meanings.
The material significance of a c ode concerns the social framework that gives rise to it and the consequences it 
has for that social framework. The Murcott reading discussed the cooked dinner. The cooked 
dinner has a symbolic significance; it conveys a message: 
I think it lets him know that I am thinking about him -as if he k nows I am expecting him. Fair play, 
hes out all day -its not as if hes been very demanding -its really a pleasure to cook for him. (Murcott 
1982, 209) 
But it also has material conditions and consequences: 
The nature of the dinner, its mode of preparation, demand that the woman be in the kitchen for a 
require d 
time before [the husbands] homecoming- and that not too infrequently, even daily, she has 
been shopping. Otherwise, the cooked dinner, visibly composed of appropriate items, could not be 
ready on time. If a job defines how a man occupies his time during the working day, to which the 
wage packet provides regular testimony, prop er provision of a cooked dinner testifies that the 
woman has spent her time in correspondingly wifely fashion. (Murcott 1982, 208 -9) 
The cooked dinner not only expresses a meaning, but is possible only within a particular social context 
where wo m
en, on the whole, play a different role in the home and workplace, and it reinforces that 
division of labor insofar as those responsible for preparing the cooked dinner come to have different 
Haslanger 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Environmentalism (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23: Environmentalism</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 5/3/17  Rose Lenehan
Most important claims from this paper: 
(1) Ecosystems are valuable as means but not ends
(2) Various natural states  being good or bad makes sense only by reference to human lives
(3) [Therefore] environmental goals need to be balanced with other human needs
Its possible to reject  claims (1) and (2 ) while keeping (3) .
Further reading: 
Annie Dillard, Pilgrim at Tinke r Creek 
Elizabeth Kolber t, The Sixth Extinction 
Jonathan Franzen, Carbon Capture: Has climate change made it harder for people to care about 
conservation?&lt; http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2015/04/06/carbon-capture &gt;
Aldo Leopold 
John Muir 
Edward Abbey 
&lt; http://www.friends-bwca.org/issues/sulfide-mining/ &gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food   5/3/ 17  Rose Lenehan 
   
II. William Baxter, People or Penguins: The Case for Optimal Pollution   
Plant life &amp; animal life are valuable only as means to human ends.  
 
Conservationists often say things like the following: The use of DDT in food production is 
causing damage to the penguin population.  The scientific fact is often asserted as if the correct 
implication that we must stop agricultural use of DDT followed from the mere statement of 
the fact of penguin damage. (481) 
 
For Baxter, Penguins are important because people enjoy seeing them walk about rocks; and 
furthermore, the well-being of people would be less impaired by halting use of DDT than by 
giving up penguins. [M]y observations about environmental problems will be people-oriented, 
as are my criteria. I have no interest in preserving penguins for their own sake.  (481) 
 
Baxter says position is the only tenable starting place for analysis  because (481-482): 
1. Most people really think and act this way. 
2. This attitude doesn t portend any massive destruction of animal and plant life because 
people depend on them in obvious ways and they will be preserved because and to the 
degree that humans do depend on them.  
3. What is good for humans is in many respects good for penguins and pine trees. Humans 
are surrogates. 
4. I do not know how we could administer any other system; decisions are either private or 
collective. Plant &amp; animal life cannot participate in decision-making processes. [What 
about e.g. infants &amp; small children?] 
Many of the more extreme assertions that one hears from some conservationists amount 
to tacit assertions that they are specially appointed representatives of sugar pines, and 
hence that their preferences should be weighted more heavily than the preferences of 
other humans who do not enjoy equal rapport with nature.  The simplistic assertion that 
agricultural use of DDT must stop at once because it is harmful to penguins is of that 
type. (482) 
[I am the Lorax, I speak for the trees! ] 
5. If animal &amp; plant life are to be regarded as ends rather than means, someone must tell me 
how much each one counts and how these life forms are to be permitted to express their 
preferences. 
6. Questions of ought  are unique to the human mind and world they are meaningless as 
applied to a nonhuman situation. I reject that we ought  to respect the balance of nature  
unless the reason for doing so, express or implied, is the benefit of man. [Consider 
examples from Wenz paper] 
 
 Which of these seems most important? 
 Can we dismiss any of them?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
  
  
  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
  
  
  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 5/3/17   Rose Lenehan
Environmentalism 
Are we obligated to help preserve ecosystems and species for their own sakes, or only when &amp; 
because doing so is best for humans? What values should guide our interaction with the natural 
world? 
I. Intro  BWCA &amp; Twin Metals Minnesota
Twin Metals Minnesota  said the rejection will have a devastating impact on the future
economy of the Iron Range and all of Northeast Minnesota, eliminating the promise of 
thousands of good-paying jobs and billions of dollars in investment in the region. 1
II. Peter Wenz, Ecology and Morality 
We have a prim a facie obligation to protect healthy ecosystems irrespective of all possible
advantages to human beings . (595)
When soil loses fertility, or washes away faster than it forms, and when water systems
exhibit abnormal floods and shortages, the land is sick . (Leopold quoted at 596)
A healthy ecosystem consists of a great diversity of flora and faunain a relatively 
stable balance, evolving slowly rather than changing rapidly, because its diversity enables 
it to respond to change in a flexible manner that respects the system s integrity. In all of
these respects a healthy ecosystem is very much like a healthy plant or animal.  (596)
The obligation in question is not to preserve ecosystems from every and any threat to
their health and existence. Rather, the obligation for which I am contending is to protect 
ecosystems from oneself.  [This is important: The negative duty not to cause harm seems
stronger than the positive duty to bring aid.] (597) 
Wenz seems to think that plants, animals, and ecosystems can be healthy or ill; their interests can 
be furthered or hindered; and in virtue of that, they are to be treated as ends rather than means.  
The prima facie obligation to protect healthy ecosystems might come from the: 
-Duty not to destroy needlessly
-Duty not to destroy things of aesthetic value
-Duty not to destroy things that are good of their kind (so long as good of its kind is not bad in
itself)
Need the concept of destruction apply here?
Which of the three grounds for the duty seems most plausible?
1 https://www.nytimes.com/2016/12/15/us/boundary-waters-minnesota-mining.html</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food   5/3/ 17  Rose Lenehan 
   
Lets focus on #6.  There is no right  or  morally correct  state of nature to which we 
should return.  
From the fact that there is no normative definition of the natural state, it follows that there is no 
normative definition of clean air or pure water hence no definition of polluted air or of 
pollution except by reference to the needs of man. (483) 
 
 Notice that Wenz and Leopold seem not to share this view. 
 
 Is it not tragic or horrible for animals and ecosystems  when natural disasters kill them? 
What effects on animals are morally relevant? [They suffer; they feel emotion; they go 
extinct]  Is it tragic that ecosystems are destroyed only because animals will suffer &amp; go 
extinct, or for further reasons?  
 
Baxter concludes that in making decisions that have environmental consequences we need to be 
at all times thinking in terms of the costs to humans, and whether resources are being used 
efficiently to meet various human needs. 
 
(Questionable claims/concepts in bold!) 
 
[So o]ur objective is not pure air or water but rather some optimal state of pollution. [A 
level of pollution at which humans flourish not none, because we are better off with some 
of the things that cause pollution.] Low levels of pollution contribute to human satisfaction 
but so do food and shelter and education and music. To attain ever lower levels of 
pollution, we must pay the cost of having less of these other things.  (483) 
 
Resources are limited. Even the most efficient use of them will yield less than our 
population, in the aggregate, would like to have .  (484) 
 
A new dam requires x hours of labor, y tons of steel and concrete, and z amount of capital 
goods If these resources are devoted to the dam, then they cannot be used to build 
hospitals, fishing rods, schools, or electric can openers.  That is the meaningful sense in 
which the dam is costly.  (484) 
 
Trade-off by trade-off, we should divert our productive capacities from the production of 
existing goods and services to the production of a cleaner, quieter, more pastoral nation up 
toand no further than the point at which we value more highly the next washing machine 
or hospital that we would have to do without than we value the next unit of environmental 
improvement that the diverted resources would create.  (485) 
 
 How much of the badness of the environmental destruction we re wreaking is a matter of 
the horrible effects it is having and will have on other humans [theft of resources as well 
as destruction of way of life] and how much is a matter of other reasons? [species 
extinction, destruction of beautiful landscapes, etc.]</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Animal Liberation and Moral Community (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16: Speciesism</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 3 April 2017 
that all men are created [with] equal [intelligenceetc.], for that would be clearly false.  Instead it is 
claiming that the well -being of each person is of equal value. Happiness is happiness, pain is pain, 
regardless of whose it is. 
The idea that each persons welfare is of equal value does not entail, however, that we must be treated the 
same way. Va luing their welfare equally will require recognizing their differences and providing 
differential treatment. A system of formal equality is one that guarantees equal treatment in the sense that it 
does not allow arbitrary factors such as race or sex to b e the basis for differential treatment. A system of 
substantive equality aims to demonstrate equal respect for everyones welfare. In order to achieve substantive 
equality, something must be done to address different needs even though it involves differe nt treatment. 
Example: access to the break room. 
IV. Animal suffering
With these points in place, we can now turn to Singers argument supporting the equality of animals.
1.The capacity to suffer (experience pleasure and pain) is the basis for equal consideration in a moral
commun i
ty. (3 56) 
2.Someone is granted equal consideration just in case their welfare counts equally to others regardless of
what t h
ey are like or what abilities they may possess, though what form our consideration should 
take m ay vary according to the characteristics of those affected. ( 354) 
3.Non-human animals have the capacity to suffer. ( 354)
4.Ther e
fore, the welfare of non -human a ni mals should count equally to the welfare of humans. ( from 1-
3) 
5.Therefore, we should make as mu ch effort to avoid causing pain and suffering to non -human animals
as we do to avoid causing pain and suffering to humans, taking into account the different ways that 
sentient beings can suffer. ( from 4) 
6.Therefore, we should make radical cha nges in o ur treatment of animals that would involve our diet,
the farming methods we use, experimental procedures in many fields of science, our approach to 
wildlife and to hunting, trapping and the wearing of furs, and areas of entertainment like circuses , 
rodeos, and zoos. (from original , see footnote 2 ) 
Steinbocks Objection 
Certain capacities, which seem to be unique to human beings, entitle their possessors to a privileged position i 
n the moral community. (401) These capacities include: responsibi lity for action, moral 
autonomy, capacity to reciprocate, ability to be motivated by altruism and moral concern, and a desire for self-respect. It is true that we would not tolerate a hierarchical society based on a degree of intelligence or 
cognitive cap acity. But a minimal level of intelligence can be used as a cut -off point (402) for moral 
consideration. This does not entail that we must treat humans with limited capacities with less respect 
and consideration, because we have special duties and spec ial feelings towards them that we dont have 
towards non -human animals. 
Questions: Do we really have special duties t o memb e
 rs of our species, as a group. that we dont have toward members
of other species. What are these duties and how do they justify speciesism?
Is it really the capacity to suffer that entitles one equal consideration, or is it other higher -level ca p acities
that food -animals and experimental animals dont have. If the latter, how do we justify the idea that we
should treat humans without these higher -level capacities with greater respect than non -human animals?
It is difficult to compare the suffering of non -human a ni mals and the suffering of humans, since we cant
talk to non -human animals. Might it be that the happiness brought about by wearing a fur coat
outweighs the suffering of the animals that were killed to make it?
Haslanger 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 3 April 2017 
Animal Liberation and the Moral Community 
1)What is our immediate moral community? Who should be treated as having equal moral worth?
2)What is our extended moral community? Who must we take into account morally speaking?
3)How does a thing get into our moral community? What entitles it to moral consideration?
I.Our moral community
The notion of rights applies best within our immediate moral community. Its not just that we must
treat in s
iders  with respect; they are owed that respect because of th eir moral status, .
Inner circle (a): entitled to 
full set of rights, based on 
[their capacities, intrinsic 
value?]. Outer circles (b), (c): entitled 
to modified sets of rights 
based on?. 
The moral community 
What about: non -human 
animals, fetuses, infants, brain -
damaged &amp; mentally ill adults? Outside our moral community 
but still valuable? 
On what basis do things qualify as belonging in (a), i.e., the inner circle? One possible answer1: full critical 
self-awareness; the ability to manipulate complex concepts and to use a sophisticated language; and the 
capacity to reflect, plan, deliberate, choose, an accept responsibility for acting (182). These belong in (a) because they are or could be full moral agents. Animals are not included. Space aliens with sufficient 
cognitive capaci ties might be included.  What about fetuses?  Infants?  Brain damaged adults?  Human 
beings in comas or seriously senile? 
Let us say, then, that although underdeveloped or deficient humans are also, like animals, not full 
members o f 
the moral community b ecause they lack autonomy, they must nevertheless fall within 
the most immediate extension of the moral community and as such are subject to its protection. 
(Fox, 189) 
So it seems that on his view, they fall within (b). Why? It cannot be because they wil l develop t he full 
range of capacities distinctive of autonomy, because they may not. Rather, he suggests sympathy with the 
idea that we are connected to them via a chain of love and concern (189).  But the question isnt 
whether we happen to feel more concern for a suffering infant or brain damaged adult than a suffering 
puppy or elephant, its whether we should feel more concern for one than the other.  What are our actual 
moral responsibilities here, and why? Is it OK simply to destroy creatures who l ack autonomy, or cause 
them to suffer?  Is it OK simply to destroy ecosystems? 
1 See, e.g., Mic hael Allen Fox, The Moral Community, in Hugh LaFollette, Ethics in Practice . Oxford 2006. 
Haslanger 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 3 April 2017 
V.Animal killing
Singer acknowledges that the question of killing animals is more complicated than the question of causing
pain. Hum
an lives are very diffe rent from non -human lives. Humans are capable of self -awareness,
planning, complex social relationships, and the like, that make for goods over the span of a life that arenot available to non -human animals. To kill a human is to put an end to distinctiv ely human goods. So
killing a human is worse than killing an animal, and if there is pressure to choose between killing a humanand killing a non -human animal, it would usually be permissible to kill the animal.
Acknowledging this, however, Singer maintai ns
3: 
To avoid speciesism we must allow that beings who are similar in all relevant respects have a simila r 
right to life and mere membership in our own biological species cannot be a morally 
relevant criterion for this right. (Si nger All Animals are Equal , 357 ) 
So Singer is willing to hold that killing animals should be treated as comparable to killing babies with 
serious b
irth defects or killing someone in a state of advanced senility. Whether or not that is ever justified 
is an open question.  
In other words, Singer thinks that his approach to animal rights helps us understand that the moral 
boundary w
e should respect is not the boundary between humans and non -humans, but between beings 
with certain capacities and others without them. Some humans lack the full spectrum of normal human 
capacities; some non -human animals have capacities that significantly overlap ours. The capacity to 
suffer is one that unites us with non -humans in a moral community; complex intellectual and emotional 
capacities divide h umans into smaller sub -groups. As Singer sees it, these broader and narrower 
groupings are the morally relevant ones. Instead most of us are making the serious error of treating the 
boundaries of our species as the boundaries of our moral community. 
Ques tions: 
Is it p e
rmissible to kill plants? Must we all become fruitarians?
Isnt it natural for animals to kill and eat animals of other species? If so, then why shouldnt we do the
same? W h
at is the relationship between whats natural and whats mo rally required?
Isnt there something especially valuable about all humans, even if in particular cases they cant
manife s
t the full range of human capacities? How should we understand the notion of human dignity
or human worth?
3 Applied Ethics: Critical Concepts in Philosophy , vol 4, ed. Ruth Chadwick and Doris Schroeder, Routledge 2002. 
Haslanger 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 3 April 2017 
Singer suggests that the boundaries of our moral community are set by which individuals have interests, in 
particular interests based in their capacity to suffer, i.e., experie nce pain. Beings with more complex 
capacities for pain and suffering lie within (a), and those with less complex capacities lie in (b) and (c). 
II.Our obligations to things of value
Recall the distinction between instrumental goods and intrinsic good s: someth ing is instrumentally good if
it is good as a means to some other good.  Intrinsic goods are good in themselves. We can now begin to
clarify this further. Whether or not something is an instrumental good is a matter of how we value it: do we
value it as a means to something else, or do we value it for its own sake? A heuristic to determine whether
you value something instrumentally is to consider: would you still value it even if it didnt have the same
effects?
Intrinsic goods are better cont rasted n o t with instrumental goods, but extrinsic goods. An extrinsic good 
is valuable because of its relation to something else as opposed to some fact about it. A heuristic to bring 
out the contrast is the isolation test: X is intrinsically valuable just in case it would be valuable even in a 
world where there was nothing else. Possible examples (some controversial): 
Valued instrumentally: vaccin a tions Extrinsically valuable: photo of Gandhi, wedding ring 
Valued for its own sake: pleasure Intrinsica lly valuable: health, happiness 
We now need another distinction between conferred and unconferred goods. Something has conferr ed va lue
 
just in case it is valuable because someone values it. Something has unconferred value just in case it has
 
value regardl ess of whether or not it is valued. Note that if things have conferred value, they are 
extrinsically valuable. (Can things be extrinsically valuable without that value being conferred?)
 
Value conferred: money
 
Value unconferred: honesty, courage (moral vir tue, generally)
 
Questions to consider:
 
i) Is an y
thing intrinsically good that is not good for humans?
ii) Is all value conferred (by humans)?
Definitions and possible principles:
Pro Tanto obligation (only s o  far obligation) also sometimes called a prima facie obligation (at first glance
obligation): an obligation that may be overridden by other moral considerations. 
Intrinsic value principle (recall Kants Principle of Humanity): Things wi th intrinsic value should be valued for 
their own sake and not merely instrumentally. 
Possible principle: Becaus e of their intrinsic value, we have a prima facie obligation to avoid destroying 
animals, and healthy ecosystems (of a certain degree of complexity) and what e lse? independent of 
human attitudes towards the m or go o d they may bring to humans. 
III. Equal consideration
Pain, suffering, and death, are generally agreed to be bad things. From a moral point of view, it seems
tha
t the badness of pain doesnt depend on who feels it; its badness resides simply in what it feels like.  As
Peter Singer says, How bad a pain is depends on how intense it is and how long it lastspains of the
same intensity and duration are equally bad2 Although it is morally permissible perhaps even
morally required for me to respond to my daughters pain differently from a strangers pain, in cases
where I dont have such special duties it seems that I should be impartial and respond simply to the
badness of the situation.
Claims of equality are not descriptive claims about equal tal ents, a b ilities, and the like. Rather, they are 
claims about moral worth and respect. It is clear that the Declaration of Independence is not asserting 
2 See Equality for Animals. Practical Ethics 1979, Ch. 3. https://www.utilitarian.net/singer/by/1979 ----.htm 
Haslanger 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Politics and Famine (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec06/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6: Famine Relief: Ethics or Politics</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 2/22/17 
Famine Relief: Ethics or Politics? 
I.Ethics or Political Philosophy?
The distinction between an ethics and a political philosophy is the central idea in Kupers critique of Singer.  
Kuper argues that Singer takes famine to be an ethical problem, i.e., one that we should address as 
individuals; instead, he maintains, it is really a political problem and should be addressed by a political 
economy (which charts the causal dynamics of the global economy) , a theory of justice (provides normative 
ideals and principles) , and a political sociology (identifies the roles of individuals and institutions in achieving 
the just ends) . (Kuper, 114) 
II.Sen and Entitlements
Why should we take global hunger to be a matter of politics? Isnt it just about having enough food? Sen 
argues not. Although there are cases of natural disasters and such that call for emergency aid, the 
majority of hunger in the world is chronic, and is not necessarily an issue of poverty, i.e., the poorest are 
not always those who suffer from chronic hunger. Why not? 
Sen suggests that the issue is food entitlements . A persons food entitlement is roughly, the food that that 
person actually has the ability to acquire . (52) There are three elements of the system to consider: 
Endowments  land, labor power, wealth 
Direct entitlements  what can be acquired directly from ones endowments 
Exchange entitlements  what can be acquired from exchange/trade of ones endowments and direct 
entitlements. 
If one owns no land and has no wealth, everything depends on the exchange of ones labor power, or 
what one earns from the exchange of labor power. The actual command over food that different 
sections of the population can exercise depends on a set of legal and economic factors, including those 
governing ownership, transfer, production and exchange. It is, thus, quite possi ble for some groups, e.g., 
a particular occupation group such as landless rural labourers, to have a sharply reduced food entitlement 
even the overall availability of food in the economy is unaffected or enhanced. (77) Can you give a 
scenario where this might happen? (E.g., see p. 53) 
Because the issue isnt directly about food production and food supply, but about food distribution and 
entitlements, the discussion of hunger has shifted to the issue of food security , where food security is 
understood pr imarily as a matter of how reliably people have the actual ability  physically and 
economically  to acquire proper nutrition . (54) 
III.Cosmopolitan ism?
In his book Cosmopolitanism, Kwame Anthony Appiahs discusses several principles relevant to our global
responsibilities :
Global Community Principle : We belong to a global community and have [moral] obligations to all other 
humans. 
Cultural Equality Principle: Cultures organize themselves in different and (mostly) in equally valuabl e ways, 
with different and (mostly) equally valuable practices. 
On Appiahs version of cosmopolitanism , a kind of partiality towards ones family and compatriots is 
permissible: 
Individual Partialism: It is morally permissible in deciding how to act to be somewhat partial towards ones 
near and dear, and to conform ones behavior to the morally acceptable norms of ones society. 
We should distinguish, however, individual partialism from state partialism : 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 2/22/17 
State Partialism: It is morally permissible for a state to be partial towards some proper subset of its citizens 
and to conform its decisions to norms of some sub -groups of citizens over others. 
State partialism is arguably contrary to the demands of justice.  However, st ate p artialism should be 
distinguished from State Isolationism , the extreme version of which states: 
State Isolationism: A state is responsible for its own citizens, and is not responsible for the citizens of other 
countries. 
Singer seems to hold a very st rong form of ethical cosmopolitanism . As Singer puts it in his reply to Kuper: 
Strong Cosmopolitanism : The interests of all persons ought to count equally [in an individuals decision about 
how to act], and geographic location and citizenship make no intrinsic difference to the rights and 
obligations of individuals. (121) 
It seems that Kuper wants to agree with Singer on strong cosmopolitanism, and their disagreement lies in 
whether we can be good cosmopolitans without relying on political philosophy in order to make the right 
decision. As Singer sees it, the disagreement between them is really about the facts: which course of 
action will make the most positive difference. Kuper suggests that individual action is likely to be harmful 
without a full a ppreciation of social structures and their interdependence. Singer can allow this, though he 
thinks that Kuper is wrong about the facts.  Singer believes that it is very clear that some direct charitable 
giving will make a positive difference, even if it d oesnt solve the problem in the long run. 
What exactly, then, is Kuper asking for (115 -6)? 
1) Appropriate ideal ends. (theory of justice, political economy)
2) Coordination of collective action. (political sociology , politics )
3) Sustainable development st rategies over the long run. (political economy and sociology , also effective
global organizations and policies? )
4) Criteria for distinguishing fair from unfair unequal distributions. (t heory of justice)
5) Realistic limits on our idealism. (political econ omy)
6) Respect for the poor as agents. (maybe relevant to Duflo et al? )
7) Identification of the proper agents of justice and aid: who bears responsibility for the poor? (theory of
justice)
Questions: 
Singer seems to maintain that he does not need fancy political theories to provide answers to these
questions. (1, 4, and 7) are answered by his utilitarianism. (2, 3. 5) are answered by the agencies he
recommends (Oxfam, etc.). (5) is provided by both.  So how do his recommendations fall short?
Kuper seems to hold that state action is ultimately required in order to solve the problem of hunger
relief. Does Singer disagree?
Does Kupers list (1 -7) really address the issue of food security? How?
Does Kuper really endorse strong cosmopolitanism? What should I as an individual do if I take my
obligations to the hungry seriously? Buy clothes from fair -trade organizations?  Go on holidays to
countries that depend on tourism? Lobby my government to give aid? Oppose corporations that are
exploitative of the global poor? Is this enough? Does it take my obligations seriously enough?
Do you think that the issue of food security is just about the facts? Or are there normative moral and
political issue s to be addressed? If so, what are those issues?
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Religion, Virtue and Food Production (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10: Gender, Race, Religion, and &#8230;</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 3/8/17 
right thing, and so forth. The orga nizing claim of vir tue theory is that: 
An action is right insofar as it is the manifestation of a virtuous character trait, where virtuous 
character traits are [those tha t are present in the fully flourishing human being ]. 
The portion of the claim in square brackets is disti nctive o f Aristotles theory; virtue theorists disagree 
amongst themselves about what character traits constitute the virtues. Aristotles further elaboration is 
this: 
Virtue (excellence), then, is (a) a state of character (b) concerned with choice, (c) l ying in a mean, the 
mean relative to us, (d) this being determined by a rational principle, and by that principle by which 
the man of practical wisdom would determine it. ( NE 1106b36- 1107a2) 
On Ari
stotle's view the happy life, i.e., the eudaimo n life, is a life of human excellence.  Human excellence 
consists in the rational activity which best realizes our rational capacities, i.e., the excellence of our 
rational part. Our rational part has two sub -parts: theoretical reason and practical reason. Moral vir tue 
is the excellence of practical reason, but also depends on the exercise of theoretical reason. 
Examples: courage (rather than brashness or cowardice), consideration (rather than sentimentality or 
callousn
ess) 
How do we employ virtue ethics in decidin g how to act ? Note that virtue ethics doesnt say: do this, do 
that.  Rather, it tells us how we should be , what sort of character we should cultivate.  The rough formula 
for action is simple: do what the virtuous person would do in these circumstances.  But how does that 
help? Are we supposed to mimic virtuous people? Yes and no. 
Virtue, i.e., the dispositions or capacities to act and feel in the right sort of way, is something one cultivates 
by habitua
tion. One does not simply decide to have a good ch aracter; nor does one become virtuous 
simply by understanding what virtue is. One must establish in oneself the stable disposition to behave properly. To become virtuous , we must start by acting properly, by imitating the behavior that would 
arise from a virtuous person's state of character. Through repeated practice we develop in ourselves the 
right sorts of dispositions, and along with these dispositions we gain an understanding of our action and its relation to the good. Eventually we not only perfor m the virtuous act, but perform it as a result of our 
virtue. 
From the point of view of some virtue theorists, your relationship to the environment and your food 
practic
es are deeply connected to the sort of person you are, i.e., they c onnect the disposi tion to respect 
the environment, animals, food workers, etc. with other human excellences or virtues .  Rather than 
looking for moral principles that require we give to famine relief or forbid eating meat, they ask What 
sort of person would want to allow som eone to starve? or What sort of person would cause the pain and 
suffering of an animal just to enjoy the taste of bacon? 
III. Virtue and the Environment
We may think it a virtue to appreciate nature. The question is why? Is this defensible? Thomas Hill
sug
gests1:
though indifference to non -sentien t nature does not necessarily reflect the absence of virtues, it 
often signals the absence of certain traits which we want to encourage because they are, in most 
cases, a natural basis for the deve lopment o f certain virtues. ( 10) 
What virtues? 
1)Proper humility , which is  connected to an attitude which measures the importance of things
independently of their relation to oneself or to some narrow group with which one identifies. (15 )
1 See Thomas Hill Ideals of Human Excellence and Preserving the Natural Environment, in Additional Resources on 
Environmentalism on the Stellar site. 
Haslanger 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 3/8/17 
Religion, Virtue, and Eating 
I.Religious Imperatives
Many religions have strict laws about the production and consumption of food. It may seem that these are
arbitrar
y or senseless in this day and age. However, the basis for food restrictions are often deeper than
they might seem on the face of it.  Our relationship with food is so meaningful and pervasive, and also so
connected to everything around us, that it seems to be a manifestation of our way of being in the world,our broader approach to life.
Religion is one of the main ways that cultures have attempted to understand the world and the 
indiv
iduals place within it. It attempts to answer questions like: 
Who am I? Why am I here? Am I the master of my universe, or a small part of something
larger ?
Wha
t is the right way to live? What values should I stand for?
What do I owe to others? What do I owe to the world, t he cosmos ?
Many religions promote an attitude of humility, of care and concern, and of fair ness and justice towards 
others. Many also promote an attitude of mindfulness in all ones actions, respect for ones body and 
mind .  These values have implications for the food system: production (treatment of farm workers and 
slaughterhouse worker, treatment of animals and the environment), distr ibution (treatment of other food 
workers and concern with hygiene), and consumption (what I eat, how much I eat, when, why, and with whom). In other words: 
Food and the regulation of food plays such a huge role in the spiritual disciplinary regimes of these religio
ns because food connects us to every level of being in the cosmic vision  what we eat affects the 
health of our bodies, the sustainability of ecosystems and human communities, the well -being of other 
creatures, and on and on. FES, p. 286. 
Moreov er, for many, religion is central to their identity. 
For some religious people ...acting mo rally is not simply a matter of producing the most well -being 
but, rather, of being a certain sort of person or standing for certain things or siding with God. Suc h a 
person abstains from pork not because of its effects on well -being but, rather, because doing so is a 
way of showing her devotion go God or a way of indicating the alignment of her being with a certain 
vision of the world. Refusing to eat animals is l ike wearing a flag lapel pin or voting for a candidate 
who is sure to win anyway: Its a way of showing support for something. But, in the food case, because our eating practices are often central parts of our identities, showing support for this dietary 
regime over that one is also, typically, a way of showing who you are. Moreover, its value is not reducible to the effects it produces. FES, p. 284 
One need not be religious, however, to think that ones actions stand fo
 r something. There are secular forms 
of this as well. For example, Robert Adams suggests: 
A central part of living well is being for the good and against evils. We face the question how we can be for and 
against goods and evils that we are relatively powerless to accomplish or prevent. One of 
the most obvious answers is that we can give more reality to our being for the goods and against the evils by expressing our loyalties symbolically in action. FES, p. 285 
II.Virtue Ethics
For most of the 20
th century, utilitarianism and deontology were the main contenders within moral
theory.  In the past two decades, however, Virtue T heory has seen a resurgence. Virtue theory is
historically associated with Aristotle who was, perhaps, its most eloquent defender. The core idea shared
by all virtue theories is that moral theory should be concerned with the character of agents. In particular,
it should be concerned with harmony of mind, acting for the right reasons, being naturally disposed to the
Haslanger 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 3/8/17 
2)Self-acceptance (som eti mes treated as part of pro per humility), which includes a full appreciation of the
fact that despite our awesomely distinctive human powers, we share many of the needs, limits, and
liabilities of animals and plants. ( 20)
3)Aesthetic sensibility, whic h is not just an ability to distinguish beautiful from ugly people, but involves
curiosity, a mind open to novelty, the ability to look at things from unfamiliar perspectives, empathetic
imagination, interest in details, variety, and order, and emotional freedom from the immediate and the
practical which, Hill argues, is probably necessary to appreciate the best in human beings. ( 23)
4)Gratitude , which in volves cherishing things that give pleasure.  People who have no tendency to cherish
things that give them pleasure may be poorly disposed to respond gratefully to p ersons who are good to
them. (24 )
Consider also further issues raised in the FES introdu ction to Food and Religion 
Authenticity
Moral Taint
Moral Motivation
Food as Fuel
Farms as Organ isms
Profit
ing from Wrongdoing and Having Others Do Wrong
Hill is clear to note, however, that: 
The appreciation of the environment that provides evidence of these virtues is not merely a matter of
scienti
fic knowledge of the natural world, but requires a certain perspective which is quite different
from being able to recite detailed information. ( 12).  It is an attitude that concerns what one values
as well as what one knows. ( 14)
The connections between respect for the environment and these virtues ar e not lo gically necessary,
but may be psychologically almost universal.
IV.Questions
1.Is there anything wrong with just viewing food as fuel, as a necessary but not very meaningful part of
life?
2.How do we 
determine whether behaving a particular w ay is vir tuous or not? Arent there
disagreements about this? Who is right and how would we know, anyway?3.Acting in ways that are symbolic of virtue is not the same thing as being virtuous, e.g., wearing a flag
lapel pin d
oes not mean one is actually patriotic.  What is the real value (if any) in acting symbolically?
For more information about the Day without Women see: 
http://www.womenstrike.org / 
https://www.womensmarch.com/womensday / 
https://socialistworker.org/2017/02/24/why -were -taking -act ion-on-march -8 
Haslanger 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Food Security and Food Sovereignty (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec08/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8: Food Sovereignty</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 3/1/17 
Food Security and Food Sov ereignty 
1.Continuing discussion of Young, Five Faces of Oppression.
Procedural justice: civil r ights to democratic participation on equal terms, due process, bodily integrity, etc. 
Distributive justice: distribution of important things such as health care, wealth, access to education. 
Principles: what makes for a just distribution?
Extent: Intergenerational justice, global justice
Socia
l jus
tice: justice in social relations. 
Five faces?
Collective self -deter mi nation
Environmental justice: justice towards non -human agents or ecosystems 
New reading, Kyle Powys Whyte, Food Justice and Collective Food Relations, FES. 
2.Elem en
ts of Food Justice
Farm -to-fork conti nuum: Food systems are complex chains of fo od production, distribution, consumption, 
and the recirculation of food waste. (123) 
How do we think of justice within the system(s)? What are the requirements of food justice? ( 92, 123) 
Possi
ble elements: 
a) Everyone should have access to suffic i ent safe and healthy food for an active and healthy life .
b) Everyone should have access to culturally -approp r iate food.
c) Everyone who works in the food system (from farm workers, slaughterhouse workers, grocery store
worker s
, truckers, restaurant servers, garbage collectors/sanitation workers), should be paid livable and fair
wages and work in safe conditions.
d) Everyone should have the opportunity to participate equally and in culturally -approp r iate ways in the
social institutions that shape how the food they eat is produced, distributed and used and how food refuse is
recirculated. (124)
e) The production, distribution, consumption, of food and the recirculation of food waste should occur in
ways th a
t are environmentally responsible and show due care to the land, animals, other societies, and future
generations. (93 -4)
What sorts of justice and injustic e  are relevant in each case?  Why are all of these part of food justice? 
3.Food Security1 
Recall that we discussed in connection with the Singer and Sen articles that achieving food security is not a 
matter of providing foodstuffs, but of providing entitlements. This also addresses the issue Duflo (et al) raise: an entitlement gives one access to a good, but doesnt require one to make use of that access. One might 
forego that access or trade it for something else. 
What are the arguments for (b)? 
4.Food Sovereignty
Whyte argues that food systems are embedded in culture, and in order to respect an individual, we should 
respec t 
their culture. (Culture allows persons to achieve good lives in ways that they could not achieve 
through their individual efforts alone. (125)  It also provides us a context for developing identities and 
1 Information on food security in the US: https://www.ers.usda.gov/topics/food-nutrition-assistance/food-security-
in-the-us/. Glo
bally: http://www.ifpri.org/topic/food-s ecurity 
Haslanger 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 3/1/17 
relations integral to their identities.) To disrupt an individuals culture is to violate their rights and the rights 
of the community to create and maintain a collective form of life. 
Collective self -determination refers to a groups ability to provide the cultural, social, economic, and 
political relations needed for its members to pursue good lives.  Food contributes to collective self -
determination through its integral roles in family and ceremonial life, as a source of nourishment and 
income, as a facilitator of trust and good will in society, as a carrier of a groups heritag e and 
knowledge, and as a vital good that political leaders are entrusted to protect through laws and policies. (125) 
the value of foods is not just that they provide goods such as nutrition, the fulfillment of cultural 
prefe r 
ences, and financial stabilit y. In the case of manoomin, the food is a kind of hub whose value 
lies in how it can bring together many of the collective relations required for people to live good lives. 
(127) 
4.Violations of Food S over eignt y
Se
ttler Americans have pressured Anishina abe t o abandon ricing (economically through commercial
rice production and false advertising, through environmental degradation, destruction of habitat,
appropriation of land, etc.).
These activities are unjust because ricing practices are central to Anish inaabe  cultural life, and Settler
Americans dont have a morally weighty reason for their interference.
oThe fact that others derive benefit from interfering with a groups collective food relations is
not it
self a morally weighty reason to do so. Further more, this morally weighty reason
should be one that the affected group, in this case the Anishinaabek, would accept as alegitimate reason. (129)
food justice not only involves establishing food sovereignty based on establishing a groups uniquefood r ela
tions, but also ensuring that other groups acknowledge and take responsibility for the ways
in which pursuit of their own collective self -determination can commit food injustice. (131)
oThere is an inevitable interdependence between groups within food webs . (1 32)  How
should we enact intergroup responsibilities in relation to diverse groups? (132)
5.Questions
1.What if a groups internal practices are unjust? What does justice demand when there is a conflict
between the groups self -determ ination and sovereignty.on the one hand, and equality and self -
determination of individual group members on the other hand? (111) 
2.What if cultures have developed unhealthy food practices that result in health care challenges that will
place e
conomic and l abor pressure on the national health care network. Is intervention allowed?
3.How do we account for food deserts in urban areas? Are there violations of food sovereignty in these
cases? Wha
t is the best response to food deserts?
Haslanger 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Consequentialism and Famine (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec04/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3: Global Hunger (Consequentialist Ethics Approach)</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 2/15/17 
Note that Singer is not aiming to defend consequentialism. His point is to draw on consequentialist insights about 
morality to raise deep challenges to our ordinary moral beliefs; in particular, he's concerned to show that the line 
we draw between DUTY and CHARITY is misplaced. Here's t he argument: 
1.Suffering and death from lack of food, shelter and medical care are very bad.
2.PREVE
NT SUFFERING PRINCIPLE (PSP): If it is in our power to prevent something bad from
happening, wi
thout thereby sacrificing anything of comparable moral im portance, we ought,
morally, to do it.
This principle doesn't require that we promote hap piness; it simply requires that we prevent bad. It also allows
that we only have to act if nothing comparably important is at stake.
For the principle to avoid collapsing into a maximizi ng requirement , we have to introduce the notion of a
baseline (otherwise, if things are bad simply by being less than optimal , then we'd be required to do everything
a maximizing principle requires).
3.The things we'd have to gi ve up in ord er to make large contributions of money, time, and/or
energy to famine relief, are less important (morally speaking) than life, food, shelter, or medical
care.
4.So we ought to make large contributions of money, time, and/or energy to famine relief.
Furthe
r notes:
What we ought to do is not affected by the proximity or distance of those we're aiming to affect. It may be
psychologi
cally difficult to identify with others far away, and so difficult to care about them, but that's compatible
with its being a moral requirement that I act with their welfare in mind.
What we ought to do doesn't depend on whether I alone or millions of us could equally well help out. One
might fee
l less guilty if others are also shirking --but why should this m atter morally? Am I less obligated to save
the drowning child if others are also watching?
But is the Prevent Suffering Principle plausible? It would seem to require that we make contributions that would 
reduce ou
rselves (and dependents?) to the level o f marginal utility --i.e., that level at which, by giving more, I'd be 
worse off than those I'm aiming to help. This clearly contradicts our ordinary judgments, so would require very strong backing --which Singer doesn't try to offer. Instead he suggests a weaker principle that seems extremely 
plausible. Here are the revised premises: 
2*. MODIFIED PREVENT SUFFERING PRINCPLE (MPSP: weaker/moderate version): If it is 
our power to 
prevent something very bad from happening, without thereby sacrificing anythin g 
morally significant, then we ought, morally, to do it. 
Example: saving a drowning child only at the cost of ruining ones new shoes.
3*. The t
hings we'd have to give up in order to make large contributions of money, time, and/or 
energy to fam
ine rel ief, are not morally significant. 
4 (same as before). So we ought to make large contributions of money, time, and/or energy to 
famine rel
ief. 
Questions for Singer: 
Singer relies heavily on an analogy with refusing to sacrifice ones new shoes to save a dr owning ch ild. Is this
analogy apt? How is this case different from giving to famine relief? What can we learn from the differences?
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 2/15/17 
How should we determine the moral significance of something? Are my shoes morally significant if they bring
me happiness ? If they help me to get a good job that supports my family?
IV.Duty and Charity
The move from the strong to the weak version helps, but it puts added pre ssure on premise (3*)  are the sacrifices
we'd have to make morally insignificant? We tend to distinguish DUTY from CHARITY  what we give to relief
organizations here or abroad is morally optional  were good to do it, but we don't really have to. If we
recognized that aid and assistance to relieve suffering is not morally optional, then our lives would look very
different.
But why should we think that our "luxuries" aren't morally significant? If happiness is morally significant, and 
luxuries
 bring us happiness, why aren't they morally significant? What marks the line between the morally 
signif icant and the morally insignificant?  Singer seems to think that the only thing that matters morally is 
suffering and relief from it  as long as you've reached the baseline for a reasonable life, anything more is morally 
irrelevant.  Is this plausible? I t might seem that a life for everyone at the baseline might be a pretty gloomy 
existence, but is this true?  What does the research in empirical psychology tell us? Singer would certainly ask us to 
look at the alterna tive: some people suffer and die when t hey could be helped, while others luxuriate in their 
riches? Is this a morally acceptable situation? 
V.Lifeboat Ethics
It migh
t be tempting to respond to Singer that the affluent have a right to wha t they have earned and what they
have purchased with wh at they have earned. And no one has a right to demand it be given to them. Lets grant
this for the sake of argument.  The problem is that Singer is not arguing that those dying of starvation have a
right to be given aid (though some others would argue f or that). Rather, he is arguing that even if we have a right
to our wealth, we are doing something morally wrong by holding onto it and not using it to help those who are
suffering and dying for lack of food, water and medical care.
Garrett Hardin offers an argu ment against aid in consequentialist terms. In fact, he claims that not only do we 
have no moral obligation to give relief aid to poor countries, but we are morally obliged not to provide aid. He 
relies on an analogy with a lifeboat. Do those on a lifeboat have an obligation to bring aboard all others who are 
drowning? Hardin says No. The right action is to bring aboard only that number compatible with the safety of 
those on board, for any other action would be to bring about, or at least risk, disaster. He then argues that we 
shouldnt help feed the starving in poor countries because given the patterns of population growth and limitations on resources, like overloading the lifeboat, this will only result in worse consequences down the road. 
Que stions for Hardin: 
Are we cu
rrently in a lifeboat situation? Are rich countries at their carrying capacity?
Does it matter if the lifeboat (wealth) was obtained unjustly or immorally?
Who is responsible for the famine? If we [those in the First World] are respo nsible for inequity in the
distribution of resources, should they [those in the Third World] suffer for it?
Is population growth in poor countries the primary cause of famine? Is it plausible that aid to poor countries
causes pop
ulation growth? H ow does adequate food, education and health care affect population growth?
Is it really better to avoid the risk of a slightly worse disaster [the lifeboat capsizing] by allowing a certaindisaster 
[all those in the sea to drown]?
Suppose we grant that, in the future, m ore will die of starvation if we give to famine relief now than will die if
we withhold aid. What are we to make of all the additional years lived and people born between now andthen?  Many lives will be lost, but many will also be gained.
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 2/15/17 
Consequentialism and Famine 
I.Moral Theory: Introduction
Here are five questions we might want an ethical theory to answer for us:
i) Which acts are right and which are wrong? Which acts ought we to p erform (understanding the "ought"
as a moral "ought")?a.Who is part of our moral community? Towards whom (or what) do we have moral duties and
obligat
ions? (Some/all other humans? Animals? Ecological systems? Androids/computers?)
b.How do moral oughts interact with other reasons for action? Do they always trump other
reasons?
ii) What ma
kes a parti cular action right or wrong?
status?What is it about the action that determines its moral 
iii) How do we know what i s right and wrong?
iv) What, if anything, motivates us to do what is right?
Normative ethi cs: add r esses first- order questions about our moral lives, questions about what morality 
requires/permits us to do, and what is morally valuable. E.g. should we be vegetarians? Is euthanasia permissible? Is it (morally) good to devote oneself to a life of pleasure? 
Meta -ethics: addresses questions about first- order ( n
 ormative) ethical judgments, e.g., about the nature of 
morality; the meaning of moral talk; whether morality is absolute or relative; whether moral judgments can be 
true or false (objective ) or merely subjective, how we can have knowledge of moral truth. 
II.One Normative Theory (to start): Consequ entialism
Consequentialisms whole focus is on con sequences of action. The project is to figure out what is intrinsically
good, e.g., pleasure, happiness, welfare, preference satisfaction, or some other list of objective goods (health,
knowledge, etc.), and then the right thing is to bring that good(s) about or minimize the opposite.
One version of consequentialism is Eudaimo nistic Utilitarianism (eudaimonia means flourishing  in 
Greek) : 
Greatest Happiness Principle : actions  are right in proportion as they tend to promote happiness, 
wrong as they tend to produce the reverse of happiness. (John St uart Mill, Utilitarianism ) 
Or as contemporary mo ral theo rists state it: 
You ought always to act so as to maximize happiness /flourishing , i.e., the right act is the act that 
results in the greatest amount of happiness /flourish ing overall. 
Different forms of consequentialism vary in the kind of consequen ces the y consider relevant, and the kind of 
requirement with respect to those consequences (maximize, etc) .  A template might look like this: 
YOU OUGHT ALWAYS TO A CT SO AS TO [fill in mode of action here ] [fill in kind of 
consequence here ]. 
For example, another consequentialist principle might look like this: 
You ough
t always to act so as to relieve suffering . 
III.Duty to Prevent Suffering
Conseque
ntialism does seem to capture some basic elements of moral thinking, e.g., that conseq uences matter,
and that moral thinking ought to be impartial in how it regards each person's well -being. Drawing on these
insights Peter Singer argues that our obligations to those who suffer are much greater than what we might have
though t.
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 2/15/17 
Appendix: Tragedy of the Commons 
Question: Is it true that if each individual acts rationally to promote their own self -interest, this will result in the 
best for society as a whole? Garrett Hardin argues not (see recommended readings): 
The tragedy of t he commons develops in this way. Picture a pasture open to all. It is to be expected that 
each herdsman will try to keep as many cattle as possible on the commons. Such an arrangement may 
work reasonably satisfactorily for centuries because tribal wars, po aching, and disease keep the numbers of 
both man and beast well below the carrying capacity of the land. Finally, however, comes the day of 
reckoning, that is, the day when the long- desired goal of social stability becomes a reality. At this point, 
the inh erent logic of the commons remorselessly generates tragedy. 
As a rational being, each herdsman seeks to maximize his gain. Explicitly or implicitly, more or less 
conscious
ly, he asks, "What is the utility to me of adding one more animal to my herd?" This u tility has 
one negative and one positive component. 
1) The positive component is a function of the increment of one animal. Since the herdsman receives all
the proce
eds from the sale of the additional animal, the positive utility is nearly +1.
2) The negat ive compo nent is a function of the additional overgrazing created by one more animal. Since,
however, the effects of overgrazing are shared by all the herdsmen, the negative utility for any particulardecision- making herdsman is only a fraction of -1.
Addi ng together the component partial utilities, the rational herdsman concludes that the only sensible 
course f
or him to pursue is to add another animal to his herd. And another; and another.... But this is the 
conclusion reached by each and every rational he rdsman sharing a commons. Therein is the tragedy. 
Each man is locked into a system that compels him to increase his herd without limit -in a world that is 
limited. Ruin is the destination toward which all men rush, each pursuing his own best interest in a s ociety 
that believes in the freedom of the commons. Freedom in a commons brings ruin to all.  
(See Hardin 1968, http:/ /www.garretthardinsociety.org/articles/art_t ragedy_o f_the_commons.html ) 
Also YouTube: 
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WYA1y405JW0 
 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Waste (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20: &#65279;Waste and Freeganism (Gleaning)</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 4/24/17 
Waste 
Some data ? 
	 Crazy Horse Canyon Landfill received the delivery of 200 tons of excess, rejected, or misbagged 
pr
oduce everyday until the landfills closure in 2009. The dump closed because it was full. 
(Bloom 2010, 2) 
	 The average U.S. supermarket pr oduce item travels 1,500 miles before it arrives at its
 
destination. (Bloom 2010, 4)
 
	 If you allow the (unrealistic) estimate that growers of lettuce harvest 90% of the crop, then it is still a 
huge loss. In 2007, the Salinas Valley produced 153,495 acres of lettuce. So that means it left 
to rot 15,350 acres (over 13 million pounds). (Bloom 2010, 5) 
	 The estimate in 2009 was that the US wastes roughly half of its food and 40 percent of
 
av
ailable calories. (Bloom 2010, 10)
 
	 In 1995, th e USDA estimated that milk had the second -highest loss rate of any food item: about 
a third of it isnt consumed. That year, 16 billion pounds of milk were wasted. (Bloom 2010, 10) 
Some reasons to be a freegan? 
	 Many of agricultures ill effects on laborers, animals, and the environment could be reduced if 
we ate what would otherwise be wasted. (Singer and Mason, FES, 223). 
	 Were saving food that would otherwise totally go to waste  pe rfectly good food. ( FES, 221) 
	 Even products that contain no animal ingredients can hu rt animals, when land is cleared to grow 
crops or when oil companies go into wilderness areas to provide the fuel needed to truck the goods around the country. ( FES, 222) 
	 Freeganism is not only about free food. Behind it lies a view about how to live on
 es life, one 
that rejects the priorities set by the consumer society and the lifestyle that results from accepting those priorities.  Because most people see their status as linked to wealth and what they can buy, 
they are locked into working, often un satisfying jobs, to earn the money to enhance their 
status.[Freegans] are doubly free  free from the subordination to the consumer ethos and free 
from the need to work to satisfy their needs. ( FES, 223) 
Haslanger 1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
  
  
  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
  
  
  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Animal Welfare and Industrial Animal Agriculture (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17: Respect for Animals</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
  
  
  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
  
  
  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 4/5/17 
Animal Welfare and Industrial Animal Agriculture 
Recommended:
 
Jonathan Safran Foer The Truth about Eating Animals, FES, pp. 16 -21.
 
Introduction to Industrial Animal Agriculture , FES, pp. 322 -337.
 
Humane Society of the USA, The Welfare of Animals in the Meat, Egg, and Dairy Industries, FES, pp. 
347-352.
 
Questions: 
1.	 What are the best arguments again st the current standard treatment of animals in industrial animal 
agriculture? Are there any plausi ble arguments in favor of the current practices? 
Utilitarian/Consequentialist? (Sing er and Tnnsj)
 
I assume total hedonistic utilitarianism, which is the view that what matters is the total amount of
 
happiness in the world. According to this view, we ought to maximize the total amount of happiness in
 
the world. (Tnnsj, FES 363)
 
My conjecture is that both animals held in captivity and wildlife experience on aver age enough
 
happiness to comp ensa te for [the pain and suffering they experience]. (Tnnsj, FES 364)
 
Kantian? (Korsgaard) 
A human being who lives a life governed only by desires and instincts, not by values, would certainl y 
be a l
esser being. But that doesnt mean that the other a nimals are lesser beings. They are simply 
beings of a different kind. (Korsgaard FES 371) 
The claim of the other animals to the standing of ends in themselves has the same ultimate 
foundation as our own -the e ssentially self -affirming nature of life its elf. (Korsgaard FES 371) 
Virtue Theory? (Hil l?) 
Other? (Re the environment, efficiency, etc?) 
The topic of cruelty to animals, while important from a practical viewpoint, because much of our 
pre
sent treatment of animals involves the infliction of suffering for no good reason, is not very 
interesting philosophically. What is philosophically interesting is whether we are justified in having different standards of necessity for human suffering and for animal suffering.  (Steinbock, 251) 
[Singer] thinks that the principle of equality requires that, no matter what the nature of the being, its 
suf
fering be counted equally with the like suffering of any other being. In other words sentience doe s 
not simply provide us with reasons for acting; it is the only relevant consideration for eq ual 
consideration of interests. (Steinbock, 251) 
2.	 What standards are appropriate for the treatment of non -hum a n animals in the meat, egg, and dairy 
industries, e.g., are free -range egg farms permissible? Other humane f arming practices that 
produce animal products? Why or why not ? 
3.	 What standards are appropriate for animal testing? Managing zoos? Participating in animal 
enter
tainment (circuses, rodeos, Sea World)? Owning pets? Why? 
Haslanger 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Capitalism and the Food System, part 1 (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13: Capitalism and the Food System, part 1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Capitalism and Food 2 
- The correlations between higher weight and greater health risk are weak except
at statistical extremes. The extent to which those correlations are causal is poorly
established. There is literally not a shred of evidence that turning fat people into
thin people improves their health. And the reason theres no evidence is thattheres no way to do it. So saying lets improve health by turning fat people intothin people is every bit as irrational as saying lets improve health by turning
men into women or old people into young people. Actually its a lot crazier,
because there actually are significant health differences between men and womenand the old and the young  much more so than between the fat and the thin.
oAn arbitrary BMI threshold is used to gauge obesity.
But theres no reason to think BMI tracks anything useful.
And people at or near the threshold for obesity are actuallyhealthier than those at lower normal weights.
Most of the reduced health among people at higher weights comes
from weight cycling, or having ones weight yo-yo up and down,
which is a result of dieting.
- In a different (now paywalled) 1999 article in the New Republic, Campos explains
why we obsess about obesity if it is not in fact a health problem: [Americans]
long to believe that medical experts can solve the problem of their expanding
waistlines. The reason for this can be summed up in six words: Americans thinkbeing fat is disgusting. That psychological truth creates an enormous incentive togive our disgust a respectable motivation. In other words, being fat must be
terrible for ones health, because if it isnt that means our increasing hatred of fat
represents a social, psychological, and moral problem rather than a medical oneA rational public health policy would emphasize that the keys to good health (atleast those that anyone can do anything aboutgenetic factors remain far more
important than anything else) are, in roughly descending order of importance:
not to smoke, not to be an alcoholic or drug addict, not to be sedentary, and notto eat a diet packed with junk food.
How does industrys marketing of diet foods look in this context? 
4 Questions 
Do you, as a consumer, object to the food safety system and/or the industry use of food 
science discussed in the readings? Why or why not? 
What are the best justifications industry gives, or could give, for these practices? Are 
they adequate? Would you be willing to participate in these practices? Why or why not? 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Capitalism and the Food System, part 2: 
Science, Safety, and Health 
24.03: Good Food 
Haslanger/Jaques 
22 March 2017 
Last week, we saw that the food system, under capitalism, provides both opportunities 
and incentives for exploitation and other forms of oppression of workers. 
This week, we are looking at ways that the food system, under capitalism, provides both 
opportunities and incentives for behavior toward consumers that may also be morally or 
politically objectionable. 
- Monday, the film showed how involvement of corporations made peoples access
to clean water (much) worse.
- Today, well look at how capitalism interacts with the development of food
products, the food safety system, and issues of health.
1 Food Safety 
In the Hylton reading, we saw that the food safety system in the U.S. is deeply flawed. 
- The governments ability to protect people from contaminated food is remarkably
limited.
oRecalls are voluntary, and its very difficult even to satisfy the
requirements to request one, even when hundreds or thousands of peoplehave been sickened.
oEven when plants fail to meet contamination limits, the regulators cannotrequire that they be shut down.
oThere is a crazy quilt of agencies responsible for food safety, some ofwhom are primarily responsible for things like promoting agriculture, and
only secondarily for food safety.
oOther countries do better; Europe does not have the problems we do, as a
rule.
Is this system morally or politically objectionable? Are consumers wronged by it? Why or why not? 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Capitalism and Food 2 
2 The Science of Junk Food 
In the Moss reading, we saw that a wide range of foods are engineered to be addictive 
to be tasty in the precise ways that cause you to eat more and more, to deceive you about when youve had enough, etcand to get you to eat things, and eat in ways, that maximize profits for the food industry, even if this is very bad for your health. 
- Army MRE research and sensory-specific satiety.- Lunchables: the power of convenience and the illusion of control.- Cheetos and vanishing caloric density.- Reducing perceived harmful ingredients causes people to eat even more.
- Potato chips as the perfectly addictive food, and the measures taken to get
around peoples sense that they should not eat them.
- Coca-Cola increased marketing to the poor abroad when sales fell in the U.S.
It can be tempting to say that people should know that these foods are bad for them, 
and not eat them. Why might this be an inadequate response? 
- Many unhealthy foods are marketed as healthy: see Pollan on the dangers of
ingredient-based food science.
- Industry figures admit their products are like cigarettes, only with worse health
effectsand everyone has to eat. Furthermore:
oFood deserts, the structure of food stores, and economics mean manypeople have very limited choices.
oAs Finkelstein &amp; Zuckerman note, these foods, engineered as they are,become a cheap and easily available source of pleasure.
Are the food industry practices described here morally or politically objectionable? Are consumers wronged by them? Why or why not? 
3 Myths about healthy eating and obesity Pollans how-to-eat slogan: Eat food. Not too much. Mostly plants. 
- What does he mean?
- It looks like every part of Pollans slogan is at odds with the food industry.
oOne example: the food industry tries to convince you that what is needed
for health is more engineering of your food.
oOther examples?
Campos describes how our discourse about obesity is rooted in false claims about health. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Capitalism and Liberty (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12: Capitalism and Liberty</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 3/15/17 
alternatives, when the extraction is only possible because the victim has: an upbringing that has 
habitualized him to the receipt of bad treatment; a subordinat e position in a work- related power 
relationship; or a vulnerable physique in a culture that tolerates rape. Of course, Wertheimers theory has the disadvantage of calling every case in which one person extracts an unfair 
advantage from another an act of w rongful exploitation, rendering Wertheimers theory too 
broad.((571) 
Questions: 
1) Are you acting freely or autonomously when you are coerced? It seems that you are acting of your own 
free will in some sense  you could have chosen to be killed instead o f giving up your money  but your 
liberty is clearly being c ompromised. (See Wertheimer p. 565) Some think that one important role of the 
state is to protect us from these infringements on our liberty. 
2) Are you acting freely or autonomously when you are under duress? Again you are clearly acting of 
your own free will when you choose to enter into a disadvantageous contract, but if others can take 
advantage of the threats that circumstances pose to your well -being, are you free? Do you have the 
libert ies that society should aim to protect? 
2. Negative and Positive Liberty 
Negative liberty is the absence of obstacles, barriers or constraints. One has negative liberty to the exten
t that actions are available to one in this negative sense. Positive liberty is the possibility 
of acting  or the fact of acting  in such a way as to take control of one's life and realize one's 
fundamental purposes. 
(Ian Carter, http://plato.st anford. edu/entries/liberty -positive -negative /) 
An important source of this distinction is Isaiah Berlin. He sugg e sts we ask: 
To determine the scope of negative liberty: What is the area within which the subject  a person or 
group of persons  is or shou ld be left to do or be what he is able to do or be, without interference by 
other persons? 
To determine the scope of positive liberty: What, or who, is the source of control or interference that can 
determine someone to do, or be, this rather than that? (1969, pp. 121 22). 
Some have argued that the difference lies in the site of control: am I being controlled from the outside 
or from th
e inside, or am I in control of my own life? While theorists of negative freedom are 
primarily interested in the d egree to which individuals or groups suffer interference from external bodies, 
theorists of positive freedom are more attentive to the internal factors affecting the degree to which individuals or groups act autonomously. (Ian Carter, op. cit.) 
Questions: 
1) When we affirm our right to life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness, what are affirming? Are we 
being gi
ven the right to negative and positive liberty? What are our moral obligations regarding the 
negative and positive liberties of others? 
2) What qualifies you to having a right to liberty? What about criminals? Do they forsake their right to 
liberty
?  What about non -citizens? Do only humans have a right to liberty (in either sense)? 
3) What is legitimate for the st ate (or o ther agents) to do in order to protect liberty? 
4) If there is a right to private property, what does that right consist in? What are the capitalists rights? 
Haslanger 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 3/15/17 
Capitalism and Liberty : Background Concepts 
This is not a course in economics, political science, nutrition, geography, etc. Many of the readings we do 
make claims about matters in these areas of research. It is always important to read critically and consider 
the evidence for the claims being mad e. This course is focused on moral issues in ethics and politics.  So it 
will be useful to have some background moral and political concepts. 
1. Capitalism 
A capitalist econom y is one based on privately owned means of production and in which goods and 
services are created for profit. There are many different forms of capitalism, depending on the ways and 
extent to which the state is involved in the economy. For example, under laissez -faire or minimal state 
capitalism, there is no regulation of the eco nomy, protections of workers, etc. The role of the state is 
simply to provide police protection, the basic institutions needed for trade, e.g., the printing of money, 
and a legal system for protecting property rights. Social welfare capitalism is a system in which trade is 
(more or less) unregulated, but the state provides some form of safety net, e.g., unemployment benefits, social security, subsidized health care, collective bargaining rights. See Appendix of handout with 
diagram. 
A. Exploitation 
We considered Iris Youngs understanding of exploitation as a form of oppression. She said: 
Exploi
tation occurs through a steady process of the transfer of the results of the labor of one 
social g
roup to benefit another. ( FES 140) 
But is this an adequate definition? There is a steady process by which professors transfer the results of
 
their sch
olarly activity to benefit students, the general public, etc.  Is this exploitation?  It seems not.
 
There do seem to be cases, however, in which workers ar e vulne rable to exploitation. How can we
 
capture this?
 
Capital goods: materia l resources, means of production .
 
Consumer goods: the cool stuff consumers like to buy , and by extension, services they like to have.
 
Marxian model: How do ca pital goods become consumer goods? Labor. The capitalist is the owner of
 
the capital goods and hires laborers to produce consumer goods using them.1 Heres the pinch: the
 
capitalist then sells the consumer goods for a profit. What this means is that the consumer goods are sold
 
for more than the value of the capital goods (including their upkeep, etc) + labor costs.  The capitalist, then, 
extracts surplus value from the [goods+labor ] and pockets it. The surplus value is, some argue, produced
 
by the worker  after all, without the worker the capital goods would not have value to consumers  and
 
yet accumulated by the capitalist. This suggests that in cases where the worker and the capitalist are
 
distinct (i.e., the workers are not the owners of the capital goods) the worker is not paid his or her true value, i.e., 
what the worker actually produces, and so is exploited .
 
But the problem is that workers enter into a contract with the employer and in doing so seems to consent to
 
the
 deal.  The idea is that the contract makes the arrang ement a fair form of coordination: each gets what
 
they bargain for.  And if workers doesnt like the terms of the contract, they can find work elsewhere.
 
1 Notice that in the contemporary context, laborers often contribute more than simply their labor, e.g, they may 
themselves own tools and other means of production and even capital goods, and exploitation can occur at various 
levels. Consider the farmer who sells corn or soybeans to ConAgra. The farmers labor plays a role in creating the 
material resources (foodstuffs) that go into making the consumer goods (packaged foods). If the corporation sells the packaged foods for a profit, then there are several groups of laborers who arent compensated for the value they contribute: the farmer (and/or farmworker) and the factory worker. 
Haslanger 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 3/15/17 
As Wertheimer says in the essay assigned for today, consent is morally transformative.  (561). What does 
that mean?  There is a sense in which consent has the power to change an action from being 
impermissible to being permissible.  It might even change a harmful act into one that is not harmful, or 
may make it illegitimate to complain about something. This is not to say, however, that consent is all that 
is relevant in making an act wrong.  For example, people may consent to being party to actions that are morally wrong on other grounds. (Wertheimers example is prostitution, p. 562.) 
B. Consent 
It seems that merely saying the right words is not sufficient for consent. In medicine we ask for informe d 
consent . I dont meaningfully or validly consent if Im manipulated, or if pressured by threats.  How do we 
determine whats important for valid consent ? Wertheimer suggests that we should look at why consent is 
valuable (564). He suggests it rests on the value of: 
	 voluntary cooperation (because we aim for cooperation that is mutually beneficial?) 
	 autonomy (because w e value each individuals ability to s hape their own life  think of Kant and 
persons as ends in themselves capable of creating value). 
He points out that the value of voluntary cooperation yields a ne gative dimension of consent : you arent 
permitted to force me to do something without my cons ent; and a positive dimension : in giving consent, I 
must be in a position act on my own values that have been formed in response to reasons in a context 
where I can critically reflect on what is valuable. The idea seems to be that Im not (fully) autonomo us if I 
just act in accordance with anothers will, but must make the values I act on my own by reflecting on them 
and endorsing them. 
So what implications does this have for consent? Liberto considers two clauses that might be included 
in an acc
ount of wrongful exploitation that correspond to these aspects of consent. 
Exploitation theorists usually stipulate two necessary and jointly sufficient conditions for an act being one 
of wrongful exploitation. There must be something morally problematic about the gain 
that the exploiter achieves (e.g., the gain is unfair or is motivated by opportunism).  One might call this the Advantage Clause. In addition, there is some predicament that must characterize the circumstances of the exploited persons (e.g., a condition of desperation or a state of being 
without options). I will call this the Vulnerability Clause. ( FES, p. 567) 
Liberto considers how to de
 fine the vulnerability clause by comparing two conceptions of exploitation 
(Ive used W for worker and  E for employer to make the definitions more vivid, but the definitions are 
intended to apply broadly and not just to workers and employers) : 
Valdman s: W is wron gfully exploited by E if and only if E extracts excessive benefits from W under 
conditions where W cannot reasonably refuse, i.e., W must have an urgent need that can only be met by E. 
(FES, 567, 568 ) 
Wertheimers: W is wrongfully exploited by E if and only if E transacts with W to Es advantage in a way that is unfa
ir to W, and where there is a gap between what W agrees to and a normative baseline that is 
set by what two friends would agree to under normal circumstances. ( FES, 568) 
Liberto argues that Valdmans account is too narrow: it is too demanding to say that W is exploited only if 
W coul dn
t reasonably refuse. Sometimes we can reasonably refuse but are still exploited. ( Poor Student 
Renter and Lewd Promotion, pp. 569 -70) But we might worry that Wertheimers is too broad: if we make a 
deal that benefits me because I have some advantages in the situation that a friend wouldnt normally use 
to influence you, am I exploiting you?  Is the normative baseline really set by friendship? 
Liberto sums things up: 
Wertheimers theory has at least three advantages over Valdmans: it can accommodate the 
wrongfu
l exploitation that occurs when an advantage is extracted from someone with reasonable 
Haslanger 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
  
  
  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
  
  
  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Genetically Modified Organisms (GMOs): Good, Bad, or ??? (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec24/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>25: GMOs</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 10 May 2017 
a) GMOs may not be safe. 
b) GMOs are not adequately tested. 
c) GMOs may be environmentally risky.
 
d) The companies and university scientists developing GMOs are not to be trusted . 
e) GMOs are not sustainable. 
f) Resistance to GMOs is politically important way to protest rampant capitalism, globalization, 
corporate greed, the decline of rural communit ies, etc. 
g) Other?? 
Some considerations f or: 
a-b) Many GMOs have been tested extensively; although they are not a testable class, we can test 
th
em individually.  
c) There are ways to regulate the use of GMOs to address risks of environmental impact; n ot using 
GMOs in many cases causes other environmental hazards. 
d) This is too broad a claim  man y companies and scientists are trustworthy. But it is true that 
many are just out to make a buck, including apparently benign companies like Whole Foods. e) This needs to be elaborated, but there is a risk of super bugs and super weeds that are 
herbicide and pesticide resistant. This is a risk for any farmer that relies on a single 
her
bicide/pesticide, and might be managed by deploying a refuge strateg y (FES, 450) in crop 
management (not relying on monocultures and creating space s where insects can find refuge from 
the insecticide). 
f) It will be difficult to feed the hungry around the globe, especially given expected climate change, 
unl
ess we invest i n GMOs. Also, some GMOs can make a huge difference to the health of a 
population, e.g., golden rice. 
g) Other?? 
5.  On what points (if any) do the stakeholders agree and disagree?  ( Find common g round )  
	 Can we use points of agreement to settle disagreeme nts ? 
	 Are there some disagreements that will be intractable? Why? 
	 Should we focus on debates between only a subset of the stakeholders? Which ones? Why? 
6.  How should we det ermine the value of GMOs? ( Identify what matters, any competing values ) 
	 What valu es s hould guide our evaluation of the positions? 
	 Are there shared values to rely on? 
	 If there arent shared values, how might we defend the values we will employ against our 
oppon e
nts values? 
7.  What policy should be endorsed? (Policy) 
	 Based on our eva luation of GMOs, what policies should be put in place? 
	 How does individual preference based on individual values relate to public policy? 
Haslanger 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 10 May 2017 
Genetically Modified Organisms (GMOs): Good, Bad, or ??? 
How do we engage in discussion with others who disagree with us? How do we engage in discussion with 
the scientifically illiterate?  The discussion of GMOs seems especially challenging.  Why? 
To some extent, it is a product of our political culture. There is often little critical scrutiny of the iss
ues within a particular tribe.  For example, just as many on the political right discount the 
broad scientific consensus that human activities co ntribute to global warming, many on the left 
disregard the decades of scientific studies demonstrating the safety and wide -reaching benefits of 
GE crops. 
Both the left and the right (and the center) discard reason when it doesnt suit their politics. (Rona 
ld, FES 451) 
How might we unde rtake constructive discussion with those who disagree with us, or when we are 
uncertain of the right conclusion? 
1. Why are GMOs an issue? (Cla rify the i ssue) 
	 Is the question a matter of individual choice (what should I ea t?) , or education (should GMOs be 
labeled?), or broad policy (should GMOs be banned, or regulated, or ??)? 
	 Is the question about the existing GMO system, or about any GM O system, even under more 
ideal conditions? 
2. What are GMOs? (Agr ee on d efinitions) 
	 Are there multiple definitions? Why? (Do different stakeholders give different definitions?) 

	 Are there terms within the definition that need to be defined? 
	 How do we decide between the different definitions ? 
	 What is at stake in giving a definition? 
For e xample: De finitions from , e.g., Wikipedia: 
A genetically modified organism (GMO) is  an organism whose genetic material has been altered 
using genetic engineering techniques. Genetic engineering , also called genetic modification , is the direct 
manipulation of an organism's genome using biotechnology . 
Biotechnology is g enerally accepted as the use of living systems and organisms to develop or make useful 
products. For thousands of years, humankind has used biotechnology in agriculture, food production and 
medicine.[1] The term itself is largely believed to have been coined in 1919 b y Hungarian engineer Karl 
Ereky . In the late 20th and early 21st century, biotechnology has expanded to include new and diverse 
sciences such as genomics , recombinant gene technologies, applied immunology , and development of 
pharmaceutical therapies and di agnostic tests.[2]. 
3.  Who are the stakeholders in the development, consumption and critique of GMOs? ( Identify the 
community of stakeholders ) 
4.  What is at issue between these stakeholders?  What are their different claims? ( Ide ntify c onjectures and 
disagreements ) 
	 Are there errors and misunderstandings that might be corrected? 
	 Are some stakeholders better posi tioned to have the relevant knowledge? 
Some considerations a gain st (but rememberthese must be evaluated in relation to the issues defined in 
(1)): 
Haslanger 1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
  
  
  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
  
  
  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Flow: For the Love of Water</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1149583/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14: Film Screening</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Capitalism and the Food System, part 2 (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15: Capitalism and the Food System, part 2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Capitalism and Food 2 
- The correlations between higher weight and greater health risk are weak except 
at statistical extremes. The extent to which those correlations are causal is poorly 
established. There is literally not a shred of evidence that turning fat people into 
thin people improves their health. And the reason theres no evidence is that theres no way to do it. So saying lets improve health by turning fat people into thin people is every bit as irrational as saying lets improve health by turning 
men into women or old people into young people. Actually its a lot crazier, 
because there actually are significant health differences between men and women and the old and the young  much more so than between the fat and the thin. 
o
	 An arbitrary BMI threshold is used to gauge obesity. 
But theres no reason to think BMI tracks anything useful. 
And people at or near the threshold for obesity are actually healthier than those at lower normal weights. 
Most of the reduced health among people at higher weights comes 
from weight cycling, or having ones weight yo-yo up and down, 
which is a result of dieting. 
-	In a different (now paywalled) 1999 article in the New Republic
 , Campos explains 
why we obsess about obesity if it is not in fact a health problem: [Americans] 
long to believe that medical experts can solve the problem of their expanding 
waistlines. The reason for this can be summed up in six words: Americans think being fat is disgusting. That psychological truth creates an enormous incentive to give our disgust a respectable motivation. In other words, being fat must be 
terrible for ones health, because if it isnt that means our increasing hatred of fat 
represents a social, psychological, and moral problem rather than a medical one A rational public health policy would emphasize that the keys to good health (at least those that anyone can do anything aboutgenetic factors remain far more 
important than anything else) are, in roughly descending order of importance: 
not to smoke, not to be an alcoholic or drug addict, not to be sedentary, and not to eat a diet packed with junk food. 
How does industrys marketing of diet foods look in this context? 
4 Questions 
Do you, as a consumer, object to the food safety system and/or the industry use of food 
science discussed in the readings? Why or why not? 
What are the best justifications industry gives, or could give, for these practices? Are 
they adequate? Would you be willing to participate in these practices? Why or why not?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Capitalism and the Food System, part 2:
 
Science, Safety, and Health
 
24.03: Good Food 
Haslanger/Jaques 
22 March 2017 
Last week, we saw that the food system, under capitalism, provides both opportunities 
and incentives for exploitation and other forms of oppression of workers. 
This week, we are looking at ways that the food system, under capitalism, provides both 
opportunities and incentives for behavior toward consumers that may also be morally or 
politically objectionable. 
-
Monday, the film showed how involvement of corporations made peoples access 
to clean water (much) worse. 
- Today, well look at how capitalism interacts with the development of food 
products, the food safety system, and issues of health. 
1 Food Safety 
In the Hylton reading, we saw that the food safety system in the U.S. is deeply flawed. 
- The governments ability to protect people from contaminated food is remarkably 
limited. 
o
	 Recalls are voluntary, and its very difficult even to satisfy the 
requirements to request one, even when hundreds or thousands of people have been sickened. 
o	 Even when plants fail to meet contamination limits, the regulators cannot require that they be shut down. 
o	 There is a crazy quilt of agencies responsible for food safety, some of whom are primarily responsible for things like promoting agriculture, and 
only secondarily for food safety. 
o	 Other countries do better; Europe does not have the problems we do, as a 
rule. 
Is this system morally or politically objectionable? Are consumers wronged by it? Why or why not?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Capitalism and Food 2 
2 The Science of Junk Food 
In the Moss reading, we saw that a wide range of foods are engineered to be addictive 
to be tasty in the precise ways that cause you to eat more and more, to deceive you about when youve had enough, etcand to get you to eat things, and eat in ways, that maximize profits for the food industry, even if this is very bad for your health. 
-	Army MRE research and sensory-specific satiety. 
-	Lunchables: the power of convenience and the illusion of control. 
-
	Cheetos and vanishing caloric density. 
-	Reducing perceived harmful ingredients causes people to eat even more. 
-	Potato chips as the perfectly addictive food, and the measures taken to get around peoples sense that they should not eat them. 
-	Coca-Cola increased marketing to the poor abroad when sales fell in the U.S. 
It can be tempting to say that people should know that these foods are bad for them, and not eat them. Why might this be an inadequate response? 
- Many unhealthy foods are marketed as healthy: see Pollan on the dangers of 
ingredient-based food science. 
-
Industry figures admit their products are like cigarettes, only with worse health effectsand everyone has to eat. Furthermore: 
o	 Food deserts, the structure of food stores, and economics mean many people have very limited choices. 
o	 As Finkelstein &amp; Zuckerman note, these foods, engineered as they are, become a cheap and easily available source of pleasure. 
Are the food industry practices described here morally or politically objectionable? Are consumers wronged by them? Why or why not? 
3 Myths about healthy eating and obesity Pollans how-to-eat slogan: Eat food. Not too much. Mostly plants. 
-
	What does he mean? 
-	It looks like every part of Pollans slogan is at odds with the food industry. 
o	 One example: the food industry tries to convince you that what is needed 
for health is more engineering of your food. 
o
	 Other examples? 
Campos describes how our discourse about obesity is rooted in false claims about health.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
  
  
  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
  
  
  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Three Moral Theories (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec03/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2: Moral Theory</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 Feb ruary 13, 2017 
3. Virtue Ethics (Aristotle): foc us is on character. 
Virtue (excellence), then, is (a) a state of character concerned with choice, (b) lying in a mean, (c) 
the mean relative to us, (d) this being determined by a ration al principle, (e) and by that principle by 
which the man of practical wisdom would determine it. (Nich. Ethics 1106b36 -1107a2) 
In simpler terms: 
An action is right insofar as it is the manifestation of a virtuous character trait, where virtuous char
acter traits are those that are present in the fully flourishing human being. 
III. Utilitarianism (a v ersion of consequentialism) 
In developing a theory of right and wrong, utilitarians begin by asking what, if anything, is good i n and of 
itself, something tha t is not merely instrumentally good --as a means to some other good --but is good per se . 
They answer this question by looking at the structure of human desire, what it is that (well -informed) people 
ultimately aim for in action. The idea is that once we understand what this good is, the right act is the one 
that promotes the maximum amount of it. 
So what is the ultimate good? We considered several possibilities in the first section of the course on goodne s 
s (or welfare). Mill, however, proposes that happ iness is the greatest good. Suppose hes right.  It 
would seem then that the more happiness the better --if it is good for me to be happy, it's even better if I 'm 
happy and others are too; and then it seems that if happiness is really what's important, then in order to 
promote the good we ought simply to aim to bring about the greatest amount of happiness. Our own 
happiness is a fine thing, but it's no more valuable than someone else's happiness --it's the total amount of 
happiness that matters. Thinking along these lines leads to the Utilitarian or "greatest -happiness" principle. 
Objections: 
	 What utilitarianism says is right/wrong conflicts with ordinary moral judgments, e.g., promise keeping, 
not puni
shing the innocent. 
	 Utilitarian thinking doesnt respect ordi nary moral distinctions, e.g., between killing and letting die, 
harming and failing to help. 
	 Utilitarianism is too demanding: every decision and every action has to be morally evaluated for its con
sequences. 
	 Utilitarianism is not demanding enough: some time s reasons or motivations for acting seem relevant to 
moral appraisal, not just the consequences; but utilitarianism doesnt care about what comes before the 
action except insofar as it has good or bad consequences. 
Useful distinctions for the utilitari an: 

	 Direct vs. indirect effects. 
	 An actions being right/wrong vs. an actions being praiseworthy/blameworthy 
IV.	 Deontology (Ka ntianism) 
The most important alternative to utilitarianism, historically speaking, derives from the work of Immanuel 
Kan
t (172 4-1804), and so predictably is called a Kantian approach, or sometimes a deontological approach. 
At the core of Kant's ethics is a principle known as the Categorical Imperative (CI) which Kant states in 
different ways. 
One interpretation of the CI is the "You are No Exception Principle. (YANE) It does seem to be ubiquitous 
in m
oral life.  We generally think it is wrong to do something that we know would be problematic if 
everyone else did it too, e.g., cheating on an exam, removing a pollution control dev ice from a car, stealing a 
book from the bookstore. In each of these cases the agent's goals could not be achieved if everyone else did the same thing, so the success of the action depends on making a distinction between what the agent does and 
what other s do. But making oneself an exception this way seems wrong. Kant thought that in cases like this 
there was a sort of inconsistency. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 Feb ruary 13, 2017 
The idea is that in any intentional action, I am implicitly or explicitly acting on a principle of some kind. 
Con
sider two shopkeepers, both of whom are committed to giving correct change to their customers. They 
act, however, on different principles, or what Kant called "maxims": 
Mr. Practical: Whe n I can gain a good business reputation by giving correct change, I shall gi ve correct 
change. 
Mr. 
Righteous: When I can perform a morally right act by giving correct change, I shall give correct 
change. 
In each case there is a generalized form of the maxim of the form: 
Gen
eral Form: Whenever one is ________, he/she shall ________. 
On Kant's view, what matters in evaluating an action is not the consequences, but the principle that is emp
loyed in intending or willing. Two individuals can do the same thing, but one of them do wrong and the 
other right, depending on what they will. Some maxims fail the test, so the corresponding action is immoral, 
e.g., (in generalized form): 
Whenever one has an exam and doesn't feel like studying, she shall copy off of her neighbor's work. 
Pre
sumably we could not all act on this maxim, for i f we are all planning to copy off each other, there will be 
no work to copy! The underlying rationale for an approach such as this is to show that the source of morality 
is in reason or rationality ; those who are immoral are in some important sense acting irrationally . On this 
view, we don't ground morality in God's will, or in the seemingly arbitrary moral codes of particular cultures. 
Morality is grounded in reason itself, and the demands of morality can be discovered through rational 
reflection. 
Objec tions: 

	 It appears in many cases that one can adjust the statement of the maxim so that the problem disappears, 
e.g
., consider the maxim: whenever one has an exam and doesn't feel like studying, and everyone else is 
well-prepared, and she can do it without being caught, she shall copy off her neighbor's work. 
	 In some cases a maxim cannot be generalized, but its failure is not due to moral factors. E.g., consider a per
son who decides to withdraw all his money from the bank as soon as the Dow Jones reaches a certain 
numberx. This maxim would not be one that everyone could act upon, but not due to constraints on morality. 
Consider another formulation of the CI drawing on the "Respect for Persons Principle" (RPP). Th
 is principle 
allows that we can use others as a means to accomplish our own ends; after all, we rely crucially on others all the time.  You rely on your professors to teach you things we serve as a means to your ends of gaining 
knowledge. But these are cases in which there is consent your professors aren't deceived or coerced into 
serving your needs. According to the (RPP), cheating on your final would be wrong because you would be using me (or your TA) as a mere means to a good grade: you would be involving us in a scheme whereby you would get a good grade, but it would be a scheme that we would not or better: could not reasonably  
consent to. 
On this view the Kantian picture has a strong negative component comprising the duty 
 of justice : Don't treat 
others as a mere means. And a positive compo nent comprising the duty of beneficence : As far as possible 
treat others as ends in themselves, i.e., as a rational person with his or her own aims, objectives, goals, conceptions of the good, etc. 
Objections: 
	 It is a difficult and complicated matter to figure out how to help others achieve their own ends. We cant 
provi
de them with everything they need or want. How much is enough? 
	 How is it a demand of rationality that we respect others as ends in themselves (remember that Kant wan
ted to ground morali ty in reason itself)?  What justifies this account of morality? 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food Feb ruary 13, 2017 
Three Moral Theories 
I. Introduction 
Here are five questi ons we m ight want an ethical theory to answer for us: 
i) Which acts are right and which are wrong? Which acts ought we t o perform (understanding the 
"ought" as a moral "ought")? 
a. Who is part of our mor al co mmunity? Towards whom (or what) do we have moral duties and 
obligations? (Some/all other humans? Animals? Ecological systems? Androids/computers?) 
b. How do moral oughts interact with other reasons for action? Do they always trump other 
rea
sons? 
ii) What makes a particular action right or wrong? 
status? What is it about the action that determines its moral 
iii) How do we kno w what is right and wrong? 
iv) What, if anything, motivates us to do what is right? 
Normative ethics : ad dresses first -order questions about our moral lives, questions about what morality 
requires/permits us to do, and what is morally valuable. E.g. should we be vegetarians? Is euthanasia permissible? Is it (morally) good to devote oneself to a life of pleasure? 
Meta -ethics: a
 ddresses questions about first -order (normative) ethical judgments, e.g., about the nature of 
morality; the meaning of moral talk; whether morality is absolute or relative; whether moral judgments can 
be true or false (objective) or merely subjectiv e, how we can have knowledge of moral truth. 
II. The Big Three 
1. Consequentialism: foc us is on consequences of action. 
One version of consequentialism is Uti litarianism (Mill) : 
Greatest Happiness Principle : a ctions are right in proportion as they tend to promote happiness, 
wrong as they tend to produce the reverse of happiness. 
Or as contemporary moral theorists state it: 
You 
ought always to act so as to maximize happiness, i.e., the right act is the act that results in the 
greatest amount of happiness overall. 
2. Deontology (Kant): foc us is on moral rules or reasons. 
Categorical Imperative (version 1: Pri nciple of Universal Law ): Act only on that maxim whereby 
thou canst at the same time will that it should become a universal law. 
Categorical Impe rat ive (version 2: Principle of Humanity ) So act that you use humanity, whether in 
thine own person or in that of any other, in every case as an end withal, never as a means only. 
In more contemporary terms: 
You are No Exception Principle (YANE): "in wha tev er you do, you should act for reasons that 
could serve as acceptable reasons for everyone." (Sayre -McCord, 5) 
and 
Res
pect for Persons Principle (RPP): In all action one should respect others as sources of value and 
never merely as an instrument for on es own purposes. (Sayre -McCord, 7) 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 Feb ruary 13, 2017 
To summarize, on the Kantian view (in contrast to utilitarianism): 
	 The focus of moral evaluation is the maxim or principle implicit in the act, not the results. A good action 
mig
ht have bad results and vv. 
	 Acts can't be ranked on an order of merit. 
	 The theory works well when information is scarce. Utilitarian calculations require a lot of data in order 
to m
ake plausible predictions about consequences.  But because it is usually clear w hen an action would 
use another as a mere means (in contrast to what would promote human happiness overall), a Kantian view doesn't require that we have as much knowledge in order to determine what is right or wrong. 
V. Virtue Theory 
There seem to be thre e co
 mponents of any action: 
a)	 The person who performs the action 
b)
	 The action itself 
c) Consequences that result from the action 
To 
determine the moral status of an action, utilitarianism has us look at (c), deontology (b), and virtue theory 
(a). What matters for virtue theory, more specifically, is the character of the agent. 
For example, suppose your friend is struggling in 8.01 and the course is a breeze for you. Your friend asks 
for 
help with the material. You, however, want to watch Hero es. What should yo u do? According to the 
utilitarian, you should consider the likely consequences: overall it will bring about more happiness in the 
world if your friend does well in 8.01 than if you watch Heroes right now. According to the deontologist, 
you should consider the maxim of your action: helping others when it is of little cost to you is universalizable, and respects your friends ends. Suppose you help your friend, but purely out of moral duty, not because you want to or care about how well your friend does. It seems that you have done the right 
thing, but have you done it for the right reasons?  If you act in this way  so that your desires and emotions 
are disengaged from your action  do you have a healthy moral character? The virtue theorist says no. 
For the virtue theorist the primary question is: how can I live a good life? Aristotle thought that the best life 
wa
s the life of a fully realized human being: a human being who demonstrated excellence in all human 
capacities, e.g., the capacity for emotio n, for practical rationality, for theoretical rationality. This was a life 
of human flourishing. Just as the virtues of a tool (e.g., a pen) are those features (e.g., having flowing ink) that enable the tool to perform its proper function (e.g., writing) , so the virtues of a person are those features 
(kindness, generosity, courage) that enable it to excel as a human being. 
Virtues are dispositions to act in certain ways for certain reasons and with certain feelings. Amy has the 
vir
tue of courage if Am y tends to take the appropriate risks for the sake of important things without 
panicking. Amy has the vice of cruelty if she tends to hurt others without concern for their well -being and 
takes pleasure in it.  Unlike utilitarianism and deontology, virtue ethics cannot give us a formula for deciding 
how to act. Rather, it can only suggest a model for how we should aim to be, what sort of character we 
should strive for: have those character traits that are present in a fully flourishing human being. 
Objecti ons: 

	 Could one be happy or flourish, without a good character? Could one have a good character without bei
ng happy or flourishing? 
	 Arent there some actions that are morally right, even if a non -vir tuous person performs them? If a 
virtuous person does something that has terrible consequences (perhaps unforeseen), wasnt it the wrong 
thing to do? 
	 If we are a novice at virtue, and don't have knowledge of how to act properly, how do we know how to 
bec
ome virtuous? What are the states of character that lead t o human flourishing? Are there a single set 
or are there different ways of flourishing? 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
  
  
  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
  
  
  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Deontology and Famine (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec05/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5: Global Hunger (Political Approaches)</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 2/21 /17 
to.  Why not? Because we are choosing a life based on the value of imparting knowledge. Our choice to do 
this is something of value, and deserving of respect. 
Worth noting: on the Kant ian view (in contrast to utilitarianism): 
The focus of moral evaluation is the maxim or principle implicit in the act, not the results. A good action
might h
ave bad results and vv.
The theory works well when information is scarce. Utilitarian calcul ations require a lot of data in order to
make plausible predictions about consequences. But because it is usually clear when an action would use
another as a mere means (in contrast to what would promote human happiness overall), a Kantian view
doesn't require that we have as much knowledge in order to determine what is right or wrong.
D.Kantian Duties toward s Others
On this view the Kantian picture has a strong negative component comprising the duty of justice :
Don't treat others as a mere mean s. 
You ca nt abuse and exploit people, or treat them as merely things in your way, things to be dealt with, or 
things in
 any sense.  And a positive component comprising the duty of beneficence : 
As far as possible treat others as ends in themselves, i.e., as a rat ional pe rson with his or her own aims, 
objectives, goals, conceptions of the good, etc. 
So granted, we must never exploit, deceive, or coerce others; but it is a more difficult and complicated matter 
to figure out how to help others achieve their own ends .  People are complicated: we each want and aim for 
many things and sometimes our goals are even incompatible. Moreover, in treating people as ends, we must 
be sensitive to human limitation, both cognitive limitations and limitations on our autonomy. Ono ra ONeill 
suggests: 
To treat one another as ends in themselves such beings have to base their action on principles that do not 
undermine but rather sustain and extend one anothers capacities for autonomous actionSince finite 
rational beings cannot gener ally achi eve their aims without some help and support from others, a general 
refusal of help and support amounts to failure to treat others as rational and autonomous beings, that is as 
ends in themselves. ( ONeil l in DMI (recommended readings) 469) 
In tra ditional terms, duties of justice are perfe ct duties, i.e., they are absolute requirements, the violation of which 
is immoral.  Duties of beneficence are imperfect duties, i.e., they are duties to act in ways that further certain ends 
or goals, but there a re legitimate choices about how to do this. Another way to think of it is that corresponding 
to duties of justice are rights: I have a right to bodily integrity and you have a perfect duty to respect my bodily integrity.  People have many needs, however, and although you may have a duty to help those in need, it may 
be morally permissible to meet someone elses needs rather than mine. But it would be morally wrong of you 
to ignore everyones needs but your own. 
III. Rights
Do individuals, however, have a moral rig
 ht to adequate nutrition?  (Or, in Sens words, food entitlements? 
Well talk more about Sen et al tomorrow.) What if we are starving and no one steps up to help? Does no one 
have a duty to help me?! (See especially pp. 54 -57 in FES. ) 
Rights a re standardly divided into negat ive rights and positive rights . It is possible to map some of the discussion of 
these onto the Kantian picture.  Negative rights correspond to perfect duties: we are all, always, morally 
required to treat others with respec t for their integrity and not interfere with them.  Positive rights, however, 
e.g. the right to food, healthcare, etc. seem to require that we take action not only to respect and protect the
right in q
uestion, but also to fulfill it.  If I have a positive right to adequate nutrition, then someone must fulfill
it if I lack food.  According to those who hold that we only have imperfect duties to provide for others, i.e., that
providing food to others is only a duty of beneficence, there is no positive right t o adequate nutrition; at best
others have an imperfect duty to do what they can.
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 2/21 /17 
Deontology and Famine 
I.Recap
Consequentialism (Bentham, Mill, Singer)
The rightness or wrongness of something depends entirely on the goodness or badness of its consequences. 
Act Utilitarianism: You oug ht always to act so as to maximize utility [diff erent theories emphasize 
happiness, pleasure, or welfare.], i.e., the right act is the act that results in the greatest amount of utility 
overall. 
Singer relies on a consequentialist assumption to conclude that we ought to give large amounts to charity t o 
reliev
e the suffering of distant others: 
Modified Prevent Suffering Princi ple: If it is our power to prevent something very bad from 
happening, withou t thereby sacrificing anything morally significant, then we ought, morally, to do it. 
Note that althoug h Singe r focuses on famine, the bad in question need not be hunger. It might be medical 
care, the ravages of war, injustice of other kinds. 
For many, Singers conclusions seem too demanding. Why shouldnt we each enjoy what we have? Are the 
distan
t needy really entitled to what Singer demands of us? Possible lines of criticism are many: 
Partiality: Far away people I dont even know have no moral cl aim on me. Distance/relationships
matter. (See also pp. 43 -46 in FES. )
oWhy does distance matter morally?
oBut what about the homeless in Central Square?
Ind
ividual Responsibility: It isnt my fa ult that some people are suffering.  Why should I have to sacrifice
for them?  In fact, empirical research suggests that people are making their own choices to buy TV s
instead of food.  If they are hungry, it is their own fault. (See Duflo et al.)
oIs moral responsibility a causal notion, i.e. I am responsible for what I cause? Or is it broader?
Is t
here a forward -looking  notion of responsibility: I am responsible for making the world
better than it is now? We all must do our part.
Is there a collective notion of responsibility: I alone didnt cause suffering, but I am part of asystem t
hat did? (See also pp. 46 -47 in FES.)
oAre individuals always sufficiently educat ed t o make good food/health choices?
oWhat is the standard of living that we are entitled to? Is i t only bare existence?
Charity skepticism: It is un likely that anything I give will make a difference. In fact, charity might make
things worse. (See pp. 57 -59 in FES. )
oIs this true of all gi ving? Is there no useful intervention, ever?
Lifeboat: There are too many people on the planet anyway. It is inevitable that some will die, and we
must a
llow this so that the rest (and the planet?) can survive. (See pp. 47-52 in FES.)
oSee questions about this approach on the previous (2/15) handout.
II.De
ontology
Lets think more about individual responsibility. Accord ing to deontology there are some basic or non -
derivative moral considerations beyond or in addition t o good effects, and these give rise to our moral obligations,
i.e., what we ought to do. The most important alternative to consequentialism, historically speaking, derives
from the work of Immanuel Kant (1724 -1804), and so predictably is called a Kantian approach. The
utilitarian takes happiness or pleasure to be intrinsically good and seeks to maximize it; Kantians, however,
take the good will , i.e., our ability to conform our will to reason, to be intrinsically good.  The right way to honor
whats good ab out a good will is not to maximize, however, but to respect such wills.
A.Kantian Deontology: Categorical Imperative
At the core of Kant's ethics is a principle known as the Catego rical Imperative (CI) which Kant states in different
ways. (See Kants Groundwork for the Metaphysic of Morals in recommended reading.)
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 2/21 /17 
CI -Universal Law formulation: Act only on that maxim whereby thou canst at the same time will that it should 
become a universal law . (11) 
CI -Principle of Humanity formulation: So act tha t you use humanity, whether in thine own person or 
in that of any other, in every case as an end withal, never as a means only. (29) 
In more contemporary terms: 
You are No Exception Principle (YANE): " in whatever you do, you should act for reasons that co uld 
serve as acceptable reasons for everyone." (Sayre -McCord, 5) 
and 
Respect 
for Persons Principle (RPP): In all action one should respect others as sources of value and 
never merely as an instrument for ones own purposes. (Sayre -McCord, 7) 
B.You Are No Excep tion Principle
We generally think it is wrong to do something that we know would be problematic if everyone else did it too,
e.g., ch
eating on an exam, removing a pollution control device from a car, stealing a book from the bookstore.
In each of these cases the agent's goals could not be achieved if everyone else did the same thing, so the success
of the action depends on making a distinction between what the agent does and what others do. But makingoneself an exception this way seems wrong. K ant thought that in cases like this there was a sort of irrationality.
The idea is that in any intentional action, I am implicitly or explicitly acting on a principle of some kind. The principl
e is given by your reason for acting , not necessarily your motive. Consider three shopkeepers, both of whom 
are committed to giving correct change to their customers. They act, however, on different principles, or what Kant called "maxims": 
Mr. Practical: When (an
 d only when?) I can gain a good business reputation b y giving correct change, I 
shall give correct change. 
Ms. Sympathetic: When I feel it appropriate to give correct change which I always do because Im a 
sympathetic person I shall give correct change. 
Mr. Righteous: When I can perform a morally right act by giving correct change, I shall give correct 
change. 
In each case there is a generalized form of the maxim of the form: 
General 
Form: Whenever one is ________, he/she shall ________. 
On Kant's view, what matters in evaluating an action is the princip le that is employed in intending or willing. 
Two individuals can do the same thing, but one of them do wrong and the other right, depending on what they will. Some maxims fail the test, so the corresponding action is immoral, e.g., (in generalized for m): 
Whenever one has an exam and doesn't feel like studying, she shall copy off of her neighbor's work. 
Presumably we could not all act on this maxim, for if we are all planning to copy off each other, there will be 
no work t
o copy! The underlying rationa le for an approach such as this is to show that the source of morality 
is in reason or rationality ; those who are immoral are in some important sense acting irrationally . 
C.Respect for Persons Principle
Although there seems to be somethi ng right about the (YANE) version of the CI, it isn't clear that it captures
what makes an action right or wrong. So let's turn to the "Respect for Persons Principle" (RPP): In all action
one should respect others as sources of value and never merely as an instrument for ones own purposes.
(Sayre -McCord, 7)
This principle allows that we can use others as a means to accomplish our own ends; after all, we rely crucially on others 
all the time. Your professors serve as a means to your ends of gaining knowledge. But thes e are 
cases in which there is consent your professors aren't deceived or coerced into serving your needs. According 
to the (RPP), cheating on your final would be wrong because you would be using me (or your TA) as a mere means to a good grade: this would be a scheme that we would not or better: could not reasonably consent 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Justice and Food Production (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11: Justice in Food Production</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 3/13/17 
2) Are you acting fr eely when you ar e under duress? Again you are clearly acting of your own free will
when you choose to enter into a disadvantageous contract, but if others can take advantage of the threats
that circumstances pose to your well -being, are you free? Do you have the liberties that society should
aim to protect?
3.Complicity
when asked if it is reasonable to assume that an American who has eaten a fresh tomato from a 
grocery stor e 
or food -service company during the winter has eaten fruit picked by the hand of a 
slave, Malloy said, It is not an assumption. It is a fact. (Estabrook 2009, FES, p. 13) 
Months after I stopped working on the kill floor, I argued with a friend over who was more morally res p 
onsible for the killing of the animals: those who ate the meat or the 121 workers who 
did the killing. She maintained, passionately, and with conviction, that the people who did the killing were more responsible because they were the ones performing the physical actions that 
took the animals lives.  Those who ate the meat, she claimed, were only indirectly responsible.  I 
took the opposition position, holding that those who benefited at a distance, delegating this terrible work to others while disclaiming responsibility for it, bore more moral responsibility, 
particularly in contexts like the slaughterhouse, where those with the fewest opportunities in 
society performed the dirty work. My friends position was the 120+1 argument [the +1 is the person who pulls the trigger to shoot the animal], an argument repl icated across myriad realms 
where morally dirty work is performed by a select few, out of the sign of the many who implicitly or explicitly authorize it but manage to evade responsibility for it by virtue of the citizenship, the 
taxes they pay, their race, their sex, or the actions of their ancestors. (Pachirat 2013, in FES, p. 
555) 
What is the consumers moral responsibility for harms to workers? 
What is the states responsibility? 
4.Political philosophy
Moral theory considers right action, and how indivi duals ought mora l ly to act. But of course, individuals
live in societies, and in societies there are many individuals simultaneously acting and pursuing a good life.
So two questions emerge:
What is an individual entitled to in their pursuit of a good li fe among others , g iven that there are
limited resources?
How should a just society be organized? In particular, how can a society best enable its members
to flourish, com
patible with justice for all?  What moral principles should constrain and guide the
organization of society?
Of the three moral theories we considered, utilitaria ni sm is the one best suited to provide an immediate 
response to these questions: society should be organized in such a way to maximize happiness for all; an individual is entitl ed to all and only whatever maximizes happiness for all. A common complaint against 
utilitarianism, however, is that it does not take seriously enough the rights of the individual. So what 
other theoretical options are there?5. The Big Three (Political Theories)
1 
Libertarianism provides another approach to the organization of society that focuses heavily on rights. 
Libertarians maintain that the most important political value is personal liberty . Personal liberty is absolute: 
1 Another part of political theory, not covered here, is political economy. Political economy c oncerns the relationship 
between the political structure of a society, e.g., the state, and the economy. Famous political economists include: 
Thomas Hobbes, John Locke, Karl Marx, Adam Smith, Friedrich Hayek, John Maynard Keynes , et al. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 3/13/17 
an individuals liberty cannot be violated to maximize happiness or any other good, even the overall 
amount of p e
rsonal liberty in a society. The only legitimate restrictions on individual liberty are those 
necessary to pro tect the liberty of others.  
The right to liberty is a cluster of negative r i ghts. Violation of such rights would include (a) being killed or 
assaulted or other physical violence against one, (b) being coerced, being prevented from activities that do no harm to others, (c) having your property taken or controlled, providing that you are not violating the 
rights of others. Libertarians believe that the cluster of negative rights that constitute personal liberty 
determine that only a minimal state is justi fied.  A minimal state cannot go beyond protecting its members 
from violence, theft, fraud; distributive justice in such a state is a matter of historical entitlement to 
property. We saw before that guaranteeing such liberties does not ensure freedom, if we conceive of 
freedom as a capacity to live decently according to ones values, for a minimal state would not provide any safety net or protection from exploitation. Robert Nozick is a paradigm libertarian. 
Egalitarianism comes in a variety of forms. Bu t the main idea  is
  that the value of individual happiness 
and the value of liberty do not exhaust the values that a society has an obligation to protect and foster. In 
addition, a society ought to manifest the value of equality amongst its citizens. Egal itarians differ in how 
they answer the following questions: 
(a)	Equality of what?  Equality of wealth?  Equality of opportunity?  Equality of respect?
(b)What are the legitimate means for creating equality, compatible with other values?
Equality and lib erty are of t en thought to be in tension. Suppose the goal is equality of wealth. Achieving 
and maintaining equal wealth amongst citizens would seem to require violations of liberty. To consider a 
simplistic example, suppose I gave you each $100. Some wo uld save it; some would spend it; others 
would invest it. Maintaining equality of wealth would require a redistribution of resources over time, i.e., taking wealth from some and giving it to others. But this seems to violate the right to private property: if I 
create wealth through my effort, am I not entitled to keep it? Is it not a violation of my rights to have it taken from me?  Although this concern is vivid when aiming for equality of wealth, it is less obviously so 
when equality of respect or oppor tunity is the goal. 
Libertarianism seems to do too little to protect our well- being and a r
 obust sense of freedom; 
egalitarianism seems to do too little to protect our liberty. Are there other options? 
Liberal egalitarianism attempts t o articulate a balance between equality and liberty. Typically, liberal 
egalitarians will articulate a domain of negative rights that are inviolable (even to achieve equality), a 
domain of positive rights that promote freedom (e.g., the right t o education), and principles of distribution 
that  respect the value of equality.  
John Rawls is a paradigm liberal egalitarian. He suggests that: 
A just society is fair.
A test of a fair distribution is whether everyone could reasonably consent to it.
People should reasonably consent to an arrangement that is mutually advantageous.
The best wa
y to come up with a mutually advantageous arrangement is to be impartial.
Impartiality is best achieved through abstracting away from our particular differences.
Idea: ignorance is a good tool for achieving impartiality. 
Example: d
ividing a pizza. If I dont know which slice Im getting, Ill divide it evenly. 
The Original Position: In Rawls, he calls the framework of supposed ignorance from which we are to 
decide on the pr i
nciples of justice, the original position. In the original position 
We dont know what our society is like because we want to be impartial across cultures, andacross generat
ions.
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 3/13/17 
We also dont know what our individual natural talents or soc ial advantage s  are, because we dont
want to skew the society to favor those who just happen to be lucky to be born to rich parents or
with special talents.
We also dont know our religion or fundamental conception of the good because we want oursocial framewo 
rk to be tolerant of the full range of conceptions of the good.
Rawls argues that from this original position, it would be rational to (a) be concerned most with the 
distribution of w
hat he calls primary goods, i.e., goods that would be good for you regardless of what 
else you value, e.g., basic liberties, health, money, opportunity, and (b) to decide that primary goods should be distributed according to two principles, with the first given priority over the second : 
The liberty principle: Each person i s 
 to have an equal right to the most extensive basic liberty compatible 
with a similar liberty for others, where such liberties include: 
Freedom of speech &amp; assembly
Freedom of conscience &amp; thought
Freedom of the person
The right to hold property
The maximin principle (or in Rawls te r ms: the Difference Principle): social and economic inequalities are 
permissible only to the extent that they are attached to positions open to all, and they benefit the least well-off. 
Objections: 
a) The liberal egali tarian appro a
 ch is biased towards the disadvantaged; those better off deserve their
advantages and they shouldn't be taken away. In fact, fairness comes from the unrestricted working of
market forces. Reply: If fairness requires that we level the playi ng field so that no one is disadvantaged by
bad luck, then the successful dont deserve their advantages and the market will not yield fair results. Isthere a better conception of fairness?  What is it?
b) It is not the responsibility of society or gover nment to make t
 hings fair. Reply: What is the
responsibility of society? Why isnt it to make things fair? Wont fair societies also be more stable, more
democratic, more just? How ought we organize societ y if not to achieve these aims?
6.Neo -liberalism
Neo-liberalism is  a
 globalized political economy that favors privatization, free trade, deregulation, and
such to avoi
d government spending and government interference in the social sphere.
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 3/13/17 
Justice and Food Production 
1.Food Sovereignty, again
Before when we talked about food sovereig n ty (Kyle Powys Whyte reading), the main issue was the protection 
of a way of life, a culture. In the Thompson reading, the issues broaden to economic justice. As he says, 
the global food system should be understood as a systemic nexus that functions to ex tract the 
last sh r
ed of economic value from the production, distribution, and consumption of food and to 
repress any form of political action against it. Everyone needs to eat. Therefore, control of food 
is a powerful locus for both profit -taking and the exercise of social control. Food sovereignty is, 
on this view, a mode of resistance against this totalizing food regime. (163) 
What are some of the wrongs that have been documented in the food regime? 
Slaughterhouses
oSee also Pachirat Slaughterhouse Wor kers in FES, pp. 5 46-555.
Tomato pickers, other farm workers
oSee also Seth Holmes, Farm Workers in FES, pp. 532 -546.
oSee a l
so article in yesterdays Guardian:
htt
ps://www.theguardian.com/global -development/2017/m a r/12/slavery -sicily -farming -
raped -beaten- exploited- rom anian -women
Restaurant workers
What precisely are the wron gs here? What makes these things wrong? Are t hese forms of oppression? 
Consider again Youngs categories: exploitation, marginalization, powerlessness, cultural imperialism, 
systematic v i
olence. 
Who is responsible for the harms ? 
Wh
o (what groups?) are primari l y the victims of these harms? Does that matter? 
2.Harm to workers
Slavery: Chattel slavery, forced labor, d ebt bondage 
Lim
ited options/forced options 
Mistreatment, brutality 
Exploitation 
In thinking about this it is useful to draw a distinction between coercion and duress. To be coerced into 
doing something is to be forced to do it on pain of severe harm or death. If someone hold a gun to your 
head and says Your money or your life!, that is coercion, and when you hand over your money it is 
arguable that you dont actually consent to giving the money, you do it just to save your life.  Duress 
(though it can be defined in different ways) is different from coercion in several ways: (i) there may be no one forcing you (it may be circumstances that cause your duress), (ii) the threat may be not b e immediate 
serious harm or death (it may be serious harm over the long term), and (iii) you may consent to the actions taken under duress (you may enter into a disadvantageous contract to avoid the long term threat of hunger, homelessness, etc). 
Questions : 
1) Are you acting freely when you are coerced? It seems that you are acting of your own free will in some
sense  you could ha ve 
chosen to be killed instead of giving up your money  but your liberty is clearly
being compromised.
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Locavorism (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec23/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24: Locavorism</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 8 May 2017 
If widely adopted, either voluntarily or through political mandates, locavorism can only result in higher costs and 
increased poverty, greater food insecurity, less food safety, and much more significant environment al damage than is presently the 
case. (14) 
Only through greater technological advances, economies of scale and international trade can we achieve the 
locavores worthy goals of improving nutrition while diminishing the environmental impact of agricultu ral 
production. (14) 
buying or abstaining from buying local food should be a sho pping decision, not a moral or political one. (15) 
Getting the most for your hard- ear ned dollar is not only enlightened self -interest, but also the best way to 
create a be tter world. (15) 
What is enlightened self -inte rest?  What is the relationship between morality and enlightened self -interest? 
III. A variety of argu ments 
Prosperity argument :  all economically prosperous episodes in human history have been characterized to one 
degree or another by the expansion of a communitys food provisioning. (18) 
Prosperity and economic growth depends on cities: they produce concentrated markets for rural 
goo
ds, technological innovations , and capital for rural deve lopment (22). 
Urbanization is impossible without food imports (22). 
Urban food producers have been increasingly distant from urban centers due to increasing land value, 
bet
ter transportation and preservation technology and health reasons (24). 
Cultural Arg ume nt: Humans have always traded foods and recipes, and this is how cultures have flourished. (6, 
19, 25) 
Efficiency Argument: Agr icultural areas should be devoted to producing the food that their soil and climate best 
supports. (26) Health Argument : In the
  last two centuriesconsumers went from shopping in dry goods stores to the 
permanent summertime produce sections of progressively larger supermarkets whose ever expanding range 
of offerings have become only safer, healthier, and considerably more a ffordable. (29) 
Food Security Argument: Pe rhaps most remarkablehas been humanitys capacity to nearly defeat famine and 
hunger. (29) 
Critique of Suspicion: Hi storically, the push for greater agricultural self -sufficiency was never limited to political 
and military leaders bent on imperialistic pursuits, but also often included a fair number of romantic 
ideologues, politically connected nationalists, supporters of good old and small is beautiful ways (31) 
note what they are asking : in  whose int erests is the recommendation that we should buy local food? What 
idea/symbol/meaning is being sold in addition to the food? (This critique of suspicion is also evident in the 
Introduction where they discuss the claim that SOLE is essentially a fad promot ed by bicoastal urban agri -
intellectuals whose knowledge of and practical experience with food production is l imit ed to the world of 
hobby gardening (9)) 
Historical argument : Bu y/grow local food has been tried before and was not successful.  (35- 40) the fact 
remains that none of [the past attempts] lasted once more people had more options available to them. (39) 
Question s: 
1) 
De Bres says that you need to ask yourself some questions about your own values, attachments, and 
pri
orities. (506). Are t here particular values, etc. such that, if you adopt them, you should be a moderate 
locavore?  Which ones? 
2) Desrochers and Shimizu seem to suggest that they agree with locavores on the moral and political objectives 
an
d simply disagree on how to achieve them.  Do you agree?  Are there moral and/or political differences too? 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
  
  
  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
  
  
  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 8 May 2017 
Locavorism 
1. Basic questions 
(i) What moral considerations should we bring to bear on our food choices, as individuals? 
(ii) How should we organize ourselves socially and politically to produce and consume food in a way that
 
is ju
st?
 
Factors to con sider (others??):
 
Human health &amp; nutrition Global justice (global hunger, exploitation)
 
Environmental impact, sustainability Cultural meanings, community
 
Animal well -being Aesthetic concerns
 
Fair labor practices Prosperity
 
1. Locavorism: Wha t is it? 
a) the idea that an ever- gro wing portion of our food supply should be produced in close proximity to the 
consumers who will eat it. (Desrochers and Shimizu 2012, 4; all references in parentheses below are to this 
book ; those indicated FES are to Helena de Bress article. ) 
b) The idea that the food we eat should be indigenous to the region. (6) 
c) The attitude that local foo d isdesirable simply because of its geographical origin and is not more affordable, 
nutritious, safer, or better tasting than alternatives produced further away. (13) 
Questions: 
Are these adequate definitions? How could they be improved? 
What is the mos t plausible/charitable version of locavorism? 
o Distinguish ra dical locavorism from moderate locavorism. (FES, 497) 
Possibly: 
d) Consumers should choose to purchase food grown and processed locally, if the climate supports such crops, 
and should limit th e f ood they purchase requiring significant transportation and energy expenditure. 
2. Arguments in favor of locavorism: 
Most seem to have the form:
 1) Buying local food is better for ______ [the economy, the environment, our health, our community.], than
 
buyi
ng non -local food.
 
2) We are morally required to do what is best for ________.
 
Conclusion: We are morally required to buy local food in preference to non -local food.
 
Note that even if premise (1) is true, the normative premise (2) is very strong: it sa ys what we are required to do, 
not just what is per missible or good to do.  None of the arguments seem to provide a basis for a radical locavorism
 
that requires one to buy only local food at all times. Are there reasons to draw a more moderate conclusion?
 
Consider:
 
Economic (7, FES 500) Taste, Nutrition and Safety (9, FES 499-500)
 
Environmental (7, FES 498-99) Social (6), Agrarian (FES 500-505)
 
Security (8)
 
Political (FES 505-506)
 
3. Against Locavorism 
Desrochers and Shimizus main claims: 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Consumer Ethics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19: Vegetarianism and Veganism</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 4/19 /17 
Consumer Ethics (2) 
1.	 Intro 
Suppose you learn that a product has been produced under morally problematic conditions. What should 
you do? YOU arent causin g pain to or killing animals. YOU arent exploiting slaughterhouse workers or 
polluting t he rivers with pesticides. So should you adjust your behavior? If so, what is the principle that 
you should rely on in judging what to do? 
Compare: 
	 The NCAA exploi ts college students.  Should we watch college basketball, attend games, etc.? 
	 After a party an extra plate of cold cuts is left over. It is in perfect condition. Is there any reason 
not to eat it? 
	 The electrical company in your town relies on coal to pro duce power. The result is terrible air 
pollution. Should you go without electricity? 
Think through the models we have for making moral judgments: 
Efficacy/Inefficacy issues? Does it really matter what an individual decides to do? 
How do we calculate the expected consequences of an action? (See p. 173) 
Are consequences all that matter? 
2. Threshold effects and supply chains 
Many have pointed out that it is very unlikely that a single individual s decision to become vegetarian (or 
vegan) will make a difference to the suffering and/or death of non -human animals. There is plenty of 
slack  in the system to accommodate the waste  of a few animals. 
But what ab out threshold effects? Singer and others have argued that even if your decision is not likely to 
matter, there is a chance that it will matter. For ex ample, there is threshold  at which a meat producing 
enterprise will cut down the amount it produces in response to consumer demand. How do you know 
that your decision is the one that makes the difference? Or more plausibly, shouldn t we calculate the 
consequences of your decision taking into account the chances that your decision will matter? 
3. Practical rationality and expected consequences 
Just to get the hang of this, suppose that you are facing a decision under conditions of uncertainty: 
suppose the question is whether to take an umbrella or not, on a day when the chance of rain is one half. 
Since the value of taking as opposed to leaving the umbrella will be different depending on whether or not 
it rains, we might start out by listing all the possible scenarios, and how well things work out for us in all of 
them.  There are four: 
	 Take it and it rains 
	 Take it and it doesnt rain 
	 Leave it and it rains 
	 Leave it and it doesnt rain 
How should we decide? Heres a proposal: 
Practical Rationality Principle : The practically rational thing to do is the t hing with the highest expected 
value, where the expected value (x) = the sum of the values of the various possible outcomes that x could 
give rise to, weighted according to their probabilities. 
Should I take an umbrella along to class on a day when the cha nce of rain is 50% ? 
Haslanger 1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 4/19 /17 
Probability .50 .50 
Possibilities Rain Dry Expected Value 
Take 10 -4 3  
Leave -20 2 -9 
Expected value of TAKE 
= value of taking if rain x chance of rain + value of taking if dry x chance of dry 
= 10 x .50 + -4 x .50 = 3 
Expected value of LEAVE 
= value of leaving if rain x chance of rain + value of leaving if dry x chance of dry 
= -20 x .50 + 2 x .50 = -9. 
This suggests you should take the umbrella. But if the pro bability of rain is different, (or the values you 
assign to the possible outcomes) you could reach a different result. E.g., if the probability of rain is only 
10%: 
EV(TAKE)= 1 + 3.6 = -2.6 
EV (LEAVE)= -2 + 1.8 = -.2 
How is this relevant in the case of, say, the decision to purchase meat? It may be a low probability that 
your choice will make a difference, but the outcome, if it does, may be significant. It may be, for example, 
that your decision occurs at a tipping point, so that along with others choices to be vegetarian, the day 
comes whe n a slaughterhouse becomes unprofitable and so closes. The chances are low, but the good 
outcomes, one might think, are huge. 
Probability .001 .999 
Possibilities Closes Stays open Expected Value 
Go Veg 1,000,000 -1 ~999 
Stay Omnivore -20 2 -9  
It looks like even if there is a small chance of making a big difference, the practically rational thing to is go 
vegetarian! 
In the readings, however, there seems to be some doubt about whether this is the right approach by 
emphasizing that we know how supply chains work. E.g., Budolfson argues that the problem with [this 
sort of] reasoning is that we can know enough abo ut the supply chains to know that threshold effects are 
not sufficiently lik ely and are not of sufficient magnitude to drive the expected effect of c onsumption 
anywhere close to the average effect .we might call that mistake the Average E ffects Fallacy.  Do you 
find that argument convincing? 
4. Group Harm 
McPherson argues that there is a further way of thinking about the wrong of meat eating, even if the 
expected consequences argument doesn t work.  Here is the principle: 
GROUP HARM: If one can avoid being part of a group that together does serious wrong, then one acts 
wrongly b y continuing to be a member of that group. (FES 198) 
Haslanger 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 4/19 /17 
Application to the case at hand: If omnivores, as a group, do wrong, then one acts wrongly by continuin g 
to be an omnivore. 
5. Complicity 
ANTI -COMPLICITY : It is typically wrong to aim to benefit by cooperating with the wrongful elements 
of others  plans. (FES 199) 
Can you think of an example that demonstrates this? Is it wrong even i f your involvement in the other s 
plans make no differen ce to the harm that is caused, e.g., if the wrong is demand -insensitive ? 
6. Kantianism /Deontology 
Is there a way to apply Korsgaard s Kantian argument to draw consequences for consumer ethics? All 
consumer ethics, or only ethics concerning vegetarianism/vegan ism?  What about sweatshop labor? 
Other labor practices? 
7. Virtue Ethics 
Recall the discussion of social meaning (see handout from 3/6/17 on Food and S ocial Meaning  and 
3/8/17 on Religion, Virtue, Food ). How do our consumer choi ces convey our values? What values 
does the purchase of meat convey? Does it really convey a disresp ect for animal s? 
Haslanger 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
  
  
  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
  
  
  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Is it Bad to Kill Animals? (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-03-good-food-ethics-and-politics-of-food-spring-2017/resources/mit24_03s17_lec17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18: Harming and Killing</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food 4/10/ 17 
Is it Bad to Kill Animals? 
I. The duty to eat our friends 
In his essay, Eating our Friends, Roger Scruton argues that we may agree that the current system of 
ind
ustrial animal agriculture is morally problematic because of the pain and suffering it causes to non -
human animals. However, suggests that we are not onl y allowed to eat meat, raised humanely, but may 
even have a duty to do so. 
In support of his claim that we are morally permitted to eat animals that are raised and killed humanely, 
he c
laims that for cattle: 
To be killed at 30 months is not intrinsica lly m ore tragic than to be killed at 40, or 50, or 60.  And 
if the meat is at its best after 30 months, and if every month thereafter represents an economic 
loss, who will blame the farmer for choosing so early a death?  In doing so he merely reflects the choice of the consumer, upon whose desires the whole trade in meat, and therefore the very 
existence of his animals, depends. (392 -3) 
But he goes beyond this to argue that humane animal husbandry is a complex moral good. (393) Ani
mal farming is one of the kindest uses of land yet devised, and  
the result of raising animals [traditionally, humanely] will change the character of meat -eat ing, 
which will become not only more expensive, but more ceremonialThe animal brought to the 
table will have enjoyed the friendship and protection of the one who nurtured him, and his death 
will be like the ritual sacrifices described in the Bible and Homeric literature  a singling out of a 
victim for an important office to which a kind of honor is attached. Such it s eems to me would be 
the life of the virtuous carnivore, the one who is prepared to eat only his friends. (393) 
He goes on to suggest that virtuous carnivorism will be more effective in changing farming practices than 
veg
etarianism. I would suggest not on ly that it is permissible for those who care about animals to eat 
meat; they have a duty to do so. (394) Why? Conscientious carnivores can exert more pressure on those engaged in meat production to do so only through humane practices. 
II. The Surprisin g C
 laim: 
Elizabeth Harman argues against The Surprising Claim (39 6): 
(a) We have strong reasons not to cause intense pain to animals: the fact that an action would cause 
inte
nse pain to an animal makes the action wrong unless it is justified by other considerations; and 
(b) We do not have strong reasons not to kill animals: it is not the case that killing an animal is wrong unl
ess it is justified by other considerations. 
[Note that in Harman, an imals  sometimes seems to mean non-human animals , and sometime s animals 
generally.] 
A. Argume nt against the Surprising Claim (397): 
1. If 
it is true that we have strong moral re asons against causing intense pain to animals, such that doing 
so is impermissible unless justified by other considerations, then part of the explanation of this truth is that 
animals have moral status. 
2. If it is true that we have strong moral reasons against causing intense pain to ani mals, such th at doing 
so is impermissible unless justified by other considerations, then part of the explanation of this truth is that 
significantly harming something with moral status is impermissible unless justified by other considerations. 
3. If an action pa inlessl y kills a healthy animal in the prime of life, then that action significantly harms the 
animal.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu  
  
  
  
24.03 Good Food: The Ethics and Politics of Food Choices 
Spring 2017 
  
  
  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>24.03: Good Food	 4/10/ 17 
4. If it is true that we have strong moral reasons against causing pain to ani mals, such that doing so is 
impermissible unless justified other considerations then painlessly killing a healthy animal in the prime of 
life is impermissible unless justified by other considerations (1,2,3). 
5. Therefore, the Surprising Claim is false (4). 
Response 1 (72 8): Death is bad for an animal. But i t doesnt harm an animal to kill it (painlessly) after a 
life in which the animal is well cared for , because one does not harm someone by depriving him/her/it of 
something good . 
	 What is it to harm something? Not e the difference between harming and failing to benefit. 
	 Is harming some thin g just a matter of causing that thing bad experiences? 
	 Actively and physically interfering with [an animal] in such a way that [it] is deprived of a 
ben
efit does typically harm that [animal]. (398 ) 
	 When is the animal harmed, if painlessly caused to di e? 
Response 2 (39 8): 
(i) The death of a person is bad for her only because it frustrates her desires and p lans for the future. 
(ii) Therefore, death is bad in general only because it frustrates desires and plans. 
(iii) Animals do not have desires and plans for  the future. 
(iv) Therefore, animals' deaths are not bad for them. 
Problem: (i) is false because someones future may be good for him/her/it, even if he/she/it doesnt have 
pla
ns and desires for it. (398-9) 
Response 3 (39 9): 
It is true that animal pain matters morally. But it is a mistake to conclude that this is because animals have 
moral status. Rather, animals lack moral status. But stages of animals have moral status. Animal pain 
matters morally because an animal stage is in pain. What is better or worse for the animal does not matter 
morally, though what is better or worse for stages of it does. 
	 This view is implausible. When we perform painful surgery on an animal, we cause di scomfort to 
stages of th e animal for the sake of the whole. This is what justifies the surgery. We are not 
permitted to cause pain to one morally significant being for the sake of others. But we are justified 
in causing pain to one stage of an individual for the sake of her long term good. 
Response 4 (401): M cMahons Time Relative Interests View
 
We have strong reasons against causing animal pain, and we have some reasons against painlessly killing
 animals in the prime of life, but these reasons are weakened by animals lack o f deep psychological
 
continuity over time. On this view, we may have weak reasons not to kill animals, but not strong ones.
 
Problem: the fact that non- hum
 an animals have a weak connect to their futures does not show that they
 
dont have an interest in a l ong and healthy future. Consider the examples of Billy and Tommy : we
 
should perform surgery on animals  even painful surgery  that will enable them to live a longer healthy
 
life.  Why would this be the case if killing them now is permissible and doesnt harm them?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
