<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/</course_url>
    <course_title>How to Stage a Revolution</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>History </list>
      <list>American History </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Achieving Statehood: Haiti Among the Powers of the Earth</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Past and Coming Attractions 
Units 1-3: the Atlantic revolutionary era 
(minus the Spanish American revolutions of 
the early 19th century)  
Unit 4 
Legacies 
Comparisons 
Theory 
Egypt 
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Achieving Statehood: 
Haiti Among the Powers of the Earth 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Map of the United States and Territories from April 20, 1803 to March 27,
1804 removed due to copyright restrictions. See: Wikipedia.
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>1770 Map 
This image is public domain 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>When in the Course of 
human events, it 
becomes necessary for 
one people to dissolve 
the political bands which 
have connected them 
with another, and to 
assume among the 
powers of the earth, the 
separate and equal 
station to which the 
Laws of Nature and of 
Natures God entitle 
them . . .  
This image is public domain 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Maps of the United States prior and after the 1763 Treaty of Paris have
been removed due to copyright restrictions. See: Wikipedia.
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>What is a Slave Revolution?/ 
What Does It Mean to Abolish Slavery? 
Improve the conditions of labor (more free days per 
week) for all slaves 
Free only the most prominent slave insurgents and 
permit them to exercise a leadership role 
Compensate for labor while keeping slaves attached 
to their plantations 
Eliminate the property element  
Eliminate the element of racial subordination 
Rid the land of white masters/overseers 
Divide plantations into small landholdings to be 
maintained by peasants 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Photo courtesy of Stefan Krasowski  on Flickr. CC-BY.
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Authoritarianism, Poverty, and Foreign Intervention: Explaining Modern Haiti</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_25/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>25</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Explaining Modern Haiti: 
Authoritarianism, Poverty, and Foreign Intervention 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Haiti and the Social Question  
 
[T]o avoid this fatal mistake [of trying to solve 
the social question with political means, thereby 
leading to terror] is almost impossible when a 
revolution breaks out under conditions of mass 
poverty. (102)  
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>The image is public domain. NASA/Goddard Space Flight Center Scientific Visualization Studio.
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Photo courtesy of Stefan Krasowski  on Flickr. CC-BY.
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Haitian Political Regimes, 1804-1843 
Dessalines, 1804- 1806  
Divided rule 
Alexandre Ption, 1807-1818 (rules over the south 
as president of Republic of Haiti) 
Henry Christophe, 1807-1820 (rules over north, 
declares monarchy in 1811) 
Jean-Pierre Boyer, 1818-1843 (reunites north 
and south in 1820, occupies Santo Domingo in 
1822)  
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>1770 Map 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Image removed due to copyright restrictions. See: States and Territories of the
United States of America April 30, 1803 to March 27 , on Wikipedia.
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Photo courtesy of Alan B. Photography on Flickr. CC-BY-NC-SA.
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>How did the Revolution in Haiti Begin? (I) The Free People of Color</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Moreau le Jeune drawing of Code Noir invoked by slave, 
frontispiece to Bernardin de Saint-Pierre s Voyage  l Isle 
de France  (1773)  
This image is public domain 
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Article 55 
 
Masters twenty years of age may free their 
slaves by any act toward the living or due 
to death, without their having to give just 
cause for their actions, nor do they require 
parental advice as long as they are minors 
of 25 years of age. Article 55 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>How Did the Revolution in Haiti Begin? (I): 
The Free People of Color 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Growth of the free colored population 
1700 
 
500 
 
12.3%  1764 
 
5,500 
 
33.5%  
 1789  
 
27,548 
 
89.4%  Year 
 
Total Pop. 
 
As % of white  
population 
Note: These figures almost certainly significantly undercount the 
actual numbers of free people of color, since they are based on 
the official census figures which did not include persons 
manumitted informally so as to evade payment of the freedom 
tax after late 1730s/early 1740s. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Article 42 
 
Only masters shall be permitted, when they 
believe their slaves so deserve, to chain them 
and beat them with canes or rope.  We forbid 
masters from applying torture to their slaves or 
from inflicting any kind of mutilation, on pain 
of confiscation of the slaves and special 
prosecution of the masters.  Article 42 
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Title Page of Code Noir (1735) 
This image is public domain 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>11 Degrees of Racial Separation 
Griffe : child of a mulatto and a black person (3/4th 
black)  
Quarteron : a person of  black background 
Mestifs : 1/8th black 
* 
A language of biological criteria based on social 
conventions 
Racial mixture corrupts  
Translating sexual fantasy and anxiety 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Aerial view of Le Cap 
This image is public domain</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Revolts/Rebellions in the  
18th-Century Caribbean 
Gaoul in Martinique 
(1717) 
Scattered white revolts 
in colonial Saint-
Domingue, and by free 
people of color in 1760s 
Makandal in 1757- 1758  
Tackys revolt in Jamaica 
(1760- 1761)  
 
This image is public domain 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>11 Degrees of Racial Separation 
Mulattos (also called 
sang-mls ): persons 
born of one white 
and one black 
parent, or a mulatto 
parent and a 
multresse , or a 
quarteron  and a 
griffe  
This image is public domain 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Robespierre, May 1791 
 
The issue was not whether to  accord 
political rights  to the free people of 
color, but rather whether to 
conserve  rights they already 
enjoyed prior to the Revolution.  
 
[T]he old laws  (les lois 
anciennes ) had never been 
abrogated, and had vested free people 
of color with the same rights as 
white colonists.  Robespierre on free colored rights 
This image is public domain 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>These images are public domain 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Opening  of Code Noir 
This image is public domain 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Article 59 
 
We grant to freed slaves the same rights, 
privileges and immunities that are enjoyed 
by freeborn persons. We desire that they 
are deserving of this acquired freedom, 
and that this freedom gives them, as much 
for their person as for their property, the 
same happiness that natural liberty has on 
our other subjects.  Article 59 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Article 26 
 
Slaves who are not fed, clothed and maintained by 
their masters according to what we have ordered by 
these articles will be able to notify our attorney general 
and provide him with their statements, on the basis of 
which, and even on his own initiative, if the 
information comes to him from elsewhere, the masters 
will be prosecuted upon his motion and without cost, 
which we wish to be observed for the crimes and 
barbarous and inhumane treatment of masters towards 
their slaves. Article 26 
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Julien Raimond, 1791 pamphlet on the history  
of white prejudice against free people of color 
 
 
 Louis XIV had granted to freed persons, properly 
understood, the right of citizens.  
 
 
Will the National Assembly be less just than a 
despot? Raimond on free colored rights 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>1770 Map 
This image is public domain</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Britain&#8217;s Fatal Triumph: The English Colonies, 1754&#8211;1765</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_03/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Prelude to Revolt: A Review 
*1754-1763: French and Indian War (Seven Years War in Europe) ended in the Treaty of Paris/Peace of Paris. 
* April 1763-1766: Pontiacs Uprising: French allied Native nations and tribes in Ohio and the Ohio Valley follow the call of th e 
Delaware Prophet who urged them to return to their traditional ways of life, refuse closer economic relations with the triumph ant 
British, and resist further European encroachment on Indian lands.  The Ottawa Chief Pontiac takes up the call and begins to 
unite Indians across tribal and national divisions.  The Seneca (western Iroquois), Lenape, Wendat (Huron), Chippewa, Miami, 
Potawotomi, and dozens of smaller tribes join the uprising.  Much of this outrage and anger is fueled by Jeffrey Amhersts bl atant 
disrespect for Indian sovereignty and brutal tactics.  The British reputation for dishonesty in economic and military affairs is also a 
factor.   
*October 7, 1763: Proclamation of 1763 formalizes Britains acquisition of French territory in North America under the Treaty of Paris.  It 
also regulates trade and land expansion to reduce conflicts on the western frontier between white colonists and Native people s. 
*1764: Parliament enforces the Navigation Acts (1650) more stringently to move raw materials from the colonies, prohibit non-British 
goods and materials, and limit the ability of colonial actors to compete with English manufacturers.   (The most offensive of the 
acts was the Sugar Act of 1733, which threatened the profitable New England rum and molasses trades.) 
*March 22, 1765: Stamp Act passed to underwrite costs of maintaining ten thousand troops on the western frontier where the remnants 
of New France, the expansion of New Spain, and the rise of pan-Indian resistance posed threats. 
*March 5, 1770: Boston Massacre: A mob taunts a sentry at the Customs House and the conflict escalates as other British troops come 
to his aid.  The soldiers fire into the mob and five men are killed.  Crispus Attucks a black man is first person shot and, t hanks to 
Paul Reveres etching, becomes a symbolic martyr for the colonial cause.   
*summer 1765: Sons of Liberty: merchants and artisans in Boston --the Loyal Nine --begin organizing civil disobedience against the 
Stamp Act.  This movement grows into Sons of Liberty.  Organizations appear in all the colonies and force Stamp Act distributors 
to resign.  By 1766 royal governors are in hiding and the Sons manage to displace the royal governments in most of the colonies.   
*November 2, 1772: Committee of Correspondence created at the Boston town meeting to maintain discourse with other colonies o n 
rights and violations.   
*March-June 1774: The Intolerable Acts: Boston Port Act prohibits shipping into Boston Harbor in response to disorders; 
Administration of Justice Act regulates trials of those arrested or questioned in MA; Massachusetts Government Act transfers a 
broad range of public offices from election to appointment by the crown or governor; Quartering Act empowers governors to 
house the kings forces in uninhabited houses and other buildings as required for order and security; Quebec Act extends 
freedom of religion to Catholics in British Canada but also creates mechanism for establishing the Church of England.  
*April 1, 1774: Boston Tea Party: Mob dressed as Mohawks (eastern Iroquois) dump 342 crates of tea into Boston Harbor.  Four British 
regiments descend upon Boston and Governor Thomas Gage replaces Thomas Hutchinson.   
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Peter Jeffersons Son 
. . . and his friend Meriwether Lewis 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Queen Aliquippa, 1754  
George Washington and Christopher Gist pay homage 
Surveying lands in western Pennsylvania 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>The Conestoga Massacres 
The Extermination of the Susquehannocks, 1763 
The Paxton Boys march on Conestoga (Paxtung Presbyterian Church in  PA) 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>The Immigrant Trade 
The Pennsylvania Germans (Dutch) 
4This image is public domain.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>West of Appalachia     
 Mr. Floyd has sent you a Description of 3000 Acres of Land he surveyed last 
Summer and which has not been appropriated.  Should this suit, let me now by 
a Line &amp; I will make out a Certificate &amp; send it to any Place you direct.  As I 
imagine you will receive this before you set off for the Congress, you can send 
an Answer to the Care of Alex[ande]r Craig in W[illia]msburg at the meeting of 
the Merchants from whence I can readily get it.   
  But if this Land will not answer your Purpose I can readily have a Tract 
Surveyed as Floyd sets off tomorrow for the Ohio &amp; I can when I receive your 
Letter have an Opp[ortunit]y of writing him.  The Warrant should be lodged 
with me, if it is sent to Mr. Craig I can get it safe. 
 
  --Col. William Preston to General George Washington,  
  April 9, 1775 
 
(Washingtons family owns significant land claims in Pennsylvania and Ohio. 
Many Virginians have invested heavily in these western lands.) 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>George Washingtons Childhood 
Surveyor of Indian Lands  
Thomas Lord Fairfax VI 
 George Washington at 16 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Savages and Slaves 
The Racial Destiny of Colonial America . . . the number of purely white People in the  
World is proportionably very small. . . . why  
Should we in the Sight of Superior Beings,  
Darken its People?   why increase the sons  
of Africa, by Planting them in America, where 
we have so fair an Opportunity, by excluding 
all Blacks and Tawneys, of increasing the lovely 
White and Red?  But perhaps I am partial to the 
Complexion of my Country, for such kind of  
Partiality is natural to Mankind. 
  --Benjamin Franklin, 1751 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Colonel Washington  
The Virginia Militia Officer Surveys Ohio 
(while on duty during the French and Indian War) 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Eastern Elite v. Backcountry Settlers 
The Paxton Boys March toward Philadelphia 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The European Great Migration 
How Germans, Scots, Swedes, Hollanders (and Quakers and Presbyterians and Mennonites 
and Anglicans and Congregationalists and Hugenots and Lutherans) etc. became white. This image is public domain.
Map of European migration removed due to copyright
restrictions. See: Introduction to Colonization
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Britains Fatal Triumph 
The Aftermath of the French and Indian War (1754-1763) 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>The Advent of Biological Warfare 
At virtually the same moment that Franklin and other intellectual and political leaders are 
condemning the massacres in Conestoga and Lancaster, PA, Amherst is designing 
biological warfare against the western Indians and hes being celebrated as a hero.  
Col. Henry Bouquet and the Ottawa Chiefs 
Lord Jeffrey Amherst 
Commander of the British forces in North America 
10</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction and The 2011 Revolution in Egypt</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_01/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Mohamed Morsi, Member of the Muslim Brotherhood of Egypt 
Fifth President of Egypt (30 June 2012 to 3 July 2013), currently under arrest 
This image is public domain.
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain.
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Hosni Mubarak,  
Fourth President of Egypt, 
1981 -2011 
This image is public domain.
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Demographics 
Population of Egypt in 2013:  84,314,000 
Population of Other North African and Middle Eastern Countries (2012) 
 
Libya: 6.423,000 
Tunisia:  10,777,500 
Syria: 22,530,746 
Saudi Arabia: 29,195,895 
Iraq: 31,129,225 
Iran: 77,176,930 
Major Egyptian Cities  (2012): 
 
Cairo: 8,105,071 
Alexandria: 4,388,219 
Giza:  3,348,401  Religious Breakdown: 
 
Muslim (Sunni): 90% 
Coptic Christian: 9% 
Other Christian: 1% 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>THE OUSTER OF MUBARAK IN EGYPT 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Image courtesy of W123 on Wikipedia. CC-BY.
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>TWO QUESTIONS FOR RECITATION THIS WEEK : 
Why was Mubarak forced to resign the Presidency? 
Was the overthrow of Mubarak a revolution? 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Gamal  Abdel Nassar 
Second President of Egypt, 1954- 1970  
Emergency Law, 1967- 2012:  
 
Police powers extended 
Constitutional  rights suspended   
Heavy censorship  enforced  
All non-governmental political activity , street demonstrations , and  
 non-approved political organizations,unregistered financial  
 donations were formally banned.  
 
This image is public domain.
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Anwar Al-Sadat, Third President of Egypt, 1970-1981 
This image is public domain.
8</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Final Freedom? The Abolition of Slavery in Haiti</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Aerial view of Le Cap 
This image is public domain 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Jean-Franois and Biassou to the  
Civil Commissioners, Dec. 21, 1791  
The bad treatment of their masters, most of whom torture their slaves by 
mistreating them in all sorts of ways, taking away their two hours [of 
midday rest], and their holidays, and Sundays, leaving them naked, 
without any help even when they are sick, and letting them die of misery.  
Yes, sirs, how many barbarous masters there are who enjoy being cruel to 
these miserable slaves, or else managers or administrators who, to stay in 
their employers  good graces, afflict a thousand of the same cruelties on 
the slaves as they pretend to carry out their responsibilities. 
 
Oh, sirs, in the name of humanity, deign to look favorably on these 
unfortunates by clearly outlawing such harsh mistreatment, abolishing the 
terrible plantation prisons, . . . and trying to improve the condition of this 
class of men. 
 
 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Final Freedom?  
The Abolition of Slavery in Haiti 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>1770 Map 
This image is public domain 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>What is a Slave Revolution?/ 
What Does It Mean to Abolish Slavery? 
Improve the conditions of labor (more free days 
per week) for all slaves 
Free only the most prominent slave insurgents 
and permit them to exercise a leadership role 
Compensate for labor while keeping slaves 
attached to their plantations 
Rid the land of white masters/overseers 
Divide plantations into small landholdings to be 
maintained by peasants 
 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Sonthonax, Decree of Aug. 29, 1793 
To restore order and tranquility . . . 
 
All the negres and mixed blood peole currently in 
slavery are declared free to enjoy all the rights of 
French citizens; they are nevertheless subject to the 
[following] regime . . . 
 
The ngres currently working on the plantations of 
their former masters are required to remain there.  
They will work in agriculture . . . 
 
The Code Noir  is provisionally repealed.  
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>23 August.  Revolt of the negroes in Saint -
Domingue.  The contradictory decrees of the 
National Assembly on the freedom of the negroes, 
notably that of May 13, have handed the colony 
over to all of the horrors of civil war.  
This image is public domain 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>How Did Revolution in Haiti Begin? (II) The Slave Revolts</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Map of the Trans-Atlantic Slave Trade removed due to copyright restrictions.
See The Trans-Atlantic Slave Trade Database .
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>10 This image is public domain</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>What is a Slave Revolution?/  
What Does It Mean to Abolish Slavery?  
	 Improve the conditions of labor (more free days 
per week) for all slaves 
 Free only the most prominent slave insurgents  
and permit them to exercise a leadership role  
	 Compensate for labor while keeping slaves 
attached to their plantations 
	 Rid the land of white masters/overseers 
	 Divide plantations into small landholdings to be maintained by peasants 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution 
Fall  2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Jean-Franois and Biassou to the  
Civil Commissioners, Dec. 21, 1791
	
The bad treatment of their masters, most of whom torture their slaves by 
mistreating them in all sorts of ways, taking away their two hours [of midday rest], and their holidays, and Sundays, leaving them naked, 
without any help even when they are sick, and letting them die of misery. 
Yes, sirs, how many barbarous masters there are who enjoy being cruel to these miserable slaves, or else managers or administrators who, to stay in 
their employers  good graces, afflict a thousand of the same cruelties on 
the slaves as they pretend to carry out their responsibilities. 
Oh, sirs, in the name of humanity, deign to look favorably on these 
unfortunates by clearly outlawing such harsh mistreatment, abolishing the 
terrible plantation prisons, . . . and trying to improve the condition of this 
class of men. 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>1770 Map  
  
2 This image is public domain</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 This image is public domain</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>12 This image is public domain</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>News of the 1791 slave insurgency  
	 https://archive.org/stream/gazettedesaintdo0 
1moza#page/854/mode/2up 
	 https://archive.org/stream/gazettedesaintdo0 
1moza#page/890/mode/2up 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>How Did the Revolution in Haiti Begin? (II):  
The Slave Revolts  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>11 This image is public domain</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 This image is public domain</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>1770 Map  
  
9 This image is public domain</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Comparing the American, French, and Haitian Revolutions</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_24/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Prosperity or freedom? 
 
The outcome of the American Revolution, as 
distinct from the purposes which started it, has 
always been ambiguous, and the question of 
whether the end of government was to be 
prosperity or freedom has never been settled . 
(127)  
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Comparing the American,  
French, and Haitian Revolutions 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Hannah Arendt 
This image is 
public domain 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution 
Fall  2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>The Social Question  
The French Revolution  was overwhelmed by 
the cares and worries which actually belonged in 
the sphere of the household and which, even if 
they were permitted to enter the public realm, 
could not be solved by political means, since 
they were matters of administration, to be put 
into the hands of experts, rather than issues 
which could be settled by the twofold process of 
decision and persuasion . (81)  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>1969 photo of Hannah Arendt removed due to copyright restrictions. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Haiti and the Social Question  
 
[T]o avoid this fatal mistake [of trying to solve 
the social question with political means, thereby 
leading to terror] is almost impossible when a 
revolution breaks out under conditions of mass 
poverty. (102)  
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Revolution Today: Faculty and Student Discussion</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_26/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>26</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Goddess of Democracy, Tienanmien Square, 1989 
 
         
 Photos courtesy of Robert Corma and Matthew Black on Flickr. CC-BY-NC-SA.
Goddess of Democracy,  
University of British Columbia, 1991  
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The American Revolution  
. . . and Its Radical Legacies.  
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Of Fear and Reality  
The situation of the St. Domingo fugitives (aristocrats as they are) calls aloud for 
pity and charity. Never was so deep a tragedy presented to the feelings of 
man...I become daily more and more convinced that all the West India Island 
will remain in the hands of the people of colour, and a total expulsion of the 
whites sooner or later take place. It is high time we should foresee the bloody scenes which our children certainly, and possibly ourselves (south of the Potomac), have to wade through and try to avert them. 
--Jefferson to James Monroe 
14 July 1793 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>The Strange Career of American  
Revolution  
Do you realize that the Vietnamese people proclaimed their own independence 
in 1945 after a combined French and Japanese occupation. And incidentally, 
this was before the Communist revolution in China. They were led by Ho Chi 
Minh. And this is a little-known fact, and these people declared themselves 
independent in 1945. They quoted our Declaration of Independence in their 
document of freedom, and yet our government refused to recognize them. President Truman said they were not ready for independence. So we fell victim as a nation at that time of the same deadly arrogance that has 
poisoned the international situation for all of these years. 
--Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.  
Why I am Opposed to the War in Vietnam   
Riverside Church, NYC, 30 April, 1967  
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain.
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Delacroix, Liberty Leading Delacroix, Greece on the 
the People, 1830 
14 Ruins of Missolonghi, 1826</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Thomas Jefferson s Fears  
Behold you then, my dear friend, at the head of a great army, establishing the liberties of 
your country against a foreign enemy. may heaven favor your cause, and make you the 
channel thro  which it may pour it s [sic] favors. while you are exterminating the 
monster aristocracy, &amp; pulling out the teeth &amp; fangs of it s associate monarchy, a 
contrary tendency is discovered in some here. a sect has shewn itself among us, who 
declare they espoused our new constitution, not as a good &amp; sufficient thing itself, but 
only as a step to an English constitution, the only thing good &amp; sufficient in itself, in their eye. . . . what are you doing for your colonies? they will be lost if not more effectually succoured. indeed no future efforts you can make will ever be able to reduce the blacks. all that can be done in my opinion will be to compound with them as has 
been done formerly in Jamaica. we have been less zealous in aiding them, lest your 
government should feel any jealousy on our account. but in truth we as sincerely wish their restoration, and their connection with you, as you do yourselves. 
--Jefferson to the Marquis de Lafayette 
16 June 1792 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Jacques-Louis David, Intervention of the Sabine Women, 1799  
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Revolution Today  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Nanine Vallain , Libert , 1792 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Allegories of Liberty  
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Jacques-Louis David, Oath of the Horatii , 1785  
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>A-J Gros , Allegory of the Republic , 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Womens Rights Convention  
When, in the course of human events, it becomes necessary for one portion of the family of man 
to assume among the people of the earth a position different from that which they have 
hitherto occupied, but one to which the laws of nature and of nature s God entitle them, a 
decent respect to the opinions of mankind require that they should declare the causes that 
impel them to such a course. 
We hold these truths to be self-evident: that all men and women are created equal; that they are 
endowed by their Creator with certain inalienable rights; that among these are life, liberty 
and the pursuit of happiness; that to secure these rights governments are instituted, deriving their just powers from the consent of the governed. . . . Such has been the patient sufferance of the women under this government, and such is now the necessity which constrains them to demand the equal station to which they are entitled. 
The history of mankind is a history of repeated injuries and usurpations on the part of man 
toward woman, having in direct object the establishment of an absolute tyranny over her. . . 
--Seneca Fall, New York, 1848 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Delacroix, Liberty Leading the People , 1830  
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Frdric-Auguste Bartholdi,  
Statue of Liberty,  
Unveiled in New York  
Harbor, 1886  
16
Photo courtesy of andos_pics on Flickr. CC-BY-NC-SA.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Making of a Caribbean Plantation Colony: Slavery and Slave Revolts before the Revolution</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>These images are public domain 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Moreau le Jeune drawing of Code Noir invoked by slave, 
frontispiece to Bernardin de Saint-Pierre s Voyage  l Isle 
de France  (1773) 
This image is public domain 
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>A demographic transformation 
1681  
7,000 total 
65% white 
31% slave 
3% free black 
and mulatto  
 
1789 
530,000 total 
5% white 
90% slave 
5% free people of 
color 
 
 
 
 1700  
14,000 total 
29% white 
66% slave 
3.6% free black 
and mulatto 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>1770 Map 
This image is public domain 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Title Page of Code Noir (1735) 
This image is public domain 
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Map of the Trans-Atlantic Slave Trade removed due to copyright restrictions.
See The Trans-Atlantic Slave Trade Database.
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Article 42 
 
Only masters shall be permitted, when they 
believe their slaves so deserve, to chain them 
and beat them with canes or rope.  We forbid 
masters from applying torture to their slaves or 
from inflicting any kind of mutilation, on pain 
of confiscation of the slaves and special 
prosecution of the masters.  Article 42 
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>The Making of a Caribbean Plantation Colony: 
Slavery and Slave Revolts before the Revolution 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Frederick Douglass, speech at the 1893 
Chicago Worlds Fair  
We should not forget that the freedom you and 
I enjoy to-day, that the freedom that eight 
hundred thousand colored people enjoy today 
in the British West Indies; the freedom that has 
come to the colored race the world over, is 
largely due to the brave stand taken by the black 
sons of Haiti ninety years ago.  When they struck 
for freedom . . . they struck for the freedom of 
every black man in the world.  
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Article 26 
 
Slaves who are not fed, clothed and maintained by 
their masters according to what we have ordered by 
these articles will be able to notify our attorney general 
and provide him with their statements, on the basis of 
which, and even on his own initiative, if the 
information comes to him from elsewhere, the masters 
will be prosecuted upon his motion and without cost, 
which we wish to be observed for the crimes and 
barbarous and inhumane treatment of masters towards 
their slaves. Article 26 
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>These images are public domain 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Opening  of Code Noir 
This image is public domain 
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
25</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Road to Independence: Toussaint Louverture&#8217;s Story</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>1770 Map 
This image is public domain 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>The Road to Independence: 
Toussaint Louvertures Story 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Camp Turel Proclamation, Aug. 29, 1793 
Brothers and friends  
 
I am Toussaint Louverture; perhaps my name has made itself 
known to you.  I have undertaken vengeance.  I want Liberty 
and Equality to reign in Saint Domingue.  I am working to 
make that happen.  Unite yourselves to us, brothers, and fight 
with us for the same cause. 
 
Your very humble and obedient servant, 
 
Toussaint Louverture. 
General of the armies of the king, for the public good.  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>This image is public domain 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Images of Fort de Joux and a statue of Toussaint Louverture removed
due to copyright restrictions. Please see: Above links to Wikipedia.
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>1770 Map 
This image is public domain 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>These images are public domain 
10</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Race and Revolution: Slavery and the Roots of Colonial Independence</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_04/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>The Dirty Business of the Empire 
The Triangular Trade and the European Perception of America 
QuickTime and a
 decompressor
are needed to see this picture.
This image is public domain 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Enlightened Racism 
The first difference which strikes us is that of colour.  . . . And is the difference of no importance?  Is it not the 
foundation of a greater or less share of the beauty in the two races?  Are not the fine mixtures of red and 
white , the expressions of every passion by greater or less suffusions of colour in the one, preferable to that 
eternal monotony, of black  which covers all the emotions of the other race?  Add to these, flowing hair, a 
more elegant symmetry of form, their own judgment in favour of the whites , declared by their preference of 
them, as uniformly as is the preference of the Oranootan (orangutan) for the black  women over those of his 
own species.  The circumstance of superior beauty, is thought worthy attention in the propagation of our 
horses, dogs, and other domestic animals; why not in that of man? 
. . . They secrete less by the kidnies, and more by the glands of the skin, which gives them a strong and 
disagreeable odour.  . . . They seem to require less sleep. . . . They are at least as brave, and more 
adventuresome.  But this may perhaps proceed from a want of fore-thought, which prevents their seeing a 
danger till it be present.   
      --Thomas Jefferson 
        Notes on the State of Virginia , 1781- 82 
This image is public domain 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Savages and Slaves 
The Racial Destiny of Colonial America . . . the number of purely white People in the  
World is proportionably very small. . . . why  
Should we in the Sight of Superior Beings,  
Darken its People?   why increase the sons  
of Africa, by Planting them in America, where 
we have so fair an Opportunity, by excluding 
all Blacks and Tawneys, of increasing the lovely 
White and Red?  But perhaps I am partial to the 
Complexion of my Country, for such kind of  
Partiality is natural to Mankind. 
  --Benjamin Franklin, 1751 
This image is public domain 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>There has been in town a conspiracy of the negroes.  At present it is kept 
pretty private, and was discovered by one who endeavoured to 
dissuade them from it.  He being threatened with his life, applied to 
Justice Quincy for protection. . . . I wish most sincerely there was not a 
slave in the province; it always appeared a most iniquitous scheme to 
me to fight ourselves for what we are daily robbing and plundering from 
those who have as good a right to freedom as we have. 
   
  --Abigail Adams,  
   Boston Garrison  
       22 September 1774 
This image is public domain 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Race and Revolution 
His Royal Highness George III, King of Great Britain, the Worlds Largest Empire  
This is supposing the present race of kings in the world to have had an honorable 
origin; whereas it is more than probable, that could we take off the dark covering of 
antiquity, and trace them to their first rise, that we should find the first of them nothing 
better than the principal ruffian of some restless gang, whose savage manners or 
pre-eminence in subtility obtained him the title of chief among plunderers; and who by  
increasing in power, and extending his depredations, over-awed the quiet and  
defenseless to purchase their safety by frequent contributions.   
   --Thomas Paine, Common Sense , 1776  
This image is public domain 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Markets and Modernity 
Slavery and the Rise of the Atlantic World 
This image is public domain 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Review: American Slavery and the 
Fates of Native Peoples 
By 1750 the population of African people on the Atlantic Coast of North America 
is greater than the Native American population east of the Mississippi.  
In a generation there will be more African peoples on the Atlantic Coast than 
there are Native Americans in all of the territories that will become the 
continental United States (Eastern, Mid-Western, Southern, Great Plains, and 
Western Indians combined).   
These enslaved people are concentrated in the agricultural and manufacturing 
regions that are driving the economic expansion and population growth in the 
Thirteen Colonies. 
Historians have documented 33,387  slaving voyages, between 1514 and 1866, 
of the type described in class.  These ships transported 12,521,336 men 
(64.6%), women (35.4%), and children (20.9%) into the Americas.  The 
Caribbean and Brazil were the primary destinations for slave ships but 
thousands of ships embarked from the British North American mainland.  The 
average death rate on a ship (for the enslaved) was 11.9%.  
After 1800 there are more Africans in the American slave colonies and nations 
than indigenous peoples in all of the Americas.  The Native population of the 
Americas has dropped from 53,904,000  in 1492 to 8,470,000 in 1820.     
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Race and Liberty  
He has endeavoured to prevent the population of these states; for that purpose obstructing the 
laws for naturalization of foreigners, refusing to pass others to encourage their migrations 
hither, and raising the conditions of the new appropriations of lands. 
 
He has excited domestic insurrections amongst us, and has endeavoured to bring on the 
inhabitants of our frontiers, the merciless Indian Savages, whose known rule of warfare, is 
an undistinguished destruction of all ages, sexes and conditions. 
 
[He has incited treasonable insurrections of our fellow citizens, with the allurements of forfeiture 
and confiscation of our property.   
He has waged cruel war against human nature itself, violating its most sacred rights of life and 
liberty in the persons of a distant people who never offended him, captivating and carrying 
them into slavery in another hemisphere, or to incur a miserable death in their transportation 
thither.  This piratical warfare, the opprobrium of INFIDEL powers, is the warfare of the 
CHRISTIAN king of Great Britain.  Determined to keep open a market where MEN should be 
bought and sold, he has prostituted his negative for suppressing every legislative attempt to 
prohibit or to restrain this execrable commerce.  And that this assemblage of horrors might 
want no fact of distinguished die, he is now exciting those very people to rise among us, and 
to purchase that liberty of which he has deprived them, by murdering the people for whom 
he also obtruded them: the paying off former crimes committed against the LIBERTIES of 
one people, with crimes which he urges them to commit against the LIVES of another.]  
    --The Declaration of Independence, 1776 
7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Endings and Beginnings</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-001-how-to-stage-a-revolution-fall-2013/resources/mit21h_001f13_lec_12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Recitation Debate Prompt: 
 
 
The events in Egypt in 2011 and 2012  
parallel developments in France from  
1789 to 1794. 
 
 
Prepare 
arguments for both  
the pro and con positions. 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>The Constitution of 1795 
Legislature:  Bicameral; Council of 500 to initiate all legislation; Council of Elders  
(250, married or widowed, over 40 years old) to pass or reject, but not amend, legislation  
from Council of 500; 2/3 of first councils to come from previous National Convention;  
has complete control over treasury and law, and can declare war 
V oting:  Direct universal male suffrage over 21, but only eligible to vote for representatives  
to electoral assemblies.  These representatives must own or rent property worth 100-200  
days worth of labor (about 60,000 electors).  These electors in turn elect the 750 deputies  
to the two Councils.  
Executive:  No king; instead a Directory of five members, chosen by the Elders from a list  
presented by the 500.  A new Director each year, so that the entire body would turn over  
every 5 years.  Assembly also chooses ministers, who report directly to Assembly  
(no Cabinet).  Directory could not initiate, make, or veto laws, but only suggest laws to  
Council of 500; can conduct diplomacy, supervise military, and enforce laws. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>A-C-G Lemonnier, 
Entre deux chaises: 
le cul par terre , 1797 
Directory Coups 
1)Year V (1797): 182 of 234 deputies elected 
 are royalists   arrest of 2 directors, 53 deputies,  
Closing of rt-wing newspapers, deportations of royalists. 
2)Year VII (1799):  Neo-Jacobins growing too strong,  
purge 3 Directors, leads to 18- 19 Brumaire coup against 
Council of 500, end of Directory. 
This image is public domain 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Toussaint Louverture  
&amp; Napolon Bonaparte 
These images are public domain 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>When did the  
French Revolution  
end? 
Satirical, post- 
Thermidorian print: 
Robespierre  
guillotining the last  
executioner.  
This image is public domain 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Vicomte Paul Barras, 
Aristocrat and Officer 
Paul Barras, 
Director The Directory, 
1795-1799  
These images are public domain 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Jacques-Louis David, 
Portrait of Emmanuel- 
Josph Sieys , 1817 
(Fogg Art Museum, 
Harvard University) 
This image is public domain 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Jacques-Louis David, 
Napoleon Crossing 
The Alps, 1801  
This image is public domain 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Eighteenth-Century Map of the Caribbean 
This image is public domain 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Hyacinthe Rigaud,  
Louis XIV , 1701 J-A-D Ingres, Napoleon 
Enthroned, 1806 
The First Empire,  
1804-1815  
These images are public domain 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>This image is CC-0 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Declaration of the Rights and  
Duties of Citizens, 22 August 1795  
Rights 
 
2)Liberty consists in the power to do that which does not injure the rights of others. 
3)Equality consists in this, that the law is the same for all, whether it protects  
 or punishes.  
4)Security results from the cooperation of all in order to assure the rights of each. 
5)Property is the right to enjoy and to dispose of one s goods, income, and the 
  fruits of one s labor and industry. 
 
Duties 
 
1)The declaration of rights contains the obligations of the legislators; the  
 maintenance of society requires that those who compose it should both 
 know and fulfill their duties. 
4)No one is a good citizen unless he is a good son, good father, good brother,  
 good friend, good husband. 
8)It is upon the maintenance of proerty that the cultivation of the land, all the  
 productions, all means of labor, and the whole social ordre rest. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Endings &amp; Beginnings 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21H.001 How to Stage a Revolution
Fall 2013
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>The Bourbon Restoration, 
1815 
Louis XVI, 1789 Louis XVIII,  ca. 1815 
These images are public domain 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Bacler d/Albe, General 
Bonaparte in Milan in  
Year V  (1797). 
This image is public domain 
10</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
