<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/</course_url>
    <course_title>Human Origins and Evolution</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Anthropology </list>
      <list>Archaeology </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Modern Primates and their Relevance to Understanding Human Origins</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture05/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution Spring, 2006 
Key Terms, Concepts and questions to ponder 
Lecture 5: Primates - their importance in understanding human evolution 
You should become familiar with the following terms and concepts from this lecture and your 
accompanying readings in Campbell et al. You should also give some consideration to the problems and 
issues mooted in the "To Ponder" section. 
Vocabulary 
Primates 
Prosimii (prosimians)
lemurs
lorises
tarsiers
Anthropoidea (anthropoids) -monkeys, and apes including humans
Ceboidea - Platyrrhini   -New World monkeys
Cercopithecoidea - Catarrhini -Old World monkeys
Hominoidea (hominoids) - apes, lesser and greater including humans
Hylobatidae (hylobatids) - gibbons and siamangs
Pongidae (pongids) - orangutans
Panidae (panids) -gorilla, chimpanzee, bonobo (pygmy chimp)
Hominidae (hominids) - humans
features characterizing Primates 
features characterizing hominoids 
reproductive strategies: parental investment 
K - selection -pattern of few offspring and extensive parental care 
r -selection -pattern of large number of offspring and little parental care 
To Ponder 
) What selection pressures might have selected for bonobo behaviors?
) What selection pressures might have selected for chimpanzee behaviors?
) How does the environment contribute to selection pressures in terms of
distribution of food resources?
availability of safety and shelter?
presence of predators?
) What behavioral characteristics are likely to have been displayed by the common ancestor of chimps, 
bonobos and humans?  
) Can we always recognize when similar modern traits are derived from a common ancestor, as opposed 
to similarities which evolved in parallel? 
) What is the role of sexual dimorphism in Primate species? 
) What are the roles of canines and canine dimorphism in Primates?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Early Hominids - Variations and Taxonomy - Presentations</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture09/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>) Energy efficiency of bipedal locomotion model 
special advantage of bipedalism -greatest energy efficiency - walking at a slow pace. 
) Thermo-regulation model  -P. Wheeler  (1991)
bipedalism reduces skin exposure to sun and heating in midday.
Models involving reproductive and social behaviors relating to food acquisition 
) Provisioning/supplemental feeding model -Lovejoy 
) Dual reciprocity subsistence model -food sharing  -Isaac 
Models involving behaviors relating to social cooperation within and between groups 
) Coalitional enforcement hypothesis -Bingham
the possibility of remote killing promotes social cooperation</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>argues for primacy of gathering - based on chimp models - female chimps more frequent tool 
users 
long range gathering and foraging strategy in which adults carried babies, tools and food over a 
wide range, eventually becoming upright bipeds. 
female food gathering/tool use heightened sociability and increased communication was 
advantageous, leading to brain/culture elaboration. 
) Aquatic ape hypothesis -Elaine Morgan  -1972 - The Descent of Woman 
-a feminist viewpoint  (developed ideas first suggest by a marine biologist, Alister Hardy in 1960) 
argues apes became aquatic in the late Miocene and the Pliocene as the African environment 
dried out, animals took to water for shelter and resources. -Then returned to land in the past 
couple of million years.  
a recent variant (2002) of the underlying aquatic nature of early hominin evolution is that of M. 
Verhaegen who suggests that bipedalism is an adaptation for wetland wading and climbing as early 
hominins foraged for plants in shallow water and along stream channels 
Dietary and foraging posture related models 
) Small object feeding -C. Jolly (1970) Seed eaters 
based on baboon model - Theropithecus gelada 
developed as a feeding posture to eating small objects which are evenly distributed within patches, in 
low trees and bushes. A refinement of these views can be found in 
Mark F. Teaford and Peter S. Ungar 
2000 Diet and the evolution of the earliest human ancestors. Proceeding of the National Academy of Sciences USA 97 (25) 13506-11. 
Abstract: Over the past decade, discussions of the evolution of the earliest human ancestors have focused on the 
locomotion of the australopithecines. Recent discoveries in a broad range of disciplines have raised important 
questions about the influence of ecological factors in early human evolution. Here we trace the cranial and dental 
traits of the early australopithecines through time, to show that between 4.4 million and 2.3 million years ago, the 
dietary capabilities of the earliest hominids changed dramatically, leaving them well suited for life in a variety of 
habitats and able to cope with significant changes in resource availability associated with long-term and short-term 
climatic fluctuations. 
) Foraging postures - Recently Jonathan Kingdon (2003) in Lowly Origin suggests that bipedalism 
arises as a condition from preadaptations evolved among Miocene squat feeding ground apes. Features such as stable flexed leg, broad pelvis, flexible waist, vertical spine, good head balance and mobile shoulders evolve before bipedalism. 
) Habitat Variability/Instability  -R. Potts (1996) 
bipedalism as an adaptation to instability of habitats in periods of marked environmental change. Bipedalism combined with retained arboreal abilities provides earliest hominids a wide and flexible ecological niche. 
Energy efficiency models -based on the assumption that bipedal locomotion is evolving in an 
open hot tropical savanna among diurnal gathering and ?scavenging/hunting? hominoids.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution Spring, 2006 
Lecture 9:  Key Terms and Concepts 
Vocabulary: 
prime movers hypotheses
multiple factor/systems approaches theories
teleology models
scenarios 
Notes: Hominin/human origins:  hypotheses and speculation 
prime movers versus more integrated approaches in explaining origins of humans/hominids 
the fallacy of teleology - A doctrine explaining phenomena by final causes or outcomes. 
The two major developments in human evolution 
) transition to bipedal locomotion 
) elaboration of brain/culture system 
Generally acknowledged functions of bipedalism 
) seeing over tall grass - greater ability to avoid predators 
) carrying weapons 
) tool use, free hands 
) long distance stride and energy efficiency 
) carrying young (delayed maturation - longer learning time) 
) provisioning - carrying food 
) thermo-regulation potential 
Conditions for the original adoption of bipedalism - continued debate 
arboreal bipedalism
forest and woodland floor adaptation
savanna, light woodland adaptation
Hypotheses -old and new 
) Tool use and hunting hypothesis -Darwin is an early proponent  -male focus,  esp. hunting 
principal elements:  bipedalism, tool using in hunting/defense, small canines, intelligence, manual 
skills, tool making, tool using - sociability 
) Tool use and gathering hypothesis -Nancy Tanner  -On Becoming Human a response to 
perceived male chauvinistic bias of previous model</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Homo ergaster and erectus: Emerging Modern Morphology</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture16_17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution Spring, 2006 
Lectures 16 -17: Key terms, concepts and questions to ponder 
You should become familiar with the following terms, concepts, people and places from your readings 
in Campbell et al. and the reader for these two lectures.  You should also give some consideration to the 
problems and issues mooted in the "To Ponder" section. 
Vocabulary 
Homo ergaster 
Nariokotome (KNM-WT-15000) 
Dmanisi (Georgia) 
KNM-ER-1808 hypervitaminosis A 
Homo erectus 
Pithecanthropus Trinil Ngandong 
Sinanthropus Zhoukoudian (Choukoutien) 
taurodontism 
Homo antecessor Atapuerca
Lower Palaeolithic / Early Stone Age (Mode 1 and 2 technologies)
Acheulian Industrial Complex Olorgesailie 
bifaces Kilombe 
handaxes Terra Amata 
cleavers Berekhat Ram 
Schningen 
Homo floresiensis 
Chopper/Chopping Tool Tradition 
Movius line 
soft hammer percussion 
levallois core technique (prepared core technique) 
To Ponder 
) Provide short answers for the "Review Questions" in Chapters 10 - 13 of Campbell et al. 
) What sort of factors, physical and/or cultural were probably involved with the expansion of Homo 
erectus  (ergaster) from tropical African regions to the rest of Eurasia? 
P.T.O.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>--------------------------------------------------------) Did Homo erectus apparently stagnate with regard to material culture, as Campbell et al. suggest 
(p.308, #2). 
) Are there strong reasons for arguing that hunting, the development of male and female 
roles and home bases first evolved with Homo erectus, as opposed to with earlier forms 
of Homo, like habilis or rudolfensis? 
) How would we recognize evidence of intraspecific violence among early hominids? 
) How much may the vagaries of archaeological preservation of organic materials have influenced our perception of the cultural capabilities of Homo erectus? 
Lectures 16 - 17: Homo ergaster, erectus and slowly emerging modern human behaviors  -additional notes 
More skulls of Homo ergaster  from Dmanisi 
Vekua, A.,  D. Lordkipanidze,  G.P. Rightmire,  J. Agusti,  R. Ferring,  G. Maisuradze,  A. Mouskhelishvili,  M. 
Nioradze, M. Ponce de Leon,  M. Tappen,  M. Tvalchrelidze, and  C. Zollikofer. 
2002 A New Skull of Early Homo from Dmanisi,Georgia. Science 297:85-89. (5 JULY 2002) 
Abstract: Another hominid skull has been recovered at Dmanisi (Republic of Georgia) from the same strata in which 
hominid remains have been reported previously.  The Dmanisi site dated to ca. 1.75 million years ago has now produced 
craniofacial portions of several hominid individuals, along with many well-preserved animal fossils and quantities of stone 
artifacts. Although there are certain anatomical differences among the Dmanisi specimens, the hominids do not clearly 
represent more than one taxon.  We assign the new skull provisionally to Homo erectus (= ergaster). The Dmanisi 
specimens are the most primitive and small-brained fossils to be grouped with this species or any taxon linked unequivocally 
with genus Homo and also the ones most similar to the presumed habilis -like stem.  We suggest that the ancestors of the 
Dmanisi population dispersed from Africa before the emergence of humans identified broadly with the H.erectus grade. 
Lordkipanidze, D., A. Vekua,  R. Ferring,  G.P. Rightmire,  J. Agusti,  G. Kiladze,  A. Mouskhelishvili,  M. 
Nioradze, M. Ponce de Leon,  M. Tappen and  C. Zollikofer. 
2005 Anthropology: The earliest toothless hominin skull. 
Nature 434, 717 -718 (07 April 2005) 
Abstract: The site of Dmanisi in the Eurasian republic of Georgia has yielded striking hominin, faunal and archaeological 
material as evidence for the presence of early Homo outside Africa 1.77 million years ago, documenting an important 
episode in human evolution. Here we describe a beautifully preserved skull and jawbone from a Dmanisi hominin of this 
period who had lost all but one tooth several years before death. This specimen not only represents the earliest case of 
severe masticatory impairment in the hominin fossil record to be discovered so far, but also raises questions about 
alternative subsistence strategies in early Homo. 
An offspring of Homo erectus ? 
Brown, P., T. Sutikna, M. J. Morwood, R. P. Soejono, Jatmiko, E. Wayhu Saptomo &amp; Rokus Awe Due 
2004 A new small-bodied hominin from the Late Pleistocene of Flores, Indonesia. 
Nature 431:1055-61. 
Abstract: Currently, it is widely accepted that only one hominin genus, Homo, was present in Pleistocene Asia, represented 
by two species, Homo erectus and Homo sapiens. Both species are characterized by greater brain size, increased body 
height and smaller teeth relative to Pliocene Australopithecus in Africa. Here we report the discovery, from the Late 
Pleistocene of Flores, Indonesia, of an adult hominin with stature and endocranial volume approximating 1m and 380 cm3,
respectivelyequal to the smallest-known australopithecines. The combination of primitive and derived features assigns 
this hominin to a new species, Homo floresiensis. The most likely explanation for its existence on Flores is long-term 
isolation, with subsequent endemic dwarfing, of an ancestral H. erectus population. Importantly, H. floresiensis shows that 
the genus Homo is morphologically more varied and flexible in its adaptive responses than previously thought.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>&#8220;Archaics&#8221;: Not Quite Us Physically, Not Quite Us Mentally</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture19_20/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19-20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution Spring, 2006 
Lecture 19 and 20:  The Neandertals 
Vocabulary and questions to ponder 
You should become familiar with the following terms, concepts, people and places from 
your readings in Campbell et al. (Ch. 14) for these lectures.  
Vocabulary 
Homo neanderthalensis     ( a.k.a.  Homo sapiens neanderthalensis )
Feldhofer Cave  (Germany)
La Chapelle-aux-Saints  (France) La Ferrassie (France)
Shanidar (Iraq)
Neandertals as examples of Bergmanns and Allens rules 
Bergmanns rule
1) among mammals of similar shape, the larger mammal loses heat less rapidly 
than the smaller mammal, and 
2) among mammals of similar size, the mammal with a more linear shape will lose 
heat more rapidly than the mammal with a non-linear shape. 
Allens rule 
1) mammals in cold climates tend to have short bulky limbs, allowing less loss of 
body heat and, 
2) mammals in hot climates tend to have long slender limbs, allowing greater loss 
of body heat. 
Sites with Neandertal mtDNA evidence
Feldhofer Cave  (Germany)
Mezmaiskaya Cave (northern Caucasus region)
Vindija Cave (Croatia)
Upper Pleistocene Wrm glaciation
Middle Palaeolithic Middle Stone Age
prepared core technologies
Levallois core technology
disk core technology
Sites
Combe Grenal (France) Vindija Cave (Croatia)
Shanidar (Iraq) Monte Circeo (Italy)
Tata (Hungary) Divje Babe I  (Solvenia)
Mobility patterns
Radiating mobility Circulating mobility
(Neandertals) (modern H. sap. sap.)
Tabun Qafzeh
Kebara Skhul</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Origin of Modern Homo sapiens : Morphology and Genetic Evidence</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture21_22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution	 Spring, 2006 
Lectures 21 - 22:   Key terms, concepts and questions to ponder 
You should become familiar with the following terms, concepts, people and places from 
your readings in Campbell et al (9th ed.) Ch. 15 and 16,   [Campbell/Loy (8th ed), Ch. 16 and 
17] for these two lectures.  You should also give some consideration to the problems and issues 
mooted in the "To Ponder" section. 
Vocabulary 
Homo sapiens sapiens 
archaic Homo sapiens 
Cro-Magnonman 
anatomically modern H. sapiens 
Herto 	 (Ethiopia) 
Upper Palaeolithic
Chatelperronian
Aurignacian
Gravettian (Perigordian) 
Solutrean 
Magdalenian 
Dolni Vestonice 
To Ponder regional continuity hypothesis 
rapid replacement hypothesis 
mtDNA 
behaviorally modern H. sapiens 
Omo - Kibish  (Ethiopia) 
blade technology (indirect percussion) 
backed blades 
burins 
venus figurines 
geometric microliths
groove and splinter technique 
Lascaux 
)	 Describe the changes that took place in human culture across the Middle/Upper 
Palaeolithic transition.  What are the alternate ways of explaining this corpus of 
dramatic changes? 
)	 What are the implications of the regional continuity and rapid replacement models for 
understanding the nature and time depth of modern human morphological variation 
among regional populations.today? 
)	 What are the implications of the increasing rate of change and increasing regional 
variation in tool kits (both stone and other materials) in the Upper Palaeolithic? 
)	 How do the vagaries of preservation and the historical accident of where most 
archaeological research has been conducted influence our understanding and 
perspective on human cultural development over the past 40,000 years?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Modern Homo sapiens I: Cultural Diversity Becomes the Norm</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22-23</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution Spring, 2006 
Lecture 22:  Upper Palaeolithic Art -   Key terms and concepts 
Vocabulary 
Upper Palaeolithic industries  (western Europe) 
Magdalenian 
Solutrean 
Gravettian (Perigordian) 
Aurignacian 
Chatelperronian (associated with Neandertals at Arcy-sur-Cure and St. Csaire) 
chattel or mobile art 
parietal or fixed art 
venus figurines 
spear throwers  (atlatls) 
Sites: (French unless otherwise noted) 
Grotte Chauvet        (http://www.culture.gouv.fr/culture/arcnat/chauvet/en/index.html) 
Doln Vstonice (Czech Republic) 
Willendorf (Austria) noted for Venus figurine 
Isturitz carved bone batons, engravings 
St. Michel dArudy horse image with possible bridle 
Le Roc de Sers bas-relief carved wild cattle 
Lascaux 
Brassempouy realistic Venus figurine head 
Le Tuc dAudoubert modeled clay bison on cave floor 
Niaux 
Rouffignac 
Altamira (Spain) [1st recognition of age of Up. Pal. paintings] 
Pech Merle 
Gargas (Spain) hand imprints 
Vogelherd (Germany) early sculpture in the round - horse image</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Earliest Hominids: The Australopithecines and Affines</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture07_09/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7-8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution	 Spring, 2006 
Lectures 7 to 9:   Key terms, concepts and questions to ponder 
You should become familiar with the following terms, concepts, people and places from your 
readings in Campbell et al and the other assigned readings for these three lectures. You should also give some 
consideration to the problems and issues mooted in the "To Ponder" section. 
Vocabulary 
Australopithecus australopithecines 
Sahelanthropus tchadensis ca. 6 - 7 myr Chad 
Orrorin tugenensis ca. 6.0 myr Baringo Hills, Kenya 
Ardipithecus ramidus ca. 5.5 - 4.6 myr Awash, Ethiopia 
(initially Australopithecus ramidus) 
Ardipithecus kadabba Middle Awash 
Australopithecus 
A. anamensis	 West Turkana, Allia Bay 
A. afarensis	 Laetoli, Hadar 
A. africanus	 Taung, Sterkfontein S. Africa 
A. garhi	 Middle Awash, Ethiopia 
A. bahrelghazali	 Lake Chad 
Kenyanthropus platyops ca. 3.5 myr West Turkana 
Paranthropus 
P. aethiopicus	 West Turkana, S.W. Ethiopia 
P. boisei	 Olduvai Gorge, Koobi Fora, S.W. Ethiopia 
P. robustus	 S. Africa 
type specimen 
Raymond Dart Osteodontokeratic culture 
To Ponder 
)	How are 'species' of living animals recognized and defined? How are fossil species recognized. Are 
living and fossil species comparable entities? 
)	Why is it so difficult for palaeoanthropologists to determine how many hominid species and genera they have discovered, and how they relate to one another evolutionarily? 
)	What theoretical positions underlie "lumping" and "splitting" in the classification and taxonomy of 
fossil Plio-Pleistocene hominids? 
)	What are the variables commonly cited as possibly contributing to the reduction of canine size in early 
hominids? 
)	How can we recognize which early hominids were potential makers and users of stone tools? What are 
the sources of evidence available to us to attempt this?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Early Homo: How Should Homo Be Defined?</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Figure 3. Oblique views of KNM-ER 1470, the lectotype132 of Homo rudolfensis , and KNM-ER 
1813, the best-preserved cranium of Homo habilis  sensu stricto.31 It has been proposed that 
both these taxa should be transferred from Homo to Australopithecus . These species would 
thus become, respectively, Australopithecus rudolfensis  (Alexeev, 1986)130 Wood and Collard, 
199964 and Australopithecus habilis  (Leakey, Tobias, and Napier, 1964)31 Wood and Collard, 
1999.64
 
Figure 4. Lateral views of KNM- ER 3733, a representative of Homo ergaster , and KNM-ER 1813, 
a representative of Australopithecus habilis . 
 
 Images of skulls removed due to copyright restrictions.Images of skulls removed due to copyright restrictions.(E, F, G) (A, B, C)
Monophyly Common adaptive 
strategy
An illustration of the conflict between defining a genus using claclistic 
and evolutionary systematic criteria. With which group of species should species D be classified?. If it is grouped with species A, B, and C, the 
resulting genus would be monophyletic but not adaptively coherent, whereas 
if it is grouped with species E, F, and G, the resulting genus would be adaptively coherent but not monophyletic.D
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution Spring, 2006 
Lecture 11:   Key Terms, Concepts and questions to ponder 
You should become familiar with the following terms and concepts from your readings in Campbell et 
al and Wood and Collard, 1999 for this lecture. You should also give some consideration to the problems and 
issues mooted in the "To Ponder" section. 
Vocabulary 
Homo habilis ? (Australopithecus habilis) 
Homo rudolfensis (?Kenyanthropus rudolfensis?) ? (Australopithecus rudolfensis) 
Homo ergaster 
monophyly common adaptive strategy 
Notes: 
Definition of the genus Homo -historical perspectives 
Competing definitions of the genus category 
) evolutionary systematic method 
a genus is a species or group of species of common ancestry that occupies a 
different ecological situation or adaptive zone than occupied by the species of 
another genus. 
for a very reasoned defense of the traditional evolutionary taxonomic method and its 
application to recognizing genera, see  Marks, J. 2005.  Phylogenetic trees and 
evolutionary forests.  Evolutionary Anthropology 14:49-53. 
) cladistic method 
a genus is a group of species that are more closely related to one another than they 
are to any species assigned to another genus. 
for an attempt to address both the issue of genera as monophyletic entities and the 
recognition of genera as presenting different adaptive zones see Wood, B. and M. Collard, 
1999 The changing face of genus Homo. Evolutionary Anthropology 8(6):195-207. 
To Ponder 
) What are the characteristics which distinguish Australopithecus  from Homo?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Homo heidelbergensis and neanderthalensis or Early &#8220;Archaic&#8221; H. sapiens?</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture18_19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution Spring, 2006 
Lectures 18 - 19:   Successors to Homo erectus 
Key terms, concepts and questions to ponder 
You should become familiar with the following terms, concepts, people and places from 
your readings in Campbell/Loy for these three lectures.  You should also give some consideration 
to the problems and issues mooted in the "To Ponder" section. 
Vocabulary 
Homo antecessor 
Homo heidelbergensis 
Homo neanderthalensis 
Homo sapiens 
Candelabra model 
(regional continuity) 
Middle Palaeolithic 
Mousterian Industry 
Mousterian of Acheulian Tradition 
Typical Mousterian 
Denticulate Mousterian 
La Quina Mousterian 
La Ferrassie Mousterian 
Bodo archaic Homo sapiens 
Homo sapiens neanderthalensis 
Homo sapiens sapiens 
Noahs Ark model 
(replacement hypothesis, Out of Africa) 
Middle Stone Age 
prepared core technologies 
Levallois core technology 
disc core technology 
Kabwe</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Tertiary Higher Primates: Our Pre-Hominid Predecessors</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture06/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution Spring, 2006 
Lecture 6:   Key Terms, Concepts and questions to ponder 
You should become familiar with the following terms and concepts from your readings in Campbell et 
al for this lectures.  You should also give some consideration to the problems and issues mooted in the "To 
Ponder" section. 
Vocabulary 
continental drift 
Laurasia Gondwanaland 
arboreal hypothesis visual predation hypothesis 
Eocene 
Adapidae 
Omomyidae Siamopithecus 
dental formulas postorbital bar 
prosimians anthropoids 
Oligocene Fayum Depression 
oligopithecines parapithecids 
propliopithecids Aegyptopithecus 
catarrhines platyrrhines 
Miocene 
Proconsul Oreopithecus 
Sivapithecus Gigantopithecus 
Dryopithecus 
dental apes suspensory apes 
To Ponder 
)	 What features distinguish prosimians from higher primates? 
)	 Campbell et al. point out that perhaps 2 to 4 % of the 5-7,000 fossil primates species which probably 
existed in the last 60 millions years are known to us.  What factors contribute to the scarcity and 
incompleteness of the primate fossil record?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction: The Search for Human Ancestors, Approaches to the Study of Human Evolution and an Introduction to Human Osteology</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture01_02/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1-2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution	 Spring, 2006 
Lectures 1 - 2:   Key Terms, Concepts and questions to ponder 
You should become familiar with the following terms and concepts from the first two 
lectures and your readings in Campbell/Loy.    You should also give some consideration to the 
problems and issues mooted in the "To Ponder" section. 
Vocabulary 
palaeoanthropology archaeology 
palaeontology anthropology 
principle of superposition (Stenos law) parsimony (Occams Razor) 
uniformitarianism (Charles Lyell) natural selection  (Charles Darwin) 
Geological Time Scale	 continental drift 
relative dating chronometric dating 
stratigraphy K-Ar dating 
biostratigraphy (faunal correlation) palaeomagnetism 
species 	 binomial classification system (Carl Linnaeus) 
Primates 
Anthropoidea (anthropoids) 
Hominoidea (hominoids) 
Pongidae (pongids) 
Panidae (panids) 
Hylobatidae (hylobatids) 
Hominidae (hominids) 
Parental investment 
K - selection   -pattern of few offspring and extensive parental care 
r -  selection -pattern of large number of offspring and little parental care 
To Ponder 
)	 What characteristics define humanness? 
)	 What are the characteristics which distinguish hominids from the remaining great apes? 
)	 In general, what pattern of parental investment do Primates exhibit in comparison with 
other mammals and non-mammals?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Archaeology of the Early Hominids I: Olduvai Gorge and Koobi Fora</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture12_14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12-13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution	 Spring, 2006 
Lectures 12 -14: Key terms, concepts and questions to ponder 
You should become familiar with the following terms, concepts, people and places from your readings 
in Campbell et al. for these three lectures.  You should also give some consideration to the problems and 
issues mooted in the "To Ponder" section. 
Vocabulary 
Pleistocene 
Palaeolithic / Stone Age hard hammer percussion 
Lower Palaeolithic/Early Stone Age soft hammer percussion 
Middle Palaeolithic/Middle Stone Age 
Upper Palaeolithic/Later Stone Age 
Industrial Complex
Industry
site and assemblage
Kada Gona  (Ethiopia) (ca. 2.6 myr.) 
Shungura Formation (Ethiopia)
FtJi1 and FtJi2 sites  (ca. 2.4-2.3 myr.)
Olduvai Gorge 
Oldowan industry Koobi Fora 
choppers KBS tool site (FxJj 1)  (ca. 1.8 myr.) 
discoids HAS site  (FxJj 3)   (ca. 1.8 myr.) 
flakes (unretouched) Site FxJj 50  (ca. 1.65 myr.) 
manuports DK I  site (C &amp; L, Fig. 9-9; 9-10) (ca. 1.9 myr.) 
FLK 1 site  (ca. 1.75 myr.) 
cutmarks
refitting
microwear traces
To Ponder 
)	How can we recognize which early hominids were potential makers and users of stone tools? What are 
the sources of evidence available for us to attempt this? 
)	By what features are early archaeological sites recognized? 
)	How can we be certain the sites we recognize actually owe their origin to hominid as opposed to non-hominid agency? 
)	What are some of the mechanisms by which bone and stone accumulations can be created? 
)	How do we recognize that a piece of stone has been modified by human agency? 
)	How do we go about determining the functions of stone tools?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Modern Homo sapiens II: To the Threshold of Civilization</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/lecture24_25/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution Spring, 2006 
Lectures 24 - 25:   Key terms, concepts and questions to ponder 
You should become familiar with the following terms, concepts, people and places 
from your readings in Campbell et al  2006, Ch. 17 or Campbell/Loy (8th ed.), Ch. 18, 
Molnar, and Jablonski/Chaplinfor these two lectures. 
Vocabulary 
Bergmanns rule genetic drift 
Allens rule founder effect 
Glogers rule adaptation to stresses via natural selection 
clinal distribution of traits 
biological races 
ethnic groups 
xenophobia (fear and hatred)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Slowly Emerging Modern Behaviors: Early Stone Age / Lower Palaeolithic Age</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-987-human-origins-and-evolution-spring-2006/resources/handout17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>However. the Kinneret Drinaee Authorit" has areued for "ears that it needed to dredee a stretch of the Jordan near the 
Gesher site to urevent regular flooding ofihe nearbvkula vdev and (ts farmland. "Our main concern was to urotect human life," 
-1). .\III~. \11 11.. .It 11r.1~ 11111..111\ .rl.~r.~?~r.: .lh~.l 1 1\1.11. 1.1 .11-1~1111r.: 11.~.b..1?1r.? ~~~.IC.I-I.C.LIIII) 11. 11111.1111~ .ili.~~l-
,III., I., ,c1 .\l.ll.llllllc. \11111II) I.%% 11.1 11.1.1c.l r1.c I,.) . 11c1 111.1. 1111.1 1c 1\c ik.l.~l 1.11 1 111 l1.11. IIc)!\.I, .I. .I.c.I 111. 
11.1 r1..r.r1. 1. lir..IrI.~rIIL.It IIII~C 11111.111) I.1.l111 .CL.IC.I I.r..~~l~.l~~ 1 !~LLI..IIL.I?II.? ~~~r1.18~1 !~111..111 11.11 !!111. 1 11. III 1.1 
I. I.. Ill. I.. 111 1,.111..11.1.I. .l,I I,.) 111111.~1 \\.,I. !\1.1.1. \\ 1.1111.1~.1 I,..II.I.I..!\ 11.cr. 111.1~ 11.111.11..1.1 
11111 It I,.,)11. I..1111 1. 111.1 11, I111111 .\...I.I,,.1I. 111~l.1.I.11~1. \1 111.1 i I1,.-l1.l111 .111~111c~\ 11.1\~1.11) I,. 
.1c111.11c11. I..1.1. I..] IL..I.I L\.1\ 111.1.. 11 ic.I.7 11, 111.11.1.,~1. .11111~1 11c.1 .L\CI 11 1.111..ll~.I 11.1111. I II., I 1.11.11.c1~1-1.1.1 
-111 11..111.111.1 11.111.1.. 111, 11\~1l111.1. 111.11...l1,I~I\ I11l ,,.I..1111. 1 ILI.!\, -11.1.1 .\.I\ I11.I. I.. l.l I..1.1. \1.11..1 
~eiheron fo:iand flown over it by aircraft since &amp;e dredging took place, says that the workers left the dirt and s&amp;d in heaps by 
the river. "Strata which contain fossil remains, manmade stone artifacts, and a lot of organic material were all destroyed," she 
claims. "We will never be able to scientifically study this material because it is now out of context." Sat disputes that 
characterization. "They are lying about the amount of damage," he says, insisting that his crew dredged only in the river and not on 
the banks. Sat says that despite attempts at negotiations bemeen his authority and the IAA, the IAAwould not compromise on 
dredging in the Gesher area. "They were preventing me from doing my job." 
Recent excavations at Gesher had only begun to tap into a wealth of exceptionally well preserved plant and animal 
remains, which have allowed scientists to begin reconst~ucting the prehistoric climatic conditions and ecology, says Goren-Inbar. 
Thus experts in human evolution will be lamenting the destruction for a long time to come. "Sites like Gesher are found very 
rarely," says Gamble. "This is not a record that should be discarded into a drainage ditch."</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.987 -Human Origins and Evolution Spring, 2006 
Lecture 17: Homo evgastev, evectus and slowly emerging modern human behaviors -addtional notes 
Finds at the Gesher Benot Ya'aqov site 
One of the emerging central sites in our understanding of the Acheulian period is the site of Gesher Benot Ya'aqov in 
Israel. Two impoltant papers on materials fiom th~s site have appeared very recently. These deal with the presence of 
early fire and evidence for diet and food processing. 
The Gesher Benot Ya'aqov site has also appeared recently in a somewhat more unfortunate light as the news item below 
("Mudslinging") relates. Part of the Gesher Benot Ya'aqov site has been intentionally destroyed by Israeli 
development authorities. One would hope in th~s day and age, and especially in a country like Israel whch is usually 
verv conscious of its archaeoloeical resources. that th~s kind of th~m shouldn't and wouldn't haooen. BUT it is u u . . 
happening to irreplaceable archaeological resources regularly, all around the world. 
Goren-Inbar, N., N. Alperson, M E. Kislev, 0. Simchoni, Y. Melamed, A. Ben-Nun, and E. Werker 
2004 Evidence of Hominin Control of Fire at Gesher Benot Ya'aqov, Israel. 
Science 304: 725-727. 
Goren-Inbar, N., G. Sharon., Y. Melamed, and M. Kislev 
2003 Nuts, nut crachng, and pitted stones at Gesher Benot Ya'aqov, Israel 
Proceedinps of" the National Academy . of" Sciences. USA 99(4):2455-2460 
Abstract: 
The Acheulian site of Gesher Benot Ya'aqov (Israel) has revealed a unique association of edible nuts with pitted 
nuts now kxtinct ;n tie Levant. In addjtion, the site yielded an assemdage of pitted hammers and anvils similar in pit ' 
morphology to those used by chimpanzees and contemporw hunter-gatherers. This is the first time, to our knowledge, that 
Dredging at Israeli Site Prompts Mudslinging 
Michael Balter 
Science 287:205-206, (14 January 2000) 
A prehistoric site critical for understanding early human evolution appears to have suffered permanent damage after a 
local Israeli drainaee authoritv alleeedlv bulldozed a bie chunk of it last month. Prehistorians claim that the earth movine. 
undertaken to ure6nt flooding of &amp;ar6y fms during;ainstorms, has destroyed their ability to make sense of the comuiex layers at 
While the current state of Gesher is contested, the site's importance is not. Gesher Benot Ya'aqovwas first discovered in 
the 1930's and has been excavated several times since. Along with the nearby prehistoric site of Ubeidiya, also in the Jordan valley, 
Gesher is a key location for understanding how and when Homo erectus -an ancestor of modem humans -moved out of Africa, 
probably through the so-called Levantine corridor that includes Israel. "Israel and the Jordan valley are one of the great crossroads 
of human prehistory" says Clive Gamble, an archaeologist at the University of Southampton in the United Kingdom. "A site like 
Gesher provides cmcial information on the skills and capabilities of the earliest hominids as they came out of . Africa". During 
recent excavations at Gesher, stone tools such as hand axes and cleavers found in layers dated to 780,000 years ago were very 
similar to those at African sites of the same age. "The destmction of a site like Gesher is the destluction of a vital piece of our 
global heritage," Gamble says. 
P.T.O.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
