<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/</course_url>
    <course_title>Interfacial Phenomena</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Mathematics </list>
      <list>Mechanical Engineering </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Contact Angle Hysteresis, Wetting of Textured Solids (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>15.3. Wenzel State (1936) Chapter 15. Contact angle hysteresis, Wetting of textured solids 
15.3 Wenzel State (1936) 
A Wenzel state arises when the uid impregnates the rough solid. The change in wetting energy associated 
with a uid front advancing a distance dx (see Fig. 15.7) is 
dEW = r(SL  SV )dx + cosdx (15.6) 
If r = 1 (smooth surface), Youngs Law emerges.
 
If r &gt; 1: cos  = r cose
 
Note: 
1.	 wetting tendencies are amplied by roughening, 
e.g. for hydrophobic solid ( e &gt; /2, cos e &lt; 0  e 
 
/2 for large r )
 
2. for e &lt; c (depends on surface texture)  demi-wicking 
/ complete wetting 
3. Wenzel state breaks down at large r  air trap ped within 
the surface roughness  Cassie State 
15.4 Cassie-Baxter State 
In a Cassie state, the uid does not impregnate the rough
 solid, leaving a trapped vapour layer. A uid placed on
 the rough surface thus sits on roughness elements (e.g.
 pillars or islands), and the change of energy associated
 with its front advancing a distance dx is
 
dE
c = S (SL  SV )dx +(1  S)dx + cosdx
 
(15.7)
 
For equilibrium (d Ec/dx = 0), we require:
 
cos = 1+S + S cose (15.8) 
Note: 
1.	 as pillar density S  0, cos  1, i.e.    
2. drops in a Cassie State are said to be in a fakir
 
state.
 
3.	 contact an
gle hysteresis is greatly increased in the
 
Wenzel state, 
decreased in the Cassie.
 
4. the maintenance of a Cassie state is key to water
 repellency
.
 
Crossover between Wen zel and Cassie states: 
1+SFor dE W &gt; dEc, we require r cose +cos &gt; s cose +(1s)+cos, i.e. cos e &lt; rS = cosc, 
i.e. one expects a Cassie state to emerge for cos e &gt; cosc. Therefore, the criterion for a Wenzel State 
giving way to a Cassie state is identical to that for spontaneous wicking. 
Figure 15.7: The wetting of a rough solid in 
a Wenzel state. 
Figure 15.8: The wetting of a rough solid in 
a Cassie-Baxter state. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 62	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>15.2. Wetting of a Rough Surface Chapter 15. Contact angle hysteresis, Wetting of textured solids 
II. Raindrops on window panes (Dussan+Chow 1985) 
If 1 = 2 then the drop will fall due to unbalanced 
gravitational force. 2 can be as large as a, 1 as small 
as r. Thus, the drop weight may be supported by the 
capillary force associated with the contact angle hystere
sis. 
Note: Fg  R3g, Fc  2R(cos1  cos2) which implies 
gR2 that FG 	  Bo. In general, drops on a window pane FC  
will increase in size by accretion until Bo &gt; 1 and will then roll 
downwards. 
15.2 Wetting of a Rough Surface  
Consider a uid placed on a rough surface. Figure 15.5: A raindrop may be pinned 
Define: roughness parameters on a window pane. 
Total Surface Area Area of isl an ds r =	 &gt; 1 S = &lt; 1 (15.4) Projected Surf. Area Projecte d Area 
The change in surface energy associated with the uid front advancing a distance dz : 
dE = (SL  SV )(r  S)dz + (1 S)ds	 (15.5) 
Spontaneous Wetting  ( demi-wicking) arises when d E &lt; 0 
SV SL 1Si.e. cose = &gt;  cosc, i.e. when e &lt; C. Note: rS 
1.	 can control e with chemistry, r and S with geometry, so can prescribe wettability of a solid. 
2. if r  1, C = 2 , so one expects spontaneous wicking when e &lt; /2 
3. for a at surface, r  1, c = 0: wicking requires cos e &gt; 1 which never happens. 
4. most solids are rough (except for glass which is smooth down to  5A). 
Wetting
 of Rough Solids  with Drops 
Consider a drop placed on a rough solid. Define: Eecti v e contact angle  is the contact angle apparent
 
on a rough solid, which need not correspond to e. Observation:
 
 &lt; e when e &lt; /2 (hydrophilic)
 
 &gt; e when e &gt; /2 (hydrophobic).
 
The intrinsic hydrophobicity or hydrophilicity of a solid, as prescribed by e, is enhanced by surface
 
roughening.
 
Figure 15.6: A drop wetting a rough solid has an eective contact angle  that is generally dierent 
from its equilibrium value e. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 61	 Prof. Joh n W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>15.1. Contact Angle Hysteresis Chapter 15. Contact angle hysteresis, Wetting of textured solids
Figure 15.2: Pinning of a contact line retreating from left to right due to surface impurities.
Figure 15.3: A range of contact angles is possible at a corner.
Manifestations of Contact Angle Hysteresis
I. Liquid column trapped in a capillary tube.
2can be as large as a;1can be as small as
r. In general 2&gt; 1, so there is a net cap-
illary force available to support the weight of the
slug.
2R(cos1cos2) =gR2H(15.2)/bracehtipupleft /bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft /bracehtipupright /bracehtipupleft /bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft /bracehtipupright
max contact force weight
Force balance requires:
2(cos1cos2) =gH (15.3)R
Thus,anequilibriumispossibleonlyif2(cosrcosa R)&gt;
gH. Figure 15.4: A heavy liquid column may be
trapped in a capillary tube despite the eects
Note: if a=r(no hysteresis), there can be no equilib- of gravity.
rium.
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 60 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15. Contact angle hysteresis, Wetting 
of textured solids 
Recall: In Lecture 3, we dened the equilibrium contact angle e, which is prescribed by Youngs Law:
 
cose = (SV  SL)/ as deduced from the horizontal force balance at the contact line.
 
Work done by a contact line moving a distance d x:
 
Figure 15.1: Calculating the work done by moving a contact line a distance d x. 
dW = (SV  SL)dx cosedx (15.1)         
contact line motion from creating new interface 
In equilibrium: dW = 0, which yields Youngs Law. It would be convenient if wetting could be simply 
characterized in terms of this single number e. Alas, there is: 
15.1 Contact Angle Hysteresis  
For a given solid wetting a given liquid, there is a range of possible contact angles: r &lt;  &lt;  a, i.e. the 
contact angle lies between the retreating and advancing contact angles; r and a, respectively. That is, 
many  values may arise, depending on surface, liquid, roughness and history. 
Filling a drop Dr aining a drop 
 begin with a drop in equilibrium with  = e  begin with a drop in equilibrium with  = e 
 ll drop slowly with a syringe  drain drop slowly with a syringe 
  increases progressively until attaining a, at   decreases progressively until attaining r, at which point the contact line advances which point the contact line retreats 
Origins: Contact line pinning results from surface heterogeneities (either chemical or textural), that 
present an 
energetic impediment to contact line motion. 
The pinning of a contact line on impurities leads to increased interfacial area, and so is energetically 
costly. Con t
act line motion is thus resisted. 
Contact Line Pinnin g at Corners 
A nite range of contact angles can arise at a corner 1 &lt;  &lt;  +1; thus, an advancing contact line 
will generally be pinned at corners. Hence surface texture increases contact angle hysteresis. 
59</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>15.4. Cassie-Baxter State Chapter 15. Contact angle hysteresis, Wetting of textured solids 
Summary: 
Hydrophilic: Wenzels Law ceases to apply at small e when demi-wicking sets in, and the Cassie state 
emerges. Hydrophobic: Discontinuous jump in 
 as e exceeds /2  Cassie state. Jump is the largest for large 
roughness (small S) 
Historical note:
 
1.	 early stu
dies of wetting motivated by insecticides 
2.	 chemists have since been trying to design superhydrophobic (or oliophobic) surfaces using combina
tions of c
hemistry and texture 
3.	 recent advances in microfabrication have achieved   ,   0 (e.g. Lichen surface McCarthy ) 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 63	 Prof. Joh n W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Instability Dynamics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>12.3. Rupture of a Soap Film (Culick 1960, Taylor 1960) Chapter 12. Instability Dynamics 
J 
hx Note: Surface area of rim/ length: p = 2R where m = hx = R2  R = where R is the rim  J  hx radius. Therefore the rim surface energy is P = 2 = 2 hx . Total surface energy of the system  [ ]
is 2x + 2(hx )1/2. )1/2SArim  2
hx ( h Scale:	   1 for x  h.SAsheet 2x x 
The rim surface area is thus safely neglected once the sheet has retracted a distance comparable to its
 
thickness.
 
Some nal comments on soap lm rupture.
 
1. for dependence on geometry and inuence of , see
 
Sav
va &amp; Bush (JFM 2009).
 
 
2. form of sheet depends on Oh =  .2h 
3. The growing rim at low Oh is sub ject to Ra-Plateau 
 scalloping of the retracting rim  rim pinches o
 
into drops
 
4. At very high speed, air-induced shear	 stress leads
 
to ap
ping. The sheet thus behaves like a apping
 
ag, but with Marangoni elasticity.
 
 Figure 12.5: The dierent shapes of a retract
ing sheet and rim depend on the value of Oh. 
Figure 12.6: The typical evolution of a retracting sheet. As the rim retracts and engulfs uid, it eventually 
becomes Rayleigh-Plateau unstable. Thus, it develops variations in radius along its length, and the retreating rim becomes scalloped. Filaments are eventually left by the retracting rim, and pinch o through a Rayleigh-Plateau instability, the result being droplets. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 48	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>12.3. Rupture of a Soap Film (Culick 1960, Taylor 1960) Chapter 12. Instability Dynamics
12.3 Rupture of a Soap Film (Culick
1960, Taylor 1960)
We assumeO=h1, so that viscous eects are negligible.R
The driving curvature force is thus resisted principally by uid
inertia. Assume dynamics is largely 2D (true for a planar lm,
or for bubble burst for r(t)h).
Retraction of a Planar Sheet
Note: Force/ length acting on the rim may be calculated exactly
via Frenet-Serret
FC=/integraldisplay
( n)ndl (12.15)Figure 12.3: Rupture of a soap lm ofCthickness h.
where ( n)n=dt
dl /integraldisplaydtFC=dl=(t1
Cdlt2) = 2x (12.16)
At timet= 0, planar sheet of thickness hpunctured at x= 0, and retracts in x direction owing to Fc.
Observation: The rim engulfs the lm, and there is no upstream disturbance.
Figure 12.4: Surface-tension-induced retraction of a planar sheet of uniform thickness hreleased at time
t= 0.
Rim mass: m(x) =hxand speed v=dx.dt
Since the inertial force on the rim is equal to the rate of change of rim momentum
d d2dm dv12dm1dFI= (mv) =v mv=v+mv=v+ (mv2). (12.17)dt dx dx Dx 2dx2dx
The force balance us between the curvature force and the inertial force
d1 12= (mv2)+hv2(12.18)dx2 2
Integrate from 0 to x:
12x=hxv21+h2 2/integraldisplayx
v2dx (12.19)
0
The rst term is the surface energy released per unit length, the 2nd term the K.E. of the rim, and the
3rd term the energy required to accelerate the rim. Now we assume vis independent of x(as observed in
xexperiments), thus/integraltext
v2dx=xv2and the force balance becomes 2x =hxv2
0
/parenleftbigg /parenrightbigg 1/22v= is the retraction speed (Taylor-Culick speed) (12.20)h
E.g. for water-soap lm, h150mv102cm/s.
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 47 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.1 12. Instability Dynamics
 
We proceed by considering the surface tension-induced 
instability of a uid coating on a cylindrical ber. Dene mean thickness 
 1 h = h(x)dx (12.1) 0 
Local interfacial thickness Capillary Instability of a Fluid Coating on a Fiber 
h(x) = h + coskx (12.2) 
Figure 12.1: Instability of a uid coating on 
Volume conservation requires: a cylindrical ber. 
      
(r + h)2dx =(r + h0)2dx (r + h + coskx)2dx = (r + h0)2  
0 0 0 
2 1 2 
(r + h)2+ 2  = (r + h0)2  (r + h)2 = (r + h0)2  = (r + h0)2 1 2 2 2(r + h0)2 
which implies 
1 2 
h = h0  (12.3) 4r + h0 
Note: 
h &lt; h0 which suggests instability. fSo, when does perturbation reduce surface energy? i.e. when is 2 (r + h)ds &lt; 2(r + h0)?0 J( )[ ]1/2dh 1Note: ds2 = dh2 + dx2  ds = dx1+dx 2 dx1+ 2k2 sin2 kx
f f 1 1 (r + h)2k2. (r + h)ds = (r + h + coskx)(1+2k2 sin2 kx)1/2dx = (r + h)+0 0 2 4 
1 (r + h)2k2 &lt; (r + h0). So the inequality holds provided ( r + h)+ 4 
Substitute for h from (12.3): 
1 2 1(r + h)2k2 + &lt; 0 (12.4) 4r + h0 4
We note that the result is independent of : 
k2 &lt; (r + h0)1(r + h)1  1 (12.5) (r + h0)2 
i.e. unstable wavelengths are prescribed by 
2  = &gt; 2(r + h0) (12.6) k 
as in standard inviscid Ra-P. All long wavelength disturbances will grow. Which grows the fastest? That is det
ermined by the dynamics (not just geometry). We proceed by considering the dynamics in the thin 
lm limit, h0  r, for which we obtain the lubrication limit. 
45</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>12.2. Dynamics of Instability (Rayleigh 1879) Chapter 12. Instability Dynamics
12.2 Dynamics of Instability (Rayleigh 1879)
Physical picture: Curvature pressure induced by perturbation drives Couette ow that is resisted by
viscosity
d2vdp= 0 (12.7)dy dx
wheredpis the gradient in curvature pressure, which is independent of y( a generic feature of lubricationdx
problems), so we can integrate the above equation to obtain
1dpv(y) =/parenleftbiggy2
hy/parenrightbigg
(12.8)dx2
Flux per unit length:
Q=/integraldisplayh1dpv(y)dy=
0h3(12.9)3dx
Conservation of volume in lubrication problems requires that Q(x+dx)Q(x) =hdxt
dQ h3d2
=dx0p h=3dx2 (12.10) t
Curvature pressure
p(x) =/parenleftbigg11+ R R 2/parenrightbigg
=
1/parenleftbigg1
r+hhxx/parenrightbigg
(12.11)
Substitute (12.11) into (12.10):
hh3
=021
t3x2/bracketleftbigg
hxx (12.12) r +h(x)/bracketrightbigg
Nowh(x,t) =h+(t)coskxhx=ksinkx,hxx=2kcoskx,ht=dcoskxdt
So coskxdh3 2=0 h3 2coskxkk4 d=where=0kk4
dt3/bracketleftBig
(r+h)2 dt 3 (r+h0)2
Fastest
growing mode whend/bracketrightBig
8/bracketleftBig /bracketrightBig
= 0 =2k
dk (r+h0)24k
3so
= 2
2(r+h0) (
12.13)
is the most unstable wavelength for the viscous mode.
Note:
Recall that for classic Ra-P on a cylindrical uid thread
9R.
12(r+h)4We see here the timescale of instability: =0
3.h0
Scal
ing Argument for Pinch-o time.
Whenhr,h3
ph01v
2 2vr 0h0
r r h0 r3
r4
pinch (12.14)h3
0Figure 12.2: Growth rate as a func-
tionofwavenumber kforthesystemde-
picted in Fig. 12.1.
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 46 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Fluid Jets (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>11.3. Fluid Pipes Chapter 11. Fluid Jets 
The column is thus unstable to disturbances whose 
wavelengths exceed the circumference of the cylinder. 
A plot of the dependence of the growth rate  on the 
wavenumber k for the Rayleigh-Plateau instability is 
shown in Fig. 11.4. The fastest growing mode occurs for kR
0 = 0.697, i.e. 
when the wavelength of the disturbance is 
max  9.02R0 (11.32) 
By inverting the maximum growth rate max one may 
estimate the characteristic break-up time: 
 Figure 11.4: The dependence of the growth R03 
tbreakup  2.91 (11.33) rate  on the wavenumber k for the Rayleigh
 Plateau instability. 
R.  Note: In general, pinch-o depends on Oh = ( ) 1/2 
At low Oh, we have seen that pinch  R2 ,  = 9.02R. 
At high Oh, when viscosity is important, pinch  R ,  increases with . 
A water jet of diameter 1cm has a characteristic break-up time of about 1/8s, which is consistent with 
casual observation of jet break-up in a kitchen sink. Related Phenomena:
  Waves on jets 
When a vertical water jet impinges on a horizontal reservoir of water, a eld of standing waves may be excited 
on the base of the jet (see Fig. 11.5). The wavelength is determined by the requirement that the 
wave speed correspond to the local jet speed: U = /k. Using our dispersion relation (11.30) thus yields 
2 I1(kR0)( )
U2 = = 1 k2R2 (11.34) 0k2 kR2 I0(kR0)0 
Provided the jet speed U is known, this equation may be solved in order to deduce the wavelength of the 
waves that will travel at U and so appear to be stationary in the lab frame. For jets falling from a nozzle, 
the result (11.5) may be used to deduce the local jet speed. 
11.3 Fluid Pipes 
The following system may be readily observed in a kitchen sink. When the volume ux exiting the tap is such that the falling stream has a diameter of 2  3mm, obstructing the stream with a nger at a 
distance of several centimeters from the tap gives rise to a stationary eld of varicose capillary waves upstream of the nger. If the nger is dipped in liquid detergent (soap) before insertion into the stream, the capillary waves begin at some critical distance above the nger, below which the stream is cylindrical. Closer inspection reveal that the surface of the jets cylindrical base is quiescent. 
An analogous phenomenon arises when a vertical uid jet impinges on a deep water reservoir (see 
Fig. 11.
5). When the reservoir is contaminated by surfactant, the surface tension of the reservoir is 
diminished relative to that of the jet. The associated surface tension gradient draws surfactant a nite distance up the jet, prompting two salient alterations in the jet surface. First, the surfactant suppresses surface waves, so that the base of the jet surface assumes a cylindrical form (Fig. 11.5b). Second, the jet surface at its base becomes stagnant: the Marangoni stresses associated with the surfactant gradient are balanced by the viscous stresses generated within the jet. The quiescence of the jet surface may be simply demonstrated by sprinkling a small amount of talc or lycopodium powder onto the jet. The uid jet thus enters a contaminated reservoir as if through a rigid pipe. 
A detailed theoretical description of the uid pipe is given in Hancock  &amp;
  Bush (JFM, 466, 285-304) . 
We here present a simple scaling that yields the dependence of the vertical extent H of the uid pipe on 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 43 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>11.2. The Plateau-Rayleigh Instability Chapter 11. Fluid Jets 
11.2 The Plateau-Rayleigh Instability 
WeheresummarizetheworkofPlateau andRayleigh ontheinstability 
of cylindrical uid jets bound by surface tension. It is precisely this Rayleigh-Plateauinstabilitythatisresponsibleforthepinch-o ofthin water jets emerging from kitchen taps (see Fig. 11.2). 
The equilibrium base state consists of an innitely long quiescent 
cylindrical inviscid uid column of radius R0, density  and surface 
tension  (see Fig. 11.3). The inuence of gravity is neglected. The 
pressure p0 is constant inside the column and may be calculated by 
balancing the normal stresses with surface tension at the boundary. Assuming zero external pressure yields 
 p
0 =   n  p0 = . (11.11) R0 
We consider the evolution of innitesimal varicose perturbations on the interface, which enables us to linearize the governing equations. The perturbed columnar surface takes the form: 
R
0 + et+ikz R = , (11.12) 
where the perturbation amplitude   R0,  is the growth rate of 
the instability and k is the wave number of the disturbance in the z-
direction. The corresponding wavelength of the varicose perturbations is necessarily 2/k . We denote by  u
r the radial component of the 
perturbation velocity,  uy the axial component, and  p the perturbation 
pressure. Substituing these perturbation elds into the N-S equations and retaining terms only to order  yields: 
u
r 1p=  (11.13) F igure 11.2: The capillary-driven t  r instability of a water thread uz 1p(11.14) falling under the inuence of =  t z gravity. The initial jet diameter 
The linearized continuity equation becomes: is approximately 3 mm. 
ur ur uz + + = 0 . (11.15) r r z 
We anticipate that the disturbances in velocity and 
pressur
e will have the same form as the surface dis
turbance (11.12 ), and so write the perturbation ve
locit
ies and pressure as: 
( )
t+ikz (ur,uz,p) = R(r),Z(r),P(r)e . (11.16) 
Substituting (11.16) into equations (11.13-11.15) yields the linearized equations governing the perturb
ation elds: 
1dP Momentum equations : R =  (11. 17)  dr 
ik P (11.18) Figu re 11.3: A cylindrical column of initial radius 
 Z =  
R0 comprised of an inviscid uid of density , bound 
dR R by surface tension . Continuity: + + ikZ = 0 . (11.19) dr r 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 41 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11. Fluid Jets 
11.1 The shape of a falling uid jet 
Consider a circular orice of a radius a ejecting a ux Q of uid density  and kinematic viscosity  
(see Fig. 11.1). The resulting jet accelerates under the inuence of gravity gz. We assume that the jet 
Reynolds number Re = Q/(a) is suciently high that the inuence of viscosity is negligible; furthermore, 
we assume that the jet speed is independent of radius, and so adequately described by U(z). We proceed 
by deducing the shape r(z) and speed U(z) of the evolving jet. 
Applying Bernoullis Theorem at points A and B: 
1 U2 + gz + PA =1 U2(z)+PB (11.1) 2 0 2 
The local curvature of slender threads may be expressed in terms of 
the two principal radii of curvature, R1 and R2: 
1 1 1   n = +  (11. 2) R1 R2 r 
Thus, the uid pressures within the jet at points A and B may be simply 
related to that of the ambient, P0: 
  , PB  P0 + (11.3) PA  P0 + a r 
Substituting into (11.1) thus yields 
1  1  U2 + gz + P0 + = U2(z)+P0 + (11.4) 2 0 a 2 r 
from which one nds 
 1/2 
U(z)  2 z 2 (a) 
= 1+ + 1   (11. 5) U0  Fr a We r       
acc. due to g dec. due to  Figure 11.1: A uid jet extruded 
where we dene the dimensionless groups from an orice of radius a ac
celerates under the inuence of U2 INERTIA 0Fr = = = Froude Number (11.6) gravity. Its shape is inuenced ga GRAVITY bothbythegravitational accelerU02a INERTIA ation g andthe surfacetension . 
 C
URVATURE We = = = Webe r Number (11.7) 
Note that  gives rise to a gradi-
Now 
ux conservation requires that ent in curvature pressure within  r the jet, /r(z), that opposes the 
Q= 2 U (z)r(z)dr = a2U0 = r2U(z) (11.8) acceleration due to g. 
0 
from which one obtains 
( )1/2 [( )]1/4 r(z) U0 2 z 2 a = = 1+  + 1  (11.9) a U (z) Fr a We r 
This may be solved algebraically to yield the thread shape r(z)/a, then this result substituted into (11.5) 
to deduce the velocity prole U(z). In the limit of We , one obtains 
( ) 1/4 ( ) 1/2 r 2gz U(z) 2gz = 1+ , = 1+ (11. 10) a U02 U0 U02 
40</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>11.3. Fluid Pipes Chapter 11. Fluid Jets 
Figure 11.5: a) The eld of stationary capillary waves excited on the base of a water jet impinging on a 
horizontal water reservoir. b) The uid pipe generated by a falling water jet impinging on a contaminated 
water reservoir. The eld of stationary capillary waves is excited above the uid pipe. The grids at right 
are millimetric. 
the governing system parameters. We assume that, once the jet enters the uid pipe, a boundary layer 
develops on its outer wall owing to the no-slip boundary condition appropriate there. 
Balancing viscous and Marangoni stresses on the uid pipe surface yields 
V    , (11.35) H H 
where  is the surface tension dierential between the jet and reservoir, V ist he jet speed at the top of 
the uid pipe, and H is the boundary layer thickness at the base of the uid pipe. We assume that the 
boundary layer thickness increases with distance z from the inlet according to classical boundary layer 
scaling: 
 ( z )1/2 
 . (11.36) a a2V 
Thus, at the base of a pipe of height H 
( H )1/2 
(H) = (11.37) a2V 
Substituting for (H) from (11.36 ) in to (11.35) yields 
()2 
H  (11.38) 3V 
The pipe height increases with the surface tension dierential, and decreases with uid viscosity and jet speed. 
MIT 
OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 44 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>11.2. The Plateau-Rayleigh Instability Chapt er 11. Fluid Jets 
Eliminating Z(r) and P(r)y ields a dierential equation for R(r): 
2 d2R dR (
r + r  1+(kr)2) 
R = 0 . (11.20) dr2 dr 
This corresponds to the modied Bessel Equation of order 1, whose solutions may be written in terms of 
the mo
died Bessel functions of the rst and second kind, respectively, I1(kr) and K1(kr). We note that 
K1(kr) as r  0; therefore, the well-behavedness of our solution requires that R(r) take the form 
R(r) = CI1(kr) , (11.21) 
where C is an as yet unspecied constant to be determined later by application of appropriate boundary 
condi
tions. The pressure may be obtained from (11.21) and (11.17), and by using the Bessel function 
identity I0() = I1(): 
C ik P(r) =  I0(kr) and Z(r) =  P(r). (11.22) k  
W
e p
roceed by applying appropriate boundary conditions. The rst is the kinematic condition on the free 
surface: 

R
= u n  ur . (11.23) t 
Substitution of (11.21) into this condition yields 
 C = . (11.24) I1(kR0) 
Second, we require a normal stress balance on the free surface: 
p0 + p=   n (11.25) 
( )
We write the curvature as   n = 1 1+ , where R1 and R2 are the principal radii of curvature of R1 R2 
the jet surface: 
1 1 1  t+ikz =   e (11.26) R0 + et+ikz R2R1 R0 0 
t+ikz 1= k2 e . (11.27) R2 
Substitution of (11.26 ) and (11.27) into equation (11.25) yields: 
  ( ) t+ikz p0 + p =  R2 1 k2R02 e (11.28) R0 0 
Cancellation via (11.11) yields the equation for p accurate to order : 
( ) tikz p=   1 k2R2 e . (11.29) R2 0
0 
Combining (11.22), (11.24 ) and (11.29) yields the dispersion relation, that indicates the dependence of 
the gr
owth rate  on the wavenumber k: 
2 I1(kR0)( )
= kR0 1 k2R2 (11.30) 0R3 I0(kR0)0 
We rst note that unstable modes are only possible when 
kR0 &lt; 1 (11.31) 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 42 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Coating: Dynamic Contact Lines (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>17.1. Contact Line Dynamics Chapter 17. Coating: Dynamic Contact Lines 
Note: 
1. rationalizes Homann s data (obtained for e = 0)  U  3 
D 
2. U = 0 f or d = e (static equilibrium) 
3. U =0 as d  0: dissipation in sharp wedge impedes motion. 
dU Ue ) e U4. U(d) has a maximum when   = 32  2  d =   3 Umax = e dd 6D de3 9 3D 
Figure 17.9: Left: Schematic illustration of the ow in the vicinity of an advancing contact line. Right: 
The dependence of the dynamic contact angle on the speed of withdrawal. 
 E.g. In water, U= 70m/s.  With e =0.1 radians and D = 20, Umax =0.2mm/s 
 sets upper bou nd on extraction speed for water coating ows. 
MIT OCW: 18.357  Interfacial Phenomena 72 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 17. Coating: Dynamic Contact Lines 
Figure 17.3: Left: Forced wetting on a ber. Right: The coating thickness as a function of the Reyonolds 
number Re. 
pfilm  p0 + b , pmeniscus  p0  p 
b resists entrainment. 
U pForce balance: e2  = L bL. ePressure match:  1  L  be, substitute into the previous equation to nd L2 b 
e  bCa 2/3 (Bretherton  s Law)	 (17.1) 
Note: 
	 this scaling is  valid when e  b, i.e. Ca2/3  1. 
)1/2(
	 At higher Ca,  lm is the viscous boundary layer that develops during pulling:   
 L
U s , where 
Ls is the submerged length. 
Displacement of an interface in a tube 
E.g. air evacuating a w ater-lled pipette, pumping oil out of rock with water. 
Figure 17.4: Left: Displacing a liquid with a vapour in a tube. Right: The dependence of the lm 
thickness left by the intruding front as a function of Ca = U/. 
In the limit of h  r, the pressure gradient in the meniscus p , where l is t he extent of the dynamic rl
meniscus. 
2  h As on a ber, pressure matching: p0 +   p0 +  l  (hr)1/2 when h  r. r rh l2 
Force balance: U/h2  /rl  /r(hr)1/2  ' -v" '-v" 
viscous curvature 
2/3h  rCa (Bretherton 1961)	 (17.2) 
U 
 . where Ca = 
2/3Thick lms: what if h = ord(r)? For h  r, Taylor (1961) found h  (r  h)Ca. 
MIT OCW: 18.357  Interfacial Phenomena 69	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>17. Coating: Dynamic Contact Lines
 
Last time we considered the Landau-Levich-Derjaguin Problem and deduced 
h Ca2/3 for Ca = &lt; 103 c  
h  cCa1/3 for Ca  1. 
The inuence of surfactants 
Surfactants decrease   which aects h slightly. But the principle eect is to generate Marangoni stresses 
that increase uid emplacement: h typically doubles. V 
Figure 17.1: The inuence of surfactants on ber coating. Gradients in  induce Marangoni stresses that 
enhance deposition. 
Fiber coating : ( )
11Normal stress: p0 + + = p0  gz.R1 R2 
If b  c, 1  1  curvature pressures dominant, cant be balanced by gravity. R1 b 
Thus, the interface must take the form of a catenoid: 1 
R1 + 1 
R2 = 0. 
zhe )
For wetting, e =0  r(z)= bcosh where h  bln(2c/b). b 
Note: 
1. gravity prevents meni scus from extending to  h deduced by cutting it o at c. 
2.	 h is just a  few times b (h  c)  lateral extent greatly exceeds its height. 
Forced wetting on bers e.g. optical ber coating. 
Figure 17.2: Etching of the microtips of Atomic Force Microscopes. As the ber is withdrawn from the 
acid bath, the meniscus retreats and a sharp tip forms. 
68</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>17.1. Contact Line Dynamics Chapter 17. Coating: Dynamic Contact Lines 
Figure 17.7: The advancing and retreating contact angles of a drop. 
Figure 17.8: A drop advancing over a solid boundary behaves like a tractor tread (Dussan 1979 ), ad
vancing though a rolling motion. 
Flow near advancing contact line 
We now consi der the ow near the contact line of a spreading liquid (d &gt; e): 
z consider d  1, so that slope tan d =  d  z  dx. x
 
dU U
 velocity gradient: dz  dx 
 rate of viscous d issipation in the corner 
1 1 dv  2 1  1 zmax =d x U2 
= dU =  dx dz (17. 3) dz d2x2 corner 0 0 1 1U2 3U2 dx =3  dxdx = (17.4) d2x2 d x0 0 J dx JL dxde Gennes approximation:  = ln L/a   D 0 x ax 
where L is the drop size and a is the molecular size. From experiments 15 &lt; D &lt; 20. 
Energetics : 
3
DFU ==  U2 (17.5) d 
rate of work done by surface forces equals the rate of viscous dissipation. 
Recall: 
 F = SV  SL  cos d = (cos e  cos d) 
 e )
2  2 in the limit e &lt; d  1, cos   1  2  F 2 2 de
 substitute F int o the energetics equation to get the contact line speed: 
 e )
U = Ud d 2  2 (17.6) e6D 
 where U=   30m/s. 
MIT OCW: 18.357  Interfacial Phenomena 71 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>17.1. Contact Line Dynamics	 Chapter 17. Coating: Dynamic Contact Lines 
17.1 Contact Line Dyna mics
 
Figure 17.5: The form of a moving meniscus near a wall or inside a tube for three dierent speeds. 
We consider the withdrawal of a plate from a uid bath (Fig. 16.6) or uid displacement within a 
cylindrical tube. Observations: 
	 at low speeds, t he contact line advances at the dynamic contact angle d &lt; e 
	 dynamic contact  angle d decreases progressively as U increases until U = UM. 
	 at suciently hi gh speed, the contact line cannot keep up with the imposed speed and a lm is 
entrained onto the solid. 
Now consider a clean system free of hysteresis.
 
Force of traction pulling liquid towards a dry region:
 
F(d)= SV  SL  cos d.
 
Note:
 
	 F(e) = 0 in equilibrium. How does F depend on U?
 
What is d(U)?
 
	 the retreating cont act line (F &lt; 0) was examined with
 
retraction experiments e.g. plate withdrawal.
 
	 the advancing cont act line (F &gt; 0) was examined by Ho
mann (1975) for the case of e = 0.
 
	 he found d  U1/3 Ca1/3 (Tanners Law) 
Dussan (1979) : dr op in vicinity of contact line advances like a 
tractor tread 
Figure 17.6: Dynamic contact angle d 
as a function of the dierential speed U. 
For U &gt; U M, the uid wets the solid. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 70	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Marangoni Flows (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture9/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>9. Marangoni Flows
 
Marangoni ows are those driven by surface gradients. In general, surface tension  depends on both the 
temperature and chemical composition at the interface; consequently, Marangoni ows may be generated 
by gradients in either temperature or chemical composition at an interface. We previously derived the 
tangential stress balance at a free surface: 
n  T  t = t   , (9.1) 
where n is the  unit outward normal to the surface, and t is any unit tangent vector. The tangential 
component of the hydrodynamic stress at the surface must balance the tangential stress associated with 
gradients in . Such Marangoni stresses may result from gradients in temperature or chemical composition 
at the interface. For a static system, since n  T  t = 0, the tangential stress balance equation indicates 
that: 0 = . This leads us to the following important conclusion: 
There cannot be a s tatic system in the presence of surface tension gradients. 
While pressure jumps can arise in static systems characterized by a normal stress jump across a uid 
interface, they do not contribute to the tangential stress jump. Consequently, tangential surface stresses 
can only be balanced by viscous stresses associated with uid motion. 
Thermocapillary ows: Marangoni ows induced by temperature gradients (T). 
d Note that in general &lt; 0 Why? A war mer gas phase has more liquid molecules, so the creation of dT 
surface is less energetically unfavourable; therefore,  is lower. 
Approach Through the interfacial BCs (and (T)s appearance therein), N-S equations must be coupled 
Figure 9.1: Surface tension of a gas-liquid interface decreases with temperature since a warmer gas phase 
contains more suspended liquid molecules. The energetic penalty of a liquid molecule moving to the 
interface is thus decreased. 
to the heat equation 
T + u  T = 2T (9.2) t 
30</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 9. Marangoni Flows 
E.g.4 Marangoni Shear Layer (Fig. 9. 3) 
Lateral  leads to Marangoni stress  shear ow. The resulting T(x,y) may destabilize the layer to 
Figure 9.3: a) Marangoni convection in a shear layer may lead to transverse surface waves or streamwise
 
rolls (c). Surface deection may accompany both instabilities (b,d).
 
Marangoni convection.
 
Smith &amp; Davis (1983ab) considered the case of at free surface. System behaviour depends on Pr = /.
 
Low Pr: Hydrothermal waves propagate in direction of .
 
High Pr: Streamwise vortices (Fig. 9.3c).
 
Hosoi &amp; Bush (2001) considered a deformable free surface (Fig. 9.3d)
 
E.g.5 Evaporatively-driven convection 
e.g. for an alcohol-H 2O solution, evaporation aects both the alcohol concentration c and temperature . 
The density (c,) and surface tension (c,) are such that  &lt; 0,  &lt; 0, d &lt; 0, d &lt; 0. Evaporation  c d dc 
results in surface cooling and so may generate either Rayleigh-B enard or Marangoni thermal convection. 
Since it also induces a change in surface chemistry, it may likewise generate either Ra B or Marangoni 
chemical convection. 
E.g.6 Coee Drop 
Marangoni ows are  responsible for the ring-like stain left by a 
coee drop. 
	 coee grounds stick  to the surface 
	 evaporation leads to  surface cooling, which is most pro
nounced near the edge, where surface area per volume ratio
 
is highest
 
	 resulting thermal Marangon i stresses drive radial outow
 
on surface  radial ring
 
Figure 9.4: Evaporation of water from 
a coee drop drives a Marangoni ow. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 33	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 9. Marangoni Flows 
Note: 
1.	 the heat equation must  be solved subject to appropriate BCs at the free surface. Doing so can be 
complicated, especially if the uid is evaporating. 
Ua 2. Analysis may be si mplied when the Peclet number Pe =  1. Nondimensionalize (9.2) :   a  x = ax , t = t  , u = Uu to get U 
( ) 
   PeT+ u    T = 2T	 (9.3) t 
Note: 
Ua Pe = Re Pr =   1 if Re  1, so  one has 2T = 0.   
The Prandtl number Pr = O(1) for many common (e.g. aqeous) uids. 
E.g.1 Thermocapillary ow in a slot (Fig.9.2a) 
 d T USurface Tangential BCs  = =   viscous stress U  1 H.L dT L H	  L 
Figure 9.2: a) Thermocapillary ow in a slot b) Thermal convection in a plane layer c) Thermocapillary 
drop motion. 
E.g.2 Thermocapillary Drop Motion (Young, G oldstein &amp; Block 1962)
 
can trap bubbles in gravitational eld via thermocapillary forces. (Fig.9.2c).
 
E.g.3 Thermal Marangoni Convection in a Plane Layer (Fig.9.2b).
 
Consider a
 horizontal uid layer heated from below. Such a layer may be subject to either buoyancy- or
 
Marangoni-induced convection.
 
Recall: Thermal buoyancy-driven convection (Rayleigh-Bernard) (T)= 0 (1 + (T  T0)), where  is
 
the thermal expansivity. Consider a buoyant blob of characteristic scale d. Near the onset of convection,
 
gTd2 one expects it to rise with a Stokes velocity U  gd2 = . The blob will rise, and so convection    
d d will occur, provided its rise time rise = = is less th an the time required for it to lose its heat U gTd2 
d2 and buoyancy by diusion, diff = . 
dif f gTd3 Criterion for Instability:  Ra &gt; Rac  103, where Ra is the Rayleigh number. rise  
Note: for Ra &lt; Rac, heat is transported solely through diusion, so the layer remains static. For
 
Ra &gt; Rac, convection arises.
 
The subsequent behaviour depends on Ra and Pr. Generally, as Ra increases, steady convection rolls 
 
time-dependency  chaos  turbulence.
 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Int erfacial Phenomena 31	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 9. Marangoni Flows 
Thermal Marangoni Convection 
Arises because of the  dependence of  on temperature: (T)= 0  (T  T0) 
Mechanism: 
	 Imagine a warm sp ot on surface  prompts surface divergence  upwelling. 
	 Upwelling blob is  warm, which reinforces the perturbation provided it rises before losing its heat via 
diusion. 
 U 	 Balance Marangoni and vi scous stress: d d
 
d d
 	 Rise time: U  
	 Diusion time diff = d
 2 
dif f  Td Criterion for instability:  Ma &gt; Mac, where Ma is the Marangoni number. rise Note: 
1. Since Ma  d and Ra   d3, thin layers are most unstable to Marangoni convection. 
2. B enards original experi ments performed in millimetric layers of spermaceti were visualizing Marangoni 
convection, but were misinterpreted by Rayleigh as being due to buoyancy  not recognized until 
Block (Nature 1956). 
3.	 Pearson (1958) perfor med stability analysis with at surface  deduced Mac =80 . 
4.	 Scriven &amp; Sternling  (1964) considered a deformable interface, which renders the system unstable at 
all Ma. Downwelling beneath peaks in Marangoni convection, upwelling between peaks in Rayleigh
B enard convection (Fig. 9.3a). 
5.	 Smith (1966) showe d that the destabilizing inuence of the surface may be mitigated by gravity. 
d dT 2Stability Criterion: &lt; gd  thin lay ers prone to instability. dT dz 3 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 32	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Instability of Superposed Fluids (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 14. Instability of Superposed Fluids 
We now deduce p from time-dependent Bernoulli: 
  1 u2 + p+ gz = f(t) (14.6) + t 2 
21 where u= 4V2  V x + H.O.T. 
Linearize: ( ) 1  +  V + p + g = G(t) (14.7) t 2 x 
so 
  V  + p  p+ = (+  )g+(+   )+ ( + + ) = (xx + yy) (14.8) t t 2 x x 
i
s the linearized normal stress BC. Seek normal mode (wave) solutions of the form 
ix+iy+t  = 0e (14.9) 
kz ix +iy+t  = 0e e (14.10) 
where 2 = 0 requires k2 = 2 + 2 . 
  V   1Apply kinematic BC: = at z = 0 z t 2x 
1 k0 = 0  iV0 (14.11) 2 
Normal str
ess BC: 
k20 = g(  +)0 + (+0+  0)+ 1 iV (+0+ + 0) (14.12) 2
 
Subst
itute for 0 from (14.11 ):
 
[ ] [ ]1 1 1 1 1 k3 =  +(  iV)+( + iV) + gk(  +)+ iV  +(  iV)+( + iV)2 2 2 2 2 
so (   + ) 1 22 + iV   2V+ k2C02 = 0 (14.13)  + + 4 
( 
+ ) 
g where C2  + k.0 ++ k ++ 
Dispersion relation: we now have the relation between  and k 
1 ( +   ) [ + 2 ]1/2 
 = i k  V  (k   V ) k2C2 (14.14) 02  + + ( + +)2 
where k = (,),k2 = 2 + 2 .
 
The system is UNSTABLE if Re ()&gt; 0, i.e. if
 
+ 2 C2(k  V )&gt; k2(14.15)  + +0 
Squires Theorem:
 
Disturbances with wave vector k = (,) parallel to V are most unstable. This is a general property of
 
shear ows.
 
We proceed by considering two important special cases, Rayleigh-Taylor and Kelvin-Helmholtz instability.
 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 56 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>14.2. Kelvin-Helmholtz Instability Chapter 14. Instability of Superposed Fluids 
14.2 Kelvin-Helmholtz Instabilit y 
We consider shear-driven instability of a gravitationally stable base state. Specically,   + so the 
system is gravitationally stable, but destabilized by the shear. 
2 2Take k parallel to V , so ( V  k) = k2Vand the instability criterion becomes: 
g2 + k (14.17) +V &gt; (  +)k 
Equivalently, 
2  2 +  (14.18) +V &gt; (  +)g2  
Note: 
Figure 14.4: Kelvin-Helmholtz instability: a gravi
1. System stabilized to short  distu rbances by tationally stable base state is destabilized by shear. 
surface tension and to long  by gravity. 
2. For any given  (ork), on e can nd a critical
 
V that destabilizes the system.
 
Marginal Stability Curve: 
(   + g 1 )1/2 
V(k) = + k (14.19) + k + 
dV d 2V(k) has a minimum where = 0, i.e. V= dk dk
0. J 
This implies   +  = 0  kc = g = k2  
1 .lcap 2The corresponding Vc = V(kc) = + g is the min
imal speed 
necessary for waves. 
Figure 14.5: Fluid speed V(k) required for 
the growth of a wave with wavenumber k. E.g. Air 
blowing over water: (cgs)  2 2V= 1 103  70  Vc  650cm/s is the mini-c 1.2103 
mum wind speed required to generate waves. J 
1103 1These waves have wavenumber kc =  3.8cm, so c = 1.6cm. They thus correspond to capillary 70 
waves. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 58 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>14. Instability of Superposed Fluids
 
Figure 14.1: Wind over water: A layer of uid of density + moving with relative velocity V over a layer 
of uid of density  . 
Dene interface : h(x,y, z) = z  (x,y) = 0 so that h = (x,y,1). 
The unit normal is given by 
h (x,y,1) n= =	 (14.1) |h| ()1/2 x 2 + y 2 +1
Describe the uid as inviscid and irrotational, as is generally appropriate at high Re. 
Basic s
tate:  = 0 , u =  ,  = 2Vx for z. 1 
Perturbed state:  =  1Vx +  in z, where  is the perturbation eld. 2
Solve 
  u = 2 = 0 (14.2) 
subject to BCs: 
1.	   0 as z   
 2.	 Kinematic BC: = u  n,t 
where 
( )1 1    u =  Vx + =  Vx+ x+ y+ z (14.3) 2 2 x y z 
from which ( ) 1    =  V + (x)+ (y)+	 (14.4) t 2 x y  z 
Linearize: assumeperturbation elds ,  andtheirderivatives aresmall and thereforecanneglect 
their products. 
Thus  (x,y,1) and  =  1Vx + t 2 z 
  1  =  V on z = 0	 (14.5) z t 2 x 
3.	 Normal S
tress Balance: p  p+ =   n on z = .
 
Linearize: p  p+ = (xx + yy) on z = 0.
 
55</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>14.1. Rayleigh-Taylor Instability Chapter 14. Instability of Superposed Fluids 
14.1 Rayleigh-Taylor Instabilit y 
We consider an initially static system in which heavy uid overlies light uid: + &gt; , V = 0. Via 
(14.15), the system is unstable if 
  + g  C2 + k &lt; 0 (14.16) 0 = + k  + + 
k2 42i.e. if +   &gt; g = g2 . J 
Thus, for instability, we require:  &gt; 2c where c = is the capillary length. g 
Heuristic Argument: 
Change in Surface Energy: [f ] 
1ES =   l= 0 ds = 42k2. 
arc length Figure 14.2: The base state and the per- Change in gravitational potential energy: f ( ) turbed state of the Rayleigh-Taylor system, =  1g h2  h2 dx =  1g2. EG 02 0 4heavy uid over light. When is the total energy decreased?
 When 
Etotal = E S + EG &lt; 0, i.e. when g &gt; k2 ,
 
so  &gt; 2lc.
 
The system is thus unstable to long .
 
Note:
 
1. The system is stabilized to small  distu rbances by
 

 
2. The system is always unstable for su. large  
3. In a nite container with width smaller than 2 c,
 
the system may be stabilized by .
 
4. System may be stabilized by temperature gradients
 
since M
arangoni ow acts to resist surface defor
mation. E.g. a uid layer on the ceiling may be
 stabilized by heating the ceiling.
 
Figure 14.3: Rayleigh-Taylor instability may 
be stabilized by a vertical temperature gradient. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 57 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Capillary Rise (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>8.1. Dynamics	 Chapter 8. Capillary Rise 
Inertial Regime 
1. th
e timescale of	 establishment of Poiseuille
 
ow i
s  = 4a 2
 , the time required for bound 
ary eects to diuse across the tube 
2.	 until this time, viscous eects are negligible 
and the capillary rise is resisted primarily by Figure 8.4: The various scaling regimes of capillary 
uid inertia rise. 
7 2cos Initial Regime: z  0, z  0, so the force balance assumes the form 6 a az = We thus infer 
6 cos z(t) = t2 .7 a2 
7 (7 ) 2cos Once z  a, one must also consider the column mass, and so solve z + a	 z= . As the col6 6 a 
2 22cos umn accelerates from z = 0, zbecomes important, and the force balance becomes: 1 z = 2 a ( ) 1/2 4cos  z = U = is independent of g,.a
 ( ) 1/2
 4cos z = t.a 
Viscous Regime (t  ) Here, inertial eects become negligible, so the force balance assumes the form: 
2cos   8zz	 8zz 2cos   ga2 ( H )
 gz = 0. We thus infer H  z = , where H = ,  z =  1a a2	 ga2 ga 8 z 
	 8H Nondimensionalizing: z = z/H, t = t/,  = ;ga2 
 1 z	 1  t We thus have  z = z   dt =  dz = (1 1z  )dz = z  ln(1 z ). 1 1z  
 Note: at t  , z  1. 
  	 Early Viscous Regime: When z  1, we consider ln( z  1) = z   1 z 2and so infer z =2t .2 [ ] 1/2 acos Redimensionalizing thus yields Washburns Law: z = 2 t
Note that z is independent of g. 
Late Viscous Regime: As z approaches H, z  1. Thus, we consider t = [z  ln(1z )] = ln(1z ) 
and so infer z = 1 exp(t ). 
2cos  8H Redimensionalizing yields z = H[1 exp(t/)], where H = and  = ga ga2 . 
2 ( ) 1/2  4a	  4cos  4 a 2 Note: if rise timescale  = , inertia dominates, i.e. H  Uintertial=  inertial 	 a  
overshoot arises, giving rise to oscillations of the water column about its equilibrium height H. 
cos Wicking In the viscous regime, we have2= a 
8zz
a2 + g. What if the viscous stresses dominate 
gravity? This may arise, for example, for predomi
nantly horizontal ow (Fig. 8.5). 
2acos  1 d 2Force balance: = zz = z	 z = 8 2 dt( ) 1/2  acos  
2 t t (Washburns Law). 
Note: Front slows down, not due to g, but owing to 
increasing viscous dissipation with increasing col- Figure 8.5: Horizontal ow in a small tube. 
umn length. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 29	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>8.1. Dynamics Chapter 8. Capillary Rise 
8.1 Dynamics 
The column rises due to capillary forces, its rise being resisted by a combination of gravity, viscosity, uid I
inertia and dynamic pressure. Conservation of momentum dictates d (m(t)z(t)) = FTOT +vv  ndA,dt S 2wherethesecondterm ontheright-hand sideisthetotalmomentumux, which evaluatesto a2z = mz, 
so the force balance on the column may be expressed as 
  
1 2  m+ ma z= 2a cos  mg a2 z 2az  v (8.2) 2 ; ; ; ; ;
Inertia capillary force Added mass weight ; viscous force dynamic pressure 
where m = a2z. Now assume the ow in the tube is fully developed Poiseuille ow, which will be 
2 ( )
aestablished after a diusion time  =  . Thus, u(r) = 2z 1 ar 2
2 , and F = a2z is the ux along the 
tube. 
du  4The stress along the outer wall:  =  z.|r=a = dr a 
Finally, we need to estimate ma, which will dominate the dynamics at short time. We thus estimate the ( 1changeinkineticenergy asthecolumnrisesfrom z to z+z. Ek = mU2)
, where m = mc+m0+m 2 
(massinthecolumn,inthesphericalcap, andalltheothermass,respectively). Inthecolumn, mc = a2z, 
2 u = U. In the spherical cap, m0 = a3, u = U. In the outer region, radial inow extends to , but 3 
u(r) decays. 
Volume conservation requires: a2U = 2a2ur(a) ur(a) = U/2. 
a aContinuity thus gives: 2a2ur(a) = 2r2ur(r) ur(r) = r22 ur(a) = 2r2
2 U. 
eff U21 I (r)2Thus, the K.E. in the far eld: 1 m = urdm, where dm = 2r2dr. 2 2 a 
Hence 
1 ( ) 21 a2 
m = eff  U 2r2dr =  U2 2r2 a 1 1 1 = a4 dr = a3 
2r2 2a 
Now 
1)U2 1 (mc + m0 + m+ m2UU = Ek = 2 2
 
1 1
 (eff )
U2 = mc+ mc + m0 + m 2UU = 2 2 
1 ( ) 
U2 (2 1 )
= a2z +a2z+ a3+ a3 UU2 3 2 Figure 8.3: The dynamics of capillary rise. 
7  4Substituting for m = a2z, ma = a3 (added mass) and v = z into (8.2) we arrive at 6 a 
( )7 2 cos 1 8 z zz + a z=  z2   gz (8.3) 6 a 2 a2 
The static balance clearly yields the rise height, i.e. Jurins Law. But how do we get there? 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 28 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 8. Capillary Rise 
We want to predict the dependence of rise height H on both tube radius a and wetting properties. We 
do so by minimizing the total system energy, specically the surface and gravitational potential energies. 
The energy of the water column: 
E = (SL  SV )2aH+ 1 ga2H2= 2aHI +1 ga2H2 
 ;  2 2
surface energy  ;  
grav.P.E. 
will be a minimum with respect to H when dE = 0dH 
2SV SL 2 I H = = , fr om which we deduce ga ga
LV cos Jurins Law H = 2 (8. 1) gr 
Note: 
1. describes both capillary rise and descent: sign of H depend 
s on whether  &gt; /2 or  &lt; /2 
2. H increases as  decreases. Hmax for  = 0 
3. weve implicitly assumed R  H &amp; R  lC. 
The same result may be deduced via pressure or force ar
guments. 
By Pressure Argumen t 
Provided a  c, the meniscus will take the form 
aof a spherical cap with radius R = . Therefore cos 
cos  cos pA = pB  2= p0  2= p0  gH a a
 
2cos 
 H = as pr eviously. ga 
By Force Argument 
The weight of the column supported by the tensile force act
ing along the contact line: 
a2Hg = 2a(SV  SL) = 2a cos, from 
which Jurins Law again follows. 
Figure 8.2: Deriving the height of capillary rise in 
a tube via pressure arguments. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 27 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>8. Capillary Rise
 
Capillaryriseis oneofthemost well-known and vividillustrationsofcapillarity. Itisexploitedinanumber 
of biological processes, including drinking strategies of insects, birds and bats and plays an important role in a number of geophysical settings, including ow in porous media such as soil or sand. 
Historical Notes: 
	 L
eonardo da Vinci  ( 1452 - 1519) recorded the eect in his notes and proposed that mountain streams 
may result from capillary rise through a ne network of cracks 
	 Jacques Rohault (1620-1675) : erroneously suggested that capillary rise is due to suppresion of air 
circulation in narrow tube and creation of a vacuum 
	 Geovanni Borell i (1608-1675): demonstrated experimentally that h  1/r 
	 Geminiano Montanari  ( 1633-87): attributed circulation in plants to capillary rise 
	 Francis Hauksbe e (1700s): conducted an extensive series of capillary rise experiments reported by 
Newton in his Opticks but was left unattributed 
	 James Jurin (1684-1750): an English physiologist who independently conrmed h  1/r; hence 
Jurins Law. 
Consider capillary rise in a cylindrical tube of inner radius a (Fig. 8.2) 
Recall:
 
Spread
ing parameter: S = SV  (SL + LV ).
 
We now dene Imbibition / Impregnation parameter:
 I = 
SV  SL = LV cos
 
via force balance at contact line.
 Note: in capillary rise, I is the relevant parameter,
 
since motion of the contact line doesnt change the
 energy of the liquid-vapour interface.
 
Imbibition Condition: I
 &gt; 0. 
Note: since I = S + LV , the imbibition condition 
I &gt; 0 is always more easily met than the spreading 
condition, S &gt; 0 Figure 8.1: Capillary rise and fall in a tube for two 
 most liquids soak sponges and other porous me- values of the imbibition parameter I: 
dia, while complete spreading is far less common. I &gt; 0 (left) and I &lt; 0 (right). 
26</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>More on Fluid Statics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>6.1. Capillary forces on oating bodies Chapter 6. More on Fluid statics 
Figure 6.2: A heavy body may be supported on a uid surface by a combination of buoyancy and surface 
tension. 
6.1 Capillary forces on oating bodies 
 arise owing to interaction of the menisci of oating bodies 
 attractive or repulsive depending on whether the menisci are of the same or opposite sense 
 explains the formation of bubble rafts on champagne 
 explains the mutual attraction of Cheerios and their attraction to the walls 
 utilized in technology for self-assembly on the microscale 
Capillary attraction Wan t to calculate the attractive force between two oating bodies separated by 
a distance R. Total energy of the system is given by 
f 1  1 h(x) 
Etot = dA(R)+ dx gz dz (6.5) 
 0 
where the rst term in (6.5) corresponds to the total surface energy when the two bodies are a distance 
R apart, and the second term is the total gravitational potential energy of the uid. Dierentiating (6.5) 
yields the force acting on each of the bodies: 
dEtot(R)F(R) =  (6. 6) dR 
Such capillary forces are exploited by certain water walking insects to climb menisci. By deforming the freesu
rface, they generate a lateral force that drives them up menisci (Hu &amp; Bush 2005). 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 23 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>6. More on Fluid statics
Last time, we saw that the balance of curvature and hydrostatic pressures requires
g= n=xx
(1+2)3/2.
x
We linearized, assuming x1, to nd (x).Note: we can integrate directly
xxx d2d1gx= g =3/2(1+2dxx)/parenleftbigg
2/parenrightbigg
dx1/2(1+2
/integraldisplayx)
1
g2 d1 1= dx= 1 = 1 sin 2 dx1/2 1/2x(1+2x)
(1+2x)
1sin+g2=2(6.1)
Figure 6.1: Calculating the shape and maximal rise height of a static meniscus.
Maximal rise height: At z=hwe have =e, so from (6.1)1gh2=(12sine), from which
h=
2c(1sine)1/2wherec=/radicalbig
/g (6.2)
Alternative perspective: Consider force balance on the meniscus.
Horizontal force balance:1sin+ gz2= (6.3)2
horiz. pr/bracehtipupleft
oj/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft
ecti/bracehtipupright
on of T 1/bracehtipupleft /bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft /bracehtipuprightT2
hydrostatic suction/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
Vertical force balance:
cos=
vert. proj. of T/integraldisplay
gzdx (6.4)/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft /bracehtipupright
1
wei
Atx= 0, where =e, givescose= weight of uid d/bracehtipupleftx
ght/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft
of flu/bracehtipupright
id
isplaced above z= 0.
Note:cose= weight of displaced uid is + /according to whether eis smaller or larger than.2
Floating Bodies Without considering interfacial eects, one anticipates that heavy things sink and light
things oat. This doesnt hold for objects small relative to the capillary length.
Recall: Archimedean force on a submerged body FA=/integraltext
pndS=gVB.S
In general, the hydrodynamic force acting on a body in a uid
Fh=/integraltext
TndS, whereT=pI+2E=pIfor static uid.S/integraltext 
HereFh=pndS=S/integraltext
gzndS=/integraltext SgzdVby divergence theorem. This is equal toV
gdVz=gVz= weight of displaced u/integraltext
id. The archimedean force can thus support weightV
of a body Mg=BgVifF&gt; B(uid density larger than body density); otherwise, it sinks.
22</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Spinning, Tumbling and Rolling Drops (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>7.2. Rolling drops Chapter 7. Spinning, tumbling and rolling drops
Light drops: For the case of  &lt;0,  &lt;0, a spinning drop is stabilized on axis by centrifugal pressures.
For high||, it is well described by a cylinder with spherical caps. Drop energy:
1E=I2+ 2
rL2
S fR/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleftaat/bracehtipupleftyot ional/bracehtipuprightur ce energK.E./bracehtipupleft /bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft /bracehtipupright
2Neglecting the end caps, we write volume V=r2Land moment of inertia I=mr= Lr4.2 2
Figure 7.3: A bubble or a drop suspended in a denser uid, spinning with angular speed .
The energy per unit drop volume is thusE=12r2+2.V4 r
Mini
mizing with respect to r:
31d/parenleftbig /E/parenrightbig 1 1/3/2=12r2= 0,whi ch occurs when r=/parenleftBig
4. Nowr=V=4
2 dr V 2 r 2/parenrightBig
L/parenleftBig
2/parenrightBig
/parenleftbig3/2/parenleftbig /parenrightbig
Vonneguts Formula: =12V
3/2/parenrightbig
allows inference of fromL, useful technique for small 4 L
as it a
voids diculties associated with uid-solid contact.
Note:rgrows with and decreases with .
7.2 Rolling drops
Figure 7.4: A liquid drop rolling down an inclined plane.
(Aussillous and Quere 2003 ) Energetics: for steady descent at speed V, MgVsin=Rate of viscous
dissipation= 2/integraltext
(u)2dV, whereVdis the dissipation zone, so this sets V =V/Ris the angularVdspeed. Stability characteristics dierent: bioconcave oblate ellipsoids now stable.
MIT OCW
: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 25 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>7. Spinning, tumbling and rolling 
drops 
7.1 Rotating Drops 
We want to nd z = h(r) (see right). Normal stress 
balance on S: 
1 2P + 2 r =   n 
2 "    
centrifugal 
Nondimensionalize: 
 ( r ) 2 p +4B0 =   n,a
 ap 2 = "	   
curvature 
3 a centrifugal where p ,  = = = =  8 curvature 
Rotational Bond number = const. Dene surface 
functional: f(r,) = z  h(r)  vanishes on the 
surface. Thus 
2f zhr (r)r rhr r hrr n = ||	 )3/2 = and  n = (1+h2 (r))1/2 r2(1+h2 
r	 r Figure 7.1: The radial prole of a rotating drop. 
Brown + Scriven (1980) computed drop shapes and stability for B0 &gt; 0: 
1. for	  &lt; 0.09, only axisymmetric solutions, 
oblate ellipsoids 
2. for 0.09 &lt;  &lt; 0.31, both axisymmetric and 
lobed solutions possible, stable 
3. for	  &gt; 0.31 no st ab le solution, only lobed 
forms 
Tektites : centimetric metallic ejecta formed from 
spinn
ing cooling silica droplets generated by mete
orite impact. 
Q1: Why are they so much bigger than ra indrops? V 
From raindrop scaling, we expect c  but g 
both ,  higher by a factor of 10  large tektite 
size suggests they are not equilibrium forms, but 
froze into shape during ight. 
Q2: Why are their shapes so dierent from those of 
raindr
ops? Owing to high  of tektites, the internal 
dynamics(esp. rotation)dominatesthe aerodynamics  drop shape set by its rotation. 
Figure 7.2: The ratio of the maximum radius to 
the unperturbed radius is indicated as a function of . Stable shapes are denoted by the solid line, their metastable counterparts by dashed lines. Predicted 3-dimensional forms are compared to photographs of natural tektites. From Elkins-Tanton, Ausillous, 
Bico, Qu er e and Bush (2003). 
24</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Spreading (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>18.2. Immiscible Drops at an Interface Pujado &amp; Scriven 1972 Chapter 18. Spreading 
 t1/10 But this is not observed; instead, one sees R . Why? 
Hardy (1919) obser ved a precursor lm, the evidence of which was the disturbance of dust ahead of the 
drop. This precursor lm is otherwise invisible, with thickness e  20A 
Its or
igins lie in the force imbalance at the contact line (S &gt; 0) and its stability results from interactions 
between the uid and solid (e.g. Van der Waals) 
Physical picture 
Force at Apparent Contact Line: F =  + SL  
2 
cos d  SL = (1  cos d)  d for small 2 
d. 
3DNote: F  S. Now recall from last class: FU = U2 .d 
d 2 dR d ULetting F  2 , we nd U = = F =  d3 , where dt 3D  6D  U=  . Since the drop is small, it is a section of a sphere, so 
that  U = R3d (18.4) Figure 18.2: The precursor lm of a4 
dd spreading drop. 3 dR =  1Hence . Substituting in dR from above, we nd: R dt  d dt dt 
1 dd U
d dt = R 3 
d.
 
1/3 1/3  U1/3  dd
 13/3Now substitute R = L (U/d) and L =  U d dt L d 
( ) 3/10 L d = (Tanner  s Law) (18.5) Ut
)1/10 (
 so using (18.4) yields R  LU t , which is consistent with observation. L 
18.2 Immiscible Drops at  an Interface Pujado &amp; Scriven 1972 
Gravitationally unstable congurations can arise (a &lt; b &lt; c or c &lt; a &lt; b). 
 weight of drops su pported by interfacial tensions. 
 
 if drop size R &lt; lbc bc , it can be suspended by the interface. (bc)g
Sessile Lens, a &lt; c &lt; b: stable for drops of any size, e.g. oil on water. 
Figure 18.3: An immiscible liquid drop oats on a liquid bath. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 74 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>18.5. The Beating Heart Stocker &amp; Bush (JFM 2007) Chapter 18. Spreading 
18.5 The Beating Hea rt Stocker &amp; Bush (JFM 2007) 
. 
When a drop of  mineral oil containing a small quantity of non-ionic, water-insoluble surfactant (Tergitol) 
Figure 18.5: An oil drop oscillates on the water surface. Note the ring of impurities that marks the edge 
of the internal circulation. 
is so emplaced, a sessile lens with S &lt; 0 is formed. However, no equilibrium shape emerges; the lens 
is characterized by periodic uctuations in radius, and so resembles a beating heart. 
The phenomenon was  rst reported by Buetschli (1894), a professor of Zoology at the University of 
Heidelberg, in his treatise Investigations on Protoplasm. It was subsequently described qualitatively by 
Sebba (1979, 1981). 
Motivation : Th e ultimate goal of physiologists is to be able to explain living behaviour in terms of 
physicochemical forces. Thus, any expansion of our knowledge of such forces, based on inanimate systems, 
should be examined to see whether this might not oer insight into biological behaviour . Sebba (1979). 
Many biological syst ems exhibit periodic behaviour; e.g. oscillations of cells of nerves and muscle 
tissue, oscillations in mitochondria, and biological clocks. Conversion of chemical into mechanical energy 
is one of the main processes in biological movements; e.g. chloroplast movements and muscle contraction. 
Observations: 
 lens behaviour is  independent of water depth, strongly dependent on surfactant concentration  
 for  = 0  no beating - stable sessile lens 
 for moderate  st eady beating observed 
 for high  d rop edges become unstable to ngers 
 for highest , l ens explodes into a series of smaller beating lenses. 
 beating marked  by slow expansion, rapid retraction 
 odour of T ergitol always accompanies beating 
MIT OCW: 18.357  Interfacial Phenomena 76 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>18. Spreading 
Recall: gravity currents, the spreading of heavy uid under the inuence of gravity.
 
further reading: John E. Simpson -Gravity Currents: In the Environment and the Laboratory.
 
Stage I: Re  1
 
Flow forced by gravity, and resisted by uid iner
tia:
 
gh U2	     U  g h where g = R R 
 g. 
VContinuity: V = R2(t)h(t) = const.  h(t)  R2(t)
 
dR
  U   g V 1  RdR  g Vdt  R(t) dt R 
 V)1/4t1/2	 Figure 18.1: Spreading of a uid volume un(g der the i nuence of gravity. 
 UR Note: U  g h decreases until Re =   1. 
Stage II: Re  1 
p = 2 u gh UFlow forced by gravity, resisted by viscosity:   r z2 R h2 
now substitute for h(t)= V/R2(t) to obtain: 
3	 3dR R gV	(gV)1/8 
1/8U =    R  t	 ( 18.1) dt t R7	  
18.1 Spreading of sma ll drops on solids 
For a drop of undeformed radius R placed on a solid substrate, spreading will in general be driven by both 
gravity and curvature pressure. 
gh	 h Gravity: pg  , Curvature: pc  R3 .R 
Continuity V = R2(t)h(t) =const. 
pg gR2 gV 1Which dominates?  = Bond number. Bo =   gravity becomes progr essively more pc 	 h h 
important as the drop spreads !? 
Recall: 
	 drop behaviour dep ends on S = SV  SL  . 
	 When S &lt; 0: P artial wetting. Spreading arises until a puddle forms. 
	 When S &gt; 0: Comp lete wetting. Here, one expects spreading forced by the unbalanced tension at 
the contact line. 
U  R2  S  2R	 (18.2) h '-v" '-v" '-v" '-v" drop area contact line force perimeter 
viscous stress 
U	  R3dR  SU Thus, we expect RdR  S  Shdt   R2 dt  
)1/4(SU 1/4 R  t	 (18. 3)  
73</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>18.5. The Beating Heart Stocker &amp; Bush (JFM 2007)	 Chapter 18. Spreading 
	 placing lid on t he chamber suppresses the oscillations  evaporation is a critical ingredient. 
Physical pictur e 
Stage I: S low expansion of drop.
 
Adsorption of surfactant onto oil-water interface  ow decreases. Evaporation of surfactant from air-
water surface  aw increases.
 
Stage II: Rapid retraction.
 
Flushing of surfactant onto air-water interface  aw decreases and ow increases. BUT WHY?
 
Internal circulation : conned to the outer extremities
 
of the lens, absent in the at central region. Marangoni
 
ow associated with gradient in  - indicates  is low
est at the drop edge. Consistent with radial gradi
ent in adsorption ux along surface. Reects geomet
ric constraint - less surfactant available to corners than
 
bulk.
 
Such Marangoni shear layers are unstable to longitu
dinal rolls or transverse waves (as in the wine glass).
 
The ushing events are associated with breaking Marangoni waves (Frenkel &amp; Halpern 2005 ).
 
Another surfactant-induced auto-oscillation : The Spitting Drop (Fernandez &amp; Homsy 2004) 
	 chemical reaction pr oduces surfactant at drop surface 
	 following release of  rst drop, periodic spitting 
	 rationalized in t erms of tip-streaming (Taylor 1934), which arises only in the presence of surfactant 
(de Bruijn 1993) for /d  104 and Ca = G/ &gt;0.4 
Figure 18.6: Internal circulation of the beat
ing heart. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 77	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>18.3. Oil Spill Chapter 18. Spreading 
18.3 Oil Spill 
3 Distinct phases: 
J1/4 t1/2Phase I Inertia vs. Gravity: U  g h(t)  R(t)   (g U0)
(
g  V3 )1/8 
t1/8Phase II Viscosity vs. Gravity : as previously, R  0 
 
Phase III Line tension vs. Viscosity: For S &lt; 0, an equilibrium conguration arises  drop takes the 
form of a sessile lens. For S &gt; 0 the oil will completely cover the water, spreading to a layer of molecular 
thickness. 
Phase IIIa Viscou s resistance from dissipation within oil. As previously: )1/4(
U SU t1/4R2  2RS  R h  
Phase IIIb Spreading driven by S, resisted by viscous dissipation in the underlying uid.  
Blasius boundary la yer grows on base of spreading current like   t. 
  ( )1/2 S 1/4t3/4t  RdR  S  U R2  S  2R where   t1/2  R  . dt  
18.4 Oil on water: A  brief review 
When an oil drop is emplaced on the water surface, its behaviour will depend on the spreading coecient 
S  aw  oa  ow (18.6) 
For S &gt; 0, t he droplet will completely wet the underlying liquid, and so spread to a layer of molecular
 
thickness.
 
References: Franklin (1760); Fay (1963); DePietro &amp; Cox (1980); Foda &amp; Cox (1980); Joanny (1987);
 
Brochard-Wyart et al. (1996); Fraaije &amp; Cazabat (1989).
 
For S &lt; 0, an  equilibrium conguration arises: the drop assumes the form of a sessile lens.
 
The statics of the sessile lens have been considered by Langmuir (1933) and Pujado &amp; Scriven (1972).
 
their dynamics has been treated by Wilson &amp; Williams (1997) and Miksis &amp; Vanden-Broeck (2001).
 
Figure 18.4: An oil drop spreading on the water surface. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 75 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Wetting (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3. Wetting 
Puddles . What sets their size?
 
Knowing nothing of surface ch emistry, one anticip at es that Laplace pressure balances hydrostatic pressure
 J
if /H  gH  H &lt; c = /g = capillary length. 
Note: 
1. Drops with R &lt; c remain heavily spherical 
2. Large drops spread to depth H  c so that 
Laplace+hydrostaticpressuresbalance atthe 
drops edge. A volume V will thus spread 
to a radius R s.t. R2c = V, from which 
1/2R = (V/ c) . 
3. This is the case for H2O on most surfaces, Figure 3.1: Spreading of drops of increasing size. where a contact line exists. 
Note: In general, surface chemistry can dominate and one need not have a contact line. 
More generally, wetting occurs at uid-solid contact. Two possibilities exist: partial wetting or total
 
wetting, depending on the surface energies of the 3 interfaces ( LV ,SV ,SL).
 
Now, just as  = LV is a surface energy per area or tensile force per length at a liquid-vapour surface,
 
SL and SV are analogous quantities at solid-liquid and solid-vapour interfaces.
 
The degree of wetting determined by spreading parameters :
 
S = [Esubstrate]dry  [Esubstrate]wet = SV  (SL + LV ) (3.1) 
where only LV can be easily measured.
 
Total Wetting : S &gt; 0 , e = 0 liquid spreads completely in order to minimize its surface energy. e.g.
 
silicon on glass, water on clean glass.
 
Note: Silicon oil is more likely to spread than H2O since w  70 dyn/cm &gt;  s.o.  20 dyn/cm. Final
 
result: a lm of nanoscopic thickness resulting from competition between molecular and capillary forces.
 
Partial wetting : S &lt; 0, e &gt; 0. In absence of 
g, forms a spherical cap meeting solid at a con
tact angle e. A liquid is wetting on a particular 
solid when e &lt; /2, non-wetting or weakly wetting 
when e &gt; /2. For H2O, a surface is hydrophilic 
if e &lt; /2, hydrophobic if e &gt; /2 and superhy
drophobic if e &gt; 5/6. 
Figure 3.2: The same water drop on hydrophobic 
and hydrophilic surfaces. 
Note: if g = 0, drops always take the form of a spherical cap  attening indicates the eects of gravity. 
11</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>More Forced Wetting (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16. More forced wetting
 
Some clarication notes on Wetting. 
Figure 16.1: Three dierent wetting states. 
Last class, we discussed the Cassie state only in the context 
of drops in a Fakir state, i.e. suspended partially on a bed of 
air. There is also a wet Cassie state. More generally, the Cassie-Baxter model applies to wetting on a planar but chemically heterogeneous surfaces. Consider a surface with 2 species, one with area fraction f
1 and 
equilibrium contact angle 1, another with area fraction f2 and 
angle 2. Energy variation associated with the front advancing 
a distance dx: dE = f
1(SL  SV )1dx + f2(SL  SV )2dx + cosdx. 
Thus, dE = 0 when 
cos = f1 cos1+f2 cos2 (Cassie-Baxter relation) (16.1) 
Special Case: in the Fakir state, the two phases are the solid 
(1 = e and f1 = S) and air ( 2 = , f2 = 1 S) so we have 
cos = S cose  1+S (16.2) 
as previously. As before, in this hydrophobic case, the Wenzel state is energetically favourable when 
dEW &lt;dEC, i.e. cos C &lt; cose &lt; 0 
where cos C = (S  1)/(r  S), i.e. E is between /2 and C. 
However, experiments indicate that even in this regime, air may remain trapped, so that a metastable 
Cassie state emerges. 
16.1 Hydrophobic Case: e &gt; /2, cos e &lt; 0 
In the Fakir state, the two phases are the solid (  = e, f1 = ) and vapour ( 2 = , f2 = 1 s). 
Cassie-Baxter: 
cos = S cose  1+s (16.3) 
as deduced previously. As previously, the Wenzel state is energetically favourable when dEW &lt; dEL, i.e. 
S 1 cosC &lt; cose &lt; 0 where cos C = rS . Experiments indicate that even in this region, air may remain 
trapped, leading to a meta-stable Fakir state. 
Figure 16.2: Wetting of a tiled (chem
ically heterogeneous) surface. 
64</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>16.2. Hydrophilic Case: e &lt; /2 Chapter 16. More forced wetting 
Figure 16.3: Relationship between cos  and cose for dierent wetting states. 
16.2 Hydrophilic Case: e &lt; /2 
Here, the Cassie state corresponds to a tiled surface with 2 phases corresponding to the solid ( 1 = e,
 
f1 = S) and the uid ( 2 = 0, f2 = 1 S).
 
Cassie-Baxter  cos = 1  S + S cose, which describes a Wet Cassie state. Energy variation:
 
dE = (r  S)(SL  SV )dx +(1  S)dx.
 
SL  SV 1 S dE = 0 if cos e = &gt;  cos (16.4) c r  S 
For e &lt; c, a lm will impregnate the rough solid. Criteria for this transition can also be deduced by 
equating energies in the Cassie and Wenzel states, i.e. r cose = 1 S +S cose  e = C. Therefore, 
when /2 &gt; e &gt; C, the solid remains dry ahead of the drop  Wenzel applies  when e &lt; C  lm 
penetrates texture and system is described by Wet Cassie state. 
Johnson + Dettre  ( 1964) examined water drops on wax, whose roughness they varied by baking. They 
showed an increase and then decrease of   = a  r as the roughness increased, and system went from 
smooth to Wenzel to Cassie states. 
Water-repellency : important for corrosion-resistance, self-cleaning, drag-reducing surfaces. It requires 
the maintenance of a Cassie State. This means the required impregnation pressure must be exceeded by the curvature pressure induced by roughness. E.g.1 Static Drop in a Fakir State 
The interface will touch down if  &gt; h. Pressure balance:    so  &gt; h  l2 &gt; h i.e. R &lt; l2 
R l2 R h . 
Thus taller pillars maintain Fakir State. (see Fig. 16.5) 
E.g.2 Impacting rain drop : impr egnation pressure  P  U2 or Uc where c is the speed of sound in 
water. E.g.3 Submerged surface, e.g. on a side of a boat. P = gz is i
 mpregnation pressure. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 65 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>16.3. Forced Wetting: the Landau-Levich-Derjaguin Problem Chapter 16. More forced wetting 
Figure 16.4: Contact angle as a function of surface roughness for water drops on wax. 
Figure 16.5: To remain in a Cassie state, the internal drop pressure P0 + 2/R must not exceed the 
curvature pressure induced by the roughness, roughly /. 
16.3 Forced Wetting: the La ndau-Levich-Derjaguin Problem 
Withdraw a plate from a viscous uid with constant speed. What is the thickness of the lm that coats 
the plate? Consider a static meniscus. 
VFor relatively thick lms (C a  1), balancing viscous stresses and gravity:   gh h 
  1/2V 1/2h   cCa (Derjaguin 1943) (16.5) g 
 V viscous where c = and Ca = = is the Capillary number. g  curvature 
But this scaling is not observed at low Ca, where the coating is resisted principally by curvature pressure  
rather than gravity. Recall static meniscus (Lecture 6): (x) = 2 c (1 sin(x)) and internal pressure:   
p(x) = p0  g(x). As x  0, (x) 2c and p(x) p0  2gc. It is this capillary suction inside 
the meniscus that resists the rise of thin lms. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 66 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>16.3. Forced Wetting: the Landau-Levich-Derjaguin Problem Chapter 16. More forced wetting
Thin lm wetting
We describe the ow in terms of two distinct re-
gions:
Region I: Static meniscus. The balance is between
gravity and curvature pressures: g nso curva-
ture n1/c.
Region II: Dynamic meniscus (coating zone). The
balance here is between viscous stresses and curvature
pressure. Dene this region as the zone over which lm
thickness decreases from 2h toh,whose vertical extent L
t
o be specied by pressure matching. In region II, cur-
vature nh/L2. Matching pressure at point A:
p20h h
L2p0gcL ch L=chgc 
is the geometric mean of candh.
Figure 16.6: The two regions of the meniscusForceb
alanceinZoneII:viscousstressvs. curvaturepres-
VPh1 next to a moving wall.sure:h2 L L2.L
3
/2Substitute in for Lh3VL3Ca2ch3/2h/3  V
cCawherec=/radicalBig
,
gCa= .
Implicit in above: hL,Lc,gh
3, or equivalentlyLCa1/31. Matched asymptotics give
h0.942cCa/3.
E.g.1Jump ou
t of pool at 1m/s: Ca102soh0.1mm300g entrained.
E.g.2Drink water from a glass, V1cm/sCa104.
Figure 16.7: Left: A static meniscus. Right: Meniscus next to a wall moving upwards with speed V.
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 67 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Marangoni Flows II (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>10.4. Bubble motion	 Chapter 10. Marangoni Flows II 
3. Vertical Soap Film 
	 Vertical force balan ce: gh(z)= d . The weight of a soap dz 
lm is supported by Marangoni stress. 
	 Internal dynamics: note  that lm is dynamic (as are all
 
Marangoni ows), if it were static, its max height would
 
be c. It is constantly drying due to the inuence of gravity.
 
d du 	 On the surface:   b alance of Maran goni and visdz dx 
cous stresses. 
d2 u	 Inside: g  dx2 Gravity-viscous. 
Figure 10.6: The  weight of a vertical 
soap lm is supported by Marangoni 10.4 Bubble motion stresses on its surface. 
Theoretical predictions for the rise speed of small drops or bub
bles do not adequately describe observations. Specically, air bubbles rise at low Reynolds number at 
rates appropriate for rigid spheres with equivalent buoyancy in all but the most carefully cleaned uids. 
This discrepancy may be rationalized through consideration of the inuence of surfactants on the surface 
dynamics. The ow generated by a clean spherical bubble or radius a rising at low Re = Ua/ is in
tuitively obvious. The interior ow is toroidal, while the surface motion is characterized by divergence 
and convergence at, respectively, the leading and trailing surfaces. The presence of surface contamination 
changes the ow qualitatively. 
The eective surface elasticity imparted by the surfactants acts to suppress the surface motion. Sur
factant is generaly swept to the trailing edge of the bubble, where it accumulates, giving rise to a local 
decrease in surface tension. The resulting for-to-aft surface tension gradient results in a Marangoni stress 
that resists surface motion, and so rigidies the bubble surface. The air bubble thus moves as if its surface 
were stagnant, and it is thus that its rise speed is commensurate with that predicted for a rigid sphere: the 
no-slip boundary condition is more appropriate than the free-slip. Finally, we note that the characteristic 
Marangoni stress /a is most pronounced for small bubbles. It is thus that the inuence of surfactants 
is greatest on small bubbles. 
Figure 10.7: A rising drop or bubble (left) is marked by internal circulation in a clean system that is 
absent in a contaminated, surfactant-laden uid (right). Surfactant sticks to the surface, and the induced 
Marangoni stress rigidies the drop surface. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 39	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>10.2. Surfactants Chapt er 10. Marangoni Flows II 
Surfactants and a murder mystery . From  Nature, 22, 1880 : 
In the autumn of 1878 a man committed a terrible crime in Somerset, which was for some time involved 
in deep mystery. His wife, a handsome and decent mulatto woman, disappeared suddenly and entirely from sight, after going home from church on Sunday, October 20. Suspicion immediately fell upon the husband, a clever young fellow of about thirty, but no trace of the missing woman was left behind, and there seemed a strong probability that the crime would remain undetected. On Sunday, however, October 27, a week after the woman had disappeared, some Somerville boatmen looking out towards the sea, as is their custom, were struck by observing in the Long Bay Channel, the surface of which was rued by a slight breeze, a streak of calm such as, to use their own illustration, a cask of oil usually diuses around it when in 
the water . The feverish anxiety about the missing woman suggested some strange connection 
between this singular calm and the mode of her disappearance. Two or three days after - why not sooner I cannot tell you - her brother and three other men went out to the spot where it was observed, and from which it had not disappeared since Sunday, and with a series of sh-hooks ranged along a long line dragged the bottom of the channel, but at rst without success. Shifting the position of the boat, they dragged a little further to windward, and presently the line was caught. With water glasses the men discovered that it had caught in a skeleton which was held down by some heavy weight. They pulled on the line; something suddenly gave was, and up came the skeleton of the trunk, pelvis, and legs of a human body, from which almost every vestige of esh had disappeared, but which, from the minute fragments remaining, and the terrible stench, had evidently not lain long in the water. The husband was a sherman, and Long Bay Channel was a favourite shing ground, and he calculated, truly enough, that the sh would very soon destroy all means of identication; but it never entered into his head that as they did so their ravages, combined with the process of decomposition, set free the matter which was to write the traces of 
his crime on the surface of the water. The case seems to be an exceedingly interesting one; the calm is not mentioned in any book on medical jurisprudence that I have, and the doctors seem not to have had experience of such an occurrence. A diver went down and found a stone with a rope attached, by which the body had been held down, and also portions of the scalp and of the skin of the sole of the foot, and of clothing, by means of which the body was identied. The husband was found guilty and executed. 
MIT OCW: 18.357  In
 terfacial Phenomena 37 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>10.2. Surfactants Chapter 10. Marangoni Flows II 
Figure 10.3: The footprint of a whale, caused by the whales sweeping biomaterial to the sea surface. The 
biomaterial acts as a surfactant in locally suppressing the capillary waves evident elsewhere on the sea 
surface. Observed in the wake of a whale on a Whale Watch from Boston Harbour. 
Special case: expansion of a spherical surfactant-laden bubble. 
 dR d dR = 2 dR +(  n) ur = 0. Here   n =2/R, ur = so + 2 =0  d 4R2 =const., so t dt dt R dt  R 
the surfactant is conserved. 
Marangoni Elasticity The pr incipal dynamical inuence of surfactants is to impart an eective 
elasticity to the interface. One can think of a clean interface as a slippery trampoline that resists 
deformation through generation of normal curvature pressures. However, such a surface cannot generate 
traction on the interface. However, a surface-laden interface, like a trampoline, resists surface deformation 
as does a clean interface, but can also support tangential stresses via Marangoni elasticity. Specically, 
the presence of surfactants will serve not only to alter the normal stress balance (through the reduction 
of ), but also the tangential stress balance through the generation of Marangoni stresses. 
The presence of sur factants will act to suppress any uid motion characterized by non-zero surface 
divergence. For example, consider a uid motion characterized by a radially divergent surface motion. 
The presence of surfactants results in the redistribution of surfactants:  is reduced near the point of 
divergence. The resulting Marangoni stresses act to suppress the surface motion, resisting it through an 
eective surface elasticity. Similarly, if the ow is characterized by a radial convergence, the resulting 
accumulation of surfactant in the region of convergence will result in Marangoni stresses that serve to 
resist it. It is this eective elasticity that gives soap lms their longevity: the divergent motions that 
would cause a pure liquid lm to rupture are suppressed by the surfactant layer on the soap lm surface. 
The ability of sur factant to suppress ows with non-zero surface divergence is evident throughout 
the natural world. It was rst remarked upon by Pliny the Elder, who rationalized that the absence of 
capillary waves in the wake of ships is due to the ships stirring up surfactant. This phenomenon was also 
widely known to spear-shermen, who poured oil on the water to increase their ability to see their prey, 
and by sailors, who would do similarly in an attempt to calm troubled seas. Finally, the suppression of 
capillary waves by surfactant is at least partially responsible for the footprints of whales (see Fig. 10.3). 
In the wake of whales, even in turbulent roiling seas, one seas patches on the sea surface (of characteristic 
width 5-10m) that are perfectly at. These are generally acknowledged to result from the whales sweeping 
biomaterial to the surface with their tails, this biomaterial serving as a surfactant that suppresses capillary 
waves. 
MIT OCW: 18.357  In terfacial Phenomena 36 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>10.2. Surfactants	 Chapter 10. Marangoni Flows II 
Figure 10.2: a) A typical molecular structure of surfactants. b)The typical dependence of  on surfactant 
concentration c. 
10.2 Surfactants 
Surfactants are molecules that have an anity for interfaces; common examples include soap and oil. 
Owing to their molecular structure (e.g. a hydrophilic head and hydrophobic tail, Fig. 10.2a), they 
nd it energetically favourable to reside at the free surface. Their presence reduces the surface tension; 
consequently, gradients in surfactant concentration  result in surface tension gradients. Surfactants thus 
generate a special class of Marangoni ows. There are many dierent types of surfactants, some of which 
are insoluble (and so remain on the surface), others of which are soluble in the suspending uid and 
so diuse into the bulk. For a wide range of common surfactants, surface tension is a monotonically 
decreasing function of  until a critical micell concentration (CMC) is achieved, beyond CMC there is no 
further dependence of  on  (Fig. 10.2b). 
Surfactant properties : 
	 Diusivity prescri bes the rate of diusion, Ds (bulk diusivity Db), of a surfactant along an 
interface 
	 Solubility prescri bes the ease with which surfactant passes from the surface to the bulk. An 
insoluble surfactant cannot dissolve into the bulk, must remain on the surface. 
	 Volatility prescri bes the ease with which surfactant sublimates. 
Theoretical Approach : because  of the dependence of  on the surfactant concentration, and the ap
pearance of  in the boundary conditions, N-S equations must be augmented by an equation governing 
the evolution of . In the bulk, 
c = Db2+ u  c c	 (10.1)  t 
The concentration of sur factant  on a free surface evolves according to 
 2+ s  (us)+(s  n)(u  n)= J (,Cs)+ Ds	 (10.2) st 
where us is the surface velocity, s is the surface gradient operator and Ds is the surface diusivity of 
the surfactant (Stone 1999). J is a surfactant source term associated with adsorption onto or desorption 
from the surface, and depends on both the surface surfactant concentration  and the concentration in the 
bulk Cs. Tracing the evolution of a contaminated free surface requires the use of Navier-Stokes equations, 
relevant boundary conditions and the surfactant evolution equation (10.2). The dependence of surface 
tension on surfactant concentration, (), requires the coupling of the ow eld and surfactant eld. In 
certain special cases, the system may be made more tractable. For example, for insoluble surfactants, 
J = 0. Many surfactants have suciently small Ds that surface diusivity may be safely neglected. 
MIT OCW: 18.357  In terfacial Phenomena 35	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>10. Marangoni Flows II 
10.1 Tears of Wine 
The rst Marangoni ow considered was the tears of wine phenomenon (Thomson 1885 ), which actually 
predates Marangonis rst published work on the subject by a decade. The tears of wine phenomenon 
is readily observed in a wine glass following the establishment of a thin layer of wine on the walls of the 
glass. 
An illustration of th e tears of wine phenomenon is shown in Fig. 10.1. Evaporation of alcohol occurs 
everywhere along the free surface. The alcohol concentration in the thin layer is thus reduced relative to 
that in the bulk owing to the enhanced surface area to volume ratio. As surface tension decreases with 
alcohol concentration, the surface tension is higher in the thin lm than the bulk; the associated Marangoni 
stress drives upow throughout the thin lm. The wine climbs until reaching the top of the lm, where 
it accumulates in a band of uid that thickens until eventually becoming gravitationally unstable and 
releasing the tears of wine. The tears or legs roll back to replenish the bulk reservoir, but with uid 
that is depleted in alcohol. 
The ow relies on t he transfer of chemical potential energy to kinetic and ultimately gravitational 
potential energy. The process continues until the fuel for the process, the alcohol is completely depleted. 
For certain liquors (e.g. port), the climbing lm, a Marangoni shear layer, goes unstable to streamwise 
vortices and an associated radial corrugation -the tear ducts of wine (Hosoi &amp; Bush, JFM 2001). When 
the descending tears reach the bath, they appear to recoil in response to the abrupt change in . The 
tears or legs of wine are taken by sommeliers to be an indicator of the quality of wine. 
Figure 10.1: The tears of wine. Fluid is drawn from the bulk up the thin lm adjoining the walls of the 
glass by Marangoni stresses induced by evaporation of alcohol from the free surface. 
34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>10.3. Surfactant-induced Marangoni ows Chapter 10. Marangoni Flows II 
Figure 10.4: The soap boat. A oating body (length 2.5cm) contains a small volume of soap, which serves 
as its fuel in propelling it across the free surface. The soap exits the rear of the boat, decreasing the local 
surface tension. The resulting fore-to-aft surface tension gradient propels the boat forward. The water 
surface is covered with Thymol blue, which parts owing to the presence of soap, which is thus visible as a 
white streak. 
10.3 Surfactant-induced Marangoni ows 
1. Marangoni propulsion 
Consider a oati ng body with perimeter C in contact with the free surface, which we assume for the sake 
of simplicity to be at. Recalling that  may be though of as a force per unit length in a direction tangent 
to the surface, we see that the total surface tension force acting on the body is: 
Fc = sd (10.3) 
C 
where s is the unit vector tangent to the free surface and normal to C, and d is an increment of arc 
length along C. If  is everywhere constant, then this line integral vanishes identically by the divergence 
theorem. However, if  = (x), then it may result in a net propulsive force. The soap boat may be 
simply generated by coating one end of a toothpick with soap, which acts to reduce surface tension (see 
right). The concomitant gradient in surface tension results in a net propulsive force that drives the boat 
away from the soap. We note that an analogous Marangoni propulsion technique arises in the natural 
world: certain water-walking insects eject surfactant and use the resulting surface tension gradients as 
an emergency mechanism for avoiding predation. Moreover, when a pine needle falls into a lake or pond, 
it is propelled across the surface in an analogous fashion owing to the inuence of the resin at its base 
decreasing the local surface tension. 
2. Soap lm stability 
Pinching a lm  increases the surface area, decreases 
 and so increases . Fluid is thus drawn in and 
the lm is stabilized by the Marangoni elasticity. 
Figure 10.5: Fluid is drawn to a pinched area of a 
soap lm through induced Marangoni stresses. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 38 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Definition and Scaling of Surface Tension (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>2.6. A few simple examples	 Chapter 2. Denition and Scaling of Surface Tension 
Note: 
1. Pressure inside a drop / bubble is higher than that outside  P  2/R  smal ler bubbles have 
higher Laplace pressure  champagne is louder than beer. 
Champagne bubbles R  0.1mm,   50 dynes/cm, P  102 atm. 
42. Forasoapbubble(2interfaces) P = , sofor R  5cm,   35d ynes/cmhave P  3105atm. R 
More generally, we shall see that there is a pressure jump across any curved interface: 
Laplace pressure p=  n. 
Examples : 
1.	 S
oap bubble jet - Ex it speed (Fig. 2.4b) ( ) 1/2 ( )
4 470dynes/cm Force balance: p = 4/R	   300cm/s  airU2  U  air R 0.001g/cm33cm
2.	 Ostwald Ripening : The coarsening of foams (or emulsions) owing to diusion of gas across inter
faces, which is necessarily from small to large bubbles, from high to low Laplace pressure. 
23.	 Falling drops: F orce balan ce Mg  airU2agives v
fall speed U  ga/air.
 
drop integrity requires airU2  ga &lt; /a
 v
raindrop size a &lt; c = /g  2mm.
 
If a drop is small relative to the capillary length,  maintains it against the destabilizing inuence
 
of aerodynamic stresses.
 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 10	 Prof. J ohn W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>2.3. Surface tension: a working denition Chapter 2. Denition and Scaling of Surface Tension 
Figure 2.2: a) The free surface between air and water at a molecular scale. b) Surface tension is analogous 
to a negative surface pressure. 
2.3 Surface tension: a working denition 
Discussions of the molecular origins of surface or interfacial tension may be found elsewhere (e.g. Is
raelachvili 1995, Rowlinson &amp; Widom 1982 ). Our discussion follows that of de Gennes, Brochard-Wyart 
&amp; Qu er e 2003. 
Molecules in a uid feel a mutual attraction. When this attractive force is overcome by thermal 
agitation
, the molecules pass into a gaseous phase. Let us rst consider a free surface, for example 
that between air and water (Fig. 2.2a). A water molecule in the uid bulk is surrounded by attractive 
neighbou
rs, while a molecule at the surface has a reduced number of such neighbours and so in an 
energetically unfavourable state. The creation of new surface is thus energetically costly, and a uid 
system will act to minimize surface areas. It is thus that small uid bodies tend to evolve into spheres; for example, a thin uid jet emerging from your kitchen sink will generally pinch o into spherical drops in order to minimize the total surface area (see Lecture 5). 
If U is the total cohesive energy per molecule, then a molecule at a free surface will lose U/2 r
 elative to 
molecules in the bulk. Surface tension is a direct measure of this energy loss per unit area of surface. If the characteristic moleculardimensionis Randits areathus R
2, thenthe surfacetensionis   U/(2R)2 . Note 
that surface tension increases as the intermolecular attraction increases and the molecular size decreases. For most oils,   20 dynes/cm, while for water,   70 dynes/cm. The highest surface tensions are 
for liquid metals; for example, liquid mercury has   500 dynes/cm. The origins of interfacial tension 
are analogous. Interfacial tension is a material property of a uid-uid interface whose origins lie in the dierent energy per area that acts to resist the creation of new interface. Fluids between which no interfacial tension arises are said to be miscible. For example, salt molecules will diuse freely across a boundary between fresh and salt water; consequently, these uids are miscible, and there is no interfacial tension between them. Our discussion will be conned to immiscible uid-uid interfaces (or uid-gas surfaces), at which an eective interfacial (or surface) tension acts. 
Surface tension  has the 
 units of force/length or equivalently energy/area, and so may be thought 
of as a negative surface pressure, or, equivalently, as a line tension acting in all directions parallel to the surface. Pressure is generally an isotropic force per area that acts throughout the bulk of a uid: small surface element d S will feel a total force p(x)dS owing to the local pressure eld p(x). If the surface S is 
closed, and the pressure uniform, the net pressure force acting on S is zero and the uid remains static. 
Pressure gradients correspond to body forces (with units of force per unit volume) within a uid, and so appear explicitly in the Navier-Stokes equations. Surface tension has the units of force per length, and its action is conned to the free surface. Consider for the sake of simplicity a perfectly at interface. A surface line element d  will feel a total force d owing to the local surface tension (x). If the surface 
line element is a closed loop C, and the surface tension uniform, the net surface tension force acting on 
C is zero, and the uid remains static. If surface tension gradients arise, there may be a net force on the 
surface element that acts to distort it through driving ow. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 6 Prof. J
 ohn W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>2.6. A few simple examples Chapter 2. Denition and Scaling of Surface Tension 
Figure 2.3: Surface tension may be measured by drawing a thin plate from a liquid bath. 
2.6 A few simple examples 
Measuring surface tension. Since  is a tensile force per unit length, it is possible to infer its value by 
slowly drawing a thin plate out of a liquid bath and measure the resistive force (Fig. 2.3). The maximum 
measured force yields the surface tension . 
Curvature/ Laplace  p ressure: consider an oil drop in water (Fig. 2.4a). Work is required to increase 
the rad
ius from R to R+ dR: 
dW = podVo  pwdVw + owdA (2.14) ' v ' ' v ' 
mech. E surface E 
where dVo = 4R2dR = dVw and dA = 8RdR . 
For mechanical equilibrium, we require dW = (p
0  pw)4R2dR + ow8RdR = 0  
P = (po  pw) = 2 ow/R. 
Figure 2.4: a) An oil drop in water b) When a soap bubble is penetrated by a cylindrical tube, air is 
expelled from the bubble by the Laplace pressure. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 9 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>2.5. The scaling of surface tension Chapter 2. Denition and Scaling of Surface Tension 
The Reynolds number prescribes the relative magnitudes of inertial and viscous forces in the system, 
while t
he Froude number those of inertial and gravity forces. The Bond number indicates the relative 
importance of forces induced by gravity and surface tension. Note that these two forces are comparable 
1/2when Bo = 1, which arises at a lengthscale corresponding to the capillary length: c = (/(g)) . For 
an air-water surface, for example,   70 dynes/cm,  = 1g/cm3 and g = 980 cm/s2, so that c  2mm. 
Bodies of water in air are dominated by the inuence of surface tension provided they are smaller than the capillary length. Roughly speaking, the capillary length prescribes the maximum size of pendant drops that may hang inverted from a ceiling, water-walking insects, and raindrops. Note that as a uid system becomes progressively smaller, the relative importance of surface tension over gravity increases; it is thus that surface tension eects are critical in many in microscale engineering processes and in the lives of bugs. 
Finally, we note that other frequently arising dimensionless groups may be formed from the products 
of Bo, Re and Fr: 
U
2a Inertia We = = = Weber n umber (2.8)  Curvature 
U Viscous Ca = 
= = Capill ary number (2.9)  Curvature 
The Web
er number indicates the relative magnitudes of inertial and curvature forces within a uid, and 
the capi
llary number those of viscous and curvature forces. Finally, we note that if the ow is marked by 
a Marangoni stress of characteristic magnitude  /L, then an additional dimensionless group arises that 
characterizes the relative magnitude of Marangoni and curvature stresses: 
a Marangoni Ma = = = Maran goni number (2.10) L Curvature 
We no
w demonstrate how these dimensionless groups arise naturally from the nondimensionalization of 
Navier-S
tokes equations and the surface boundary conditions. We rst introduce a dynamic pressure: 
pd = p g  x, so that gravity appears only in the boundary conditions. We consider the special case of 
high Reynolds number ow, for which the characteristic dynamic pressure is U2 . We dene dimensionless 
primed variables according to: 
a    u = Uu , p d = U2 pd , x = ax , t = t , (2.11) U 
where a an
d U are ch aracteristic lenfth and velocity scales. Nondimensionalizing the Navier-Stokes equa
tions and appropriate boundary conditions yields the following system: 
(u  )1      2   + u  u = pd + u ,    u = 0 (2.12) t Re 
The normal stress condition assumes the dimensionless form: 
1 2 1 E    pd + z + n   n =  n (2.13) Fr Re We 
The rel
ative importance of surface tension to gravity is prescribed by the Bond number Bo, while that 
of surface tension to viscous stresses by the capillary number Ca. In the high Re limit of interest, the 
normal force balance requires that the dynamic pressure be balanced by either gravitational or curvature stresses, the relative magnitudes of which are prescribed by the Bond number. 
The nondimensionalization scheme will depend on the physical system of interest. Our purpose here 
was simp l
y to illustrate the manner in which the dimensionless groups arise in the theoretical formulation 
of the problem. Moreover, we see that those involving surface tension enter exclusively through the boundary conditions. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 8 Prof. J
 ohn W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>2.4. Governing Equations Chapter 2. Denition and Scaling of Surface Tension 
2.4 Governing Equations 
The motion of a uid of uniform density  and dynamic viscosity  is governed by the Navier-Stokes 
equations, which represent a continuum statement of Newtons laws. 
(u )
+ u u= p+ F +  2 u (2.1) t 
  u = 0 (2.2) 
Th
is represents a system of 4 equations in 4 unknowns (the uid pressure p and the three components of 
the velocity eld u). Here F represents any body force acting on a uid; for example, in the presence of 
a gravitational eld, F = g where g is the acceleration due to gravity. 
Surface tension acts only at the free surface; consequently, it does not appear in the Navier-Stokes 
equation
s, but rather enters through the boundary conditions. The boundary conditions appropriate at a 
uid-uid interface are formally developed in Lecture 3. We here simply state them for the simple case of 
a free surface (such as air-water, in which one of the uids is not dynamically signicant) in order to get a feeling for the scaling of surface tension. The normal stress balance at a free surface must be balanced by the curvature pressure associated with the surface tension: 
n  T  n = (  n) (2.
 3) 
[1 [
where T = pI + u  +(u)T]
= pI + 2E i s the stress tensor, E = u +(u)T]
is the 2 
deviatoric stress tensor, and n is the unit normal to the surface. The tangential stress at a free surface 
must balance the local surface tension gradient: 
n  T  t =   t  (2.4) 
where t is the unit tangent to the interface. 
2.5 The scaling of surface tension 
Fundamental Concept The laws of Nature cannot depend on arbitrarily chosen system of units. Any 
physical system is most succinctly described in terms of dimensionless variables. 
Buckinghams Theorem For a system with M physicalvariables(e.g. density, speed, length, viscosity) 
describable in terms of N fundamental units (e.g. mass, length, time, temperature), there are M  N 
dimensionless groups that govern the system. 
E.g. Translation of a rigid sphere  through  a viscous fluid: 
Physical variables: sphere speed U and radius a, uid viscosity  and density  and sphere drag D; M = 5. 
Fundamental units: mass M, length L and time T; N = 3. 
Buckinghams Theorem: there are M  N = 2 dimensionless groups: Cd = D/U2 and Re = Ua/. 
System is uniquely determined by a single relation between the two: Cd = F(Re). 
We consider a uid of density  and viscosity =  with a free surface characterized by a surface tension 
. The ow is marked by characteristic length- and velocity- scales of, respectively, a and U, and evolves 
in the presence of a gravitational eld g = gz. We thus have a physical system dened in terms of six 
physical variables ( ,,,a,U,g ) that may be expressed in terms of three fundamental units: mass, length 
and time. Buckinghams Theorem thus indicates that the system may be uniquely described in terms of 
three dimensionless groups. We choose 
Ua Inertia Re = = = Reynolds number (2.5)  Viscosity 
U2 Inertia Fr = = = Froude number (2.6) ga Gravity 
ga2 Gravity Bo = = = Bond n umber (2.7)  Curvature 
MIT OCW
: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 7 Prof. J ohn W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>2. Denition and Scaling of Surface 
Tension 
These lecture notes have been drawn from many sources, including textbooks, journal articles, and lecture 
notes from courses taken by the author as a student. These notes are not intended as a complete discussion of the subject, or as a scholarly work in which all relevant references are cited. Rather, they are intended as an introduction that will hopefully motivate the interested student to learn more about the subject. Topics have been chosen according to their perceived value in developing the physical insight of the students. 
2.1 History: Surface tension in antiquity 
Hero of Alexandria (10 AD - 70 AD) Greek mathematician and engineer, the greatest 
experimentalist of antiquity. Exploited capillarity in a number of inventions described in his 
book Pneumatics , including the water clock. 
Pliny the Elder (23 AD - 79 AD) Author, natural philosopher, army and naval commander 
of the early Roman Empire. Described the glassy wakes of ships. True glory comes in doing 
what deserves to be written; in writing what deserves to be read; and in so living as to make 
the world happier. Truth comes out in wine. 
Leonardo da Vinci (1452-1519) Reported capillary rise in his notebooks, hypothesized that 
mountain streams are fed by capillary networks. 
Francis Hauksbee (1666-1713) Conducted systematic investigation of capillary rise, his 
work was described in Newtons Opticks, but no mention was made of him. 
Benjamin Franklin (1706-1790) Polymath: scientist, inventor, politician; examined the 
ability of oil to suppress waves. 
Pierre-Simon Laplace (1749-1827) French mathematician and astronomer, elucidated the 
concept and theoretical description of the meniscus, hence the term Laplace pressure. 
Thomas Young (1773-1829) Polymath, solidmechanician, scientist, linguist. Demonstrated 
the wave nature of light with ripple tank experiments, described wetting of a solid by a uid. 
Joseph Plateau (1801-1883) Belgian physicist, continued his experiments after losing his 
sight. Extensivestudyofcapillaryphenomena, soaplms,minimalsurfaces,dropsandbubbles. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2.2. Motivation: Who cares about surface tension?Chapter 2. Denition and Scaling of Surface Tension 
2.2 Motivation: Who cares about surface tension? 
As we shall soon see, surface tension dominates gravity on a scale less than the capillary length (roughly 
2mm). It thus plays a critical role in a variety of small-scale processes arising in biology, environmental science and technology. 
Biology 
	 all small creatures live in a world dominated 
by surface t en 
sion 
	 surface tension important for insects for many 
basic fun ct
ions 
	 weight support and propulsion at the water 
surface 
	 adh
esion and deadhesion via surface tension 
	 the pistol shrimp: hunting with bubbles 
	 underwater breathing and diving via surface 
tension 
	 nat
ural strategies for water-repellency in 
plants an d 
animals 
	 the dynamics of lungs and the role of surfac
tants and i
mpurities 
Figure 2.1: The diving bell spider 
Geophysics and environmental science 
	 the dynamics of raindrops and their role in the 
biosphere 
	 
mostbiomaterialis surface active, stickstothe 
surface of d r
ops / bubbles 
	 chemical, thermal and biological transport in 
the surf zon
e 	 early life: early vessicle formation, conne
ment to an i n
terface 
	 oil recovery, carbon sequestration, groundwa
ter ows 
	 d
esign of insecticides intended to coat insects, 
leave plan
t unharmed 
	 chemical leaching and the water-repellency of 
soils 
	 oil sp
ill dynamics and mitigation 
	 disease transmission via droplet exhalation 
	 dynamics of magma chambers and volcanoes 	 the exploding lakes of Cameroon 
Technology 
	 capillary eects dominant in microgravity set
tings: NASA 
	 
cavitation-induced damage on propellers and 
submarines 
	 
cavitationinmedicine: usedtodamagekidney 
stones, tumou r
s ... 
	 design of superhydrophobic surfaces e.g. self-
cleaning wi n
dows, drag-reducing or erosion-
resistant surfaces 
	 lab-on-a-chip technology: medical diagnostics, 
drug deli
very 
	 microuidics: continuous and discrete uid 
transport an
d mixing 
	 tracking submarines with their surface signa
ture 
	 in
kjet printing 
	 the bubble computer 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 5	 Prof. Joh n W. M. Bush This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on page http://news.sciencemag.org/sciencenow/2011/06/spiders.html#panel-2.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Fluid Sheets (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>13.2. Circular Sheet Chapter 13. Fluid Sheets 
Figure 13.1: A circular uid sheet generated by the impact of a water jet on a circular impactor. The 
impacting circle has a diameter of 1 cm. 
13.2 Circular Sheet 
We consider the geometry considered in Savarts original experiment. A vertical uid jet strikes a small 
horizontal circular impactor. If the ow rate is suciently high that gravity does not inuence the sheet shape, the uid is ejected radially, giving rise to a circular free uid sheet (Fig. 13.1). 
U2DFor We = &gt; 1000, the circular sheet is subject to the apping instability. We thus consider  
UR  3010 U2 We &lt; 1000, for whichthe sheetis stable. Scaling: Re =  3104  1. Fr = 2  30 0.1 0.01 gR 103 10 
so inertia dominates gravity.
 The sheet radius is prescribed by a balance of radial forces; specically, the inertial force must balance
 the curvature force:
 
u
2h = 2 (13.4) 
Continuity requires that the sheet thickness h depend on the speed u, jet ux Q and radius r as 
Q 1 h(r)=  ( 13.5) 2ru r 
Experiments (specically, tracking of particles suspended within the sheet) indicate that the sheet speed u isi
ndependent of radius; consequently, the sheet thickness decreases as 1/r. Substituting the form (13.5) 
for h into the force balance (13.4) yields the sheet radius, or so-called Taylor radius: 
Qu RT = (13.6) 4 
The sheet radius increases with source ux and sheet speed, but decreases with surface tension. We note that
the uid proceeds radially to the sheet edge, where it accumulates until going unstable via a modied 
Rayleigh-Plateau instability, often referred to as the Rayleigh-Plateau-Savart instability, as it was rst observed on a sheet edge by Savart. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 50 Prof
 . John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>13.5. Water Bells	 Chapter 13. Fluid Sheets 
13.5 Water Bells 
All of the uid sheets considered thus far have been conned to a plane. In 13.1, we considered circular 
sheets generated from a vertical jet striking a horizontal impactor. The sheet remains planar only if 
the ow is suciently fast that the uid reaches its Taylor radius before sagging substantially under the inuence of gravity. Decreasing the ow rate will make this sagging more pronounced, and the sheet will no longer be planar. While one might expect the sheet to fall along a parabolic trajectory, the toroidal curvature of the bell induces curvature pressures that act to close the sheet. Consequently, the sheet may close upon itself, giving rise to a water bell, as illustrated in Fig. 13.5. A recent review of the dynamics of water bells has been written by Clanet (Ann.Rev.). We proceed by outlining the theory required to 
compute the shapes of water bells. 
We consider a uid sheet extruded radially at a speed u
0 and subsequently sagging under the inuence 
of a gravitational eld g = gz. The inner and outer sheet surfaces are characterized by a constant 
surface tension . The sheet has constant density  and thickness t(r,z). Q is the total volume ux in 
the sheet. The characteristic Re is assumed to be suciently high so that the inuence of viscosity is 
negligible. 
We dene the origin to be the center of the impact plate; r and z are, respectively, the radial and 
vertical distances from the origin. u is the sheet speed, and  the angle made between the sheet and the 
vertical. rc is the local radius of curvature of a meridional line, and s the arc length along a meridional 
line measured from the origin. Finally,  P is the pressure dierence between the outside and inside of 
the bell as may be altered experimentally. 
Flux conservation requires that 
Q= 2rtu	 (13.14) 
while Bernoullis Theorem indicates that 
2 2 u	 = u +2gz (13.15) 0 
The total curvature force acting normal to the bell surface 
is given by 
( 1 )cos 2  n = 2 + (13.16) rc r 
Note that the factor of two results from there being two Figure 13.5: A water b ell produced by the 
free surfaces. The force balance normal to the sheet thus impact of a descending water jet on a solid 
takes the form: impactor. The impactor radius is 1 cm. Fluid 
is splayed radially by the impact, then sags 2 2cos	 tu2 
+  P + gtsi n = 0 (13.17) under the inuence of gravity. The sheet may 
rc r rc close on itself owing to the azimuthal curvature of the bell. Equations (13.14), (13.15 ) and (13.17) may be appropri
ately 
nondimensionalized and integrated to determine the
 
shape of the bell.
 Note:
 
	 the bell closes due to the out-of-plane curvature 
	 the inuence of g is r
 eected in top-bottom asymmetry. Note that g is not signicant in Fig. 13.5. 
The relevant control parameter is Fr = INERTIA/GRAVITY = U2/gL  1 
	 if deected upwards by the impactor, the bell with also close due to  
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 53	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>13.3. Lenticular sheets with unstable rims (Taylor 1960) Chapter 13. Fluid Sheets 
13.3 Lenticular sheets with  unstable rims (Taylor 1960)
 
Figure 13.2: A sheet generated by the collision of water jets at left. The uid streams radially outward in 
a thinning sheet; once the uid reaches the sheet rim, it is ejected radially in the form of droplets. From 
G.I. Taylor (1960). 
We now consider the non-axisymmetric uid , such as may be 
formed by the oblique collision of water jets (see Fig. 13.2), a geometry originally considered by Taylor (1960). Fluid is ejected 
radially from the origin into a sheet with ux distribution given by Q(), so that the volume ux owing into the sector between 
 and  + d is Q()d. As in the previous case of the circular 
sheet, the sheet rims are unstable, and uid drops are continuously ejected therefrom. The sheet shape is computed in a similar manner, but now depends explicitly on the ux distribution within the sheet, Q(). The normal force balance on the 
sheet edge now depends on the normal component of the sheet speed, u
n: 
u2 ()h() = 2 (13.7) n
The sheet thickness is again prescribed by (13.5), but now Q= 
Q(), so the sheet radius R() is given by the Taylor radius 
u2 Q()nR() = (13.8) 4u 
Computing sheet shapes thus relies on either experimental mea
suremen
t or theoretical prediction of the ux distribution Q() 
within the sheet. 
13.4 Lenticular sheets with  stable rims 
In a certain region of parameter space, specically, with uids more viscous than water, one may encounter uid sheets with stable rims (see wwwmath.mit.edu/bush/bones.html). The force balance describing the sheet shape must change accordingly. When rims are stable, uid entering the rim proceeds along the rim. As a result, there is a centripetal force normal to the uid rim associated with ow along the curved rim that must be considered in order to correctly predict the sheet shapes. 
Figure 13.3: The Fluid shbone 
formed by the collision of two jets of a glycerine-water solution. Bush &amp; 
Hasha (2004). 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 51 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>13.4. Lenticular sheets with stable rims Chapter 13. Fluid Sheets 
The relevant geometry is presented in Fig. 13.4. 
r() is dened to be the distance from the origin 
to the rim centreline, and un() and ut() the nor
mal and tangential components of the uid velocity 
in the sheet where it contacts the rim. v() is de
ned to be the velocity of ow in the rim, R() 
the rim radius, and ( ) the angle between the po
sition vector r and the local tangent to the rim 
centreline. Finally, rc() is dened to be the ra
dius of curvature of the rim centreline, and s the 
arc length along the rim centreline. The dierential equations governing the shape of a stable uid rim bounding a uid sheet may be deduced by consideration of conservation of mass in the rim and the local normal and tangential force balances at the rim. 
For a steady sheet shape, continuity requires 
that the volume ux from the sheet balance the tangential gradient in volume ux along the rim: 
 (
0 = u
nh vR2) 
(13.9) s 
The normal force balance requires that the curvature force associated with the rims surface tension balan
ce the force resulting from the normal ow into the rim from the uid sheet and the centripetal force 
resulting from the ow along the curved rim: 
Figure 13.4: A schematic illustration of a uid sheet 
bound by stable rims. 
2R2vu2 h+ = 2 (13.10) n rc 
Note that the force balance (13.7) appropriate for sheets with unstable rims is here augmented by the 
centripetal force. The tangential force balance at the rim requires a balance between tangential gradients in tangential momentum ux, tangential gradients in curvature pressure, viscous resistance to stretching of the rim, and the tangential momentum ux arriving from the sheet. For most applications involving high-speed sheets, the Reynolds number characterizing the rim dynamics is suciently large that viscous resistance may be safely neglected. Moreover, the curvature term   ngenerally depends on ; however, 
accurate to O(R/r
c), we may use   n= 1/R. One thus obtains: 
 (2) R2  ( 1)
R2 v = hutun  . (13.11) s  s R
Equations (13.9)-(13.11 ) must be supplemented by the continuity relation, 
Q()h(r,)= ( 13.12) u0r 
in addition to a number of relations that follow directly from the system geometry: 
1 sin (  )
un = u0 sin , u T = u0 cos , = +1 (13.13) rc r  
The system of equations (13.9-13.13) may be nondimensionalized, and reduce to a set of coupled ordinary equat
ions in the four variables r(),v(),R() and ( ). Given a ux distribution, Q(), the system may 
be integrated to deduce the sheet shape. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 52 Prof . John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>13. Fluid Sheets 
13.1 Fluid Sheets: sha pe and stability 
The dynamics of high-speed uid sheets was rst considered by Savart (1833) after his early work on 
electromagnetism with Biot, and was subsequently examined by Rayleigh (1879), then in a series of 
papers by Taylor ( Proc. Roy. Soc., 1959 ). They have recently received a great deal of attention owing to 
their relevance in a number of spray atomization processes. Such sheets may be generated from a variety 
of source conditions, for example, the collision of jets on rigid impactors, and jet-jet collisions. There 
is generally a curvature force acting on the sheet edge which acts to contain the uid sheet. For a 2D 
(planar) sheet, the magnitude of this curvature force is given by 
1 
F c = (  n)ndl (13.1) 
C 
Using the rst Frenet-Serret equation (Lecture 2, Appendix B), 
dt (  n)n = (13. 2) dl 
thus yields 1dt F c =  dl = (t1  t2) = 2x (13.3) 
C dl 
There is thus an eective force per unit length 2 along the length of the sheet rim acting to contain the 
rim. We now consider how this result may be applied to compute sheet shapes for three distinct cases: i) 
a circular sheet, ii) a lenticular sheet with unstable rims, and iii) a lenticular sheet with stable rims. 
49</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>13.6. Swirling Water Bell Chapter 13. Fluid Sheets 
13.6 Swirling Water  Bell 
Consider the water bell formed with a swirling jet ( Bark et al. 1979 ).
 
Observation: Swirling bells dont close. Why not?
 
Conservation of angular momentum: as r decreases, v increases as does FC  v2/r.
 
Sheet velocity:
 
v = ues + ve (13.18) '-v" '-v" 
in plane swirl 
Continuity: Q= 2rhu (13.19) 
Conservation of Angular Momentum: vr = v0r0 (13.20) 
2 2 2Energy conservation: u + v = 2gz+ u + v0z (13.21) 0 
2 2cos hu2 hv2 cos Normal force balance: + + ghsin = P + + (13.22) R r R r 
Ev
idently, the bell fails to close owing to the inuence of the centripetal forces induced by the swirl. 
Figure 13.6: Swirling water bells extruded from a rotating nozzle. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 54 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Water Waves (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 19. Water waves 
Flow past an obstacle.
 
If U &lt; cmin, no steady waves are generated by the obstacle.
 
If U &gt; cmin, there are two kvalues, for which c = U:
 
1. the smaller k is a gravity wa ve with cg = c/2 &lt; c  energy swept downstream. 
2. the larger k is a capillary w a ve with cg = 3c/2 &gt; c, so the energy is swept upstream. 
Figure 19.3: Phase speed c of surface waves as a function of their wavelength . 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 80 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>x19. Water waves
 
We consider waves that might arise from disturbing the surface of a pond. 
We dene the normal to the surface: n = 
(x ,1) 
(1+2 )1/2 
xx Curvature:   n = (1+2 )3/2 
xWe assume the uid motion is inviscid and irrota
tional: u = . Must deduce solution for velocity 
potential  satisfying 2 = 0. 
B.C.s: 
 1. = 0 on z = hz 
2. Kinematic B.C.: 
D = uz      on z = . Figure 19.1: Waves on the surface of an inviscid ir + = Dt t x x z 
3. Dynamic B.C. (time-dependent Bernoulli ap- rotational uid. 
plied at free surf
ace): 
 1 2 + ||+ g + pS = f(t), independent of xt 2 
where ps = p0 +   n = p0   xx 
)3/2 is the surface pressure. (1+2 
x
Recall: unsteady inviscid ows Navier-Stokes: 
[ ( ) ]u 1 2 + u  u  ( u) = (p+) (19.1) t 2 
[ ]
 1 2For irrotational ows, u = , so that u  t 2+ ||+ p+ = 0. 
2 1Time-dependent Bernoulli:  + ||+ p+ = F(t) only. t 2 
Now consider small amplitude waves and linearize the governing equations and BCs (assume , are 
small, so we can neglect the nonlinear terms 2,2,, etc.) 
2 = 0 in h  z  0.
 
Must solve this equation subject to the B.C.s
 
 1. = 0 on z = hz
 
 
 2. = on z = 0.t z 
3.  + g + p0  xx = f(t) on z = 0.t
 
eik(xct) ik(xct)
Seek solutions: (x,t) = , (x,z,t) = (z)e
i.e. travelling waves in x-direction with p hase speed c and wavelength  = 2/k. 
Substitute  into 2 = 0 to obtain zz  k2= 0 
kzSolutions: (z) = e ,ekz or sinh(z ),cosh(z). 
To satisfy B.C. 1: = 0 on z = h so choose (z) = Acoshk(z + h). z 
From B.C. 2: 
ikc= Ak sinhkh (19.2) ( ) 
ik(xct)From B.C. 3: ikcAcoshkh+ g + k2e = f(t), independent ofx, i.e. 
ikcAcoshkh+ g+ k2= 0 (19.3) 
( )
ic 2 g k (19.2) A =  into (19.3)  c= + tanhkh denes the phase speed c = /k.sinh kh k  
Dispersion Relation: ( ) k3 
2 = gk+ tanh kh (19.4)  
78</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 19. Water waves 
Note: as h . tanhkh  1, and we obtain deep water dispersion relation deduced in our wind-over
water lecture. 
Physical Interpretation 
 relative importance of  and g is p
rescribed by the Bond numb er Bo = g 
k2 = (2)2 
g2 = (2)2 2 
c 
2 
where c = J
/g is the capillary length. 
 for air-w
ater, Bo  1 for   2c  1.7cm. 
 Bo  1,   2c: surface eects negligible  gravity waves. 
 Bo  1 :   2c: inuence of g is negligible  capillary waves. 
Special Cases: deep and shallow water. Can expand via Taylor series: For kh  1, tanh kh = ( )
kh 1 (kh)3 + O(kh)5, and for kh  1, tanh kh  1.3 
A. Gravity waves Bo  1: c2 = kg tanhkh. Shallow water (kh  1)  c = gh. All wavelengths travel at the same speed (i.e. non-dispersive), so 
one can only surf in shallow wat er. J
Deep water (kh  1)  c = g/k, so longer waves travel fast er, e.g. drop large stone into a pond. 
2 k B. Capillary Waves: Bo  1, c=  tanhkh. 
 
Deep water kh  1  c = k so short waves travel 
fastest, 
e.g. raindrop in a puddle. 
J 
hk2 Shallow water kh  1  c = . 
An interesting note: in lab modeling of shallow water waves ( )( ( )) 2 g k (kh  1) c + kh 1 k3h3 + O(kh)5= k  3 ( ) ( )h gh +  1 gh2k2 + O(kh)4gh. In ripple tanks,  3 ( )1/2 3choose h = to get a good approximation to g( )1/2 ( )3 370 nondispersive waves. In water,  1/2 g 103 
Figure 19.2: Deep water capillary waves, 0.5cm. 
whose speed increases as wavelength de
creases. ( )1/4 ( )1/2 4g g From c(k) can deduce cmin = . for kmin =  
Group velocity : when c = c(), a wave is called dispersive 
since its dierent Fourier components (corresponding to dierent k or ) separate or disperse, e.g. deep  
water gravity waves: c  . In a disper si
ve system, the energy of a wave component does not propagate 
at c = /k (phase speed), but at the group velocity: 
d 
d cg = = (ck) (19.5) dk dk
  J  1 cDeep gravity waves:  = ck = gk. cg =  = gk = g/k = 2 .k k 2 J 1/2 J/  3 3Deep capillary wave: c = ,  = /k3/2  cg = = /k1/2 = c.k k 2 2 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 79 Prof. John W. M. Bush This image has been removed due to copyright restrictions.
Please see the image on http://people.rit.edu/andpph/photofile-c/splash1728.jpg.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Stress Boundary Conditions (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>5.3. Fluid Statics Chapter 5. Stress Boundary Conditions 
5.3 Fluid Statics 
Webeginbyconsidering static uid congurations,forwhichthestresstensorreducestotheform T = pI, 
so that n  T  n = p, and the normal stress balance equation (5.8) assumes the simple form: 
p p =  n (5.17) 
The
pressure jump across a static interface is balanced by the curvature force at the interface. Now since 
n  T  d = 0 for 
a static system, the tangential stress balance indicates that  = 0. This leads to 
the following important conclusion: There cannot be a static system in the presence of surface tension 
gradients. While pressure jumps can sustain normal stress jumps across a uid interface, they do not 
contribute to the tangential stress jump. Consequently, tangential surface (Marangoni) stresses can only 
be balanced by viscous stresses associated with uid motion. We proceed by applying equation (5.17) to describe a number of static situations. 
1. Stationary Bubble : W
 e consider a spherical air bubble of radius R submerged in a static uid.
 
What is the pressure drop across the bubble surface?
 
The divergence in spherical coordinates of F = (Fr,F,F) is given by
 
1  ( ) 1  1  F = r2Fr+ (sinF)+ F. r2 r r sin   r sin  
1  2
Hence  n|S = r2|r=R = so the normal stress jump (5.17) indicates that r2 r R 
2 P = p p = (5.18) R 
The p
ressure within the bubble is higher than that outside by an amount proportional to the surface 
tension, an
d inversely proportional to the bubble size. As noted in Lec. 2, it is thus that small bubbles 
are louder than large ones when they burst at a free surface: champagne is louder than beer. We note that soap bubbles in air have two surfaces that dene the inner and outer surfaces of the soap lm; consequently, the pressure dierential is twice that across a single interface. 
2. The static meniscus  (
e &lt; /2) 
Consider a situation where the pressure within a early with z. Such a situation arises in the static 
static uid varies owing to the presence of a gravi- meniscus ( below). 
tational eld, p= p0 +gz, where p0 is the constant 
ambient pressure, and g = gzis the grav. acceler
ation. The normal stress balance thus requires that 
the interface satisfy the Young-Laplace Equation : 
gz =   n (5.19) 
The vertical gradient in uid pressure must be balanced by the curvature pressure; as the gradient is constant, the curvature must likewise increase lin-
Figure 5.3: Static meniscus near a wall. 
The shape of the meniscus is prescribed by two factors: the contact angle between the air-water 
interface and the wall, and the balance between hydrostatic pressure and curvature pressure. We treat 
the contact angle e as given; noting that it depends in general on the surface energy. The normal 
force balance is expressed by the Young-Laplace equation, where now  = w  air  w is the density 
dierence between water and air. We dene the free surface by z = (x); equivalently, we dene a 
functional f(x,z) = z  (x) that vanishes on the surface. The normal to the surface z = (x) is thus 
f z (x)xn = = (5.20) |f| [1+(x)2]1/2 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 17 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>5. Stress Boundary Conditions 
Today: 
1. Derive stress conditions at a uid-uid inter
face. Requi r
es knowledge of T = pI +2E
 
2. Consider several examples of uid statics 
Recall: the curvature of a string under tension may support a 
normal force. (see right) 
5.1 Stress conditions at a uid-uid interface 
We proceed by deriving the normal and tangential stress boundary conditions appropriate at a uid-uid 
interface characterized by an interfacial tension . 
Figure 5.1: String under tension and the inuence 
of gravity. 
Figure 5.2: A surface S and bounding contour C on an interface between two uids. Local unit vectors 
are n, m and s. 
Consider an interfacial surface S bounded by a closed contour C. One may think of there being a force 
per unit length of magnitude  in the s-direction at every point along C that acts to atten the surface S. 
Perform a force balance on a volume element V enclosing the interfacial surface S dened by the contour 
C:     
Du dV =f dV + [t(n)+t(n)] dS +s d (5.1) Dt S V V C 
Here  indicates arc-length and so d a length increment along the curve C.
 
t(n) = n  T is the stress vector, the force/area exerted by the upper (+) uid on the interface.
 [
Thestresstensorisdenedintermsofthelocaluidpressure andvelocityeld as T = pI+u +( u)T]
. 
The stress ex
erted on the interface by the lower (-) uid is t(n) = n T= n  T [
where T= pI +
u+(u)T]
. 
Physical interpretation  of  terms 
I
Du dV : inertial force associated with acceleration of uid in VV Dt I 
f dV : body forces acting within V 
I
t(n) dS : hydr odynamic force exerted by upper uid S It(n) dS : hyd rodynamic force exerted by lower uid S I
s d : surface tension force exerted on perimeter. C 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>5.3. Fluid Statics Chapter 5. Stress Boundary Conditions 
Figure 5.5: a) Water strider legs are covered with hair, rendering them eectively non-wetting. The 
tarsal segment of its legs rest on the free surface. The free surface makes an angle  with the horizontal, 
resulting in an upward curvature force per unit length 2 sin that bears the insects weight. b) The 
relation between the maximum curvature force Fs = 2P and body weight Fg = Mg for 342 species of 
water striders. P = 2(L1 + L2 + L3) is the combined length of the tarsal segments. From Hu, Chan &amp; 
Bush; Nature 424, 2003. 
4. Water-walking Insects 
Small
objects such as paper clips, pins or insects may reside at rest on a free surface provided the curvature 
forceind
ucedbytheirdeection ofthefreesurfaceissucienttobeartheirweight(Fig. 5.5a). Forexample, 
for a body of contact length L and total mass M, static equilibrium on the free surface requires that: 
Mg &lt; 1 , (5.35) 2Lsin 
wh
ere  is t
he angle of tangency of the oating body.
 
This simp
le criterion is an important geometric constraint on water-walking insects. Fig. 5.5b indicates
 
the dependence of contact length on body weight for over 300 species of water-striders, the most common
 
water walking insect. Note that the solid line corresponds to the requirement (5.35) for static equilibrium.
 Smaller insects maintain a considerable margin of safety, while the larger striders live close to the edge.
 The maximum size of water-walking insects is limited by the constraint (5.35 ).
 
If body proportions were independent of size L, one wou
 ld expect the body weight to scale as L3 and 
the curvature force as L. Isometry would thus suggest a dependence of the form Fc  Fg 1/3, represented 
as the dashed line. The fact that the best t line has a slope considerably larger than 1/3 indicates a variance from isometry: the legs of large water striders are proportionally longer. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 20 Prof. Joh
 n W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>5.4. Appendix B : Computing curvatures Chapter 5. S tress Boundary Conditions 
5.4 Appendix B : Computing curvatures 
We see the appearance of the divergence of the surface normal,   n, in the normal stress balance. We 
proceed by briey reviewing how to formulate this curvature term in two common geometries. 
In cartesian coordinates ( x,y,z), w e consider a surface dened by z = h(x,y). We dene a functional 
f(x,y,z) = z  h(x,y) that necessarily vanishes on the surface. The normal to the surface is dened by 
f z hxx hyyn = = (5.36) |f| ( )1/2 1+h2 + h2 x y
and the local curvature may thus be computed: 
( )
 (hxx + hyy) hxxhy 2 + hyyhx2 +2hxhyhxy   n = (5.37) ( )3/2 1+h2 + h2 x y
In the simple case of a two-dimensional interface, z = h(x), these results assume the simple forms: 
z hxx hxx n = ,   n = (5.38) 1/2 3/2(1+h2 ) (1+h2 )x x
Note that n is dimensionless, while   n has the units of 1/L. 
In 3D polar coordinates ( r,,z), we consider a surface dened by z = h(r,). We dene a functional 
g(r,,z) = z  h(r,) that vanishes on the surface, and compute the normal: 
r  1 h g z hr r n = = , (5.39) )1/2 |g| (1 h21+h2 +rr2 
from which the local curvature is computed: 
 2 hrh2  r2hrr  hrrh2 
 + hrhhr   n = r r (5.40) h  h2h + hrhtheta  rhr 
r2 (1 )1/2 h21+h2 +rr2 
In the case of an axisymmetric interface, z = h(r), these reduce to: 
z hrr rhr  r2hrr n = ,   n = (5.41) 1/2 3/2(1+h2) r2 (1+h2)r r
5.5 Appendix C : Frenet-Serret Equations 
Dierential geometry yields relations that are of- Note that the LHS of (5.42) is proportional to the 
ten useful in computing curvature forces on 2D in- curvature pressure acting on an interface. Therefore 
terfaces. the net force acting on surface S as a result of cur
vature / Laplace pressures: I I dt dt F = (  n)n d = d = (t2  t1)(  n)n = (5.42) C C d 
d and so the net force on an interface resulting from 
dn curvature pressure can be deduced in terms of the  (  n)t = (5.43) d geometry of th e end points. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 21 Prof. Joh n W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>5.3. Fluid Statics Chapter 5. Stress Boundary Conditions 
Figure 5.4: A oating non-wetting body is supported by a combination of buoyancy and curvature forces, 
whose relative magnitude is prescribed by the ratio of displaced uid volumes Vb and Vm. 
Equations (5.27-5.31) thus indicate that the curvature force acting on the oating body is expressible in 
terms of the uid volume displaced outside the line of tangency: 
Fc = gVm (5.32) 
The relative magnitude of the buoyancy and curvature forces supporting a oating, non-wetting body is thus pre
scribed by the relative magnitudes of the volumes of the uid displaced inside and outside the 
line of tangency: 
Fb Vb = (5.33) Fc Vm 
For 2D bodies, we note that since the meniscus will have a length comparable to the capillary length, 
1/2c = (/(g)) , the relative magnitudes of the buoyancy and curvature forces, 
Fb r  , (5.34) Fc c 
is prescribed by the relative magnitudes of the body size and capillary length. Very small oating objects (r  
c) are supported principally by curvature rather than buoyancy forces. This result has been 
extended to three-dimensional oating objects by Keller 1998, Phys. Fluids, 10, 3009-3010. 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 19 Prof. Joh n W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5.3. Fluid Statics Chapter 5. Stress Boundary Conditions
As deduced in Appendix B, the curvature of the free surface n, may be expressed as
xxn= xx (5.21)(1+2)3/2x
Assumin g
thattheslopeofthemeniscusremainssucientlysmall, 2
x1, allowsonetolinearizeequation
(5.21), so that (5.19) assumes the form
g=xx (5.22)
Applying the boundary condition () = 0 and the contact condition x(0) =cot, an d solving (5.22)
thus yields
(x) =ccoteex/c(5.23)
wherec=/radicalbig
/gis the capillary length. The meniscus formed by an object oating in water is exponen-
tial, decaying over a length scale c. Note that this behaviour may be rationalized as follows: the system
arranges itself so that its total energy (grav. potential + surface) is minimized.
3. Floating Bodies
Floating bodies must be supported by some combination of buoyancy and curvature forces. Specically,
since the uid pressure beneath the interface is related to the atmospheric pressure p0above the interface
by
p=p0+gz+ n, (5.24)
one may express the vertical force balance as
Mg=z/integraldisplay
pnd=Fb+F .
c/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipuprightc (5.25)
C
buo/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
yancy urvature
The buoyancy force
Fb=z/integraldisplay
gznd=gVb (5.26)
C
is thus simply the weight of the uid displaced above the object and inside the line of tangency ( see gure
below). We note that it may be deduced by integrating the curvature pressure over the contact area C
using the rst of the Frenet-Serret equations (see Appendix C).
F   c=z/integraldisplay
(n)nd=z
C/integraldisplaydtd=z(t1t2) = 2si n (5.27)
Cd
At the interface, the buoyancy and curvature forces must balance precisely, so the Young-Laplace relation
is satised:
0 =gz+ n (5.28)
Integrating this equation over the meniscus and taking the vertical component yields the vertical force
balance:
Fm
b+Fm
c= 0 (5.29)
where
Fm
b=z/integraldisplay
gznd=gVm (5.30)
Cm
dtFm
c=z/integraldisplay
( n)nd=z/integraldisplay
d=z(t1t
Cm Cmd2) =2sin ( 5.31)
where we have again used the Frenet-Serret equations to evaluate the curvature force.
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 18 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>5.1. Stress conditions at a uid-uid interface Chapter 5. Stress Boundary Conditions
Now ifis the characteristic height of our volume VandRits characteristic radius, then the accel-
eration and body forces will scale as R2, while the surface forces will scale as R2. Thus, in the limit of
0, the latter must balance. /integraldisplay
t(n)+t(n) dS+/integraldisplay
sd= 0 (5.2)
S C
Now we have that
 t(n) =nT,t(n)=nT=nT ( 5.3)
M
oreover, the application of Stokes Theorem (see below) allows us to write
/integraldisplay
sd=
C/integraldisplay
Sn(Sn)dS (5.4)
S
where the tangential (surface) gradient operator, dened
   S= [Inn]=n (5.5)n
appears because andnare only dened on the surface S. We proceed by dropping the subscript son
, with this understanding. The surface force balance thus becomes
/integraldisplay/parenleftBig
 nTnT/parenrightBig
dS=
S/integraldisplay
n( n)dS (5.6)
S
Now since the surface Sis arbitrary, the integrand must vanish identically. One thus obtains the interfacial
stress balance equation, which is valid at every point on the interface:
Stress Balance Equation
 nTnT=n( n) (5.7)
Interpretation of terms :
nTstress (force/area) exerted by + on - (will generally have both and/badblcomponents)
nTstress (force/area) exerted by - on + (will generally have both and/badblcomponents)
n( n) normal curvature force per unit area associated with local curvature of interface,  n
tangential stress associated with gradients in 
Normal s
tress balance Takingn(5.7) yields the normal stress balance
 nTnnTn=(n) (5.8)
The jump in the normal stress across the interface is balanced by the curvature pressure.
Note: If n= 0, th ere must be a normal stress jump there, which generally involves both pressure and
viscous terms.
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 15 Prof. John W. M. Bush/negationslash</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>5.2. Appendix A : Useful identity Chapter 5. Stress Boundary Conditions
Tangential stress balance Takingd(5.7), where dis any linear combination of sandm(any tangent
toS), yields the tangential stress balance at the interface:
 nTdnTd=d (5.9)
Ph
ysical Interpretation
LHS represents the jump in tangential components of the hydrodynamic stress at the interface
RHS represents the tangential stress (Marangoni stress) associated with gradients in , as may
result from gradients in temperature or chemical composition cat the interface since in general
=(,c)
LHS contains only the non-diagonal terms of T- only the velocity gradients, not pressure; therefore
any non-zero at a uid interface must alwaysdrive motion.
5.2 Appendix A : Useful identity
Recall Stokes Theorem: /integraldisplay
Fd=/integraldisplay
n(F)dS (5.10)
C S
Along the contour C, d=md, so that we have
/integraldisplay
Fmd=
C/integraldisplay
n(F)dS (5.11)
S
Now letF=fb, wherebis an arbitrary constant vector. We thus have
/integraldisplay
(fb)md=/integraldisplay
n((fb))dS (5.12)
C S
Now use standard vector identities to see ( fb)m=b(fm) and
(fb) =f( b)b(
f)+b ff b=b( f)+b f (5.13)
sincebis a constant vector. We thus have
b/integraldisplay
(fm)d=b/integraldisplay
[n( f)(f)n]dS (5.14)
C S
Sincebis arbitrary, we thus have
/integraldisplay
(fm)d=/integraldisplay
[n( f)(f)n]dS (5.15)
C S
We now choose f=n, and recall that nm=s. One thus obtains
/integraltext
sd=/integraltext
[n(n)(n)n]dS= [nn+n( n)(n)n]dS.C S S
We note that n= 0 since must b/integraltext
e tangent to the surface Sand (1n)n=2(nn) =
12(1) = 0, and so obtain the desired result:
/integraldisplay
sd=/integraldisplay
[n( n)] dS (5.16)
C S
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 16 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Young&#8217;s Law with Applications (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>4.1. Formal Development of Interfacial Flow Problems Chapter 4. Youngs Law with Applications 
This is a system of 4 equations in 4 unknowns ( u1,u2,u3,p). These N-S equations must be solved subject
 
to appropriate BCs.
 
Fluid-Solid BCs : No-slip : u = Usolid.
 
E.g.1 Falling sphere: u = U on sph ere surface, where U is the sphere velocity. 
E.g.2 Convection in a box: u = 0 on the box surface.
 
But we are interested in ows dominated by interfacial eects. Here, in general, one must solve N-S
 equations in 2 domains, and match solutions together at the interface with appropriate BCs. Diculty:
 These interfaces are free to move  Free boundary problems.
 
Figure 4.4: E.g.4 Water waves at an air-water in
terface. 
Figure 4.3: E.g.3 Drop motion within a uid. 
Continuity of Velocity at an interface requires that u = u.
 
And what about p ? Weve seen p  /R for a static bubble/drop, but to answer this question in
 
general, we must develop stress conditions at a uid-uid interface.
 
Recall: Stress Tensor. The state of stress within an incompressible Newtonian uid is described by
 
1 [
the stress tensor: T = pI + 2E wh ere E = (u) +( u)T]
is the deviatoric stress tensor. The 2 
associated hydrodynamic force per unit volume within the uid is   T . 
One may thus write N-S eqns in the form: Du =   T + f = p+ 2u + f.Dt 
Now: Tij = force / area acting in the ej direction on a surface with a normal ei. 
Note: 
1.	 normal stresses (diagonals) T11, T22, T33 in
volve both p and ui
 
2. tangential	 stresses (o-diagonals) T12, T13,
 
etc., involve only velocity gradients, i.e. vis
cous stresses
 
3.	 Tij is symmetric (Newtonian uids) 
4.	 t(n) = nT = st ress vector acting on a surface
 
with normal n
 
E.g. Shear ow. Stress in lower boundary is tan
genti
al. Force / area on lower boundary: 
uTyx =  x 
y |y=0 = k is the force/area that acts on 
y-surface in x-direction.
 
Note: the form of T in arbitrary curvilinear coordi- Figure 4.5: Shear ow above a rigid lower bound-
nates is given in the Appendix of Batchelor. ary.
 
MIT OCW: 18.357 Interfacial Phenomena 13	 Prof. John W. M. Bush</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>4. Youngs Law with Applications
 
Youngs Law : what is the equilibrium contact angle e ? Horizontal force balance at contact line: 
LV cose = SV  SL 
SV  SL S cose = = 1+ (Young 1805) (4.1) LV LV 
Note: 
1. When S  0, cos e  1  e undened and
 
spreading results.
 
2. Vertical force balance not satised at contact
 
lin
e  dimpling of soft surfaces.
 
E.g. bubbles in paint leave a circular rim. 
3. Thestaticcontact angleneed nottakeitsequi
lib
rium value  there is a nite range of pos
sible static contact angles.
 
Figure 4.1: Threeinterfacesmeet atthecontactline. Back to Puddles: Total energy: 
1 V 1 E = (SL  SV )A+ LV A+ gh2A= S + gVh (4.2) 2 h 2  v   v  surface energy grav. pot. energy 
dE 1 1Minimize energy w.r.t. h: = SV h1 
2 + gV = 0 when S/h2 = g dh 2 2 J
2S e J
h0 = g = 2c sin 
2 gives puddle depth, where c = /g. 
Capillary Adhesion: Two wetted surfaces can
 
stic
k together with great strength if e &lt; /2, e.g.
 
Fig. 4.2.
 Laplace Pressure:
 ( )
1  cos e cos eP =   2
R H/2 H 
i.e. low P inside lm provided e &lt; /2. 
cos eIf H  R, F = R22is the attractive force H 
between the plates. Figure 4.2: An oil drop forms a capillary bridge 
between two glass plates. 
E.g. for H2O, with R = 1 cm, H = 5 m and e = 0, one nds P  1/3 atm and an adhesive force 
F  10N, the weight of 1l of H2O.
 
Note: Such capillary adhesion is used by beetles in nature.
 
4.1 Formal Development  of Interfacial Flow Problems 
Governing Equations: Navier-Stokes. An incompressible, homogeneous uid of density  and viscosity 
=  (is dynamic and  kinematic viscosity) acted upon by an external force per unit volume f evolves 
according to 
  u =0 (c ontinuity ) (4.3) (u )
+ u u= p+ f+  2 u (Linear momentum conservation) (4.4) t 
12</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction, Notation (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-357-interfacial-phenomena-fall-2010/resources/mit18_357f10_lecture1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1. Introduction, Notation 
We consider uid systems dominated by the inuence of interfacial tension. The roles of curvature pressure 
and Marangoni stress are elucidated in a variety of situtations. Particular attention will be given to the dynamics of drops and bubbles, soap lms and minimal surfaces, wetting phenomena, water-repellency, surfactants, Marangoni ows, capillary origami and contact line dynamics. Theoretical developments will be accompanied by classroom demonstrations. The role of surface tension in biology will be highlighted. 
Notation 
Nomenclature:  denotes surface tension (at uid-gas interface) 
 denotes interfacial tension (at uid-uid or uid-solid interface). 
Note on units: we will use predominantly cgs system. 
2Unit of force: 1 dyne = 1 g cm s = 105N as the cgs unit of force, roughly the weight of 1 mosquito.
 
Pressure: 1 atm  100kPa = 105N/m2=106 dynes/cm2 .
 
Units: [ ]=dynes/cm=mN/m.
 
2What is an interface?: roughness scale , from equality of surface and thermal energy get  kT 
  (kT/)1/2 . If   scales of experiment, can speak of a smooth interface. 
1.1 Suggested References 
While this list of relevant textbooks is far from complete, we include it as a source of additional reading 
for the interested student. 
 Capillarity and Wetting Phenomena: Drops, Bubbles, Pearls, Waves by P.G. de Gennes, F. Brochard-Wyart and D. Qu er e. Springer Publishing. A readable and accessible treatment of a wide range of capillary phenomena. 
 Molecular theory of capillarity by J.S. Rowlinson and B. Widom. Dover 1982. 
 Intermolecular and surface forces by J. Israelachvili. Academic Press, 2nd edition 1995. 
 Multimedia Fluid Mechanics Cambridge University Press, Ed. Bud Homsy. A DVD with an extensive section devoted to capillary eects. Relevant videos will be used throughout the course. 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
