<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/5-35-introduction-to-experimental-chemistry-fall-2012/</course_url>
    <course_title>Introduction to Experimental Chemistry</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Chemistry </list>
      <list>Analytical Chemistry</list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Mod 2 Lecture Summary 2 (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/5-35-introduction-to-experimental-chemistry-fall-2012/resources/mit5_35f12_module_2ls2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>Practical aspects of FTIR Spectroscopy</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>IR Spectroscopy  Spectra Interpretation  
Challenges 
 Ambiguous peaks 
 Misinterpreting overtone, combination vibrations 
 Misinterpreting impurities 
 Poor reproducibility of sample preparation  artifacts 
Important Tools / Strategies  knowledge of chemistry, reactants, solvents 
 systematic peak assignment (e.g. Mohrig)  complementary characterization (NMR, UV-Vis, EA) 
 peak shape/intensity, shoulders 
 computerized databases 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Sample Preparation Considerations and Issues  
Choice of Sampling Technique 
 State of analyte 
 Material compatibility 
 IR absorbance of cell materials 
 Path length 
Sample Preparation Caveats 
 IR signal scatter  dirt, scratches, cracks 
 Too concentrated/dilute 
 Opaque pellets  Too thick 
 Too thin (fragile) 
 Wet KBr  Wet sample 
 Reproducible preparation 
 Sample is not what you think it is Warning Signs for Poor Samples 
 Big/wide water signal 
 No features or only Nujol/PE/etc 
 Broad and non-distinct signals 
 Sloping base line  Misaligned positioning 
Warning Signs of Instrument Failure 
 Unresponsive (hardware/software) 
 Error messages 
 No instrument/computer/printer comm 
 Laser weak or dead  CCD or photodetector is dead 
 Bad settings from previous user(s) 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>W.H. Freeman. Source: Mohrig, J. R., C. N. Hammond, and P. F. Schatz. Techniques in Organic
Chemistry, Third Edition. 2010. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our CreativeCommons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.
3IR Spectroscopy  Spectra Interpretation</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
5.35 / 5.35U Introduction to Experimental Chemistry
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Mod 1 Lecture Summary 3 (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/5-35-introduction-to-experimental-chemistry-fall-2012/resources/mit5_35f12_module_1ls3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>Linear and nonlinear spectroscopy</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 3  Fall 2012 
 
  3.3 Fluorescence emerges in all directions. So me reaches the photodetector, producing a 
signal whose time-dependence is measured. As the excited molecules return to the 
ground state, the amount of fluorescence decreases. 
 
Youll make measurements of fluorescence, but not time-resolved. The fluorescence 
spectrum reveals excited-state energy leve ls, similar to the absorption spectrum.  
 In many cases, molecules or materials lose th eir energy non-radiatively, heating up their 
surroundings. Either way, the time for re laxation back to the ground state is 
T1. It 
measures how long it takes for en ergy to leave the molecules.  
 Other contributions to total dephasing rate: 
NMR spin echo measurements can determine the amount of inhomogeneous dephasing. 
Inhomogeneous dephasing is due to variatio n (inhomogeneity) in the surroundings of 
different molecules that lead to slight shifts in their resonant frequencies. 
 First an RF pulse flips the spins by 90 degrees (a   pulse), aligning them along the x 
axis. Then they start to precess  but not all at exactly the same frequency! So some run 
ahead of the pack, and some behind.   Then another RF pulse comes a certain time, 
, later, and flips the spins 180 degrees (a 
 pulse), keeping them in the xy plane but re versing their directions  so the fast ones 
find themselves trailing the pack and the sl ow ones find themselves leading! And after 
another time period  they are all re-phased! This produc es a signal, just like before they 
went out of phase. And this is measured. So  the inhomogeneous deph asing is removed!  
    Spin echo measurement
 
 
 
  
 
  If the time interval 
 is increased, the signal still decays due to lifetime ( T1), which in the 
spin case means the spins lose their net alignments in the xy-plane. The signal also decays 
due to pure dephasing: the molecules still ha ve their excited-state energy (i.e. the spins 
are still aligned in the xy-plane) but they no longer oscillate phase-coherently  not just 
time RF 
signal  pulse 
echo/2 pulse 
Echo signal</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 3  Fall 2012 
 
  3.4 out of sync with each other, but no longer coherent relative to their own oscillations at 
the beginning.  
 If the lifetime also is determined in a pump-probe measurement, then the pure 
dephasing can also be determined.  Photon echo measurements can be used to determine vibrational or electronic 
inhomogeneous dephasing rates.  A similar measurement can be made except with the  pulse first, then /2. The first 
pulse delicately places the system in the hi gher spin level, without any coherent spin 
oscillations, by exactly reversing the initia l magnetization. The second pulse takes the 
system from there to the xy pl ane, where precession leads to  oscillating signal. After the 
first pulse, the system can relax back down to  the ground state (the initial spin level)  
this is energy relaxation, at the rate 
1 given by the lifetime T1. So if you delay the 
second pulse, the oscillating signal streng th decreases at that rate, which can be 
measured!</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 3  Fall 2012 
 
  3.1 Linear and nonlinear spectroscopy 
Weve seen that we can de termine molecular frequencie s and dephasing rates (for 
electronic, vibrational, or spin degrees of freedom) from frequency-domain or time-
domain measurements whose results ar e related through FT. In general:  
 
Parameter  Time Domain S(t)  Frequency Domain S()
Large0 Fast oscillations High frequency 
Small0 Slow oscillations Low frequency 
Large Fast decay Broad linewidth 
Small Slow decay Narrow linewidth 
 
The FT relations obtain for the light field itse lf as well as the material responses to it. 
Short pulses of light have broad spectral widths.  
 
Dephasing rate  can have very different origins.  
 
Damping  the energy decays  back to zero  rate 1, time T1 = 1/1 
Pure dephasing  energy is retained, oscillation phase is lost  rate 2*, time T2* = 1/2* 
 ( T2* notational convention is from NMR) 
Inhomogeneous dephasing  energy is retain ed, and oscillations stay in phase on any 
individual molecule, but oscillations on di fferent molecules go out of sync  rate 3, time 
T3 = 1/3. Sometimes inhomogeneous dephasing ra te (or inhomogeneous linewidth) is 
labeled  . 
Total dephasing rate is sum of all three contributions:  = 1 + 2* + 3 
 
  
 
  
 
   
This can happen if different local molecular environments cause diffe rent local resonance 
frequencies 
0.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 3  Fall 2012 
 
    Time-resolved fluorescence measurement  
 
 
 
FluorescencePump pulse Photodetector Sample 
 3.2 How can we distinguish the different contributions?? 
In linear spectroscopy  where the sample response is linearly proportional to the EM field  we cannot!  But there are many nonlinear spectr oscopies that make it possible.  
Nonlinear spectroscopy : sample response is a 
nonlinear  function of the driving field 
 Time-resolved pump-probe measurements
  measure 1 
An excitation or pump light pulse makes excited states. They may dephase quickly, but the energy is still there in excited molecules that are not oscillating coherently anymore.  
A variably delayed probe pulse can be used to monitor the excited-state population and 
its decay to the ground state.  
 
 
 
 
 Probe delay time A Probe 
pulse 
Pump Photodetector  Sample 
 
This can be done on femtosecond, picoseco nd, nanosecond,, many-second time scales. 
The probe pulse absorption is changed by th e pump pulse because the excited states and 
ground states absorb differently.   
Time-resolved fluorescence
 
Sometimes the excited mole cules return to the ground state by fluorescence   they emit 
a photon. Unlike absorption, wh ich can be described classica lly or quantum mechanically, 
fluorescence is purely quantum mechanical! Thats because the excited molecule just 
spontaneously emits the photon  there s no driving force acting on it.  
 
   F l u o r e s c e n c e  
   
 
   Photon(a) After 
Molecule  
(Ground state )Before 
Molecule  
(Excited state ) Ground 
state Excited 
state 
E = h =  = 
hc/ = hc
 (b)pulse 
Time</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
5.35 / 5.35U Introduction to Experimental Chemistry
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Spectroscopy</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/5-35-introduction-to-experimental-chemistry-fall-2012/resources/mit5_35f12_module_1ls1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>Module 1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 1  Fall 201 2 
  1.5Absorption spectroscopy
To record an absorption spectrum, we need lots of frequency components.  
   1 1 2 2 3 3 0 cos cos cos cos E t E t E t E t d E t           L
(Note weve neglected polarization &amp; phase)  
Usually the distribution of frequencies E0() is smoothly varying. How to measure it, 
before and after a sample?  
Absorption spectrometer 
UV-VI
S spectrometer schematic illustration 
Ocean Optics UV/VIS Spe
ctrometer (from instruction manual). 1 optical fiber connection, 2 slit, 3 filter, 4 
collimating mirror, 5 grating, 6 focusing mirror, 7 collector lens, 8 detector.  
Diffraction grating separates the freque
ncy components 
Intensity of each is measured at a CCD 
Intensity 
2
04cIE  (units of Watt/m2 = Joule/s/m2) 
Change in light intensity dI() at any frequency due to sample absorption: Proportional to 
- incident intensity I0() Image removed due to copyright restrictions. Please see:
Ocean Optics. USB4000 Fiber Optic Spectrometer Installation and Operation
Manual. Document Number 211-00000-000-02-201201. Appendix C, p. 27.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 1  Fall 201 2
1.7
Integral above is a Fourier integral . In general, f(t) and F(w) are Fourier transforms  of 
each other if they are related through the following integrals.  
     
     1cos
2
1cos
2F f t t dt
f t F t d

  






General result: We can measure the time-dependence of the field  whatever it is, 
Gaussian or otherwise  and determine the frequency-dependence taking the inverse 
Fourier transform as shown above.  
The field can be full
y characterized through measurement, and mathematical description, 
in the frequency domain  (measure the amplitude of each frequency component, and if 
needed the phase also) or in the time domain  (measure the time-dependent profile of the 
field).  
How can we determin
e the time-dependent profile of a light field? It oscillates too fast 
to measure electronically.  
Can measure the fiel
d optically  with an interferometer .  
Beamsplitter (dashed line) transmits and reflects equal parts of the light which return to 
the beamsplitter after reflection off the mirrors. Depending on mirror positions, they 
interfere constructively or destructively. Detector measures oscillating intensity as 
function of mirror position!</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 1  Fall 201 2 
  1.1SPECTROSCOPY 
5.35 Module #1 
Introduction to spectroscopy 
Spectroscopy permits measurement of a tremendous amount of information, often in a 
very simple way.  
Module consists of UV-VIS, fluorescence, IR, and NMR spectroscopy experiments 
Youll use spectroscopy to probe:  
Electronic orbitals of molecules &amp; quantum dots (UV-VIS, fluorescence) 
Vibrations of molecules (IR) 
Spin states of protons in small molecules &amp; proteins (NMR) 
And youl l learn how spectroscopy works! Seek an understanding that permits creative use 
of spectroscopy to measure the information that you need, in whatever way allows it to 
be determined.  
Light absorption 
Absorption spectra  reveal the frequencies at which light absorption occurs. These reveal 
molecular resonances and energy levels, structure and dynamics.  
The y-axis is absorptivity 
The x-axis is frequency or wavelength, measured in units that are reasonable for the part 
of the spectrum youre in.  
Why is light absorbed at some frequencies and not others? 
5.111 &amp; 5.112 picture of light absorption: purely quantum mechanical  
Light represented as photons, molecule represented as quantized energy levels  
Correctly conveys conservation of energy 
Photon energy = difference between quantum state energies A 
(nm)  or (Hz)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 1  Fall 201 2 
  1.8
  01 cos I t I t  where t  is the temporal delay between the two fields. In terms of the spatial delay x  
  01 cos I x I kx
Position domain  measurement of the field
Fourier transform of  
    cos
  I k dx I x kx
gives output as a function of wavelength through relation  = 2/k  
or as a function of frequency through relation /k = c  
As before, make mea
surement with &amp; without sample in place, and compare results to 
determine absorption spectrum.  
Works the same way in FTI
R even with an incoherent (or partially coherent) light source 
The sample response
 to light 
Classical equation of motion  
 2
0 2cosd Q dQb KQ aE tdt dt  
Q is the vibrational coordinate 
b is a friction coefficient 
K is the force constant 
a is a coupling constant between the electric field of the light &amp; the molecular vibration  
Note: Like the class
ical equations of motion generally, this is a differential equation  
Techniques for solving differential equations are taught in a math course on differential 
equations! 
We are going to look at solutions of this equation, and you should plug them in to verify 
that they solve it, but you are never going to have to solve a differential equation on your 
own in this module !!  
You do not need math beyond basic calculus for any aspect of this module</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 1  Fall 201 2 
  1.3
-1 -0.5 0 0.5 1 
E(t) 
or 
E(x) 
 
Time or Position  For a single frequency: 
   0, cosx t E kx t     E
      (1) 
Note the various features;  
Polarization  unit vector 
  (assumed time-independent)  
Amplitude  E0 (assumed time-independent)  
Oscillating part . A propagating wave oscillates in time and space .  
Temporal oscillation period T = 2/. Frequency   in units of rad/s or s-1. 
Alternate frequency variable  = 1/T = 2, units cycles/sec or Hz.  
Spatial oscill
ation period = wavelength  =  = 2/k.  
k  wavevector , in units of m-1.  
Sometimes we use wave number variable  
% = 1/, in units of cycles/m or cm-1   
Phase (assumed time-independent) 
Light speed in vacuum
 c = 3 x 108 m/s = /T = /k.  
Simplified scalar expres
sion for the field at one position: 
(neglecting polarization &amp; phase) 
 0cos E t E t</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 1  Fall 201 2 
  1.2Important information is not conveyed in this picture. Molecule does not generally end up 
in a stationary state! 
Classical mechanics : complementary picture of light absorption.  
 
Light represented as a classical electromagnetic wave. 
Molecule represented as a classical harmonic oscillator, driven by the EM field 
Both pictures convey important information!  
Well rely on the classical picture mostly, since your physical intuition is classical.  
To understand spectroscopy, its essential to understand three things.  
What is light?  
What is matter?  
How do they interact? 
The electromagnetic (EM) field: What it is and how it can be measured 
Well examine the electric field first, the magnetic field later for NMR  Before  
Molecule  
(Ground state)  Photon  After  
Molecule  
(Excited state)  (No more 
photon)  (a) 
Ground 
state  Excited 
state  
E = h =  = 
hc/ = hc
% (b) 
  
EM wave  Molecule  
(Not vibrating)  
 Before  
 
  After  
 
Molecule  
(Vibrating)  
 EM wave  
(Attenuated)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 1  Fall 201 2 
  1.9
Simplest case: No driving force, no damping
Initial condition: Stretch the spring to some initial displacement Q0, and let go  
Solution: 
   00cos Q t Q t   with resonance frequency  
0 K . 
  
Next simplest case: No driving force, but damping included
Initial condition: Stretch the spring to some initial displacement Q0, and let go  
Solution : 
   0costQ t Q e t
 = b/2 is the damping constant
oscillation frequen
cy 
22
0 
Full treatment: Driving force included, damping included 
Assume steady state   driving force is on forever 
Solution: 
   sin Q t t A
 
 0
1222 2 2 2
04aE
   
A
  
Vibrational amplitude A() increases as the driving frequency approaches the resonance 
frequency 0. The vibrational amplitude depends linearly on the driving field amplitude.  
Power absorbed:
 force  x velocity . Were interested in the power averaged over a cycle of 
the light. 
  
  
 222
00
22 2 2 2 2 2
0 04 4aE aEP        
 
  (5) 
Lorentzian  function for the absorption spectrum, with width given by the damping 
constant .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 1  Fall 201 2
 1.4Please see: The Electromagnetic Spectrum</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
5.35 / 5.35U Introduction to Experimental Chemistry
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 1  Fall 201 2 
1.6- concentration c of the absorbing species 
- absorptivity () of the sample, discussed much further later 
- for an infinitesimal sample, the thickness dL 
dI() = -() c dL I 0()  -() c dL I ()  where I() is intensity after the sample 
dI()/I() = -() c dL   can be integrated to derive Beers Law (do the derivation!)  
Result for macros
copic (thick) sample: 
   0log ( )I I c L A       
A() is typically displayed in an absorption spectrometer. If concentration c is in units of 
molecules/cm3, then () is in units of cm2. If concentration is in moles/liter, then () is 
usually written as (), the extinction coefficient, in units of liter/mole-cm.  
Well treat () or A() below by deriving the power absorbed by a classical oscillator 
when its driven by a periodic force of frequency .  
Fourier transform s
pectroscopy (FTIR) 
Instead of separating frequency components, could measure the time-dependent field 
Simple example: Gaussian  distribution of frequencies, peaked at p with bandwidth .  
     22
0 cos cosp t
p E t d E e t e t        

with  = 1/(2).  
Light field temporal profile   is a pulse  with a Gaussian time dependence and a duration, , 
that is given by the inverse of the spectral bandwidth. Lets look at such a pulse.  
Pulse is short becaus
e many frequency components go out of phase and cancel at long 
times. Broader frequency range  shorter pulse duration  
E(t) 
t</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Mod 1 Lecture Summary 2 (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/5-35-introduction-to-experimental-chemistry-fall-2012/resources/mit5_35f12_module_1ls2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>Spectroscopy in frequency and time domains</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 2  Fall 2012 
 
  2.3 The sample response to light 
What happens to the sample when light hits it? How does light interact with matter? 
Well consider IR light and molecular vibrations   similar for UV-VIS and NMR 
 
Classical equation of motion  
 
  
     2
0 2cosd Q t dQ tb KQ t aE tdt dt        
  
Q(t) is the time-dependent vibrational displacement 
 is the reduced mass 
b is a friction coefficient 
K is the force constant 
a is a coupling constant between the electric field of the light &amp; the molecular vibration  
 
Note: We will plug solutions for Q(t) into the equation of motion to see that they work, 
but you will not need to find solutions for Q(t) on your own.  
You do not need math beyond basic calculus for any aspect of this module 
 
Simplest case: No driving force, no damping 
Solution: 
   00cos Q t Q t   with resonance frequency  
0 K . 
  
With damping: 
   0costQ t Q e t  
 = b/2 is the damping constant  
oscillation frequency 
22
0   
 
 
With the driving force: 
Solution: 
   sin Q t t A  
 
 0
1222 2 2 2
04aE
   
A
  
 
Vibrational amplitude A() increases as the driving frequency approaches the resonance 
frequency 0. The vibrational amplitude depends linearly on the driving field amplitude.  
 
The vibrational oscillations are in phase with the driving force (  = /2) when driven far 
off resonance, out of phase (  = 0) when driven on resonance.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 2  Fall 2012 
 
  2.5 
In NMR, the frequency depends on the applied magnetic field in the z direction. The 
magnetic field strength dictates how big is the restoring force for spins to align in that 
direction.  
 
QM picture: two spin energy levels given by z-component magnetic moment quantum 
number mI = :  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
   0costQ t Q e t
 gives Lorentzian absorption spectrum through FT.   
 
 
 
 22
0A
  
   
 
 
 
 
 
Compare generally the time domain and frequency domain signals: 
 
Parameter  Time Domain S(t)  Frequency Domain  S() 
Large  0 Fast oscillations  High frequency  
Small  0 Slow oscillations  Low frequency  
Large   Fast decay  Broad linewidth  
Small   Slow decay  Narrow linewidth  
 E 
B E = h = = 
pB 
mI = +1/2 mI = -1/2 
0 
0 Proton spin energy levels as a 
function of applied magnetic field B. 
The proportionality constant p (no 
relation to any damping rate) is 
called the gyromagnetic ratio.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
5.35 / 5.35U Introduction to Experimental Chemistry
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 2  Fall 2012 
 
  2.4 
Power absorbed: force  x velocity . Averaged over one or many cycles: 
 
  
  
 222
00
22 2 2 2 2 2
0 04 4aE aEP        
 
  (5) 
 
Lorentzian  function for the absorption spectrum, with width given by the damping 
constant .  
 
  
 
 
 
 
 
 
This is what is measured in an absorption spectrum: how much power gets absorbed from 
the incident light at each frequency 
 
Note that  is really a  dephasing rate, which may be due to ordinary damping (loss of 
vibrational energy) but may be loss of vibrational phase coherence even when energy is 
retained. More on this later.  
 
Measurements in the time domain 
NMR: measure 
   0costQ t Q e t  directly 
RF pulse induces net magnetization vector M to precess about z axis (permanent applied 
magnetic field direction). The component of M along x or y undergoes damped oscillations.  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Vibrational &amp; electronic oscillations also can be measured on ultrafast (femtosecond) time 
scales.  
 z 
y 
x M After  
 z 
y 
x M Before</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 2  Fall 2012 
 
  2.1 Spectroscopy in frequency and time domains 
 
Last time we introduced spectroscopy and spectroscopic measurement.  
I. Emphasized that both quantum and classical views of spectroscopy are important 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Quantum mechanical  light is pho
tons (quanta of energy), molecule is discrete states 
with quantized energy levels 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Classical mechanical  light is classical EM wave, molecule is classical oscillator with 
continuous vibrational amplitudes 
  
In both cases, power absorbed is highest when the light frequency is on resonance .  
 
The two pictures are compatible because amplitude  is NOT equivalent to energy  in QM. 
The system could be in a stationary  state of high energy or it could be oscillating but an 
energy measurement has some probability of yielding zero excess vibrational energy.  
 
II. We looked at the EM wave 
   0, cosx t E kx t     E
 
Simpler form for molecules at fixed location ( x = 0) and neglecting polarization &amp; phase 
 0cos E t E t 
 
 
III. We looked at how a conventional spectrometer works and what it measures 
Incident and transmitted light intensities at various frequencies are compared to 
determine the absorption spectrum of the sample 
 Before  
Molecule  
(Ground state)  Photon  After  
Molecule  
(Excited state)  (No more 
photon)  (a) 
Ground 
state  Excited 
state  
E = h =  = 
hc/ = hc
 (b) 
  
EM wave  Molecule  
(Not vibrating)  
 Before  
 
  After  
 
Molecule  
(Vibrating)  
 EM wave  
(Attenuated)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 2  Fall 2012 
 
  2.2 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Beers law:  
   0log ( )I I c L A         
 
IV. We looked at FTIR, our first example of Fourier transform spectroscopy  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Interferometer measures the interference between two replicas of the field as oone 
mirror is variably delayed, revealing the EM oscillation cycles in the position domain.   
 
The frequency content of the field can be determined through Fourier transformation.  
 
     
     1cos
2
1cos
2F f t t dt
f t F t d

  






 
 
or really FT between x and k 
 
     
     1cos
2
1cos
2F k f x kx dx
f x F k kx dk






 
 
Now well address how light interacts with the sample.  
  Image removed due to copyright restrictions. Please see:
Ocean Optics. USB4000 Fiber Optic Spectrometer Installation and Operation
Manual. Document Number 211-00000-000-02-201201. Appendix C, p. 27.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>5.35 Module 1                               Lecture Summary 2  Fall 2012 
 
  2.6 FT relation applies to any type of spectroscopy and to any time or frequency dependence! 
Reproduces multiple peaks, complex lineshapes, etc.  
 
Dephasing rate   has several contributions:  
Damping  the energy decays back to zero 
This happens because the vibrating molecule interacts (collides) with other molecules and 
gradually stops vibrating. The vibrational energy goes into other degrees of freedom  
other vibrational modes of the same molecule or of other molecules, or molecular 
rotational or translational motion 
Pure dephasing   the energy stays the same but the coherence decays away 
This happens because the vibrating molecule interacts (collides) with other molecules and 
the vibrational phase gets shifted  
Inhomogeneous dephasing  the energy stays the same, and the coherence remains for 
any individual molecule, but the collective coherence decays 
This happens because different molecules might have slightly different vibrational 
frequencies due to somewhat different environments. After awhile the oscillations at 
different frequencies go out of phase  
 
All these effects lead to decay of net (superposed) oscillation amplitude in the time 
domain and to broadening of the absorption line in the frequency domain 
 
The time and frequency domain signals are always related through Fourier 
transformation, regardless of the cause of dephasing 
 
All these dephasing contributions can occur with magnetic spins, molecular vibrations, and 
electronic transitions</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction to Coordination Chemistry</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/5-35-introduction-to-experimental-chemistry-fall-2012/resources/mit5_35f12_module_2ls1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>Module 2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
5.35 / 5.35U Introduction to Experimental Chemistry
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lecture Overview
 
 Review bonding in Co compounds with Crystal Field 
Theory 
 Describe reactions in the lab 
 Practical aspects of FTIR Spectroscopy  Modeling hydration kinetics in Co complexes  Resources for researching/writing reports (Erja Kajosalo) 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Reactivity of Cobalt Complexes
 
_ 1_ _1 1_ 
Co2+ d7
1_ 1_ 1_ 1_ 1_
1 1 1 1 1
1_ 
S= 1/2 S = 3/2 
Co2+ =&gt; more reactive labile 
Co3+ =&gt; less reactive non labile 
We take advantage of this in the lab! 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Approaches to Laboratory Learning
 
Be wary of the Cookbook Approach
 
Be wary of He Said, She Said 
Be wary of Ego
 
Learning the hard way is sometimes the
 
best way 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>http://www.arjournals.com/ojs/index.php?journal=Chem 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>O 
H H Cobalt Complexes
 
Cobalt(II) nitrate hexahydrate
 
-O 
 N+ O 
-O	 Outer 
Coordination -O2 e-Sphere 
donor 
N+ O 
-O 
How could you determine if this is correct?
 
6CoOH2
OH2OH2 H2O
OH2 H2O2+
Inner Coordination 
Sphere</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5Introduction to Coordination Chemistry 
Alfred Werner  Nobel Prize in 1913 
Bioinorganic chemistry  currently hot research area  
Co is a Group 9 element  
Aufbau Principle 
1s 
2s  2p 3s  3p  3d 
4s  4p  4d  4f Co : [Ar] 4s2 3d7 
Co2+ has d7 
Co3+ has d6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>d Orbitals in Cobalt Complexes (Crystal Field Theory) 
_  _  _  _  _ 
 
   
1 1 1 1 1 1 
Co3+  _ _ _ 1_ 1_ 1_d6
1_ 1_ 1_ 1_ 1_ 1_
 1_ 
 1_ 1_ 
Low High Spin 
Spin 
7d Orbitals in Cobalt Complexes (Crystal Field Theory) 
o _  _  _  _  _ _  _ 
_  _  _ eg 
t2g</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
