<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/</course_url>
    <course_title>Introduction to Propulsion Systems</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Aerospace Engineering </list>
      <list>Propulsion Systems</list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Reacting gases (cont.); temperature dependence of specific heats</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>For a full understanding of this subject one must have recourse to Statistical Mechanics,
which deals with the thermal behavior of matter from a microscopic viewpoint, drawing on 
quantum mechanics. There is not time for such a discussion here, so we must be contentwith a summary of some of the results. 
A key concept is that of active degrees of freedom. This is the number of terms in the
classical expression for total energy that are quadratic in a coordinate or a velocitycomponent. According to the Law of Equipartition of Energy each of these states if fully 
excited will contain an energy per mol of T/2 where  is the ideal molar gas constant.  
Real molecules behave quantically, so at low enough temperatures, where the quantum of
energy is greater than the available thermal energy per molecule, a quantum degree offreedom may not be active. Generally, translational and rotational quanta are small enough
that translational degrees of freedom are regarded as active in all cases of interest to us, but
vibrational freedoms become active only at temperatures of the order of 2,000-3,000K. Taking the simplest case first: 
a) Monoatomic gases 
The molecule of a monoatomic gas can be thought of as a point mass, and as such it has three
translational degrees of freedom. So the Internal Energy (per mol) is 3T/2, so we find a 
molar Specific Heat at Constant Volume 
c
v=12.47 Joule/mole/K ( Monatomic) 
The ideal gas constant being = 8.32J/mole/K, the Specific Heat at Constant Pressure is 
cp= c += 20.79 Joule/kg mole/K v 
and the ratio of specific heats is =5/3= 1.667. 
All of these values are independent of temperature because the translational degrees of
freedom are fully excited at normal temperatures. 
b) Diatomic molecules. 
The simplest non-trivial case, the diatomic molecule, may be thought of as a "dumbbell" with 
in general unequal weights on the two ends, connected by a spring that can extend along theline of their common centers. 
Like the monoatomic molecule, the diatomic molecule as a whole has 3 translational degrees
of freedom, each containing energy T/2 per mol. In addition it has 2 rotational degrees of 
freedom (note that the moment of inertia about the line of centers is very small, so this degree 
of freedom does not count). Each of these rotational degrees of freedom is fully excited at
the temperatures of interest here (though not at very low T) and contains T/2.  So at "low" 
temperatures (near room temperature) the Internal Energy per mole is 5T/2 and the Specific 
Heat at Constant Volume is 
c
v=20.79  Joule/mole/K ( Diatomic at low T) 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>!( ) 2 p 2 
c
KpH = pH 2
= " = !
# 2 p 
" c 
pH 2 (# ) pc" 
!2 "#KpH (Tc )( p$ 
c ) 
For n = .25, T c = 3480K, we calculate from the standard chemical potentials K pH = .35 atm, 
2 1 .42 so  = (0.5)(.35) ;  = 1/ 2 p pc c 
For p c = 100 atm, and the estimated temperature, we now have  = .042 as a second estimate. 
So, using Eqs. (2) for  and (1) for , we find =2x0.5-0.019=0.481, and  
=1-0.481-(0.019+0.042)/2=0.489: 
H2 + .25 0 2 ! (.481)H2O + (. 489)H2 + (.019)OH + (.042)H 
With this composition we can now go back and calculate T c more accurately: 
0 = h H2(To) + .25 h 02(To) = .481 [10.6(T c-298)-57,800] 
+.489 [7.5(T c-298)] + .019 [7.8(T c-298)+10.06] 
+ .042 [5(T c-298)+ 52.09] 
T -298 = .481 (57, 800)! .019(10. 06)! .042(52.09) 
c =3047.481(10. 6)+.489(7. 5)+.019(7.8)+ .042(5) 
Tc=3345 K 
We stop the iteration here. A useful observation is that, just as the first approximation for Tc
was too high because it ignored the endothermic dissociations, the second is likely to be too
low, because it must have over-estimated these dissociations, since the equilibrium shifts in
favor of dissociation when the temperature is high. It is a good idea to under-relax the 
temperature, as for example using for the next estimate the average of the previous two:
1Tc ! (3480 + 3345) = 3413 K2 
Temperature dependence of specific heats 
In working through the above example, we assumed for simplicity that the specific heats of
the gases were constant. In fact they vary with temperature, generally increasing withincreasing temperature. Generally we account for this by taking the specific heat or the
enthalpy from tables of thermodynamic properties. But it is desirable for you to understand 
qualitatively why the specific heat varies, hence the following discussion. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>It follows that 
   c= c += 29.11  p v Joule/mole/K (Diatomic at low T) 
and =7/5= 1.4. 
 
At higher temperatures, the vibration of the molecule along its line of centers is excited, 
introducing two more degrees of freedom. This happens gradually between roomtemperature and the maximum temperatures encountered in propulsion devices. It is this 
variation that causes the variations of c
v of interest to us here. If the vibrational degrees of  
freedom are fully excited, the Internal energy per mole is 7 T/2 and  
 
   cv=37.41 Joule/mole/K ( Diatomic at high T) 
Correspondingly, 
   cp= cv+= 45.73  Joule/mole/K  (Diatomic at high T)
and =9/7= 1.286. 
 c) Polyatomic Molecule  
Most polyatomic molecules are non-linear, so they have an additional rotational degree of
freedom as compared to diatomic molecules. Thus at low temperatures, the Internal Energy
is 6T/2=3T. It follows that 
 
   c
v=24.94 Joule/mole/K (Polyatomic at low T) 
 
   c  33.260  p= cv+= Joule/mole /K (Polyatomic at low T) 
 
and the ratio of specific heats  is  =4/3= 1.333. 
 
The behavior of the vibrational degrees of freedom of polyatomic molecules can be very
complex if the number of atoms is large. A useful rule for estimating their energy content is to compute the number of vibrational degrees of freedom as the difference of the total for themolecule minus the translational and rotational degrees of freedom. Thus if N is the number 
of atoms, Vibrational Degrees of Freedom = 3N-6, and the Internal Energy per molecule if 
they are all excited is 3kT+(3N-6)kT=(3N-3)kT. The ratio of specific heats then becomes  
 
3N     " 2! =  (Polyatomic at high T)3N " 3 
 
and it is clear that this can be close to 1 for N large.  
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 Lecture 11 
Subject:  Reacting Gases (continued); Temperature dependence of specific heats. 
Reacting gases (continued) 
We were at the point in the last lecture of solving for the composition in the combustion
chamber. 
If we set T c and P c, we can solve for the set of six relations outlined for ! ,",#,$.. .., and the 
gas composition is known. But how do we find T c and p c?  As indicated earlier the pressure 
is determined by the mass flow and the nozzle throat area: 
pA m! = c t 
c *(Tc ) 
We regard the pressure as prescribed for now. 
To find T c we go back to the definition of !H0 and write conservation of energy asf
hH2(To ) + nh02(To ) = !["hH2 0(Tc ) + "H0 
fH20] 
+![hH2(Tc )] + "[#h0 H (Tc ) + #H0 
f 0 H ] 
+!["hH (Tc ) + "H0 
fH ] + #[h02(Tc )] 
+!["h0(Tc ) + "H0 
f 0] (7) 
where the symbol !hH2O (Tc ) means the excess specific enthalpy of H2O at Tc, over and above 
that at the reference temperature Tf=298.16K. For species like H2 and O2 the  is omitted,
because the enthalpy at Tf is zero, by convention. These excess enthalpies are tabulated vs. T
in standard data sets. 
If the ,  ... are known we can solve this for T c. 
In general, we have to represent the K p(Tc)'s and the h(T c)'s and solve this system
numerically. This is no problem but requires iteration and some care to ensure that the
numerical procedures converge. 
The primary constituents in the products are H 20 and H 2, so as a fi rst estimate, assume 
=0, =0, =0, =0.  Then !" 2n, ! + #" 1 , #" 1$ 2n and we can now estimate  the 
magnitudes of  and . The quantities  and  will be henceforth neglected, because of the
fuel-rich nature of the mixture. For example from (5) of the previous lecture, 
(! p )2 
K2 c ! 2
pH 2 O " ( " ) = = KpOH ( # pc )( $ pc )2 #$ 2 pc 
" " 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>" K pOH ! 2 = 2
( $ )# pc K 2 
pH2O 
and for =+=1 and the above estimates for  and , 
! 2 = (2n)2 1 K pOH 
1" 2npc K 2 
pH2O 
We now need an estimate  of T c. From (7), and using constant specific heats, 
hH2(To ) + nhO2(To ) ! 2n["hH20(Tc ) + "H0 
fH2 0] 
+(1-2n)[hH2(Tc)] 
where we read from tables 
!H 0 = "57.8 kcal
 
fH20 gmole
and we approximate for now 
cpH2= 7.5 cal/mole/K cpH2O = 10.6 cal/mole/K 
Let h(T o)=0 (as noted above this is arbitrary: we assume we are injecting gaseous H2 and O2 
at t0=298K). The energy balance then becomes 
0=2n[(10.6)(T c-298)-57,800]+(1-2n)[7.5(T c-298)] 
and we can solve this for (T c-298): 
2( 1 . 1 51 05 n n 5 7 , 8 0 0 ) Tc  298 = = 2n(10.6) + (1 2n+)7.5 7.5 6.20n 
To proceed further we must specify n. Let us take n=0.25, or half the stoichiometric value of 
0.5. This corresponds to an Oxygen/Hydrogen mass ratio of 4.  A more usual value is about 
5. Then we find T c = 3480 K as a first estimate. 
Now we have to check to see what the actual composition is for this temperature. Using the 
methods explained before, the values of K p0H and K pH20 at the estimated temperature are: 
n Tc Kp,0H Kp,H20 
atm1/2 
0.25 3480 1.70 4.93 
And from our previous result for , p1/2 ! = 0.19 , so now if p c=100 atm, =.019 as a secondc 
estimate, compared to the original estimate of 0. 
What about ? From Eq. (4) of the previous lecture, 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Hyperbolic orbits; interplanetary transfer</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The miss distancep!="a#sin($"%&amp;)="a#sin%&amp;=
#2"1
The excess hyperbolic velocity,v!= 2E=("a)
In the specialized technical literature, the term c3 is often used, meaning simply v2
!.
2) Interplanetary transfer
We assume for the moment that our craft has escaped the field of planet 1 (meaning it
is outside its sphere of influence), and so may be considered to be in orbit about the Sun.  In order for it to reach planet 2, its orbit about the Sun must intersect that of planet 2.  
Assume that the planetary orbits are circular.  Then it is clear that the trajectory of leastenergy which will allow the transfer is that which is just tangent to the orbits of the homeand target planets; this is called the Hohmann transfer orbit, which is the half-ellipse thatis sketched in the figure. The Heliocentric velocity at the start of this Hohman arc is theperiapsis (perihelion in this case) velocity, as described at the end of the last lecture:
vp1=S2r2
r1r1+r2r1 
r2 r2 
 P1 at 
launch P2 at 
launch 
Sun 
P1 and P2 
at arrival 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>so that if we launch the ship in the direction of motion of the planet, it must have a
relative velocity 
vre l, 1=S 2r(2!1)r1 r1+r2
with respect to planet 1 after escape from the planet.  By definition, this is the excess
hyperbolic velocity relative to the planet, v1, and the total energy relative to planet 1 at
he edge of the sphere of influence is simply 
( v2
1) .
Suppose the launch was for the surface of planet 1 (radius R ), and ignore its rotation. 
Just after launch, during which the rocket has imparted an ins1
tantaneous velocity 
1increment V1, the energy per unit mass (relative to the planet) is (!V2 1
21)" , and thisR1
must be the same as ( v1)2, by energy conservation with respect to planet 1 inside the 
sphere of influence. We then have  
121121(!V)" =v=S 2r
1R12#1 (2"1)2
2 2r1r
from which the first delta-1+r
V delivered by the rockets must2
 be
!V2=1+S 2r
1 (2"1)2
R1r1r1+r2
The procedure is similar when considering the approach to planet 2. The spacecraft willhave then a heliocentric velocity equal to the apoaxis (apohelion) velocity 
va2=S2r1 r r+r
and a relative velocity with respe2
c1
t to t2
he planet
vre l,2=S 2r(1!1)r r +r
which is also the excess hyperbol2
ic veloc1
ity w2
ith respect to planet 2. It is worth noting a  
this point that the spacecraft heliocentric velocity is less than that of the planet itself, so that, as seen from the planet, the spacecraft will be approaching from its advancing side. For capture into a circular orbit of radius R
c2, the geometry is shown below: 
To Sun
Vrel,2V2 
rc,2 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50  Lecture 4
Subjects: Hyperbolic orbits. Interplanetary transfer.(1) Hyperbolic orbits 
The trajectory is still described by 
pr= , but now we have &gt;1, so that the1+!cos"
radius tends to infinity at the asymptotic angle !"=#$cos$1(1 /%).
The parameter p still has the geometrical significance indicated in the figure, and is
therefore a positive number. It is still related to a and  through p=a(1!"2), but now a
is a negative number, so it is (-a) that has a geometrical significance, as indicated in the
figure. Note also tat  is still defined as the ratio of the distance from periapsis to center 
to the distance from focus to center. 
The energy is still given by 1E=v2 !=! , and is now positive. The angular 2 r 2a
momentum is still given by h=r2!! =p=a(1"#2). 
There are a few new parameters of interest in this case:The trajectory deflection, 
1 1!="#2("#$#
%)="#2 cos1=2 sin#1
&amp; &amp; 
  -a 
 p 
 r -a 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Just before the insertion rocket firing, the energy per unit mass relative to planet 2 is
equal to  (vrel,2)2, and it is also equal to the sum of the kinetic energy at that point of
1closest approach, plus the potential energy : (vclosest app .)2!2.  Thus we must have2 rc2
v2S 2r= 2+ (1!1)2
closest app .rc2 r2 r1+r2
and the insertion velocity increment must be this, minus the orbital velocity around planet2:
22S 2r(11)2 !V2= + " "2
rc2r2 r1+r2 rc2
Comparison to simple Escape+Transfer+Capture.
A simple-minded approach to the same mission would be to first apply an impulse at the
surface of planet 1 to achieve escape ( !V
zero velocity with respect to planet 1, apply a second impulse to enter thesc,1= 21/R1), then, after slowing down to 
e elliptic transfer 
orbit towards planet 2 (this would be our v,1), then, in the vicinity (but still outside the
SOI of ) planet 2, apply a third impulse to mrel
atch the heliocentric velocity of planet 2 (this
would be our v,2), and finally, starting from zero relative velocity far from planet 2, 
apply a fourth impulse to capture the craft into orbit about planet 2 (this is equal to therel
escape velocity from a distance R2 to the planet, !Ve ,2= 22/R2). You can easily 
check that the two impulses we derived before are, ressc
pectively,
!V1= (!Vesc,1)2+(v2
rel,1)
!V2= (!V2
sc,2)2
e +(vrel,2)
and so our previous scheme is definitely more effective. These two strategies are called 
sometimes the Hohmann (simple, four impulses) and the Oberth (combined, two impulses) maneuvers.
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Aircraft engine noise: principles; regulations</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec36/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>36</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>1$ ro' 2
  !(r,")= &amp; P k  dcos")      (12) 2#oao% r ( 
 
cos2!This flux has now a 2 distribution (no sound at 90 to the dipole axis, r
maximum along the dipole axis). The total radiated power is 
2 (Prk d )2
  Pd=2!#!"($)r2sin$ d$ =!o
or,    (13) 3 %oao
Aside from the 1 factor, this differs from P3m, the monopole power, by the factor 
(kd)2=(2!d/")2, which is, by assumption a small number, and becomes smaller 
the longer the wavelength is (or the lower the frequency ! =ao/k).  
 
An important observation is that a physical dipole requires application of an external oscillatory force. A possible physical implementation of the radiating dipole is any vibrating compact object, such as a fan or a turbine blade. The dipole axis is then the direction of vibratory motion, and the surrounding air is forced back and forth as it would between the hypothetical two monopoles in counter-phase.     (c) Quadrupoles  Strongly turbulent flows, such as an engine exhaust jet, are known to be strong sources of acoustic radiation. If the jet is steady and subsonic, there is no possibility of macroscopic monopole (expansion/contraction) type of radiation, and since there is no external force in the body of the fluid, no dipole sources either. However, there are fluctuating pressures at different points (turbulent eddies), exerting forces on each other with zero net on the larger scale. The lowest order multipole with these features is the Quadrupole, which can be built up from two dipoles with a common axis, and separated by 2d and with opposing directions.  The detailed derivation is similar to that for a dipole. We calculate (in the far field) 
   
p'Pr=!2o(k dcos")2cosk(r!aot)    (14) r
   
and for the acoustic power flux,  
" Pr% 2(kdcos()4
!=2$ o'      (15) # r&amp; )oao 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Elementary sources. It is useful to examine the simplest acoustic sources, which are 
all configurations with an im
posed pressure fluctuation or an imposed wall 
vibration. The first in a systematic series of such sources are shown below:  
3From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>which integrates for all directions to a radiated power 
 
8 (Pr   P =!o)2(kd)4
q       (16) 5 "oao
 The quadrupole radiator pattern is more sharply directional along the axis 
(cos4!), and is an additional (kd)2 weaker than the dipole, with an even stronger 
rate of increase with frequency.  It should be noted that the collinear-dipole type of quadrupole is not the only one possible, but all of them share the (kd)
4 feature (although with different 
angular patterns).      
  
  
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
 Subjects discussed: Aircraft Engine Noise : Principles; Regulations  Noise generation in the neighborhoods of busy airports has been a serious problem since the advent of the jet-powered transport, in the late 1950's.  Although piston-engined aircraft had caused some concerns prior to that, it was the turbojet-powered first generation jets (707, Comet, DC-8) with their jet noise that led to wide public concern, and to regulations by some airport authorities.  With the continuing growth of airline travel, the problem has continued to expand, leading to rules promulgated by the FAA that limit the noise that any individual aircraft can make at each of 3 measuring stations. 
 
 
  Noise is the human ear's response to pressure fluctuations in time, at the ear of the observer.  As such it has both physical and psychological aspects.  Thus, one person's music can be another person's noise.  There is general agreement for example that the exhaust noise of motorcycles is annoying, but the biker will not agree.  We will from this point on avoid the psychological and concentrate on the physical aspects of aircraft noise, without meaning to imply that the latter is more important.  Noise is transmitted from the source (aircraft) to the observer by sound wa ves.  So 
let us begin with a brief review of sound propagation.   Conservation of mass  
     
D!+!"u =0    (1) Dt
 
 Conservation of momentum  
     Du ! ="#p      (2) Dt
 
Suppose the velocity and pressure to be the sum of a large steady component and a small time-varying one  
1From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.Lecture 36</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>(a) Monopoles 
 Suppose now the perturbation is due to a pulsating sphere, whose radius 
oscillates by some small 
!r0 at a frequency . This sets up spherically symmetric 
pressure field that oscillates at  as well, and propagates as a sound wave train.  
In spherical coordinates, the wave equation is  
1!2p " 1!    =a2 2 2(r2!p " )    (7) 
0!t r !r !r
 We expect acoustic energy to be conserved, and since at least the compression 
part of this energy varies as 
p'2, let us try a solution of the Monopole form: 
    p'=P(r0)cos k(r!arot)    (8) 
It can be seen by direct substitution that this does satisfy the wave equation. The 
quantity k= /a is called the wave number,  and the wavelength  is 2"0 != = 2a"0. k #
 
The velocity field (purely radial) can be calculated from (4)  
!u'1!p'    r="       (4a) !t #o!r
 and from (8), after integrating in time, 
4From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>! 
  u =u ! 
0+u ! ' (t)  p=p o + p'(t)  = o + '(t) 
 
and further suppose that ! 
  u 0=0.  Then to first order in small quantities (1) and (2) 
become 
     !"' ! +" u !t0#. '=0    (3) 
  
      
"u !' 
!0 =#$p'     (4) 
  "t
 
In the absence of heat conduction and viscosity, ' and p' are related isentropically, 
i.e.  
   p2(!=2)" dp dp# ="   or p' "'=!  p1!1 p0!0 p0 p0
It follows that     p' = 
p 0!'="RT0!'#a2
o!'    (5) !0
where a 0 is the speed of sound. 
 
So in 1a 
     !"' 1 !p'=!t a2  
0!t
 Now taking    
! (1a) - !.(2a) we have !t
 
1!2p'    2 2 " #2p'=0     (6) a0!t
 
In one dimension (for a plane wave)  
1!2p'!2p    " =0 a2
0!t2!x
 This is a Wave Equation, satisfied in general by solutions of the form p' = p'(x 
aot), 
so that p' is constant for x = aot. Thus the solution for a plane wave would be of the 
form 
    p ! =Pcosk(x"a0t) 
Excitation 
 We can now ask how such waves are generated in an engine. Some of the main sound sources are schematized below: 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>u' P r # ( )
r=osinr a t
%cos" &amp; 
 (r"a (9) !ot)"o(    
oaor$ kr ' 
 
The acoustic power flux (energy crossing unit area per unit time, averaged over one cycle) is the average of the work done by 
p !:  
 
1 r2
   !=#" P2% ( p'u'
rdt = ' o*  "o    (10) 2$oao&amp; r) 
 
where 2" 2"!= = . # kao
2r2
The net acoustic radiated power is P2 P
m=4"r#=2"o, which is seen to be !oao
independent of r, as it should. The monopole power radiated is independent of 
wave number k=2!/", and only dependent on pressure amplitude. A possible 
physical implementation of a monopole source is a pulsating jet, such as produced by a pulse-jet (like that in the V-1 missile), or by the oscillations during an engine surge.  (b) Dipoles   Consider next two monopoles of equal strength P operating in counter-phase to each other, and spaced a small distance d along the x-direction. If an observer is 
located at a distance r from one of them, and at an angle  from the x direction, 
its distance to the other will be (approximately 
r+dcos!. Then the pressure p' 
at the observers location will vary as  
  
p'Pr=ocosk(r!aot)Pr!ocosk(r+dcos"!a (11) r r+dcos0t)  "
 
Expanding the second term and assuming d to be much smaller than both, the 
wavelength (1/k) and the observation distance r, 
 
  p'Pr=o(k dcos!)sink(r"aot)+(dcos#)P r0cosk(r"a t) (11b) r r r0
of the two terms in (11b), the first has the 1/r dependence that will ensure energy 
flux conservation at all distances, while the second will decay faster and will be negligible for distances r&gt;&gt;1/k; this is the near-field dipole sound, which can be important near the source. We concentrate here on the far-field contribution (first term in (11b)).  The calculation of the far-field power flux is as before, remembering that it is still 
a radial flux, even though there is an angular dependence in . So we still have 
the first equality in Eq. (10), and the calculation is straightforward. We obtain  
 
 
 
 
  
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Compressor blading; design; multi-staging</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec26/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>26</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Starting and Low-Speed Operation 
 
Because the density variation through the compressor is much less at low speed 
conditions, the compressor develops adverse blade loading situations in both the inlet and 
the outlet stages at low operating speeds. As shown in the sketch, the axial velocity in the 
inlet stages tends to be lower, and that in the outlet stages higher, relative to the blade 
speed, than at design, so the front stages tend to be stalled and the rear ones to 
windmill. This makes it difficult to design a compressor that will operate satisfactorily 
over a wide range of speeds. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
The solution to this problem has taken two forms: one is to divide the compressor into two or even three spools, operating at different speeds, the other is to use stator blades 
of variable angle, to adjust the flow direction at low speeds. Most modern high pressure 
ratio engines use both. 
 
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>.116 DT=.195 +     D .293353
!H= +  
T !H
 
The solidities at hub and tip, !H and !T are of course design choices, but since the 
spacings S H and S T are related by 
S   Hr=H. STrT
!   HC=HSTC=HrT !TCTSHCTrH
 Let us choose 
!T = 1, C H/CT =1, then !H=2 
 
DT=.195 +.116 =.311
   .353  DH=.293 + = .4702
Both of these are acceptable from the viewpoint of losses, but D H barely so. It is 
generally true that the hub section of the blade is limiting from the viewpoint of diffusion. 
 
Mach Number Effects: 
 
Typically the first stages of modern aircraft engine compressors operate with axial Mach 
number  0.7 and blade tangential Mach number M T 1.3 giving  
   (M1)T=M2
1+M2
T=1.48 
so the tips of the blades see supersonic flow.  For r H/rT = 0.5, (M 1!) H=.49 +.42 =.95, 
so the hub is at a very high subsonic speed. Just as for inlets, hub and tip therefore require 
quite different diffusion techniques. At the hub, blading that is the equivalent of a 
subsonic inlet is called for  
  
 
 
  
 
 
  
 
At the tip, the blades must be designed to minimize shock losses. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Subjects: Compressor Blading; Design; Multi-Staging 
 
Compressor blading; Radial variations 
 
In all of the discussion so far the blade speed has been taken as a parameter. In fact the 
blade speed varies with the radial location in the compressor, so the designs that we 
have discussed are applicable only at one radius in any real compressor. In practice it is 
usual to begin a compressor design with such a treatment, called a mean line design 
carried out at some mean radius. But the effects of the blade speed variation with radius 
are important, so we must be aware of the constraints they impose on the design. 
 
 
 
Normally it is desirable for the pressure (or temperature) ratio of a rotor blade row to be 
approximately constant over the radial length of the blade, so that the outlet airflow has 
uniform pressure. From the Euler equation 
Tt2"(r2#!r#)    !1=2 1 1 Tt1 cpTt1
Supposing for simplicity that !1 = 0 (no inlet guide vane), we see this condition requires 
const    r2!2=const .; !2=  r2
This implies that the rotor blade row should generate a Free Vortex in the flow   
 
 
 
 
116.50 Lecture 26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Now let us draw the velocity triangles for tip and hub, assuming r H/rT = , and w 1 = w 2 = 
const = !rT/2. 
 
  
Here it has been assumed that !2(rH)="rH, (that is that !'2=0) and it follows that 
 
  !2(rT)="rH/2 ="rT/4 
 The approximate blade shapes as sketched are determined by the condition that the 
leading and trailing edges are aligned with the flow. We see that the blades are strongly 
twisted from hub to tip. 
 
Now let us see what these variations imply for the Diffusion Factor, D. 
Taking v
1 = 0, 
   D =1V " !2#+2!#1 V 1" 2$V 1" 
Remember that these are relative to the rotor blade.  
 From the geometry,   
 
 
   TIP      HUB 
  
!2"!1=#rT/4    !2"!1=#rH=#rT/2 
 
 V 1! ="rT1+1/4 =1.12"rT   V 1! ="rH2="rT/ 2 
 
# 1&amp; # 3&amp; 2
 V 2! ="rT% (2 +% ( =.901 "r  "r  $ 2V ! = = "r/2' $ 4' T 1 H T
 
1
 DT=1.901 1/4 1! +    D =2(1.12 )H1! +2
1.12 "T 2 (2 / 2 ) 
"H
   
  
  
  
2V'2V'1
V'2 V1
V2V'1V2V1
wrTwrH
v2r = 1 v2H 2 =  2wrHv2H50% reaction at hub
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Multi-staging 
 
Because  increases, the flow area must decrease as we go through the compressor. We 
can choose to effect this area variation by decreasing the tip radius, by increasing the hub 
radius, or something in between, like keeping a constant mean radius. All these solutions 
have both advantages and disadvantages. 
 
The constant outer diameter design maintains the blade velocity at the maximum for the 
entire length of the compressor, hence gives the highest pressure ratio for a given number 
of stages. But because the length of the blades becomes small at the exit end of the 
compressor, leakage through the tip clearance is most serious for this design choice. 
 
The constant inner diameter design minimizes the tip clearance problem and also yields 
lower stresses in the discs of the last stages, but requires more stages for a given pressure 
ratio. 
 
The Polytropic Efficiency 
 
What is most nearly constant among stages of a multi-stage compressor is the limiting 
isentropic efficiency for small compression, which is called the Polytropic efficiency: 
1dp(dht)S#t
t RTtdlnp$!Poly" = =t %1dlnp=t dht cpdTt cpdTt $dlnTt
If we assume  Poly remains constant along the compression path, this definition can be 
integrated to  
T     t,out p!"1
=(t,out)!#Poly Tt,in pt,in
#$1
or  ! ="#%Poly
c c . Inserting this into the definition of the normal Isentropic Efficiency 
allows one to compute it in terms of  Poly and the finite pressure or temperature ratio: 
$%1
#c$% #!c" =c$%
&amp;c%1$%1  
#c$!poly%1
As an example, take a multi-stage compressor with an overall pressure ratio  c=16 and 
assume the polytropic efficiency is constant and equal to 0.9 in all stages. Its isentropic 
efficiency (ideal work required divided by actual work) is then calculated to be c=0.856. 
This is less than  Poly, the small-increment efficiency, because the last stages of the 
compressor receive gas that is hotter than it should, due to the inefficiencies in the 
previous stages, and hence more work is needed to compress it. It could be mentioned 
here that a similar argument can be made for turbines, and in that case one finds Poly&gt;c, 
because the extra thermal energy due to inefficiencies of the early stages is now available 
for conversion to work by the latter stages. 
One warning: the isentropic efficiency of a compressor with N stage, each with a stage 
efficiency  s (close to  Poly)  is not N
s. 1$%1
1 
 
 
 
 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Compressor-turbine matching; gas generators</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec31/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>31</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Using these ideas, one can generate and plot a set of Gas Generator Characteristics,such as those below. With this Gas Generator, we can do lots of things 
a) Turbojet b) Turbofan  
c) Turboprop 
d) Unducted fan  
e) Helicopter  
Notice that the single free variable chosen for this plot is the normalized rotational speed (as a fraction of its design value). The quantity in the denominator is the non-
dimensional compressor-face temperature 
2= T2/T0, because the blade speed r is 
made non-dimensional with the speed of sound at station 2. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
Subjects: Compressor -Turbine matching; Gas generators 
Compressor-turbine matching: 
We have described the characteristics of both compressors and turbines.  
Assembling the two with a combustor between gives us a gas generator, which is the heart of any gas turbine engine. Once we understand its behavior we canappreciate most of the real characteristics of aircraft engines, and graduate fromthinking of them
 as a lot of abstract equations. 
Actually, we have already done in Lecture 20 most of the work needed to understand the performance of an ideal Gas Generator, including the important concept of the Compressor operating line, which is set by the flow passing characteristics of the rest of the engine. We sum
marize here the main findings of that 
work: 
(a) If the nozzle and the turbine stators are both choked, the turbine temperature 
ratio is fixed once the flow area ratio A4/A2 is set. 
(b) One additional single parameter is sufficient to specify all the other gas generator 
parameters. This can be the temperature ratio =Tt4/Tt2, or the compressor 
temperature ratio c, or the engine-face Mach number M2, or the normalized air mass 
fhflow m2, or the fuel flow ratio . cpTto 
(c) A Compressor Operating Line in the plane of compressor pressure ratio vs. 
normalized flow can be calculated once the ratios of all the flow areas are known. For a given choice of one of the parameters listed above, a point is selected along this operating line. 
(d) All the above is independent of the compressor specifics. After the compressor 
has been selected, its perform
ance map (pressure ratio vs. normalized flow) contains 
normalized rotational speed lines as additional information. This parameter is therefore to be added to our list of possible parameters (as is done in the figure at the end of this lecture), each of which uniquely specifies the state of the gas generator. 
It follows from the above that a single degree of freedom is left to the pilot (or to the engine controller), unless geom
etry can be varied. It is probably most intuitive to 
think of this unique freedom as the normalized fuel factor, or the peak tem
perature 
ratio Tt4/Tt2, since these closely relate to the engine throttle control. 
It is to be noted, however, that many idealizations have been made to obtain these sim
ple results. If the turbine or the nozzle un-choke, or if the engine inefficiencies 
are rigorously accounted for, the overall detailed behavior is more complex, but its main qualitative features are not too different. 
1Lecture 31</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rocket equation; gravity loss; optimum acceleration</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>This is an (implicit) equation for m(t) in terms of v!v0, with the initial acceleration a 0m0 c
as a parameter.   
 
The last term is often termed the"gravity loss", since it is the reduction in velocity increment that the vehicle suffers due to the (downward) acceleration of gravity. As a
0 
increases, the gravity loss decreases, since the time over which gravity acts is reduced. So 
why not use a very large av!v m(t)
0 to get the largest possible 0 for a given ?  To see c m0
why we must examine the effect of the acceleration on the mass of the propulsion system. 
We divide the mass of the rocket into parts: 
m0=mstruct+meng+mpay+mprop 
When all the propellant has been expended, at the time tb,  m(tb)=mstruct+meng+mpay, or 
as a fraction of initial mass 
m(tb)m=0!mprop=1m!prop"1!m' m0 0 0
Here the prime on the propellant fraction indicates that it is divided by m0, i.e. is the 
fraction of the initial mass represented by the propellant. 
Clearly, the smaller m(t) or the closer m'prop is to 1, the larger the v!v0 that can be m0 c
achieved.  But the limit is set by: 
m(tb)=1!m'mprop=m'struct+m'eng+m'pay
0
We want to design the components of our vehicle so th at m 'struct and m 'eng are as small as 
possible, given the loads and available technology.  
The engine mass is proportional to the thrust it develops; define 
EngineWeight m g m m "!= =eng=eng=eng
Thrust F m0(a0/g) n
where we call for short  a0/g=n. Notice that this is the number of gs due to thrust only, 
while the more commonly used g-number (the specific downwards force felt by a pilot) 
includes gravity and would be n+1. 
 
We now have  m!(tb)=m!pay+ms!tr+n", and the rocket equation becomes
1!m"!m"vb!v0=!cln(m"pay+ms"tr+n#)!(pay str!#)  nm mprop
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>vt
=!"c(h)dm t
!
0 "0g(h)dt; ht
=vdtm !0
As indicated, both c and g are functions of h.  In the case of c, the dependence is through 
the atmospheric pressure, p 0, an effect we will explore in detail later. The atmospheric 
pressure varies with weather and with temperature, but a rule of thumb is: 
pr r
 !
0=e!E
6.68 r - rE = km p0(rE)
In fact the pressure variation is much more important in the context of aircraft engines, 
whose thrust is essentially proportional to the atmospheric density, other factors being 
equal. 
The gravitational attraction varies as g(r) = g  (rEE/r)2   , where r E is the Earth's radius,  r =
+ h and gE is the gravitational acceleration at the Earths surface. Since rockets 
typically operate for a short time only, g may be taken here as a constant to a good 
approximation. 
If as a first approximation we take c and g constant we can integrate the rocket equation 
to get: 
  v!vm(t)
0=!cln !gt m0
and this is the usual form of the Rocket Equation. Remember that it applies to a vertical 
launch.  For other flight paths the last term changes. Also remember that we have neglected atmospheric drag forces (this last approximation is valid for large rockets, but 
may not be for smaller vehicles, which have more area per unit volume). 
2) Gravity Loss &amp; Optimum Acceleration 
As we will see, it is helpful to express this relation as one for the mass ratio in 
terms of the velocity change, since it is the latter that is set by the mission, e.g. launch to 
LEO.  But this leaves gt  to be determined.  If we make the additional assumption that m.
= constant, then 
m m(t )m.
tFtm0a0
0! = = = tc c
where a 0 is the initial acceleration, defined as the thrust divided by the initial mass. 
Note that a0&gt;g for achieving takeoff. 
So now we can eliminate t, to find 
v!v0 m(t)g" m(t)% =!!n ! 1!
  c m a $ 
0 0 # m '  
0&amp; 
2rE</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Fig. 1 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>We notice here that the logarithmic term (the ideal velocity increment) decreases with n 
(heavy engine), but the last parenthesis (the gravity loss) decreases with n (reduced burn 
time). We can optimize the choice of initial acceleration by differentiating wrt. to n: 
 
   " 1!m#! +pay!ms#tr=0  m#s#2
pay+mtr+n" n
which is a quadratic equation with the solution 
  
1!m"pay!ms"tr 1!m"pay!ms"tr 2(m"pay+ms"tr)(1!m" " nopt +( )+pay!m=str) 2 2 #
Some reasonable estimates are: 
m 'struct !0.1 ; !=0.02  
For these values, Fig. 1 shows how the actual velocity increment varies with n=a0/g for a 
range of payload fractions. The optima are clearly visible, and can be obtained from the graph or calculated from our quadratic solution. These n
opt values, and the associated 
maximum velocity increments, are shown in Fig. 2. Interestingly, n  varies little, and 
stays in the range from 3 to 4, familiar to astronauts. The velocity incopt
rement is usually set 
by the mission requirement, e.g. to get to LEO, and Fig. 2 illustrates how small the 
payload fraction becomes if this required velocity increment exceeds the jet velocity c (in 
fact, for this example, m0!=0for  (v!v0)!1.5) 
 
This optimization has considered only the effects of the "gravity loss" and the engine 
weight on the choice of a0.  If we include other effects, such as drag, we may get a g
different answer. A large value of n implies reaching high speeds at low altitudes, where 
air density is still high, and for small rockets this would generate large drag losses. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Fig. 2 
 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 Lecture 1 
 
Subjects: Rocket Equation; Gravity Loss; Optimum Acceleration. 
 
1) Rocket Equation 
 
A rocket is a propulsive device that produces a thrust force F on a vehicle by ejecting mass a high relative velocity c. This force is simply equal to the rate of momentum outflow from a control volume that encloses the vehicle. If 
 m! is the mass expulsion rate, 
we then find 
   F = m.
c 
This is a particularly useful result because c and m.
 are insensitive to the operating 
environment of the rocket. In more detail, c is not necessarily the velocity of the expelled 
mass as it leaves the rockets exit plane, because the pressure field may continue 
accelerating this mass for some distance. In that case, c represents the limiting far field velocity of the ejected mass.   
For a rocket-powered vehicle in a vertical launch from the Earth, 
mdv=!cdm!mg"dv=!cdm!gdtdt dt m
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Compressors and fans</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec24/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>.   F = (m  per blade) (v2 - v1) 
 
where v is the tangential component of V at any point.  The power delivered to the fluid by a blade is the force times the blade velocity and this must equal the change in fluid energy per blade, across the rotor, so  
   Power = F r 
.   Power per blade = (r) (m  per blade) (v
2 - v1) 
.           = (m  per blade) c p (Tt2 - Tt1) 
     c
p (Tt2 - Tt1) = r (v2 - v1) 
 
This is the famous (and important) Euler Turbine Equation.  The pressure generally rises across both rotor and stator blade rows.  If the flow relative to the blades is subsonic we can see this easily from Bernoulli's equation:     A
2 &gt; A 1  (because of the turn towards axial) 
  V 2 &lt; V 1 
1  p1 +  2V21
1 = p22 +  2V2 
  p2 &gt; p1 
 The energy exchange across the rotor is most generally understood as follows.  We 
focus on a streamtube passing through the rotor, with a mass flow m: 
 
 
The torque on the rotor due to this stream tube is 
.    =  m(r 2v2 - r1v1)  
and the power is  
.   Power =  =  m (r2v2 - r1v1) 
Equating this to the total enthalpy rise of the fluid 
.   Power =  m  cp (Tt2 - Tt1) 
        c p (Tt2 - Tt1) = (r 2v2 - r1v1) 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>In the sketch the surface of rotation defined by the dashed line is termed a 
meridional stream surface. On this stream surface, the cross section of the blades looks like: 
 
To simulate the rotational symmetry of the actual blade rows we think of a cascade, extending to infinity in both directions. In this limit the rotor blades then have a constant velocity and the stators are stationary.  To describe the effect of the blades,  Velocity Diagrams are used, which show how the velocities change across the rotor and stator blade rows, and in particular the effects of the relative motion of the two: 
                       
If  the velocities at 3 are the same as at 1 then we can put another identical stage after this one.  The energy exchange all takes place in the rotor blade rows. The force on a blade F is equal to the rate of change of tangential momentum per blade: 
r 
       V1 
(absolute)  V1 
(relative) 
Rotor 
V2 
(absolute) V2 
(relative) 
r 
V3 
(absolute) 
r        V
1 
 V1 
 
V2 V2 
Composite Velocity Triangle 
Stator 
2wr
Rotor
Stator
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
 Subject:  Compressors and Fans  These are fluid dynamic devices, i.e., they depend on fluid accelerations to compress and expand gases, in contrast to positive displacement devices such as the familiar piston engine. The moving blades exert a force on the fluid by virtue of their motion, resulting in an added velocity of the fluid, and an increase in its energy in stationary coordinates. It is the fact that the force is dependent on the blades' velocity, roughly as the square, that makes this a dynamic machine. In contrast, the energy per unit mass added to the fluid in the positive-displacement piston-cylinder mechanism is nearly independent of the speed of the piston, depending only on the volumetric compression ratio. 
   
 
Large aircraft engine compressors or fans are mainly of the axial-flow type, with rotating rows of rotor blades, separated by stator blades. A cross-sectional view through the axis looks like 
 
   
Both rows of blades function to deflect the flow in the tangential direction, the rotors adding angular momentum in the direction of the rotation, the stators removing it.  Because of their motion, the rotating blades can do work on the flow, increasing its energy.  The stator blades in contrast only diffuse the flow, exchanging momentum for pressure rise.   
1Positive Displacement    Fluid Dynamic
wr
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.
r
wMeridional Stream Surface
R S R S R S
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.Lecture 24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>This is the Euler Turbine Equation in a general form, although the left hand side is even more generally the total enthalpy rise in the streamtube across the rotor, whether or not the gas can be modeled as being ideal.  The Euler Turbine Equation applies to other geometries than the axial flow one, e.g. the centrifugal or radial compressor 
   
In this case v 1  0 and if the vanes are radial, v 2  r  so we have 
 
2   cp (Tt2 - Tt1) = (r 2)  
 For the axial compressor, r
2  r1, and we have  
 
   c p (Tt2 - Tt1)  r(v 2 - v1) 
 
T   t2 (#r)2v!1$!v'"2 1
Tt1 c T&amp;
p t 1%#r) (
 
!R T ("r)2v#v    = 1 $ 2 1 '&amp; )  cpTt1!RT1%"r(
 
   Tt2 T!1=("!1)1M2$ v2!v1&amp; 
TT
t1 T % 
t1 #r'  
 
 
4wr
r2
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Film cooling; thermal stresses; impingement cooling; how to do cooling design</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec30/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>30</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50
Topics: Film cooling; Thermal stresses; Impingement 
Cooling; How to do cooling design 
Film cooling: With internal cooling the heat flux through the blades surface increases as the external 
gas temperature increases. That is large T
r  T w implies large q w. This large heat flux 
must be conducted through the blade material according to 
k !Twqw = t 
where t is the thickness of blade skin. 
So for a given back-side T, a small t is needed if the surface facing the hot gas is to be 
maintained at an acceptable level. As noted in the last lecture, it is also necessary to 
match the internal cooling precisely to external heat load to prevent a large T w variation. 
All of these difficulties can be mitigated somewhat by the technique known as film 
cooling, which is illustrated in the figure: 
Essentially the idea is to introduce cooling air into the boundary layer over the surface of 
the blade, reducing the effective temperature of the gas heating the surface. This lowers 
the heat flux, making less cooling air necessary. In addition the cooling air cools the wall 
in passing through the small holes. 
The performance of film cooling is related to the mass velocity ratio 
! fufm = !sus 
where f refers to the film coolant and s to the free stream flow: 
1From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.Lecture 30</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Now with this cooling effectiveness, how do we estimate the heat transfer rate to the 
wall? The usual approach is to assume that the conventional film coefficient h, or the 
equivalent Stanton number St, can be applied, with an effective gas temperature given by 
the cooling effectiveness, Thus, 
qwh = Tr f ! Tw 
where h is that for a normal boundary layer, and Trf ! Tw = Tr ! Tw !" ad (Tr ! Tc ) . We then 
calculate 
qw = !ucp (Trf " Tw )St 
where h or St are correlated in the usual way to the Reynolds number and Prandtl number. 
Impingement cooling 
Because the heat transfer rate is largest at the leading edge of the blade where the 
boundary layer thickness is least, special measures are sometimes called for to cool this 
region. One is Impingement Cooling, illustrated in the figure: 
3From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.
From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MITPress, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>modulus and inversely to the thermal conductivity. Unfortunately the oxidation-resistant 
Nickel and Cobalt alloys favored for turbine blades have relatively low thermal 
conductivity and high modulus, so thermal stress is a controlling problem for turbine 
blades. It results in cracking an ultimately limits the blade life. 
( 1!")#Ult .A related material quantity is the Figure of Merit, Z = (in K), which is aE$ 
measure of the allowable temperature difference across the plate. A few values are: 
Material Cu SS 302 Ti Alloy Steel 
Z (K) 35 111 136 234 
The Z value is low for copper, but, of course, even a small temperature difference can 
drive a large heat flux through copper. 
How to design cooled blades 
It is presumptuous to engage this subject at the tail end of a one-hour lecture, because this 
is one of the most difficult areas of gas turbine design. But the intent here is simply to 
outline the way one might proceed, as follows: 
a) Estimate the q w over the blade surface for specified T w.  
b) Find the thermal stresses in the skin.  
c) Find the reduction in q w required to limit the stresses to acceptable values,  
hence the !ad required of the film cooling. 
d) Find the arrangement of cooling holes and cooling air flow for film cooling, to 
give the required effectiveness. 
e) Find the internal cooling airflow to absorb the residual q w. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>For the scheme shown the cooling rate can be correlated as 
! d .8$ 
&amp;% e '0.85( l )( d )( d 
d p L )0.4 
Nustag = 0.44 Re.7 
d#" p 
where the Reynoldss number is that for the impinging jet 
(!u)Jet dRed =  
and the Nusselt Number similarly is based on the jet diameter d
h d Nu = kfluid 
Thermal stresses 
For a thin skin supporting a temperature difference due to a heat flux, 
a thermal stress is generated by the tendency of the hot side of the wall to expand relative 
to the colder side. To see this we can note that in general the strain in the material due to 
a combination of a normal stress  c and a temperature difference from some mean 
temperature is 
! = (1"# )$ 
Ec + % (T " T ) 
If the plate extends to infinity in both directions, then the strains on both the hot and cold 
sides will be the same (note however that this assumes the plate does not curve or bulge). 
In this approximation the stress, called the Thermal Stress, is found by equating the two 
strains: 
(1!") # H
E !#C = !$(TH ! TC ) 
If the plate is unloaded, force balance imposes ! H = "!C , and the temperature difference 
is related to the heat flux through the plate by TH ! TC = t qw /k. Combining and solving 
for the cold-side stress (a positive tension), we obtain 
! C = " E ( t)2k(1#$ ) qw
The quantity !E /k is termed the thermal stress susceptibility. Clearly we would like it 
to be small. It is proportional to the thermal expansion coefficient, and to the elastic 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>As indicated in the figure, which shows heat transfer rate versus the (dimensionless) 
magnitude of the cooling air flow, the cooling air actually has two effects on the heat 
transfer to the wall, which can be separated by varying the cooling air temperature 
relative to the wall temperature. If the cooling air is at the wall temperature its effect is to 
increase the heat transfer, by stirring the boundary layer. But if it is cooler than the wall, 
this effect is partially offset by the reduction of the effective hot gas temperature, so that 
there is a best cooling air flow rate. 
To make these trends quantitative for design purposes, we define a Cooling Effectiveness 
by the relation 
Tr " Trf!ad = Tr " Tc 
where T r is the adiabatic recovery temperature, i.e. the temperature the wall would 
reach if adiabatic in the absence of film cooling, T rf is the recovery temperature in the 
presence of film cooling, and T c is the coolant temperature, which is the lowest T rf. The 
cooling effectiveness so defined applies to a specific geometrical arrangement of cooling 
holes, and also on the cooling mass flow rate. A set of data for a single row of holes is 
shown in the figure below. The effectiveness decreases downstream of the row of holes, 
and in general increases with cooling flow, at least for the range shown. 
2From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Turbine solidity; mass flow limits; blade temperature</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec28/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>28</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Subjects: Turbine solidity; Mass flow limits; Blade temperature 
 Solidity and aerodynamic loading: 
 
Just as for the compressor, the blade spacing required to assure that the flow directions at the 
exits from the nozzles and the buckets are as intended, is determined by the aerodynamic 
loading limits of the blades.  Instead of the Diffusion Factor that we used to characterize this loading in the compressor, it is usual to define a Zweifel Coefficient  
 
             1   v 1=0 
    V1      V 1 
     r 
     
   
     p     s   r 
   c
x 
    
  
     2 
     
V2      V 2  v 2=-r 
 
    r 
 
   
   !Z"(pp#ps)dx
cxx1x2$
%pt1#p2 
 where x is the axial coordinate, and   p
p = pressure on the pressure side 
  p s = pressure on the suction side 
This is a measure of the pressure difference across the blade divided by the outlet dynamic 
pressure. In the ensuing argument we will relate it to the quantities that define the velocity 
triangle, just as we did for the Diffusion Factor.  
From a tangential momentum balance, if s is the blade spacing and c is the axial chord, 
   
!1w1v 1" #v "2 =cx$x2(pp#p)dx
sxc 
1x
Substituting in the above definition of the Zweifel Coefficient and assuming that p t2=pt1, 
and M2&lt;&lt;1, 
  
116.50 Lecture 28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>v #"w1
2 2sv #2 1 $v #2 !w v ! os   z=1 2=c" 2
2! ; =sin" !  
"V 22! 2! 2
22 2# cxV V 
 
cx v" v"  !Z=2sin#cos11 sin 21
2"#2"$= #2"$1 s v2" v2"
which equals sin 2 2 when v 1=0. 
 
Zweifel's design rule is that loss is minimized for 0.8 &lt;   &lt; 1.0. 
 
Mass flow per unit of annulus area and blade stress:  
Since the pressure and hence density are higher at the inlet to the turbine than at the 
compressor inlet one might think that the mass flow per unit area would not be an 
important factor in the turbine. But it is because for a given blade speed the stress at the 
root of the blade increases with blade length and hence with the annulus area.  
This is readily seen by computing the stress at the blade root. Consider a blade rotating as 
in the figure.  The stress is given by   
   
  
  !
 
This is often quo e that for 
a given blade tip is 
necessary to increase the flow area. 
 Returning to the question of the mass flow per unit area, we can compare stations a &amp; b 
outside the nozzle as shown in the figure.  The mass flow density is given by 
 
   
aVa Ha =  bVb Hb cos b (rH)=$rT 2 r"#T
Flow 
rrdr2 2 2
="#2%rH #=" A
H 2 2 &amp;
ted as the "AN2 limit" on turbines, N being the rpm. One can se
 speed the stress increases as the radius of the root decreases, as 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>V2
b =w2(1+tan2!b) ;V b"2 =w2+(wtan!b#$r)2 
 
so that, after some cancellations, 
 
   V b!2 "V2
b ="#r(#r"2wtan$b) 
 
1wWe now recall that the degree of reaction can be written as  R=1! tan# o w"rb, s e can 2
eliminate the term  w tan b. The result is 
 
Ttr'  -1 3!4     = 1 -   M2R
Tta 2T  
1"!1+ M2
2b
So we find that T tb' is generally lower than T tb, reflecting the fact that the blade is running 
away from the stator flow, but also that it increases as R increases.  Therefore for a given 
blade speed the impulse turbine will have a lower blade temperature than the 50% reaction 
turbine.  This just introduces one more factor in the turbine design. 
 
  
 
 
 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>where H denotes the blade height.  
The temperatures and densities at the two stations are related by 
-11 + M21
T 2ab ! " 
 =   , b T=$ b%   ' ()1
 Ta -1 &amp;1+2 ! # Ma Ta 
2b
and substituting these we find  
M  a#1!+1
+!"1 2 2 (!"1)
$2Mb&amp; H' =bcos)b(A
M2
b%1+!"1 =*)bH=bcos) 
2Ma( Ha (A*)aHb
a
 
 Suppose M b = 1, then we see that as  b increases and therefore cos  b decreases, M a 
decreases, so the mass flow per unit area decreases.  Recalling that we wanted large b in 
order to get large work from the turbine we see that there is a tradeoff between high work and 
low stresses. 
 Rotating blade temperature: 
 
Another matter of interest is the temperature of the rotating blades, since the hotter they are the less stress they can tolerate.  As we shall see, the stagnation temperature relative to the 
moving blades is not equal to that entering the nozzles. 
 
Let T
tb' be the stagnation temperature relative to the rotating blade: 
V !2 2
b V b! "V2
    T tb! =Tb+ = T +b
tb  2cp 2cp
from which 
T !     tb1V !2 "V2
= +b b
Ttb 2cpTb(1#"1 
+ M2
b)2
Now, from velocity triangles,   
 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Turbine cooling; general trends and systems; internal cooling</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec29/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>29</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>2cqw = 2!Ste ["ucp (Tr # Tw )s] $ m ccp (Tw # Tc ) 
m c Tr $ Tw" 2#St e!us Tw $ Te 
For Tr  Tw = 200*K, Tw  Tc = 400*K , and =1, 
m!c $' " 2# (.005 ) 1 
() * .005%&amp; !us 2 
Actually a ratio more nearly .01 is required, because the cooling air is not heated all the 
way to the blade temperature. This is per blade row, not counting casing cooling. For a 
two-stage turbine, including these effects we may need 2-4% of the air flow. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50
Subjects: Turbine cooling; General trends and systems; Internal cooling 
Turbine cooling trends: 
As we have learned from our performance analyses for turbojets and turbofans, the thrust 
per unit of airflow of the aircraft engines increases monotonically with turbine inlet 
temperature ratio, which we have designated as !t . Though it is less obvious, the thermal 
efficiency and specific impulse also increase due to the increase in !t . Thus, there is a 
powerful incentive to increase the turbine inlet temperature. 
The trend of temperature increase with time is shown in the figure: 
In the early period, the increase was limited by metallurgical progress in developing 
oxidation-resistant materials, primarily Nickel and Cobalt based alloys, that could operate 
for long times at high temperatures. Beginning in the mid-60s, the technology of air 
cooling was introduced, and most advancement since then has been due to more refined 
cooling techniques, although the introduction of directionally-solidified and single-crystal 
blade materials has allowed some increase in metal temperature. 
Cooling Systems: The general scheme for air cooling of the hot section of an engine is 
shown in the figure below: 
1From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.Lecture 29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>cqw = #St = fraction of heat flowing thru the blade row which enters the blade.!ucp (Tr " Tw )s 
Here as before c is the blade chord and s is the blade spacing. 
Fortunately, S t is a small number because the boundary layers on the blades are very 
thick compared to the blade chord. In fact S t depends on the details of the boundary layer 
behavior, and of course, is not a constant, but for our purposes here we can think of S t as 
being an average value for the blade surface. To estimate its magnitude we can model the 
blades as flat plates, in which case the local S t is given approximately by:
0.66 (laminar) 2 St = Cf = 
Rex 
.05922 St = Cf =
).2 (turbulent)
(Rex 
where Re x is the Reynolds number based on distance from the leading edge of the plate. 
One important difficulty for turbine cooling arises because transition from laminar to 
turbulent flow occurs at some Reynolds number in the range of 3 !105 to 106 . Looking at 
the expressions for S t we see that for example if the transition occurs at Re x=106, then 
St = 0.66 10-3 (laminar)  
St = 0.037 (turbulent)  
So the heat transfer jumps suddenly by a large factor at the point of transition. 
To get an idea of the magnitude of Re x in an engine let us look at some typical numbers. 
For p t4 = 20 atm,  t = 6, T t = 6(298) = 1788 K, Re x = 3  107/m at M = 1, so for a blade 
that has a chord of 4 cm, Re x based on chord is 1.2  106 and we would expect transition 
on the blade surface. Actually external flow turbulence tends to promote the transition so 
that it will probably occur at a lower value than this. But the exact location of the 
transition is difficult to predict. 
This gives rise to a major problem in scheduling the internal cooling system so that 
internal cooling matches the external heat transfer. 
Internal cooling rate: For the internal cooling flow we model the flow as that through a long thin passage, for 
which 
12Stint. = Cfint = 0.023(ReD ).2 
One important question to be addressed is how much cooling air is required. Forming a 
heat balance such that the heat flux into the blade equals that absorbed by the cooling 
flow, 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>In most all cases the cooling air is drawn from the compressor discharge because it must 
be at a higher pressure than that of the part of the flow path to be cooled. This leads to the 
important condition that the cooling air temperature is the compressor discharge 
temperature. As shown in the diagram, some of the air is used to cool the turbine nozzles, 
by a combination of internal convection cooling and film cooling, processes that will be discussed in detail below. Another portion of the cooling air is transferred onto the rotor 
and used to cool the rotating blades and their supporting disc. Here again a combination 
of internal convection and film cooling is used. 
Internal Convection Cooling: 
In this form of cooling, the blade temperature is maintained below that of the hot gas 
passing through the turbine by a flow of compressor-discharge air through passages 
internal to the blade, as suggested in the diagram. To model this process we must 
therefore model first the heat transfer to the outside of the blade from the hot gas, then the 
heat transfer on the inside to the coolant. The objective in cooling design usually is to 
maintain the blade temperature nearly constant in the presence of a variation of the heat 
flux to its surface from the hot gas. 
External Heat Transfer: Let us look first at the heat transfer to the outside of blade. We can write it as 
qw = St[!ucp (Tr " Tw )] 
where u is the mass flow density in the hot gas, T r is the recovery temperature and T w 
is the wall temperature. The definition of T r is the temperature the wall would reach if 
adiabatic, and it is close to the external stagnation temperature. S t is defined by this 
relation, but what is its physical significance? We have 
2From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rocket staging; range of aircraft; climb &amp; acceleration</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>We define the Specific Impulse by: 
F=gI m.
where m.
 is the fuel mass flow, so that m. dm = - .  Note that the inverse of I is the dt
Specific Fuel Consumption, SFC, in appropriate units. From this definition and the force
balances we obtain 
mg dm=!gIL/D dt
dm D=!dtm LI
If we assume D/L and I are constant (Here we are implying models for both the 
propulsion system and the aircraft), then  
m(t) D!n =!tm0 LI
The range R = u 0t where u 0 is the flight velocity, so 
L mR=u0I!n0
D m (R)
where m(R) is the aircraft mass at the range R.  This is the Breguet Range Equation. 
As in the case of the rocket, it is useful to divide the mass m 0 into structural, 
payload, engines and fuel:
m0=mstruct+meng+mfuel+mpay
or 1 = m'
struct+m'eng+m'
fuel+m'
pay
If the fuel is expended at R, 
m(R)=m'+m'+m'=mstruct eng pay 1!m'
fuel
0
For a fixed m'structand m'eng, we can trade off between m' '
pay and mfuel, hence between 
Range and Payload.  If we define: 
m'empty=m'+m'
struct eng
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>we can write
m(R)=m'mmempty+'
pay
0
and
R=u0IL!n1
D m'
empty+m'pay
from which
R
m'
pay=e!U0I(L/D)!m'
empty
(quite similar to what we obtained for a rocket).
From this we can construct a Range vs. Payload chart.  As an example, suppose
m'
empty=0.7; u0IL=(300m)(4000 s)(15) =1.8x107mD s
R(km)
m'
pay=e!
1.8x104!0.7
00'mpay
R(km)
1.8 x 104
Note this is not a straight line, although it is close.
Climb &amp; Acceleration
Sometimes we are more interested in climb and maneuver rather than cruise, as 
for fighter aircraft.  Then an Energy Approach is most helpful..1 .2 .3 .357 .4.3
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>#V
and    (m2
!pay)2=(m!t)c
f)2"(ms!"
r2=e "$ 
 
But the total velocity increment !V=!V1+!V2 is prescribed, and so we obtain  
 
(mpay)2=("V
e!1 "V!"V
c!#)(e!1
c!#)
  (m0)1   
"V "V "V
(1 !"V
=e!!#e!1
c+e!c c)+#2
 It is easy to se that this is maximum when 
!V1=!V" !V1, i.e., when !V2=!V1. If this 
staging is selected, the overall payload fraction is 
  
(m )"V
    (pay 2)=(e!2c
m0)opt !#)2 (1
This derivation can easily be extended to N&gt;2 stages, but things are more complicated if 
the structural fractions or the jet velocities are different among stages. 
 Range of Aircraft  
 For aircraft, the simplest measure of performance is cruise fuel consumption and 
the resulting range.  At one time this was also the critical performance measure for transports, bombers and fighters.  This is less true now for transports because the ranges accessible with modern engines and airframes are in the order of 8,000 miles.  For 
bombers aerial refueling extends the range to the extent that again range is no longer such 
a challenge (although refueling is quite expensive).  Range is still important for fighters because the requirements for high speed and maneuverability conflict with those for long range. 
 
Consider an aircraft in straight, level flight  
 
 
    F=DL mg= =  L/D L /D
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 Lecture 2 
 
Subjects: Rocket staging; Range of aircraft; Climb &amp; Aceleration 
 
1) Rocket Staging  
The reason for staging is to avoid having to accelerate empty tanks. Assume for simplicity only two stages; one does not want to stage either too early (and then carry a heavy second stage tank) or too late (and carry a heavy first stage tank for a long time). It can be shown that for ideal symmetrical stages (same specific impulse, same structural 
fractions), the velocity increment should be divided equally between the stages, and this 
is a good first cut for more general cases.  In its simplest form, staging consists of just replacing the payload of the first stage by a 
complete second stage, which in turn has its own payload, as shown in the sketch. 
 
     
 
We go back to the rocket equation, and neglect gravity losses. Write for short !=ms"tr, 
and assume this structural fraction is the same for both stages (in each case the structural mass is normalized by the initial mass of that stage); assume also that the jet velocity c is 
the same for both stage engines (although typically the first stage engine will be larger and have a bigger thrust). The final payload is given by  
    
(mpay)2=(m'
pay)2(m0)2 
and we also have  
V
   ("
m0)2=(mf)1!(mstr)1
1=(m)1(e!c
0 !#)  
1Payload
Stage 2
Stage 1
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Suppose the aircraft is climbing at angle ! from the horizontal.  The equation of motion 
along the path is
mdu0=F!D!mgSin"dt
udu0 (F!D)u0
0 = !gu 
dt m0Sin"
but u0Sindh!= , so it follows thatdt
gdh+udu0 (F!D)u0dE
0 = "dt dt m dt
Were we define a Total Energy E ghu2
= +0 per unit mass.2
If we had a simple model for F and D as a function of u 0 and h we could integrate this as
we did for the rocket.  But, as we shall see later in the semester these dependencies are
much more complex for the aircraft engine than for the rocket. Thus for the two classesof engine we have these quite different thrust characteristics:
Rocket Engine
- Nearly independent of its environment, atmosphere and speed.Aircraft Engine  - Strongly dependent on flight speed and atmosphere.
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ablative cooling</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 Lecture 15
 
Subject:  Ablative cooling
By ablation we mean the recession of a surface due to heating, usually by a hot gas.  
It is the key process for 
a)  Re-entry heat shieldsb)  Solid propellant nozzlesc)  Rocket case insulationd)  Fire-proofing skyscrapers' structures
Consider a hot gas flowing over a surface which can
1)  evaporate, and2)  whose vapor can react with the external flow
 
  
A heat balance at the surface gives 
   q
s = q w - (v) w hw    (1)
 where the heat of ablation, h
w=hw  h s, in J/kg,  can include a heat of vaporization 
and decomposition and q w is the heat flux from the fluid boundary layer.
 
Let us assume that it is useful to write
u2e   q w =  eueSt (H e +   - H2w)
 where H
w is the total enthalpy for the wall material at the wall temperature, and
He=cpgTge is the gas specific enthalpy at the temperature Tge just outside the 
boundary layer . Notice that this generalizes our previous expression for heattransfer by replacing the total enthalpy for the static enthalpy; this is of general validity for high-speed flows. By energy conservation in the core flow, 
u2
He+e=c2pgTc.
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Equations (1) or (2) can be used to select the proper thickness of the ablative 
(sacrificial) layer, once the burn time is given:  !Abl =r tb. 
Now let us look at some numerical examples, to show the magnitudes of the terms:  
JouleA. For carbon, Hf
g = 172 kcal/gmole=60 x 106   kg
172000 cal            h w - hs =   = 15,000    12 g
320 c1.2 8, pg! !2500 J/Kg/K , s  2000 kg/m3kg/m3 
 0.2 20
  and assume T
c-Tw=1,000K. 
 
p p Now  eue  =! " 0.65  
RT RT
 
105(pcatm) kg    
8.32 x103  58 (p c atm) m2  s
(3000)20
 Taking pc=100 atm and St=0.001, we then calculate 
 
2,500 *1,000 r! "58"100"0.001 =1.2"10#4m/s=0.12 mm /s 2,000 "60"106
         So in 100 sec., the change in the surface is  12 mm = 1.2 cm.  
 This is of the right magnitude, but most important is to see what it depends on.  B. For rubber h
w-hs  10,000 cal/gm mole. For an approximate empirical 
formula C 10 H20 , this gives per unit mass 
 
10000 10000 cal Joule      =    70   280,000   120 + 20 140 g kg
  Also c
p  1 cal/g  4,000 Joule/kg K  
  So now we would get about 100 times the regression rate for carbon. In this 
case though, if the rubber is used in the casing of a solid rocket engine then 
eue &lt;&lt; 
1(eue)throat , maybe by   , so the net regression may end up being similar. 100
 
     
  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Quantitatively, Lees says, for small surface blowoff effect, 
St B v)
     = c1.2 8, 320 (
! !2500 J/Kg/Kw, B =   Sto eB!1pg 0.2 20 eueSto
while Sutton quotes Lees as giving for the larger blowoffs 
St   = 1.27 B-.77 5 &lt; B &lt; 100 Sto
These give the same trends, but somewhat different numbers. We adopt here Lees 
!sr St Bformulation: We had =", so B=! =!!eueSB 
t Sto e"1
 
   or eB!1="  #  B =!  n(1+") 
 
+-% cpg(Tc"Tw)(/
so finally,   !sr=,!n'1-+ !u S    (1) 
-.&amp;cs(Tw"T*0 e e to
 w#)+$hw)-1
and then 
% c(T"T) ( q (pg
s=(!sr)csT"c w
wTw#)=!eueSt0cs(Tw"Tw#)!n'1+  
 &amp;cs(T* (1)
w"Tw#)+$hw)
mAt the throat, (!eu!p
e)= =c
t *. This is where qw, and hence r, is maximum.  
 Atc
Numerically, one often sees !hw&gt;&gt;cs(Tw"Tw#), and also ! &lt;&lt;1. This would leave 
us with the approximations 
 
cpg(T  !r"c#Tw)
s !eueSto      (2) $hw
     St!Sto      (3) 
 
and going back to the surface heat balance, qs!o, i.e., to the first order, the heat 
does not penetrate below the ablating layer, which is as intended. 
   
 
  
  
 
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Then the heat transfer to the solid is  
u
2e q s =  eueSt (H e +   - H w) - (v) w (hw - h )2s 
 Since q
s is the heat flux available to heat the wall, it is clear that the evaporation 
reduces the wall heat flux, i.e. the heat flux into the solid.  
Now what determines (v)
w?  First note that (v) w = r s where r is our "recession 
rate". Consider a "thermal wave" propagating into the solid. We will now work in 
the receding frame, in which we can assume a steady situation. If the recession rate 
is r(m/s), we see solid material moving at !y="r, and convecting a heat flux . Then, 
if there is no local heat generation, 
d dT    (!ks!r"scsT)=0    dy dy
dTwhich integrates to ks +r!scsT=const .=r!c T , or dys s w"
d(T!T k w")r + (T!Tw")=o  (! =s, heat diffusivity, in m2/s) dy # "scs
 
r
    T!Tw" =(Tw!Tw)e!y#
"  
 
dT" rThe heat flux at at y = o is qs=!ks$ =ks (Tw!Tw&amp;), giving dy# y=o%
 
  qs=!scsr(Tw"Tw#),   or !srq=s cs(Tw"Tw#)
     
So returning to our expression for the heat flux to the wall,    
     qs=!eueStcpg(Tc"Tw)"!sr#hw 
    
!srcs(Tw"Tw#) 
 
!  euecpg(Tc"Tw) c (T"T)!r  !sr= S! , s=pg c w%&amp; cs(Tw"Tw#)+$ht
w !eueStcs(Tw"Tw#)+$hw
 
You may compare this to Sutton pg. 510 Eq. 15-6  
Now how does (v)
w influence St
wall with u=0, so it will tend to retard the flow near the wall.  ? Physically, we know that the vapor comes off the  
 
 
  
 
 
 
 
 
 
   
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Engine structures; centrifugal stresses; engine arrangements</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec32/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>32</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
Subjects discussed: Engine structures; Centrifugal stresses; Engine arrangements 
Centrifugal stresses and design of discs By disc we refer to the rotating structural members that carry the rotating blades in 
the turbom
achine.  They are unusual as structural members in that they must 
withstand very large tensile stresses generated by centrifugal forces. Their mass is a large part of the total mass of an engine, and they set the limit on blade speed, so an understanding of their characteristics is essential to appreciating the performance limits of modern aircraft engines. 
We begin by describing the state of stress of a small volume element of a disc. The net outwards elastic force on the element is  
d (! zrd" )dr #! z dr d" = ! r dz drd" dr dr 
and, by design, in order to utilize the material most efficiently, we wish to keep the 
stress level  constant throughout the disc. The force balance is then 
!z" 2r2d#dr = $% r(dz )drd#dr 
1 dz "(# 2r) 
z dr = !$ 
"# 2r2 
z = ct. x exp(! )2$ 
Add a rim and consider the radial force balance on a slice of this rim, as in the 
bottom left sketch. There are B blades, not necessarily at the same stress as the disc, and their centrifugal pull is smoothly distributed around the periphery: 
1From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.Lecture 32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>$ bH AbB!oWoTo (rHd" )# 2rH + d" = $ zHrHd" + $WoTod" 2% 
Rim centrifugal Centrifugal Support from Radial force 
force pull from blades rim stress from hoop stress 
" 0# 2rH 2 + (2B
$ )! bH (Ab /WoTo )! = (2)zHrH1+ WoTo 
So the disc supports the rim, and reduces its stress.  Now we add an inner rim; it 
supports the disc and there are no blade loads, so in this case 
!IWITI (rId" )# 2rI = $% zIrId" + %WITId" 
"# 2rI 2 
! = (3)zIrI1$ WITI 
For the blades themselves, the full blade mass is supported by the root stress: 
" b# 2 rT! bH = $ Ab (r)dr (4)
rH AbH 
So how do we design a disc 
a) From aerodynamics, choose r T, rH/rT, B, A b(r) W o 
b) Set permissible stresses  and bH (rT may then be limited by (4)) 
c) Choose a T o and get Z H from (2) 
d) Choose an r I and get Z I from (1) 
e) Get W ITI from (3) 
Engine arrangements 
As noted, engines are unusual amongst engineering structures in that such a
large fraction of their total mass is rotating at high speeds.  This large rotatingmass must be supported on bearings so as to maintain quite close clearances between the blade tips and the stationary casings, on the order of 1 mm on a 
rotor of 1 m diameter, or one part in 10
3. At the same time of course the 
stationary structure must be as light as possible.  
All existing engines use ball and roller bearings to support the rotating
assemblies, called "spools".  These are shown schematically in the figure: 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT 
 Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.
The function of the squeeze films will be discussed in the next lecture.   
 Ordinarily each rotating spool is supported by one ball bearing that positions itaxially and also absorbs radial loads, and one or more roller bearings that accept radial loads but allow axial movement to accommodate thermal expansion and structural deformations.  Two-spool support arrangements are shown schematically in the figure: 
From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT 
 Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.
The top arrangement uses just two bearings, one ball and the other roller, to support each of the two spools. It is compact and at least in principle relatively light. The lower arrangement uses three bearings on the inner spool, one ball and two roller, and four bearings on the outer (low speed) spool, one ball andthree roller. Both of these arrangements have advantages and both have been used successfully in high-bypass commercial transport engines.  This is just onemore illustration of the fact that design solutions are not unique. 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Aircraft propulsion, configuration and components</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>AIRCRAFT PROPULSION CONFIGURATION AND COMPONENTS  
Notes by Fredric Ehrich  are unavailable due to copyright restrictions. They are based on the following 
references.   
 
Cited References  
 
Ehrich, F.F., 1981, Turbine Propulsion, Turbofan, Encyclopedia of Science and Technology , McGraw -Hill, NY  
Ehrich, F.F., 1990, Energy Conversion: Jet Engine, Encyclopaedia Britannica, ed. 15  
Ehrich, F.F., 1991, Turbine Propulsion, Turbofan, Turbojet, Turboprop, Turboramjet, Aircraft Engine 
Performance, Encyclopedia of Science and Technology , McGraw -Hill, NY  
Fehr, V.S., 2003, Aircraft Engine Structures: Load Paths &amp; Mount Design, Unpublished lecture, P&amp;W,  E. Hartford, CT  
Fowler, T.W., 1989, Jet Engine Propulsion Systems for Engineers , GE Aircraft Engines, Cincinnati, OH  
GE Aircraft Engines, 1992A, CF34 Turbofan Installation Manual , SEI -567, Lynn, MA  
GE Aircraft Engines, 1992B, CF34 -3A1 Training Guide , SEI -765, Lynn, MA  
Hawkins, R.C. , 1984, Unducted fan for Tomorrows Subsonic Propulsion, Aerospace America , October, pp. 52- 55 
Kent, W., 1950, Mechanical Engineers Handbook , Wiley, NY, vol. 2, ed. 12  
Korthals -Altes, S.W., 1987, Will the Aerospace Plane Work, Techno1ogy Review , Jan., pp 43 -51  
McMahon, P.J., 1971, Aircraft Propulsion , Pitman, London, p 260  
Ray, M. G. and Browne, J. L., 1980, T700 Engine Integral Inlet Separator, 6th European Rotorcraft and Powered 
Lift Forum , No. 37, Univ. of Bristol, UK  
Sweetman, B., 1986, Aerospace Planes and Trans -Atmospheric Vehicles, Interavia , March, pp. 305 -308  
Treager, I. E., 1979, Aircraft Gas Turbine Engine Technology , McGraw -Hill, NY, ed. 2  
 General References  
 
Bent, R. D., and McKinley, J. L., 1985, Aircraft Powerplants , McGraw -Hill, NY, pp 429 ff  
Kerrebrock, J.L., 1978, Aircraft E ngines and Gas Turbines , MIT Press, Cambridge, MA  
Rolls Royce plc, 1986, The Jet Engine , Derby, UK, ed. 4  
Taylor, J. W. R., 1987, Janes All the Worlds Aircraft</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Jet noise, turbomachinery noise</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec37/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>37</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>+iB(" #$ Rt)
incidence ! e 
where B is the number of moving blades. It follows that 
i[(V ! B)"! B# Rt]
p' stator = e 
So the Effective Speed of Rotation of the disturbance is 
= (d" ! Eff dt )const . phase = B! R 
V # B 
In early engines there was a tendency to make V  B and they were very noisy. Now 
we use the rule V = 2B + 1, so that the rotor-stator interaction is no more likely to generate propagating disturbances than is the rotor rotation itself. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
Subjects discussed: Jet noise, Turbomachinery noise 
Having reviewed the mechanisms for noise propagation and the three types of 
acoustic sources - Monopoles, Dipoles and Quadrupoles, we can now examine aircraft engines as sources of noise. 
Jet Noise 
We begin with jet noise because historically it was the principal source of concern
with the introduction of jet transports. Jet noise is generated by the turbulentmixing of the high speed exhaust jet with the ambient air.  We can think of the mixing region as a region of strong turbulent flow, 
that can be modeled as a random array of Quadrupoles, since there is no mass 
source, and no force in the fluid. 
In a turbulent jet, in order of magnitude P ~ !ou2 (u being the jet velocity) and
the size of the fluctuating regions is some fraction of the diameter D of the jet. 
Similarly, the spacing d of these regions must also be some factor times D. The 
wavenumber k = !  can be estimated by noting that ! ~ u /D. We then have,ao
(!ou2D)2 " u u8D2 
Pq ~ $ D%
' 4
~ !o (17)5!oao #Dao &amp; ao 
The striking feature is the scaling of this radiated power with the 8th power of the
jet velocity (a result due to Lighthill (1963). To compare it to the jet kinetic power, 
note that 
Pjet ~ (!ouD2 )u2 = !ou3D2 (18) 
so that 
5Pq 
Pjet ~  ! $ u =  M 5 
jet (19) #" &amp;% ao 
1From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.Lecture 37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>From the Cartesian wave equation (Lecture 36), a plane wave propagating in the !
direction of the wave vector k has the general form 
"i(#t"kxx"kyy )] p! = Re[ p e (23) 
provided kx, ky and  satisfy the dispersion relation, that is obtained by 
substituting (23) into the wave equation itself: 
!2 = a02(kx 2 + ky 2) (24) 
Also, the moving boundary condition represented in the figure above is of the form 
(23), with x=0, ky=(2/s) and ! = 2
#" 
s vs . Substituting these  and ky in (24) and 
solving for kx, 
2! ( vs )2 #1 (25) kx =  " s a0 
and we can see that kx is real only if vs&gt;a0 , i.e., only if the source is moving at a 
supersonic speed . The direction of the sound waves is given by 
! = tan"1(ky /kx ) = sin"1(a0/vs) (26) 
namely, the Mach angle at the wall Mach number. 
For a source moving at subsonic speed, the sound is in fact exponentially attenuated 
over a distance of the order of s/2. Physically, the reason is that for a supersonic
source the waves from the infinity of pressure peaks and troughs on the wall 
interfere constructively with each other when their direction is as in (26). For asubsonic source there is no such direction, and interference is always destructive. 
In the case of turbomachinery, the supersonic relative velocity can come from
 two 
sources: 
a) Supersonic tip speed 
b) Subsonic tip speed, but interacting blade rows 
To understand the second situation, consider a rotor operating in the vicinity of a stator. The stator blades produce a pressure variation 
iV" p' stator ! (incidence )e
where V is the number of stationary vanes. 
The disturbances from the rotor are periodic in rotor coordinates, so 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>This very strong sensitivity to jet velocity (or Mach number) is one of the 
significant disadvantages of the pure turbojet as compared to the high bypass turbofan (the other being its lower propulsive efficiency, although that disappears at a high enough flight Mach number). 
Turbomachinery noise 
Vibrations of lifting blades, or periodic passage of lifting blades past the
observer, produce dipole-type radiation, which emits a power given by Eq. (13). 
Estimating in this case ro ~ d ~ c (blade chord), k ~ ! ~ u , where u is now theao aoc 
blade speed, and P = !ou2 , the power radiated per blade is 
6 2 3P ~ ! u c / a (20)bl o o 
The force on one blade is of the order of Fbl ~ !ou2cH ~ !ou2c2 , and so the
acoustic efficiency is 
3Pbl u 3!bl.noise = ~ $" 
'% 
= MT (21)Fblu #ao &amp; 
This is noise generated, but the duct, even with no special absorbing design, 
attenuates the sound, and in fact, forbids propagation for the lower range of 
frequencies. The frequency is here related to the blade Mach number MT and the 
number B of blades: 
!rT B!rot rT= = BMT (22)ao ao 
and so MT must be higher than a certain threshold for blade noise to propagate. 
In order to understand this phenomenon let us look at the simple case of sound 
emitted by a moving source, meaning that the pressure perturbation on a given surface x=0 is a sliding sinusoid, moving a velocity v
s in the y-direction. 
Y 
(-)  vs 
s X 
p
(+) 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Aircraft engine modeling; turbojet engine</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Our tasks in estimating F are then 
.a)  to estimate m o 
ue b)  to estimate     . uo
 
Many of the engines we deal with will have 2 exhaust streams.  In this case we apply (3) separately to each stream.  Let us begin with a Turbojet Engine, shown schematically below, and break the  engine into a set of Components with functions as follows. 
Diffuser (d) - Brings airflow from the flight Mach number M o, to the axial 
Mach number M 2, required by the compressor.  
 
 Compressor (c) Raises temperature and pressure of airflow, as nearly  isentropically as possible.   Combustor (b) Raises temperature, nearly at  constant pressure.   Turbine (t) Drops temperature and pressure, as nearly isentropically as  possible.   Afterburner (a) Heats air again, at nearly constant pressure ( to a higher  temperature than the turbine can tolerate without cooling).  
Nozzle (n) Expands hot gases to produce a high-velocity jet. Station  7  denotes the sonic throat. 
  We first note that for this engine,  
2Station Numbers
Diffuser pdCompressor TurbineNozzle
BurnerAfterburner papc tcpt tt
pb0 1 2 3 45 6
uomfma
7e
ue
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare. 
Adapted from Figure 1.4 Kerrebrock, Jack L. (1992). Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines (2nd Edition). MIT Press.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>F 2 #t
m  = [#a !"1o$c$t"1]( ) "M
0 0 #o$0  (8) 
c
 
So far we have not made this peculiar to the turbojet engine, because we have not included the relationship between the compressor and turbine.  The fact that distinguishes the turbojet engine from other engines we may consider later is that the turbine power equals the compressor power, so  
   T (  - 1) = T  (1 -  ) toc t4 t
 

   o = 1 -  ( - 1)      (9) tc
t
 
So finally for the Turbojet Engine  
   
F 2
. [#= #t"#o($c"1)"t]"Mo  (10) 
moa !"1 #o$
oc
 
.We are also interested in the fuel consumption. We get m  from a combustor heat f
balance, 
. . C Tp o    m  = m   f o ( - h toc)      (10b)
so that the fuel-specific impulse, 
 I=F/ (m!fg) is 
 
    I = (hao)(F/m  oao)   (11) 
gCpTo(!t"!o#c)
 
Discussion on nozzle choking   Eq. (6b) was the condition for the exhaust to be at   
least sonic, with
pe!p0 or for the throat to be sonic. It involves both the compressor 
and the turbine temperature ratios, but we can eliminate the turbine ratio using the 
shaft balance (Eq. (9)), so that the condition is now 
"! " (1#c#1
0c )%+1$    (12) 
! 2
When the equal sign applies, we have Me=1 while still pe =p0. This limit can be 
rearranged into a quadratic equation for c : 
   !2 $
c"(#+1)+1#!c+ = 0 
2#0
with the two solutions 
    +,"#+1!c =  (#+1)2$+1#"  
2 2 2 #0 
 
 
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
 Subject: Aircraft Engine Modeling; Turbojet engine.  All aircraft engines are Heat Engines, in that they use the thermal energy derived from combustion of fossil fuels to produce mechanical energy in the form of kinetic energy of an exhaust jet.  The excess of momentum of the exhaust jet over that of the incoming airflow produces thrust.  In studying these devices we thus employ two types of modeling.  
a)  Thermodynamic, in which the production of mechanical energy from thermal is studied by the approaches of Thermodynamics. Here the change in thermodynamic state of the air as it passes through the engine is studied.  The physical configuration of the engine is not identified.  Rather the processes are specified, by pressure and temperature ratios. 
  b)  Fluid mechanical, in which we relate the changes in pressure,  temperature and velocity of the air, to the physical characteristics of the  engine.  With these ideas in mind, let's first outline a general approach to the modeling of aircraft propulsion systems. Our general expression for thrust , in which we have a main interest, is 
. .   F = m 
eue - m ouo + A e(pe - po)  (1) 
.
. . mf where m e = (1 + f) m o  ; f =   .mo
We write this more conveniently in dimensionless form as  
F u
e Aepope     = (1 + f)   - 1 + (  - 1)  (2) . uo . pm uo
o o mouo 
 In our modeling of the aircraft engine we will often assume p
e = p o, and usually take 
f&lt;&lt;1, so, using the flight Mach number M0=u0/a0, this expression becomes simply 
F ue     = M o [   - 1]    (3) . umoao o
but it should be recalled that just as for the rocket engine, the behavior of the nozzle can be somewhat more complex. In practice the deviation from ideal expansion becomes important for supersonic flight. In particular, there can be sonic or supersonic underexpansion, with an exhaust pressure p &gt;p . This happens in particular with purely convergent nozzles, that are comm
e
only0
 used in subsonic 
engines, when they operate off-design. It can also happen in a variable-geometry  supersonic nozzle that is not correctly adapted to the ambient pressure.   
1Lecture 18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>It can be verified that c must be between these two roots to ensure Me!1 . The +
c is 
normally very high, so the relevant condition is &gt; -
c . Values of -
c are tabulated 
below: 
 
 =4              =6              =8 
M0=0 1.296 1.253 1.234 
M0=0.85 1.066 1.059 1.056 
 
These are fairly low compressor ratios, even for stationary engine conditions, so the assumption of a choked nozzle is a good one in general. Whether or not the nozzle is also matched is a different question, as noted before.   
 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>u    eM=eTe uoMoTo
 
It is most efficient to find the exit Mach number and temperature by keeping track of the stagnation temperatures and pressures through the several components.  The following procedure works for all aircraft engines, so it's worth your paying some attention to the procedure itself, as well as the result. We employ the defining relations for the stagnation properties:  
# !"1    Tt=T1+ M2% 
$ &amp;        
2
!
!"    p p# 11 M2% !"1
t= + $ 2 &amp; 
 It is very helpful to define a set of symbols that represent explicitly ratios of these stagnation properties and distinguish them from the static or thermodynamic properties of the gas, because in general it is the stagnation properties that most conveniently represent the effect of the components on the fluid as it flows through the engine. Thus, 
 
 
 A ratio of p 's will be denoted by the symbol ; t
 A ratio of T 's will be denoted by the symbol t. 
 A ratio of a stagnation temperature to the ambient static temperature T  o
 will be denoted  and   A ratio of a stagnation pressure to the ambient static pressure p  will be o
 denoted . 
So for the flow upstream of the engine,  
T 1    to !=1"+ M2#
o 2o=To 
 
p 1    to !=(1"+ M2 !"1
o)!
=#p 2o 
o
The turbine-inlet temperature is represented by 
T    t4=!t 
To
or, alternatively, by  
    T!=t4T=t4!=t 
Tt2Tt0!0
which is more convenient for scaling purposes, since it relates two engine total 
temperatures, a ratio that is often independent of ambient conditions. For the compressor and for the turbine (both ideal by assumption),   
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>pt3=!c,Tt3
c;p T=" !c="# #
p T#$1 #
c   t5=! "1
p$
t,t5=Tt;!t="t 
t2 t2 t4 t4
 
Now let us use this system of notation to develop expressions for the Thrust and Specific Impulse of the Turbojet Engine.  We begin by tracking the changes of stagnation temperature and pressure through the engine.  Temperature accounting:  
   T =T(1+
!"1M2
te e 2 e)=To#o$c$b$t=To#t$t   (4) 
 
Pressure accounting:  
   
p =p(1+!"1M2)!
!"1
te e 2 e =po#o$c$b$t    (5) 
 
From (5), if p  = p (ideally expanded nozzle) and if    1 e o b
   (1+!"1M2)=(# $ $ $ )!"1
!
2 e o c b t =%o&amp;c&amp;t    (5b) 
 
where the second equality assumes that the compression and expansion processes are reversible adiabatics. From this we find an expression for the exit Mach number,  
    
M2 2
e= [# $ $ "1]    (6) 
!"1o c t
It is very important to realize that although this expression for the exit Mach number 
is written in terms of temperature ratios, it comes from the pressure changes in the engine.  This is a general result, namely that the exit Mach number depends on the ratio of jet stagnation pressure to the ambient pressure, not at all on the temperature.  
If the exhaust is to be choked (
Me!1), we must have, from (6),  
2(#0$c$t"1)%1    (6b) 
!"1
which may not be satisfied at low power and/or low Mach number. 
 From (4) 
    Te !t" !=t
To1#$1=t !=       
+ M2!o"c"c
2e
So far these are quite general expressions applicable to any gas stream.  
substituting them in our expressions for the velocity ratio and the thrust we have  
2[#o$c$t"1](#t)
u    e!"1 # $=o c   (7) 
u0 Mo
 Finally, the thrust per unit of mass flow (times the speed of sound to make it dimensionless) is   
 
 
 
 
 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Exhaust nozzles</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec23/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>pte pte= = (1+ ! 
2 "1 Me 2)!!
"1 
po pe 
ptewhere = ! 0 " c " tp0 
and the area ratio is then set by this Mach number, 
Ae 1 [1+ !"1 Me 2
] ! +1
2 2(!"1) = A7 Me ! +1 
2 
Since pte/p0 involves 0, Me for this matched condition does depend on flight Mach 
number, and so does then Ae/A7. This is important for supersonic engines, as we 
discuss below. 
These relations taken together serve to define the geometry of an ideally expanded 
nozzle. If the nozzle is not ideally expanded, the behavior is quite like that of the rocket nozzle at off-design conditions, as discussed earlier. 
Effects of nozzle mismatching: Subsonic vs. supersonic 
We can use Eqs. (15) and (18) of Lecture 19(b) to calculate the thrust of engines whose nozzles are respectively pressure-matched or truncated at the sonic point. We illustrate this for two different engine designs, one subsonic and one supersonic: 
Case 1: M0=0.85 (0=1.1445) 
Case 2: M0=2  (0=1.8)  
For both cases, we take t=6.25 and M2=0.6 (or m2 = 0.8416 ). We also assume the 
" t compressor ratio is that which gives maximum thrust in each case ( !c = /" 0 ).
The results are shown below: 
M0 c t AThroat/A2 Ae/A2 (!2 )Matched (!2 )Truncated 
0.85 2.1844 0.7831 0.2658 0.2700 0.9682 1.4991 
2 1.3889 0.8880 0.7093 0.7190 0.9682 0.7666 
There is little effect (8%) on thrust for the subsonic nozzle when the nozzle is truncated at its throat, but the effect is a 26% thrust reduction in the supersonic case. This is why such engines carry an adjustable convergent-divergent nozzle. 
Additional Requirements: 
The exhaust nozzle may have to meet a number of other requirem
ents.  Some are: 
a) Variable area for afterburning, to increase throat area in proportion to the square root of the temperature after afterburning: 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
Subject: Exhaust nozzles 
Like the inlet, the nozzle can range from very simple to quite complex.  A simple fixed-area convergent form
 usually suffices for subsonic aircraft except when jet 
noise suppression is required, while a complex variable-area convergent-divergent device is essential for adequate perform
ance in supersonic aircraft.  In either case, 
the functions of the nozzle are two: 
a) Provide the required throat area to match the mass flow and exit conditions of the engine. 
b) Efficiently expand the high-pressure, high-temperature gases at the engine exhaust to atmospheric pressure, converting the available thermal energy to kinetic energy. 
Throat Area: 
The required throat area is determined by conservation of mass. We had fromLecture 20
 
pt 2 A2m = !m2 RTt 2 
and if the throat (station 7) is choked, 
m = ! pt 7 A7 = ! pt 5 A7 
RTt 7 RTt 5 
" pt 5 "#1 Tt 5= (!c!t ) and Equating and using = !"t , we can calculate pt 2 Tt 2 
A7 m2(M2)= " " +1A2 !c "#1 !t 2("#1) $ 
The ratios in the expression for A7/A2 are determined by cycle analysis, as outlined 
previously, so from this expression we can find the nozzle area ratio as a function of the engine parameters.  As we have seen in our discussion of the matching of components, once the nozzle area is set, the operating point of the engine depends 
only on the turbine temperature ratio . 
Exit Area : 
The ratio of exit area to throat area required for ideal expansion can be found
from the usual compressible channel flow relations.  Thus the exit Mach number is set by the stagnation pressure of the jet and the ambient pressure 
1Lecture 23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.
 
Such nozzles have been built in a number of forms. At the top is the relatively simple type used on the F-111 and F-15 engines, which have top flight Mach numbers of the order of 2. At the bottom is the type used on the SR-71, which reaches 3.5 or thereabouts.  b) Noise suppression  As we shall see in Lecture 37, the principal way to decrease jet noise is to lower thejet velocity for a given thrust. The turbofan is the most efficient way to do this, but for some applications it is not practical to use a fan.  In this case there is the desire to increase the mass flow rate of the jet, by mixing in additional air that lowers the velocity for a given total momentum.  One way to do this is the lobed mixer:   
 
 
 
 
3From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
 Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.
Lobed mixers are also used sometimes in turbofans to help equalize the core and bypass stream velocities, and hence increase performance (by 3-4%). The improvement is, however, less than if the velocity changes were isentropic.  
 c) Thrust-vectoring, as for advanced VTOL aircraft.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rotordynamics of the jet engine</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec38/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>38</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>ROTORDYNAMICS OF THE JET ENGINE: ROTOR VIBRATION IN HIGH -SPEED ROTATING 
MACHINERY 
 
Notes by Fredric Ehrich  are unavailable due to copyright restrictions. They are based on the following 
referen ce.
 
 
Ehrich,
 F.F., (Editor).  Handbook of Rotordynamics . 2nd edition.  Krieger Publishing Co., 1999.  
http://www.krieger -publishing.com/html/stackengineering_55.html</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Nozzle flow of reacting gases</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 Lecture 12
Subject: Nozzle flow of reacting gases
In the last two lectures we discussed the phenomena that occur in the combustor, and how to 
estimate the properties of the gas in the (near) stagnation state there. Suppose now that we
have determined the composition of the gases in the rocket chamber, and we wish to compute
the flow through the nozzle, taking account of chemical reactions.
There are three things that we must account for, that were not included in the simple model
based on ideal gas behavior.  The first is that the composition of the gas is not necessarily 
constant in the flow, so that all the properties that are composition dependent must be treated as variables along the flow direction.  These include the specific heats, the gas constant R and 
the ratio of specific heats  .  Second, the sum of the thermal enthalpy and the kinetic energy is
no longer constant because there can be exchange of chemical energy and thermal energy. 
But if the enthalpy is defined as in the previous two lectures, i.e., including in it the chemica l 
enthalpy of formation, then the sum of it and the kinetic energy is indeed conserved.Finally, because of this energy exchange between chemical and kinetic, there can be a change
in the entropy of the flow. Fortunately we can neglect this entropy change in some important
special cases, as will be explained. To take these effects into account quantitatively we may proceed as follows:
 
The chamber condition is specified by T
c, pc and the mole (y i), or mass (x i), fractions of the
various chemical constituents.  As explained in the last two lectures we can compute all thethermodynamics properties of the gas per unit mass at chamber conditions:
Hc=!xiH!
i ;   Hi=(!hi(Tc)+Hfi) /Mi
TdT pS Si
c=!xi i Si="cpi !RTiln (S
Trr
where it will be recalled that x i is the mass fraction of species i and therefore
!xi=1 
Notice also that each enthalpy Hi is now per unit mass, and so is Hc.
 
To deal with the flow we note first that energy conservation for the gas flow gives
u2
Hc = H(T,p) + 2     (1)
which replaces the ideal gas energy equation
u2
(cpTc = cpT + 2 )  pi, cpi per unit mass)
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>xy
i=iMi; yx
!yiMi=i/Mi
i !xi/Mi
For example for a mixture of H 2 + H 20 
y1
H2=,y1
2H2O=2
x1)
2=2(2 1
H =1
2(2)+12(18) 10
x1
2(18) 9
H2O= =1
2(2)+12(18) 10
The above are all the relationships we need, so let us see how we proceed, for given chamber 
conditions, p c and T c. 
a) Compute x i (pc,Tc)
Hc 
Sc
b) Select a value of p&lt;pc.  We can treat p as the independent variable, finding all the
other properties as functions of it.   If we wish to find the conditions at the nozzle exitthen the pressure is the exit pressure, p=p
e.
c) From the Entropy equation (2e or 2f),  find T
T pr!1
(This replaces "
T  = (p )  of the Ideal Gas model) c c
1) For Frozen Flow, since x i (p,T) = x i (pc,Tc) are known, Eqs. (2f) and (2g) 
contain only T as an unknown, and can be solved iteratively at each p (this 
replaces the enthalpy conservation iteration we did in the chamber). 
 2) For Equilibrium Flow, we still have s = s
c, but now we don't know the x i, 
so we have to solve for them at each p, as noted above.
A. Assume a T 
B. Compute the y i (and x i) from K pi(T)
C. Compute S(T,p) and Iterate on T until it equalsS
c(Tc,pc). 
d) In either Fozen or Equilibrium cases, having T and x i(T,p) compute H(T,p), then
the velocity is given by
u2
2  = H c - H(T,p) 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>These procedures enable you to describe the flow in the nozzle with p as the independent
variable. Having u, p, T we can find  and hence u and the variation of the nozzle areawith p.  In particular, to find the throat area we can compute u for a set of values of p 
near (1/2)p
c and by plotting them determine the p that maximizes u.  This is the throat
pressure, and the maximum value of u defines c*=pc/ (!u)t
 
Normally, of course, such calculations are handled by standardized computer programs.  They all follow the logic outline above although the numerical procedures may become quite complex because of considerations of stability etc.  You don't need to know all the 
details, but it is important that you understand the logic they follow.  As we say, Garbage 
In-Garbage Out.  Be sure you know what the computer is doing. 
A very widely used suite of codes for thermochemical problems in aerospace is the CEA 
set, available at http://cearun.grc.nasa.gov.
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>We must have some statement about the variation of the entropy, since in general the transfer 
of energy from chemical to thermal takes place at a finite rate and there is therefore an 
entropy increase. 
But there are two limiting cases for which the entropy change is very small 
 a) chemical equilibrium 
b) frozen flow 
The case of Chemical Equilibrium will be approached if the reactions occur fast enough to 
keep up with the temperature and pressure changes caused by the expansion (flow time &gt;&gt; 
reaction time), so the chemical energy is transferred through an infin itesimal 
!T, and 
  S=!xi(p,T)Si(p,T)=Sc (2e) 
and the x i are determined by Equilibrium at the local T &amp; p. Re-calculating all these mass 
fractions is clearly a tedious task, but conceptually not very different from what was done for the chamber conditions, with the major difference that Entropy per unit mass, rather than 
Enthalpy per unit mass is now constrained.   In the case of Frozen Flow the reactions occur so slowly that the x
i are fixed at their chamber 
values (flow time &lt;&lt; reaction time).  In this case there is no chemical energy release and 
again
S=!xi(pc,Tc)Si(p,T)=Sc (2f) 
These are two limiting cases, which provide upper and lower limits for the velocity u, at a 
given p, since the case of Equilibrium Flow gives the maximum thermal energy availability 
for conversion to kinetic energy, while the Frozen Flow case gives the minimum. 
 In these calculations, the entropy per unit mass S
i of one species at (p,T) is related to that per 
mol, Si(p,T)=S  
i(p,T) /Mi , and this can be calculated from tabulated standard molar 
entropies, which are at p=1atm, as    
S  
i(p,T)=S  0
i(T)!"ln(pi(atm)); pi=pyi  (2g) 
It is important to note that the conservation laws for both energy and entropy are per unit 
mass . Thus it is the total energy and the entropy of a fixed mass of gas that is conserved.  At 
times it will be convenient to write the relations in terms of moles of the constituents (using 
yi rather than x i) but a fixed mass of gas may contain different numbers of moles at different 
points in the flow, so if we use the y i we must be careful to keep track of the changes in the 
number of moles.  
 To go from mole fractions  to mass fractions or vice-versa, 
  
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Heat transfer and cooling</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>In this type of cooling, the important mechanisms are 
  1) Boundary layer heat transfer to the wall from the nozzle flow. 
 2) Decomposition and evaporation of the material of the wall, which 
 generates a buffer gas layer, reducing the heat transfer rate. 
 c) Heat Sink Cooling  Here the wall temperature is maintained at a sufficiently low level by conduction of the heat into the material of the wall, so the mechanisms are   1) Boundary layer heat transfer to the wall from the nozzle flow. 
 2) Conduction of the heat into the wall, resulting in a temperature rise 
 with time. 
 d) Radiative Cooling  For small rocket engines used in space applications, for example for station keeping, it may be possible to cool the nozzle by thermal radiation, eliminating the requirement for cooling passages, or for erosion of the nozzle as in ablative cooling.  Since all of these cooling schemes have in common the heat transfer through a boundary layer to the wall, this aspect of them will be discussed first.      Heat transfer from a flowing fluid to a surface. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>For this process it is conventional to define a film coefficient h by:      q = h(T
g - Tw) 
 where Tg is the gas' stagnation temperature and Tw is the wall temperature. 
    
A more detailed way to represent this is:  
    q = uc
p (Tg - Tw) St 
 
where St is the Stanton Number, with the physical meaning  
heat flux to wall   St =   energy flux in flow relative to wall 
 
Equating the two relations for the heat flux,
    h= uc
p  St  
and in dimensionless form we can write 
hL uL cp
    = ( ) St kf  kf 
where the group on the left is called the Nusselt number, and the group involving 
just fluid properties is the Prandtl number:     Nu = Re Pr St  
                Nusselt           Reynolds      Prandtl  Stanton  
 Here L is the length scale of the flow, for which we have differing interpretationsdepending on the flow geometry.  Heat Transfer to Passage Flows and Frictional Pressure Drop  Consider first the heat transfer to fluid flowing through a long narrow passage,which may represent the cooling passages in the nozzle.  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>L If the length L of the passage is such the   &gt; 20, the flow becomes  Fully Developed, d 
meaning that it has velocity and temperature profiles independent of x.  The heat 
balance on a fluid element of length dx is  
    (
!uA)dTg = S qdx  
 
where A is the cross sectional area of the passage and S is the surface area per unit
D2A Dlength (perimeter). For a circular passage, S = D, A =  ,   =  ; more generally, 4 S 4 
D here is defined as the hydraulic diameter, D=4A/S.  
Writing q
w = !ucpSt (Tw " Tg ), we then have 
dTg 4S     = t (Tw  ! T) dx Dg 
If Tw and St can be taken as constant, this integrates to 
 
 Tg  
xT   Tw ! T (T4S
g = w ! T 
g0)e ! tD  w  
T w0  
  x/D  
The total heat transferred to the fluid in a length L is then
L
  Q = m! cp[Tg (L) ! T] = m! c(T! T)(1! e4S ! t D ) g0 p w g0  
 But any time there is boundary layer heat conduction to a wall, there is also wall friction, and in the case of a duct, pressure drop. To see this quantitatively, take nowa force balance on the same fluid element: 
dp u
2 
    A   dx = -    Sdx dx wSdx = -c f 2 
dp S u2 4 u2 
           = -c f    = -   cf   dx A 2 D 2 
and if compressibility is ignored, the pressure drop p=p0-p in a pipe length L is
4c  f "u2 
  !p = L D 2 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Image: Wikipedia.  Wikipedia User:  Donebythesecondlaw. License CC BY-SA.
This content is  excluded from our  Creative Commons license.
For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>c   S! f .67= .023 Re" 1"  
5
t Pr Pr".67  2 
 
Heat Transfer Through Boundary Layers  On the gas side of the rocket nozzle wall we have a nearly inviscid flow, with a thinviscous layer near the wall. In rocket nozzles, the flow is strongly influenced by a streamwise pressure gradient.  The "favorable" pressure gradient produced by thepressure drop in the flow direction accelerates the flow in the boundary layer, so theBoundary Layer tends to be thinner than it would be on a flat plate or on a pipe withfully developed flow. It is thinnest at the nozzle throat, where the pressure gradient 
is the strongest. For this reason and because u is largest there, the heat flux is
largest at the nozzle throat.   Much of the early progress in quantifying the heat transfer rate at the throat came from using data from passage flows, with Boundary Layer Thickness   
Tube diameter D
h(    ). One then applies various techniques to estimate , and2 2 
applies the passage flow data in the form 
 
    St = .023 R-1/5  Pr-.6  7e  
(u) where R! 2
e !  . But it is hard to accurately predict , so in practice one resorts 
to empirical results. Bartz (See HP pg. 549) recommended for the nozzle throat 
 
h   St =   = .023 (R-1/5 -.67 
GceD) Pr   p 
 where D is the throat diameter.  With these elements you are now in a position to analyze the most critical processes in the cooling system for  a convectively cooled rocket engine. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 Lecture 14 
  Subjects:  Heat Transfer and Cooling  Because the combustion temperatures in most rocket engines are far beyond the levels tolerable by most common structural metals, the walls of the combustion chambers and nozzles must be cooled.  The high pressures in the combustion chambers exacerbate the cooling problem by causing very high heat transfer rates, as we will see. For these reasons cooling is one of the critical technologies of rocketengines.  There are four ways of cooling rocket chambers and nozzles:
a) Convective cooling by fuel or oxidizerb) Ablative coolingc) Heat sink coolingd) Radiation cooling 
 We will discuss each of these briefly, then return to a discussion of the physicalmechanisms of importance in each, with the major emphasis on the first two because they are of the greatest practical importance.  a) Convectively Cooled Chambers and Nozzles 
There are 3 rather distinct heat transfer processes involved in such cooling:  
  1) Boundary layer heat transfer to the wall from the nozzle flow.  
 2) Conduction through the wall. 
 3) Convective heat transfer to the fluid in the cooling passages. 
b) Ablatively Cooled Chambers and Nozzles 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>It is interesting to calculate the ratio of the non-dimensional pressure drop and the 
heat added. In particular, for small values of 4StL/D, so that the expression for Q can
be expanded to first order, we find
(!p / "u2) c/ 2       
("f Q / m! c p (Tw # Tg0) St 
which is a quantity we will shortly find to be of order unity.  Sometimes we define a "friction factor" f 
! 4Cf . We then find that f or c f can be 
uD hrepresented as a function of only the Reynolds Number, defined as  R e  !      
where u is the mass flow per unit area of the passage and D  is the hydraulicdiameter, defined as above. All fluid mechanics texts present the variation of C h
f or f, 
and a sample is shown at the end of this lecture. Note that in that graph the quantity  
hf on the left scale is p/, and the scale on the left is e
equivalent sand roughness (for a hydraulically sms/d, where e
ooth surface, es is the 
&lt;&lt;1). 
 s
Although there is some dependence of this relationship on Mach number for Mach 
numbers approaching 1, for most of our purposes we can take this relationship for the friction coefficient to be valid. For incompressible flow, the pressure drop is then directly calculable from the definition of the friction coefficient.  For comp ressible flow we must account for the acceleration of the flow that occurs 
because of decreasing density as the fluid is heated.  
 Reynolds Analogy  To transfer our understanding of the viscous pressure drop to heat transfer, we observe that both in turbulent flow and in laminar flow the same mechanism transports momentum and energy to the wall (flow eddies in turbulent flow, molecular motion in laminar flow). Thus we would expect the ratio of heat flux into the wall to heat flux along the wall to equal the ratio of momentum flux into the wall divided by momentum flux along the wall. 
q u2
#! 
   =w c= f 2  !ucp (T " Tw  ) !u2 !u2
This results in 
c      St = f 2 
More detailed analysis shows that the thermal conductivity matters slightly, and we find (Hill/Peterson, pg. 129) 
    .67 cS  Pr  = f 
t  2 
cpwhere Pr =   is the Prandtl Number. k 
 
Now we can use the empirical information on pressure drop to estimate heat transfer. Thus for turbulent flow in a smooth pipe, 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Turbojet engines (cont.); design parameters; effect of mass flow on thrust.</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>In terms of our expression for thrust, since 
 
F u=Mm  ao(e!1)
o u0
      
ue=(F/m  ao) /Mo+1u0
and we can write the expression for the propulsive efficiency in terms of our expression for thrust 
2   !propulsive =F 
+2m  aoM0
.Since F/m a o ~ 2 to 3 for low M o, prop is not good for the turbojet at low Mach numbers.  
We will see later how this deficiency is remedied by adding a fan to the engine to produce a Turbofan. 
 
Thermal and Overall Efficiencies  
 
The Thermal Efficiency is define for the Turbojet Engine as  
 $ &amp; u2u2
m e#0' 
power #in# % jet  2 2 (  !thermal " =  
power #in#fuel #flow m  fh
 
Finally we can define an Overall Efficiency as  
  power #to#airplane Fu!overall" =0 
power #in#fuel#flow m  fh
 
We see that  
    !overall=!thermal!  
propulsive
 
It is also important that the overall efficiency is directly related to the specific impulse:  
Fu! =0 F gu
overall =0gu=0I m  fhm  fg h h
 
 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>(F)2 2
m  amaxF= (#2  
!"1t"1)+Mo"Mo
o
           (11) 
   ()   =maxF (aoh)(F/m  a0)
 CpTog(!t"!t) 
 
As an example take:  = 6.25 !  = 2.5 ,  = 1.4 t t
 
   (F)max F=5(2.25) +M2
m  ao!M  
o
o
 
   ()   =  (aoh)F
m  ao maxFCpTog3.75
 
  aoh (283m/s)(4.3 x107J/kg)= =6178 s 
CpTog(1004 J/kgK )(200 K)(9.81 m/s2)
 
There is an upper limit on M  reached when the compressor outlet temperature equals the o
turbine inlet temperature, so no fuel can be added. That is we must have    &lt;  Since o c t  0 
increases with Mach number, the theoretical limit is reached when =1 and  =, i.e. when c 0 t
!there is no compressor and we have a ramjet. But for   = t  the real limit is reached c!o
when   = !, i.e., all the compression is due once again to the ram effect, but we are o t
allowing a good margin for heat addition in the burner, so this ramjet does produce maximum 
thrust. For a currently practical value of  = 9,   &lt; 3 or M  &lt; 3.9 t o o
 
Propulsive Efficiency 
 
The Turbojet engine is attractive for its simplicity and its good thrust behavior at high Mach numbers.  Unfortunately it is not very efficient at low Mach numbers, because its jet velocity 
is too high.  To see this we consider the Propulsive Efficiency, defined as 
power #to#airplane!propulsive "power #in#jet
   Fu02m  (ue#u0)u0 2u0 =2 =$ 2
&amp; ueu0' m  =u u#(e#0)(ue+u 0) (um e+u0)
% 2 2 ( 
From this we see that there is a direct conflict between the desire for high jet velocity to give 
high thrust, and jet velocity near the flight velocity, to maximize the propulsive efficiency. 
  
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Subject: Turbojet engines (continued); Design parameters; Effect of mass flow on thrust.  In this chapter we examine the question of how to choose the key parameters of the engine to obtain some specified performance at the design conditions, and how the performance varies if these parameters are changed, still at the design conditions. Later we will look at a complementary question, namely, how the performance of a particular design changes when 
conditions are different from design conditions. 
 With the results that we worked out last time for the Turbojet engine, let us look at the 
.dependence of F/m a  on the principal parameters, M
,  and  .  We can view them this o o c t
way 
  ! design choice (compressor pressure ratio) c
  M
! flight speed o 
 
   or  ! combustor outlet temperature, an operating variable, limited by turbine 
materials to some maximum value. 
 Assuming the exhaust is matched, we can re-write Eq. (10) of the previous lecture as  
  
F 2 1
. = [#t(1" )"#
moa !"
o1 #0$o($c"1)]"M 
o
c
 
we can see that since   &gt;1, F always increases with  . This relationship is displayed o cm  at
o
below for a subsonic case: 
 
116.50 Lecture 19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>For a given  , what is the variation with  ?  By inspection we see there is a maximum at the t c
maximum of the bracketed quantity, so at the value of  that satisfies c
  ![ (11) ( 1)]#1#$ $ # " $=t$#=0 
!"t
c #o"o c#2 o
c o"c
This value is  
!   ( )  = t cmax!o
This result can be seen to be equivalent to Tt3=T0Tt4, namely, the compressor exhaust 
should be at the geometrical mean of the ambient and combustor exhaust temperatures. If it 
were much lower or much higher, the T-S diagram of the equivalent Brayton cycle would be too skinny, and enclose too little area (too little work per unit mass): 
 
(a) Too little compression  (b) Optimal compr.         (c) Too much compr.  
T     T    T 
   T
t4     Tt4     Tt4 
             T t3 
        T t3                     T t3 
   T 0     T 0    T 0 
            S     S    S   Whether this power is utilized as jet kinetic energy, as in the turbojet, or as shaft power in a 
turboprop, is immaterial.  Also, as far as this argument, the compression T
t3/T0 can be 
arbitrarily divided between ram compression ( 0) and mechanical compression ( c). 
What is the meaning of this for the turbojet? Putting this value into (10) and the 
corresponding expression for the specific impulse, we have the thrust and I for engines optimized for thrust per unit of airflow:  
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Orbital mechanics; single force center</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 Lecture 3 
 Subjects: Orbital mechanics; Single force center   The most usual application of rocket engines is to propel vehicles under conditions where the behavior of the vehicle is largely determined by the gravitational attractions of one or more bodies of the solar system, and where aerodynamic drag is not very important.  So it is essential to understand the behavior of an orbiting body in order to appreciate the requirements which must be met by the rocket engine.  For this reason we shall spend a short time discussing orbital mechanics.  It should be noted, however, that the intent is to present only the aspects that define the requirements for propulsion systems, not to discuss the details of orbital computations.  For these the student should refer to a text on celestial mechanics or spacecraft guidance.  Forces between bodies. The planetary Sphere of Influence  The gravitational attraction between two bodies of masses m and M is given by 
 
Q=GmM1
r2 
where G = 6.67x10-11m3 kg-1 s-2, and r is the distance between the bodies. The 
gravitational acceleration is then f=GM /r2!/r2, where =GM is the gravity 
constant of the body with mass M. 
 We are interested in the motion of a small body (spacecraft) in the force fields of one or more larger bodies. If we consider the Sun and two or more planets, the problem is extremely difficult mathematically.  For our purposes, it can be simplified immensely by considering the motion of the spacecraft under the influence of only the dominant attractor at any given time. On the interplanetary scale, this means the Sun most of the time, but near enough one of the planets (inside its Sphere of Influence, SOI), the planet will dominate. To estimate correctly the radius of the SOI, one should work in the frame of reference of the planet. The gravitational acceleration of the planet alone on the S/C is f
p,SC, and the  perturbation due to the Sun of the spacecraft acceleration with respect 
to the planet is fS,SC-fS,p. Conversely, the gravitational acceleration of the Sun alone on the 
S/C is fS,SC, and the perturbation due to the planet of the spacecraft acceleration with 
respect to the Sun is fp,SC-f , which, since the distance to the Sun is much greater that that 
to the SC, is almost equal tp,o fS alone. We now state that the relative errors in ignoring 
either of the two perturbationsp, SCare the same on the SOI: 
 
   fS,SC!fS,pf!p,SC f!p,SC 
 fp,SC fS,SC fS,p
 
The difference on the left hand side numerator is approximated to first order as  
   "ff,
S,SC!fSrpSC
S,p! rrp,SC=2"Sr3 
S,p
Substituting this and the  other accelerations into the SOI definition, and rearranging, one 
finds rSOI (= rp,SC) to be given by 
     r
SOI 1!
 rS,p 21/5(Mp)2/5 MS
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>c=a a(1-) p r 
 - 
          
With reference to the figure, the polar equation of the trajectory is    r=  , 1+!cos"
where p=a(1!"2),   is the eccentricity and a is the semi-major axis. If &lt;1, all the 
quantities listed are positive and the trajectory is closed (an ellipse with a focus at r=0). 
The case when &gt;0 will be discussed later. The quantity p is called the parameter, and 
has the significance shown in the figure. The minimum and maximum radii are called the 
periapsis and apoaxis, respectively (perigee and apogee for orbits around Earth); they are given by  
   
rp
p= = a(1"!);rp
a= = a(1+!) 1+! 1"!
The potential energy per unit mass, with zero at infinity, is  Ep=!/r.  
 
The two constants of the motion are: 
(a) The total energy per unit mass,     E1=v2 !=!  2 r 2a
(b) The angular momentum per unit mass,   h=r2!!=p=a(1"#2) 
 
a3/2
The time to complete one orbit is      T=2!   

Using the conservation of energy, the velocity magnitude is given by the so-called vis-
2viva equation:        v= !  r a
The circular orbital velocity (r=a) is therefore     vc= =   r a
Notice that the kinetic energy in a circular orbit is EK=/ 2a=!E=!1 / 2Ep. More 
generally, the average kinetic and potential energies satisfy these same curious 
relationships for any elliptic orbit.   
The trajectory first becomes open when =1, r  tends to infinity, and the total energy 
becomes zero. When this happens, the body is a
 on a trajectory to barely escape the 
attractor, arriving at infinity with zero velocity. The velocity on this trajectory depends on 
2distance as vesc= . r
As a final note, the apogee and perigee velocities occur frequently in orbital calculations. 
They are related to the apogee and perigee radii by p
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>2  r    rvp=a2&gt;v ;v=p&lt;v rc
pra+r,p a
p rara+rc,a
p
Although the formulation in terms of the classical orbital elements a, , p, etc, is 
standard, most simple problems can be solved quickly by using the energy and angular 
momentum conservation laws between judiciously selected points, often the apogee and perigee themselves.  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Since Mp/MS is a small number, r /r&lt;&lt;1. We can therefore model the relative body 
motion near the planets (r&lt;rSOI S,p
SOI) as being under the influence of a single force center (the 
planet), while the body and the planet experience a common acceleration toward the Sun. Far from the planet (r&gt;r ) we ignore its field and consider the body motion as influenced only by the Sun. For pre
SO
liI
minary calculations, these limiting models are simply patched 
at the SOI.  To see how far from a planet is far, we refer to Table 1-1, which gives the ratios of the planet's mass to that of the Sun and the size of hteir spheres of influence.  
Table 1-1 
 
                                      Relative mass          Orbital Radius, km      r
SOI (Km) 
Mercury                         .167 x 10-6                   .578 x 108         98,000  
Venus                            .245 x 10-5                   1.08 x 108          536,000  
Earth                              .300 x 10-5                   1.49 x 108      791,000  
Mars                               .324 x 10-6                   2.27 x 108      501,000  
Jupiter                            .956 x 10-3                   7.77 x 108      41.6x106 
Saturn                            .286 x 10-3                   1.42 x 109      47.3x106 
Uranus                           .437 x 10-4                   2.86 x 109      44.9x106 
Neptune                         .518 x 10-4                   4.49 x 109      75.5x106 
Pluto                               .28 x 10-5                    5.89 x 109      30.8x106 
Earth's Moon,  M /M=.368 x 10-7           r =.384 x 106         
 M E E,M57,600  
We see for example that the sphere of influence of the Earth is just about twice the 
distance to the Moon. On one hand this means we can just barely ignore solar perturbations in considering cis-lunar operations not very near the Moon, but also that the Moons own motion about the Earth must be appreciably affected by the Suns attraction. Notice also the relatively large size of the SOI of the Moon in the Earth-Moon system (15% of the Earth/Moon distance).  We can therefore reduce the complex many-force center situation to a set of simpler ones, namely  a)  Motion in the single force field of a planet  b)  Motion in the single force field of the Sun  c)  Transition from a Sun-dominated to a planet dominated situation, or vice versa.  As we shall see this transition can be thought of as a change of coordinate system.  Motion under a Single Force Center  The subject of motion under a single gravitational attractor is covered in all Dynamics textbooks, and so we only give here a summary of the main conclusions and working equations.   
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction to component matching and off-design operation</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec20/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 dimensional quantities (flow rate, peak pressure, etc.) will be different, depending on p o, 
etc. 
 
(8) The Operating Line in the compressor map. Compressor performance is typically presented as a map of 
!c vs. m 2, with lines of constant normalized 
rotational speed ! and "c superimposed. The details are the subject of later 
Lectures, but the general shape is as shown below. (The flow and speed variables 
are renormalized by the Design values): 
  
  
 =m2
(m2)des 
 
 
   
 Actually the nominal operating line shown in the figure i s not a property of the 
compressor, but rather of the rest of the engine. We can calculate this line with the information we have now, before deciding what particular compressor to use. From Eqs. 
(11) and (9), 
 
A    m 2=4!"/"#1
c     (19) A2$
 
and from the shaft power balance (Eq. 7), 
 
"    ! =c#1      (20) 1#"t
 
where we recall that !t is fixed for a fixed geometry. Eliminating , Kerrebrock, Jack L. (1992). Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines (2nd Edition).
MIT Press,  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5  # u P A&amp; u P A   !2=% "m e e e
2 + ( ) "m o o e
2 )   (17) % (  
$ R TtoPtoA2' R TtoPtoA2
&amp; # ) &amp; ) - 0 ( 2# 2%e+ # 1A ! =m #,1A
2"e
2 $( #+1t+( %t%c+ ,/" m 2M0 +1 2  (18) 
' #+1 * A+ #/#,
' 2 . $* o$o A21 
!# # # # # # " # # # # # # $  
  *!2($)
 
Once again, the normalized thrust depends on both,  and M o, but the structure is fairly 
simple, and in particular, the portion !*
2 of !2 (neglecting the incoming momentum and 
the external pressure) is a function of  alone. This portion can be very easily scaled 
between conditions, and the rest can be subtracted separately. 
 
A note on : the near-constancy of the engine operating point  
 
Two important points in the flight envelope of an aircraft engine are (a) Take-off 
conditions (Mo!0.25, To!290K), and (b) End-of-climb conditions (M 00.85, 
T0220K. The total temperatures are Tto=290 (1+0.2!0.252)=294K (take-off) and 
Tto=220 (1+0.2!0.852)=252K (end of climb). Suppose the engine is dimensioned for 
end-of-climb, which is common, and that the peak temperature T t4, which will have to be 
maintained for many hours of cruise, is selected at a conservative T t4 = 1600K. We then 
1600have ! = = 6.35 at this condition. If we now decided to maintain  = 6.35 also  for 252
take-off, we would need then Tt4=6.35!294 =1868K . While this is too high for long-
term operation (creep, corrosion), it may be acceptable for the few minutes per cycle that 
the engine will be at take-off maximum power. 
 
As a second example, consider a commercial jet in a long cruise. As the fuel is consumed 
and the weight decreases, so must the lift L=1/2!0u2
0AwcL. Now, the lift coefficient will 
be kept close to that for optimum L/D, and the Mach number M 0 is unlikely to change 
much, as it will stay just below the transonic drag peak, and so u2
0 will be proportional to 
T0 due to the speed of sound variation. Together with the density part of lift, we can see 
that the ambient pressure p 0 must be decreasing in proportion to the airplanes weight, 
i.e., the plane must be climbing gradually. Turning now to the forward force balance, 
given a constant L/D, the drag, and hence the engine thrust, must also be decreasing in 
time in the same proportion as the ambient pressure. Therefore, from Eq. (14), the 
nondimensional thrust !2(",M0) will remain constant, and since M 0 does too, the peak 
temperature ratio  will also remain constant, and with it all the important ratios like c, 
M2, etc. 
 
In other words,  may not vary much among (important) flight conditions, and the engine 
will be operating at a fixed nondimensional condition (constant compression ratio, 
nondimensional flow, compressor inlet Mach number, etc.). But of course, the</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 Since !c=!c("), we see now that M2=M2(!) as well (the supersonic solution for M 2 
given m 2 can be disregarded). 
 
(3) Dimensionless air flow. Returning to (8), we see that the dimensionless mass flow 
 
   m m  
2!       (10) # P A&amp; 
% "to 2( % R T( $ to' 
 
(flow rate as a fraction of what the compressor would pass if its inlet were choked), is 
once more a unique function of . This is very useful for scaling from one operating 
condition to another. 
 
(4) Fuel/air ratio. The combustor heat balance is 
 
   m  fh=m   cp(Tt4!Tt3)=m   cpTt2("!#c)    (11) 
 
and using Tt2=Tto and f!m  f/m  , 
 
fh   =!"#c(!)      (12) cpTto
 
so the quantity f/Tto is another function of  alone. But notice that f itself does depend 
on M o at a fixed T o. 
 
(5)Throat pressure (normalized) 
 
P 7P=t2Pt3Pt4Pt5Pt1P7 Pto PtoPt2Pt3Pt4Pt5Pt7
 
Pand 7 1 $ 2'! /!"1P P=!/!"1=&amp; ) . Also t3=! ="#/#$1, t5=! ="#/#$1; Pt7$ !"1 ' % !+1( Pc cPt t
&amp;1 + #1) t2 t4
% 2 ( 
 
P 2!
$ ' 
   7=&amp; "t"c(#)!*1
    (13)P)   
to% !+1 ( 
 
which is yet another function of  alone. 
 
(6) Thrust (matched nozzle). We already have Eq. (10) of Lecture 18, but it is sometimes 
better to normalize thrust by the total free-stream pressure on the compressor inlet, P toA2,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 16.50  
  
Subject: Introduction to Component Matching and Off-Design Operation 
 
At this point it is well to reflect on which of the many parameters we have introduced 
(like M 2, c, t, t, f, etc.) are free for the pilot to control, and what the inter-relationships 
are that determine the others. This connectivity is in part mechanical, like the shaft power 
balance (Eq. 9 of Lecture 18), but it also comes via flow continuity among components. 
This topic is usually relegated to the very end of the study of engine components, where 
it is introduced under the rubric of Component Matching (Lecture 31 in our NOTES). 
We find it advantageous to move most of it forward to this point. 
 
The price to pay for the insight to be gained is the need to introduce one assumption at 
this point (to be justified later). This is the assumption that the stators leading to the 
turbine (the turbine nozzles are choked. This means the mass flow rate can be written 
as 
# "+1&amp; 
P   (")t4A # &amp; 4 2m =m  4=!     % 2(")1)( !="%   
R (  (1) 
T % ( 
t4 $ "+1' $ ' 
Where A 4 is the effective flow area of these nozzles. But in addition, we have already 
shown in Lect. 18 that the exhaust nozzle is also choked. Passing the same flow through 
two choked apertures in series imposes very strong constraints on the flow conditions. 
The flow can be expressed at the throat as 
 
   m  =m  P A
7=!(")t7 7      (2) 
R Tt7
 
and equating (1) and (2) , 
 
P   t7Tt4A=4      (3) Pt4Tt7A7
 For a non-afterburning turbojet, 
Pt7!Pt5 and Tt7=Tt5 
 
! A   t=4        (4) 
"tA7
 
#
and if the turbine is ideal, !t="t#$1 , and we obtain 
 
2(()1)
" A% (+1
   ! =$ 4
t '        (5) 
# A7&amp; 
  
 
 
 
 
 
 Lecture 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 We take now  t=7, or T t4=1540K in the stratosphere. The geometry of the engine must 
have been specified in advance. This means that the turbine temperature ratio (Eq. 5) is a 
known fixed number. For the example, we select  t such as to obtain maximum thrust at 
M0=1. From the shaft balance equation,  
#     !t=1"0 #t(!c"1)
and we put now  0=1.2 and  c=7/1.2=2.2048 (at M 0=1). This fixes  t=0.7935. 
Similarly, the area ratio A 4/A2 must have been fixed, and we select it here so as to obtain 
at M 0=1 a compressor-face Mach number M 2=0.5, which, from Eq. (8) implies 
m 2=0.7464. From Eq. (9) then,  
! "    m 2=0.7464(c)3.5 0 2.2048 1.2
and the rest of the steps are as described above. The table below summarizes the results: 
 
M0 0 1 2 2.5 
0 1 1.2 1.8 2.25 
c 2.4458 2.2048 1.8032 1.6426 
m 2 0.9796 0.7464 0.4523 0.3648 
M2 0.8486 0.5 0.2737 0.2172 
!2 2.9117 1.5531 0.5795 0.3503 
F/(p 0A2) 2.9117 2.9399 4.534 5.985 
 
We find that at a fixed altitude the thrust is nearly constant up to Mach 1, then it increases 
rapidly. Actually the increase is less rapid than this simple model predicts, because of 
losses in the supersonic flow in the engine inlet. 
Finally to this point, we should note that an aircraft normally flies at increasing altitude as 
the Mach Number increases, so that dynamic pressure !p0M2
0 is roughly constant.  In this 
case the change in F between Mach 1 and Mach 2 is actually a thrust reduction.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2  2(
" A%( +1
and then  !t=$ 4'        (6) 
# A7&amp; 
 
This is a strong result: as long as both, the turbine nozzles and the exhaust throat remain 
choked, the turbine maintains the same pressure and temperature ratios (same operating 
point), regardless of fuel flow, Mach number, altitude, etc.  We can now trace the 
variability of other quantities: 
 
 (1) Compressor ratios. In terms of  = T t4/Tto, Eq. (9) of Lecture 18 gives 
   
!c=1+"(1#!) ;  !/
c="# #$1
t c    (7) 
 
Thus  c and  c do vary, but only as a function of the single quantity :  
c =  c () for a given engine. 
 
(2) Mach number at compressor inlet (M 2). The flow at compressor inlet is 
generally subsonic, so we express the flow rate there as  
"
$ "+1+1
' 2("#1)
P A &amp; ) 
m  =m  2=!t2 2m 2(M2)  ;  m )=M2
T2(M2 &amp; )  
R 2   (8)
1"#2 +2t1&amp; M) % 22( 
 The dimensionless flow function 
m 2(M2) increases to a maximum of 1 when  
M2 = 1, then decreases again.  
  Equating (8) to (1), we see that 
     
m 2(M2) 
  1 
 
m 2(M2)P T A=t4 t2 4 Pt2Tt4A2
 
 
   0           1   M 2 
 
For an ideal combustor, Pt4=P#
t3, and so, using !c="/#$1
c, Tt2=Tto, 
 
 
!"/"#1
  m 2(M2)=c A4       (9) $A2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 which is known from flight conditions. If P e = P o (variable nozzle, or just design point for 
a fixed nozzle), 
 
F m  (u!u)   !2"  =e o     (14) PtoA2 PtoA2
 
u   !2m P A u #=2"to 2 e o 
RTtoPtoA2
 For u
e, we go back to Lecture 18, Eq. (7): 
  
2 #   ue=ao (#  !1o$c$t"1)" $c
 
aand  o ! R /  To != = . All together then, 
RTto R /  Tto "o
 
#' 2$ ($o&amp;c&amp;t%1)* 
  !2="m 2) %Mo,     (15) $o()  #%1 &amp;c ,+  
 
Here the quantities m 2 and !c depend on  only, but we can see that the Mach number 
"#1Mo appears explicitly (as M o and as !o=1+ M2
2o), so the normalized thrust !2 
depends on both  and M o. 
 
(7) Thrust (truncated sonic nozzle). We now have me=m7=1, but P e = P 7 &gt; P o, so 
 
F m  (u ("P)A!2= =e"uo)+Pe o e
PtoA2 P
   toA2   (16) 
u  
e"u $
o PeP' 
    =#m oAe
2 +&amp; "
R ) Tto% PtoPto( A2
    
2 2 !and this time M e = 1, so ue=!RTe=!R T =!+1t5 RT!+1to"#t 
 
u 2so that e ! P= "#t depends on  alone. Since we also know that m 2 and e are 
R Tto !+1 Pto
functions of  alone, it makes sense to separate out Eq. (16) in the form</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7  A    m 2=4!"/"#11#!t
c      (21) A2 !c#1
 
or, in terms of !c, 
A 1"#    m 2=4!t
Ac $"1      (22) 
2!$
c"1
 
which is the equation for the operating line (written in reverse). 
 
If the compressor is already available, we see from (22) that we can adjust the nozzle area 
A4 to place this line in a good place on the map, i.e., below the stall line and through 
the best efficiency points. 
TSince m 2 depends on ! =t4, varying TTt4 moves the operating point along the operating 
to
line, and this is what the pilot does with the throttle stick to power the engine up or down. 
At each selected , the engine settles to a !c, a M 2, a (normalized) rotation rate, etc. 
 
Effects of Mach number 
 
If we look at operation of a given engine at different flight Mach numbers, we may try to 
maintain the same non-dimensional conditions throughout, which, as we have seen, can 
be done by maintaining for example a constant compressor inlet Mach, M 2. This, in turn 
Tguarantees a constant ! =t4, but since now we have a varying Mach number, so that Tto
Tt0 increases with M 0, we may find that the turbine inlet temperature T t4 needs to become 
too high at the higher Mach numbers. For example, T t4 would have to be 1.8 times higher 
at M 0=2.0 than at static conditions, and 2.25 times at M 0=2.5. 
 
A more reasonable assumption is that the ratio  t=Tt4/T0 can be maintained the same at all 
Mach numbers, since at least in the stratosphere, T 0 is almost invariant. The compressor 
1"t(1#!)temperature ratio now follows from !c= +t, where the numerator is a "0
constant; thus,  c will be lowered as the Mach number increases, but less strongly than 
would be required to maintain maximum thrust per unit flow ( !c="t/"0). The flow 
parameter m 2 is now determined by Eq. (9), i.e. compressor-turbine flow matching, and 
then the compressor-inlet Mach number from Eq. (8). Once these parameters are known, 
we can use Eq. (15) to calculate the normalized thrust; since we are interested in the 
effect of Mach number, it makes sense to re-normalize thrust by p 0A2,  or 
F#
=!p A2"0#$1. 
0 2
 
A numerical example</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Turbofan engines</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec21/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>#!o
t=1" [(!"1)+$(!"1)]
     #c f
t   (15) 
  
Substituting this gives us our result for the thrust of the turbofan. It doesn't really help to carry out the substitution at this point. Instead let us think about how to simplify the expressions to make them more easily understandable.   For this engine there are more parameters than for the turbojet: 
    
t, c - as before 
    ,  f - characterizing the fan flow. 
 
We can relate some of the parameters to others by noting that the highest propulsive 
momentumefficiency is realized when u 8 = u 6, since this maximizes the ratio of     in energy
the jets.  For this situation, the two 's  in the thrust equation are equal, and this 
requires that: 
# !t&amp;       % ( [!o"c"t)1] =!o"f)1   (16) $ !0"c' 
       (u 8 = u 6) 
Solving for  f as a function of  using (15), 
 
   !o"c
!t(!o"f#1)+1!2"=!o
o"c#c[("!c#1)+$("f#1)]  
t
   !! " #1+t
o f =!t#!o[("c#1)+$("#!o"f1)] 
c
 
1+"t
t#"
"o!c#"o(! +    !c#1)"
f=o$ "o+"o$
 
1+" !t
t+" $    !o(1+#c)$"
f="o!c   (17) "o(1+#)
When this equation is satisfied, the thrust equation becomes simply 
    F=(1+!)[2(m  a"#1$o%f#1)#M0
o] 
Now as for the turbojet there is still the choice of the compression ratio. Generally 
we want to choose it for maximum power, which in this case for given turbine inlet 
temperature  t and bypass ratio  means maximum thrust. To maximize F, we 
choose  c to maximize  f, since F increases monotonically with  f.  From the 
expression for  f   
 
!"    f $=#$!"o+t 
c $ "2=0
o c
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
 Subject: Turbofan Engines  
In the lecture 19 we saw that for low M
o,  p is not very high for turbojets. In essence 
there is too much kinetic energy in the exhaust jet (per unit mass). This is the main 
reason for use of the Turbofan engine.  I
f it is designed for subsonic cruise flight it 
looks like: 
 
 
 In both of these diagrams the inlet has been greatly simplified, of course.    
If designed for both subsonic cruise and for supersonic flight with afterburning it 
looks more like:  
1From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.
From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MITPress, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.Lecture 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Let us now see how we can model these engines thermodynamically. In the first 
(cruise engine) we have 2 jets.  Up until we evaluated  t, our argument for finding 
the jet velocity applies to either jet.  Thus from equation (8) of Lecture 18 we get for 
the core jet:  
F 2 #   c= (t)[# $ $ "1]"M m  ao !"1#t
o$o c o
c
For the fan stream, there is no turbine, so let us repeat the argument. 
1   T t8 = T 8(1 +  2
28) = f 
and 
1! !
   p  = p (1 +  28)!"1= po  f = p o ( t8 8o f)!"1 2
So for p8 = p o 
1    1 +  2 = 28of 
2
    M8 = (#!"1o$f"1) 
As in the turbojet, a fixed convergent nozzle is more likely to be sonic and under-expanded, namely, to have M
8=1 and p8&gt;p0, but we will here ignore the differences 
this entails.  We also have 
T !     8=o"f=1  To!o"f
so 
, 2(* 1F. 0+f")/
1
   BP#u &amp; ).1=M8 "1
!ma0 " =%1(M$ '0 "1  !0 u0 . M0 1
. 1
 - 0
adding this thrust to the thrust of the core jet, we find the total thrust: 
 
 F={2(#t
!"1#o$c)[#o$c$t"1]"Mo}+%{2
!"1(#o$f"1)"Mo} (14) m  ao
Now we need  t. We will see later that most  engines have two shafts, but for now we 
lump their power together; at off-design conditions, this would have to be modified. 
From a work balance between the compressor, fan and turbine, (both shafts),  
  
m  cp(Tt4!Tt5)=m  cp(Tt3!Tt2)+"m  cp(Tt7!Tt2)  
       
!t(1"#t)=!o(#" 
c1)+$!o(#f"1)
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>"   !2"
c=t
"2  (!c)Fmax=t 
o "0
Notice that this is precisely the same result as for the Turbojet. Substituting in the 
expression for  f 
1+"+"(1+#)$"$"   (! =o
f)t t t
max F  "o(1+#)
 
 
("   (!f)max F=t#1)2
+1     (17b) "o(1+$)
! F+ $ + *)1)2.
  # ( 
 2  .
&amp; =(1 +)t+*)1" m  'a- % ()1- 1+'o )0 Mo0   (14b) 
0max , / , / 
 Now we have 3 parameters, 
  
t - which we set at the maximum feasible value 
  M o - flight speed 
   - the prime variable distinguishing the turbofan 
 
As before 
  2 2!propulsive = =/  u6 Fm a+10+2u0 M0(1+")
 
The variation of F/ma 0 and  p with M 0 and  is shown in the figures below for 
t=6.25.  Of course for the higher bypass ratios we are really only interested in the 
range of M 0&lt;1, but the lower bypass and higher M 0 range may be of interest for a 
supersonic transport. 
 
  
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Modeling of rocket nozzles; effects of nozzle area ratio</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>The thrust is also expressible in terms of the effective exhaust velocity c, as we discussed in 
Lecture 1. Then we have 
    F!m!cp=cAt=p
 c*cAtcF 
and we see that 
     c=c*cF 
 
The "Characteristic Velocity" c* depends mainly on propellant properties. The Thrust 
Coefficient cF depends on propellant properties through  (or equivalent), but mainly on the 
pressure ratio and nozzle geometry.  So by the definitions of c F and  c*  we have managed to 
separate the effects of propellant properties and the effects of nozzle geometry into the two 
factors of c. This separation, though demonstrated only for ideal gases, holds also for the more general situation of complex chemically reacting propellants.  
Effects of Non-ideal Expansion 
 So far we have assumed in the discussion of c
F that the flow fills the nozzle and is supersonic 
to the exit.  If this is the case, the thrust is given by the above expression for c F . But in fact 
the flow can be somewhat more complex than this, depending the ratio p c/p0 compared to 
that which leads to ideal expansion.  This behavior is summarized in the figure below. 
 
 
 
Here A n is the throat area, A e the exit area.  The ideally expanded situation is at the upper 
right, and it is the condition at which thrust is maximum for a given external pressure p0. This 
is easier to visualize than to prove analytically: if the divergent nozzle were extended a little by adding a section at its exit, this section would see an internal pressure lower than p
0, and 
would therefore generate suction, or negative thrust. If on the contrary, the nozzle were shortened a little, one would lose the positive thrust that was being produced by the removed 
portion.  
 Returning to consideration of a given nozzle, if p
0 is lowered below its ideal matching 
pressure (for example by the rocket ascending in the atmosphere) the nozzle becomes 
underexpanded, as at the lower right.  In this case the flow fills the nozzle and our formula 
for F works fine. Kerrebrock, Jack L. (1992). Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines (2nd Edition).
MIT Press,  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>If on the other hand p 0 is larger than corresponds to ideal expansion, the situation can 
become more complex.  For pressure ratios p 0/ pe&lt; 2 to 2.5, the nozzle is likely to remain 
full, and again the formula holds. But for larger pressure ratios the oblique shocks that form 
at the exit of the nozzle are strong enough to separate the boundary layer, and the point of 
separation moves into the nozzle so that its effective area decreases, as shown at the upper left.  In this case the separation occurs approximately at a pressure p
s such that p s/p0 =  to 
1/(2.5).  
Again we can use the formula for thrust by replacing p
e by p s and A e by A s, the area at which 
the pressure is p s. So now 
     F=m.
us+As(ps!po) 
 
With this understanding, we can write the thrust coefficient for the separated nozzle as  
1
F 2!
2
  ! 2+
# 1&amp; p!"!"1 A# p[1 (s s s "p)!]o&amp; % = " + % (  pcAt !"1$ !+1' pc At$ pc' 
 
where now it is understood that p s is the pressure at which the separation occurs and A s is 
the corresponding area. 
   
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>and for ideal gases, we have the estimate of c* given by 
 
   c* RT1
=c 2"+
;!="( )2("#1) ! "+1
F 
Substituting these into the expression for F and non-dimensionalizing it: 
 
1
F 2!+
 !1
  !2#2&amp; "
% !"1 p #
[ ]"= % p1"(e A p)! 
+e e o &amp; (  pcAt !"1$ !+1' pc At$ pc' 
where the area ratio is itself related to the pressure ratio through continuity:  
A !"+
e=tut "#1 21
= ( )2("#1) 1 At!eue 2"+1pe)1/" p"#1
( 1 #(e)"
pc pc
More generally, we define a Thrust Coefficient by       
    
F!pcAtcF 
 
and the above expression then gives us an estimate of c F for ideal gases. 
 The dependence of c
F on nozzle area ratio and pressure ratio is conventionally 
summarized as in the figure below, which is drawn for =1.2 and 1.3. Notice:   
- is replaced by k in these graphs 
-p
c is replaced by p1 
-pe is replaced by p2 
-pa, or p0, the ambient pressure, is replaced by p
 3 
  
 
 
 
   
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50  Lecture 7  
 
Subject:  Modeling of rocket nozzles; effects of nozzle area ratio. 
 In the last lecture we saw how the throat area of the nozzle controls the mass flow rate. Now we will explore the effects of the shape of the nozzle downstream of the throat. 
 
The Mach number and hence velocity at any point in the nozzle is determined by the ratio of the area of the stream tube to the area of the throat (the area ratio), so if we assume that 
 
 a)  The nozzle flows full, i.e. the streamtube shape matches the    shape of the nozzle 
 b)  The flow is supersonic to the point x downstream of the throat, 
 
then we can find M(x) from A(x)/A t and it in turn determines p(x), T(x) and u(x). 
 
As we shall see, it is the pressure that determines whether the nozzle flows full, so it is 
convenient to relate the exit velocity directly to the pressure.  We do this from the Energy 
Equation, 
u2
     Tc!T+  2cp
   u2=2cp(Tc!T)=2cpTc[1T! ] Tc
So at any point in the nozzle where s=s c 
p"!11
    u= 2cpTc[1!( )"]2 pc
and this is independent of whether the nozzle is full at this pressure, because the area is not 
referred to.  In particular, if we apply this at the end of the nozzle where the pressure is p e, 
the velocity at that point is  
p"!11
    ue= 2cpTc[1!(e)"]2 pc
You know from your previous work that if the nozzle flows full the thrust of the rocket can be written 
    
F=m.
ue+Ae(pe!po) 
 
substituting the expression for u e we then have the following expression for F in terms of the 
pressure ratio p e/p0. 
p   ."!11
F=m!2cpTc[1!(e)"]2+Ae(pe!p
 po) 
c
 The mass flow rate is given in terms of c* by  
     m.p!cAt c*
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>30.60.81.01.21.6
1.41.82.0C
F
Area ratio e = A2 lAt
Thrust coefficient C F versus nozzle area ratio for k = 1.20.k = 1.20
Region of flow separation
for conical and bellshaped nozzles Line of optimumthrust coefficientP
2=P3
1 2 4 6 80 40 60 100 8 10 202.02.53.35.010.020.033.350.01003335001000
p1lp3 = 200p1lp3 = 8Maximum value=2.246
Thrust coefficient CF versus nozzle area ratio for k = 1.30.0.60.81.01.21.41.51.82.0CF
Area ratio e = A2 lAt1 2 4 6 80 40 60 100 8 10 20Region of flow separation
for conical and bell shapednozzles Line of optimumthrust coefficientP
2=P31000
500
200
100
50
33.3
10.0
5.0
3.3
2.5
2.020.0p1lp3 = 333k = 1.30
p1lp3 = Maximum value=1.9648Image by MIT OpenCourseWare. After Sutton and Biblarz 2001.
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare. After Sutton and Biblarz 2001.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Combustors; afterburners</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec34/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>34</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
 Subjects: Combustors; Afterburners  Combustors:  The combustor of an aircraft engine releases an enormous amount of heat per unit volume, second only to high-pressure rocket engines.  In designing the combustor we must implement solutions to the following difficulties:  a)  The gas temperature at the outlet is well above the limits of the materials from which the combustor is built.  b)  Kerosene-air mixtures will only burn in a narrow range of mixtures near stoichiometric.  c)  The overall mixture is very lean, and varies over a wide range with changes in the power setting of the engine.  These requirements are met by introducing the fuel as a spray into a primary zone where the combustion is near stoichiometric and is stabilized by a recirculating flow generated by a set of jets from the periphery.  The gas leaving the primary zone is then cooled by mixing with additional air before it exits to the turbine nozzles.  
 
   
There are also a number of secondary requirements to be met, some of which are quite challenging too:  -The burner must be dimensioned to assure re-starting at high altitude, when pressure, and hence chemical rates, are low. Designs that are optimized for cruise may not meet this requirement. -The combustor must have an operating life of over 20,000 h., or some 5,000 cycles. -Pollutant formation must be below legally allowed limits (see next lecture). -The total pressure drop must be small, despite the strong flow turbulence that is purposely introduced for enhanced mixing. -The temperature profile at combustor exit must be uniform (or sometimes must meet some prescribed radial profile).  
1From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.Lecture 34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Now let us look at some of the fundamental phenomena involved in the combustion 
process. The fuels used commonly in aircraft engines (kerosene, JP-4), react with air only in gaseous form, so they must be atomized, vaporized, and mixed with the air, starting from liquid form. Even then, the fuels burn only in nearly stoichiometric proportions, so we have to first burn with such proportions, then mix with air to get the desired temperature. 
As an example, take a stoichiometric mixture of octane  (C
3H8) and oxygen: 
   C 3H8 + 5 0 2  3CO 2 + 4H 20 
 
fuel   ! $ 3(12) +8# &amp; = (0.23)"air%stoich5(32)=0.0633  
whereas normal fuel/air ratios in jet engines are around 0.03. The ratio of fuel to 
stoichiometric fuel is called the fuel equivalence ratio, , and is here seen to be as 
as low as 0.3/0.66=0.45. Normal hydrocarbon fuels do not ignite this far from stoichiometry, even at the relatively high compressor discharge temperture.  In the molecular mixture, the reaction proceeds by molecular collisions. There is an activation energy, A, and the kinetic energy of impact between the reacting 
1molecules   mv
2 must exceed A in order that a reaction to occur.  Since the 2
molecules have a kinetic energy distribution according to Boltzmann 
    f(2
"mv
v2
2)!e2RgT 
v2 "A
the fraction of molecules with  m2&gt;A is  !eRT. The number of such collisions 
per unit volume and time, called the reaction rate, is 
   reaction rate  n-A/RT02   nfuel  n ... e  
so for a given fuel-air mixture we find 
 
   reaction rate  pne-A/RT  
 
where n=2 if 2 molecules are involved, 3 if 3 molecules are involved, etc.  Combustion in premixed gases is the simplest to visualize and in a sense the easie st 
to experiment on, although is not often the actual mechanism in practical combustion systems.  We imagine a flame front propagating into the premixed fuel and air  
fuel &amp; air
mixtureReaction
Products
vflame
       
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The rates of propagation of such flames are determined by a balance between reaction time and products diffusion time, and are roughly as shown in the figure: 
 
  
 This however is the laminar rate.  Turbulence increases the rate by at least two mechanisms.   a) stretching of the flame front   b) wrinkling of the flame front 
Both of these mechanisms are promoted by a high level of fluid turbulence that is generated by the jets of air entering the primary zone and the mixing zone.  Combustor sizing:  The chemical energy density in the burner is the mass of fuel per unit volume, times the fuel heat value, 
E/V =!afh. If the time to full combustion, t 
burnis known, we can 
then calculate the power density as 
     P/V!=afh tburn
The burning time must be estimated differently for design (or cruise) conditions and 
for low-pressure conditions.   
(a) For design conditions  the pressure and temperature are fast enough that the rate-limiting step is not the reaction itself, but the turbulent mixing of the fuel and air, or of the rich primary burnt gas with the dilution air. Let l
t be a 
caracteristic turbulent eddy size (of the order of the combustor diameter or width), and u
t some characteristic eddy velocity (some fraction of the mean 
flow velocity in the burner). Then we estimate tburn!lt/ut. For a numerical 
estimate, take a=3 kg/m3, f=0.027, h=43MJ/kg, ut=u =50 m/s and  lt=0.1 m. 
We then calculate a power density  x
P/V=1.7x109 W/m3 
 which is of the right order, and obviously very high. 
 
 
 
 
3From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>We can now calculate the combustor volume Vc=Pth/(P/V), where the total 
thermal power is Pth=m  afh, and the airflow can be expressed as m  a=!auxAc. 
Substituting and simplifying, the combustor length, Lc=Vc/Ac is found to be  
     Lu
c!xlut 
t
which simply says that the combustor length scales with its width, or with 
whatever determines the  eddy size. We could call this photographic scaling.   
(b) At low pressure, chemical reactions limit the combustion time, and assuming a bi-molecular reaction mechanism, 
n n C(T) t =products products
burn = !  n  producs R(T)n1n2"a
The power per unit volume is now proportional to the air density, and repeating the steps of case (a), we arrive at a combustor length estimate 
    
Lc!C(T)ux "a
which is independent of width or any other size parameter. In other words, 
the chemically-limited combustor length is independent of engine size. 
 Roughly speaking, the larger of the two estimates must be chosen in order to satisfy conditions both at design and at low pressure. For a given engine family, the smaller engines will be chemically limited and will all tend to have equal length combustors (so the combustor is most prominent in the smallest of them), but at some larger size, length will need to be increased in proportion to width in order to obtain sufficient mixing.       Afterburners:  The afterburner faces a different set of requirements  a) High outlet temperature b) High flow Mach number c) Low pressure drop required when non-afterburning d) Accepts flow from both core and fan  In afterburners the flame needs to be stabilized by bluff bodies, usually triangular in shape as indicated in the diagram. This is because the flame speed, even accounting for turbulent effects, is not as large as the mean flow speed, and the flame would be carried away without some recirculatory zone where combustion has time to occur.   
 
 
 
 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
  Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission. 
The requirement for stability is that the fuel-air mixture spend a certain time,  c, that 
is required for the chemical reactions to initiate, in the mixing layer adjacent the 
recirculating wake.  So the flow time  f must be greater than this "chemical time"  c.  
From the flow geometry,  
L    f =   V
So we require 
L      &gt; c V
The length/breadth of the wake region is nearly independent of the absolute 
Lbreadth, so we can say that L = (  )D, and we see that a certain size of flame holder D
is required such that 
 
D L     ( )  &gt;  c V D
Since V and  c are independent of engine size, we find that D is as well.  This is an 
example of lack of geometric scaling, analogous to the low-pressure scaling for the main combustor.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Non-chemical rockets; optimum exhaust velocity</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>So we see that it only makes sense to choose !V c&lt;1 or &gt;1 for such systems.  This is c !V
because for !V&gt;1 the exponential is so small it outweighs the term representing m elect.  c
Expanding the range 0&lt;(!V)copt&lt;1,
  
Let us take a look at the meaning of these results:  
V1) If we choose a  and have given  and V, this gives us the (!
o e )copt, and in turn the
mmaximum pay.   mtot
2) For given V and !Ve, increasing a o (for a faster mission) increases ( )copt, which reduces 
mpay.mtot
m3) For given V and a0 , reducing  e (lighter power plant) increases pay.mtot
Take an example:
  
Suppose that the mission gives as a requirement  V = 104 m/s and technology enables  e = 
melect = 20 kg/kW  = 0.020 kg/WP
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50  Lecture 5
Subjects: Non-Chemical rockets; Optimum exhaust velocity 
1) Non-chemical rockets
A shared characteristic of all non-chemical propulsion systems is that the energy and 
propellant mass are separate initially
Chemical
Chemical
Energy
massmc.
Non-chemical 
Energy
Source
Propulsive    Mass
m.m.c
22
mc
.
There are several possible energy sources:
1)  Solar
a)  Photovoltaic
b)  Solar thermal
c)  Solar pressure
2)  Nuclear
a)  Fissionb)  Radioisotopec)  Fusion?
There are also many ways to bring the mass and energy together to produce thrust, but allbehave according to the rocket equation.
m"V
final=e!c
mtot
or breaking the final mass into its constituent parts,
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Here the group (!eao"V) is determined by technology level 2(!e), the mission 
requirement (V) and how fast we want to achieve it (a o).  So we should consider this 
relation a way to find c opt to maximize m pay/mtot , given V, a o and  e.
Differentiating,
m!(pay)m"V#tot c$a"# (V=e+oV c)( )2=0
(" 2)"!V
c
(!V))2e"(!V
copt
copt =(#ao!V) (2)2
which we must solve for the optimum c/ V). For graphical presentation, let us eliminate the
group (!ao"V) between (2) and (1):  2
m"V
pay=e!cV(1"! ) (3)mtot c
Equations (3) and (2) are represented below over a broad range of V/c: 
 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>m"V
pay! mpropsys+m
=ec!struct
mtotmtot
There are 2 general categories of systems, Thermal and Electrical, separable according to 
whether the energy is available in electrical or mechanical form, or only as thermal
energy at some limiting temperature.
A. Thermal
Here the energy is used directly to heat the propellant, which is then expanded 
through a nozzle to produce thrust.  
CTc Energy
Propellant
Now there is a chamber temperature T c, limited by the energy source, and the exhaust
velocity is given approximately by:
c22cpTc= or c!2"RcpTc! T2 "#1Mc
What limits T c? 
1)  Source Temperature  e.g. Tsun = 6000K
2)  Materials 
So for these we generally want low M, e.g., H 2 ! 2H.  For a nuclear thermal rocket
H2
graphitecT&lt;~3000K
c &lt; 8500 m/s
Figures of merit are: a)  Specific impulse, c; b)  Thrust per unit mass, F
mengg
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>B. Electrical
 
If the energy is available in electrical form, then there is no limit in principle on c (other 
than the speed of light) and in practice we can achieve very high c with good efficiency by using any of a number of electrical accelerators.
The system requirement is to produce a V on a payload, m
pay.  In the absence of gravity 
mloss, "V
final=e!c, so why not make it very close to 1 by increasing c?  To see the answer mtot
we must analyze the whole system, and take account of the mass of the energy source.
m.
m, c
.mmpaymelectP
maccel
propellant
The total mass of the system can be broken out as: 
mtot = m pay + m elect + m prop + m eng + m struct
so that ratio of final mass to initial mass is 
m"V
final! +cmpay melect+meng+m=e=struct
mtot mtot
The Figure of Merit for such a system is 
m"V
pay=e!cm!elect+meng+mstruct
mtot tot
Letus neglect meng+ mstruct for the moment, compared to m
m  + melect (or simply redefine m  to 
include eng struct , which makes sense for some missions) .pay
We know that:
F=m  c 
and the power P is
Pm  c2Fc! =2 2
Define a specific weight m!e"elect, and an initial acceleration aF
Po= . Thenmtot
m"V
pay=e!c#!eP"V
=e!c#!eFc
mtot mtot 2mtot
or finally in terms of the minimum number of dimensionless parameters,
m"V
pay=e!c!(#eao"V c)( ) (1)mtot 2 "Vm
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>aThen !e o"V = 100 a o where a o is in m/s2.2
We can still choose how fast we want to do the mission, within limits.  We know that the
upper limit of !eao"V = 1/e= .368.  So for the assumed mission and technology, 2
a100a o=!e o"V!.368.  This implies a o !.00368  m/s2 or 3.8x10-4 g's and for this maximum2
mavailable acceleration, pay m = 0, not a very useful result!  Suppose we insist on pay = 0.5.  mtot mtot
This gives (!v) = .3, which in turn implies !eao"v= .07. The acceleration is then a o = copt2
.07 = 7x10-4 m/s2 = 7x10-5 g's.  This is only about 1/5 the maximum acceleration, but now100
we have lots of payload. 
The time required to achieve the V is  
"V
mpr m!
opellant 0(1!ec)ct= = 1"V
= (!e!c)
 m! F/c a0
and for our example, 
104/ 0.3t="4(1"e"0.3)7
7!10!1.23!10s.=142 days
 
This type of propulsion requires patience! Note that for a H 2, 02 rocket,
m#Vm104
pay!e" "
c"struct!e4500".1!.0084  mtot mtot
So we would probably use 2 stages.  But the main point is the very much smaller payload to 
total mass ratio of the chemical system. In addition, if the coasting period for a chemical
rocket is very long, as in an interplanetary transfer, a continuous low thrust can in many casesaccelerate the mission.
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Modeling of thermal rocket engines; nozzle flow; control of mass flow</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Nozzle Flow
Let us focus on the Nozzle Flow first.  For this purpose we regard the combustor as just a
source of hot gas of known chemical composition, stagnation temperature T c and stagnation 
pressure p . c
We have already used a very simple model to represent the result of this flow process.  
Assuming that the expansion was to zero pressure and therefore zero temperature we used 
conservation of energy to show that  
c=2cpTc=2!RT!"1c   (model 1)
where c was defined as the "exhaust velocity" meaning the velocity which, multiplied by themass flow rate, gives the thrust.  Now we want to explore the fluid mechanical processes in 
more detail, and also represent the characteristics of the gas more accurately.
The gas is in fact a mixture of gases resulting from the combustion process Its composition is 
specified in terms of mole fractions y
i of species i or mass fractions x i of species i.
For example if the rocket burns H 2 and O 2 in a mixture ratio of 3 moles of H 2 to 1 mole of
O2to produce H 20 and H 2, (by mass O/F=32/(3x2)=5.3, comparable to O/F=6 in the Shuttle
SSME engine),
3H2+02!2H20+H2
then the mole fractions and mass fractions of H 20 and H 2 are as shown in the table.
 H 2 H 20
x 1/19 18/19
y 1/3 2/3
With these mole or mass fractions we can compute the properties of the gas mixture, such as
the specific heats, the gas constant and .
The fluid-mechanical and heat transfer phenomena that are of importance to describe are:
1) The effects of nozzle shape on flow
2) The effects of chemical reactions during the flow
3) The heat transfer from the flow to the nozzle
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50  Lecture 6
Subject: Modeling of Thermal Rocket Engines; Nozzle flow; Control of mass flow
Though conceptually simple, a rocket engine is in fact physically a very complex device and 
difficult to represent quantitatively by mathematical models.  But the difficulty and high cost
of arriving at a successful design makes it essential that the  performance-limiting 
phenomena be described as accurately as possible.  It is no longer feasible to approach thedevelopment of a new rocket engine by a purely cut-and-try method.
The range of phemomena that must be dealt with is suggested by the sketch.  They range
from the fluid dynamics of the pumping system through the very complex phenomena ofcombustion to structures with heat transfer rates beyond those experienced anywhere otherthan in reentry from space. 
Hot gas, Tcpc 3D Supersonic Flow
Fuel OxidizerPump
Thrust Chamber
mixing and combustionq
Heat Transferu epe
To deal with this complex situation, we use models that represent adequately the phenomenawe want to deal with, while suppressing other phenomena.  Some models we will find useful
are those for:
1) Turbopumps
2) Injectors
3) Combus ion
4) Nozzle Flow5) Heat Transfer
6) Structure of combustion chambers and nozzles
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>and then from (3) 
p  c !=(1"1!
+ M2)!"1 p 2
With these we can write (1) in the form, 
p p T 1 T pm.
=!uA= uA=cM"RTc RT pcT RcTcTc
=(1!"1! 1
+ M2)" +!"12pMc!T/RA 2 Tc
c
m.
! M=pAcRT 1!+1 
c(1!"+ M2)2(!"1)
2
For given (and constant) p c and T c, this expression gives the mass flow per unit area as a 
function of the Mach number M.  Since the mass flow is constant, we have the desired 
expression for M as a function of A(x). 
We see that the mass flow per unit area, u, is proportional to the stagnation pressure and 
inversely proportional to the square root of the stagnation temperature. 
It is both conventional and useful to plot the function of Mach number in ratio to its value at 
the point in the flow where M=1. The value of u at this point we call 
"+u*. It is given by
1
*"# "+1'
(!u)p% 2("'1)=cRT $ 2&amp; 
C
Then the ratio is  
"+1
$ 1 ' 2("#1)
"+
!u A* &amp; ) 
= = M*&amp; 2
1) !u A 1"#&amp; + M2) % 2 ( 
This function of M is shown in the figure. 
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Effect of Nozzle Shape 
 
The phenomena that influence the coupling between nozzle shape and the flow can be 
divided into two general classes, first those associated with the gas dynamics and second those associated with the properties of the gas. Depending on how accurately we attempt to model each of these, our model of the flow can vary enormously in complexity.  The range of 
possibilities is shown schematically in the figure, where sophistication of the modeling 
increases away from the origin along two axes, one measuring gas dynamics, the other fluid properties.  
 
Along the gas dynamic axis the description can range from the simple channel flow model that we will discuss here to very sophisticated three-dimensional descriptions of the transonic flow.  Similarly along the properties axis the range is from the thermally and calorically 
perfect gas model we will use (often called the "ideal gas") to full kinetic description of the 
effects of chemical reactions that occur as the gas flows through the nozzle. The simplest model of all (Model 1) equates the kinetic energy of the exhaust flow to the thermal energy in the chamber 
 
Here we will limit the discussion of the coupling of flow to the geometry of the nozzle to a simple model (Model 2) at the origin.  The implications of the more complex phenomena will then be discussed separately through two more models.  Model 5 will deal with the effects of 
chemical reactions, and Model 3 with the effects of nozzle shape other than the simple area 
variation. Model 4 will represent some special chemical and fluid mechanical aspects of solid rocket motors.  
 CFD+Combustion MOC with 
ideal gas 
Dusty flow 
Frozen, but c p(T) 
One-D reacting gas 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Some of the dominant features are: 
1) There is a maximum in the mass flow per unit area at M=1. 
2) For M&lt;1, u (and also u) increases with M, so M increases with decreasing A. 
3  For M&gt;1, u (and also u) decreases with M, so M increases with increasing A. 
We note however that p always decreases with increasing M.  It follows that if we want to 
increase M from a small value to one in excess of 1, as we do in a rocket nozzle, the nozzle 
should be shaped as in the sketch at the beginning of the lecture, with a convergence to a 
minimum area "throat", followed by a divergence. 
For given p cand T c, the area of the throat controls the mass flow. 
To get an idea of the required throat size we can evaluate the (dimensional) factor in front of 
the function of M for a set of typical values.  
Say p c = 100 atm = 107N/m2
Tc = 3000K
!=1.2 
 R =8.32 x103
 = 640 J/kg/K13
 
!p =107 1.2=7.91x103
c kg/m2/s RTc (640)(3000)
 
We define the throat of the nozzle as the point of minimum area, where M=1 and call the area there A
t.  Then
 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>m.
! 2!+1
= ( )2(!"1 ) pcAt RTc!+1)
The conclusion that the point of minimum area in the nozzle controls the mass flow is valid 
beyond the limits of our simple ideal gas mode.. More generally, we define a quantity c* by 
m.p!cAt that is a measure of the mass flow per unit area at the throat. For the ideal gas c*
model, 
RT 1!+1
c*c!+= ( )2(!"1) ! 2
For the example above, 
(640)3000 2.2c*= ( )5.5
1.2 2!2138m /s
In general c* depends only on the propellant combination  and p c. 
One further condensation of these formulas that is sometimes useful is to define the 
2"+1
quantity  !="( )2("#1), which is close to 0.65 for most values of , and then write "+1
c* RT=c p;m  =cAt
! c*
 
 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Model 2: Channel Flow of Perfect Gas
The channel flow model (often erroneously referred to as "one-dimensional flow") is one in 
which the entire flow is considered to be in a single stream tube having a mass flow that is 
constant along the axis of the stream tube. The stream tube is considered to be narrow enough that the angle of the walls to the axis may be considered small, the gas properties 
nearly constant across the stream tube, and the components of velocity normal to the axis 
small enough that their squares are negligible compared to that of the streamwise velocity. 
If the cross-sectional area of the streamtube is denoted A(x), the conservation of mass 
becomes
uA(x) = m.
= constant (1)
The conservation of energy becomes
hu2
+ = h(Note: v2
&lt;&lt;1)2cu2
or if the specific heat is assumed constant.
cpTu2
+ = c2pTc (2)
The final relationship defining the flow is a connection between two of the thermodynamic properties of the fluid. In general this is a description of the variation of the entropy of the 
fluid along the flow direction.  For our simple model we assume that the flow is Isentropic  (Adiabatic and Reversible).  The entropy is referred to a reference state which we take to be 
the chamber condition.  Conventionally, we assume that the velocity in the chamber is low 
enough that this is also the stagnation condition in the chamber.
s!sT
c="cdT
p !R!np=
T0
cT pc
so if s is constant, and cpis as well,
cp!nT
p !R!n=0Tc pc
and from this it follows that
T pR
=( )Cp p!"1
=( )!
Tcpc pc (3)
where
c!"p; cp-cv=Rcv
We want to manipulate these three relationships to arrive at an expression giving the 
variation of Mach number with A, hence with x.  We begin by expressing equation (2 )in the 
form:
T u2!"1 u2
c=1+ = 1+ M2,M2!T 2cpT 2 "RT
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Models for rocket engines; flow of reacting gases</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>This substance has physical properties much like those of water, but has a positive Standard 
Heat of Formation of 50.6 kJ/ mole.  If we assume for now that it decomposes to produce N 2 
and H 2, and the enthalpy of each can be approximated by c pT, then the chamber temperature 
is given by 
   [cpN 2+2cpH 2](Tc!T0)="H0
f,N2H4 
 
where the specific heats are per mole if the heat of formation is as well. In this argument we 
have assumed that the products of combustion are nitrogen and hydrogen.  In general there might be some ammonia and perhaps other compounds in the decomposition products of hydrazine.  We will see how to deal with this in the following discussion. For a first-cut 
estimate, say both N
2and H2 behave as ideal diatomic molecules with =1.4, so that, for each 
of them, cp=/(-1)=1.4/0.4*8.314= 29.1 J/mole/K. We then obtain Tc-T0=580K, and if 
T0=298K, Tc=878K. 
 
Now let us extend the argument to the somewhat more complex situation of a H 2 - O 2 liquid 
bipropellant rocket 
 
  
  
 
To avoid some complexity, we assume that the hydrogen and oxygen are gases, at 298.16K.  
They react to form products according to 
 
  H2+nO2!"H2O+#H2+$OH+%H+&amp;O2+'O 
 
Here n is set by the mix of propellants injected, but the coefficients on the right side are to be determined. We regard p
c as given for this discussion. Actually it is set by the nozzle throat 
area for specified mass flows of hydrogen and oxygen, which in turn are determined by the 
pressure differential across their injector orifices, and the total orifice areas. So we have to 
find T c and the values of !,",#,$,%,&amp; for given n. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>To find !,",#,$,%,&amp; (6 unknowns), we first note that the total moles of hydrogen and 
oxygen atoms must be equal on the right and left.  In general we must have Conservation of 
Atomic Species 
H: 2!+2"+#+$=2 (1)
O:!+"+2#+$=2n (2)
If the reaction products are in Chemical Equilibrium (as we shall assume) the other four 
relations needed to find the six unknowns are provided by the Law of Mass Action, which provides a set of relationships between the pressure of each of the compounds which is not an element and the pressures of its elementary constituents.  These expressions take the form of 
Equilibrium Constants defined through the stoichiometric relationship for formation of each 
of the compounds:  
 
H2+1
2O2!H2O KpH 2O(Tc)p
=H2O
pH2(p12 (3)
O2)
H2!2H KpH(Tc)p2
=H(4)pH2
H2+O2!2OH KpOH(Tc)p2
=OH(5)pH2pO2
O2!2O KpO(Tc)p2
=O(6)pO2
The actual choice of reactions to be equilibrated is arbitrary, as long as the chosen set can 
be used to generate by linear combinations any of the included species out of the major 
expected product species. In our case we mainly expect to see H2O and, since the mixture is 
purposely fuel-rich (n&lt;1/2), excess hydrogen in the form of H2. It is a good practice to select 
reactions in which only one of the minor species appears, so as to facilitate iteration 
starting with the majors only. In the set above, this is true of all but reaction (5), in which two 
minors (O2, OH) appear. We can replace (5) by the result of eliminating O2 between (3) 
and (5), namely 
2
H22K2p+OH!2HpH2O=H2O
2O (5)KpOHpH2pOH
As indicated by the functional expression, the K's are dependent only on the temperature.   This can be shown fairly readily by general thermodynamic arguments. Because of the wide latitude in selecting the set of reactions to equilibrate, Standard thermodynamic tables do not 
list all possible K
p(T), but they do list the basic quantities from which they can be calculated, 
namely, the Standard Chemical Potentials, 0
i(T)(molar Gibbs Free Energies at 1 atm.  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>which the reactions occur at standard temperature and pressure while heat is added or 
removed in the amount necessary to keep the temperature constant, and the volume is 
expanded or contracted as needed to maintain the pressure constant as well. The heat added 
in such an ideal process is defined as the Standard Heat of Formation !H0
f of the products if 
the reactants are the elements in their standard states. 
 The second step involves using the heat added in the first step to change the temperature of 
the products.  The temperature change is then given by the Steady Flow Energy Equation as  
h(T0
p,p0)!h(T0,p0)=!"Hf 
where the products are indicated by the subscript p and the reactants by the subscript 0, but 
note that the pressure is the same in both states. 
 
Every chemical substance has a Standard Heat of Formation defined in this way.  For 
example for water, 
H1
2+O22!H2O(l)
 
"H0
f,H2O(l)=#68.3174 kcal /mole
The rather cumbersome notation is necessary to indicate that the reaction product in this case is liquid water. The heat of formation of gaseous water would differ from this by the heat of 
vaporization. 
Note that the heat of formation of water is negative, so that heat is released in its formation.  
The convention that heat added is positive is purely arbitrary. 
From the definition of the heat of formation, it is zero for the elements in their standard 
states.  
In general one should remember that substances that are stable at normal temperature and 
pressure have negative heats of formation, those that are unstable (explosives) have positive heats of formation. 
As a simple example of the application of these ideas to rocket engines, consider a monopropellant rocket engine using Hydrazine, N
2H4: 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50  Lecture 10   
Subjects:  Models for rocket engines; Flow of reacting gases
Models for Rocket Engines
In Lecture 6 we described in general terms a set of models we might use to describe the
various features of rocket engines, making the point that no one model incorporates all thefeatures. The models we have discussed thus far are: 
Model 1;
c2
=c2pTc
which simply equates the kinetic energy of the exhaust to the thermal energy in thechamber, ignoring all questions of efficiency and gas dynamics.
Model 2;, which describes the nozzle flow for c
p and   constant, enabling an 
approximate description of the effects of the pressure expansion ratio and of the gas
properties.  This resulted in the definitions of the Thrust Coefficient c F, and 
Characteristic Velocity c*, which are applicable for more general situations than thismodel represents.  The model in turn gave us approximate formulae for estimating c
F
and c* for particular nozzle geometries and propellants.  
Model 3, which describes the behavior of the flow in terms of the actual geometry of
the nozzle, but within the simplification of ideal gas behavior.
Model 4, which dealt with Solid Propellant Internal Ballistics.  This models the gas
formation process for solid rockets, combined with the most important fluid 
mechanical phenomena governing the burning rate and stability.
In all of these models, the properties of the gases in the combustion chamber were taken asgiven.  It should be clear by now that this is a key issue in understanding rocket engines.  So we need a model that connects the properties of the gases in the chamber to the propellantcharacteristics, i.e. a model that describes the combustion process.  This set of processes we
term Combustion Thermochemistry.  We will treat it as Model 5.
Model 5 - Combustion Thermochemistry
In this model we want to represent what happens in the combustor, to convert liquid 
propellants (one or two) to hot gases at T
c and p c.  Qualitatively, what happens is that the 
difference between the chemical energies of the reactants (the chemicals injected into thecombustion chamber) and that of the reaction products ( the hot gases we seek to describe) shows up as thermal energy of the latter. To describe this quantitatively it is helpful to show
it as a sequence of two steady flow processes.  The first is the formation by chemical
reactions of the products from the reactants at standard temperature and pressure.  Of coursesuch a process cannot happen in an isolated reactor, but we can think of it as a process in 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>partial pressure), or the Standard Entropies, s0
i(T), also at 1 atm. pressure. For example, the
equilibrium constant for reaction (3) above is calculated as
10
KpH2O=exp[H2O!0
H2!0
!2O2]!T
where each of the chemical potentials is read from the tables for the given T. If the standard 
molar entropies are listed instead, we can calculate first each of the standard chemical 
potentials as 0
i(T)=hi(T)!T s0
i(T), where hi is the molar enthalpy. 
Returning to Eqs. (3)-(6), each of the p's can be written in terms of , , etc, if p c is set.
Thus if !"#+$+%+&amp;+'+( then by Dalton's Law of Partial Pressures,
p!p p!p!
H2O=c H2=c     p!
OH=pc pH=pc p!
" " " "O2=p"c p!
O=p"c
We will continue this discussion in the next lecture.
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Turbines; stage characteristics; degree of reaction</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec27/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>27</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>These coefficients can all be readily visualized from a scaled velocity triangle in 
which the blade speed r is taken to be unity: 
Vb b 
 Vb
 1 
/2 R 
 
Drawing the velocity triangles for R= 1/2 (called 50% reaction) and for R=0 (called
Impulse),  
In the 50% reaction turbine the pressure drop in the moving blades equals that in 
the nozzles, while in the impulse turbine there is no pressure drop in the buckets. It all takes place in the nozzles. 
In designing the turbine we have some latitude in choosing the degree of reaction R. The tangential velocity of the blades, hence M
T, is limited by the 
strength of materials at high temperature, so it may seem that we would like to use small R to maximize the temperature drop per stage.  But the efficiency of theturbine decreases as R is decreased from R=1/2 toward R=0.  The reason is that the boundary layers have more tendency to separate in the moving blades for R=0 than for R=1/2 because for R=0 there is no pressure drop as the flow isdeflected. 
Radial variations: Just as for the compressor, the requirement for a constant temperature drop from
hub to tip across the turbine flow path, places constraints on the degree ofreaction. Since M
T is proportional to radius, it is larger at the tip than at the hub
of the blades, so if Mb is about constant, R must decrease from the tip to the hub.  
Thus typically if the degree of reaction is near 1/2 at the tip it may be considerably smaller at the hub. 
4From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>(Vc')2 - (V b')2 change in KE in rotorR = = (Vc')2 - (V b')2 + V b2 - V a2 Total change in KE 
Then, for constant axial velocity. 
sec2 !c '"sec2 !b ' R = (sec2 !c '"sec2 !' b + sec2 !b "1) 
For zero exit swirl, i.e. v c = 0. 
vc = r  w tan c' = 0; tan c' = r= MT 
w Mb cos b 
and with this relation we can eliminate c' from the expression for R. 
Similarly,  
r MTw tan b' = w tan b -r; tan b' = tan  b -w = tan  b -Mb cos b 
Using sec2 = 1 + tan2 we can now eliminate  b' and find 
Mb Sin bR = 1 -2 
and using this to eliminate M b Sin b in the expression for the temperature ratio 
(-1)M T2 
1 -t = 2(1-R) ( zero exit swirl)  
1 + 
2-1Mb2  
From this result we see that  for a value of M T limited  by stresses and the
temperature and for a given value  of M b, the temperature drop in the turbine, hence 
its work per unit of mass flow, is related to R.  As R increases the work decreases. An alternative often used representation is in terms of the so-called flow and power 
coefficients,  and . The definitions are 
$ht vb % vc w ; # = = ! = "r ("r)2 "r 
For zero exit swirl, vc=0, we can also put ! = vb /("r) = Mb sin#b / MT , so that 
" R = 1! or " = 2(1! R)2 
which very directly shows how the stage power decreases with the degree of
reaction. In terms of flow coefficient and stator exit angle, 
1R = 1! 2 " tan#b 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>expand the flow to a high velocity and turn it, imparting an angular momentum to 
the flow. The buckets generally further expand the flow, and turn it back toward the axialdirection. The combination of the two blade rows is called a Turbine Stage. Here we use the alphabetical notation to avoid confusion with the numerical station notation for the engine. Station a is equivalent to station 4 in the engine layout, andfor a single stage turbine, station c should be equivalent to station 5 in the engine. Ageneral stage layout is indicated at the top and two specific blade types at thebottom. 
From the Euler equation, for the general situation, 
cp (Ttc - Ttb) = (v crc - vbrb) 
Ttc rc rb1 - = (  v b - vc)Ttb cpTtbrc
Let us assume r b/rc = 1, and also that v c = 0 . The latter is desirable if the rotor is the 
last stage of a turbine, in order that there not be swirl in the flow entering the jet nozzle. 
T
tc (rb)
1 - = 1 - t = v b Ttb cpTtb 
Writing this in terms of Mach numbers and the flow angles indicated in the 
diagram, with vb = Vb sin !b = " RTb Mb sin !b , and !rb = " RTb MT , 
(!"1)MT MbSin#b1 -t = (No exit swirl )!"11+ Mb 22 
Here M T is the tip Mach number of the blades and M b is the flow Mach number. 
From this we can see that we want large M T and large M b Sin for large work per 
stage. 
Degree of Reaction 
As for the compressor there are many possible design choices for the turbine.  One 
key choice is the relative amounts of pressure drop in the nozzles and buckets.  This is best characterized in terms of the Degree of Reaction, which we will define as the ratio of static enthalpy change in the rotor to that in the rotor plus stator (stage):
hb ! hcR =  (hb ! hc ) + (ha ! hb ) 
We now use energy conservation in the moving frame of each element: 
1
2 12 h
a + 12 V
a 2=  hb +12 V
b 2 2V !b
to obtain the alternative interpretation Vc!2; hb + hc + =  
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
 Subjects: Turbines; Stage characteristics; Degree of reaction  Turbines behave according to the same principles of dynamic energy exchange as compressors.  However they differ from compressors in some important ways.  First since they extract energy from the flow rather than adding it, the pressure drops throughout a turbine. This leads to different fluid mechanical limitations than for compressors.  Second, because of the thermodynamic requirements, they operate in gases at high temperatures, so that materials and cooling requirements are of central importance.  We will begin by exploring the fluid-mechanical energy exchange in the turbine.    Euler Equation:  The exchange of energy is described by the Euler equation, just as for compressors.  We will discuss here only axial flow turbines such as are generally used in aircraft engines, but it is important to realize that turbines in fact come in a wide variety of types, from extremely large hydraulic turbines for hydroelectric power generation to  the familiar lawn sprinkler. 
 
.  
  Axial flow turbines use a stator blade row (usually called a nozzle row) followed by a rotating blade row that extracts the energy (often called the buckets).  The nozzles 
1From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.Lecture 27</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Solid propellant gas generators; stability; grain designs</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec9/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>So we have:
stability for n &lt; 1
instability for n &gt; 1
The time scale for growth is Vcc* , and using (1 )!c=pc/(RTc) andm!=pA/c*,!nRTcA c t
t
t1#
growth!cVct!residence
1"nm  1"n
For typical values, this time is about 1 millisecond, which is of course short compared to 
most rocket burning times, so we conclude that if n&lt;1 the chamber pressure will relax from a 
perturbation in a time of order of 1 millisecond.  If n&gt;1 the rocket will explode in about the 
same time. Grain Designs
 
The burning time is set by mission requirements, in particular by the acceleration level of thevehicle. For example for an acceleration of 2 "g's" and a propellant fraction of 0.7,  
tc[1m(t) 2500= ! ]" [.7]"89secao m(o) 2(9.8)
The regression rate as quoted above is about 0.7 cm/s, so in the direction normal to theburning the thickness of the grain must be about 56 cm.  Grain Designs
 
The geometry of the grain must be chosen so as to meet the above requirements.  Thesimplest grain configuration is what is termed "end burning".  
 
 
a)  End burning:
Here the grain regresses axially across the end facing the nozzle.  The outer (cylindrical) 
surfaces of the grain are generally bonded to the case with an intermediate layer of insulating 
material such a rubber and coated with a substance that inhibits decomposition.  As the grain recesses it leaves the layer of rubber, which protects the case from the hot combustion gases. This type of grain works well if the size of the grain needed for the application results in a 
length that matches the desired burning time. But if the two do not match then a design must 
4Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.Ab
CRubber insulation
r</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Once the rocket is built and ignited, it has a mind of its own.  That is p c, Tc, r and the mass 
flow  are all set by the propellant properties and geometryof the grain.  For design purposes 
we want to find the relationship between these performance parameters and the geometry.
 
First assume the rocket is operating in steady state, then
m  rApcA
p=b!p=t c*
and using the above expression for the regression rate,
apn
cAp
b!p=cAt c*
where A b is the "burning area", ie the surface area of the grain that is regressing. Solving for 
pc gives 
p1!n
c=ac*A"b
p (1)At
So given the propellant properties we can compute the chamber pressure, and the mass flow
of the propellant.  Combined with a nozzle model, this enables us to compute the thrust of the
rocket and its specific impulse Stability
 
This relationship applies if  the operating point is stable,  that is if the pressure and mass flow 
are steady in time.  If a, n, c*, 
p are all well defined, we can get p c from it.  Note however  
that p c depends on A b and that it can be sensitive to unintended variations in the grain 
configuration..
 
Cracking of the grain or its debonding from the case can lead to increases in the burning area, 
very high p c and an "explosion".  This is probably the most frequent cause of solid rocket 
failures. 
We have assumed that there is a steady p c. To determine whether this is a stable operating 
point, we first construct a model that allows unsteady behavior of p c. In first approximation, 
unsteadiness implies a variation in the mass stored in the chamber, which modifies the mass 
balance we used to determine p c. 
 d(. p A!Vc
c Adtc)=rb!p"t
c*
2TcAb
pc
AtVcC
LCrack
r
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>c) Segmented Grains
 
The normal process for manufacturing solid propellant grains consists of mixing the 
ingredients in a batch process (essentially a big food mixer), then pouring it into the case, where the rubber matrix cures.  Because of limits on the size of the mixer and for safety and transportation reasons, the amount that can be poured into a single case is limited.  So for 
very large rocket motors such as the Space Shuttle Solid Rocket Boosters, the grain is made 
up of several axial "segments" that are poured separately then assembled to make the complete motor.  It was a failure of one of the case joints that led to the Challenger accident.
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>=apn
cAp
b!p"cAt
c*
d(dV 1dp!Vc
c c)=!c +Vc
c ;T"constdt dt RTcdtc
=!r.
A V1dp+c
c b cRT
  cdt
=!capn V
cAb+cdpc
RTcdt
Substituting above, and noting that !p&gt;&gt;!c , 
Vcdpc p A p A=(!p"!c)Abapn
c"c t
RTcdt c*#!Abapn
c"c t
pc*
Now suppose the chamber pressure consists of a steady part plus one that varies in time, 
 pc = p co + p c(t)  where p c&lt;&lt;p co
Vcd!pc=a(p p )nA(pco+!p
co+!
cdtc b "p#c)At
RT c*
apn(1!pc)nAp A=co+c
b"p#co t(1!p+ )pco c* pco
!apn(1+n"pc)Ap#$coAt
copb p (1"p+c)
co c* pco
The zeroth order terms on the right hand side cancel out, leaving 
Vcd!pc != )p"papn
coAbn(pc#coAt(!pc)RTcdt pco c*pco
# =apn!1 At
coA% 
$ bn"p! 'pc*&amp; c 
1d!pcRT=c[apn"1AbnA
co #p"t]!pcdt Vc c*
So we have divergence if the quantity in brackets &gt;0, stability if it is &lt;0.  Simplifing 
the expression by use of Eq. (1): 
apn!1A nA"!t aA
co b p ="bn A
p !t=(n!1)At
c* Aac*"bc* c*
pAt
1d!pc RT="cAt(1"n)!pcdt Vcc*
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50  Lecture 9
Subject:  Solid Propellant Gas Generators; Stability; Grain designs
We have thus far discussed two models for the nozzle flow in rocket engines, the Channel 
Flow Model and the Two Dimensional Isentropic Model.  Now we will introduce a model for the source of the hot gases in Solid Propellant Rockets.
Gas Generators
The distinguishing feature of a solid propellant rocket is that the fuel and oxidizer are pre-
mixed.  Typically, a modern propellant consists of:
polybutadiene 14%
aluminum 16%
ammonium perchlorate 70%
It is prepared as a physical mixture of NH
4 ClO 4 grains and aluminum powder in the plastic 
matrix
The mixture reacts at the surface of the propellant grain to produce hot gas.  The surface regresses( i.e. decomposes and evaporates) at  a rate:
r.
=apn
c
where a and n are empirical coefficients.  This is an empirical rule.  There is no straightforward way to derive it from first principles.  The physical processes involved are quite complex, including heat  transfer to the grain by conduction,  convection and radiation, decomposition of the solids, mixing and finally combustion in the gas phase.
Typical values of the empirical constants are:
r = 6.8x10
-3 @ 6.9x106 N/m2
n = 0.15
r = 1,775 kg/m3
and as we shall discuss, such a propellant gives a specific impulse
Is= 260 - 265 sec (at ground)
Is=280  295  sec (in vacuum)
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>be found that gives the right burning length for the particular grain mass that is required for 
the mission.
b) Radial burning:
A configuration that shortens the burning time for a given grain mass is the "radial burning"
grain:
This configuration has the disadvantage that the burning area increases as the grain regresses, 
resulting in an increase of chamber pressure with time, a situation that is undesirable for threereasons. First, the case must be designed structurally for the maximum pressure and it is used
inefficiently for much of the burn time.  Second, at least for launch systems, we want a high 
chamber pressure at the beginning of the burn to provide a high nozzle pressure ratio in thepresence of the high atmospheric pressure. And finally, if the thrust increases with time itexacerbates the increase in acceleration due to the decreasing mass of the vehicle that results
from the propellant consumption, and results in very high g loads at the end of burning.
To get around these difficulties, many large rocket engines use a "star" grain 
configuration that has the objective of maintaining the burning area constant as the grain regresses, or even decreasing it.
c) "Star" grain
These grains have a series of points protruding inward, as shown in the sketch, such that as
the points burn off, they keep the area roughly constant.  In a first approximation one can seethat the periphery of the "star" should be equal to the outer(circular) periphery of the grain, so 
that the burning area is equal at beginning and end.  Detailed geometric constructions have
been developed that keep the area very nearly constant throughout the burn.
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Types of nozzles; connection of flow to nozzle shape</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>There is a maximum angle (equal to 130.5 degrees for =1.4, and 208.5 degrees for  = 1.2).
Nozzle Shaping
How do we shape a nozzle using this information?  Let us assume =1.4 so we can use the
tables, and suppose we want to design a nozzle for (pc/pe)design= 100.
1) Start with Channel Flow to get the exit Mach number and area ratio. For  = 1.4, 
Meis approximately 3.7, and A e/At is 8.2. Suppose we want a nozzle that produces this
Mach number at the exit, and that the flow should be approximately parallel to the axis.  The
nozzle should therefore look something like:
For simplicity, let us assume the flow turns around a corner downstream of the throat, where 
the Mach number is M 0&gt; 1, to an angle 1, and let us indicate just three of an infinite number 
of waves making up the "expansion fan". Since the centerline is an axis of symmetry, the 
waves must reflect from it while canceling the flow deviation, so that the flow downstream of the reflection is axial. When the flow passes through these reflected waves it is deflected toward the axis.  If the wall turns to match this deflection where the reflected wave hits it, the 
wave is just cancelled.  The net result is that the flow arrives at the exit with an axial 
direction and a uniform Mach number.  Because of the crossing of waves from two 
expansion fans, the detailed flow properties at most points need to be computed step-by-step.  
For a good discussion of this see Liepmann &amp; Roshko. Unfortunately time does not permit it here, except for the uniform region just downstream of the sharp turn, where things are simple.
Since the flow is isentropically turned by the corner to the angle  
1, M1is determined by this 
angle, from !(M1)"!(M0)=!1. Also, since the flow is again turned by the second set of 
waves through the same (but opposite) angle, !(Me)"!(M1)=!1. By addition, 
2!1=!(Me)"!(M0)
5M0
M1Me
q1CL
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Mach wave 
a 
V 
 
V V du 
d 
dV 
 
dv 
 
  
 
Associated with this turning is a change in total velocity dV and changes in velocity du and 
dv in the original direction and perpendicular to it. For d  small,  
 
     dv Vd , du dV  
 
From the geometry of the diagram,  
du       tan dv 
and substituting the above values for du and dv, Note - Such a nozzle was originally planned for the DC-X, but was not used because of weight and development cost. It was included in the Rockwell concept for the X-33, which was abandoned for unrelated structural reasons. 
Connection of flow to nozzle shape  Our channel flow model connects the flow Mach number to the area of the flow passage, but it gives no information as to how the area should vary along the axis.  We will now consider another model for the flow, called in its more fully developed form the Method of Characteristics, or MOC. This is our Model 3, that provides a basis for quantifying the connection between the nozzle shape and the flow.  For this purpose we will consider the flow to be in two dimensions, supersonic and isentropic. The same procedures can be extended to axisymmetric flow, but the mathematics are somewhat more involved. For references see the following:  
Kuethe &amp; Chow, pp 219-228 Hill &amp; Petersen, pp 523-530 
  The expansion of the flow in the supersonic nozzle occurs primarily through weak, 
isentropic waves. Such a wave in a supersonic flow stands at an angle  to the flow, and 
turns that flow through an angle d  as shown in the diagram.  
1 1 sin1  sin1  tan1 
V M M2 1  1 tan 
M2  1 a 
  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>b)  The External Expansion nozzle, termed by Rocketdyne the "Aerospike". Schematically, it 
operates with the flow configuration shown in the top figure at design, with the outerstreamtube essentially parallel to the axis and at atmospheric pressure.
At higher back pressures, that is at lower altitudes than the design value the bounding streamline adjusts by moving inward as shown in the lower figure, and there is no problem with suction, and no separation as encountered in the bell nozzle at high external pressure 
conditions. In detail, the flow now has a complex structure, with repeated oblique shocks and 
expansions, but this has little effect on performance.
Advantages cited for this type of nozzle are:
1) Better off-design performance
2) Ability to use modular combustors around a nozzle spike, as suggested by the view
below, looking upstream at the spike.
Disadvantages are:
3) It is difficult to cool the spike.
4) It tends to be heavy, because the structure is not based on simple cylindrical
pressure vessels as in the bell nozzle.
2Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.M0
M0(Me)design
Me&lt; (Me)design
LCLC</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>du dV 1= =dv Vd! M2"1
It follows that we can relate V to  and M 
dV d!=V M2 
"1
From the energy equation we can relate V to M.
T 1 dT "1= (!"
T1!"1# = 1)MdM
M2T1!"
01+ + M2
2 2
M2V2dM dV dT= #2 =2"!RT M V T
"!1MdV dM 12
dT dM= + = !2 dM
V M 2T M 11"!+ M2M
2
dM[1=  M "]d#
11!+ M2 M2"1
2
Rearranging, and counting angles from the sonic point, we have an expression for  in terms 
of M (the so-called Prandtl-Meyer function): 
MM2!1dM(M) = "1 r1! 1+ M2M
2
= !+1Tan"1!"1(M2"1)"Tan"1M2"1 !"1 !+1
This function is tabulated in Kuethe &amp; Chow and Liepmann &amp; Roshko. It is plotted below:
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50  Lecture 8
Subjects: Types of Nozzles; Connection of flow to nozzle shape.
Types of Nozzles
The axisymmetric convergent-divergent "bell" nozzle that has been used as the example to 
this point is the standard for rocket nozzles, for several reasons:
1) Structural - It has essentially only "hoop" or tangential
stresses which are the easiest to design for.
2) Cooling - It can be constructed with walls of simple tubular 
construction that enables the cooling in a straightforward way.
3) Matching to combustor -  It is easy to match to the  
combustor, which is most naturally a simple cylinder.
But it has some disadvantages, which stem from the need to operate at overexpanded conditions at low altitude (specifically, the nozzle is overexpanded, not the flow). The flow
situation shown as the left diagrams in the last lecture implies:
4) An overexpansion thrust loss, whether or not separation occurs.5) Flow instability when overexpanded with separating flow, which may lead to 
uncertainty or unsteadiness of the thrust direction.
These have led to variations on the basic bell nozzle design, and some radically differentdesigns.  Amongst the variations are:
a)  Extendable nozzles. Here the idea is to use the short inner nozzle at low altitudes, and 
deploy the outer extension at high altitudes, so that the expansion ratio is more nearly ideal at
all operating conditions.
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>which determines 1. After this, the Mach number M1 follows directly from either of the
above formulas. Of course, if M0=1, ( M0)=0, and the results simplify further.
 
To get the geometry correct we have to take account of the actual shape of the nozzle throat. 
More important, this whole argument has been in two dimensions and real rocket nozzles are almost always axisymmetric, but again time does not permit discussing these matters.
 
This sort of calculation results in a nozzle that will produce an axial exit flow of uniform Mach number for a given expansion ratio. The length can be excessive, however, and non-idealities tend to cancel the small thrust contributions of the far downstream sections. 
Methods have been developed to generate shorter nozzles while accepting some losses due to 
non-uniformities. The so-called Rao nozzle is the nozzle with the optimal contour for a
given (less than ideal length). 
These same ideas can by used to understand the external expansion, or "plug" nozzle. It looks 
like:
In this case each of the expansion waves from the outer "lip" is cancelled by a turn in the 
contour of the center body, so that there is just one family of expansion waves.  This can be 
either a two-dimensional nozzle or an axi-symmetric one.  It is the basis for the Aerospike 
nozzle projected for use in the X-33 by Lockheed Martin. It has also been used for aircraft, 
eg. the F-4, in which the underside of the aft fuselage provides the expansion surface.  Such a 
nozzle is also a key ingredient of the SCRAMJET idea, as exemplified by the X-30 and later 
implementations.
6MeM0
CL
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Pollutant; motivations for control; formation; strategies for reduction</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec35/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>35</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>00 = rated pressure ratio F 00 = rated thrust in Newtons 
 
In 1990 FAR 34 was issued by the FAA, regulating only smoke and unburned hydrocarbons, 
and setting the limits for these essentially at the values attained by the oldest engines in 
operation.  
The Committee for Aviation Environmental Protection (CAEP), an international organization 
under ICAO, has periodically updated the emission limits on NO
X. The various CAEP 
regulations, including CAEP-6 , in effect as of 2008, are displayed in the figure below. The units on the ordinate are in grams of pollutant per kN of thrust, averaged over a standard airport turnaround cycle. The abscissa is the overall pressure ratio of the engine. For 
reference, the CAEP-1 regulation is from 1986, and the CAEP-4 is from 1998. It is clear that 
the trend is to tighten the emission rules over time, and also that commercial engines do comply, as they must, with the rules in effect at the time they enter service (and usually 
ahead of time, in anticipation of further strengthening of the rules). 
Mechanisms for  formation of pollutants;  
The principal pollutants are Unburned Hydrocarbons, Carbon Monoxide, and Nitrogen Oxides. They are formed as follows. 
 
 UHC - mostly at idle and low power, due to poor atomization etc.   Also from
 venting of fuel systems. 
215 20 25 30 35 4090
8070
60
5040
30
20
Overall pressure ratio-12%DP(NOx)/F00(g/kN)CAEP1
CAEP2
CAEP4
CAEP6
CFM56-5A
CFM56-5B/P
CFM56-5B/2P
CFM56-5C
CFM56-5C/PCFM56-7B
CFM56-7B/2
CF34
CF34(LEC)
Dem21
SM146
CFM56-TAPS
ANTLE
CLEAN
RRD LNlll
AST(USA)
UEET(USA)CAEP6-10%
CAEP6-20%
CAEP6-30%CAEP1
CAEP2
CAEP4 CAEP6
FUTURE
PROJECTSCFM
DAC
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Subjects discussed: Pollutant. Motivations for control. Formation. Strategies for 
reduction  
Motivations for control 
 
The motivations for control of emissions from aircraft, other than purely esthetic or ethical, 
stem from legislation regulating the amounts of emission in the neighborhood of airports, and the possibility of regulation of emissions into the upper atmosphere. We will discuss each of 
these in turn.  
 Emissions in airport neighborhoods; 
 
In 1973 the EPA published standards, to go into effect in 1979. They are compared in the 
table to the actual emissions from three engines in wide use at the time the standards were 
issued.  
1979 EPA Proposed Standards 
     1979  
Actual Emissions 
  Pollutant Std  JT8-D JT9D-7 CF6-50 
 
  CO  4.3  1.9  10.4  10.8 
  UHC  0.8  2.7  4.8  4.3 
  NOX  3  8.0  6.5  7.7 
  smoke* 19-20 visible 4  1.3 
 
All values are grams per kg thrust, per hr. in standard approach-taxi-takeoff cycle.  
Rs*  Smoke, SN = 100(1 -  ) , the reduction in optical trans mission through a glass witness plate exposed for a Rw
prescribed time.  
 Since the FAA has regulatory jurisdiction over civil aviation, the implementation of these 
standards fell to it. In July 1973 FAA issued SFAR27 to enforce only smoke regulations but 
1979 regulations were never incorporated into regulating process.  
Note:  Manufacturers lobbied against them on the basis that the increasing pressure ratios 
required for better fuel consumption would make their realization difficult. 
 
In 1981 ICAO issued international emissions standards in terms of g/kg fuel:  
 Pollutant  Standard 
 CO   118  UHC   19.6 
 NOx   40 + 2(
00) 
 Smoke   83.6 (F 00)-.274 
116.50 Lecture 35</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>CO - Due to fuel-rich combustion in primary zone. 
 Smoke - Due to fuel-rich droplet burning by diffusion flames 
 NOx - Following an element of fuel and air through the combustor we would see the 
following history of temperature and concentrations. 
 
   
  
During this transport, NO x is formed by the following sequence of reactions. 
   
N2+O!NO+N; where the O is from (near-equilibrium) dissociation of 
H20, 02 : 
p2
   Kp(T)=0 p02
 
   N+O2!NO+O 
 
   N+OH!NO+H where the H, OH are also from dissociation 
 
d[NO]69,460
   =2k[N2][0]![N2][0 ]1/2"1.45"1017T#1/2e#T
dt2  
(units are mol, cc, K) 
 
The result of this set of reactions can be summarized as in the figure (for 1 atm. pressure, 
starting at 700K). 
3From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>a) Formation of 0 3  (the Chapman cycle): 
 
Molecular oxygen provides a reservoir of O atoms through photodissociation by UV 
solar radiation: 
  O2+h!"O+O 
The atomic oxygen reacts rapidly in a three-body reactionwith molecular oxygen, to 
form ozone: 
  O+O2+M!O3+M 
The population of ozone is mainly controlled by its destruction though 
photodissociaation: 
  O3+h!"O+O2 
   
b) Effect of Nitrogen oxides: 
 
The natural effect is the continuous upwards transport of NO 2 from the troposphere and its 
photodissociation to NO and O. This is followed by ozone destruction by   
   
NO+O3!NO2+O2 
 
The natural transit time of NO 2 from the troposphere is as long as 100 years, so even a small 
amount of NO andNO 2 released in-situ  by high-flying aircraft could potentially lead to a 
strong acceleration of the ozone destruction. 
 
c) Other effects: 
 
In addition to these NOx concerns, recent information suggests that the particulate content of the exhaust, largely sulfuric acid drops formed from the sulfur in the fuel, is a major factor in the overall effect on the atmosphere.  
 
 
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Strategies for reducing N0 x 
 
  a)  Premix and burn lean     b)  Burn rich and then dilute and cool quickly  
 
Upper-Atmospheric Emissions:  
Here the threat is to the 0
3 in the upper atmosphere. No regulations are in place as yet for 
aircraft, although there is an international agreement limiting the manufacture and sale of 
fluorocarbons.  
    
4
From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MITPress, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Thrust vectoring; engine cycles; mass estimates</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>These are difficult to implement. The design issues include 
 a)  Large pressure differences  b)  Sealing against leaks of hot gases Schematically, the joints look like: 
 
   
Pressurization Systems  The systems for pressurizing the propellant for injection into the combustion chamber of liquid bi-propellant rockets range from very simple gas bottle pressurization, to complex engine cycles.  We have time only to outline them here, and indicate some of their advantages and disadvantages. 
 
  
a) Gas bottle pressurization of fuel tanks:  Advantage  Simplicity  Disadvantage - Weight of  both gas and  
  Propellant tanks   
 
            
He 
Valve 
Valve Propellant 
2Rubber in shearCenter of rotation
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>LMass = t[DL + D2] = D2t[1 +   ] D
 
D2 D3 1 1 L   Vol =  [   L +  ] = D3[   +    ] 4 6 6 4 D
 
L L L1 + 1 + 1 + Mass t D t D p D     =      = 4   = 2 t        Vol D 1 1 L D 2 L +   + 2 L + 6 4 D 3 D 3 D
 
L
Tank mass  1 + tp D      = 2        Prop mass p2 L + 3 D
 
 Example: Pressure-fed  Hydrazine (N
 2H4), Nitrogen Tetroxide (N 2O4 ) 
 p c = 20 atm = 2.03x106Pa,   Hydrazine  
       
  Titanium alloy t = 4,100 kg/m3,   8x108 Pa      
L L1+ 1Tank mass 4100 2.03+
      ~ 2 D~ .021D Prop mass62995 800 2L 2L+ +3D 3D
 
or about 0.03-0.04 when attachments are added.   Example: Including  thrust load  During engine operation, the pressure at the bottom of the tank (of length L) is 
p=p0+n!pgL, and this should replace p0 in the calculation. Here n is the sum of 
gravity and acceleration, divided by gravity (i.e., the effective gravity, in gs). If the hydrostatic second term dominates, as it may in long tanks, then we get 
MTank=2n!tgL 1+L/D MProp. " 2 /3 +L/D
Suppose acceleration is 4 g's, the tank length is 30 m, and other data are as before (except that propellant mass does not matter now). We calculate 
Tank mass       = 0.0121+L/D Prop mass2 /3 +L/D
so the static part of the pressure still dominates, but thrust loading does matter.   Note the scaling - worse for large vehicles in this case. =995 kg/m
3 
  
 
 
    
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Advantage - High Isp and simplicity relative to the preburner  
    systems to be described next.   Disadvantages - Complex startup dependent on stored heat in     system, and limit on the chamber pressure that can be     achieved due to temperature limit on turbine drive gas.   Example - RL-10 for Centaur  4) Preburner (Staged Combustion Cycle)  This system predominates in modern high-performance engines.  In US practice most if not all of the fuel is pumped to a high pressure and burned with a part of the oxidizer (to keep the temperature within the limits of the turbine), expanded through a turbine that drives the fuel and oxidizer pumps then injected into the main combustor.  The central feature is that all the propellant goes through the main combustor and nozzle. 
    
  
 
In some Russian engines that use Kerosene as the fuel, the preburner operates oxidizer rich rather than fuel rich.    Advantages - Ability to operate at very high chamber pressures,      high Isp, and flexibility of a cycle design.   Disadvantages  - Complexity of design construction and startup,      high cost, high pump delivery pressures.   6) Tank Weights (connected to pressure)  How thick do the tank wals need to be? Balancing the pressure forces against the hoop stress in a cylindrical chamber, 
t p    pD = 2t 
!   =   D 2
Assume the cylinder, of length L is terminated with two hemispherical caps: 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>b) Monopropellant or Bipropellant Gas Generator 
 
       
 
In these systems a hot gas is generated either by decomposition of a monopropellant such as H
2O2 or N 2H4 or by combustion of a small fraction of the main propellants.  
The hot gas is expanded through a turbine and dumped overboard, the turbine driving the propellant pumps.     Advantage - Simple start-up even in space, and straightforward      development process   Disadvantage - Overboard dump of exhaust reduces the effective Isp   Examples- V-2 (H
2O2), Atlas, Thor, Delta, Saturn 5, Titan  
 3) Topping Cycle (Expander)  In this system the entire fuel flow is pumped above the injection pressure, heated in the cooling jackets of the nozzle and combustion chamber, expanded through a 
turbine that drives the pump, then injected into the combustion chamber.  
   
  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 Lecture 16 
  Subjects: Thrust Vectoring ; Engine cycles; Mass estimates  Thrust Vectoring  Liquid Bipropellant rockets are usually "gimballed" to change the thrust vector 
                   
 Here all the high pressure pumps and pipes move together, and the flexible joints are in the low pressure feed pipes    Since the case is pressurized in the solid rocket we either have to have a high pressure joint between the case and the nozzle, or a way to deflect the jet from a stationary nozzle.  Because of the design difficulty of the joint, the early motors used jet deflection either by vanes or by gas injection.  1) Jet Deflection 
   
 
More modern solid rockets use movable nozzles with joints that allow rotation by means of shearing motion in elastomer layers between spherical shells. 
Fuel Tank 
Flex Line 
Pumps Actuator (in two 
planes) 
Ball Joint 
1
Vanes deflect jetGas injectionVanes Gas Injection
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Inlets or diffusers</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Note: 
T3-T2=T4-T5 
If the diffusion from point 0 to point 2 is not reversible, the entropy increases, and 
this results in a lower value of P t2. This has two effects: 
a) The expansion ratio of the nozzle is decreased, so the jet velocity and thrust arelower. 
b) The lower pressure at point 2 limits the mass flow through the compressor to a 
lower value than for isentropic diffusion. So there is a double penalty for losses inthe inlet. 
Unfortunately some losses are inevitable, the more so the larger M
o. To see why we
will discuss the flow in supersonic diffusers, beginning with the simplest. 
3From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Diffusers with internal contraction 
One might ask why we do not just use a convergent-divergent nozzle in reverse as an inlet: 
This would work at one design Mach number, the one for which the isentropic area ratio between the incoming supersonic flow and the sonic throat is exactly the as-built area ratio A
1/Athroat . But during the acceleration to this Mach number the fully 
supersonic flow cannot be established in the inlet without varying the geometry.  To see this, imagine the inlet flying at M
o , lower than the design Mach number.  The 
flow will look as depicted in the top right diagram below. This is because at the lower M
0 the flow area that would decelerate isentropically to sonic at the throat is smaller 
than the built A1: 
A/A* 
A1/A* 
A0/A* 
0 1 M0&lt;MD MD 
So, if the flow did arrive undisturbed at the inlet, it could only occupy a fraction of
it, the rest of the flow into the frontal area A1 having to be somehow disposed of. 
This spillage is accomplished by the detached normal shock; behind it the flow is 
subsonic and it can turn around the inlet. Unfortunately, the shock at the full flight
Mach number is very lossy, and it is not practical to simply force the plane to continue accelerating to the design condition (there may not even be enough thrust left to do it). What can be done is to manipulate the geometry to swallow the shock and reduce its strength. This is called starting the diffuser. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.
To "start" the diffuser, meaning to pass the shock through the convergent portion, 
we must increase the throat area until the normal shock is just at the lip. At that point, any further small increase in throat area causes the shock to jump rapidly to a position in the divergent part of the nozzle where the area is again A
1; this is because
the shock is unstable in the converging section, but stable in the divergent section.So far nothing has been accomplished, because the shock is still as strong as it was. But if the pilot now reduces fuel flow, the compressor moves down the operating line to a lower value of 
m2 and since the actual flow rate m does not change any
more, this means a higher total pressure pt2 into the compressor, and hence a weaker 
shock. This is accomplished by the flow through a repositioning of the shock to a location nearer the throat, on the supersonic side. The process can continue until theshock is almost at the throat (if too near, it may accidentally pop all the way to the front (an unstart, which is a violent transient event). The final condition isdepicted in the diagram at the bottom right.  This is an adequate solution for modest values of M
o, but for M o &gt; 1.5 the loss due to 
the shock at the throat is still excessive.    
 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Normal-Shock diffuser: 
All existing compressors and fans require subsonic flow at their inlet with 0.5 &lt; M 2 &lt; 
0.8 at high power conditions. So the inlet must reduce the flow Mach number from 
Mo &gt; 1 to M 2 &lt; 1. The simplest way to do this is with a Normal Shock. 
Here M 1 &lt; 1 is entirely determined by M o, according to the normal shock relation 
1+ !"1 2 
2 2 MoM1 = 2 " !"1!Mo 2 
The stagnation and static pressures are also determined by M o: 
pto = (2!Mo 2 !" 1 ! 1 
"1((!" 1)Mo 2 + 2 ! "! 
1 p1 2!" ) ) = 1+ (M02 "1) pt1 ! + 1 ! + 1 (! +1)Mo 2 p0 ! + 1
For low supe rsonic speeds, such diffusers are adequate because the stagnation
pressure loss is small, but at M o = 2, p t2/pto  .71, a serious penalty, and at M o = 3 
p2t/pto  .32. For example the F-16 fighter has a simple normal shock diffuser, while 
the F-15 has an oblique shock diffuser such as will be discussed next. 
4From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Oblique - Shock diffusers : 
The losses can be greatly reduced by decelerating the flow through one or more 
oblique shocks, the deflection and the pressure rise of each being small enough to be in the range where the stagnation pressure ratio is close to unity. It is very important to understand that an Oblique Shock is in fact just a normal shock standing at an angle to the flow. 
All of the change across the shock takes place because the Mach number normal to 
the shock is larger than unity. The velocity normal to the shock decreases with consequent increases in temperature and pressure, but the velocity parallel to the shock is unchanged: 
M1n is given in terms of M on by the same relation given for M 1 as a function of M o. 
But M on can be made close to 1.  The condition for a weak or sound wave is just M on 
= 1, or 
Sin = M1
o (weak compression) 
By choosing the wedge angle (or deflection angle)  we can set the shock angle. 
A series of weak oblique shocks, for each of which the M n is near unity, hence all
lying in the range of small p t loss, can yield an efficient diffuser. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
Subjects: Inlets or Diffusers 
While the Gas Generator, composed of the compressor, combustor and turbine, is 
the heart of any gas turbine engine, the overall performance of the propulsion system is strongly influenced by the inlet and the nozzle.  This is especially true forhigh M
o flight, when a major portion of the overall temperature and pressure rise of 
the cycle are in the inlet, and a correspondingly large part of the expansion in thenozzle. So it is important to understand how these components function and how they limit the performance of the propulsion system. 
Inlets or Diffusers These two titles are used interchangeably for the component that captures the 
oncoming propulsive streamtube and conditions it for entrance to the engine. The function of the inlet is to adjust the flow from the ambient flight condition, to that required for entry into the fan or compressor of the engine.  It must do this over the full flight speed range, from static (takeoff) to the highest M
o the vehicle can attain. 
Comparing the simple diagrams of subsonic and supersonic inlets, we can appreciate that the subsonic inlet has the simpler task: 
For any inlet the requirements are two: 
a) To bring the inlet flow to the engine with the highest possible stagnation pressure.
This is measured by the Inlet Pressure Recovery,  d . 
b) To provide the required engine mass flow. As we shall see the mass flow can be 
limited by choking of the inlet.  
1From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.Lecture 22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Subsonic Inlets : 
The subsonic inlet must satisfy two basic requirements: 
a) Diffusion of the free-stream flow to the compressor inlet condition at cruise. 
b) Acceleration of static air to the compressor inlet condition at takeoff. 
There is a compromise to be made because a relatively thin "lip" aligned with the entering flow is best for the cruise condition. This is to avoid accelerating the flow, already at a Mach number of the order of 0.8, to supersonic speeds that will lead to shock losses. But a more rounded lip will better avoid separation for the takeoff condition because the air must be captured from a wide range of angles: 
The minimum area, A 1 is 
set to just avoid choking (M= 1) in the inlet when M
2 
has its largest value (this isset by the maximum blade Mach number and the blade shape). 
A well designed subsonic
A1 inlet will produce astagnation pressure 
recovery 
d in the order of 
0.97 at its design condition. 
Supersonic Inlets : 
At supersonic flight speeds
the pressure and temperature rise in the inlet can be quite large.  For the best 
thermodynamic efficiency it is important that this compression be as nearly reversible (isentropic) as possible. At a flight Mach number of 3 the ideal pressure ratio is 
  pto = (1+ ! 
2 "1 Mo 2)!!
"1 =36.7 po 
while the temperature rise is  
Tto = 1+ !"1 2o = 2 Mo =2.8To 
For the turbojet cycle the compression is partly in the inlet and partly in the compressor: 
2From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines .
2nd edition. MIT Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute 
of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Critical speeds and vibration</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec33/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>33</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>and the phase can also be written down, although we omit it here. 
 
The solutions for the amplitude of z (normalized by the eccentricity e) or for F 
(normalized by M2e) are shown below, together with the phase information: 
    
  
Some important points are:  
1)  With no damping,  z/e    and F/e   for    n (resonance 
condition). 
  2)  Damping limits the resonant amplitudes to finite values.   3)  The system can be run above 
n with a flexible shaft or support, in 
which case the  mass rotates about C for very high speed (x and y tend to zero). 
 Now let us ask how the bearing stiffness and damping influence the forces on the structure.   
a) At subcritical speeds, namely, 
2&lt;&lt;2
n, F!"M#2eexp(i#t), and the forces die 
out as the square of the speed, as could be expected. Notice this condition might not mean a very low rotational speed, if the shaft and the bearings are stiff enough, or the rotor is light enough, to produce a very high natural frequency (this is unusual in jet engines, though). 
 
 
3From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50 
  Subjects: Critical speeds and vibration  Critical Speeds   As noted in the last lecture, gas turbine engines are unusual structures in that a large fraction of their mass is rotating at high speed.  Thus, vibration and dynamics have always been a serious issue with them. What is intended here is that the physical phenomena of principal importance be conveyed by study of a set of simplified models.   Schematically, we can think of the rotating system as a mass on a flexible shaft, mounted on flexible supports. If most of the mass resides in the rotor and the part of the shat adjacent to it, we can combine the two flexibilities as two springs in series with a combined stiffness which tends to restore the rotors center to the axis from whatever direction it is deflected into. More complex models, with additional degrees of freedom, would be needed if the bearings and the parts of the shaft near them had a significant mass. We still retain the simpler formulation, but will allow the rotating mass to be mounted eccentrically, to study the loads this can generate.  The schematic below shows the situation. The center of mass C has coordinates (x,y), and the geometrical shaft center, also assumed to be its elastic center, is at S. The center 
of mass is offset by a distance e from S, and rotates with the shaft at the angular rate . 
There is an elastic restoring force k
 e directed from S to O, as well as a viscous 
damping  force, normally provided by an oil squeeze film damper between the shaft and the bearing. This damping force is proportional to the rate of change of that part of OS that comes from the bearing displacement, but since we ignore the mass of the bearings, that distance is a fixed fraction of OS itself (depending on the ratio of shaft to bearing stiffness), and we model it as b
 (de/dt).  
            Y              x          C       
              e  t              
                    
                  S            y                      O      
X  
We can now write a pair of equations of motion, one for x, the other for y:  
1Lecture 33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>M x  =!kxS!bx  S  M y  =!kyS!by  S
where 
   xS=x!ecos"t; yS=y!esin"t 
 
It is actually more convenient to work with a complex displacement z=x+iy, so that a single complex equation is needed:  
    
M!z!=!kzS!bz!S; zS=z!eexp(i" t) 
 
Introducing the natural frequency !n=k/Mand the friction parameter n=b/M, 
and eliminating zS, we obtain 
     
 z  +nz  +!2
nz=e(!2
n +in!)ei!t 
 
The general solution to this equation consists of the homogeneous part alone, with two arbitrary constants determined by initial conditions, plus the forced, or particular solution, determined by the right hand side. The homogeneous solution is a 
superposition of damped sines and cosines at the natural frequency  Because of the 
damping, it will disappear some time after a transient event, leaving o
n
nly. 
 the forced 
solution, which is proportional to exp(it), like the right hand side of the equation.  We concentrate here on the forced solution only (the steady state). Putting z=B exp(it) 
and substituting into the governing equation, we can solve for B, and find  
!2
n +n!i    z=ei!t
!2 2e 
n"! +n!i
 
   zS=z!eexp( i"t)"2
=!ei"t
"2  !2e
n" +n"i
 
The force on the supports is, in complex form,  
    
F=Fx+iFy=!kzS!bz!S=M!z!=!M"2z  
 
where the last form can be directly rationalized as the result of centrifugating the 
center of mass. It is, of course, a rotating force (around O), proportional to exp(it). The 
amplitude of this force is obtained from the expression for z:  
    
F =M!2 !4 2
en +(n!n!)
(!2
n"!2 2 
) +(n!n!)2
   
 
 
 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>(b)  At supercritical speeds, 2&gt;&gt;2
n, and with relatively weak damping,  
#2
z!" en
2!0, i.e., the center of mass tends to remain stationary, with the shaft #
rotating about it.  The force then tends to F!M"2
ne=ke, a constant elastic force 
towards the center of mass (but a rotating force, that transmits to the supports and 
causes vibrations). This is the normal condition for most engines at design speed.   Elaborate procedures are followed to reduce eccentricities to a minimum, but with engine wear, they are difficult to maintain near zero. Their effects can be mitigated by (a) Staying away from operation at a speed equal to the natural (critical) frequency. (b) If normal operation is at supercritical speed, crossing the critical range as quickly as possible, and (c) Providing as much damping as practical with squeeze-film or other dampers. 
     
 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rocket casing design; structural modeling</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>case	&#13; 1,	&#13; =	&#13; 
In	&#13; our 	&#13; =	&#13; 0,	&#13; so	&#13; 2
	&#13; ix	&#13; +	&#13; 
2y	&#13; 	&#13; 	&#13; 
s!x"!
xy
max(y)2 2
 
y	&#13; =	&#13; p
2tcD	&#13; simply	&#13; the	&#13; larger	&#13; of	&#13; +#2xy
	&#13; ;	&#13;  	&#13;  ( x) 	&#13; 	&#13; 
  x
Map	&#13; or	&#13;  y y&gt;x
x.	&#13; and	&#13; usually	&#13;  :	&#13; 
	&#13; =	&#13; 4tcD
	&#13; 	&#13; =	&#13; 1
2	&#13; y	&#13;  
So	&#13; the	&#13; casing	&#13; mu 
st	&#13; be
	&#13; designed	&#13; to	&#13; withstand	&#13; t	&#13; 
pt=Dc"(a safehe	&#13; hoop	&#13; st
ty factor)!ultresses:	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13; 
3)	&#13; 	&#13; C ase	&#13; Mass 	&#13; 
Ag	&#13; 
ain	&#13; assuming	&#13; consta
(!nt
D	&#13; t
2&lt;&lt;D	&#13; and	&#13; hemispherical	&#13; caps,	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13;  M
The	&#13; mass	&#13; of	&#13; the	&#13; propellant	&#13; iscase	&#13; =	&#13;  +!DL)t	&#13; 	&#13;  se	&#13; =	&#13; D3(1+DL	&#13; )	&#13; p

D3	&#13; ca2
D L 1 1c
y	&#13; 	&#13; 	&#13; case	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13;  M
where	&#13;  	&#13; is	&#13; the	&#13; fractionprop	&#13; =	&#13; (	&#13; 	&#13; +	&#13; 
o4
l2
	&#13; )	&#13; 
	&#13; of	&#13; case	&#13; 6
v ume	&#13; 
	&#13; f
illpr
edop	&#13; =	&#13;  D3(	&#13; 	&#13; +	&#13; 	&#13; L	&#13; )	&#13; 
	&#13; by
	&#13; prop6
ella4
nD
t.	&#13; prop	&#13; 
	&#13; 	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13; L p3(1+ )Mc"case
case !=D
Mprop3L(1+ )# "2Dprop	&#13; 
	&#13; 
Typically,	&#13; for	&#13; p c
	&#13; =	&#13; 50	&#13; atm=	&#13; 750	&#13; psi	&#13; ,	&#13;  y	&#13; 	&#13; 150,000	&#13; psi	&#13; (about	&#13; 100kg/mm2	&#13; in	&#13; European	&#13; 
notation),	&#13; and	&#13; 	&#13;  case	&#13; =	&#13; .3	&#13; lnlb
3	&#13; (steel)	&#13;  ,	&#13; 
prop	&#13; =	&#13; .06	&#13; lnlb
3
M	&#13; 	&#13; 
	&#13; fprDL
	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13; case
Mop1	&#13; +	&#13; 
	&#13;  and or	&#13; L	&#13; 	&#13; =	&#13; 3,	&#13; M	&#13; .093	&#13; 
1	&#13; +	&#13; 3
2	&#13; DL	&#13; 	&#13; 
case
Mpr
	&#13; 	&#13; 
Is	&#13; this	&#13; a	&#13; reasonable	&#13; estimateop
?	&#13; For	&#13; the	&#13; Minuteman,	&#13; from	&#13; Sutton	&#13; &amp;	&#13; Ross	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13;  M case	&#13; =	&#13; 2557	&#13; lb	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  M prop	&#13; =	&#13; 45,831	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13; 
	&#13; It	&#13; seems	&#13; we	&#13; have	&#13; been	&#13; somewM
M
hcase=
pr
aop
t	&#13; con0.056
servative	&#13; in	&#13; our	&#13; design	&#13; parameters.	&#13; 
4)	&#13;  What	&#13; is	&#13; left	&#13; out	&#13; of	&#13; our	&#13; estimate?	&#13; 	&#13; .068.	&#13; D
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>a)
b)	&#13; 
	&#13; AtEndta
	&#13; bellschme
	&#13; have	&#13; 1nts	&#13; 
c)	&#13;  Shear	&#13; loads	&#13; on	&#13; pr/2
opellant	&#13; gr	&#13; the	&#13; stress
ain	&#13; -	&#13; ma
	&#13; ke	&#13; 1/2	&#13; as	&#13; thick?	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>I
	&#13; s	&#13; this	&#13; a	&#13; reasonable	&#13; estimate?	&#13; For	&#13; the	&#13; Minuteman,	&#13; from	&#13; Sutton	&#13; &amp;	&#13; Ross	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 	&#13; 	&#13; m	&#13; 
case	&#13; =	&#13; 
	&#13; 2557	&#13; l
	&#13; b	&#13; 
	&#13; 	&#13; 	&#13;  m
prop	&#13; =	&#13; 45,831	&#13; }	&#13; =	&#13; .056 	&#13; 
4)	&#13;  What	&#13; is	&#13; left	&#13; out	&#13; of	&#13; our	&#13; es timate?
	&#13; 	&#13; 	&#13; 
a)
b)	&#13;  Attac me
	&#13; 	&#13; h
c)	&#13; 	&#13; 
ShearEnd	&#13; bells
	&#13; loads	&#13; on	&#13; pr	&#13; have	&#13; 1nts	&#13; 
/2
opellant	&#13; gr	&#13; the	&#13; stress
ain	&#13; -	&#13; ma
	&#13; 	&#13; ke	&#13; 1/2	&#13; as	&#13; thick?	&#13; 
It	&#13; seems	&#13; we	&#13; have	&#13; been	&#13; somewhat	&#13; conservative	&#13; in	&#13; our	&#13; design	&#13; parameters.	&#13; 	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>where	&#13; we	&#13; have	&#13; assume(!
d	&#13; )
hydro(
spcA+!p
ap)=
tatic	&#13; grA
in e! 	&#13; 
	&#13;  qup
ilc
iA
bc
ras
ie
um,pcD=
	&#13; i.e.,	&#13;  .	&#13; 
At
wa	&#13; t
lh
l;	&#13; e
t	&#13; 
ho
it
sh
	&#13; le
ar
s	&#13; 
te
	&#13; n
pd
o,
s	&#13; x
si=
bL
il,x 
(	&#13; 
iw 	&#13; haax
tyeM
	&#13; w
)ouve
l	&#13; eit"Dt
d
p	&#13; i
cmp
Aher	&#13; 
"! =casl
eyl
	&#13; be
(a
u
Ms
ct
k
0	&#13; t
l
"ie
nn
gs"
ioD
nt
o4t
	&#13; pro	&#13; 
bo
lr
e	&#13; p
mss
.s
	&#13; Pib
u!
l
ty
tp
	&#13; 
ic
n=
o
gmp
	&#13; p
xc
=r
Le
,	&#13; ssion	&#13; of	&#13; the	&#13; casing	&#13; 
	&#13; 
and
	&#13; 	&#13; recalling	&#13; that	&#13; Mnozzle)(a+g)
xmin#Dt
	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13; a+g=F/M0=cFpcAt/M0
So,	&#13; unless	&#13; A is	&#13; less	&#13; tha(	&#13; 
M!
n	&#13; a)
bout=
Apc[A#c(1,
/c#nozzle
x )A]	&#13; 
	&#13; t	&#13; min
	&#13; "
caD
set
F,cas
	&#13; the
ereF
	&#13; will	&#13; sM
till	&#13; bet
0
	&#13; tension	&#13; at	&#13; the	&#13; casings	&#13; base .	&#13; 
2)
	&#13; 	&#13;  State	&#13; of	&#13; Stress 	&#13; 
Wi
casth
in	&#13; th
g	&#13; wis
a	&#13; r
lle
,	&#13; pr
suesentation	&#13; of	&#13; the	&#13; loads	&#13; we	&#13; can	&#13; now	&#13; deduce	&#13; the	&#13; State	&#13; of	&#13; Stress	&#13; in	&#13; the	&#13; 
tangemay	&#13; b
ntie	&#13; d
al.es
	&#13; Ic
nr
	&#13; i
tbb
heje
dc
	&#13; at	&#13; 
ese	&#13; st
	&#13; o
coa	&#13; 
	&#13; s
so
tame
te	&#13; 	&#13; 
os
fi
	&#13; mp
plal
nif
ey
	&#13; i
sn
ordinates	&#13; 
ima
git
nrg
e	&#13; a
ss
ss
	&#13; iu
nmp
	&#13; x-y	&#13; coordinattions.	&#13; We	&#13; a
es,	&#13; wssume
here	&#13; x	&#13; t	&#13; &lt;&lt;	&#13; 
	&#13; is	&#13; axD,	&#13; so
ial	&#13; th
	&#13; and	&#13; y	&#13; e	&#13; stress	&#13; 
e	&#13; a	&#13; small	&#13; t
riang
ula
	&#13; :r
	&#13; 	&#13; element.	&#13; 	&#13; The	&#13; stresses	&#13; on	&#13; the	&#13; 
element	&#13; in	&#13; general	&#13; are	&#13; tensions	&#13;  x,	&#13; y	&#13; and	&#13; shear	&#13;  xy	&#13; =	&#13; yx:	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13; asx
sx'sytxy
txy
tx', y'x
y
	&#13; 
N
tho
ew
	&#13; x	&#13; 
	&#13; c
ao
xn
iss
.i
	&#13; 	&#13; d
Iner
	&#13; t	&#13; 
rth 	&#13; 
	&#13; eae
t	&#13; s
metre
ns
ts
se
	&#13; os
	&#13;  	&#13; 
x'=	&#13; fo
	&#13; sn
t	&#13; 
ra
e	&#13; 
sp
sla
	&#13; an
ne
d	&#13; p
	&#13; se
trpendicular	&#13; t
rain	&#13; it	&#13; is	&#13; showo
n	&#13; a
	&#13; 	&#13; tl
hin
ae
t	&#13; 	&#13; making	&#13; the	&#13; angle	&#13; 	&#13; with	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13; 2 2
It	&#13; is	&#13; then	&#13; show	&#13; 
n	&#13; that	&#13; thx'
ey
	&#13; '	&#13; =	&#13; x
-(	&#13; cos
x-
y	&#13; +	&#13;  y	&#13; sin xy	&#13; sin
maximum	&#13; )	&#13; si
(o
n
r	&#13; mi + 2
	&#13; cos
nimu	&#13; +	&#13; 
m)	&#13; oxy	&#13; (cos
f	&#13;  
 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 2cos 	&#13; 
xoccurs	&#13; 	&#13; a	&#13; -	&#13; sin2
' t)
	&#13; a	&#13; 
n	&#13; a
	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  ngle	&#13;  such	&#13; that	&#13;  	&#13; 
	&#13;  tan2 	&#13; =	&#13;  	&#13; 
	&#13; s2xy 
x-y	&#13; 
and	&#13; that	&#13; these tresses	&#13; are: 	&#13; 
3Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.50	&#13;  Lecture	&#13; 13 	&#13; 
Subject:	&#13; 	&#13; Rocket	&#13; casin
	&#13; 
Thus	&#13; far	&#13; all	&#13; our	&#13; modeling	&#13; has	&#13; dealt	&#13; with	&#13; the	&#13; fluid	&#13; mechanics	&#13; and	&#13; thermodynamics	&#13; of	&#13; g	&#13; design;	&#13; Structural	&#13; modeling	&#13; 
rockets.	&#13; This	&#13; is	&#13; appropriate	&#13; because	&#13; it	&#13; is	&#13; these	&#13; features	&#13; that	&#13; set	&#13; rockets	&#13; apart	&#13; from	&#13; most	&#13; 
ot
limitations	&#13; of	&#13; rockets	&#13; as	&#13; systems	&#13; without	&#13; at	&#13; least	&#13; a	&#13; rudimentary	&#13; understanding	&#13; of	&#13; their	&#13; her	&#13; devices.	&#13; 	&#13; On	&#13; the	&#13; other	&#13; hand	&#13; it	&#13; is	&#13; not	&#13; possible	&#13; to	&#13; understand	&#13; the	&#13; characteristics	&#13; and	&#13; 
structural	&#13; characteristics	&#13; which	&#13; determine	&#13; their	&#13; mass,	&#13; durability	&#13; etc.	&#13; 	&#13; To	&#13; aid	&#13; such	&#13; 
und
Solid	&#13; Prunderstand	&#13; the	&#13; Loads	&#13; that	&#13; the	&#13; rocket's	&#13; structure	&#13; must	&#13; withstand.	&#13; Let	&#13; us	&#13; begin	&#13; with	&#13; a	&#13; erstanding	&#13; we	&#13; must	&#13; develop	&#13; some	&#13; simple	&#13; Structural	&#13; Models.	&#13; 	&#13; The	&#13; first	&#13; step	&#13; is	&#13; to	&#13; 
	&#13; opellant	&#13; Rocket	&#13; 
1) Loa
	&#13; ds	&#13; 
We	&#13; model	&#13; the	&#13; rocket	&#13; case	&#13; as	&#13; a	&#13; sphere
pay-cylinder	&#13; full	&#13; of	&#13; fuel, 	&#13; acted	&#13; on	&#13; by	&#13; the	&#13; thrust	&#13;  F	&#13; and	&#13; 
the	&#13; payload	&#13; reaction	&#13; (a+g)
(M )	&#13; where	&#13; a	&#13; is	&#13; the	&#13; acceleration 	&#13; and	&#13; g	&#13; the	&#13; gravitational	&#13; 
acceleratio
n.	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13; 	&#13; 	&#13; 	&#13; 
D
L
A A
CasingPropellent
Nozzlempay
	&#13; 
The	&#13; casing	&#13; is	&#13; subjected	&#13; to	&#13; the	&#13; following: 	&#13; 
	&#13; a)
b)	&#13; 
	&#13; intshear	&#13; loads	&#13; from	&#13; the	&#13; propellant	&#13; grain,	&#13; which	&#13; iernal	&#13; pressure,	&#13; p
c	&#13; 
s	&#13; bonded	&#13; to	&#13; the	&#13; case 	&#13; 
1Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>c)	&#13;  compressive	&#13; loads	&#13; 
To	&#13; find	&#13; the	&#13; forces	&#13; in	&#13; the	&#13; casing	&#13; due	&#13; to	&#13; the	&#13; pressure,	&#13; we	&#13; make	&#13; freeconsider	&#13; section	&#13; A -A.	&#13; -body	&#13; diagrams.	&#13; 	&#13; First	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13;  Section	&#13; A -A	&#13; 
From	&#13; this	&#13; free	&#13; body	&#13; diagram,	&#13; the	&#13; circumferential	&#13; stress  y	&#13; is	&#13; 	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  !y=pD
2t	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13;  	&#13; 
There	&#13; is	&#13; also	&#13; an	&#13; axial	&#13; load	&#13; generated	&#13; by	&#13; the	&#13; combination	&#13; of	&#13; the	&#13; internal	&#13; pressure,	&#13; the	&#13; 
compressive	&#13; load	&#13; from	&#13; the	&#13; payload	&#13; and	&#13; the	&#13; compressive	&#13; stress	&#13; in	&#13; the	&#13; propellant.	&#13; 	&#13; 
Con
	&#13; structing	&#13; another	&#13; free-body	&#13; diagram,	&#13; 
	&#13; 
[Mpay	&#13; +	&#13; (M case	&#13; +	&#13; M prop)	&#13; Lx	&#13; ](a+g)	&#13; +	&#13;  x	&#13; Dt	&#13; =	&#13; p cA	&#13; +	&#13;  pAp	&#13; 
	&#13;  	&#13;  x	&#13; =	&#13; 1
Dt	&#13; 	&#13; {pcA	&#13; +	&#13;  pAp	&#13; -	&#13; [M pay	&#13; +	&#13; (M case	&#13; +	&#13; M prop)	&#13; x
L	&#13; 	&#13; ]	&#13; (a+g)} 	&#13; 
	&#13; This	&#13; stress	&#13; is	&#13; most	&#13; positive	&#13; (tension)	&#13; at	&#13; x=0:	&#13; Ap	&#13; 
A	&#13; x	&#13; 
x	&#13;  p	&#13; pc	&#13; 
[MPay+(M Case+M prop	&#13; x/L]a	&#13; 
	&#13; 	&#13; 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Velocity triangles; compressor performance maps</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-50-introduction-to-propulsion-systems-spring-2012/resources/mit16_50s12_lec25/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>25</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Engines and Gas Turbines, (MIT Press, 1992, Sec. 5.7, pp. 3254-266), a short 
summary of which is presented below. 
In most axial compressors, incipient separation first leads to the Rotating Stall phenomenon: sections of the stalling rotor then operate in deep stall, with almost zero flow, while the rest carries normal or high flow per unit frontal area. These 
regions move backwards in the rotating frame at ~0.4  0.6 r, so that, when
observed from rest they rotate forward, but only at a fraction of the rotor speed. The reason for the bimodal flow distribution is that adjacent streamtubes become unstable with respect to flow exchange: if the rotor as a whole is near stallconditions, and one streamtube loses some flow and diverts it to its neighbors, the streamtube with less flow goes into stall and loses even more flow, while the neighbors gain flow and remain stable. The reason the stall cells move backwards relative to the rotor is an elaboration of the same argument: if one flow passage stalls, the swirling incoming flow is re-routed such that the passage ahead of the one stalled sees a more axial flow, while the one behind sees a larger incidence angle. The stall moves to this trailing passage, and the stalled passage clears. 
Rotating stall, since it moves rapidly about, tends to average out and, aside from
high-frequency excitation, may not be dynam
ically significant. On the other 
hand, the net compressor performance drops strongly, and in addition, it is not easy to reverse once started, except by stopping and re-starting the engine.Detecting rotating stall and instituting the appropriate control reaction is veryimportant. If the engine controls simply detect a loss of pumping performance (pressure loss) they may react by increasing fuel flow, which combined with the reduced airflow, may lead to overheating and burnout. 
Under some conditions having to do mainly with the ratio of flow inertia to flow 
passage capacitance, the complete pumping system (com
pressor plus choked 
turbine nozzles) can enter a global oscillation, called Surge. Unlike rotating stall, surge involves deep oscillations or even reversals of the whole flow through thecompressor, and can be mechanically destructive (certainly quite noticeable, in the form of loud, repeated bangs, accompanied by flame ejection from both ends of the engine). When stall is reached, the engine may go into either Rotating Stall or Surge. The detailed mechanisms that determine which of the phenomena will prevail are encapsulated in Greitzers B param
eter 
!r VpB = 2a Vc 
where a is the speed of sound in the burner, Vp is the plenum volume (mainly 
the burner volume) and Vc is the volume in the compressor flow passages. In a 
single-stage compressor, values of B below ~ 0.8 lead to rotating stall, while 
higher values lead to surge. For multistage (N) compressors, Bcrit. is lower by
somewhere between N and N. One favorable aspect of surge (as opposed to
rotating stall) is that it can usually be cleared by simply reducing fuel flow (or, in 
a test stand, opening the downstream throttle). 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
16.50 Introduction to Propulsion Systems
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Tt2 -1Tt1
MT 2 
w " !r 
Actually, we usually plot this in terms of the pressure ratio rather than the 
temperature ratio, and include superimposed lines of efficiency, so that the map looks like: 
Here the compressor efficiency is defined as: 
#$1 
# #$1Tt1( pt 2) $ Tt1("Tt )Ideal pt1 ( pt 2/ pt1 )#$1!c = = = ("Tt )Actual Tt 2 $ Tt1 Tt 2/ Tt1 $1 
2From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Since c&lt;1, the total pressure rise for a given total temperature rise is less than it 
could be: 
% % 
! c = [1+ " c (#c $1)] %$1 &lt; # c %$1 
' By decreasing  1 and  2 , or even making them negative, we can increase T t2/Tt1. 
What limits this increase?  The answer is best given in terms of a Diffusion Factor, 
which describes the tendencies for the boundary layer to separate under theinfluence of the pressure rise in the blade passage. 
The critical region is the suction surface of the blade. This region feels a pressure
rise due to the decrease of V from V 1 to V 2, (the prime is a reminder that these 
velocities in the relative frame) and also due to the acceleration, followed by deceleration on the suction surface. The Diffusion Factor, defined as 
v2 ! v1 V2 " D = 1! + ; #$ c 
V1 " 2#V1 " s 
is a crude, but effective way to account for these two flow deceleration components.
Here c is the chord of the blades and s is their spacing (in the peripheral direction). 
A value of about 0.5 for D is the upper limit for good efficiency. It is conventional 
and useful to represent the loss in the blading in terms of a Loss Factor, defined as 
pt 1 " pt 2!1 = pt 1 " p1 
3From Kerrebrock, Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT
Press, 1992.  Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Now we can write 16.50 
Subjects: Velocity triangles; Compressor performance maps 
In the last lecture we discussed the basic mechanisms of energy exchange in 
compressors and drew some sim
ple velocity triangles to show how we go from the 
stationary coordinate system to one in the moving blades. In more detail, the velocity triangle is: 
v1 = w 1 tan 1 
' v2 = w 2 tan 2 = r - w 2 tan 2 
' where  2 is the flow angle in the rotating coordinate system of the rotor blades. 
' The advantage of the latter form for v 2 is that it is  2 which is nearly set by the
' shape of the blades, i.e.  2 is nearly constant. The difference between the flow angle
and the angle of the chord line at the trailing edge of the blades is called the
deviation, and is usually a small number of degrees. 
Taking advantage of this small deviation, we can write the Euler equation as 
Tt 2 (!"1)MT 2 &amp; w2 tan $2# w1 tan $1 (= 1 + 1 + !"1 21" " Tt1 2 M1 ' %r %r ) 
where M 1 is the flow Mach number upstream and M T is the tangential Mach
number of the blade motion. 
Since the two flow angles expressed this way are nearly constant, the temperature 
ratio becomes a function primarily of two variables, the tangential Mach number M T 
' and the ratio of the axial flow velocity to the blade speed. For the usual case of  2 &gt; 
0,  1 &gt; 0 we get a functional dependence something like: 
1Lecture 25</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>We then find that we can correlate the losses in the form 
! cos#2 " (cos#2 " )2 
2$ cos#1 " 
.06 
.04 
.02 
0 
 .1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 
Diffusion Factor, D 
Compressor limitations. Rotating Stall. Surge. 
As the incidence angles increase in the compressor a point is reached when the flow begins to separate from the blades, with serious consequences. Large incidence angles occur when the ratio (axial velocity)/(blade speed) is low, i.e.,for a fixed rotational velocity, at reduced flow, and hence at increased pressureratio. All compressors have a fairly well defined stall line that runs diagonally from low flow and low 
! c , to high values of both. Operation must be restricted 
to the region below and to the right of this line. The operational line for thecompressor runs roughly parallel to this stall line. As we saw in Lecture 20, The reason for the compressor to be restricted to his operation line have to do with flow continuity between it and the turbine and nozzle. It is a fortunate fact that the line thus defined tends to correspond to a constant blade incidence, which,when chosen properly, is close to that which optimizes blade performance, and so the operating line is more or less the peak compressor efficiency line. 
The phenomena that occur at and beyond stall are complex, dynamical and highly nonlinear. A detailed understanding of these effects has only emerged in the last two decades, and remedial measures based on this understanding are still under evaluation. Much of the pioneering work in this field has been done atMIT (see E. Greitzer, Engineering for Power, 98, 2, (1976) and J. of Fluids Engineering, 103 (1981), Paduano et al., ASME Paper 91-GT-87, 1981). A more complete exposition of the principles is given in Kerrebrocks book, (Aircraft 
4Image by Manuel Martinez-Sanchez. Adapted from Fig. 5.12 in Kerrebrock,
Jack L. Aircraft Engines and Gas Turbines. 2nd edition. MIT Press, 1992.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
