<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-900-introduction-to-linguistics-fall-2012/</course_url>
    <course_title>Introduction to Linguistics</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>Language </list>
      <list>Linguistics </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>International Phonetic Alphabet (IPA)
Articulatory phonetics / distinctive features
Consonants: place, manner, aspiration, nasality
Vowels
Acoustic phonetics, categorical perception
The McGurk effect
Finish phonetics, start phonology</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-900-introduction-to-linguistics-fall-2012/resources/mit24_900f12_acostc_sumary/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5&#8211;7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>http://www.haskins.yale.edu/featured/bdg.php?audio=AIFF# 
	 To refresh your memory, and because it is very neat  and because you should 
learn this! (hint)  I recommend you go there too. Clicking on each stimulus will 
play it, and there is also a link to hear the entire series. 
Other phonetic distinctions that show categorical perception include: voicing distinctions
due to changes in Voice Onset Time (VOT). 
(3) 
	 Innateness: The phenomenon of categorical perception for speech sounds appears to 
be innate in humans. (I'm not sure I remembered to tell you about this, but it will 
come up when we discuss the phoneme, and also when we discuss language 
acquisition later in the semester.) In a famous experiment, Eimas et al. (1971) showed 
that infants 1 month old have categorical perception for VOT 
[http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/abstract/171/3968/303?ck=nck]. 
Method: Infant's sucking on a nipple increases in amplitude and frequency in response 
to novel stimuli, then tapers off as the stimulus becomes "old". This allows one to see 
what sorts of distinctions are perceived as new and which are not, e.g. when varying 
VOT in an otherwise constant phonetic stimulus. 
	 Language acquisition as unlearning: Other work has shown similar categorical 
effect in infants for the l/r distinction
. Strikingly, all infants appear to have 
categorical perception of this distinction, but adult speakers of languages in which l vs. 
r is not phonemic have lost categoricity! In this respect, language acquisition looks 
more like unlearning than like learning. 

	 Unique to humans? Kuhl and Miller (1975): Chinchillas trained to respond to a 
phonetic stimulus spontaneously exhibit a categorical pa/ba distinction. 
Method: Choose sounds that are equidistant from each other in VOT, e,g. at 15 ms, 45 
ms, and 75 ms VOT. Pick two sounds in the pa
 category and one in the ba category. 
Train a chinchilla to run to the other side of 
the cage when it hears the central sound 
(45 ms), heard as /pa/ by English speaking humans. After training, researchers played 
the two sounds at the extreme ends (15 and 75 ms), which humans hear one sound as -2-
ba and pa, respectively. 
Outcome: Chinchilla ran when they heard the other English pa, but not when they 
heard English ba. Apparently chinchillas (who know no English) categorize these 
human speech sounds in a manner suggestive of human abilities. 
	 Possible conclusion: Categorical perception for speech sounds relies on innate 
properties of the mammalian auditory system not unique to humans. For example, there may be limits to our ability to resolve timing differences that play a role. 
Languages can capitalize on these properties and use them to distinguish speech 
sounds 
3. McGurk effect 
	 Methodology:  Show a video image of a person producing ga, with a soundtrack ba  
so the visual image and the sound contradict each other with respect to the consonant, 
but are otherwise synchronized. 
Outcome:  Most speakers will perceive an acoustic compromise between the video and 
the audio in the form of da! 
(I screwed this up when I stated it in class, and was 
corrected by Gillian.) 
	 Watch it at: http://www.youtube.com/watch?
v=aFPtc8BVdJk. If that link gives you 
trouble, you can find the same movie all over the web. Google for "McGurk effect" 
and you will find it. 
	 The effect was discovered and first presented in: 
McGurk, Harry; and MacDonald, John (1976); "Hearing lips and seeing voices," 
Nature, Vol 264(5588), pp. 746748 
 and is most often known as the McGurk Effect
. 
	 Why is this interesting to us?
 Well, it is our third demonstration of the very same 
slogan: 
Speech perception is in your mind, not in your ears. 
 And of course this slogan is a good characterization of almost all of language  from 
word boundaries to syntactic structures. It is all in your head.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.900  2012 
Acoustic phonetics (speech perception) summary (2) Spectrograms (x=time y = frequency) of ba - da -ga (spoken by me!)
Note the rise (not that clear) for b, the shallow fall for d and the sharp fall for g. 
1. Speech Perception 
	 We hear speech sounds in such a way that we can generally tell how they were 
pronounced. That is what the "b-ness" of "b" consists in, and the "g-ness" of "g". 
	 What we pay attention to are the frequency bands that are reinforced, not suppressed, by the resonating chambers of the vocal tract. These are called formants. 
	 Vowel formants (except for diphthongs) are steady-state formants. 
The higher the vowel, the lower the first formant. 
The fronter the vowel, the higher the second formant. 
(1) 	 Fact: If a signal sounds like a set of formants that could be created by human speech, 
your mind perceives the signal as speech, even if other properties of the signal are odd. 
The duck call web site shows this for vowels. Go to 
       http://www.exploratorium.edu/exhibits/vocal_vowels/vocal_vowels.html 
	 In fact, an extremely reduced formant structure can still be perceived as speech. That 
was the point of the presentation of sinewave speech.  Go to 
http://www.haskins.yale.edu/research/sws.html for more. 
A relevant slogan: Speech perception is in your mind, not in your ears. 
2. Categorical perception 
	 Many phonetically important distinctions lie along a continuum of acoustic 
possibilities. 
For example, one can artifically produce (say, using computer software) the 
appropriate formant stucture for the syllable ba, then gradually change the initial 
transition through da to ga. In principle, one might expect to be able to produce a series of signals that gradually morphs from ba to da then ga, 
	 That is not what we perceive, though. Instead of a gradual shift from ba to da, and from da to ga, we hear a bunch of bas, then a bunch of das, then a bunch of gas. That 
is, each stimulus is assigned to one of the three categories, and we hear nothing as in 
between two categories. This phenomenon is called categorical perception . 
In class, we saw this by looking at and playing the stimuli at	 Consonant sounds, especially stops, involve rapid changes in formant pitch called 
transitions  as you expect given how the vocal tract produces a consonant. The transition is visible in F2 &amp; F3.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.900 Introduction to Linguistics
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Stages of acquisition
Learning vs. innateness vs. maturation</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-900-introduction-to-linguistics-fall-2012/resources/mit24_900f12_languagacqsum/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>(16) 	 Early pro-drop 
a. Danish  
Se, blomster har. (Jens, 2;2) 
    look flowers have/has  
b. English 
Tickles me. (Adam, 3;6)  
c. French  
Mange du pain. (Grgoire, 2;1) 
eat-3sg some bread  
Are young English-speaking children in effect "speaking Italian" until they start 
regularly using subject pronouns?  Much controversy ... 
We also saw a video of English-speaking kids "speaking German" or "speaking 
Swedish" with respect to other phenomena, making the same points. 
Alas, we did not have time for the following discussion, but you may find the topic interesting nonetheless: 
Italian kids drop subject pronouns much more often than their English-speaking 
counterparts. So English pro-drop can't just be "English-speaking children 
speaking Italian". There must be a different factor. Possibility
:  maturation. 
Root infinitive stage: Speakers of many
 languages go through a period in which 
they use infinitival verbs in main clauses, and these may lack subjects, 
(17) 	 a. Michel dormir. 
(French: 'Michel sleep-infin,') 
b. Ik ook lezen. (Dutch: '
I also read-infin.') -6-
(18) Optional root infinitive stage 
a. Danish 
Hun sove. 
she sleep -INFIN (Jens, 2;0) 
b. Dutch 
Earst kleine boekje lezen.
first little book read- INFIN (Hein, 2;6) 
'First (I/we) read little book' 
c. French Dormir petit bb. sleep -
INFIN  little baby
'Little baby is sleeping.' (Daniel, 1; 11) 
English does not have a specifically infinitive suffix, but the root infinitive state is 
found among English-speaking children as well  showing up as missing - s on 
third-person present-tense verbs.  This is not an inability to pronounce the - s, since
plural and possessive - s is regularly present (with the caveat discussed above in 
connection with the wug discussion): 
(19) 	 English root infinitives
a. Papa have it. (Eve, 1;6)b. Cromer wear glasses. (Eve, 2;0) c. Marie go. (Sarah, 2;3)
d. Mumma ride horsie. (Sarah, 2;6) 
It has been claimed that "early pro-drop" in languages like Dutch or English is largely limited to such root infinitival clauses. Hmm...  So is it pro-drop after all. 
And if so ... 
So what about parameter setting? When does it happen? 
Answer: Perhaps some syntactic parameters are set earlier than we can yet detect.   
For example, German children around age 2 already know V2  and even 
though they use root infinitives, they almost never apply V/2 to them. 
In adult German, an infinitive verb does not move to C, but remains final in VP: 
(20) 	 German (adult) infinitival verb does not move to C
Ich will [dieses Buch lesen]I want this book read-
INFIN 
'I want to read this book' 
Here are some examples of sentences uttered by the German speaking child
Andreas (2;1).  The first two examples show finite (non-infinitive) verbs, while the second two show root infinitives:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.900 Introduction to Linguistics
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>3. Phonetics 
Discussed earlier in the course. Infants discriminate the sounds of speech categorially, 
in an adult-like manner, even when the distinctions lie at arbitrary points along an 
acoustic continuum. 
Distinctions not used in the target language are lost (more accurately: suppressed in 
some fashion) during the first year of life.  See below. 
4.	 Phonology 
Child's tasks:   
determine the phonemic inventory (underlying segments) of the language 
build the phonological part of the lexicon (underlying representations) 
determine the rule system that relates underlying representations to surface forms 
Determining phonemic inventory 
Production:	 4-5 months, some speech sounds. 
6-7 months - "canonical babbling" begins. 
Babbling initially contains a wide repertory of speech sounds, and finally zeroes in on the 
speech sounds of the target language. 
Around 8-10 months, adults can recognize the target language of a babbling child 
(French, Cantonese, Arabic). By 6 months, Chinese children's babbling contains more 
tonal variation than the babbling of an American child. 
Deaf children babble vocally as well, though naturally there's no gradual 
approximation to a target language. 
Also: gestures analogous to babbling are noted in deaf children learning ASL. 
Conclusion: inner biological clock governs onset of babbling; this clock is unaware of 
child's deafness. 
Just as spoken language babbling shows properties of the language being acquired, so does sign language babbling. 
Laura Pettito's work:  Hearing children who are acquiring sign (deaf parents) babble 
manually
.  You can see the video clip from class, along with a fuller description of this 
work, at http://petitto.gallaudet.edu/%7Epetitto/archive/nature.html
. The other 
materials on Pettito's website are worth reading as well. -2-
Children with tracheostomy surgery that eliminates vocal production do not hear 
themselves babble. When the tracheostomy hole is closed, there are some delays in 
speech, but they quickly jump to age-appropriate behavior, skipping various stages.   
Conclusion: Babbling is linguistic (not motoric)  but it is not "practice" essential 
for language acquisition. It is a by-product of the process of language acquisition, not 
an essential building block. 
Perception:	 During first year, child stops discriminating certain distinctions that are 
non-phonemic in his/her target language. This parallels the refinement of 
sounds produced in babbling that approximates the target language. 
First words/Production: Not all contrasts made, much individual variation in order with which contrasts appear in production (e.g. alveolar/velar then labial). 
For example, a typical development of contrasts:  
stage 1:  p t-k  
stage 2:  p  t  k  
stage 3: voicing  
stage 4: nasal  
Perception/knowledge lags behind production: 
Children know the contrasts that they do not produce/  
Also, numerous observations that children do not recognize words produced with 
the very phonetic changes they put in them.  A child who says 
sip for ship will not 
identify
 a sip as something you sail in.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>-7-
(21) Andreas (2;1): finite and infinitive root sentence 
a.	 Ich hab ein dossen Ball.  
I have a big ball (note: dossen for grossen)  
b. 	Ich mach das nich.  
I do that not  
'I'm not doing that.'  
c. 	Thorsten Caesar haben. (note: Caesar = a doll)  
Thorsten Caesar have- INFIN  
d. 	Du das haben.  
you that have- INFIN  
	 In fact, out of 281 sentences in a corpus of Andreas's utterances on a single day, which included 231 finite sentences and 51 sentences with root infinitives, Andreas overwhelmingly applied V2 to the finite verbs and failed to apply it to the non-finite verbs  following the adult rule in this respect.  ( He disobeys the adult rules of V2 
7.8% of the time. Child data is always noisy.) 
+Finite -Finite 
Verb second 216 7  
Verb final 15 44  
	 Some example of Andreas' finite sentences with V2: 
(22) Direct object topicalization 
a. Kahehabahn fahr  	 ich.  
    toy-race-car drive I  
b. Eine Fase hab ich.  
a vase have I  
(23) Adverb topicalization
 a. Da 	 bin ich.  
there am I  
b. So macht der.  
so does he</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>entire languages oversimplifies the picture. Certain kinds of mixed languages do exist, 
but they are restricted by FOFC (the Final-over-Final Constraint).  If correct, FOFC is
(or is a by-product of) a principle of UG  a principle that restricts the ways in which languages vary (and restricts the "search space" for a child acquiringlanguage). 
Some other parameters (and how they are set in a few languages) 
[See Baker's book for much more,] 
1.	  Subject pro-drop 
(4) 	 Italian: + 
a. Io parlo italiano
(I) speak Italian 
b. Noi parliamo italiano 
     (we) speak  Italian 
(5) Chinese: + Ta kanjian
(he) see 
'He saw him'. ta le. 
he LE 
(6) English: -
*(We) speak English. 
2. 	Object pro-drop 
(7) 	 Chinese: + 
Ta kanjian ta  le. 
he see       (him
) LE 
(8) 	 Italian: -*Gianni lo  vede.  
  Gianni (him) sees.  
(Object pronouns generally move to the left of I in Italian.) 
(9) 
	English: -*John saw him. 
3. 	 Polysynthesis 
(10) 	 English: [+ incorporation into N] (and A),  but [- incorporation into V] a, I disapprove of book-burning
b. 	
A user-friendly computer is a distant goal. 
c. *The baby meat-ate last night. -
5-
(11) 	 Mohawk: [+ incorporation intoV]
 Owira'a waha'-wahrake'. 
baby      meat-ate (Baker p. 91) 
Mohawk: 
polysynthesis (V): + ("incorporation") 
subject pro-drop: + object pro-drop: + 
(12) 	 a. Wa'eksohare' 
'She dishwashed' 
b. Wa'kenaktahninu'      'I bed-bought.'  
c. Wahana'tarakwetare' 
    'He bread-cut.'  
English:
polysynthesis (V):  
subject pro-drop:  object pro-drop: 
 
(13) 	 The verb-object constraint 
The object of a verb must be the first noun (phrase) to combine with the verb; the
subject cannot combine with the verb until after the object does. 
(14) 	 ...in English compounding a. I disapprove of meat eating in here. (i.e. meat getting eaten)
b. *I disapprove of baby eating in here. (i.e. babies eating dinner) 
(15) 	 ...in Mohawk "incorporation"
*Wahawirake' ne o'wahru.  
  baby-ate 
the meat  
  'The baby ate the meat.' 
 
(compare (11) 
An acquisition perspective on parameter-setting 

	 Early production of complete sentences may show parameters set in a fashion familiar
from languages other than the language that the child is in the process of acquiring.   
Example:  pro-drop 
Danish, English and French are not pro-drop languages, but early sentence production appears to show selective omission of subject pronouns:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>-4- 
children were played different recordings in a later presentation which they could control by 
gazing at or looking away from a blinking light.   
 This time, however, the nonsense words in the first presentation were not randomly chosen 
sequences of syllables, but conformed to simple rules, or templates.  One group of infants, for 
example, heard a string of  nonsense words in which the second two syllables were identical ( ga 
ti ti, li na na ).  Another group heard words in which the first and third syllables were identical 
(ti ga ti , na li na ).   
 
The key recording in the second  pr 
esentation did not consist th is time of the same words 
rearranged, but consisted of entirely new words  that followed the same rule as the first set of 
words.  Could infants distinguish new words that followed the rule from new words that did 
not?  Strikingly, they could.  The infants preferred novel second presentations over familiar 
second presentations.  But "familiar" here meant -- not containing the same "words" -- but 
containing new words that followed the old rule.  In their words: "Infants [can] extract abstract algebra- like rul es that represent relationships between placeholders (variables), such as the 
first item X is the same as the third item Y, or more generally, that item I is the same as item J...In addition to having the capacity to represent such rules, our results ap pear to show that 
infants have the ability to extract those rules rapidly from small amounts of input and to generalize those rules to novel instances."  
 
On the other hand... 
 Morphological rule learning across the entire language takes a while longer. 
It's still miraculously fast, but far from instantaneous!   
 
Classic experiment: the "wug test".  At what age do English-speaking children 
produce the correct plural endings [-s], [-z] and [-z]?  Answer: quite early for 
[-s] (cats), and [-z] (dogs), but quite late for the [-z] that follows sibilants 
(horses, edges).  Testing is done with a mixture of nouns that the children know 
and invented nouns like the now-famous wug: 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
  
 
 
 
 
 
  % correct pre- school answers %correct first- grade answers 
glasses  75 99 
wugs  76 97 
luns  68 92 
tors 73 90 
heafs  79 80 
eras 58 86 
tasses 28 39 
gutches 28 38 
kazhes 25 36 
nizzes 14 33 
 
Note about 2/3 of the first-graders tested failed to produce adult-like plurals for words that 
end in sibilants.  That is very late by the standards of language acquisition experiments! 
 
7. Syntax 
 
(2)  What we find when we carefully study the world's languages 
 Languages are not all the same, but the ways in which they differ are highly
restricted .  The same peculiar bits show up again and again, all over the world.  
 
What's the same is called Universal Grammar  (UG) 
What's different  are settings of parameters within UG. 
 An acquisition perspective on UG and parameter setting: 
 UG reflects our genetic endowment for language  
 Parameter setting reflects our linguistic experience in early childhood.  
 
 
 For example, though we don't find verb-second in all the languages of the world,
we do find it popping up repeatedly  as discussed in the syntax lecture notes.  On 
the other hand (I am repeating myself here) there are some types of languages that are
just as easy to describe in words as the verb-second languages, which we never find: 
 
(3) Some languages that don't exist  anyw
here (as far as we know): 
a. Like German, but patterns of embedded and main clause are reversed. 
b. Main verb must follow the second phrase, third phrase, etc. 
c. Not the main verb, but the direct object must follow the first phrase.
 
 We made a similar point in class when we discussed the relative ordering of heads of
phrases and their complements.  We observed that the relative order of a head and the elem
ent that it merges with varies systematically across languages.   
 
We also observed that postulating a uniform "head-first/head-last" parameter across This is a Wug.
Now there is another one.
There are two of them.There are two
.
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Underlying representations/rule system 
(1) 	 A Japanese child's phonology 
Age 3;2: substitutes [t] for [k]  but phonological rules that apply to adult [t] only 
apply to those [t]'s that really are [t]'s for the adult. 
child adult comment 	 meaning 
mita mikan adult [k]-&gt;child [t] 'orange'  
potetto poketto 'pocket'  
neto neko 'cat'  
tama tama adult [t] stays [t] 'ball'  
terebi terebi 'TV'  
tob tob 'fly'  
mati mati tt /__i 'city'  
tsta tsta tts/__ 'ivy'  
These rules do not apply to child's [t] that corresponds to adult [k]: 
ati aki	 'fall' 
tma kma	 'bear' 
But production differences are systematic and linguistic: 
For example, common to use only initial onset and rhyme of adult production.  This 
creates syllable simplification in monosyllabic words: (bd  b).  But this simplified 
syllable is copied (reduplication) in production of a disyllabic word:  chicken  [dd], 
water [ww ]. The syllable count of the word  is preserved, with a morphological 
process known in the adult grammar (reduplication) used to create the second syllable. 
5.	 Lexicon 
Discerning word-boundaries: 
Kids already know more than they say.  Work of (the late) Peter Jucszyk and others: 
	 In 11-month old, selective looking reveals preference for pauses that coincide 
with word boundaries over pauses inserted between syllables of words. 
	 In 9-month old, no preference. 
So what happens between 9 and 11?	  A bootstrapping problem . 
How do you segment speech into words if you don't know the words?No magic bullet, it seems! 
two possibilities: -3-
Prosodic bootstrapping : 
Some common, but not universal phonological phenomena respect word boundaries.   
For example, in French, the final a of panorama is longer than the first a of 
matimaticien. 3-day old infants can distinguish ma-ti from panorama typique from 
ma-ti out of matematricien. So the information, if relevant to guessing word 
boundaries, is perceived... [Mehler et al -- this is a sucking/habituation experim
ent] 
Also, typical stress patterns get noticed.  Czech - initial / French - final / Polish -
penultimate.  English: 90% of nouns have stressed initial syllables.  If a child 
anticipates this sort of regularity, it at least narrows hypotheses...  In a 1993 studyby Juszyk, Cutler and Redanz, 9-month old American infants listened longer to words with initial stress than to other words.  No such difference among 6-month olds. 
Maybe these features are exaggerated in production by parents (motherese)? 
Statistical bootstrapping 
Sequences of syllables that overlap word boundaries are often less likely than sequences of
syllables within w
ords, simply because it's words that are being learned. 
 	pretty baby: [ tibej] (pret- ty ba- by) less common because it's not a word.  If kids 
are sensitive to these probabilities, they can form hypotheses about word/non-word on the basis of these probabilities. 
	 Computer corpus analysis does fairly w
ell (emphasize "fairly") finding word 
boundaries this way.  Do babies do this too?
 Perhaps. 
6.	 Morphology 
Child's tasks:   
determine the morphemes/words of the language  
determine the rules that combine morphemes into words  
Example: 
learn that walked contains two morphemes 
On the one hand... 
Some evidence that language acquisition device is "pretuned" to pick up 
morphological patterns. 
Those of you who read the paper by Safran, Aslin &amp; Newport on statistical 
learning by infants (one of the choices for the first paper) might be interested in 
a follow-up by Marcus et al (1999) in Science: 
In a clever twist on the Saffran et al. exp eriment, Gary Marcus of NYU and three colleagues 
did a similar experiment with 7 -month old (actually, slightly younger) infants. (Science, 
January 1, 1999). Once again, a two -minute stream of synthesized speech was played to the 
infants.  Once again, the speech stream was composed of three -syllable nonsense words, made 
from synthesized speech, with no cues identifying the word boundaries. Once again, the</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Synchronic vs. diachronic linguistics
Internalist vs. externalist views of change
Pidgins, Creoles, Creolization
Language families
The Indo-European language family: language and culture
Linguistics and the Romantic movement
History of English</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-900-introduction-to-linguistics-fall-2012/resources/mit24_900f12_hislingsumary/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23&#8211;24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.900 Introduction to Linguistics
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>-5-
 Syntactic change:  V2 &gt; SVO with V-movement to I (see overheads) 
Modern English: 1500-present 
 Loss of V-to-I. 
 Definitive loss of case.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>-2-
"The Sanskrit language, whatever be its antiquity, is of a wonderful structure; 
more perfect than the Greek, more copious than the Latin, and more exquisitely 
refined than either, yet bearing to both of them a stronger affinity, both in the roots of verbs and in the forms of grammar, than could possibly have been produced by accident; so strong indeed, that no philologer could examine them all 
three, without believing them to have sprung from some common source, which, 
perhaps, no longer exists: there is a similar reason, though not quite so forcible, for supposing that both the Gothic and the Celtic, though blended with a very different idiom, had the same origin with the Sanskrit; and the old Persian might 
be added to the same family, if this were the place for discussing any question 
concerning the antiquities of Persia." 
SIR WILLIAM JONES 
THE THIRD ANNIVERSARY DISCOURSE, ON THE HINDUS 
Delivered 2 February, 1786, to the Royal Asiatick Society 
	 William Jones' observation was informal, and we can make a similar observation for 
ourselves, just by eyeballing relevant data.  For example, the words for the first ten numbers strongly suggest that Sanskrit, Greek, Latin, Gothic, Old Irish, Lithuanian, and Old Church Slavonic share a common ancestor  but Basque, Hungarian and Turkish do not share that common ancestor. (My apologies for the small font size.) 
(1) Numerals 1-10.  Which languages are related? 
Sanskrit Greek Latin Gothic Old Irish Lithuanian Old Church 
Slavonic Basque Hungarian Turkish 
1. kas hei:s u:nus ains on venas jedin bat egy bir 
2. dva do: duo twai da d dva bi kett iki 
3. tryas trei:s tre:s reis tri try:s trje hiru hrom  
4. catv:ras tttares quattuor fidwor cethir ketur etyre lau ngy drt 
5. pca pnte quinque fimf cic penki pet bost t bes  
6. s t  hx sex saihs s ei est sei hat alt 
7. sapt hept septem sibun secht n-septyn sedm zazpi ht yedi 
8. as t a okt: octo: ahtau ocht n- atuon osm zortzi nyolc sekiz 
9. nva enna novem niun no n- devyn deve t bederatzi kilenc dokuz 
10. daa dka decem taihun deich n-de:eimt dese t hamar tz on 
Cognate: 	a word in a language X that is hypothesized to share a common origin with 
a different word in language Y. 
	 So Sanskrit dva 'two' and Greek do: 'two' are cognates. 
 But simple identification of words that look similar (what I was calling "eyeballing") is 
not enough to establish that two languages are related according to this scenario: 1822: Jacob Grimm formulates "Grimm's Law", which describes a regular correspondance 
between the stop consonants of Latin, Greek and Sanskrit and consonants in 
Germanic languages.  Pay particular attention to p&gt;f, t&gt;  and k&gt;h (the most famous 
cases  f
inal exam fodder): 
(2) Grimm's law 
Latin Greek English Latin Greek English 
p~f ped-e pod-e foot b~p labium lip 
pisc-is fish d~t duo two 
pyr fire decem deka ten 
pater pater father 
g~k genu 
gno-sco knee 
know t~ tres 
dent-e treis 
dont-e three 
tooth 
k~h cord-e kard-ion heart ph~b fer-o pher-o bear 
can-e kuon hound frater phrater brother 
cannabis kannabis hemp th~d erythr-os red 
cornu 
centum hekaton horn 
hundred vidua (w)eitheos widow 
gh~g hostis guest 
	 Reality check:  Do regular sound correspondences result from historical change?  Look 
for cases where we know the languages are related. We do indeed see the regular 
sound correspondences that we expect to find: 
(3) We know these languages are related!
French Italian Spanish Portuguese
cher caro caro caro 
champ campo campo campo 
chandelle candela candela candeia 
Note: French written "ch" is [ ].  
Here's a partial list of Indo-European languages:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.900 2011 
Historical Change summary 
1. Language acquisition is surprisingly perfect... 
"Plato's Problem" (a term from Chomsky): 
	 What's in the stimulus? 
a) acoustic continuum between phonemes 
b) no chanting of the phonemic inventory or list of phonological rules c)	 no morpheme boundaries 
d)	 no word boundaries 
e) no syntactic trees f) no indices indicating coreference 
	 How do we know so much, when we had so little evidence for this knowledge? 
	 Answer: much of our linguistic knowledge is innate. (Universal Grammar) 
o	 knowledge of the phonetic boundaries 
o	 a drive to discover word boundaries, a drive to build a lexicon 
o	 a drive to place phrase boundaries, innate knowledge of possible syntaxes 
o	 innate knowledge of Principle C, compositional semantics etc. 
2. ...but also unsurprisingly imperfect! 
	 Still -- it's not surprising that learning might not be perfect even if input is perfect.  
Imperfect learning should still deposit the child's knowledge of language within the 
boundaries of UG. Result: variation. 
	 Also: language contact produces situations where a child's input might be diverse -- native speakers, non-native speakers. Result: variation. 
	 In a random walk of variation, the variant adopted by the majority of speakers may be different at different times. Result: linguistic change. 
	 The course of linguistic change may be different in different speech communities that were united but have since been separated. Result: dialect/language distinctions 
Two speech communities that have seen a modest amount amount of distinct paths of
linguistic change are commonly said to speak dialects of the same language. 
But: Dialect, language, even speech community are imprecise concepts. The important 
point is that each of us speaks a dialect of a language. It's not the case that some of us speak a language, and others a dialect.  That usage is just
propaganda: 	 An expectation: linguistic change is always grammatical change or lexical change. It 
should reflect the structure of grammar and the nature of the lexicon. 
	 Grammatical change should look orderly:  new phonological rules entering the 
language, old rules reordered, systematic changes in choices from the "syntactic menu". Yes! 
	 Uses of this fact: 
o	 Understanding how a language whose history is recorded evolved over time. 
o	 Understanding current linguistic change. 
	 Figuring out whether two languages are related. But what does this mean? 
Something like: 
Once upon a time there was a speech community sharing a fairly uniform grammar 
that we can call the proto-language that was the ancestor of modern languages X 
and Y.   
Historical change produced dialects of the protolanguage. These dialects themselves 
produced dialects, the process iterating until we reach a period where X and Y are two 
of the dialects that can trace their ancestry to the protolanguage. 
3. Indo-European 
[See textbook pp. 285-288 and 319-327.] 
Case in point: a large group of languages spoken in Europe and Central Asia are related, 
stemming from a proto-language called Indo-European. 
The discovery of Indo-European 
Sir William Jones 
(1746-1794) 
"A language is a dialect with an army and a navy."  -Uriel Weinreich (famous linguist) 
This image is in the public domain.
Source: Wikimedia Commons.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>(4) 	 Some Indo-European languages (incomplete list) 
Albanian: Geg, Tosk dialects 
Armenian 
Balto-Slavic: 
Baltic: Latvian, Lithuanian
Slavic:  East (Russian, Ukrainian, Byelorussian), West (Czech,Slovak, Polish, Sorbian/Wendish, Old Prussian), South 
(Bulgarian,
Macedonian, Serbo-Croatian, Slovenian) 
Celtic: 	 Brythonic: Welsh, Breton, Cornish Goidelic: Irish, Scottish Gaelic, Manx Continental: Gaulish  
Germanic: 	 East Germanic: Gothic Scandinavian:
   Icelandic, Faroese, Norwegian, Danish, Swedish 
West Germanic: German, Dutch, Frisian, English, Afrikaans, 
Y
iddish 
Hellenic: Greek 
Anatolian: Hittite, Luwian, Lydian, Carian, Palaic Indo-Iranian: 
Iranian: Farsi [Persian], Pashto [Afghanistan], Kurdish 
Indic: Hindi-Urdu, Bengali, Punjabi, Marathi, Gujarati, Romany 
Italic: Ancient: Latin, Oscan, Umbrian. 
Modern (= Romance
) Spanish, Portuguese, Catalan, French, Occitan, 
Provenal, Romansch, Sardinian, Italian, Romanian, Haitian 
Tocharian: Tocharian A, Tocharian B 
4.	 Fun Facts about the Indo-Europeans that I craz
ily forgot to tell you 
1. 	They had domesticated animals. Evidence: cognate words f
or dog * kwon, horse * ekwo,
cow * gwow and pig * suH. [asterisk = hypothesized form in Proto-Indo-
European] 
2. 	They had grain. Evidence - cognate words * yewo
3. 	They had the wheel: * kwekwlo   (cf. Greek kuklos, from
 which cycle is borrowed) 
4. 	They had bee-keeping, since they have cognate words for honey: * melit 
5. 	Numbers up to 100, but not 1000. -3-
	 Most experts think: the parent language split well before 2000 BC. 
	 Possible homesite: "Kurgan culture" east of the Dniepr river, modern-day Ukraine.  
But there is hot debate about this. See, for example, a long series of blog postings in reply to an article in Nature here: 
http://geocurrents.info/cultural-geography/linguistic-geography/mismodeling-indo-
european-origin-and-expansion-bouckaert-atkinson-wade-and-the-assault-on-historical-linguistics 
	 Spread west around 4000-3500 BC; in Northern Iran 3500-3000BC; entered Greece, 
Italy, W
estern Europe 3500 BC.  [speculation: do not memorize] 
5.	 Good and Bad methods in historical linguistics 
All languages change, and change is found in all branches of language: 
 1. lexicon: 	new words, borrowing 
	 2. phonology: new rules, loss of old rules 
	 3. morphology: new morphemes 

	 3. syntax: changes in parameter settings, kinds of movement, etc.s 
Relatedness is best established on the basis of the lexicon, not syntax: 
o	 Because there are an unbounded number of possible words, finding the 
same sets of words in multiple languages is low-probability. 
o	 There is a substantially sm
aller number of possible syntactic systems, so 
finding the same syntax in multiple languages is higher-probability:  recall the V2 example. 
But we should be careful. Processes like borrowing complicate the picture: 
(5) 
A sound change in the history of Italian
Latin Italian 
1. 	flamma fjamma 'flame' 9. kla:ma :re kjamare 'shout' (L), 
'name' (I) 
2. 	flokkus fjokko 'flock of wool' 10. kla:rus kjaro 'clear' (L),  
'bright' (I) 
3. 	flumen fjume 'river' 11. ekkle:sia kjeza 'assembly'(L),
'church' (I) 
4. ple:nus 	 pjeno 'full' 12. klawstrum kjostro 'enclosure' 
5. plakere 	 pjatere 'please' 13. klawdere kjudere 'close' 
6. plumbus 	 pjombo 'lead' (= Pb) 14. glakies gjatio 'ice' 
7. plu:ma	 pjuma 'feather' 15. glu:to(ne) gjottone 'glutton' 
8. klavis 	 kjave 'key' 16. plakare plakare 'calm' 
17. floridus florido 'flowery'</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Example (5) shows a rule "lj / C_V" entering, then leaving the language. 
	 Some words (biancho, schiavo) were borrowed from other languages (Germanic and 
Slavic [via Greek], respectively) while this rule was active.  Others (florido, placare) 
were borrowed once the rule had left the language. 
	 The rule left the language once its effects were no longer transparent to a language-learning child. 
And there are many ways to go wrong when doing historical linguistics. 
(6) Which two languages are related?
A B C 
'two' er erku duo 
	 Answer: B (Armenian) and C (Greek). 
	 "Looking similar" is neither necessary nor sufficient to establish a genetic relationship 
among languages. In fact (and this is indeed weird), Armenian systematically shows [erk] where Proto-Indo-European is hypothesized to have shown [dw]: 
(7) Armenian-Greek sound correspondences 
Armenian Greek 
'two' erku duo  
'fear' erki- dwi-
'long' erkar dwa:ron  
	 In class, we saw a number of examples of "false cognates", just to warn you against accepting theories of historical relatedness on the basis of "eyeballing". For example: 
Mbabaram dog 'dog' vs. English dog 'dog'  where we know the languages are
unrelated, and Mbabaram dog is a cognate with words in nearby languages that have 
an additional first syllable lost in Mbabaram:  Yidi gudaga and Dyirbal guda. (You 
can find more information about these languages on the web.) 
And then you were further warned against "mass comparison" of lexical items that 
look alike and have vaguely similar meaning.  That was the big slide (which I won't reproduce here) with words for 'milk', 'suck', 'chew', 'breast', 'neck', 'throat' etc.  all ofwhich have an initial [m] (maybe onomatopeic, as some of you remarked) followed by an [l] somewhere and a velar or uvular consonant.   
6. History of English 
Old English: 450-1100 AD 
Languages spoken in present-day England were very much Germanic in appearance. 
SOV, verb-second, case-marked noun phrases [see overheads] -4-
Middle English: 1100-1500  
[1066 - Norman invasion of England, England under French domination] Loss of verb-second, case-marking, V-to-I  
French influence on lexicon: [blue = skipped this in class, alas] 
	 pork, beef, veal, mutton, venison (French) vs. swine/sow, cow, calf, sheep, deer 
(Germanic) [see textbook, p. 270, table 7.32] 
	 -able (from French) 
	 Loss of some words: 
wer 'man' (cf. Latin vir as in English virile) - still found in werewolf 
rice 'domain' (cf. bishopric, German Reich -- related to reach) 
	 Meaning change:
hund 'dog' &gt; hound 
docga 'mastiff' &gt; dog 
	 Sound change: 
1. Loss of [x]  (right, night) 
2. Very late in ME period: 
Great Vowel Shift 
[book, pp. 258-259] 
Image removed due to copyright restrictions. To see a graphic 
of the Great Vowel Shift, please go to: http://users.ipfw.edu/ thompsoc/LingL103/overheads/vowelshift.gif. 
3. Order of loss of [x] w.r.t. GVS:  [x] was lost when GVS was still active, vowel 
lengthened, then GVS applied. Thus: /rixt/ &gt; /ri:t/ &gt; /rajt/.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Syntactic categories (noun, verb, etc.)
Phrase structure
Subcategorization in syntax
Chomsky&#8217;s Locality Condition on subcategorization
The notion &#8220;head&#8221;
Complements and adjuncts
Head-initial vs. head-final languages
Movement
Movement as &#8220;internal merge&#8221;
wh-movement
Topicalization
V-to-C movement
Patterns of pronunciation (overt, covert, split)
Verb-second
The notion &#8220;parameter&#8221;
Movement and word-order variation
A language universal: the Final-over-Final Constraint (FOFC)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-900-introduction-to-linguistics-fall-2012/resources/mit24_900f12_syntaxsummary/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14&#8211;18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>-16-
2. Object pro-drop 
(85) Chinese: + 
Ta kanjian ta le. 
he see (him) LE 
(86) Italian: -*Gianni 
lo vede. 
Gianni (him) sees. 
(Object pronouns generally move to the left of I in Italian.) 
(87) English: -*John saw him. (92) 
(93) ...in English compounding
a. I disapprove of meat eating in here. 
(i.e. meat getting eaten)
b. *I disapprove of baby eating in here. (i.e. babies eating dinner) 
...in Mohawk "incorporation"
*Wahawirake' ne o'wahru. 
baby-ate the meat 
'The baby ate the meat.'
(compare (89
)) 
3. 
(88) 
(89) Polysynthesis 
English: [+ incorporation into N] (and A),  but [- incorporation into V] 
a, I disapprove of book-burning 
b. A user-friendly computer is a distant goal. 
c. 
*The baby meat-ate last night. 
Mohawk: [+ incorporation intoV]
Owira'a waha'-wahrake'. 
baby meat-ate (Baker p. 91) 
Mohawk: 
polysynthesis (V): + ("incorporation") 
subject pro-drop: + object pro-drop: 
+ 
(90)	 a. Wa'eksohare' 
'She dishwashed' 
b. Wa'kenaktahninu'
 
'I bed-bought.'
 
c. Wahana'tarakwetare'
 
'He bread-cut.'
 
English:
polysynthesis (V): 
 
subject pro-drop:  object pro-drop: 
 
(91)	 The verb-
object constraint
The object of a verb must be the first noun (phrase) to combine with the verb; the 
subject cannot combine with the verb until after the object does.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>-9-
8. Meaning and the structure of NP 
	 We saw that English and Japanese sentences have very similar structure.  Sisterhood, 
domination relations  these are all the same in the English and Japanese sentences that we discussed in class. Only word order was different. 
	 What aspects of a sentence determine its meaning?  Word order, or structure?  In fact, even above and beyond questions of pronouns and coreference, the meaning of a sentence has a lot to do with its structure, and very little to do with word order. 
	 We saw this by looking at how the meaning of multiple modifiers is computed. 
Consider NPs like Error! Reference source not found. )
-(49), which have two adjectives 
on the lef
t side of the NP.  The structure for these exam
ples (details omitted) is (46): 
(44)	 a. a large small shirtb. a small large shirt 
(45)	 a. a popular wrong answer
b. a wrong popular answer 
(46) 
NP 
D N' #1 
Adj1 
Adj2 N' #2 
N' #3 
The meanings of these NPs is computed by first computing the meaning of Adj2 + N', and 
then adding the meaning of Adj1 to the result.  Thus, a large small shirt is a small shirt that is on the large side. A small large shirt is a large shirt that is on the small side. A 
common wrong answer is an answer that is common within the set of wrong answers, but a wrong common answer is an answer that is common within the set of all answers  and is 
wrong. Here are some similar pairs you might enjoy thinking about: 
(47)	 a. an alleged English baron
b. an English alleged bsron 
(48)	 a. the priceless broken vaseb. the broken priceless vase 
(49)	 a. the recovered stolen property
b. the stolen recovered property Addendum: Right-hand modifiers 
We didn't spend much time at all on this additional point.  (Blame the hurricane.) But it's 
worth paying some atention to. 
With left-hand modifiers, the further to the right you are, the deeper "inside" the NP you 
are. Thus, Adj2 in (46) is deeper inside NP than Adj1 is.  
With right-hand modifiers, just the opposite is true.  The further to the 
left you are, the
deeper "inside" you are. Consider, for example, the tree in (50).  PP1 is to the left of PP2, 
but is further "inside" the tree than PP2  unlike A
dj1 in (46), which is higher in the tree 
than Adj2. 
(50)	 NP 
D 
N' N' 
PP2
 
N' PP1
 
Consider (51), for example.  A shirt of great value may acquire a hole (due, for example, 
to moths), in which case it is no longer necessarily a shirt of great value.  Thus, (51a) is a 
perfectly normal thing to say.  A shirt of great value with a hole is not necessarily
valuable, just as an alleged English baron is not necessarily English. By contrast, a shirt with a hole of great value is a shirt that has acquired a hole and  in that state  is valuable!  For example, the hole itself might have raised the value of the shirt, if (for example) it is the shirt Lincoln was wearing when he was shot.  In class I suggested that Lincoln might have bought that shirt for $1 at Walmart, but of course it is now worth millions.  That is why  (51b) is odd (marked by "#", which means "not ungrammatical, but weird for some other reason"): 
(51)	 a. A shirt of great value with a hole is worthless.
b. #A shirt with a hole of great value is worthless. 
Here are some other cutesy examples of the same sort. In (52a), we are talking about a 
man with an unusual last name, who happens to be from China.  Well, Ng (=
 //!) is an 
unusual last name in North America, even if it's common in China, so Mr. Ng qualifies as such a man.  But Mr. Smith does not.  In (52b), we are talking about a man from China with an unusual last name.  Bur Smith is an uncommon name among men from China, so Mr. Smith qualifies for this designation.  Ng is not an unusual name among men from China, so Mr. Ng does not. Thus, we have the following judgments: 
(52)	 a. the man with the unusual last name from China (#Smith, ok Ng)
b. the man from China with the unusual last name (ok Smith, *Ng) 
The examples in (53) make a similar point: 
(53)	 a. A vehicle with one wheel missing with three wheels used to have four (#three).
b. A vehicle with four wheels with one wheel missing used to have three (#four).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.900 Introduction to Linguistics
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>-5-
4. Converging evidence for the concept "head": head-final vs. head-initial languages 
	 Some Japanese sentences: 
(23)  	 John-ga        hon-o  yon da 
John-SUBJ  book-DO  read PAST 'John has read the book'/'John read the book' 
(24)	 John-ga  Mary-
ni   kono hon-o  age ta 
John-SUBJ Mary  to that book-DO  give PAST 'John has given that book to Mary/John gave Mary that book' 
(25)	 Mary-ga       kono Nihon kara-
no  kagaku no gakusei-o korosi ta 
Mary-SUBJ this  Japan from       chemistry of  student-DO kill  PA
ST 
'Mary killed/has killed this student of chemistry from Japan' 
(26)	 Mary-ga       John-ga  hon-o  yon da to omottei ru 
Mary-SUBJ John-SUBJ book-DO read PAST that  think PRESENT 
'Mary thinks that John is reading the book' 
	 Japanese word order is different from English  but if we run the same kinds of tests 
for constituency that we run in English, we come up with a structure for a complex 
sentence like (21)  that looks like (27a)  in which C follows (rather than precedes) its 
IP sister, amd I follows (rather than precedes) its VP sister.  Compare its English 
counterpart in (27b):1 
(27) a. b. 
	 ... and structures for sentences like (24) and (25) with PPs in which P follows, rather 
than precedes its sister. We call such instances of P postpositions (vs. prepositions): 
(28) 
	 The word order of Japanese is actually the same as English, except that the head of 
each phrase precedes its complement in English, and follows it in Japanese. We 
thus call English head-initial and call Japanese head-final. 
	 The fact that Japanese and English differ in whether heads precede or follow their 
complements tells us that "head first" vs. "head last" is not innate, and is something that a child acquiring just learns. It is a " parameter of variation"among languages, or 
parameter, for short.
2 
	 Notice that the English/Japanese difference gives us converging evidence for the notion head  because it is the C of CP, the I of IP, the V of VP (also the P of PP and the N of NP) that switches position as we move between Japanese and English. The 
subject of the sentence, as well as words like this, do not switch position. 
5.	 A digression worth reading:   for as an English com
plementizer
Here is why I am calling 'for' a complementizer in some cases (not discussed in class) 
	 I have been calling for a complementizer in English sentences like (14b)  that is, a C 
taking an IP as its complement.  How do we know that for really is a complementizer? 
How do we know, for example, that it is not actually a P taking the following NP as its 
complement? 
	 ...After all, there does exist a for that functions in this way, of course, as in I made the cake for Sue  which means something like "I made the cake so that Sue would have 
it and benefit from it". What makes us think that what follows 
for in the sentence 
Mary arranged for Sue to read the book really is an IP, as in (14b)?  Here's one good argument in favor of that view: 
	 There is a special use of the word 
it when it is the subject of verbs that describe the 
weather. For this reason, it is generally called "weather it": 
(29)	 a. It was raining today.
b. It rarely snows in July. 
This use of it 
looks like a pronoun, but unlike a normal pronoun, it does not refer to 
anything, and does not require you to know what the speaker has in mind when using 
the word. For example, if I enter the room and say, out of the blue... 
(30)	 I baked a cake for it. 
...you will be puzzled, since you don't know what the word it referred to. You might respond "You backed a cake for what?". 
1 I am using the "progressive forms" is thinking and is reading so the position of I is visible in English. 2 What the book by Baker is all about!.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>-2-
must contain a noun.  The noun does not have to be pronounced adjacent to the 
preposition  a determiner and any number of adjectives may linearly intervene  
but the noun must be there! This can be seen in the contrast between (5a-e) and  (5f-h) 
below: 
(5) The quick brown fox will jump ...
a. 	... over the lazy dog.
b. 	... over the dog.
c. 	... over lazy dogs.
d. 	... over dogs.
e. 	... over the ridiculous lazy green dog. 
f
.  	... *over the. 
g. 	... *over the lazy. 
h. ... *over of. 
	 Because the noun is the indispensable element in the sister that a preposition like over 
takes, we call it the head of this sister, and we label the phrase NP ("Noun Phrase") in 
its honor. 
	 Any other nodes that dominate N and are dominated by NP are labeled N' 
("N-bar"), 
since N is also the head of these nodes: 
(6) 
 Terminology: We call N' and NP projections of their head N. NP is the maximal 
projection of its head N, since it is not dominated by any further projections of that N. 
3. Subcategorization as a tool for finding heads 
	 The fact about P seen above is more general.  When a word W merges with something 
to form a phrase that is a projection of W, it is picky! It cares about what it merges with it. A particular choice of sister may be obligatory, optional or forbidden
. 
	 For example, most prepositions merge with an NP to form a PP, but prepositions differ in whether this NP is obligatory or optional: 
(7) a. Mary walked in the room.
b. Mary walked in. c.	 Mary walked into the room
d. *Mary walked into. 
	 Verbs offer a particularly rich array of pickiness possibilities.  Contrast vanish with 
erase, eat with devour; and throw with 
put, for example: 
(8) a. Bill has vanished. 
b. *Bill has vanished the blackboard. 
c.	 *Bill has erased. 
d. Bill has erased the blackboard. 
(9) a. Mary has eaten.b. Mary has eaten the pizza. 
c.	 *Mary has devoured.
d. Mary has devoured the pizza. 
(10) a. John will throw. [but limited to sports context]
b. John will throw the ball. 
c. John will throw the ball to Tom. 
d. [?]John will throw to Tom. [but limited to sports context 
e. *John will put.
f. *John will put the book.
g. John will put the book under the desk.h. *John will put under the desk. 
	 Adjectives are not quite as rich in differences, but fond (which requires a PP) contrasts 
instructively with proud (which allows, but does not require one): 
(11) a. *Mary is fond.b. Mary is fond of her friends. 
c.	 Mary is proud.
d. Mary is proud of her friends. 
	 This information forms part of the lexical entry for the prepositions, verbs and 
adjectives seen above  an
d is to a great extent arbitrary (as far as we know). It is 
called the subcategorization property of the word (e.g. "devour subcategorizes for a 
NP
")  a property we discussed earllier in the section on morphology (when we 
observed that -ness, for example, must attach to an adjective). 
	 See pp.162-167 of the textbook for their presentation of this topic. 
In a 1965 book called Aspects of the Theory of Syntax, Noam Chomsky suggested that the 
following generalization restricts the type of information that subcategorization makes use 
of:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Now suppose instead I enter the room and say (29a)  Would you be puzzled by themeaning of "it"?  You might wonder why I decided to talk about the weather, but you 
will not reply by asking "What was raining today?"  This is because you recognize the 
special it of weather sentences for what it is! 
This it is always used as a subject. We never find it as the object of indisputable
prepositions. But, lo and behold, it can be used following for in sentences like (31): 
(31)	 Mary arranged for it to rain (during the festival). 
This is a good argument that for has an alternative life as a complem
entizer, taking 
an IP as its sister, since its complement is a clause (an IP)  not the NP that 
immediately follows it, w
hich turns out to be the subject of that clause) 
...and what about the word to in sentences with complementizer for? Why is it being
called an instance of I? Why isn't it just a preposition? 
	 Well...it follows the subject and precedes the VP.  Also it is in complementary 
distribution (remember that word?) with finite auxiliary verbs like will, have and must
, 
suggesting that it is just another instance of I, despite its distinct "look". 
(32)
	 *Mary arranged for Sue to will take the quiz early. 
What's with all of these complementizers and instances of I that have "other lives" as 
prepositions and other stuff? 
	 Across the languages of the world, it is very common for "function words" 
(complementizers and I-elements especially)  to be made of "spare parts", words used 
elsewhere with other, more robust meanings. Thus that is a C, but also a Det used for 
objects remote from the speaker (as in that book); for is a C, but also a P; and 
to is an 
I, but also a P. 
	 This fact is the result of a common process by which languages change, called 
grammaticalization. Similar phenomena are very common. In many West African 
languages, for example, the word corresponding to the complementizer that is also the 
verb 'say', or can be shown to be historically derived from such a word. It is also very common for words that mean 'who' or '
what' to be recycled as 'that'.  The modern 
Romance languages did that when they developed from Latin (which had no that-
word). 
End of digression (from what we discussed in class). -6-
6.	 A possible universal of syntax: the Final-over-Final Constraint 
	 We observed that the relative order of a head and the element that it merges with varies 
systematically across languages. In particular: 
	 English is a uniformly head-first language. The lexical item that heads a phrase always precedes its sister within that phrase. 
	 Japanese is a uniformly head-final language.  The lexical item that heads a phrase always follows its sister within that phrase. 
But postulating a uniform "head-f
irst/head-last" parameter across entire languages 
oversimplifies the picture.  Certain kinds of mixed languages do exist: 
(33)	 Kinds of languages that exist: 
a. 	head-initial languages:
In languages like English
, a head of a phrase systematically precedes its sister (the
element it merged with): 
head non-head 
...that Mary will read books 
b. 	head-final languages:
In languages like Japanese, a head of a phrase systematically follows its sister (the 
element it merged with). 
non-head  head 
...Mary books read will that 
c. 	mixed languages type 1
German (head-final V and I, head-initial C):
 
...that Mary the book read will.
 
VP:	 head-final 
... [VP	 [NP das Buch ] lesen ]
the book read
 
IP:	 head-final 
... [IP [VP das Buch    lesen ] wird ]
 
the book read FUT
 
CP:	 head-initial  !! 
... [CP	 dass [IP Marie das Buch lesen  hat ]
 
that Marie the book read FUT</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>-11-
(61) 
10. Specifier of CP 
Specifiers:  Certain heads require that the last merged element of the phrase that they label 
be something special  not a modifier, and certainly not a complement (by definition).  
This is a bit of a mysterious requirement, and has a name, but not an explanation.  We say 
that these heads require a specfier. The main example of a genuine bona fide specifier 
that we have seen so far is the subject position, specifier of IP. 

	 What is the landing site for wh-movement? 
In a Standard English main clause, wh
-movement (of anything except the subject, 
actually) is always accompanied by I-to-C movement. 
I-to-C movement 
(62) [Which pizza ] will the lion ___ devour ___ 
wh-movement If the position of I tells us the location of C, then we can conclude that wh -
movement targets a position in CP just to the left of C. 
Conclusion: Wh-movement forms a specifier of CP. 
(63) 
	 Side remark (not discussed in class): In modern standard English, you only see wh-
movement when C is null (not counting an I that moved to it). Other languages, 
including earlier stages of English, are different  so there is no general ban on seeing 
both a wh-phrase and a complementizer in the same CP: 
(64) 
a. Specifier of CP + overt C in other languages 
Ik weet niet wie of Jan gezien heeft. 
I know not who if John seen has [Dutch] 
b. Men shal wel knowe who that I am. [Middle English] 
c. Je me demande quand 
que Pierre est parti. 
I wonder 
when that Pierre has left [colloquial French]</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>-4-
(21) 
C subcategorizes for the I of its sister ( to vs. [past, future]): 
(17)	 a. *Mary will believe
[
that the brown fox to depend on the lazy dog]. 
b.	 Mary will arrange
[for the brown fox 
to depend on the lazy dog].
 
c.	 Mary will believe 
[that 
the brown fox has depended on the lazy dog].
 
d.	 *Mary will arrange
[
for the brown fox has depended on the lazy dog].
 
 So I is the head of the sister of C.  Sentences are IPs. 
(22) 
I subcategorizes for the V-morphology of its VP complement (tensed vs. bare-stem) 
(18) a. ... [for the quick brown fox to [depend on the lazy dog]. 
b. *...[for the quick brown fox to [depended on the lazy dog]. 
(19) a. ... [that the quick brown fox will [depend on the lazy dog]. 
b. *... [that the quick brown fox will [depended on the lazy dog]. 
(20) a. *... [that the quick brown fox has depend on the lazy dog]. 
b. ... [that the quick brown fox has depended on the lazy dog]. 
 So V is the head of the sister of I.  Verbs head VPs. 
...Which of course is why we called them CP, IP and VP in the first place! 
[Terminology: We call the sister of the head of a phrase its complem
ent,]</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>I  (78)	 Vata verb-second 
a. N le 	 bI sak.
 
eat now rice
 
b. n k 	 yO-O  sl-e  ml  sak ny  
I will child-the  house-the in  rice give 
c.  la sak li 
we have rice eat
 
'we have eaten rice'
 
ASIA! 
Kashmiri (Indo-Aryan family of languages; Indian subcontinent) 
verb follows the first phrase, unless there's an auxiliary verb, in which case the 
auxiliary verb follows the first phrase and the main verb 
is at the end. 
[work of Rakesh Bhatt] 
(79)	 Kashmiri verb-second 
a. 
	raman dits shamas 
kitab.
 
ram+SUBJ gave sham-IO  book
 
b. ram 	 chu shamas kitab divan
 
ram+SUBJ is 
sham-IO  book giving
 
c. 	varI-varI chu ram  bat khevan.

 
slowly  is ram rice eating
 
SOUTH AMERICA! 
Karitiana (Arikm family of languages, Rondonia state, Brazil) 
Subordinate clause: verb is at the end 
Main clause: main verb follows the first phrase (or comes first), 
unless there's an auxiliary
 verb, in which case the 
auxiliary verb follows the first phrase and the main verb is at the end. 
[work of Luciana Storto] -15-
17. The Big Picture (and how verb-second is relevant to it) 
(80) 	 What we find: 
Languages are not all the same, but the ways in which they differ are highly
restricted . The same peculiar bits show up again and again, all over the world. 
What's the same is called Universal Grammar (UG)
 
What's different  are settings of parameters 
within UG.
 
An acquisition perspective on UG and parameter setting: 
	 UG reflects our genetic endowment for language 
	 Parameter setting reflects our linguistic experience in early childhood. 

	 For example, though we don't find verb-second in all the languages of the world, we 
do find it popping up repeatedly  as we just saw. 
	 On the other hand there are some types of languages that are just as easy to describe in words as the verb-second languages, which we never find: 
(81)	 Some languages that don't exist anywhere (as far as we know
): 
a. Like German, but patterns of embedded and main clause are reversed. b. Main verb must follow the second phrase, third 
phrase, etc. 
c. Not the main verb, but the direct object must follow the first phrase. 
18. Some other parameters (and how they are set in a few languages) 
[See Baker's book for much more,] 
1.  Subject pro-drop 
(82)	 Italian: + 
a. 	
Io parlo italiano
(I) speak Italian 
b. Noi parliamo italiano
(we) speak  Italian 
(83) Chinese: + 
Ta kanjian
(he) see 
'He saw him'. ta le. 
he LE 
(84) English: -
*(We) speak English.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>SYNTACTIC STRUCTURE: Generated by Merge
18SYNTACTIC STRUCTURE: Generated by Merge
18SYNTACTIC STRUCTURE: Generated by Merge
18 
    
 
  
 
 
 
   
 
 
 
 
 
 
   
  
  
    
  
    
 
   
 
 
  
  
  
  
 
 
 
 
  
   
 
   
 
  
 
 
     
 
 
   
 
      
   
       
 
 
  
 
             
 
 
 
 
 
 
  
 
 
 
 
  
 
 
  
 
 
 
 
  
 
  
 
 
  
 
 
  24.900 Fall 2012 
Syntax summary updated to 11/19 /2012 
1. Syntactic hierarchy and constituency 
 We began by reviewing basic, somewhat crude evidence that sentences are not formed 
by taking words from the lexicon and arranging them like beads on a string ... 
 ...but instead are hierarchically arranged in nested groups called constituents (or phrases) that can be represented as a tree (of the sort familiar from the textbook chapter). 
 Our initial "crude evidence" (repeated from the first class of the semester) involved the 
substrings of a sentence that can be repeated as a coherent "surprise reaction": 
(1) The "surprise reaction" test for constituentsSpeaker 1: "Guess what?  The quick brown fox will jump over the lazy dog."Speaker 2: "You're kidding!  
a. Jump over the lazy dog?"b. *Will jump over the?"
etc. 
 The structures for sentences revealed by this test and others are built from words by the recursive rule Merge the same simple rule that built words out of morphemes: 
(2) MergeForm a set whose members are two elements  and , either or both of which may be a. words from the lexicon, or
b. a set previously formed by Merge 
 ...So we expect to see Merge applying in three different ways:  combining a lexical b. Merge a lexical item with a set formed by Merge: the + lazy dog 
Then, once the derivation has built will jump over the lazy dog and separately built
the quick brown fox ... 
c. Merge two set s formed by Merge: 
item with another lexical item; combining a lexical item with a set formed by Merge; 
and combining a set formed by Merge with another set formed by Merge. We do 
indeed find all three: 
(3) The three faces of Merge:The quick brown fox will jump over the lazy dog. 
a. Merge two lexical items : lazy + dog 	 We then introduced some terminology useful for discussing syntactic structures. I did 
not define these terms in class, and I won't do that here  since in my experience, their 
meaning is easy to pick up by example.  If you have questions about these terms, 
however, do not hesitate to ask: 
(4) Terminology for referring to tree structuresnode, immediately dominates, dominates, mother, daughter, sister, root node, terminal 
node 
2. Labeling the nodes: the notions head 
and projection 
	 Syntactic structures contain more information than just patterns of sisterhood and 
immediate domination among nodes. In each constituent, one element is especially 
important (and gives the constituent its n
ame).  That element is called the head of the 
constituent. 
	 For example, consider what is allowed to be the sister to a preposition. It turns out that the sister to a preposition may contain a wide variety of miscellaneous things  but it</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>d.	 mixed languages type 2
Spoken Afrikaans (head-final V, head-initial T and C)
...that Mary will books read.
...that she has often Chopin played.
3
 
VP:	 head -final 
[VP [NP Chopin] gespeel ]
Chopin played
 
IP:	 head-initial !! 
[TP het [VP dikwels [NP Chopin] gespeel ]
 
has often Chopin played
 
CP:	 head-initial !! 
[CP dat [TP sy het dikwels Chopin gespeel]]
that she has often  Chopin played
(Biberauer, Newton, Sheehan 2009)
 
	 ...but other kinds of mixed languages appear not to exist: 
(34)a.	 mixed languages type 3
Literary Martian (head-initial V and T, head-final C): 
... Mary will read books that. (does not exist on Earth!) 
b.	 mixed languages type 3
Old High Venusian (head-initial V, head-final T and C)

... Mary read books will that (does not exist on Earth!
 
	 This is called the 
Final-over-Final Constraint (FOFC): 
(35)	 The "Final-over-Final Constraint"  (FOFC): a linguistic universal
(Holmberg 2000; Biberauer, Holmberg &amp; Roberts 2010) 
a.	 Within a single clause or noun-phrase, if a phrase is head-initial, the phrase that 
immediately contains it must also be head-initial... 
b. ...but if a phrase is head-final, the phrase that immediately contains it may 
be head-final or head-initial. 
	 If correct, FOFC is (or is a by-product of) a principle of Universal Grammar  a 
principle that restricts the ways in w
hich languages vary (and restricts the 
"search space" for a child acquiring language). 
Is Mandarin Chinese a counterexample? 
	 Mandarin Chinese has sentence-final particles that signal that the clause is a question 
 
above a VP and IP that generally look head-initial: 
3 The real -life example I have involves playing Chopin, not reading books.  Go figure ... -7-
(36)	 Ni yao kan zhe-ben shu   ma? (Mandarin, Aldridge 2009) 
you want read this- CL book Q
'Do you want to read this book?' 
	 Is Mandarin Chinese "Literary Martian"  i.e. a language that's not supposed to exist 
(but does)? 
As the team of researchers investigating FOFC note, however, we do not find this kind 
of apparent counterexample to FOFC with complementizers analagous to the English 
complementizers that or for (or German dass and Afrikaans dat). 
So it is possible that elements like 
ma in (36) are not instances of C, but modifiers of C 
that are allowed to be found on the right side in an otherwise head-initial CP. 
	 Mandarin has other small "particles" (the traditional term) that occur CP-finally, and 
raise similar problems.  For example, there is a clause-final particle le that can mark 
the completion of an action (a notion often encoded in I), and has other effects on the 
use of the sentence in discourse as well. Counterexamples to FOFC? Not really 
instances of C I don't have a good answer, and it is worth thinking about. 
	 Mandarin Chinese is also puzzling because its verbs precede their objects (as we 
expect in a head-initial language)  but in NP, relative clauses precede the noun they modify. So it'
s a language that gives syntacticians lots to worry about ... 
7. Structure and meaning:  Principle C 
	 Consider the following pair of good English sentences: 
(37)a. Hillary claims that she likes pizza.
b. She claims that Hillary likes pizza. 
Both are acceptable, but in the first sentence, 
Hillary and she may corefer  i.e. they 
may pick out the same individual in the world.  In the second sentence, however, this is 
impossible.  We can indicate coreference with identity of subscript indices, and present 
the data as f
ollows: 
(38)a. Hillary i claims that she i likes pizza. 
b.	 *She i claims that Hillary i likes pizza. 
	 The asterisk on (38b) means that the sentence is bad with the interpretation given by 
the indices. The minute she and Hillary are understood as referring to two different individuals, both sentences are fine  and we would represent that by using some 
index other than i on one of these NPs (and leaving out the asterisk). 
Now
 let's get down to business. 
	 An obvious idea about why (38b) is bad:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>-8-
(39)	 A plausible but wrong idea about (38)
A pronoun may not corefer with a NP that it precedes. 
	 Evidence that (39) is wrong comes from examples like the following.  In the (b) examples, the pronoun precedes an NP with which it is coreferent. 
(40)	 a. This new book about Hillary i claims that she i likes pizza.
b. This new book about her i claims that Hillary i likes pizza. 
(41)	 a. Hillary's i enem
ies claim that she i likes pizza.
b. Her i enemies claim that Hillary i likes pizza. 
	 It turns out that what distinguishes examples like (38b) from examples like (40b) and 
(41b) is not linear order but structure. Consider the relative positions of the pronoun 
and the NP Hillary in these examples: 
(38b) 
Error! Reference source not found. b) 
(41b) 
	 In examples like (38b) (and in response to questions, we looked at a bunch of them in 
class)  where her and Mary may not corefer  a very particular relation holds 
between the pronoun and the full NP:  the node that immediately dominates the 
pronoun NP (her) also dominates the full NP (Mary). This relation is called c-
command and turns out to be very important for all sorts of phenomena: 
(42)	 C-command 
A node  c-commands a node  iff
: 
a. the mother of  dominates , and
4
 b.  does not dominate .
	 C-command relations between pronouns and full NPs constraint the choice of possible 
referents for the pronoun, i.e. what it may refer to. The constraint in question is called 
Principle C: 
(43)	 Principle C
If an pronoun NP x c-commands a full NP y, 
x and y may not be coref
erent. 
	 Principle C is one of a group of principles that constrain coreference possibilities 
among NPs. 
(There is also a Principle A and B, which you can read about in the 
textbook.) We are learning about Principle C now, as an example of the relation 
between syntactic structure and meaning. 
	 Syntactic structure is independent of meaning in many ways. For example, we know 
that Chomsky's famous sentence Colorless green ideas sleep furiously 
is English, and 
the same sentence backwards is not (*Furiously sleep ideas green colorless)  despite the fact that the good sentence is literally meaningless (unless understood 
metaphorically). 
	 At the same time, however, syntactic structure and meaning interact in many ways. 
Principle C is just one of them. In the next section, we consider another. 
4 We don't really need clause (b) of this definition for the purposes of this class, but it needs to be part of the
definition of c -com
mand for other reasons (and I can't bring myself to leave it out).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>-14-
	 The verb "leaves its prefix behind"  just as what in W.Ulster wh-all can 
"leave all behind". 
(76)	 Die Frau an-macht ___ [jetzt das Licht an-macht]
 . 
the woman-SUBJ  makes now the light-OBJ  on 
'The woman is now turning the light on.' 
"The Germans have another kind of parenthesis, which they make 
by splitting a verb in two and putting half of it at the beginning of an 
exciting chapter and the other half at the end of it. Can any one conceive of anything more confusing than that? These things are called "separable verbs." The German grammar is blistered all ove r 
with separable verbs; and the wider the two portions of one of them are spread apart, the better the author of the crime is pleased with his performance. A favorite one is reiste ab --which means, 
departed. Here is an example which I culled from a nov el and 
reduced to English: 
The trunks being now ready, he DE- after kissing his mother and 
sisters, and once more pressing to his bosom his adored Gretchen, 
who, dressed in simple white muslin, with a single tuberose in the ample folds of her rich brown hair, had tottered feebly down the stairs, still pale from the terror and excitement of the past evening, but longing to lay her poor aching head yet once again upon the breast of him whom she loved more dearly than life itself, PARTED. " 
-Mark Twain , "The Awful German Language" 
15. I-to-C in German 
	 Actually, the main verb moves to C only when there is no auxiliary verb in I. 
	 When there is an auxiliary verb in I, the auxiliary verb moves to C (and the main verb 
is left in VP). (77) 
a. Die Frau 	 hat [gestern den Mann gesehen] hat. 
the woman-SUBJ  has yesterday the-OBJ man seen 
'The woman saw the man y
esterday.' 
b. Den Man hat die Frau 
[gestern ____ gesehen] hat 
the man-OBJ has the woman-SUBJ  yesterday seen 
'
The man the woman saw.' 
c. Gestern hat die Frau [ ___ den Mann gesehen] hat 
yesterday saw the woman-SUBJ the man-OBJ seen 
'
Yesterday the woman saw the man.' 
	 What is really happening in V2 is probably not V
-to-C but V-to -I and then I-to-C 
(which takes the Verb along). 
16. 
V/2 on four continents 
EUROPE! 
German (Germanic group of the Indo-European family of languages, Western Europe) 
Subordinate clause: verb is at the end 
Main clause: main verb follows the first phrase (or comes first), 
unless there's an auxiliary verb, in which case the 
auxiliary verb follows the first phrase and the main verb 
is at the end. 
AFRICA! 
Vata (Kru family of languages; Ivory Coast, Africa) 
verb follows the first phrase (or comes first), 
unless there's an auxiliary verb, in which case the 
auxiliary verb follows the first phrase and the main verb 
is at the end. 
[work of Hilda Koopman] 
[like German, except subordinate clauses behave like main clauses]</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>-13-
Movement 2: Topicalization to Spec,CP (= "specifier of CP") 
	 When C is null, it not only requires the verb to move to its head, it also requires a 
specifier. That is why we always have topicalization as well. 
Hypothesis: A null C also triggers movement to Spec,CP in German. 
This yields Verb-second. 
(72) Verb-second in German 
V-to-C movement 
a. Die Frau sah ___ gestern [ den Mann v]  . 
topicalization 
the woman-SUBJ  saw yesterday   the-OBJ man 
'The woman saw the man yesterday.' 
b. Den Man 
saw the woman-SUBJ  yesterday sah die Frau [gestern ____ v]. 
the man-OBJ 
'The man the woman saw.'
 
c. Gestern sah die Frau [___ den Mann v] . 
yesterday saw the woman-SUBJ the man-OBJ
 
'Yesterday the woman saw the man.'
 
	 In (72), the topicalized phrase has a dotted underline, the verb is boldfaced, and the VP  
is bracketed. The underline marks where the topicalized phrase came from, and the 
italic v marks where the verb came from. Here is (72b) in tree form, so you can see 
more explicitly how this works: (73) Structure for (72b) 
14. German Verb-second and complex phonology! 
	 Prefixed verbs: In German, some verbs with prefixes, when they move, pronounce 
the only the root in the moved position, and pronounce the prefix in the original 
position. 
(74) An example like (71), but with a morphologically complex verb root 
...dass die Frau [jetz das Licht an-macht]. 
...that the woman-SUBJ now the light-OBJ  on-makes 
'...that the woman is now turning on the light.' 
(75) What happens to anmacht in a V/2 environment? 
a. Die Frau macht ___ [jetzt das Licht an-v
] . 
the woman-SUBJ  makes now the light-OBJ  on 
'The woman is now turning the light on.' 
b. Das Licht macht die Frau [jetzt ___ an-v]. 
the 
light-OBJ makes the woman-SUBJ  now on 
'The light the woman is now turning on.' 
c. Jetzt macht die Frau [___ das Licht an-v]. 
now makes the woman-SUBJ the light-OBJ on 
'Now the woman is turning on the light.' 
 
       CP 
       C'  
    
 
        NP       C   IP 
     sah 
    NP   I' 
 N'          N'   
         VP  I 
Det N    Det       N       
         Adv  V' Past 
den  Mann    die    Frau    
       gestern   NP         V 
 
               N' 
             sah 
     Det     
     den Man n</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>We don't want to say that sometimes meaning is computed right-to-left, and sometimes 
it is computed left-to right.  Fortunately, we don't have to!  It is the structure (as
represented with tree diagrams) that determines how meaning is computed! 
...and that in turn gives us another argument for the reality of
 syntactic structure 
9. Movement 
	 Certain sentences show apparent violations of subcategorization restrictions.  In 
particular, we see a gap where a phrase should be. Such a gap is unacceptable (see 
(54)-(55)) unless the gap is "filled" by a "moved" version of the missing phrase (see 
(56) and (57)).  This phenomenon is called movement. 
(54) a. The lion will devour this pizza. 
b. *The lion will devour. 
(55) a. John can depend on Mary.
b. *John can depend on. 
c. *John can depend. 
	 The kind of movement seen in (56) below is called topicalization. 
(56) Topicalization  (a kind of movement) 
a. [This pizza ] the lion will devour ___. 
b. [Mary ] John can depend on __. 
c. [On Mary ] John can certainly depend __! 
	 The kind of movement seen in (57) is called wh-movement. 
a. I wonder [what 
which pizzathe lion will devour __ ].
 
I wonder [ ] the lion will devour ___ ].
 (57) Wh-movement 
b. I wonder [who ] John can depend on __. 
c. I wonder [on whom ] John can depend __. -10-
Wh-movement applies to phrases that contain (usually at their left-periphery) a 
question-asking word  which in English spelling usually starts with wh. The term is 
used even when describing other languages as well. 
	 Sometimes, it is the I that is missing from its normal position, and appears elsewhere.  
In these cases, we have I-to-C movement, usually found in "yes/no" questions. 
Notice that has in (58b) requires the participle form ( written) of the main verb, just as 
if it were occupying its normal position: 
(58) I-to-C movement a. Will 
the lion __ devour the pizza? 
b. Can John ___ depend on Mary? 
c. 	Did the children __ go to school? 
	 Why think that the I is moving to C?  Well, although in colloquial English (for many 
speakers  not all) I-to-C movement is possible in embedded clauses, as in (59) (where "%" indicates dialect variation)...: 
(59)	 I-to-C movement in an embedded clause (colloquial) 
%Bill is wondering [will he __ finish his homework on time] 
...this kind of I-to-C movement never cooccurs with an overt C in the embedded 
clause: 
(60) a. *Bill is wondering [will that he finish his homework on time]. 
b. 	*Bill is wondering [that will he finish his homework on time]. 
	 So C has something to do with the movement. 
Hypothesis: 
A null C (evidence: no that) triggers I-to-C movement in English 
questions.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>11. A way of thinking about movement:  "internal merge" 
Merge so far...
	 Ingredients: independent lexical items or independent results of previous 
operations of Merge 
Movement = Merge, where one of the ingredients is a subconstituent of another 
Terminology : 
a. External Merge (ingredients are independent, what we've done so far) 
b.
 Internal Merge (= movement) 
How phonology interprets movement. 
	 The syntax sends an instruction to the phonology (in many cases) to not pronounce the 
phrase in its original position. 
The original position of the phrase is also known as the trace 
of movement. 
12. Wh-movement leaves something behind 
	 The wh-all construction: Many dialects of English use what all and who all as 
optional plural forms of who and what. For example, if I ask Who all did you invite __ for dinner?, I presuppose that you are inviting more than one person. Thus, the word 
all
, when used with who and what, is a plural morpheme. 
	 The West Ulster version: The wh-all construction of West Ulster English (Northern 
Ireland; data from McCloskey 2000) has a special possibility not found in other 
dialects. The all may be pronounced in the position where the wh
-phrase "would have 
been found" if movement had not taken place.  Thus, both variants in (65)-(67) are acceptable in this dialect of English (though only the first member of each pair is 
acceptable in other dialects): 
(65)	 a. What all did you give __ to the kids? 
b. What did you give __ all to the kids? 
(66)	 a. Who all did you send __ to the shops? 
b. Who did you send __ all to the shops? 
(67)	 a. Tell me what all you got __ for Christmas. 
b. Tell me w
hat you got __ all for Christmas. 
	 What might be going on: A different pronunciation pattern. Optionally, part of the trace (all) gets pronounced, and the corresponding part "upstairs" does 
not get pronounced: -12-
(68)	 a. Tell me what all you got what all for Christmas. 
b. Tell me what all you got what all for Christmas. 
	 It is important to make sure that the all is not simply free to occur anywhere -- that it 
really does single out the position of the "trace".  The following data show this. 
(69)  *Who did he tell __ that he was going to resign all. 
(70)	 a. What did you do __ 
all after school the day? 
b. *
What did you do __ after school the day all? 
c. *What did you do __ after school all the day. 
13. Verb movement in German:  the "Verb-second" phenomenon 
Split pronunciation after movement is not unique to wh-movement.  In the next 
section, we see it in German V-to-C movement.  First, some preliminary 
information about German: 
Famou facts about German 
	 Subordinate clauses: In a normal embedded clause, the verb follows its 
complements. German thus looks like Japanese. 
(71)	 V follows its complements in a normal embedded clause 
...dass 
die Frau [gestern den Mann sah
]. 
...that the woman-SUBJ yesterday the man-OBJ  saw '...that the woman saw the man y
esterday.' 
	 Main clauses: The main clause of a German sentence has two particular properties of note: 
1. one phrase is always topicalized; and 
2. the verb is found in a surprising place  immediately after the topicalized phrase. 
This yields what is called the Verb-second (V2) property of German. V2 arises from two 
different instances of movement, both of which take place in a German main clause. 
Movement 1: V-to-C 
	 V2 is found whenever C is not filled by the word dass. This is true in main clauses, 
but also in some subordinate clauses as well. 
Hypothesis: 
A null C (evidence: no dass) triggers V-to-C movement in German 
This gets us Verb-first so far.  What about Verb-second?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>-3-
(12)	 Chomsky's Generalization concerning subcategorization
(to be criticized as not quite right  see below)
The lexical entry for a word contains subcategorization information only about its sister. 
	 Examplifying Chomsky's principle: no verb, for example, requires that its sister be an 
NP that itself contains an adjective, and no verb requirtes that its subject contain a PP. Such a verb might be the imaginary verb glork, for which we would have the 
(imaginary) data in (13): 
(13)	 The imaginary verb glork that would counterexemplify Chomsky's 
Generalization a. The queen of England has glorked a purple chair.
b. *The queen of Englandhas glorked a chair. [no adjective in its sister NP] 
c. *The queen has glorked a chair. [no PP in its subject] 
What's right about Chom
sky's Generalization? 
The significance of Chom
sky's Generalization for language acquisition:  
	 If the generalization is just the way language works  part of Universal Grammar, 
our genetic endowment for language... 
	 ...then a child who is acquiring language does not have to pay attention to the entire phrase structure tree when learning the subcategorization requirements of a word. 
Makes the task of language acquisition easier, because lots of data may simply be 
ignored by the child. 
What's wrong about Chomsky's Principle? 
Here's one example: a verb may subcategorize not just f
or a PP, but for the specific 
preposition in a sister PP: 
English vs. Russian
 
depend on zaviset' ot lit. 'depend from'
 
speak 
to govorit' s lit. 'speak with'

 
look at smotret' n
a lit. 'watch on'
 
look for iskat' knigu lit. 'seek'
 
English dialect 1 vs. English dialect 2
wait for 'actively anticipate the arrival of' wait on [!] 'actively anticipate the arrival of'
 
wait on 'serve, in a restaurant' wait on 'serve food to, in a restaurant'
 

	 These are facts learned by the child from the linguistic environment. The very fact that 
languages differ (apparently arbitrarily) tells us this. Thus, for example, English does 
not allow *Mary depends from her computer, even though Russian does. But Russian, 
in turn does not allow the equivalent of 'depend on' (*zaviset' na
), even though English does. So the lexical entry for the verb depend must care about more than just the fact that its sister is a PP. It has to be able to look inside its sister. 
	 But it still shouldn't be allowed to look anywhere it wants within its sister! There are 
still no verbs that take an NP but care about the adjective inside it, 
So we need to 
modify Chomsky's Principle, not throw it away! 
The necessary modification of Chomsky's Principle: 
(14)	 Chomsky's Principle, Revised
The lexical entry for a word contains subcategorization information about the head 
of its sister . 
We can now use the revised principle (assuming it is correct) to probe for heads of all
sorts of phrases: 
V subcategoriz
es for the complementizer of its complement when that complem
ent is 
a clause ( that vs. for): 
(15)	 a. Mary will believe 
[that the brown fox has depended on the lazy dog]. 
b. Mary will arrange

[for the brown fox to depend on the lazy dog].
 
(16)
	 a. *Mary will believe 
[for the brown fox to depend on the lazy dog]. 
b.
 *Mary will arrange
[that the brown fox has depended on the lazy book].
 

	 So C is the head of the sister of V in these examples.  Embedded clauses are CPs.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The notion &#8220;lexicon&#8221;
No word or morpheme boundaries in the speech signal
Affixes: prefixes, suffixes
The rule &#8220;Merge&#8221;
How structure interacts with sound and with meaning
Syntactic category
Affixes: reduplication, infixes
Solving morphology problems
Subcategorization
Derivational vs. inflectional morphology</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-900-introduction-to-linguistics-fall-2012/resources/mit24_900f12_morphology/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2&#8211;4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Kurdish (Indo-Iranian, Iraq) 
aaqil 'wise' 
diz 'robber' 
drai 'long' 
zaanaa 'wise' 
garm 'warm' aaqilii 'forethought' 
dizii 'robbery' 
draiii 'length' 
zaanaaii 'erudition' 
garmii 'warmth' 
We know: prefix (attach to left edge of base), suffix (attach to right edge of base) 
	 Now: Infix! Attach inside the base, according to a rule that refers to the base's sound 
structure. 
Example 1: Bontoc (Austronesian, Philippines) 
The infix -um- is positioned following the initial consonant of the base. 
'he is becoming ...' 
fikas fumikas 
kilad kumilad 
bato bumato 
fusul fumusul 
Example 2: Samoan (Austronesian, Samoa) 
This example is interesting because it is also reduplication: 'strong' 
'red' 
'stone' 
'enemy' 
"copy penultimate syllable and position it next to the original" 
'he ...' 'they ...' 
manao mananao 'wish' 
matua matutua 'be old' 
malosi malolosi 'be strong' 
punou punonou 'bend' 
savali savavali 'travel' 
pese pepese 'sing' 
laga lalaga 'weave' 
atamai atamamai 'be wise' 
galue galulue 'work' 
aloga alologa 'love' 
In these cases, the morpheme is attached in the middle of the sounds belonging to another 
morpheme.  This type of affixation is called infixation. 
Example 3: fuckin' infixation (fan-fuckin'-tastic,  Massa-fuckin'-chusetts, Missi-fuckin'-
ssippi)4 
	 The infixation of fuckin', which denotes a strong positive or negative attitude, appears 
to be determined by stress (accent). A first approximation at the correct rule is: 
4 In British, Irish, Australian and New Zealand English, bloody can be used, and appears to 
follow exactly the same rule:  Massa-bloody-chusetts, * Massachu-bloody-setts, etc. -5-
(2)	 fuckin'-infixation 
Infix fuckin' to the left of the syllable that bears main stress. 
Thus: 
(3) a. Massa-fuckin'-chusetts 
but not : b. *Massachu-fuckin's setts. 
 because the syllable -chu- bears the main stress.  Likewise: 
(4) a. Conn-
fuckin'-ecticut  
[it helps to pause after the first syllable, or to draw it out]
but not: b. *Connect-fuckin'-
icut. 
nor: c. *Connecti-f
uckin'-cut. 
	 This example shows that the rule does involve stress, and not counting syllables from the end. since the stress in Connecticut falls on the third syllable from the end (the 
antepenult), while the stress in Massachusetts falls on the next-to-last syllable (the 
penult), as we've seen. 
(5)	 un-fuckin'-believable 
	 What is especially worth noting about the whole phenomenon is that it really is rule-governed! We have clear intuitions about good vs. bad places to infix fuckin' within bases to which we have surely never heard this infixation rule applied. 
	 People sometimes think that parental input and correction is a key to language 
acquisition.  Pretty unlikely here:  ("No my little sweetheart, you know we don't say 
Massachu-fuckin'-setts. Say it properly, or you can't have dessert:  Massa-fuckin'-
chusetts. Very good!"). 
9 Multiple affixes 
	 In many languages, verbs or nouns bear a whole group of affixes.  Often these affixes 
mark agreement: they represent properties like "plural" or "3rd person" that have no meaning on the verb, but agree with a plural or 3rd person word or phrase somewhere 
else in the sentence. 
	 These agreement affixes often make it possible to leave out the plural or 3rd person 
words, and just use a verb to express thoughts like "we saw him". 
	 Languages with complex morphology of this sort present nice puzzles that will plague 
your problem sets and exams in this class!</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>5 The lexical entry for each morpheme specifies 
1. its sound 
2. its meaning 
3. whether it is a root or affix 
4. its part-of-speech (category): N, V, A... 5. if it is an affix, the part of speech it merges with: 
6. if it is an affix, its place of attachment: 
a. left edge (prefix) b. right edge (suffix) 
[c. after the first syllable, before the last syllable, before the main stress... 
(infix)]
2 
Step 2: 
	 The output of step 2 can undergo Merge again.  Another affix can be attached to it. 
	 The element to which an affix attaches (whether a root or a morphologically complex word) is called its base. 
	 When an affix attaches to the root, the root is also its base.  But when an affix attaches to a an already complex form, its base is not the root. 
Trees 
	 A tree diagram can illustrate the internal structure of a word, and reflects how it was formed by one or more operations of Merge. 
[see the textbook for lots of actual trees] 
	 Words really are trees (structures) -- not just strings of morphemes 
For example ... 
the suffix -ment attaches to a verb and produces a noun: 
govern government 
adjourn adjournment 
treat treatment 
amuse amusement 
body 
X *bodiment 
trance 
X *trancement 
power X *powerment 

	 You might say: "the morpheme next to -ment must be a verb" as an alternative to "the 
base to which -ment attaches must be a verb". 
2 Discussed below. -3-
	 An argument against this: find a prefix that makes a noun (or adjective) into a verb! 
The prefix en- (sometimes em-) forms verbs out of nouns (and adjectives): 
body --&gt; embody 
trance --&gt; entrance 
power --&gt; empower 
Now notice that these verbs can take the suffix -ment. 
Even though the morpheme next to 
-ment is not a verb morpheme, structurally -ment is being added to a verb. 
6 "Sound" in more detail 
	 Whether a morpheme even has a sound is arbitrary.  In English, the fact that a noun is singular is not represented by an overt morpheme 
(one can say there is a zero morpheme)  though plural is a morpheme with a sound 
of its own (dog vs. dog-s
). 
	 Some morphemes that do have a sound do not have a sound of their own. Their sound is a copy of sounds already present in the base.  This is called reduplication: 
Example 1: Lakhota (Siouan, S. Dakota) 
sg inanimate pl 
g gig 'to be rusty brown' 
sk skask 'to be white' 
 a
 'to be red' 
th thoth 'to be blue or green'  i 'to be yellow' 
Sound: Copy first CV of the base. 
Example 2: Ilocano (Austronesian, Phillippines) 
sg plural 
pgan pipgan 'dish' 
tlon taltlon 'field' 
dlon daldlon 'road' 
bag bibag 'lives' 
nu nunu 'carabao' 
lo ullo 'head' 
mla mumla 'plant' 
twa tawtwa 'window'</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 24.900 Fall 2012 lecture notes 
Morphology 
Why morphology matters? 
Innate bias for words 
	 If it is true that words are not marked in the physical stream of speech, two questions: 
	 Why did our brains in childhood (infancy) go to the trouble of working out 
how to parse the speech stream into words? 
	 Why do our brains now go to the trouble of segmenting the speech stream 
into words? 
	 Why is the nature of the analysis so nearly identical across languages? 
	 To question 1: One can give a functional explanation for the existence of words. 
	 It is advantageous to construct a flexible communication system out of a 
smallish set of units, combined and recombined. 
Keeps memory use under control. 
Allows novel utterances. 
	 But does this tell us how or why the baby acquires the words?  Does she do a little communication theory and decide that speech must contain words? 
Probably not. 
	 Answer is an innate bias to perform some sort of analysis of speech 
(explaining 1 and 2), and probably innate k
nowledge of what the product 
of this analysis will look like (explaining 3). 
Arbitrariness 
	 But remember: 
The words themselves are not innately specified, or else they would not differ from speech community to speech community (arbitrariness). 
	 Arbitratriness pervades language... 
English dog, French chien, Russian sobaka... 
	 ...even in "onomatopoeia"  how we represent animal sounds linguistically is fixed:1 
cow: Dutch boeh, Hungarian b, Thai maw maw (with mid tone), Bengali hamba 
dog: Russian gav-gav, Catalan bup-bup, Indonesian gong-gong 
1 http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross-linguistic_onomatopoeias#Animal_sounds What is Innate (in this domain): 
Drive to analyze speech into words. 
What is Learned (in this domain): 
What the words actually are. 
Morpheme: the minimal subpart of a word that expresses a meaning (or gramm atical 
property) 
Example: dogs contains two morphemes: 
dogs = dog 
'furry beast' + s 'plura 
dogs  d 'furry' + og '
beast' + s 'plural' 
2 How we learn words and morphemes 
Rapidly! 
	 First words appear around age 1. (One-word stage.) 
Kids already know more than they say: 
	 In 11-month old, selective looking reveals preference for pauses that coincide 
with word boundaries over pauses inserted between syllables of words. 
	 In 9-month old, no preference. 
So what happened between 9 and 11? 
How do you segment speech into words if you don't know the words? 
No magic bullet, it seems! Part of the story
 must be a statistical analysis of input 
data carried out by
 the child  and there are explicit proposals about this. 
But a deeper question remains: Why does the baby perform this statistical analysis 
performed, and why are the results saved in memory (ultim
ately, in the lexicon)?
 An approach to an answer: 
An instinct for language acquistion. 
Innate knowledge coupled with environment-dependent learning. 
3 The knowledge underlying use of a complex word 
	 Productivity of morphology: 
(1) industry, industrial, industrialize, industrialization., industrializational,
industrializationalize, industrializationalization, ...</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.900 Introduction to Linguistics
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>7 	 In the lexical entry for plural, under the heading "sound", it says not -ness, or un-, but:  
"Copy first (C)V(C) of the base." 
[C = consonant, V = vowel, parentheses = "if present...") 
	 Reduplication is extremely common in languages of the Austronesian group 
(Phillipines, Malaysia, Indonesia) 
Allomorphs 
	 Sometimes the sound of a morpheme depends on the base to which it is attached, but is not a copy of that base.  Such a morpheme will have different arbitrary (i.e. not 
copied) sounds depending on the base to which it attaches. These variants are called allomorphs. 
Example 1: English plural depends on the identity of the base to which it attaches. 
dog-s, cat-s, horse-s 
but...

 
ox-en
 child-ren
 
sheep-, deer
-
 
Note that the -s plural is productive. It is the default plural marker which we 
apply in the absence of special knowledge about an irregular plural marker.  
What is the plural of wug? The situation is more complicated still: the default affix is -z
, which regular 
phonology changes to /s/ for reasons we will discuss later.  But after -s, -z, -ch, -sh, 
-j we get a vowel as well.  This is more allomorphy... 
What is the plural of gruss? 
Sometimes the plural involves a change of vowel: mouse/mice, woman/women. 
Example 2: English past tense: 
Default is 
-d, but here too we have vowel changes, and sometimes both: 
walk/walked, industrialize/industrialized
 
run/ran, sing/sang, lead/led, strive/strove
 
sleep/slept

 -4-
Example 3: Latin forms of the verb meaning 'love' 
present past future 
you (sg)... ama-s ama-ba-s ama-bi-s 
she/he/it... ama-t ama-ba-t ama-bi-t 
we... ama-mus ama-ba-mus ama-bi-mus 
you (pl.) ama- tis ama-ba- tis ama-bi- tis 
but: 
I ... am-(a)-o ama-ba- m ama-b(i)-o 
they ... ama-nt amaba-nt ama- bu-nt 
The underlined bits are unexpected, and show allomorphs of the suffixes visible elsewhere 
in the chart. 
8 "Place" in more detail
 
Point 1: The place of attachment must be listed in the lexicon, because it's arbitrary.
 
	 For example, whether a morpheme with a particular affix is a prefix or a suffix 
varies across languages. 
Example 1: Russian vs. Bulgarian comparative and superlative affixes. 
[I think I didn't do this one in class, but here it is anyway] Bulgarian: smena / po-smena umna / po-umna 
Russian: smena / smen-ee umna / umn-ee
3 
'funny' / 'funnier' 'smart' / 'smarter' 
Example 2: The affix meaning (roughly) -ness is a prefix in Kanuri, but a suffix (as in 
English) in Kurdish. It's also worth noting that English -ness attaches only 
(mostly) to adjectives, while its Kurdish cousin also attaches to nouns 
Kanuri (Nilo-
Saharan, Nigeria) 
gana 'small' nmgana 'smallness' 
kura 'big' nmkura 'bigness' 
kurugu 'long' nmkurugu 'length' 
karite 'excellent' nmkarite 'excellence' 
dibi 'bad' nmdibi 'badness' 
3 Ignore for present purposes the -a of umna, which is a morpheme marking it as a 
fem
inine adjective of a particular sort.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>There is no termination to the process, except that the words become too long and their 
meanings too complex to keep track of all the morphemes. 
	 An interesting difference between words and sentences: We have no problem parsing 
sentences with as many words as industrializationalization has morphemes (7 of 
them!) -- compare even the process of turning a question about something else into a 
question about industrialization, which has the same meaning but 14 words! The 
multi-word phrase is much easier to understand than the multi-morpheme word.  We 
are not as good at parsing words as we are at parsing sentences. 
 Distinctions: bound morpheme vs. free morpheme / open-class vs. closed-class 
Industry is a word on its own. free morpheme 
-ize, -al, and -ation are not. bound morpheme 
	 The free morpheme industry belongs to an open class of lexical items, an extendible class of items with a wide range of meanings. You can make up new ones, and are not 
surprised to learn new ones even in adulthood: screeve, Obama, cromulent. 
	 The opposite of "open class" is "closed class" (also known as "function words"). 
Since open class items can be coined at will (more or less), it is really the closed-class 
items that identify the language  that make English English, make French French etc. 
Lewis Carroll'
s poem Jabberwocky contains lots of unfamiliar ("nonsense") open-class 
items, but all its closed-class items  all its function words  are English.  Crazy though the poem may sound, it is clearly a poem written in English! 
Twas 
brillig, and the slithy toves 
Did gyre and gimble in the wabe;
All mims
y were the borogoves,
And the mome raths outgrabe. 
Compare a version in which the open-class words are replaced with normal English, but 
the function words are replaced with "non-sense".  It no longer looks like English: 
Glorm cloudy, yurk lim noisy frogs
Rur croak yurk fidget uf lim lake;Caj nervous trid lim hunting dogs,Yurk lim hungry cats lay awake. 
Or worse, replace both function words and open-class items with made-up words: 
Glorm brillig, yurk lim slithnit tovem
Rur gyre yurk gimble uf lim wabe;Caj mimsnit trid lim borogovem,Yurk lim mome rathem nusgrabe. -2-
Because the real poem truly is written in English (because its closed-class items are 
English), the notion "translating Jabberwocky" into a foreign language is a meaningful 
one, and lots of translations have been made. 
	 free vs. bound  open vs. closed class 
	 For example: 
There are free closed-class morphemes  (prepositions, pronouns, articles...) There are bound open-class morphemes (un+kempt
, sanit+ize) 
4 How to build a morphologically complex word: the rule Merge 
You have to start somewhere! 
Step 0: 
	 Take a morpheme from the lexicon whose lexical entry does not say "I am a 
suffix" or "I am a prefix"... This starting point, which (as the textbook says) carries "the main meaning of the sentence", is the called root. 
	 Putting aside a special kind of complex word called a compound (to which we return next week)  if there's a free morpheme in the word, it'
s the root. 
Step 1: 
	 A morphological rule that we can call "Merge
" takes an appropriate 
morpheme from the lexicon and glues it to the root. (We return soon to 
what we mean by "appropriate".) 
	 A non-root morpheme in a word is called an affix. So morphologically 
complex words are made up of a root and some number of affixes.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Phonology vs. phonetics
Phonological rules
Underlying form
Complementary distribution
Phoneme and allophone
How to determine the phonemes of a language
Rule ordering
Syllable structure</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-900-introduction-to-linguistics-fall-2012/resources/mit24_900f12_phonologysum/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8&#8211;12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>-2-
	 The same points can be made with other phonological rules.  For example: 
(4) vowel length in English: 
V [+long] / __ [C, +voiced] 
(short and long vowels in complementary distribution, i.e. not distinguished in the 
lexical entries for English morphemes, but derived by a phonological rule) 
short vowel 	 long vowel 
meet   [mit] mead [mi:d] 
back [bk] bag [b:g] 
pot [pt] pod [p:d] 
loss [ls] laws [l:z] 
half [hf] have [h:v] 
made-up words 
wuck [wk] 	 wug [w:g] 
nis [ns] 	 niz [n:z] 
	 Nonsense words and the pronunciation of non-English words like wuck and wug show 
that this too is a rule. Vowel length is not part of lexical entries in English! 
	 You could not imagine, for example, /nik/ and /ni:k/ being distinguishable names for new inventions in English. 
	 On the other hand, many languages do distinguish vowel length in the lexicon. Latin, for example, and many other languages, e.g. Finnish (a brilliantly demonstrated 
for us in class): 
(5) vowel length in Finnish: 
(short and long vowels distinguished in the lexical entries for Finnish morphemes; 
note the minimal pairs!) 
tuli 'fire' tu:li 'wind'
 
ehto 'condition' ehto: 'evening'
 
sika 'pig' si:ka 'whitefish'
 (6) [l] vs. [r] in Luganda (Bantu, Uganda) [source: workbook by Gleason] 
[l] [r] / [V, -back]2 
[l] and [r] in complementary distribution, i.e. not distinguished in the lexical entries 
for Luganda morphemes, but derived by a phonological rule 
1. kd dl 'to be full of'  11. frmb 'a whistle' 
2. kd dl 'to dish up' 12. dlr 'beam' 
3. kgl 'to buy' 13. r 'name' 
4. kggl 'to open' 14. ttndr 'shop' 
5. klt 'to bring' 15. myrr 'only' 
6. ktbl 'to attack'  16. dr 'Gospel' 
7. mll 'insane person' 17. klr 'to eat with' 
8. mlm 'lame person' 18. lgr 'story' 
9. nlwn 'fought'  19. kmr 'to swallow' 
10. tlg 'we tighten' 20. prpr 'chili pepper' 
(7) [l] vs. [r] in Korean [source: workbook by Gleason] 
[l]   r / V __ V 
1. kal 'that'll go' 11. pulpyn 'discomfort' 
2. knl 'shade' 12. silkwa 'kind of fruit' 
3. mul 'water' 13. lmana 'how much' 
4. pal 'foot' 14. irm 'name' 
5. pal 'arm' 15. kiri 'length' 
6. sul 'Seoul' 16. krm 'then' 
7. tatl 'all of them' 17. kriro 'to the street' 
8. ilkop 'seven' 18. saram 'person' 
9. ipalsa 'barber' 19. uri 'we' 
10. 	 onlppam 'tonight' 20. yrm 'summer' 
([] is a high back unrounded vowel) 
(8) [l] vs. [] in English 
distinguished in the lexical entries for English morphemes: note the minimal pairs 
late rate 
lot rot 
lamb ram 
belly berry 
hail hair 
pool poor 
2 The data are insufficient to tell us whether lexical entries contain [l] and a rule derives 
[r], or whether it is the other way around.  The same is true for Korean below.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Example:  the Latin stress rule 
(21) Latin stress: data 
short penult9 closed10 penult
m-se-rum 'poor' ( NEU) a-mn-tis 'loving' ( GEN)
d-ci-mus 'we lead' re-fc-tus 'repaired'
r-fi-cit '(s)he repairs' im-pe-di-mn-ta 'baggage'
d-mi-nus 'master' con-sr-vat '(s)he preserves' 
prin-c-pi-bus 'chiefs' ( ABL) 
long penult stop+liquid
a-m:-vi: 'I have loved' c-le-bris 'crowded' ( GEN)
a-m:-bo: 'I will love' v-lu-cris 'winged' ( GEN)
du-c:-mus 'we will lead' 
hor-t:-rum 'gardens' ( GEN)
 
two-syllable words
t-git 'covers' 
m-rem 'sea' ( ACC) 
(Latin spelling: c = [k], v = [w]) 
Latin syllabification rules: 
step 1. Link all vowels to Nucleus, project Rime and Syllable:         
R R R R R R 
R R 
N N N N N N N N 
i m  p e d  i  m e n t a  v o l u c r i s 
3. 
9 Penult = second syllable from the end of a word.  Antepenult = third syllable from the 
end of the word. 
10 A syllable is closed if it contains material in its coda (e.g. [d -8-
step 2. Link each consonant that immediately precedes a vowel to Onset.  Add as many 
other consonants as possible to Onset ("maximize Onset")  so long as
phonotactics (sonority sequencing) is not violated. 
R R R R R R R R      
N O N O N O N O N O N O N O N 
i mp e d i m e n t a v o l u c r i s 
The underlined segments are not added to onsets in step 2 because of
sonority. [mp] and [nt] are not possible onsets in Latin. 
step 3. Link remaining (unsyllabified) consonants to Coda 
      
R R R R R R R R 
N C O N O N O N  CO N O N O N O N C 
i m p  e  d  i  m  e n t a v o l  u  c  r i s 
Latin stress rule: 
1. If the penult (second- to-last syllable) has branching structure in its rime (is heavy),
stress the penult.
a-mn-tis re-
fc-tus 
a-m:-vi: du-c:-mus 
im-pe-di-m
n-ta  (see syllable structures above) 
2. Otherwise, if the word has 3 or more syllables, stress the antepenult [third syllable
from end] 
prin-c-pi-bus 
d-ci-mus m-se-rum
 
c-le-bris 
v-lu-cris (see syllable structures above) 
3. Otherwise, stress the first syllable 
t-git m-rem</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>-5-
(19) Turkish vowel harmony 
singular plural 
di diler 'tooth' 
totsuk totsuklar 'child' 
asker askerler 'soldier' 
kedi kediler 'cat' 
son sonlar 'end' 
masa masalar 'table' 
getse getseler 'night' 
baba babalar 'father' 
ku kular 'bird' 
kj kjler 'village' 
jyz jyzler 'face' 
kz kzlar 'girl' 
[y], [] = high and mid front rounded vowels (Turkish spelling:  and ) 
[] = high back unrounded vowel (Turkish spelling: dotless ) 
	 In the plural suffix, we find a back vowel ([a]) when the root ends in a back vowel ([u], 
[a], [o], [;) and a front vowel ([e]) when the root ends in a front vowel ([[i], [e], [y], 
[]). This is the result of a rule of front-back vowel harmony. 
5. Phonemes 
	 Question: 
What is the inventory of the sounds that are found in the morphemes of a language as 
they are stored in the sound field of the lexicon? 
The list of these sounds is the list of the phonemes of the language. 
	 The list of actual sounds used in the language (the phonemes, as modified by the 
phonological rules of the language), is the list of its phones. 
These concepts in context 
	 Why did our brains in infancy go to the trouble of working out how to parse the speech 
stream into morphemes?  Probable answer: to store information about these units in 
the database that we call the lexicon. 
	 When the infant acquiring language notes that two or more phones are in 
complementary distribution, he/she uses this fact to economize on the distinctions made in the lexicon. Two phones in complementary distribution are taken to 
correspond to only one sound stored in memory, a 
phoneme  with the variant 
pronunciations related to the single phoneme by phonological rule. 

	 The variant forms of phoneme that are related by rule are called its allophones. 	 Review, in this connection, our discussion of aspiration: 
Tojolabal and English: 
predictable alternation of +aspirated and -aspirated (different rules) 
Spanish: 
always unaspirated 
Hindi: 
unpredictable whether a consonant is aspirated or not 
Conclusions: Tojolabal, English: 
aspiration is not phonemeic 
(for example, /t/ and /t/ are allophones of the same phoneme) 

Hindi: aspiration is phonemic 
(for example, /t/ and /t/ are distinct phonemes
) 
	 We can immediately establish that two phones are not in complementary distribution in 
a language if we can find a minimal pair of words that differ by only that phone. 
The minimal pair is the gold standard of phonological analysis. but near-mininal 
pairs will often do almost as well, i.e. two words containing XaY and XbY where X 
and Y are the same. 
At least we know that a vs. b is not predictable on the basis of X 
vs. Y.] 
6. Phonemic inventory 
	 The set of phonemes of a language are called its phonemic inventory. 
record low: 	 maybe Rotokas (S. Pacific), 11 phonemes 
record high: 	 !Xoo (Khoisan group, Botswana, Namibia), 141~160. 
80 of them are clicks! 
English: 	 about 37-41, depending on dialect and analysis 
	 Alphabetic writing systems often choose represent phonemes rather than their allophones. 
	 Speakers of languages tend to be minimally aware or unaware of allophonic distinctions. (Were you aware of the rule governing stop aspiration in English?) 
Categorical perception for non-phonemic distinctions 
seems to be suppressed in the 
process of language acquisition. Work done at Haskins laboratories in the 1970s and 80s (by Virginia Mann, among others) seems to show that adult speakers of English</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>-3-
3. What phonetic distinctions are made in lexical entries? 
Part 2: phonological rules that do not eliminate distinctions from the lexicon 
Russian  Consider the following pairs of forms from Russian. I call the forms in the left 
column "zero-ending forms" and the forms in the left column "-a forms", though the 
meaning and use of the two forms actually varies widely among the examples.  Assume 
that the -a form contains two morphemes: a root and a suffix -a (brought together into 
onew word by the rule Merge). 
(9) Final devoicing in Russian 
zero-ending form -a form 
a. grp grba 'coffin' 
b. lip lipa 'linden tree' 
c. pt pta 'whisper' 
d. g
rt g
rda 'city' 
e. ruk ruka 'hand' 
f. rk ra 'horn' 
g. rk r
ka 'fate' 
h. k
rnda k
rndaa 'pencil' 
i. ekipa ekipa
a 'crew' 
j. ras rasa 'race' 
k. ras raza 'time' 
	 step 1: Comparing the two columns, we note that sometimes the -
a form has a voiced 
consonant (stop or fricative) where the zero-ending form has the corresponding 
voiceless consonant. (Example: 
the /p/ vs. /b/ in the first example.) This already 
suggests that Russian has either a rule that makes voiced consonants voiceless in a certain environment, or else a rule that makes voiceless cons
onants voiced.  Which is 
it? 
	 step 2: Next we notice that sometimes both columns have the voiceless alternant. (Example: the /p/ in the second example.) But there are no examples in which the zero-ending form has a voiced consonant while the -a form has a voiceless consonant. 

	 Now let's add an additional fact: No Russian word is ever pronounced so as to end 
with a voiced consonant (with some law-governed exceptions coming up).  A Russian 
accent in English has this property too: an English word like [prawd] 'proud' comes out 
as [prawt]. 
	 Solution:  Russian has a rule of final devoicing that devoices a voiced consonant at 
the end of a w
ord.  The rule leaves consonants that are already voiceless alone. 
(10) Final devoicing (first version, to be revised)3 
[+consonant] !  [-voiced] / ___ # 
3 The symbol # indicates the bound ary of the word.  See the textbook for the format of phonological rules 
used here. Where the zero-ending form has a voiceless consonant and the -a form has a voiced 
counterpart, the lexicon contains a voiced consonant that the rule of final devoicing 
turns  into its voiceless counterpart. 
(11) Final devoicing in Russian 
zero-ending form -a form	 lexical entry for  the root4 
a. grp grba 'coffin' grb 
b. lip lipa 'linden tree' lip 
c. pt p
ta '
whisper' pt 
d. gr
t grda 'city' grd 
e. ruk ruka 'hand' ruk 
f. rk ra 
'horn' rg 
g. r
k rka '
fate' rk 
h. krnda
 krndaa 'pencil' kr nda 
i. ekipa ekipaa 'crew' ekipa 
j. ras rasa 'race' ras 
k. ras raza 'time' ra
z 
	 Important points: 
1. Listing the voiced alternant in the sound field of the lexical entries for the roots of 
these words makes it possible to predict the pronunciation of both the zero-ending form and the -a
 form. If we were to list the voiceless alternant, we could not predict 
when the -a
 form shows a voiced consonant and when it shows a voiceless consonant. 
2. Forms with a voiced final consonant are never pronounced that way! So this is a 
case in which the lexicon makes more distinctions than those made in the spoken form 
of the language (a voicing contrast in word-final position)  a contrast to the previous 
section, in which we saw the lexicon making fewer distinctions than those made in the 
spoken form (e.g. with respect to aspiration in English). 

	 Finally, the details of Russian motivate a restriction of the rule in (10) to exclude 
liquids (/l/ and /r/) and nasals 
(12) 	 No devoicing of liquids and nasals 
dm dma 'house' 
plan 
plana 'plan' 
sk
zal skzala 'said' 
vr vra 'thief' 
(13) Final devoicing (final version) 
+consonant 
-sonorant  -voiced / ___ # 
4 Our lexical entries ignore some irrelevant additional details of Russian phonology  for example, the fact
that the schwa vowels listed here are not actually part of the lexical entries either, but are the result of rules
that apply to other vowels when they are unstressed.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.900 Introduction to Linguistics
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Phonology Summary 
(contains all examples from class slides, and more!) 
1. Phonology vs. phonetics 
	 The path from memory (lexical access) to speech is mediated by phonology. 
	 Phonology = system of rules that apply when speech sounds are put together to form 
morphemes and words. 
(1) stop consonant aspiration in English: initial within a stressed syllable 
ASPIRATED UNASPIRATED 
initial within a stressed syllable after s or initial within an word -final (therefore syllable -
unstressed syllable final) 
pan span nap 
tone stone note 
kin skin nick 
upon supping 
attack attic 
akin hacking 
	 What English speakers know is a rule that relates a form stored in memory (in the 
sound field of the lexicon) to pronunciation. The rule concerns speech sounds, and 
therefore involves phonetics. But aspiration at the beginning of stressed syllables is not 
an inevitable part of a human language  you can have a human vocal tract and not 
use the rule exemplified in (1). This makes it a rule of phonology rather than a fact 
about phonetics. 
	 Speakers of Spanish, for example, do not have the English rule, which is why the syllable-initial stop consonants of a native speaker of Spanish sound "funny" to the 
English ear (and vice-versa). More strikingly yet, speakers of Tojolabal (a Mayan 
language of Mexico) have a rule that is almost the exact opposite of the English rule, 
aspirating word (syllable?)-final [t]. but not [t] elsewhere: 
(2) aspiration of [t] in Tojolabal: word (syllable?)-finally
1 
1. 	titam 'pig' 5. tatat kind of plant 
2. 	makton '
a patch' 6. mut 'chicken' 
3. 	potot kind of plant 7. nahat 'long' 
4. 
	tinan 'upside down' 8. 
inat 'seed' 
(t = unaspirated /t/) 
1 Source: Gleason, Henry A. (1955) Workbook in Descriptive Linguistics . New York:, Holt, Rinehart and 
Winston. Note: I only have information about [t], and don't know if the rule extends to the other stops. Fall 2012 
	 Speakers of English learned something from the data they were presented with as 
babies that caused them to internalize (learn) the rule exemplified in (1)  just as 
Tojolabal speakers learned from the data that they heard as babies, and ended up with 
the rule exemplified in (2). 
	 The English rule is real and active "on-line", governing creative linguistic behavior.  A native speaker of English will apply it to new words they have never heard. The /t/ in 
tib will be aspirated, and the /t/ in stib  (both nonsense words, I hope) will not be. 
Probably Tojolabal speakers will show similar behavior with respect to their rule. 
2. What phonetic distinctions are made in lexical entries? 
Part 1: phonological rules that eliminate distinctions from the lexicon 
	 English: lexicon does not need to distinguish aspirated from unaspirated stops. 
There is no reason to suppose that information about aspiration forms part of the sound 
field of lexical entries of English words, since it is entirely predictable. Though pan is 
pronounced /pn/ and span /spn/, there is no reason to distinguish the aspirated and 
unaspirated bilabial stops in the lexical entries of the two words. Instead, we may 
simply use the unaspirated version in the lexicon for both words (pn, spn) and let the phonological rule take care of the pronunciation difference. 
	 To make the same point differently, we could not even conceive of two distinct words 
in English that differ only in the aspiration of a stop consonant. If you invent a product and call it "pb", I could not invent a competing product and call it "pb" to 
distinguish it. The second form is simply the first form with a foreign accent! The 
English lexicon does not even allow the aspirated and the unaspirated variants to be 
distinguished. It hands the job off completely to the phonology. 
	 This too is an English-specific fact! 
In some languages the lexicon does make the 
relevant distinction. For example, Hindi, where words are often distinguished only 
by a contrast in aspiration for a stop consonant: 
(3) Hindi: lexicon distinguishes aspirated from unaspirated stops in the lexicon 
note the minimal pairs 
pal 'take care of' pal 'knife blade' 
tal 'beat' tal 'plate' 
al 'postpone' 
al 'wood shop' 
tal 'turn' tal 'bark' 
kal 'era' kal 'skin'</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>make a categorical distinction between [l] and [r], but adult speakers of Japanese do not. 
Other experiments show that infants -- both Japanese and American -- make the 
categorical distinction. So language acquisition from this perspective looks more like 
a process of losing distinctions than gaining them  
unlearning rather than learning. 
7. Distinctive features. 
	 Phonological processes tend to be "natural", in that they apply to natural classes of sounds. The environment of a rule is also generally a natural class of sounds, and the 
change effected by the rule involves a natural class of sounds. 
What is a natural class of sounds?  A group of sounds that have a common phonetic 
property.  For example, for consonants: point of articulation, manner of articulation 
and voicing. 
Other (rather sophisticated) ways of classifying sounds are discussed at length in the textbook, but were not discussed in class. Take 24.901 next Fall to learn more. 
8. Rule ordering 
	 Lexical entries may undergo more than one phonological rule. The various rules do not seem to apply equally or all at once, but are prioritized. There is controversy within the field of phonology about the precise nature of this prioritization.  (One 
currently popular approach, called Optimality Theory is not the approach taught here, 
but is stressed in other classes in linguistics.) For our purposes, the prioritization can be understood as an 
ordering of the rules: they apply in a serial fashion, each rule 
applying to the output of the preceding rule. 
	 The sequence of ordered rules is called a derivation. In class, we examined three 
problems that show how an ordered derivation works. -6-
	 Example 1: Tunica 
Answer: Vowel harmony in the 3sg fem form precedes unstressed vowel deletion  
which if it had applied first, would have eliminated the environment for harmony
[source: Roca, Iggy and Wyn Johnson. 1999. A Course in Phonology] 
Example 2: Shona 
Answer: The output of nasal assimilation (see below) reveals the place of articulation 
of a following voiceless stop that has turned into [h].  So nasal assimilation must 
precede the stop[h] rule, so it can see the difference between a [p], [k] or [t] that 
later changes to [h]. 
Roca, Iggy, and Wyn Johnson. A Course in Phonology. Blackwell Publishers, 1999.
 Blackwell Publishers. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our
Creative Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse
.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>-7-
9. Syllable structure 
This is a topic that I presented very briefly, which really deserved a full class or two toitself  mainly because the next topic was writing systems, and I wanted to discusssyllables so we could later discuss syllabaries. Here's what we talked about (and there'smore material in the textbook). 
	 Phonological segments are not arranged like beads on a string (any more than 
morphemes within a word are, or words within a sentence)  but are organized in a hierarchical fashion into syllables. 
	 Though there is some disagreement among experts (and some interesting recent work revising the model), a standard view holds that segments are grouped as in (20), where 
the Greek letter  (a lowercase sigma) indicates "syllable".
7 Note that in general, 
sonority increases as you move from either syllable-edge towards the nucleus.8 
(20) 
	 Both onset and rime  are optional, but the nucleus (containing one or more vowels, 
syllabic liquids or nasals) is obligatory. 
Evidence for the existence of onset and coda as structural units includes: 
	 The existence of phonotactic constraints (constraints on co-occurrence) within the 
onset and within the rime, vs. the near-absence of comparable constrants that cross the coda-onset divide. 
For example, in English trent is a possible (but not an actual) word, but *rtent is an 
impossible word, since [rt] is not a possible onset (violating the principle of increasing 
sonority). On the other hand, [r] may immediately precede [t] even in English, so long 
7 Linguists' spelling of rime is an homage to Coleridge's poem "The Rime of the Ancient 
Mariner" (http://www.gutenberg.org/files/151/151-h/151-h.htm -- in case you don't know 
it). 
8 Vowels are more sonorous than consonants; nasals and liquids are more sonorous than 
stops; voiced consonants are more sonorous than voiceless consonants.  Cross-
linguistically, the behavior of sibilants is interestingly anomolous:  a word like [trp] obeys 
the sonority generalization, but the initial consonant of [strp] violates it. as the [r] can be syllabified into the coda of a preceding syllable. Thus: airtent is a 
possbile word, since it is syllabified [  ejr][  tnt]. 
	 Branching rimes and branching codas attract stress in many languages, while 
branching onsets generally do not (i.e. there is a generalization that requires reference 
to these constituents within the syllable). 
(continued on next page)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>-4-
4. More phonology 
	 Phonology vs. phonetics once more: Rules like (13) are very common in the 
world's languages.  But not universal.  English, for example, does not have a rule of 
final devoicing. 
Part of having a "Russian accent" when speaking English is to erroneously apply this 
rule when speaking English. 
Another very common (but not universal) kind of rule is assimilation. 
Voicing assimilation 
(14) 	 Voicing assimilation in English: the plural suffix 
a. 	 plural morpheme as /s/:
 
[lp-s, pt-s, nk-s, lf-s ...] 
b. 	 plural morpheme as /z/:
 
[kb-z, p
d-z, g-z, hajv-z ...] 
(15) 	 Voicing assimilation in English past tense: invented words 
a. 	 plural morpheme as /s/:
 
[z
p-s, wk-s, ...] 
b. 	 past morpheme as /d/: 
 
[zb-z, w
g-z, ...] 
The point (yet again!): the past tense rule is not about a list of phones turning into another list. Rather it is about an abstract property of phones in general 
(voiced vs. 
voiceless):5 
(16) 	 Voicing assimilation 
z  [-voiced] / [-voiced] __ 
Nasal assimilation 
	 As noted, rules like (16)  assimilation rules  are very common in the world's 
languages. One of the most common phonological processes across the world's 
languages is nasal assimilation. A nasal consonant takes on the place of articulation 
of a consonant that follows it. 
5 As came up in answer to a questio n, a schwa is inserted after sib ilants:  [k sz, bzz, edz] etc. English nasal assimilation: Could there be a word chinp (vs. chimp)?  What about / ink/ (vs. /ik/ )? emd (vs. 
end)?  No, because English has a rule of nasal assimilation, identical to the rule also 
illustrated in (17) below: 
(17) 	 Itz
6 (Mayan, Guatemala): nasal assimilation 
tson 'gun' intson 'my gun' 
kab 'hand' ikab 'my hand' 
bat 'ax' imbat 'my ax' 
pal 'son' impal 'my son' 
kol 'field' ikol 'my field' 
si 'wood' insi 'my wood' 
lak 'bowl' inlak 'my bowl' 
lets 'trap' inlets 'my trap' 
(18) 	 Nasal Assimilation Rule A nasal assimilates in place of articulation to the following consonant 
	 Here is an approximation at a formal statement of the rule, using the terms introduced in class for the phonetic properties of consonants: 
[+nasal]   [a bilabial, b alveolar,  velar]/ ___ [ bilabial,  alveolar, 
 velar] 
 where , 
,  are variables that range over plus and minus values. Using the 
features discussed in the book, but not in class, that would be: [+nasal]   [ labial,  coronal,  dorsal]/ ___ [ labial,  coronal,  dorsal] 
Important note: 
From the data given, we can'
t tell what the underlying form of 'my' is in Mayan.  It might 
be in, i or im. 
Vowel harmony

 
When assimilation affects a vowel, the process is called vowel harmony . For example:
 
6 Data once again from the Gleason worksbook cited above. Gleason calls the language "Mayan", which is 
actually a language family. Thanks to Robert Henderson for identifying the actual language.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Pronouns and binding
Quantifier scope
Negative polarity items</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-900-introduction-to-linguistics-fall-2012/resources/mit24_900f12_semantics/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20&#8211;21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>107</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
Sometimes we cant accommodate a presupposition.  
 
I forgot to feed the cat this morning!  
I forgot to feed the giraffe this morning!  
108</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>96</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
How easy it is to accommodate depends on the 
plausibility of what I said.  
 
Context: We are at my house and you hear some 
scratching noises outside.  
 
(1) The cat is at the door.  
(2) The giraffe is at the door.  
(3) I keep a giraffe here. The giraffe is at the door.  
97</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>92</slideno>
          <text>Presuppositions of the 
The presuppositions of the definite often spring into 
existence, even if they werent known beforehand.  
 
I forgot to feed the cat this morning 
  
93</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>69</slideno>
          <text>Conservativity 
Natural language determiners only care about 
elements that satisfy their first argument.  
 
Det is conservative  if Det(A)(B)  Det(A)(AB): 
 
every(boy)(danced)   conservative   
=  every boy danced  
=  every boy is a boy that danced  
 
every-non (boy)(danced)    non-conservative 
=  every non -boy danced     
  every non-boy is a boy that danced [*]  
70</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>95</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
How easy it is to accommodate depends on the 
plausibility of what I said.  
 
96</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>82</slideno>
          <text>The definite article 
What is the meaning of the definite article?  
 
Some cat purred 
Every  cat purred  
The cats purred  
 
 
 
 
 
 
83</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>63</slideno>
          <text>Determiners summary 
All the sentences we have seen have the structure: 
 
Det(A)(B) 
 
Some (Boy)(Danced )     Boy  Danced    
Three (Boy)(Danced )   | Boy  Danced | = 3 
More than half (Boy)(Danced)     | Boy  Danced  | &gt;  | Boy |  
No(Boy)(Danced )      Boy  Danced  =  
Every (Boy)(Danced)  
64</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>68</slideno>
          <text>Properties of determiners 
All the sentences we have seen have the structure: 
 
Det(A)(B) 
 
For example, Reverse- mth(A)(B) 
 
blick boys danced 
=  more than half of the dancers are boys 
 
That is:  | A  B |  &gt;  | B |  
 
69</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>111</slideno>
          <text>Conclusion  
Compositionality : We calculated the meaning of 
sentences from the meaning of their parts and the 
syntactic structure they were in. 
 
 
112</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>106</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
We use this process to assign implicit parameters in a 
way that would make sentences true. 
 
Everybody in the room is taller than me 
 
 
 
Context: There are four people in the room; you, me, 
and two other people who I dont know.  
a. You:  We are brothers.  
b. You: We are four, so we can play bridge.  
107</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>103</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
We use a similar process to choose the meaning of 
ambiguous sentences. 
 
Successful lawyers and linguists are always rich  
a. [Successful lawyers] and linguists are always rich  
b. Successful [lawyers and linguists] are always rich  
 
104</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>74</slideno>
          <text>An application: Explaining entailment patterns 
     Some boy sings and some boy dances 
. Some boy sings and dances  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
75</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>50</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
Three boys danced 
 
The intersection  of the set of boys and the set of 
dancers contains three elements.  
 
| Boy  Danced | = 3 
 
 
                                                                         
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced    
   
51</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>89</slideno>
          <text>The definite article 
We might define the as:  
 
The cats purred    Cat  Purred  
 
Does this work in this context? 
 
Context: There are three cats.  
 
Every cat purred 
The cats purred 
#The cat purred 
 
 
 
 
 
90</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>91</slideno>
          <text>The definite article 
The cat purred  
 
The expression the cat presupposes:  
 Existence: there exists a cat 
 Uniqueness: there is exactly one (relevant) cat  
 
When there is exactly one relevant individual in NP, 
the returns that individual.  
 
 
the cat defined iff there is one c Cat. Returns c. 
92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Modification 
Intersective adjectives conform to an entailment  
pattern. 
 
Mitzi is a gray cat 
 Mitzi is a cat  
 Mitzi is gray 
 
A entails B iff whenever A is true, B is true.  
31</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Sentence types 
What is the meaning of a sentence?  
 
The lion devoured the pizza. 
 
Statement 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Definition: Compositional semantics 
The principle of compositionality :  
The meaning of a sentence depends  
only on the meanings of its parts  
and on the way that they are  
syntactically combined. 
20
Gottlob Frege
This image is in the public domain.
Source: Wikimedia Commons.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>108</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
Sometimes we cant accommodate a presupposition.  
 
I forgot to feed the cat this morning!  
I forgot to feed the giraffe this morning!  
 
The TA is sitting in the front row 
 Uniqueness is violated!  
 
The king of France is bald 
 Existence is violated!  
109</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
How do we model determiners?  
 
Some  boy danced  
No boy danced 
Three boys danced 
More than half of the boys danced 
Every  boy danced 
 
 
43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>56</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
Every  boy danced 
 
The set of boys is a subset  of the set of dancers.  
 
Boy  Danced 
                           
                                               
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced   
    
57</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>99</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
Normally, we assume that speakers intend to say things 
that are grammatical, relevant, and  often  true.  
 
In the closet, you will find the blue coat 
 
Suppose that after I said this sentence, you open the 
closet and find only a black coat. 
 
You may assume I just got the color confused.  
100</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>79</slideno>
          <text>An application: Explaining entailment patterns 
   Some boy sings and dances  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 S D B 
80</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Observation : The interpretation of a sentence depends 
on its syntactic structure. Different phrases make 
predictable contributions to the meaning of a sentence. 
 
The cat chased the rat 
A cat chased the rat  Building a semantic system  
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>109</slideno>
          <text>Conclusion  
The king of France is bald  
 
Modeling using sets : We defined intransitive verbs , 
nouns and adjectives  as sets of individuals.  
 
 
 
 IP 
NP  I 
is bald  
110</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>72</slideno>
          <text>An application: Explaining entailment patterns 
     John sings and John dances 
. John sings and dances 
 
     Some boy sings and some boy dances 
. Some boy sings and dances  
 
 
73</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Sentence types 
What is the meaning of a sentence?  
 
Who devoured the pizza? 
Did the lion devour the pizza?  
 
Question 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>97</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
Normally, we assume that speakers intend to say things 
that are grammatical, relevant, and  often  true.  
 
In the closet, you will find the blue coat 
98</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Basic modeling 
Mitzi is gray 
Mitzi is a cat 
Mitzi purred 
 
A set is a collection of objects. 
 
Gray  is the collection of all gray individuals. 
Cat is the collection of all individuals who are cats. 
Purred  is the collection of all individuals who purred.  
 IP 
NP  
   I 
purred  
is gray  
is a cat  
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>55</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
More than half of the boys danced 
 
Can there be boys who are not dancers?  Yes (but...) 
Can there be dancers who are not boys?  Yes. 
 
 
                                    
                                      
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced     
    
    
   
56</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>47</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
No boy danced 
 
The intersection  of the set of boys and the set of 
dancers is empty 
 
Boy  Danced  =  
 
 
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced  
48</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>73</slideno>
          <text>An application: Explaining entailment patterns 
     John sings and John dances 
. John sings and dances 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 John  S D 
74</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Basic modeling 
Mitzi is gray 
Mitzi is a cat 
Mitzi purred 
 
Mitzi is a member  of the  
set of individuals that purred. 
Mitzi  Purred IP 
NP  
   I 
purred  
is gray  
is a cat  
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>104</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
We use a similar process to choose the meaning of 
ambiguous sentences. 
 
Successful lawyers and linguists are always rich  
a. [Successful lawyers] and linguists are always rich  
b. Successful [lawyers and linguists] are always rich  
 
Since (a) is obviously false, youll normally conclude 
that I meant (b).  
105</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>What do sentences mean?  
(1) The capital of Canada is Ottawa 
(2) The capital of Canada is Montreal 
 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>66</slideno>
          <text>Properties of determiners 
All the sentences we have seen have the structure: 
 
Det(A)(B) 
 
Are there determiners that put restrictions on set B?  
A B 
AB not: AB 
67</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
English has several additional determiners:  
 
Some  boy danced 
No boy danced 
Three boys danced 
More than half of the boys danced 
Every  boy danced 
42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>76</slideno>
          <text>An application: Explaining entailment patterns 
   Some boy sings and some boy dances 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 S D B 
77</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>88</slideno>
          <text>The definite article 
We might define the as:  
 
The cats purred    Cat  Purred  
 
Does this work in this context? 
 
 
 
 
 
89</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>43</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
How do we model determiners?  
 
Some  boy danced  
No boy danced 
Three boys danced 
More than half of the boys danced 
Every  boy danced 
 
NPs with determiners dont refer to individuals. 
Rather , determiners denote set relations . 
 
44</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Observation : The interpretation of a sentence depends 
on its syntactic structure. Different phrases make 
predictable contributions to the meaning of a sentence. 
 
The cat chased the rat Building a semantic system  
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>65</slideno>
          <text>Properties of determiners 
All the sentences we have seen have the structure: 
 
Det(A)(B) 
 
All the determiners we have seen so far put restrictions 
on members of set A, but not on members of set B.  
A B 
AB not: AB 
66</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>51</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
Three boys danced 
 
Can there be boys who are not dancers?   
Can there be dancers who are not boys?   
 
 
                                    
                                      
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced    
   
52</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>58</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
Every  boy danced 
 
Can there be boys who are not dancers? No. 
Can there be dancers who are not boys? Yes. 
 
 
 
 
 
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced   
     
59</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Sentence types 
What is the meaning of a sentence?  
 
Its cold here .  
Do you know what time it is?  
 
Sentences might convey additional non-literal meaning 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>More modeling 
Proper names pick out individuals in the world.  
John danced 
 
What does some boy refer to?  
Some boy danced   
 
What about no boy ?  
No boy danced 
 
41</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>Interim summary  
AND can also be described using set intersection .  
 
Mitzi is gray AND furry     =           Gray  Furry 
 
 
OR can also be described using set union .  
 
Mitzi is gray OR black      =           Gray  Black  
 
 
38</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>53</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
More than half of the boys danced 
 
The intersection  of the set of boys and the set of 
dancers contains more than half of all the boys.  
 
| Boy  Danced | &gt;  | Boy | 
 
 
                                                                         
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced    
    
    
   
54</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Basic modeling 
Mitzi is gray 
Mitzi is a cat 
Mitzi purred 
 
 
 
We can define adjectives , nouns and intransitive verbs 
as mathematical sets of individuals. IP 
NP  
   I 
purred  
is gray  
is a cat  
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Definition: Semantics and meaning 
The semantic competence of a speaker:  
The ability, when presented with a sentence and a 
situation, to tell whether the sentence is true or false in 
the situation. 
 
To know the meaning  of a sentence is to know its 
truth conditions . 
That is, we know what the world would have to look like in 
order for the sentence to be true.  
 
 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Basic modeling 
Mitzi is gray 
Mitzi is a cat 
Mitzi purred 
 
Mitzi is a member  of the  
set of individuals that are cats. 
Mitzi  Cat IP 
NP  
   I 
purred  
is gray  
is a cat  
25</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>45</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
Some boy danced 
 
Can there be boys who are not dancers? 
Can there be dancers who are not boys?  
 
 
                                    
                                      
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced   
46</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Semantics
1
These slides were produced by Hadas Kotek.
          http://web.mit.edu/hkotek/www/</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>60</slideno>
          <text>Determiners summary 
All the sentences we have seen have the structure: 
 
Det(A)(B) 
 
Some (Boy)(Danced )     Boy  Danced    
Three (Boy)(Danced )   
More than half (Boy)(Danced)   
No(Boy)(Danced )  
Every (Boy)(Danced)  
61</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>75</slideno>
          <text>An application: Explaining entailment patterns 
     Some boy sings and some boy dances 
. Some boy sings and dances  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 S D B 
76</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>44</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
Some boy danced 
 
The intersection  of the set of boys and the set of 
dancers is not empty 
 
Boy  Danced    
 
 
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced   
45</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>What do sentences mean?  
We can grasp the meaning of a sentence without 
knowing whether its true or false.  
 
The name of the person sitting closest to the door 
starts with a D. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Modification 
Set intersection can describe other adjectives too:  
 
Mitzi is a gray  cat 
Gianni is an Italian  waiter  
T-Rex is a carnivorous  dinosaur  
This is a round  ball 
 
These are called intersective adjectives . 
 
 
 
29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>77</slideno>
          <text>An application: Explaining entailment patterns 
   Some boy sings and some boy dances 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 S D B 
 
78</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>61</slideno>
          <text>Determiners summary 
All the sentences we have seen have the structure: 
 
Det(A)(B) 
 
Some (Boy)(Danced )     Boy  Danced    
Three (Boy)(Danced )   | Boy  Danced | = 3 
More than half (Boy)(Danced)   
No(Boy)(Danced )  
Every (Boy)(Danced)  
62</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>81</slideno>
          <text>An application: Explaining entailment patterns 
     Some boy sings and some boy dances 
. Some boy sings and dances  
 
 
A entails B iff whenever A is true, B is true.  
 
We can find a situation where A is true but B is false.  
Hence, A does not entail B 
 
 
 
 
 
82</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>115</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.900 Introduction to Linguistics
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>More modeling 
Proper names pick out individuals in the world.  
John danced 
 
What does some boy refer to?  
Some boy danced   
40</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Modification 
There are also non-intersective  adjectives :    
 
George is a former  president 
This is a fake diamond  
 
The entailment pattern doesnt hold:  
 
George is a former president 
 George is a president [not valid]  
 ??George is former [not valid] 
 
 
 
 
33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>87</slideno>
          <text>The definite article 
We might define the as:  
 
The cats purred    Cat  Purred 
 
 
  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
88</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>62</slideno>
          <text>Determiners summary 
All the sentences we have seen have the structure: 
 
Det(A)(B) 
 
Some (Boy)(Danced )     Boy  Danced    
Three (Boy)(Danced )   | Boy  Danced | = 3 
More than half (Boy)(Danced)     | Boy  Danced  | &gt;  | Boy |  
No(Boy)(Danced )  
Every (Boy)(Danced)  
63</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>78</slideno>
          <text>An application: Explaining entailment patterns 
   Some boy sings and some boy dances 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 S D B 
  
79</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Interim summary  
Nouns , intransitive verbs , and adjectives  can be 
described using set intersection.  
 
            is a cat                                     Cat 
Mitzi   is gray       =                      Gray  
            purred                                     Purred 
 
37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Observation : The interpretation of a sentence depends 
on its syntactic structure. Different phrases make 
predictable contributions to the meaning of a sentence. 
 
The cat chased the rat 
The grey cat chased the rat 
The grey cat with the hat chased the rat Building a semantic system  
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Definition: Semantics and meaning 
The semantic competence of a speaker:  
The ability, when presented with a sentence and a 
situation, to tell whether the sentence is true or false in 
the situation. 
 
 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>49</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
No boy danced 
 
Can there be boys who are not dancers?  Yes. 
Can there be dancers who are not boys?  Yes. 
 
 
                                    
                                      
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced    
50</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>93</slideno>
          <text>Presuppositions of the 
The presuppositions of the definite often spring into 
existence, even if they werent known beforehand.  
 
I forgot to feed the cat this morning 
 
You will accommodate  the fact that I have a cat.  
  
94</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>86</slideno>
          <text>The definite article 
What is the meaning of the definite article?  
 
Some cat purred         Cat  Purred =  
Every  cat purred        Cat  Purred 
The cats purred        ? 
 
At first glance, the has a meaning similar to every  
 
 
 
 
 
 
87</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>80</slideno>
          <text>An application: Explaining entailment patterns 
   Some boy sings and dances  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 S D B 
 
81</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>102</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
We use a similar process to choose the meaning of 
ambiguous sentences. 
 
Successful lawyers and linguists are always rich  
103</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>52</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
Three boys danced 
 
Can there be boys who are not dancers?  Yes. 
Can there be dancers who are not boys?  Yes. 
 
 
                                    
                                      
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced      
   
53</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Observation : The interpretation of a sentence depends 
on its syntactic structure. Different phrases make 
predictable contributions to the meaning of a sentence. 
 
The cat chased the rat 
The cat licked the rat Building a semantic system  
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>112</slideno>
          <text>Conclusion  
Compositionality : We calculated the meaning of 
sentences from the meaning of their parts and the 
syntactic structure they were in. 
 
The meanings we calculated derived the truth 
conditions of the sentences.  
 
113</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Connectives 
Mitzi [I is gray or black ] 
 
Connectives  can be described in set terms.                                    
 
OR denotes set union 
Gray  Black 
 
 
                                       Gray            Black 
 
 
 
36</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>48</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
No boy danced 
 
Can there be boys who are not dancers? 
Can there be dancers who are not boys?  
 
 
                                    
                                      
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced  
49</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>What do sentences mean?  
BUT : This cant be all, since the truth-values of 
sentences can change over time or situations 
 
Reese is in room 20
The cat is on the mat 
 
 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Modification 
Mitzi [I is a gray cat ] 
 
Mitzi is a member  of the set of individuals who are gray 
AND a member of the set of individuals who are cats.  
 
Mitzi  Gray  AND Mitzi  Cat 
 
27</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>46</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
Some boy danced 
 
Can there be boys who are not dancers?  Yes. 
Can there be dancers who are not boys?  Yes. 
 
 
                                    
                                      
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced     
47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>What do sentences mean?  
(1) The capital of Canada is Ottawa 
(2) The capital of Canada is Montreal 
 
The meaning of a sentence is related to whether it is 
true or false (its truth value ).  
 
In the actual world:  
(1) is True 
(2) is False 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>84</slideno>
          <text>The definite article 
What is the meaning of the definite article?  
 
Some cat purred         Cat  Purred =  
Every  cat purred        Cat  Purred 
The cats purred    
 
 
 
 
 
85</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>How can we specify the meanings of infinitely many 
sentences in natural language?  
 
The scary lion devoured the mushroom pizza 
that I ordered last night Building a semantic system  
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>85</slideno>
          <text>The definite article 
What is the meaning of the definite article?  
 
Some cat purred         Cat  Purred =  
Every  cat purred        Cat  Purred 
The cats purred        ? 
 
 
 
 
 
 
86</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>94</slideno>
          <text>Presuppositions of the 
The presuppositions of the definite often spring into 
existence, even if they werent known beforehand.  
 
I forgot to feed the cat this morning 
 
You will accommodate  the fact that I have a cat.  
 
If no one objects to what I said, the assumption that I 
have a cat will be added to the common ground  of 
our conversation.   
95</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>105</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
We use this process to assign implicit parameters in a 
way that would make sentences true. 
 
Everybody in the room is taller than me 
 
 
 
106</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Observation : The interpretation of a sentence depends 
on its syntactic structure. Different phrases make 
predictable contributions to the meaning of a sentence. 
 
The cat chased the rat 
The cat chased the dog  Building a semantic system  
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>57</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
Every  boy danced 
 
Can there be boys who are not dancers? 
Can there be dancers who are not boys?  
 
 
 
 
 
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced   
    
58</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Connectives 
Mitzi [I is gray and furry ] 
 
Connectives  can be described in set terms.                                    
 
AND  denotes set intersection 
Gray  Furry 
 
 
                                       Grey            Furry 
 
 
35</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Modification 
Intersective adjectives conform to an entailment  
pattern. 
 
Mitzi is a gray cat 
 Mitzi is a cat  
 Mitzi is gray 
 
30</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>83</slideno>
          <text>The definite article 
What is the meaning of the definite article?  
 
Some cat purred         Cat  Purred =  
Every  cat purred    
The cats purred    
 
 
 
 
 
84</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Definition: Compositional semantics 
The principle of compositionality :  
The meaning of a sentence depends  
only on the meanings of its parts  
and on the way that they are  
syntactically combined. 
 
The task of the semantics of a language is to provide 
the truth-conditions of all the well-formed sentences in 
that language, and to do so in a compositional way 
21This image is in the public domain.
Source: Wikimedia Commons.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>90</slideno>
          <text>The definite article 
The cat purred  
 
The expression the cat presupposes:  
 Existence: there exists a cat 
 Uniqueness: there is exactly one (relevant) cat  
 
91</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>64</slideno>
          <text>Determiners summary 
All the sentences we have seen have the structure: 
 
Det(A)(B) 
 
Some (Boy)(Danced )     Boy  Danced    
Three (Boy)(Danced )   | Boy  Danced | = 3 
More than half (Boy)(Danced)     | Boy  Danced  | &gt;  | Boy |  
No(Boy)(Danced )      Boy  Danced  =  
Every (Boy)(Danced)    Boy  Danced 
65</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Basic modeling 
Mitzi is gray 
Mitzi is a cat 
Mitzi purred 
 
Mitzi is a member  of the  
set of individuals that are gray. 
Mitzi  Gray IP 
NP  
   I 
purred  
is gray  
is a cat  
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Observation : The interpretation of a sentence depends 
on its syntactic structure. Different phrases make 
predictable contributions to the meaning of a sentence. 
 
The cat chased the rat 
The rat chased the cat  Building a semantic system  
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>Modification 
Mitzi [I is a gray cat ] 
 
Set intersection : The set that results from combining 
two other sets                                       
     
Mitzi  Gray  Cat 
 
 
                                        Cat            Gray 
 
 
28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>59</slideno>
          <text>Determiners summary 
All the sentences we have seen have the structure: 
 
Det(A)(B) 
 
Some (Boy)(Danced )   
Three (Boy)(Danced )   
More than half (Boy)(Danced)   
No(Boy)(Danced )  
Every (Boy)(Danced)  
60</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>54</slideno>
          <text>Determiners 
More than half of the boys danced 
 
Can there be boys who are not dancers?   
Can there be dancers who are not boys?   
 
 
                                    
                                      
                                         Boy 
                                                       Danced    
    
    
   
55</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Modification 
There are also non-intersective  adjectives :    
 
George is a former  president 
This is a fake diamond  
 
 
 
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Sentence types 
What is the meaning of a sentence?  
 
Do your homework!  
 
Command  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>71</slideno>
          <text>Conservativity 
Universal : All natural language determiners are 
conservative. 
 
Therefore: no language has a simple determiner that means 
every- non  or Reverse -mth 
 
blarg  boys danced    Does not exit! 
=  every non-boy danced 
 
blick  boys danced    Does not exit!  
=  more than half of the dancers are boys 
 
 
72</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>100</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
Normally, we assume that speakers intend to say things 
that are grammatical, relevant, and  often  true.  
 
In the closet, you will find the blue coat 
 
Suppose that after I said this sentence, you open the 
closet and find only a black coat. 
 
Or you might assume you got the color confused and 
its really a dark blue coat.  
101</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>113</slideno>
          <text>Conclusion  
Compositionality : We calculated the meaning of 
sentences from the meaning of their parts and the 
syntactic structure they were in. 
 
The meanings we calculated derived the truth 
conditions of the sentences.  
 
When combined with a context, we yield a truth value  
 
114</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>What do sentences mean?  
We can grasp the meaning of sentences weve never 
heard before.  
 
The furry cat ate the red jellybean  
 
 
 
 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>114</slideno>
          <text>Conclusion  
Finally, we discussed the definite article and its 
presuppositions .  
 
The king of France is bald 
 Existence 
 Uniqueness 
 
 
 
 
115</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>70</slideno>
          <text>Conservativity 
Natural language determiners only care about 
elements that satisfy their first argument.  
 
Det is conservative  if Det(A)(B)  Det(A)(AB): 
 
more than half (boy)(danced)   conservative   
=  more than half of the boys danced 
=  more than half of the boys are boys who danced  
 
Reverse -mth (boy)(danced)   non-conservative  
=  more than half of the dancers are boys 
  more than half of the boys who danced are boys [*] 
71</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>98</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
Normally, we assume that speakers intend to say things 
that are grammatical, relevant, and  often  true.  
 
In the closet, you will find the blue coat 
 
Suppose that after I said this sentence, you open the 
closet and find only a black coat.  
99</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>101</slideno>
          <text>Accommodation  
We use a similar process to choose the meaning of 
ambiguous sentences.  
102</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>More modeling 
Proper names pick out individuals in the world.  
John danced 
 
39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>67</slideno>
          <text>Properties of determiners 
All the sentences we have seen have the structure: 
 
Det(A)(B) 
 
For example, every- non(A)(B) 
 
blarg boy danced 
=  every non- boy danced 
 
That is:  A  B 
 
68</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>110</slideno>
          <text>Conclusion  
The king of France is bald  
 
Modeling using sets : We defined connectives ( and, or) 
and determiners ( some , every , no, three , more than half ) 
as relations between two sets.   
 
 
111</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Modification 
There are also non-intersective  adjectives :    
 
George is a former  president 
This is a fake diamond  
 
In fact:  
 
George is a former president 
 George is not a president 
 George was a president in the past 
 
 
 
 
34</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>What is a dialect?
The politics of languages and dialects
Dialects of North American English
The &#8220;Ebonics&#8221; controversy</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-900-introduction-to-linguistics-fall-2012/resources/mit24_900f12_dialects/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>25&#8211;27</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
They [] like the front line.  [ser] 
They [be] out in the field.  [be estar] 
(lit. "They are always fighting.") 
"The Buys." Episode 3 from Season 1 of the series "The Wire." Home Box Office, 2002.
 Home Box Office. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
verbal marker  dn 
"The verbal marker dn denotes that an event has ended." 
 
I told him you dn changed. 
'I told him that you have changed.'   
 
A: You through with Michael Jordan [a magazine] I bought you? 
B: I dn already finished that. 
 'I have already finished that.' 
 
A: Push your seat. 
B: I dn pushed it.  'I already pushed it' 
A: Push it again.   
33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>44</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
 Content removed due to copyright restrictions. 
To view the Linguistic Society of Americas Resolution on the Oakland Ebonics issue, go to:
http://www.linguisticsociety.org/about/what-we-do/resolutions-statements-guides/lsa-res-ebonics  
45</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>43</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
May 2004 speech by Bill Cosby to an NAACP ceremony 
celebrating the 50th anniversary of Brown vs. Board of Education 
"Brown Versus the Board of Education is no longer the white person's problem. We've got to take the neighborhood back. We've 
got to go in there. Just forget telling your child to go to the Peace 
Corps. It's right around the corner. It's standing on the corner. It 
can't speak English. It doesn't want to speak English. I can't even 
talk the way these people talk. Why you ain't where you is go, 
ra, I don't know who these people are. And I blamed the kid until 
I heard the mother talk. Then I heard the father talk. This is all in 
the house. You used to talk a certain way on the corner and you 
got into the house and switched to English. Everybody knows it's 
important to speak English except these knuckleheads. You can't 
land a plane with why you ain't... You can't be a doctor with that 
kind of crap coming out of your mouth. There is no Bible that has 
that kind of language." 
  Bill Cosby. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.
44</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
"Remote past BIN  ": interesting semantic complications
 
"BIN situates an activity or state (or some part thereof) in the 
remote past." 
 
effect of stress: 
 
remote past BIN: 
She BIN running. 
'She has been running for a long time.' 
 
present perfect  bin:
 
She bin running.     'She has been running'
 
 
She bin had him all day. 'She has had him all day' 
31</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
And what about ... 
 
*be BIN  *Bruce be BIN running. 'It usually the case that Bruce was running a long time ago.' 
    *BIN be  *Bruce BIN be running. 'A long time ago, Bruce was in the habit of running.' 
37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
Actor Bill Cosby 
  
This image is in the public domain. Source: Wikimedia Commons.
43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Irish: 
Is     fear . 
       man him a. 
COP 
 
 'He is a man.' 
     Is   .  fuar 
     COP cold(hearted) him    
  'He is a coldhearted person.' 
T   s ina    fhear. (anois). 
      b. 
COP he in-his man (now) 
  'He is a man (now).', i.e. 'He has become a man.' 
      T  s fuar 
  
COP he cold 
  'He is cold.' (i.e. 'He feels cold.')  (source: Wikipedia, yes really )  African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
Spanish: 
 
  a. 	 Soy norteamericano.  
       I.am North.American 
 
 Estoy cansado.   
I.am  tired 
[ser] 
b. 	
 [estar] 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
Side point: expletive  it 
 
 It be knives in here.  It be ice picks in here. 
 'There are usually knives in here. There are usually icepicks in here.' 
  
Compare French expletive il: 
 
Il y a des    couteaux ici. 
 It is 
INDEF knives    here 
'There are knives here.' 
28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
Phonological features of AAVE  
 
 syllable coda cluster reduction ... 
 [hn]    'hand' 
[ds]   'desk' 
[pows]   'post' 
[ps]   'passed' 
[ms]  'mask' 
[gf]  'gift' 
[bowl] 'bold' 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Floorwalkers  Sales  Stockboys 
 all r  46%  18%  7% 
 some r  8%  35%  14% 
 no r  46%  47% 79% 
 floorwalker - cashier - stockboys 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>SAKS FIFTH AVENUE 
Image courtesy of Kent Manning on Flickr. 
MACY'S 
Image courtesy of Ruben Moreno Montoliu on Flickr. 
KLEIN'S 
5 Image courtesy of New York Public Library Digital Gallery.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
 
Aspectual be and -copula 
 
a. 	  Bruce run. 
'Bruce runs on occasions.' 
 b. 	  Bruce  running. 
'Bruce is running now.' or 'Bruce is running these days.' 
(i.e. it's part of who he is) 
 
c. 	Bruce be running.  
'Bruce is usually running.' or 'Bruce usually runs.' 
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
"Aspectual be  ": interesting semantic complications 
 
a.  Some of them be big and some of them be small. 
 b.  Sam's wholesale stores be on the outskirts of town. 
 
 
 
 c. Some iMacs be tangerine. 
but... 
Do Sam's wholesale stores move around? 
 Isn't color an intrinsic property of an iMac? 
30</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>bawt t tdd 
flapping baw t td 
dediphtongization ba: t ---
r-drop --- ta:d  
 GIRLS' RHYME: BOSTON, 1970s 
Extra, extra, read all about it. 
All the boys are mentally retarded. 
Result: ba: t ta: d 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
"The Buys." Episode 3 from Season 1 of the series "The Wire." Home Box Office, 2002.
 Home Box Office. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
verbal marker steady 
Precedes a verb form in the progressive to indicate that "an activity is 
carried out in an intense or consistent manner."  They want to do they own thing, and you steady talking to them. 'They want to do their own thing, and you're continuing to talk to them.'  Now that you got the new life, Satan steady bothering you. 'Now that you have a new life, Satan is consistently bothering you.'  May follow habitual  be 
 Them students be steady trying to make a buck. 
38</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
 
Negative concord in AAVE: 
 
He don' do nothin'. 
'He does nothing' 
 Negative concord in Russian: 
 On ne delaet niego. 
he not does  nothing 
'He does nothing.'  *On delaet niego.  
39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
Part of a rich tense/aspect system that includes:  
 
1. Present progressive: 	   He runnin. 
2. Present habitual progressive: 	 He be runnin. ("aspectual be  ")
 
3.   Present intensive hab.prog: 	  He be steady runnin. 
4. Present perfect progressive: 	 He bin runnin   
   'He has been running.' 
5. Present perfect with remote inception: 
         He BIN runnin.  
'He has been running for a long time (and still is).' 
 
and more ... 
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>AAVE Zero copula:  intrinsic property 
 
 a. 	He wild. 
 'He's a wild person' 
 b. She real nice. 
 'She's a nice person' 
 c. He not American. 
 d. If you good, you going to heaven. 
  African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
AAVE Invariant be: situation-dependent property, habitual   
 
 a. He be wild. 
 'He's acting wild/shows signs of wildness' 
 b. Sometime she be fighting. 
 c. Sometime when they do it, most of the problems always be 
wrong. 
 
 d. She be nice and happy. 
 e. Sue be knowing that song. 
(i.e. when we ask her, it generally turns out that she 
knows the song)  
 
 f. Sam's wholesale stores be on the outskirts of town. 
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
"The Buys." Episode 3 from Season 1 of the series "The Wire." Home Box Office, 2002.
 Home Box Office. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>45</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.900 Introduction to Linguistics
Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
"Remote past BIN  " 
I BIN knowing he died. 
'I have known for a long time that he died.'  A: The police going bad. B: They ain't going bad. They BIN bad.  'They aren't going bad. They have been bad for a long time.' 
 He BIN a preacher there. 
'He has been a preacher for a long time.' 
 A: Where'd you get that shirt? B: I BIN had it.   'I have had it for a long time.' 
A: Hunh B:   I BIN got it.   'I got it a long time ago.' 
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Saks  Macy's Kleins  
 all r  24%  22%  6% 
 some r  46%  37%  12% 
 no r  30%  41% 82% 
  
 
 
 Saks  ground floor  upper floor 
 all r  23%  34% 
 some r  23%  40% 
 no r  54% 26% 
 
 Saks - Macy's - Klein's (1962) 
upper floor - lower floor 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
compositional semantics 
BIN dn: remote past resultant state 
 
You should'a BIN dn called me down there. 
'You should have called me down there a long time ago,'  He BIN dn put that in there. 'He put that in there a long time ago.' 
35</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
 more about "Aspectual be "
 
a. 	  She be telling people she eight. 
'She is always telling people she's eight.'  
 
b. 	It be knives in here.  It be ice picks in here. 
 'There are usually knives in here. There are usually icepicks in here.' 
 
b. 	He doesn't even allow women to wear pants at women's 
 retreats and he doesn't even be there. 
 '...and he isn't even usually there' 
 c. 	She gotta be there for 9m so they be dn gone to school. 
'She has to be there at 9, so they have usually already gone 
to school.' 
27</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
"The Buys." Episode 3 from Season 1 of the series "The Wire." Home Box Office, 2002.
 Home Box Office. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
"The Buys." Episode 3 from Season 1 of the series "The Wire." Home Box Office, 2002.
 Home Box Office. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
Lexical features of AAVE 
 
Zero copula  a. He wild. 
 b. She real nice. 
 c. He not American. 
 d. If you good, you going to heaven. 
 Invariant  be 
a. He be wild. b. Sometime she be fighting. c. She be nice and happy. f. Sue be knowing that song. g. Sam's wholesale stores be on the outskirts of town. 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
compositional semantics 
be dn: habitual resultant state 
 
A: Y'all keep up with the news, hunh? B: Yeah, when it come on there, we be dn read it in the newspaper. 
'Yeah, by the time the news comes on there (on TV), we have 
usually already read it in the newspaper.' 
 She gotta be there for 9, so they be dn gone to school. 'She has to be there at 9, so they have usually already gone to school by then'  Anybody who don' have no money and jus' be dn got paid, must be on drugs. 'It is usually the case that anybody who doesn't have any money but has just gotten paid must be on drugs.' 
34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Arthur the Rat 
 
1.Brooklyn, NY 70-year old white female with college education 
2.Rural community in nME  73-year old white male with high 
 school education
 
3.Roxbury section of Boston, MA  young black female with high 
school education  
4.Memphis, TN  72-year old black man with college education 
5.Island in eVA  middle-aged white male with high school education 
6.Small city in scGA   middle-aged white female with college
 
education 
7.Wichita Falls, TX  middle-aged white male with (probably) high 
school education  
8.Village in nwWA 74-year old white male with high school 
education 
9.Small city in nwWI  middle-aged white woman with college 
education 
 
Source: http://www.courses.fa s.harvard.edu:80/~ling80/audio/  
2 A short tale devised to obtain phonetic representation from through out the
  country of all phonemes in American English. See link at bottom of page.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
 
Side point: expletive it 
LH (age 16): You know, like, ah, some people say if you're good an' shit, 
your spirit goin' to heaven, an' if you goodbe bad, your spirit 
goin to hell, well bullshit, your spirit goin' to hell anyway, good or 
 bad. 
KC: Why? 
LH: Why? why? Ill tell you why. 'Cause you see, doesn't nobody really 
know that  its a God, you know. 'Cause I mean I have seen black 
gods, pink gods, white gods, all color gods, and dont nobody know  
it's really a God , and when they be sayin' if you good youre goin' 
to heaven, that's bullshit. 
KC: Is that so? 
LH: 	 You ain't goin' to no heaven. 'Cause  it ain't no heaven for you to 
go to .             (W. Labov) 
29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
Phonological features of AAVE  
 
syllable coda cluster reduction   except when the coda cluster is of the form 
       [+voiced] [-voiced]  [hn] 'hand'  vs.   [pnt]  'pant' 
 [kowl]   'cold'  vs.     [kowlt] 'colt' 
  Exceptions: ain' and don' 
 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>GIRLS' RHYME: BOSTON, 1970s 
 
 
 Extra, extra, read all about it. 
All the boys are mentally retarded. 
   
A rhyme???? 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
And what about ... 
 
be BIN        BIN be 
36</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
RESOLUTION OF THE BOARD OF EDUCATION 
Oakland, CA (1996) 
Content removed due to copyright restrictions. 
To view the 1996 Oakland, CA Board of Education resolution on Ebonics, go to:  http://linguistlist.org/topics/ebonics/ebonics-res1.html  
40</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Writing systems as a technology for representing speech
Types of systems: pictographic, syllabary, alphabet
Origins of the Roman alphabet
Phonemic vs. phonetic alphabetic writing systems</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-900-introduction-to-linguistics-fall-2012/resources/mit24_900f12_writing_sys/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic  
Final devoicing in Russian 
 zero form  -a form       
1.  grp  grba  coffin  6.  rk ra  horn   
2.  lip  lipa  linden tree  7.  rk rka  fate  
3.  pt  pta  whisper  8.  krnda  krndaa  pencil   
4.  grt grda  city  9. ekipa  ekipaa  crew   
5.  ruk  ruka  hand  10. ras  rasa  race  
11. ras  raza  time  
 
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic  
Can  you  pronounce  these  words?  
The  balistanicacious  pressure  device   
It  was s imply  clantific , as she liked to say.   
Dr. Harriglon  will  see  you  to  your  room.    
Would  you  some  more  gartiletti !  I made t  hem  mysel f from  free-range   
Wookies .   
"And n  ow,  the tranya ."  
 - from  the (original  series)  Star  Trek  episode  
The  Corbomite  Maneuver  
34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic   
Final devoicing in Russian spelling  
 zero form  -a form      
1.  grp grba  6.   rk ra 
        
2.  lip  lipa  7.   rk rka 
        
3.  pt pta   8.   krnda  krndaa 
        
4.  grt grda  9.  ekipa  ekipaa 
        
5.  ruk ruka  10.  ras rasa 
        
 11.  ras raza 
    
27</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS 
... Greek!  
 written in a  
(somewhat imperfect) syllabary. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS  
Phoenician (from ca. 1100 BCE)   
http://www.ancientscripts.com  
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS  
 
After Cyril's death, Methodius continued his work. 
The alphabet that Cyril and Methodius created is to this day 
called... 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS  
... the GLAGOLITIC ALPHABET   
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic   
The rule of akan'je in Russian  
 
  In the syllable before the stress, or word-initial in an unstressed 
syllable, /o/ becomes [a]:  /nog/ becomes [nag] 'foot'   
/ngi/ stays [n gi]  'feet'   
  In other unstressed syllables, /o/ becomes [a] (Belarusian and 
some Russian dialects) or [] (Standard Russian). 
/groda/ becomes [g 
 rd]  'of the city'  (Standard Russian) 
/gorod/ becomes [g  rd]  'cities'  

24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>[] 
"back"  [i] 
"front" 
 [u]  [] [e] ( + i) 
 [o]  [a]  [] (o + i) ALPHABETS  
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS  
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS 
Hangul:  the  Korean  Alphabet  
 
The letters are arranged in blocks that mostly correspond to 
syllables: 
  /gi/   
  /gim/   
 
  /mi/   
  /min/   
-- giving the (false) impression that Hangul is a syllabary. 
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS 
A sample of Linear B script, 1450 BC   
Image courtesy of Sharon Mollerus on Flickr.
Deciphered by Michael Ventris (1922-1956), an architect and 
amateur linguist (assisted by John Chadwick, a classicist), who discovered that the Linear A texts are ... 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS 
Ugaritic cuneiform alphabet  
(W. Syria, ca.1300-1200 BCE)  
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic   
...blah, blah, blah for  umpteen more verses...  
...we get the point! .. . 
Finally, which rhymes with enough  
Though , through, plough, or dough, or cough?   
Hiccough  has the sound of cup.  
My advice is to give it up!!!   
 Gerald  Nolst  Trenite  (1870 -1946)  
33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>Reading  
How should we teach children (or adults) to read? 
 
The "Whole Language" movement of the 1990s: 
 
"English spelling is so full of irregularities, it is very hard to teach, especially to young children.  "Fortunately... we don't have to teach it explicitly!" 
40</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>Reading  
How fluent reading works.   
 
Eyes fixate briefly on each word or pair of adjacent words
(fixations are called saccades). 
 
Reading is routed through phonology: a "voice in the head". 
Some evidence: 
  Tongue twisters take longer to read than non-tongue twisters... even in Chinese!  
  The ability of deaf speakers to read oral languages such as English correlates with their degree of phonological knowledge.  
  In normal reading in an alphabetic system, every letter is  scanned and processed, though we do "error correct"...  
38</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>43</slideno>
          <text>Reading   
 
"As the information in this table reveals, in seven provinces (British 
Columbia, Manitoba, New Brunswick, Newfoundland/Labrador, Ontario, Prince Edward Island, Quebec) the only textbooks on the approved lists are those that subscribe to a whole-language philosophy... Unfortunately, in many provinces unless special permission is granted to do otherwise, schools are only permitted to purchase in quantity for classroom use textbooks that appear on the approved lists." 
 
[Marvin L. Simner, "Beginning Reading Instruction: A Position Paper on Beginning Reading 
Instruction in Canadian Schools", Canadian Psychological Association 1993]  
 
44</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS  
Cherokee syllabary,  
invented by Sequoyah (1770-1843)  
a silversmith  
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic   
HI, MY NAME IS 
ANDY 
HI, MY NAME IS 
ANDI 
36</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic   
Final devoicing in Turkish spelling  
 
1. 'rope' [ip] ip  [ipi] ipi  
2. 'louse' [bit] bit  [biti] biti  
3. 'reason' [sebep] sebep  [sebebi] sebebi  
4. 'bunch' [demet] demet  [demeti] demeti  
5. 'Ahmed' [ahmet] ahmet  [ahmedi] ahmedi  
6. 'color' [renk] renk  [rengi] rengi  
7. honor  [eref] eref  [erefi] erefi  
8. 'pilot' [pilot] pilot  [pilotu] pilotu  
9. 'wolf'  [kurt] kurt  [kurdu] kurdu  
29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic   
English trisyllabic laxing  
insane nsejn insanity nsnij  
grave ejv gravity vij  
serene sijn serenity snij  
divine dvajn divinity dv nij  
facile  fsajl facility  fslij  
(fsl) 
virtuoso  v tuowsow virtuosity  v tusij  
not just about -ity:   
contrite ~ contrition 
mendacious ~ mendacity 
Dearest  creature  in  creation,    
30</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>44</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.900  Introduction to Linguistics
 Fall 2012
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>Reading  
Success of "Whole Language" in the 1980s  
 
"We've begun seriously to affect legislative policy in states like Michigan and Kentucky as well as all of the provinces of Canada."  
[From a list of achievements of the Whole Language Movement:  
Jerome Harste (1993) "New Questions, Different Inquiries", in Carl B. Smith, ed., Whole Language: The Debate", Edinfo Press, p. 147]  
43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic   
HI, MY NAME IS 
BOBBY 
FISHER 
HI, MY NAME IS 
BOBBI 
FISHER 
37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>Reading   
How fluent reading works.  
Exceptions are flagged and processed in a special way.  Some 
consequences: 
 	 "Acquired dyslexia" after brain damage may impair "decoding" (reading of regular spellings) but spare exceptions  or vice versa. 
have vs. cave  
	 deep dyslexia 
  /hv/ vs. "I don't know" or  guessing  
(also: can't read non-words: stumped by  
bave) 
	 surface dyslexia  
  /hejv/, /kejv/ 
(can read non-words, but reads irregulars phonetically)   
39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>Reading  
The "Whole Language" movement - part 2: 
 
  English spelling is so full of irregularities, people couldn't possibly be attending to all the letters. 
 
  Reading is a "psycho-linguistic guessing game".  
 
  So teaching symbol-sound correspondences (in English at least) is a waste of time. 
42</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS  
Katakana 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS  
Glagolitic Greek Cyrillic Glagolitic Greek Cyrillic 
[]    [r]    
[b]   [s]  C ()  
[v]    [t]    
[]    [u]    
[d]    [f]    
[e]   [x]    
[]   [ts]   
[z]    [t]   
[i]   (H)  []   
[j]   [t]   
[k]    []   
[l]    []   
[m]    [e]   
[n]    [ju]   
[o]    [ja]  
[p]    
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS  
JAPANESE SYLLABARIES   
Hiragana  
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>PICTOGRAMS 
Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
 
To view an example of a pictogram from Mesopotamia, circa 3000 BC,
go to: http://www.mesopotamia.co.uk/writing/home_set.html .
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic   
Study English pronunciation.  
I will teach you in my verse   
Sounds like corpse, corps, horse, and  worse.   
I will keep you, Suzy, busy,   
Make your head with heat grow dizzy.  
Tear in eye, your dress will tear.  
So shall I! Oh hear my prayer.  
31</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>1. 'rope' [ip] [ipi] 
2. 'louse' [bit] [biti] 
3. 'reason' [sebep] [sebebi] 
4. 'bunch' [demet] [demeti] 
5. 'Ahmed' [ahmet] [ahmedi] 
6. 'color' [renk] [rengi] 
7. honor [eref] [erefi] 
8. 'pilot' [pilot] [pilotu] 
9. 'wolf' [kurt] [kurdu] Phonemic  vs.  phonetic   
Fina l devoicing in Turkish  
28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS   
This image is in the public domain. Source: Wikimedia Commons.
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Non-alphabetic cuneiform:  
Akkadian  (S.  Mesopotamia)  writing  system  
1.phonogram: representing a 
consonant-vowel combination 
like ka, ak, kak   
2.logogram: representing an  
entire word or concept.  
3.phonetic complement: 
narrows down logogram pronunciation, indicate grammatical form. 
4.determinative: indicates that 
an adjacent word is the name 
of a deity, a man, a city, etc. Not pronounced. 
This image is in the public domain. Source: Wikimedia Commons.
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS  
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Writing Systems
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic
Just compare  heart, beard, and  heard, 
Dies and diet, lord and word,   
Sword  and  sward, retain  and  Britain.  
(Mind the latter, how it's written.)  
Now I surely will not plague you  With such words as plaque and ague.   
But be careful how you speak:  
Say break and steak, but bleak and streak;Cloven, oven, how  and  low,   
Script, receipt, show, poem, and  toe.
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic   
 
HI,  MY NAME IS  
TONY  
HI,  MY NAME IS  
TONI  
35</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Phonemic  vs.  phonetic   
 
 Russian  Belarusian  
sg. pl. sg. pl. 
 
'foot'        i  
'city'     a    
'table'         
'windows'           
 
25</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>Reading   
"We now  know  that  learning to read and learning to write are a lot like  
learning to talk. We  would  think  it  funny  if  parents  hovered  over  their  
newborn's  crib,  chanting the  sounds of language one at  a time.  Parents 
are not  trying t  o t each l anguage,  but  rather  trying t  o co mmunicate with  
their child. They do not teach children individual sounds, but instead, use  
and sh are language naturally as  a part  of everyday ex  periences.  They 
respect  and a ccept  their baby's b  abblings a  s t alk.  Although d  ifferent  from  
that of grown- ups,  the  child's  language  is  celebrated and accepted 
without  criticism.  It  is  through  constant  interaction  with  family  and  
friends--through using language and hearing others use it in everyday  
situations --that children learn to talk. Our research has indicated that the  
same is true of learning t  o r ead an d w rite.  It  is through co  nstant  
interaction with family and friends. teachers and classmates -- through  
using reading and writing and observing others  reading and writing in 
everyday si  tuations --that children can learn to read and write."  
 (National  Council  of Teachers o  f English,  Elementary  School  
Practices . 1994 brochure )  
41</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS 
In the 9th century AD, two Byzantine missionaries, the brothers   
Cyril (827-869) &amp; Methodius (826-885), designed an alphabetic  
writing system  for the Moravian Slavic dialect.
This image is in the public domain. Source: Wikimedia Commons.
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS 
Hangul: the Korean Alphabet  
 
"The sounds of our country's language are different from those 
of China and do not correspond to the sounds of Chinese characters.  Therefore, among the stupid people, there have been many who, h aving something to put into writing, have in the end been 
unable to express their feelings.  
 I have been distressed by this and have designed twenty-eight new letters, which I wish to have everyone practice at their ease and make convenient for their daily use."  
King Sejong (1397-1450)  
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>ALPHABETS 
Hangul  consonants  
 
Nasal  Simple  Aspirated  Doubled   
        
   [k]  [k]     
back of  tongue raised to 
the velum  
  [n]    [t]    [t]    [l]  
tip of the tongue  
touching alveolar  
ridge  
  [m]    [p]  [p]     
two lips  
  [s]    []    []     
side view of   the 
teeth  
 []    [] (obsolete )    h  [h]    
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>CREDIT:  
Source for many of the following writing system slides: 
a now-gone class website by Prof. Richard Sproat 
(University of Illinois/Champaign-Urbana) 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>(Possibly) Independent Inventions of Writing 
 
Sumerian: ca. 3,200 BC 
 Egypt:  ca. 3,200 BC 
 Indus Valley: ca. 2,500 BC  China:   ca. 1,500 BC 
 Central America: ca. 250 BC      (Olmecs, Mayans, Zapotecs) 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <videos>
      <video>
        <video_url/>
        <video_title/>
        <transcript>
          <slice>
            <text_slice/>
            <time_slice/>
          </slice>
        </transcript>
      </video>
    </videos>
  </lectures>
</doc>
