<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/</course_url>
    <course_title>Introduction to Syntax</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>Linguistics </list>
      <list>Syntax</list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Double Objects (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ho_double_obj/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Null Subjects (pro) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ho_pro/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Case and Licensing (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln12ho_marantz91/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Unaccusativity (cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln8linking_utah/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(11) The Locative Alternation 
a. I loaded the hay onto the truck. pour 
b. I loaded the truck with the hay. fill 
Some verbs dont alternate; some languages have only a single member of each pair.  
(12) 	 Possible approaches 
UTAH-compatible 
a. 	 The thematic roles in DA/LA pairs are identical; one member is derived. 
b. 	 The thematic roles in DA/LA pairs are distinct; both members are  
 base-generated. 
UTAH-incompatible 
c. 	 The thematic roles in DA/LA pa irs are identical; both members are  
 base-generated. 
Bakers approach 
d. 	 (a) is true of DA, (b) is true of LA. 
(13) 	 Middle-level semantic analysis 
On a very gross level of description, (a) and (b) in (10)/(11) convey the same 
meanings; on a very detailed level (invol ving focus and topic), they dont. But 
there is an intermediate level, at which (10a-b) are equivalent whereas (11a-b) 
arent. Thats the level of thematic roles. 
(14) 	 In the LA, the direct object is totally  affected. It also determines the aspectual 
class of the predicate, while the PP argum ent has no such effect [15]. Baker takes 
this test (incremental them e) to be diagnostic of the true theme. In the DA, 
the aspectual class of the predicate de pends on the theme  regardless of its 
position [16]. Baker concludes that the two alternants are thematically identical. 
(15) 	 Common claim : The direct object in  the double object constr uction is affected; 
transfer of possession is implied, but not in the dative construction. 
a. 	 I taught French to the children. 
b. 	 I taught the children French.  The children learned French 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
In fact, the evidence for the subjecthood of the theme and objecthood of the agent in 
ergative languages is often mixed and indecisive.  
(7) 	 Theme is the subject because 
a. 	 It bears the case of intransitive subjects [7],[8]. 
b. 	 It can be controlled in adjuncts [9]. 
c. 	 It can be shared in VP-conjunction. 
d. 	 It has scope over negation (while the agent has scope under negation).  
(8) 	 Theme is the object because 
a. 	 The agent can bind into the theme, but not vice versa [10]. 
b. 	 The theme can, but the agent cant, be incorporated into the verb. 
(9) 	 Solving the puzzle : Universally, Agent is projected above Theme (UTAH). In 
accusative languages, the agent raises to the surface subject position [Spec,IP], 
whereas in deep ergative languages, it is the Theme that becomes a subject [12]. 
Properties (7) are sensitive to SS/LF, properties (8) are sensitive to DS.  
 A residue : Baker mentions among the invariant properties the fact that agents 
rather than themes are c ontrolled in complement nonf inite clauses. This is 
supposed to be a DS property. But in fact , in accusative languages themes can be 
easily controlled under certain verbs ( John 1 wanted PRO 1 to be elected ); although 
the controller is determined thematically (at DS), the controllee, PRO, isnt.   
Linking to Object 
Given that there is at most one  causer/agent in an event, th e subject linking ru le is pretty 
straightforward. But among the remaining argu ments  two internal  arguments in the 
interesting cases  which are we to project as direct object? 
(10) The Dative Alternation 
a. I gave the candy to the children. donate 
b. I gave the children the candy. owe 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
We also know that there are many structural asymmetries between subject and 
object. The verb forms a constituent (VP) with the object, excluding the subject; 
and the subject asymmetrically c-co mmands the object (binding, scope).  
(5) In English, the only apparent ch allenge to UTAH is psych-verbs. 
a. John likes long novels. Exp&gt;&gt;Th 
b. Long novels please John. Th&gt;&gt;Exp 
 Possible responses : i) UTAH is false; ii) one variant, probably (b), is syntactically 
derived; iii) The thematic analysis is t oo coarse, and in fact, one label (probably 
Th) masks two distinct -roles. 
(6) Is there an Experiencer -role ? 
Baker denies that Exp is a specific thematic label. Instead (following Dowty) he 
proposes a macro-role, subsuming agent and Exp as subcases. This is a fuzzy 
prototype notion, related to Levin &amp; Rappaports internal cause. In John fears 
dogs , it is a property of Johns internal make-up  though not necessarily his will 
 that causes him to respond in a particular way to dogs (p.79).  
 Note 1 : Isnt it an internal property of ch airs that makes the chair break in 
response to forceful twists, and still, chair  is the object in The pressure broke the 
chair . Is there a way to make Bakers intuition work?
 Note 2 : When both an agent and an experien cer are present, some fine-grained 
scale of Proto-Agent properties mu st select the agent as the subject: 
a. Mary deliberately annoyed Bill. 
Ergativity 
It has been claimed that in ergative languages, agents link to VP-internal positions and 
themes to VP-external positions. If so, er gative languages would be a mirror image of 
accusative languages  and a flat  refutation of the UTAH. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
c. I threw the ball to Bill. 
d. I threw Bill the ball.  Bill got the ball 
e. She sang a song for her dead lover. 
f. # She sang her dead lover a song. 
Baker agrees that there is some suggestion of affectedness, but insists that it is not 
an entailment, see [20]. The intuition is too weak to support a syntactic analysis. 
Syntactic tests 
(16) 	 Under a variety of tests, the argumen ts of DA and LA divide in the following 
manner: 
a. 	 Pattern I  theme in either alternant of DA, direct object in either alternant
 of LA. 
b. 	 Pattern II  shifted goal/benefac tive in double object construction. 
The tests diagnoze an underlying (deep) object, namely class (a) but not (b). 
(17) 	 Secondary predication : The predicate cannot be predicated of a prepositional 
object (due to mu tual c-command). 
In LA, the AP can be predicated of the di rect object, whatever its thematic role is 
[22]. In DA, there is a furthe r restriction  the AP cant be predicated of the goal, 
even when it is not a PP [23]. In fact, thats the only instance where a secondary 
predication seems to be sensitive to  thematic information (suggesting a 
misanalysis).  
Baker : Reduce predication in NP Goal-NP Theme to NP Theme-PP Goal  since the latter is 
derived from the former [24] (by P-incorporation).  
(18) 	 A-bar movement : The direct object is frozen in DOC, not in the LA [25]-[28]. 
(Possibly, the null P in [ 25]/[28a] is causing trouble) 
(19) 	 -ing nominalizations : The DOC cant be nominalized, while either alternant of the 
LA can [29]-[32]: 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(28) The thematic hierarchy 
agent/causer &gt;&gt; theme/patie nt &gt;&gt; path/location    
Agent/causer include experiencer of verbs like fear; experiencers that 
undergo change of state are themes/p atients; goal/benef active falls under 
path/location (and maybe some experien cers as well); instrumentals are 
intermediate agent-themes (left unspecified). The idea is that syntax need 
nothing beyond these coarse distinc tions for the purposes of linking. 
UTAH or RUTAH? 
Does the thematic hierarchy impose an absolute, unique syntax (Always project theme 
in [Spec,VP]), or only a pa rallel syntactic hierarchy (Always project theme above 
goal)? 
Evidence for RUTAH 
(29) agent &gt;&gt; goal 
a. Mary sent a package to John from Maraboo. 
b. John received a package from Baraboo. 
agent&gt;&gt;instrument 
c. John loaded the truck with a crane/pitchfork. 
d. The crane/*pitchfork loaded the truck. 
agent&gt;&gt;experiencer 
e. Mary deliberately worried John. 
f. John worried about the exam. 
In all these examples, projection seems to care about relative rankings of thematic roles, rather than their specific labels.
 Baker : The subjects in (b,d,f) are all prot o-agents, hence all rank topmost on the 
thematic hierarchy; cf. crane  vs. pitchfork  in (d). With (b) and (f), some internal 
property of the subject is responsible for the eventuality taking place. (Does 
receiving require intention or decision?).  
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
this line does not eliminate all relativit y from the analysis; rather, it moves the 
relativity from the statement of UTAH into the cognitive realm of what is 
perceived to be an agent (p. 110). 
(30) Psych Verbs (yet again) 
a. John fears the darkness. 
b. The darkness frightens John. 
Belletti &amp; Rizzi (1988) : i) agent &gt;&gt; experiencer &gt;&gt; th eme; ii) (b) is derived by 
NP-movement of the experiencer from a pos ition inside VP above the theme. So 
in (a), the experiencer is projected as a subject; in (b), as a second, higher object. 
Whats important is that in both cases the theme is projected lower, hence 
RUTAH. 
 Bakers reanalysis : The subject of (b) is a proto-ag ent by virtue of being a causer. 
Implication: (b) is underived, not an un accusative structure. The source of the 
special psych-effects is  a null P introducing the experiencer, which can be 
thought of as a (mental) goal or locative; see [66]. The experiencer is very much 
like an applied object (goal or benefactive), explaining why it is a weak island 
[67], why object experien cer verbs cant be nomina lized, form compounds or 
have unaccusative counterparts.  
Evidence for UTAH 
(31) Intransitives 
RUTAH predicts that all monoargumen tal verbs should project their single 
argument in the same fashion. For example, if that argument is an agent, it could 
equally be projected as subject or object , since each position trivially c-commands 
all other argument positions. Likewise for a theme verb.  
It is well-known that unaccusatives and unergatives contrast in this respect. 
Unaccusativity Hypothesis  UTAH. Hence, support for the UH is support for 
UTAH. 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Account : Only the higher argument, in [Spec,VP], can raise to [Spec,IP], due to 
locality. In dative verbs, it must be the th eme; in locative verbs,  it is either the 
material or the location, each of whic h can be projected as a theme.   
Note : Its not clear why the goal can move past the theme in (c) but not in (d). 
Baker (p. 96) appeals to the idea that NP -trace is an anaphor  subject to condition 
A in the CFC framework; in transitives, VP isnt a CFC (lacking the external 
argument) but in unaccusatives it is (there  is no external argument). This analysis 
is problematic because i) NP-traces and anaphors dont have the same 
distribution, ii) If external subjects are generated inside VP, all VPs are CFCs.  
(23) 	 Support for UTAH 
Where there are few semantic differences, there are syntactic oddities pointing to 
a nontrivial derivation (the DA); where there are significant semantic differences, 
there is no sign of such a de rivation (the LA) (p. 97). 
(24)	 A crosslinguistic challenge 
Some languages (primary object languages ) only have the DOC, not the dative 
construction [44]-[45]. Could it be that  goals in such languages are directly 
projected in [Spec,VP] and, unlike English, do not raise across the theme?
 Bakers answer : No, these goals show all the peculiarities of the English goal in 
DOC, pointing to a derived structure. The conclusion is that in some languages, 
dative shift is obligatory (cf. owe in English). 
(25) 	 Evidence for dative shift in Mohawk and Sesotho 
a. 	 The incremental theme is the them e, not the direct object, which is the 
goal, since events are indi viduated by themes [46]-[47]. 
b. 	 Themes, but not goals, can be  incorporated into V [48]. 
c. 	 A-bar movement of the applied goal/benefactive is  impossible [51]. 
d. 	 The goal can become a subject of passive but not unaccusative [53]-[54]. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
c. 	 Mary stood in line for an hour. unergative 
d. 	 The statue stood in the park for 50 years. unaccusative 
And while all measure phrases are direct  objects, not all direct objects measure 
[74]. The notion of theme, however vague, is  better suited to predict the linking in 
[74b]. 
Problem : Baker argues that stative transitiv es, like psych verbs, pose a problem 
for aspectual linking theories but not so much  for thematic ones [75]. He says that 
[75b] comments more on Johns character and tastes, while [75a] comments on a 
particular property of the dog (p. 120). But notice th at this is a consequence of 
the fact that John is the subject of [75a] and the dog  of [75b], given that the 
subject is the unmarked t opic; it doesnt explain why this fact. 
(35) 	 Linking rules (at last) 
a. 	 An agent is projected in the highest [Spec,VP]. 
b. 	 A theme is projected in the lower [Spec,VP]. 
c. 	 A goal/path/location is projected in the complement of V. 
Notes : -roles are (fuzzy) prototypes, and movement (in unaccusatives and DOC) 
may disguise the underlying structure. 
(36) 	 Final speculations : Baker suggests at the end [78]-[ 79] that the thematic hierarchy 
may in fact be reduced to lexi cal decomposition of predicates: 
[x CAUSE [y BECOME [AT STATE z]]]; he re, x is the agent, y the theme and z 
the goal/location. If this conceptual stru cture is directly mapped to the syntax 
(with abstract heads), then it follows au tomatically that x is the subject, y the 
direct object and z oblique. In other word s, the more closely our syntax reflects 
conceptual structure, the more trivial UTAH becomes, perhaps to the point of 
redundancy. 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(26) Are there languages with no dative shift ? 
In Japanese, there is an alternati on between DAT-ACC-V and ACC-DAT-V [58]. 
The case markings are invariant, unlike English. Still, there are significant 
asymmetries. Quantifiers can float off the theme but not the goal, in both variants 
(due to a null P?); theme-compounds ex ist, goal-compounds dont; There is scope 
freezing in the DAT-ACC-V order; th ere are goal passives but no goal 
unaccusatives. Baker points out that if ind eed Japanese has dative shift, then NP-
movement need not be case driven.  
What is the Thematic Hierarchy? 
(27) a. (Proto-)Agent is the highest. 
b. Theme&gt;&gt;Goal. 
(b) was denied by many researcher s (Grimshaw 1990, Kiparsky (1987), LFG 
work), but the evidence for the derived status of the goal in DOC supports it. 
Baker notes another benefit: Goal and location can be collapsed (since theme is 
higher than location on everyones account). 
c. John threw the ball to Bill / to the fence / toward th e fence / into the dugout. 
 A problem : If goal and location are two instances of the same -role, why does 
dative shift apply only to one of them? ( John threw Bill/*the fence the ball ). 
Baker : The distinction is semantic, but not thematic . Dative shift is licensed by 
the redundancy of to with goals, and perhaps by the need to assign structural case 
to animate nouns in many languages.  
 More problems : i) why isnt to redundant in the dative construction? ( John threw 
the ball *(to) Bill ); ii) The structural case-animacy link doesnt seem to be general 
enough ( Mary pleaded with John/*the stone , Mary met with the boss/*wall ). 
More generally, the problem of constraining dative shift to just the right verbs is 
very serious. A derivational th eory must allow syntax to be sensitive to semantic 
distinctions much subtler than -roles; a lexicalist theory can simply make the 
linking rules sensitive to these dist inctions, a more natural solution. 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
a. 	 Johns renting of the house to th e men / *Johns renting of the men (of)
 the house. 
b. 	 Marys spraying of paint onto the wall / Marys spraying of the wall 
 with paint. 
Account : of-NP must be a direct argument of the head noun; the goal in DOC is 
only an indirect argument (o wing to the null P), hence it  cant be case-marked by 
N (nor by P). 
(20) 	 Synthetic compounds : Only a bare argument can be incorporated into the head 
noun (the other argument must be optional). 
a. 	 *relative-depending. 
b. 	 book-reading / *children reading 
c. 	 hay-loading / truck-loading 
 There is a null P in DOC blocking compound formation. 
(21) 	 Scope freezing 
In DOC, the theme is frozen in scope: Goal&gt;&gt;Theme. The LA shows scope 
ambiguity in either alternant [36]-[37]. Unfortunately, there is no satisfactory 
explanation for scope freezing. 
(22) 	 *goal-unaccusatives / locative-unaccusative 
a. 	 The dropped a rope (down) to John. 
b. 	 The roped dropped (down) to John. 
c. 	 They dropped John (down) the rope. 
d. * John Goal dropped (down) the rope. [ VP Theme [ V V Goal]] 
e. 	 The bees swarmed in the garden. [ VP Theme [ V V Locative]] 
f. 	 The garden swarmed with bees. [VP Theme [ V V Material]] 
Note : swarm has no triadic entry, like drop; is there a truly minimal pair? 
g. * The hay loaded onto the truck / *The truck loaded with hay. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Linking of Arguments and the Nature of UTAH 
Idan Landau 
(1) 	 The Uniformity of Theta Assignment Hypothesis (UTAH) 
Identical thematic relationships between items are represented by identical 
structural relationships between those items at the level of D-structure.   
Baker (1988) left the UTAH quite vague and open to various interpretations. 
a. 	 What are the thematic roles that enter into the relationships? 
b. 	 What are the structural relations hips (X-bar notions, grammatical  
  relations)? 
c. 	 How identical is identical? Pe rhaps whats needed is equivalent. 
(2) 	 Goals of Baker (1997) 
a. 	 Establish the crosslinguistic validity of something like UTAH. 
b. 	 Specify the thematic roles relevant to UTAH. 
c. 	 Decide between an absolute a nd relative interpretation of UTAH. 
d. 	 Argue against an aspectual basis for linking. 
e. 	 Place UTAH within a minimalist context as an interface condition. 
(3) 	 Breaking down the linking problem 
a. 	 Determine the subject. 
b. 	 From the remaining arguments, determine the direct object. 
c. 	 Project remaining arguments as  obliques (transpa rent linking). 
Linking to Subject 
(4) 	 Universally, given a two-place verb with the -grid &lt;agent,patient/theme &gt;, agent 
is projected as a subject and patient/theme as an object. There are many such 
verbs like (a), and no verb like (b). 
a. 	 John hit/found/broke the table. 
b. 	 The table plit/vound/proke John. table  = theme, John  = agent 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(32) 	 Possible escape hatches for RUTAH 
a. 	 Unergatives are concealed transiti ves (with a covert/cognate object).  
b. 	 Unaccusatives are concealed trans itives, with a suppressed agent. 
c. 	 If a hierarchical thematic relation can be established between V and its 
arguments, and not only between co-arguments, then the syntactic contrast 
between the two verb classes can  be reconciled with RUTAH.  
(a) and (b) play around w ith the syntax of intransitives, (c) complicates the 
interpretation of UTAH. There is littl e motivation for any of these options. 
(33) 	 Theme vs. Goal 
Is there evidence that theme is in [Spec,VP] even in the absence of a goal? 
a. 	 Argument sharing in Edo: Only the theme can be shared, not the goal  
even when the theme is absent [61b]. 
b. 	 goal-incorporation into V is impossi ble in Mohawk even in the absence 
of a theme [48b]. [Can you see a problem with this argument?] 
c. 	 The conative alternation [70] shows that projection of an argument as a 
direct object or as a PP has seman tic consequences even when no other 
argument competes for these positions. [Can you see a problem with this 
 argument?]. 
Against aspectual linking 
Is linking to syntax informed by -roles or aspectual roles (Measurer, Terminus)? 
(34) 	 Baker points out that  on the coarse-grained -theory, the two views nearly 
converge. The COS argument is both the th eme and the measurer of the event; the 
goal is also a terminus, specifying the completion of the event. 
But L&amp;R show that aspect and unacc usativity are only loosely connected: 
a. 	 There are both telic a nd atelic unaccusatives [72]. 
b. 	 There are both telic a nd atelic unergatives [73]. 
Similarly, state/event contrast  dont fully predict unaccusativity: 
11</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Control (PRO) (cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln15cont_vs_rais/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Hornstein denies all this. Instead, he proposes the following picture: 
(2) a. -roles are features transferred from predicates to DPs. 
b. There is no limit on the number of -features a DP can accrue. 
c. There is no null case; the null subject of infinitives is caseless. 
d. Control is movement, subject to  the Minimal Link Condition (MLC). 
e. There is no PRO; there is no "control module". 
In short: Control = Raising to a -position 
(3) 	 Sample derivations (Hornsteins (45),(41))
 a. 	 Complement control
Mary hopes to win. 
[IP Mary [ VP Mary v+hopes [ IP Mary to [ VP Mary v+win]]]] 
  Features checked by Mary: external -role of win, EPP-feature of to, 
external -role of hope , EPP-feature and nominative case of matrix I0. 
b. 	 Adjunct control
John heard Mary without entering the room. 
[IP John [ I past [ VP/VP  [VP John [ heard Mary]] [ Adjunct  without 
[IP John [ I ing [ VP John [ VP entering the room]]]]]]]] 
Note : Raising of John from [Spec,- ing] to [Spec, heard ] crosses an adjunct island. 
Hornstein claims that sideward movement is not island-sensitive (Nunes 1995).  
(4) 	 The standard view of control 
a. 	 PRO exists, and it is distinct from NP-trace. 
b. 	 Hence: Control involves two ar gument chains, raising involves one. 
c. 	 The control module exists. 
Note : (4) is an extremely minimal view of co ntrol, compatible with many views of PRO 
(anaphor, pronoun, A-bar variable) and of th e control module (predication, lexical 
entailment, pragmatic inference, etc.). See, among others: Chomsky 1981, 1986, Bresnan 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Obligatory Control Cant be Raising 
or: 
Where Hornstein (1999) got it wrong
Idan Landau 
Background 
In the history of generative grammar, almost  any conceivable reduction of Obligatory Control 
(OC) has been proposed. People said that OC is a kind of... 
	Predication  (Williams 1980, Chierchia 1984, Dowty 1985, Clark 1990). 
	Anaphora (Manzini 1983, Bouchard 1984, Koster 1984, Borer 1989). 
	Agreement  (Landau 2000, Tth 2000). 
It was just a matter of time, then, for the la st option to be vigorously defended: OC is... 
	Movement  (Martin 1996, ONeil 1997, Hornstein 1999, Manzini &amp; Roussou 2000, Polinsky 
&amp; Potsdam 2002) 
There are various implementations of this idea. We  will take to task the theory put forward in 
Hornstein (1999), because it is both extremely exp licit and radical. Well see that despite its 
superficial elegance and appeal, this  theory is not a serious altern ative to any of the traditional 
accounts of OC. 
Hornsteins theory 
(1) 	 GB/early minimalist accounts of OC invoke  stipulations and redundant mechanisms: 
a. 	 An argument chain bears exactly one -role. 
b. 	 No movement to a -position. 
c. 	 No (sideward) movement to a non-c-commanding position. 
d. 	-roles are not checkable features. 
e. 	 The null case proposal (only control Infl assigns it, only PRO can bear it).  
f. 	 PRO and trace are distinct (i.e., PRO exists). 
g. 	 Raising and control are substantially different. 
h. 	 The control module exists, that is, there is a special component of grammar that  
is responsible for the choice of contro ller in OC and the interpretation of PRO. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
  i. [After PRO arb pitching the tents], darkness fell quickly.  (Kawasaki 1993) 
ii. Mary 1 was baffled. [Even after PRO 1 revealing her innermost  
   feelings], John remained untouched. 
iii. Mary 1 lost track of John 2 because, [PRO 1,2 having been angry at 
each other], he had gone one way and she the other. (Bresnan 1982) 
Hornstein explains the OC ef fect with right-edge adjuncts  by sideward movement (see 
(3b)), which is movement to a non-c-commandi ng position. Since the lo cal matrix DP  if 
there is one - does not c-command PRO in (c-i,ii,iii), sideward movement should be 
possible, and NOC, being a last resort option, should be blocked. It follows that Hornstein 
cannot explain the control contrast betw een right- and left-edge adjuncts.  
(15) The Interpretation of PRO in NOC
 Hornstein : The null subject in NOC is a pronoun (i.e., pro). 
 In reality : That's false. The null subject is a logophor  (parallel to picture -anaphora). 
(Kuno 1975, Lebeaux 1984, Williams 1992, Landau 2001) 
The antecedence conditions on logophors are stri cter than those of pronouns, making the  
 distinction empirically testable: 
a. 	 [PRO 1 having just arrived in town], the main hotel seemed to Bill 1 to 
be the best place to stay.
b. 	* [PRO 1 having just arrived in town], the main hotel collapsed on Bill 1. 
       (Williams 1992) 
c. 	 [his 1/*PRO 1 having shaved already] show s that Mary arrived more  
than 5 minutes after John 1 did. (Lebeaux 1984) 
d. 	 John sued Mary 1 for divorce because it was no longer possible 
[for her 1/*PRO 1 to support him].     (Kuno 1975) 
e. 	 Johns 1 wife thought that [for him 1/*PRO 1 to indulge himself in drinking]  
is inappropriate. 
In principle, Hornstein coul d argue that a silent logophor, ra ther than a silent pronoun, is 
inserted when NP-movement is blocked. But this would remove the alleged analogy to 
(silent) resumptive pronouns as a last resort in islands to A-bar movement (Hornstein 1999, 
fn. 42). 
"Side benefits" 
(16) De se  Interpretation 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
e. 	 Strkunum virast [t lei ast ekki llum  skla]. 
the boys. DAT seem to-be-bored not all. DAT in school 
The boys seem not to be all bored in school 
f. 	 Strkanna virast [t vera allra geti  rnnie]. 
the boys. GEN seem to-be all. GEN mentioned in the-speech 
The boys seem to be all mentioned in the speech 
Upshot : This is a compelling argument against the idea that "control=raising". The contrast 
clearly indicates that two A-chains are i nvolved in (a-c) but only one in (d-f). To 
accommodate these facts, Hornstein would have to stipulate that i) A-chains can be doubly 
case-marked, and ii) That option is license d only when the head of the chain is -marked. 
(i) has indeed been proposed in the pa st (see Yoon 1997, Bejar &amp; Massam 1999), but only 
as a parametric option, and never with the qualification in (ii). 
(22) Partial Control 
In Landau (2000) I discuss a neglected propert y of control complements, namely the fact 
that the reference of PRO need not be exhaus ted by the reference of the controller. Such 
cases are perfectly natural when the sp eaker has some salient group in mind: 
(We thought that...) 
a. 	 The chair 1 preferred [PRO 1+ to gather at 6]. 
b. 	 Bil1 regretted [PRO 1+ meeting without a concrete agenda]. 
c. 	 Mary 1 wondered [whether PRO 1+ to apply together for the grant]. 
Fact: Most control verbs allow par tial control, but most control tokens do not reveal this. 
The problem for Hornstein : There is no partial raising! The notion is theoretically 
incoherent (raise only a chunk of the reference?) and empirically unattested: 
(We thought that...) 
d. * The chair appeared to be gathering once a week. 
 Implication : The existence of partial control de stroys Hornstein's "argument from 
simplicity". If OC does not reduce completely to  raising, then a theory with both NP-trace 
and PRO is the simplest one permitte d by the facts of natural language.  
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
b.  Implicit reflexive control should be possible. 
c. John said to return later. 
d. [IP John 1 [VP t1 said t 1 [IP t1 to [ VP t1 return later]]]] 
e. John said to himself to return later. 
 In reality : Sentences like (c) never have interpretati ons like (e); implicit  controllers behave 
like pronouns w.r.t. condition B, triggering disjointness (Williams 1985, Chomsky 1986, 
Brody &amp; Manzini 1987). 
(12) The Minimal Distance Principle (MDP) 
The DP closest to PRO is the controller.
(Rosenbaum 1967, Bach 1979, Bach &amp; Partee 1980, Larson 1991, 
Manzini &amp; Roussou 2000). 
a. 	 John 1 wanted [PRO 1 to leave]. 
b. 	 John 1 persuaded Mary 2 [PRO 2/*1 to leave]. 
c. 	 John 1 promised Mary 2 [PRO 1/*2 to leave]. 
Hornstein : i) The MDP is a correct markedness condition. 
        ii) The MDP follows from the Minimal Link Condition (MLC). 
 Problems : 
i) In uncontroversial movement contexts, ML C violations are not "m arked", but completely 
ungrammatical (e.g., * John seemed it was likely to win ). Why does it become a markedness 
condition only in the context of OC? ii) In f act, MDP "violations" are not marked, but form 
semantically coherent subclasses: 
a. 	 Commitments
We 1 vowed to our leader [PRO 1 to be loyal]. 
Requests 
b. 	 The prisoner 1 asked the guard [PRO 1 to smoke one more cigarette]. 
Proposals 
c. 	 John 1 proposed to Mary [PRO 1 to help her with the arrangements]. 
In general, the choice of controller is sensit ive to both lexical and pr agmatic factors (speech 
acts, authority relations, etc.). The vast lit erature on this topic agrees that no purely 
syntactic account is tenable in this domain (Chomsky 1981, Manzini 1983, Koster 1984, 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
A puzzle for Hornstein : Why should the presence of an external -feature on the matrix 
verb license a CP projection in the complement ? The two facts seem completely unrelated. 
The standard view makes sense of this co ntrast: NP-movement cannot cross a CP-boundary 
(without violating the ban on improper movement ). Furthermore, recent studies (Rizzi 
1997, Roussou 2001, Landau, in progress) link the licensing of PRO to C. 
(20) Unaccusative Properties 
Raising predicates are unaccusative, control pr edicates are (usually) not. While  Hornstein's 
theory can, in principle, expl ain contrasts in the matrix position (by reference to its 
thematic/nonthematic status), it cannot expl ain contrasts in the em bedded position.  Two 
such contrasts are reviewed below. 
a. 	 En-cliticization (Ruwet 1972) 
Raising verbs permit en-cliticization  a diagnostic of  NP-movement in French - of 
the partitive complement of their surface subject on the embedded  verb, whereas 
control verbs do not. 
i. 	 Le directeur du dpartement semble tre accept. 
the head of-the department seems to-be accepted
The head of the department seems to be accepted
ii.	 Le directeur semble [ ec en tre accepte]. 
iii. 	 Le directeur du dpartement espre tre accept. 
the head of-the department hopes to-be accepted
The head of the department hopes to be accepted 
iv. * Le directeur espre [ ec en tre accept]. 
Explanation : ec in (ii) is a copy of the passivized-and-ra ised subject, whic h contains the en -
copy as a subconstituent. ec in (iv) is PRO, with no internal structure. If ec in (iv) is also a 
copy, as Hornstein argues, the explanation is lost. 
b. 	  Si-reflexivization  (Rizzi 1986b) 
NP-movement cannot skip a position coindexed with the moved NP: 
*[NP 1... si 1...t1], where t 1 is the trace of NP 1 and si 1 is a reflexive clitic. This  
unaccusative test for Italian disagnozes NP-m ovement in raising but not in control:  
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
i. * I due candidati 1 si1 risultavano [t 1 poter vicere]. 
   the two candidates to-each-ot her appeared to-be-able to-win 
(The two candidates appeared to  each other to be able to win) 
ii. I due concorrenti 1 si1 sono promessi [di PRO 1 essere leali]. 
the two competitors to-each-other were promised to-be loyal 
The two competitors promised to each other to be loyal 
The problem for Hornstein : If (i) violates the MLC, so  should (ii). Notice that the 
problem persists whether si is taken to spell out the goal or the agent argument. Nor is 
it an artifact of Rizzi's assumpti on that chains contain a single -role (an assumption 
rejected by Hornstein); rather, it is a cons equence of the claim that OC creates a 
chain, subject to the MLC.  
(21) Case Concord 
Floating quantifiers in Icelandic agree in cas e with their local subject, including quirky 
subjects. Sigur Dsson (1991) shows that PRO is no ex ception (notice that case is not 
transmitted from the controller): 
a. 	 Strkarnir vonast til [a PRO vanta ekki alla  sklann]. 
the boys. NOM  hope for to PRO. ACC lack not all. ACC in the school 
The boys hope not to be all absent from school 
b. 	 Strkarnir vonast til [a PR O lei ast ekki llum  skla]. 
the boys. NOM  hope for to PRO. DAT bored not all. DAT in school 
The boys hope not to be all bored in school 
c. 	 Strkarnir vonast til [a PRO vera allra geti  rnnie]. 
the boys. NOM  hope for to PRO. GEN be all. GEN mentioned in the-speech 
The boys hope to be all mentioned in the speech 
Strikingly, no case mismatch is observed in raising construc tions: The quirky case 
determined by the embedded predicate shows up  on the matrix subjec t (ONeil 1997: 109, 
attributed to H. Thrinsson): 
d. 	 Strkarna virast [t vanta ekki alla  sklann]. 
the boys. ACC seem to-lack not all. ACC in the school 
The boys seem not to be all absent from school 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
d. John fervently believes (that) theres a man here. 
e. Its fervently believed ??(that) theres a man here. 
 Problems : i) The facts are dubious. There is no general prohibition against that-deletion 
 under passives: 
f. I was told (that) Mary would come. 
ii) The account is ad-hoc; what is the ra tionale behind the alleged dependence of  
C-incorporation on passive? iii) Most serious ly  Hornsteins solution excludes not only 
(c) but also (a). 
(8) Sideward Movement from Complements 
Hornstein appeals to sideward movement in order to account for OC  into adjuncts. Yet 
nothing in the mechanism of sideward movement it self dictates that it must take place from 
adjuncts. Why dont we find sideward  movement from complements? 
a. * Johns 1 friends prefer [t 1 to behave himself]. 
b. * We urged Johns 1 friends [t 1 to talk about himself]. 
c. * John 1 persuaded friends of t 1 [t1 to nominate himself]. 
Without a constraint to rule out (a-c), neither the claim cont rol is raising nor the claim  
sideward movement is possible can be held  to be simpler than their alternatives. 
(9) Reflexive verbs 
Movement from one -position to another may be clause-internal. Hornstein proposes to 
analyse reflexive verbs this way (a-b). The que stion immediately arises  how to block this 
derivation in the much mo re typical case (c-d). 
a. Mary washed. 
b. [IP Mary 1 [past [ VP t1 [wash t 1 ]]]]. 
c. Mary saw  Mary saw herself 
d. * [IP Mary 1 [past [ VP t1 [saw t 1 ]]]].
 Hornstein : see obligatorily assigns accusative case, wash  only optionally. Therefore, in 
(d) there are two case features (Nom. and Acc.), one of which remains unchecked.   
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(23) Metonymical shift  (adapted from Postal 2002) 
Shifting from a metonym to its reference is constrained when they are linked by 
pronominal or anaphoric coreference. Some  shifts are possible, others are not: 
a. John is not parked on 26th S t .	  ( John=Johns car) 
b. John 1 hoped he 1 is not parked on 26th St. 	 (he=Johns car) 
c. John 1 didnt intend PRO 1 to be parked on 26th St. (PRO=Johns car) 
d. Microsoft went up. 	 (Microsoft =Microsofts stocks price) 
e. 	* Microsoft 1 claimed that it 1 would go up. (it =Microsofts stocks price) 
f. 	* Microsoft 1 plans PRO 1 to go up. (PRO=Microsofts stocks price) 
Although the nature of these semantic constraint s is obscure, they are clearly characteristic 
of pronominal/anaphoric coreference. Consider also: 
g. Poulain is tastier than baguettes. 
h. 	* Poulain 1 said that he 1 is tastier than baguettes. 
i. 	* Poulain 1 aspired PRO 1 to be tastier than baguettes. 
Raising constructions are not subject to these constraints: 
j. Microsoft 1 seems/is likely t 1 to have gone up. 
k. Poulain 1 seems/is likely t 1 to be tastier than baguettes. 
If OC reduces to raising, then the contrast between (f,i ) and (j,k) is mysterious.  
Conclusion 
	On a conservative count, there are 16 empirical arguments against assimilating OC to raising 
and in favor of keeping them apart. 
	On the other hand, there is not a single compelling empirical argument ( wanna-contraction 
notwithstanding) in favor of assimilating OC to raising. 
	Given this state of affairs, Hornsteins repeated  appeals to conceptual considerations  more 
simplicity, less redundancy, etc.  are prematur e. Occams razor only decides between 
empirically comparable theories. 
	Until further notice, PRO exists. 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Scenario : "The unfortunate" is a war hero w ho suffers from amnesia and remembers 
nothing of his wartime experiences. Suppose th is person sees a TV program describing his 
own exploits, and is impressed with the courage exhibited by that person, who he does not 
know is himself. The unfortunate comes to belie ve that this hero wi ll get a medal. Under 
this scenario, (a) is true but (b) is false: 
a. The unfortunate expects that he will get a medal. de se  or de re 
b. The unfortunate expects to get a medal. only de se
 Hornstein : The control chain in (c) creates a "complex monadic predicate", as in (d).
 This explains de se  readings. 
c. John 1 [VP t1 hopes [ IP t1 to [ VP t1 leave]]]. 
d. x.x hopes x leave 
Reply : No, it does not. The -abstract in (d) simply represents  variable binding, but variable 
binding cannot distinguish de se  from de re  readings (Chierchia 1990, Higginbotham 1992). 
Thus, (d) is also part of the interpretation of (e), but  unlike (c), (e) does support a de re 
reading. 
e. Everyone 1 hopes that he 1 will leave. de se or de re 
(17) Wanna-Contraction 
a. Who do you want PRO to / wanna see t wh? 
b. Johns going t NP to / gonna leave. 
c. * Who do you want t wh to / *wanna vanish?
 Hornstein : PRO in (a) is like caseless  NP-trace in (b) and unlike wh-trace in (c) w.r.t.  
 licensing wanna-contraction. 
Reply : wanna-contraction cannot be keyed to lack  of case because there is ample 
crosslinguistic evidence that PRO does bear case (case concor d in Russian, Icelandic, 
Hungarian, Greek, Romanian). But you know what  suppose Hornstein is right: The 
raising analysis of OC accounts for the highl y idiosyncratic, language-specific construction 
of wanna-contraction (maybe PRO lacks case only in  English). What follows from that? 
Very little. 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
1982, Manzini 1983, Bouchard 1984, Koster  1984, Lebeaux 1984, Borer 1989, Clark 1990, 
Sag &amp; Pollard 1991, Williams 1992, Petter 1998, Landau 2000. 
Claim : Nothing more than (4) is needed in order to set up an alternative to Hornsteins  
theory, which is empirically superior. And I mean  smashingly  superior. 
Obligatory Control 
(5) A conceptual issue: - roles or features? 
Is (2a) a sensible alternative to  (1d)? Whether or not one thinks -roles are empirically 
defensible, there is little doubt that they are theoretical ly intelligible. -roles are clearly 
relations between predicates and arguments. Whet her a given DP is Theme or Experiencer 
is entirely context-dependent. By contrast, features like [+plural ] are intrinsic and non-
relational. If the feature [+Experiencer] does not reside intrinsically in the subject of love, 
how can it check its counterpart on that verb? 
Furthermore, do we want to say that sel ectional violations cras h the derivation just 
like any other feature mismatch? What then  about the old asymme try between (6a-b)? 
(6) a. # Sincerity fears the boy. 
b. * Children fears sincerity. 
(7) Control across passive
 Fact 1 : Object control verbs can passivize. 
a. Mary 1 was persuaded t 1 [IP t1 to leave]. 
 Fact 2 : ECM verbs can passivize. 
b. John 1 was expected [ IP t1 to [ VP t1 win the game]]. 
Puzzle: Why cant subject control verbs passivize?
 c. * John 1 was hoped [ IP t1 to [ VP t1 win the game]]. 
          [i.e., it was hoped that John would win the game] 
(c) is structurally equivalent to (b): raising from a -position to a non- -position. Nothing in 
Hornstein (1999) blocks this option. 
Hornstein (2000) (reply to Brody 1999) : i) Control complements are CPs, ECM 
complements are IPs; ii) CPs blocks subject ex traction, unless C incorpor ates to the matrix 
predicate; iii) passive  verbs resist C-incorporation. Evidence: 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Comrie 1984, Melvold 1985, Farkas 1988, Sa g &amp; Pollard 1991, Petter 1998, Landau 2000, 
Wurmbrand 2001). Hornstein ignor es all that literature.  
All and all, a theory that does not derive the MDP is better off than one that does. 
Non-obligatory control 
(13) Delimiting NOC environments
 Hornstein : NOC is the elsewhere case; wh enever OC fails, NOC obtains.  
OC fails whenever the infi nitival subject cannot raise  island environments. 
A pro subject is inserted as a last resort, explaining the pronomina l properties of the  
infinitival subject in NOC. Hornstein discusses three environments: 
a. Sentential subject 
It was believed that [ pro shaving] was important.   
b. Extraposition 
It is impossible [pro to win at roulette]. 
c. Wh-complements 
John told Sam [how pro to hold oneself erect at a royal ball]. 
(14) Claim : Hornstein's NOC category is both too restrictive and too permissive. 
a. Extraposition under psychological predicates falls under OC (Landau 2001): 
i) * John 1 said that it disturbed Sue [PRO 1 to make a full of himself in public]. 
(Grinder (1970) 
b. Contrary to common belief, wh-complements fall under OC (Landau 2000): 
i. 	 John said that Mary asked [ how PRO to feed herself/*himself].  
       (Mohanan 1985) 
ii. John 1 wondered [who PRO to introduce his 1 fiance/*him 1 to]. 
iii. John 1 asked [how PRO to talk to Mary/*him 1 about oneself]. 
Note : This is particularly damaging to Horn stein's theory. Either he abandons the 
claim that NOC obtains in is lands (losing his account for (13a,b)), or he denies the 
islandhood of wh-complements.  
c. Initial adjuncts fall under NOC, c ontrary to Hornstein's prediction: 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 Problems : i) If the case feature on wash  is optional  why is th e reflexive derivation 
obligatory ? What rules out an interpretati on with indefinite object drop ( Mary washed 
pro)? ii) What's the independent criterion that de termines whether the verbal case feature is 
obligatory or not? One can only imagine one su ch criterion  whether the verb allows 
indefinite object drop or not . Hence, Hornstein predicts: 
e. 	 If a transitive verb allows object drop, it should license a reflexive reading. 
(because its case feature is optional, a nd nothing rules out a derivation like (a)). 
(e) is massively disconfirmed: John ate/watched/cursed/taugh t/preached/drew/cleaned. 
Many verbs allow (discour se-sensitive) object drop without being reflexive. 
 More generally : It is up to the lexicon, not syntax, to derive reflexive verbs. The class of 
these verbs is notoriously small and idiosyncratic (mostly referring to bodily actions), 
varying across languages (Reinhart 1997). The mechanism of movement from one 
-position to another is not only unsupported, but in fact undermined by reflexive verbs. 
(10) Implicit control 
The controller in OC may be implicit, th at is, lexically saturated but syntactically 
unexpressed. Typically, we find implicit dativ e or agent (of passive) controllers. The 
phenomenon is well-documented, its scope being subject to lexical and parametric variation 
(see Kimball 1971, Bresnan 1982, Epstein 1984, Williams 1985, 1987, Manzini 1986, Rizzi 1986a, Brody &amp; Manzini 1987, Roeper 1987, Lasnik 1988, Chierchia 1989, Clark 1990, 
Higginbotham 1999, Landau 2000). 
a. John said/shouted (to the visitors) to return later. 
b. Il generale ha ordinato  (ai soldati) di partire. 
the general has ordered (to-the soldiers) to-leave 
The general ordered (to the soldiers) to leave. [Italian; Rizzi 1986a] 
c. Gil himlic (le-Rina) lirot rofe. 
Gil recommended (to Rina) to-see doctor 
Gil recommended (to-Rina) to  see a doctor [Hebrew] 
(11) Hornstein is committed to the following conclusions: 
a. 	 All controllers are syntac tic (since they are raised ). 
 implicit controller is pro or NP-trace. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Raising vs. Control 
Rosenbaum's (1967) discovery that raising and c ontrol constructions are fundamentally distinct, 
although superficially similar, has been a majo r achievement of genera tive grammar. Throughout 
the years, it has yielded a host of empirical contrasts. Hornst ein's analysis trivializes the 
distinction (a chain with one or two -positions), and addresses non e of these contrasts (except 
one). This complete disregard for well-known fact s is perhaps the most disturbing feature of 
Hornstein's paper. 
(18) What Hornstein does expl ain: expletive &amp; idiom chunks 
a. 	 The shit seems to have hit the fan.  
b. * The shit expects to hit the fan. 
c. 	 There seems/*expects to be a man in the garden.  
Hornstein : Expletives/idiom chunks cannot check the external -roles of the matrix  
verb. We should also grant him an account of Mays (1985) observation:  
d. 	 Someone from NY is likely to win the lottery. ambiguous 
e. 	 Someone from NY is eager to win the lottery. unambiguous
 All -roles must be expressed at LF  (only the higher copy bears both -features). 
(19)	 Complementizers 
Raising complements are IPs, cont rol complements are CPs. Hence: 
A universal generalization 
Control complements may be introduced by complementizers;  
Raising complements are never introduced by complementizers.  
Hebrew  (Landau 2002) 
a. 	 Rina xadla (me-)leacben et Gil. 
Rina stopped (from -)to-irritate acc. Gil 
Rina stopped irritating Gil 
b. 	 Ha-muzika ha-roeet xadla (*me-)leacben et Gil. 
the-music the-noisy stopped (*from-)to-irritate acc. Gil 
The loud music stopped irritating Gil 
10</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Phrase Structure (cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln3ho_kayne_94/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>A-Movement (cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln6a_reconstruct/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Note : We must insert the entire which pictures of John  in one step. In particular, 
John cannot be inserted after  A-bar movement, or we lose the condition C 
violation. A reasonable way to impose this is by cyclicity. 
Thereofore, the distinction in A- and A-bar reconstruction (the answer to (14i-iii)) 
boils down to: Lexical insertion of argum ents may apply at any position in an A-
chain, but at the lowest  position in an A-bar ch ain. Why? Because A-bar 
movement cannot apply to pro. WHY? 
Given this, no distinction in the actua l process of recons truction is needed 
between A- and A-bar chains, or ana phors and names  a desireable result. 
(18)	 An intricate prediction
 a. 	 [DP  pron 1  name 2 ]3  QP 1  t 3  pron 2  t 3  
b. * [DP  pron 1  name 2 ]3  pron 2  t 3  QP 1  t 3  
In (a), t 3 provides a consistent LF position  pron 1 is bound and name 2 is free. By 
contrast, in (b) there is no consiste nt LF position: In the surface position, pron 1 is 
 unbound; in t 3, name 2 is bound and pron 1 is unbound; in t 3, name 2 is again bound. 
c. 	 Her 1 picture of Sting 2 seemed to every fan 1 to be seen by him 2 to be 
a real intrusion. 
d. 	 * Her 1 picture of Sting 2 seemed to him 2 to be seen by every fan 1 to be 
a real accomplishment.  
In deriving (c), we first move pro to the intermediate position, past the pronoun 
him; only then do we insert her picture of Sting   still within the c-ommand 
 domain of every fan  but already outside th e c-command domain of him. 
(19) 	 Explaining the bi g WHY (brief version) 
The crucial distinction wa s between A-movement of pro (possible) and A-bar 
movement of pro (impossible). In the rest of the paper, Lebeaux derives this result 
from the Stray Affix Filter (SAF), whic h is an everywhere negative condition 
(like condition C). The reasoning is as follo ws. Case features are affixes, assigned 
to DPs at case positions. pro is caseless. While A-movement may move the 
caseless pro up the tree, the moment it reaches a case position, where the case 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Actually, in order to rule out Strong Crossover in (b) as a violation of condition C, it 
is necessary to force QR before reconstruction of the pronoun. Its unclear why this 
should be so. 
(11)	 Lebeaux doesnt consider Condition B, but the facts are the same. The following 
example, from Chomsky (1995), shows th at reconstruction cant undo a condition B
 violation: 
a. * John 1 expected him 1 to seem to me t 1 to be intelligent. 
(12) 	 The argument from psych verbs is based on the false idea that they necessarily
 involve reconstruction. 
a. * Himself 1 pleases John 1. 
b. 	 Each others 1 parents please the two boys 1. 
Lebeaux argues that (b) must involve rec onstruction of the subject to a position lower 
than the experiencer. This must be also avai lable in (a); the fact that the latter is still 
bad proves that the SS-violation of c ondition C cannot be undone by reconstruction 
(hence, Condition C applies everywhere). 
But the assumption that (b) must involve reconstruction is  false; in fact, 
backward binding tells us nothing about strcuture, and falls outside sentence grammar 
(involving logophoricity ; see my first handout). Without this assumption, it may well 
be that condition C is violat ed only at LF in (a), a nd doesnt apply everywhere. 
Comparison with A-bar reconstruction 
(13) 	 A-bar reconstruction 
Condition A and variable binding (the pos itive conditions) can be satisfied by any 
position in the chain. 
a. John wondered [ [which picture of himself 1]2 Bill 1 said [ t2 that Steve liked t 2 ]]]? 
b. [Which of his 1 parents] 2 did Freud say [t 2 that a man 1 loved best t2 ]? 
Condition C (the negative condition) is violated if any chain position violates it. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
A second argument 
(4) 	 Anaphors inside moved NPs can be bound from at their base position.
 a. 	 Each others 1 presents please the two children 1. 
b. 	 Each others 1 presents are expected t 1 to please the two children 1. 
c. ?* The presents 2 are expected by each others 1 parents t 2 to please the two boys 1. 
(a) shows that psych-verbs allow backward  binding within the same clause. (b) shows 
that A-reconstruction can feed binding. (c) shows, like (3), that long QR cannot place 
the two boys  in a position high enough to bind the re ciprocal in the matrix clause.    
(5) 	 Same with variable binding : 
a. 	 His 1 mother pleases every man 1. 
b. 	 [His 1 mother] 2 seems t 2 to please every man 1. 
c. * Mary 2 seems to his 1 mother t 2 to please every man 1. 
A third (Lebeauxs fourth) argument 
(6) 	 Long distance control by deeply embedded arguments. 
a. 	 [PRO 1 seeing Claire] 2 seems t 2 to be expected t 2 to make Mark 1 happy. 
b. 	 [PRO 1 seeing Claire] 2 made Mark 1 happy. 
The idea is that PRO can only be controlled  by a clausemate of the gerund. But is it 
so? Lebeaux (1984) himself gave examples lik e (c), and (d) shows that PRO in this 
position can be controlled from discourse.  
c. 	 [PRO 1 hiding the money] showed that Mark 1 was guilty. 
d. 	 Mary 1 was disappointed. [PRO 1 helping her best friend] wasnt appreciated. 
Lebeaux cites another argument based on linked readings of two arbitrar y PROs. Overall, the 
case for A-reconstruction is compelling.  
(7) 	 Crucially, A-reconstruction is optional . If it were obligatory, (a) would violate both 
conditions A and C at LF. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Lebeauxs reasoning will follow (i). 
Late insertion of lexical arguments 
The logic of the problem is similar to that of the argument/adjunct asymmetry in 
reconstruction, discussed by Lebeaux (1988, 1991). 
(15) a. * Whose claim that John 1 stole the money did he 1 reject? 
b. Whose claim that John 1 had heard before did he 1 reject? 
The argument clause in (a) must be merged at the base position, so the name it contains is 
bound by the pronoun. The adjunct clause in (b) can be merged after wh-movement, so 
the name it contains is never bound.  
Lebeauxs intuition is that just like late merg er of adjuncts explains their invisibility to 
condition C in A-bar chains (optional reconstr uction), so can late merger of lexical 
arguments explain their invisibili ty to condition C in A-chains. 
If the argument is late inserted  what moves in an A-chain? pro (phi-features + index). 
(16) Derivation 
a. e seems to himself 1 pro 1 to like cheese. A-movement 
 b. pro 1 seems to himself 1 t1 to like cheese. Lexical insertion  
 c. John 1 seems to himself 1 t1 to like cheese. 
Note : Lexical insertion may, but need not, a pply late. To obtain binding of the 
base position in a chain, early merger must be chosen. 
(17) Crucially, late lexical insertion of  arguments is barred in A-bar chains. 
a. he1 likes pro. Lexical insertion  
 b. he1 likes which pictures of John 1. Condition C  
c. * he 1 likes which pictures of John 1. A-bar movement  
d. * Which pictures of John 1 does he 1 like? 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
a. 	 John 1 seems to himself 1 t1 to be a genius. 
A puzzle : Why is A-bar reconstruc tion obligatory? In fact, why do the two types of 
reconstruction differ in this regard? 
b. * Which remarks about Bill 1 did he 1 ignore?
 cf. c. Which remarks about him 1 did Bill 1 ignore?
(8) 	 At this stage, Lebeaux laboriously shows that abandoning the Single Tree Condition 
overgenerates non-existing readings. This could consist in ei ther letting some
 interpretive conditions apply at one level (e.g., SS) and othe rs at another level (e.g., 
LF); or in complicating th e definition of c-command to allow binding through traces. 
Either option is not  restrictive enough.  
(9) 	 The following conditions/ processes all apply at LF: 
a. 	 Fixing the relative scope of quantifiers. 
b. 	 Variable binding. 
c. 	 Binding condition A. 
d. 	 Idiom interpretation. 
By contrast, negative conditions (binding B and C) apply everywhere. 
Condition C applies everywhere 
(If any stage in the derivation of a sentence S violates condition C, S is ungrammatical). 
(10) 	 Evidence : Contexts where A-re construction  shown to exist  could undo the 
configuration which violates condit ion C, in fact remain ungrammatical. 
a. * He 1 seems to Johns 1 mother t 1 to be expected t 1 to win. 
Possible LF: e seems to Johns 1 mother e to be expected he 1 to win. 
b. * He 1 seems to every man 1 t1 to be quite wonderful. 
Possible LF: e seems to every man 1 he1 to be quite wonderful. 
No WCO c. [His 1 mother] 2 seems to every man 1 t2 to be quite wonderful. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
affix is inserted, lexical insertion must  apply, to avoid a violation of SAF. 
Consequently, A-bar movement (always proceeding from a case position) will 
already apply to a lexically filled DP. 
(20) 	 Restating the problems in  Copy Theory (A-chains only) 
a. 	 For scope, only one position in a chain is visible at LF: 
  Q P 1  t 1  [ IP  t 1  QP 2 ] 
Possibe : QP 2 &gt;&gt; QP 1 [caveat: unless QP 1 is a strong quantifier] 
b. 	 For condition A and variable bind ing, only one position in a chain is 
visible at LF: 
[DP anaphor 1/bound variable 1 ]2  t 2  DP 1/QP 1  t 2 
Consequence: (a) and (b) together  produce the scope trapping effect: 
i. 	 Two women 1 seem to each other 1 t1 to be expected t 1 to dance with
  every senator. unambiguous 
c. 	 For condition B, all positions are visible at LF. 
i. * John 1 expected [him 1 to seem to me [t 1 to be intelligent]]. 
ii. * John 1 seems to me [t 1 to be expected [t 1 to like him 1]. 
iii. * He 1 was expected [t 1 to seem to him 1 [t1 to be intelligent]]. 
Condition B is violated by the top position of the pronoun in (i), the base 
position of the binder in (ii) and the intermediate position of the binder in (iii). 
d. 	 For condition C, only the t op position is visible at LF. 
i. [Johns 1 mother] 2 seemed to him 1 [t2 to like rock music]. 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
A-reconstruction  problems and mysteries 
Idan Landau 
(1) Two women 1 seem t 1 to be expected t 1 to dance with every senator. ambiguous 
a. 	1st reading: There are two women who are expect ed to dance with every senator. 
b. 	2nd reading: It is expected that every senato r will dance with (possibly different) 
      two women. 
In principle, you could imagine two ways to obtain inverse scope in  (b): Either lower 
two women (reconstruction) or raise every senator . In practice, only the first option 
exists (perhaps because QR is clause-bound). How do we know? 
(2) The trapping effect
 Two women 1 seem to each other 1 t1 to be expected t 1 to dance with every senator. 
Unlike (1), this sentences is unambiguous   only reading (1a) exists. 
If reconstruction is the only option, we understand this  fact. Reconstruction places 
two women in its base position (only when two quantifiers are clausemates can they 
take ambiguous scope). That position is too low to bind the reciprocal in the matrix 
clause. If QR could raise every senator above two women, we should have been able 
to get the inverse scope w ithout sacrificing binding.  
 Condition A and scope relations are estab lished at a single level (otherwise, we 
could satisfy inverse scope at LF and bindi ng at SS in the example above). This is 
Lebeauxs Single Tree Condition  (there is just one interpretive interface). 
(3) More evidence against long QR 
Mary seems to two women t 1 to be expected t 1 to dance with every senator. 
Unambiguous : Only 2x &gt;&gt;  y. 
The lack of inverse scope shows that it is  in virtue of the A-chain in (1) that every 
senator  obtains wider scope than two women . Since two women does not form a chain 
in the above example, inverse scope is not observed. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
c. * Which remarks about Bill 1 did he 1 ignore? 
d. * [Whose hurting John 1]2 did he 1 persuade Bill of t 2? 
 A-reconstruction: reminder 
As in A-bar chains, Condition A and variable binding can be satisfied by any 
position in the A-chain. 
e. 	 [Each others 1 parents] 2 are expected t 2 to seem to the boys 1 t2 to 
  be quite wonderful. 
f. 	 [Pictures of his 1 father in his youth] 2 are known t 2 to seem to every man 1 t2 to
  be quite wonderful. 
However, unlike A-bar chains, the low (rec onstructed) position in A-chains does not 
violate condition C. 
g. 	 John 1 seems to himself 1 t1 to like cheese. 
h. 	 [Johns 1 mother] 2 seems to him 1 t2 to be wonderful. 
(14) 	 Stating the puzzle 
We have incontrovertible evidence that A-reconstruction exists. We also have such 
evidence that Condition C does not tolera te a bound R-expression in any position in 
A-bar chains. Why, then, does it tolerate this in A-chains? 
A-bar chain: (13c) 
a. * Which remarks about Bill 1 did he 1 ignore which remarks about Bill 1? 
 A-chain: (13f)
 b. 	 Johns 1 mother seems to him 1 Johns 1 mother  to be wonderful. 
Note : I use the copy notation instead of Le beauxs derivational notation. There is 
reason to do that, but for now, we can state the problem in 3 different ways; notice 
that each formulation points to a different type of answer.  
i) Why are early violations of condition C le thal in A-bar chains but not in A-chains? 
ii) Why is reconstruction (lowering) obligat ory in A-bar chains but not in A-chains? 
iii) Why are low copies necessarily visible in A-bar chains but not in A-chains? 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction: &#8220;The Case for Syntax&#8221; (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln1psych_intro/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 
(17)  Pesetskys explanation
 There is more s tructure than m eets th e eye. An affixal CAUS null morphem e 
(which is present in every causative psych construction) m ust raise to th e root.  In 
a cascad e configuration , the in tervening prepo sition (head ing the T /SM PP ) 
blocks th is movem ent. The resultin g struc ture e ither viola tes the Stray Aff ix Filter  
or the Head Movem ent Constraint. 
 
Note : The s yntax is m otivated  by sem antics (of causatives), but not dictated by it. 
Importantly,  the ana lysis incorpo rates syntactic constraints (S AF, HMC) that are  
irreducible to sem antics.  
 
Class II Predicates in Romance Causatives 
 
(18) Belletti &amp; Rizzi (1988) noted that class II predicates cannot be em bedded under 
causative verbs. 
 
a.    * Questo lo ha fatto preoccupare/c omm uovere/attrarre ancora pi Mario.   
 this him  has m ade worry/move/attract even m ore to Mario  
 This m ade Mario worry/m ove/attract him  even more 
b. Questo lo ha fatto apprezzare/tem ere/amm irare ancora pi Mario.   
 this him  has m ade estim ate/fear/adm ire even m ore to Mario  
 This m ade Mario e stimate/fea r/adm ire him even m ore 
 
B&amp;Rs analysis was syntactic and quite innovative (even if ultim ately false); 
well r eturn to it in the c hapter on ps ych verbs, and discuss its m erits and faults. 
 
(19) Bouchard : The causee must be a co ntrollable Substantive (to have the potential 
to contro l the course of  events desc ribed by the inf initiva l VP). Since the subject 
of class II v erbs as in (1 8a) is a Con cept, th e result is b ad. 
 
Predic tion: i) agentive class II should be fine in  caustives; thats correct, but also 
predicted under B&amp;Rs analysis. 
 
 
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 
The Case for Syntax 
 
Idan Landau 
 
 
(1) Syntax is a thankless trade; the m an on the stree t (and som e sem anticists , for that 
matter) think it is  trivial (at best) or superfluous (at worst). After all, language is 
about sound and m eaning; why m ake a bi g fuss about som ething which is neither 
sound nor meaning?  Why study structure by itself?   
 
 In short, if youre going to be desp ised for wasting your tim e anyway, why not 
choose something m ore lucrative? (m ake useless m oney, not useless theories).  
 
 [ Warning: If you are already deeply confus ed, dont proceed beyond this point]  
 
(2) The case for syntax is twofold:  i) We have purely syntactic intuition s about 
sentences; ii) Som e phenom ena (not given in advance!) call for syntactic 
explanations  (phonology &amp; sem antics cant do all the work).  
 
Syntactic intuitions : Green ideas a nd all that 
 
(3) a. Colorless g reen ideas sleep furiously.  
 b.      * Furiously sleep ideas green colorless. 
 
 What exactly does this p air teach us ? 
 
Syntactic explanations 
 
Some phenom ena walk like sem antics and ta lk lik e sem antics   bu t they a re syntax. 
Inuitions about the right theo ry are very different from  intuitions about sentences. The 
latter are  just what they  are   there is littl e roo m to play with them . The form er are a 
product of subjective bias and pr eference; there is every reason to put them  to test. Well 
have a close look at one em pirical dom ain where sem antic intuitions proved m isleading, 
and where syntactic accounts proved superior. 
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
(13) Adjunct PPs can be seperated from th e predicate in pseudocleft, argum ent PPs  
cannot:  
 
 a. What John was during the visit was angry.  adjunct PP  
 b.     * W hat John was at the governm ent was angry.  argument PP  
 
Conclusion : Bouchards undefined notion of ad junct is probably based on som e 
semantic intuition. The point is that this intu ition plays no explanat ory role in actual 
analyses, and in fact is quite m isleading. 
 
(14) Whats the evidence for (9b)? Clearly the relev ant PPs are unlike stand ard agent-
orien ted m odifiers, s ince they allow inanim ate subjects. Compare (6 ) with (b-d). 
 
 a. Mary/*the rain deliberately washed the front stairs. 
 b. This book is about the future .  
 c. This book is concerned with the trip  to Beijing . 
 d. All the ev idence poin ts at the government . 
  
(15) Bouchards prediction : The T/SM restriction shoul d disappear in agentive 
contexts. The prediction is fals e (contra Bouchards data). 
 
 a.    * W e all tried to sati sfy Bill with  his trip to B eijing. 
 b.    * Bill maliciously w orried Mary about her future. 
 c.    * The weather m an deliberatel y frightens people of  another tornado. 
 
 This fact alone falsifies Bouchards proposal. 
 
(16) Conclusion : Semantic intuitions alone do not guarantee any insight into syntactic 
phenom ena. Pesetsky him self took t rouble to sh ow that the T/SM restriction is not 
semantic. He also cited analogous facts from suggestive predicates (due to 
Higgins 1973): 
 
 a. John was angry at the guests. 
 b. Johns tone was angry (*at the guests). 
 c. John was nervous about the exam . 
 d. Johns behavior was nervous (*about the exam ). 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 
a. John deliberately disgusted/annoyed/surprised Mary. 
b.      * Johns deliberate dis gust/annoyance/surp rise of Mary. 
 
(30) Alterna tives: Appeal to hidden structure, that  is subject to well-understood 
constraints on word-form ation. Pesets ky (1995) appealed to Myers 
generalization, which bans affixation to zero-derived words (recall that CAUS is  
null). McGinnis (2000), working in Di stributed Morphology, assumed that 
causative psych predicates m ust be form ed with the v erbalizer light v , hence 
cannot be n ominalized. At any rate,  such accou nts attem pt to apply some known  
property of syntax/m orphology to the dom ain of psych verbs, and derive the 
various effects without direct re course to sem antic notions.  
 
Synthetic compounds 
 
(31) Grim shaw (1990) observed that the "the me" of c lass I verbs can occur as the non-
head of a synthetic compound, but th at of class II verbs cannot: 
 
a. a god-fearing m an, a fun-loving teenager 
b.       *a m an-frightenin g god, *a parent-appalling exploit 
 
Grim shaws accoun t: (i) the argument in the co mpound must be them atically 
lower than the argum ent lef t outs ide; (ii) the non-experiencer argum ent in both 
classes I and  II is a them e, which is them atically lower than the experiencer.  
 
Evidence for (i) : On the assum ption that Goal is h igher than T heme, we explain : 
  
 c. gift-giving to childre n / *child-giving of gifts 
 
Critique of Grimshaw  
 
(32) (31-ii) is no longer tenable. Them e is  a cover term  for Causer in class II and 
Target/Subject Matter in cl ass I (see Pesetsky 1995, am ong others). The actual 
hierarchy is: Causer&gt;&gt;E xperiencer&gt;&gt;T/SM.  
 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
(8) Bouchard (1995)  
 
 a. Concept : an entity viewe d extern ally/neutra lly. 
 b. Substantive : an entity viewed inte rnally, as a par ticipant in a n event. 
 c. I(nten tional)-subjec t: a conscious/intentional Substantive. 
 
Bouchard argues that the gramm ar m akes direct ref erence, and in numerous 
construc tions, to these  sem antic catego ries. The standard am biguity of class II 
construction s is stated as  a Concept/I-subjec t con trast in the s ubjects in terpretation: 
 
 d. Mary annoy ed Bill. 
  [deliberately, or sim ply in virtue of her existence) 
 
(9) Bouchards explanation fo r the T/S M restric tion 
 
 a. The PPs in (6)/(7 ) are ad juncts, no t argum ents (not an integral part of the 
construction). 
 b. These adjuncts m ust be controlled  by a sufficiently ag entive subject. 
 c. The subject is a Concept in (6), an  I-subjec t in (7 ), hence the contrast.  
 
Critique of Bouchard 
 
(10) Theoretically, it is not clear that the novel categorie s in (8) are delivering any 
benefit that the sim pler dichotom y  agentive/nonagentive  doesnt already 
deliver. W e know that m any grammatical  processes are sensitive to that 
dichotom y; why restate it (in vaguer term s)? 
(11) Whats the evidence fo r (9a)? Optionali ty is n ot a cr iterion for adjuncts, sin ce 
many argum ents are optional (e.g., John wrote (a letter)  to Mary ). Under two 
relevant tests, som e T/SM PPs be have as argum ents, not adjuncts. 
(12) Adjunct PPs allow local pronom inal binding, argum ent PPs dont. 
 
 a. John 1 put the tag on him self1/*him 1.     argument PP   
 b. John 1 sensed a beetle on him 1/ ?? h imself1.  adjunct PP  
 
   cf. c. Bill 1 was satisfied with h imself1/*him 1.    
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 c. Johns/* the events em barras sment/hum iliation o f Mary. 
 d. The clowns/*m ovies (constant) amus ement/enterta inment of the child ren. 
 
However, (c,d) are not typical; m ost cla ss II nom inaliz ation s are neve r eve ntive, 
regardless of agen tivity (Iwata 1995). 
 
 e. * Johns d eliberate amazem ent/depression /pleasure/deligh t/disgust/in terest of Mary.  
 
Iwatas (1995) account 
 
(24) Class II predicates ar e causatives, but their causa tive com pone nt is weak  
 (non-salient):   
 [CA USER ([X],INCH [BE ([Y],[ AT MENTAL-STATE ([AT t Z])])]])]  
 X: Causer, Y: Experiencer, Z: Targ et/Subject Matter  
 
So, The noise irritated Mary  is represented at Concep tual Structure roughly as: 
The noise (nonsaliently) caused the becom ing of the state of Marys being at the 
mental state of irritation.  
 
(25) Evidence : Adverbia l modification ta rgets the r esultant state, not the causing event. 
 
 a. This rather annoyed/ disappointed/impressed Mary. 
      b.     Mary was rather annoyed/disappointed/impressed. 
  
Note : More is going on, since m ost accom plishm ent verbs with gradab le resultant 
states are in compatible with rather : 
 
 b.      * W e rather clean ed/filled the r oom. 
 c.   The room  was rather clean/full. 
 
Psych verbs  and adjectives share so me other sem antic feature, unrelated  to low 
salience cau sation , which is  not captured by Iwata. 
 
 Second, Iwata notes that m anner adverbs take on a degree reading with class II: 
 
 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
(33) The assum ption that Goal is higher than Them e is conten tious (see Larson 1988, 
Baker 1997). Baker also notes a lethal f act for Grim shaw  goal-com pounds are 
impossible even in the absence of (the  optional) them e, as in (a).   
 
 a.        *child-readi ng, *spy-telling, *friend-writing 
  
Baker (1997) suggested that the true gene ralization underlying these facts is quite 
simple: Prep osition s cannot occur in side com pounds; see (b).  
 
 b.        *charity-(on)-d epending, *strange r-(in)-confiding 
 
So, whether an argum ent requires an overt preposition (33b) or a null one, as the 
goal in (31c)/(33a) it is excluded from  com pounds. Baker points out that thi s 
explana tion natura lly ex tends to (31b)  on the cruc ial ass umption tha t objec t 
experiencers are introduced by a (dat ive-like) null preposition.  
 
Summary 
 
Psych verbs provide an excellent exam ple for the lim its of int uitive linguistics. 
Semantic intuitions can serve as useful probe s into various problem s, but cannot deliver 
explanatory analyses  by them selves; syntax is n ecessary . The underlying assum ption of  
Bouchard, Iwata and  Grim shaw is that con cepts drawn fro m Conceptual Structu re or 
Argum ent Structu re interface directly  with grammatical phenom ena, without the 
mediation of syntactic structure and constr aints; this assum ption is often false.  
 
Caveat  
 
Its not always false. Som e phenom ena that s yntacticians insist on an alysing turn out to 
be sem antic in nature. Again, psych verbs prov ide an excellent exam ple. 
 
Backw ard binding 
 
Postal (1971) argued that th e fact that experiencer obj ects can bind anaphors em bedded 
inside the subject tells us so mething about their special synt ax. This idea was resurrected 
by Herm on (1985), Stowell (1986) and Belletti &amp; Rizzi (1988), and later adopted, in a  
different form, by Pesetsky (1995): 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 
(34) a. Each others suppor ters worried Freud and Jung. 
 b. Each others rem arks annoyed John and Mary. 
 c.      * Each others parents harm ed John and Mary. 
 d.      * Each others te achers insulted John and Mary. 
 
For all the above authors, the required st ructural relation between the experiencer 
and the anap hor is satisfied at som e non-su rface level (D-stru cture or LF). Hence, 
these cases f all under co ndition A, p roperly cons trued.  
            
(35) Subsequent research has challenged the claim  that backward binding falls under 
Condition A, or indeed, that it is even a structural phenom enon (Zribi-Hertz 1989, 
Bouchard 1992, Pollard &amp; Sag 1992, Reinhart &amp; Reuland 1993). 
 
(i) Backward binding is licensed by the cau sative nature of the construction 
rather than its psych properties: 
 
 a. Each others rem arks m ade John and Mary angry. 
 b. Pictures of him self give John the creeps. 
 c. Pictures of each other caus ed John and Mary to start cry ing. 
 d. Each others criticism  forced John and Mary to confront their problem s. 
 
 (ii) C-command plays no role in backwa rd binding  not even at DS or LF  
as can be s een in the following examples: 
                   
 a. The pictu re of hi mself in Newsweek  shattered th e peace of m ind that John  
   had spent the last six m onths trying to restore.  
 b. These nasty stories about hi mself broke Johns resistance.  
 c. These rum ors about him self caught Johns attention.  
        
Conclusion : Backward binding should be classified with logophors , whose 
anteced ent must be a subject of consci ousnes s or a participant whose point of 
view is evaluated in the discourse (see Zribi-H ertz 1989, S ells 1987). It is not a 
purely structural phenom enon, hence does not attest to any speci fic feature in the 
syntax of psych verbs.  
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
The bi zarre w orld of psych verbs 
 
(4)  Belletti &amp; Rizzis (1988) clas sification of psych verbs
 
 a. Class I : Nom inative experien cer, accusative them e. 
  John loves Mary. 
 b. Class II : Nom inative them e, accusative experiencer.   
  The show amused Bill . 
 b. Class III : Nom inative th eme, dative experiencer.   
  The idea appealed to Julie . 
 
(5)  The T/SM Restriction  
 
Pesetsky (1987, 1995) observed that the se mantic roles borne by the them e 
argum ent in class I and  in classes II/III pr edicates a re not identical. In  the firs t 
case, the them e object is in terpreted as  Target of Em otion or Subject Matter 
(T/SM), whereas in the second case the them e subject is  interpreted as a Cause. 
This is why (a) is not contradictory: 
 
 a. The article angered Bill but he wasnt angry at the article. 
 
(6) Surprisingly, the two logically dis tinct arguments cannot be sim ultaneously 
realized ; this is the T /SM restric tion:  
 
 a.    * The ar ticle in the Times angered Bill at the governm ent. 
 b.    * The Chinese d inner satisf ied Bill with h is trip to Beijing . 
 c.    * Som ething Bill h ad said both ered Mary ab out her f uture. 
 d.    * The distant rum bling fri ghtened Mary of another tornado. 
           
(7) Periphrastic causatives are not subject to th is restriction: 
 
 a. The article in the Tim es made Bill angry at the go vernm ent.  
 b.     The Chinese  dinner m ade Bill s atisfied with his trip to Be ijing. 
 c.     Something Bill had s aid made Mary bother abou t her f uture. 
 d.     The distant rum bling m ade Mary fear of another tornado. 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 d. The cavern f rightened Mary horribly. 
  [i.e., The cavern frightened Mary greatly, not in a horrible m anner] 
 
(26) Nom inalization deletes the Causer R role. It is reasonable  to suppose that an 
items deletablility is c losely conn ected with its sa liency the oute r Cause R 
function, which has low saliency  is deleted, while the em bedded em otional 
state, which constitute s the core, is p reserv ed. 
 
Critique of Iw ata  
 
(27) The intuition behind (24) has som ething to it. Many people have noticed that the 
causation involved in class II predicates is  not norm al; it s eems to involve 
immediate perception of a stim ulus, trigge ring th e resu ltant mental state already  
at the beginning of the event.  
  Still, whether the in tuition has any syntactic  force i s far from cl ear. The 
only tests for non-salient causer are the adverbial-te sts in (25). T hese see m 
pretty m uch like tests fo r statives ; yet Iwata can t argu e that class II are statives, 
given that they are compatible with the progressive (e.g., The movie is really 
scaring the childr en). Moreover, adverbial m odificati on of resultant state is found 
with othe r verbs, which crucially are  incom patible with rather: 
 
 a. He rang the bell loudly     (  The bell rang loudly) 
b. He (*rather) rang the bell. 
 
So, the rather-test and the m anner adverb test di verge; which are we to take as 
diagnostic of Cause R? 
 
(28) The greater problem  lies in (26); why should nom inalization ever delete a 
component of the conceptual structure of a predicate?  What is the principled link 
between the m orphosyntactic realization of the predicate and its conceptua l 
structure? Iwatas acco unt, being  purely se mantic, do es no t addres s this important 
question. W ithout such an account, a m ajor st ep in the analysis rem ains arbitrary.  
 
(29) Just as with Bouchards account of the T/S M restriction, Iwata predicts that 
agentive class II nom inalizations should be  OK; but in fact, in m any cases they 
are not, as he him self observed in (2 3e). One can construct minim al pairs: 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 a. Gli ho f atto spaventa re il candi dato per farlo lavorare di pi. 
  I made him frighten the candida te to m ake him  work harder 
 
(20) Problem s: i) The notion controllable Substa ntive is yet a novel notion. It is 
extrem ely hard to define, and involves im aginative capacities quite unlikely to be 
involved in gramm ar; (ii) furtherm ore, to  the extent that this notion makes any 
concrete predictions, examples like th e following (Kayne 2002) refute it. 
 
 a. Ce qui est arriv a fait pe rdre de limportance au fait que  
that which has happened has m ade lose (of the) importance to-the fact that 
Jean aim e Marie.  
  John loves Mary 
What happened m ade the fact that John loves Mary lose im portance 
 
(21) Alterna tive: Causative for mation involves case alternations. In particular, the 
original case of the embedded direct object is suppresse d, and instead it is 
assigned s tructural accu sativ e case b y the m atrix causative v erb. If the case of the 
object experiencer is oblique (involving a null preposition ), this proces s will be 
blocked and the case al ternation f ail.   
 
Causative nominaliz ations of class II predicates 
 
(22) Class II verbs dont have causati ve nom inalizations (Lakoff 1970). 
 
 a. Bills contin ual agitatio n about the exam  was silly. 
 b. Marys constant annoyance about /at/with us got on our nerves. 
 c.      * The exam s continual ag itation of  Bill was silly. 
 d.      * Our constant annoyance of Mary got on our nerves. 
 
(23)  Grim shaw ( 1990) argued that, in fact, class II nom inalizati ons have either the 
result reading or the agentive event reading, but not the non-agentive event 
reading (event reading in volves argum ent projection, result reading doesnt). 
 
 a. The em barrassm ent/hum iliation of  the bystander s. 
b. The am usement/entertainm ent of the children. 
 
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Nonconfigurationality (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ho_nonconf/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Minimalism (cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ho_mplt2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>28</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>A-Movement (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln5a_movement/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Compare Control : 
i. 	 Gianni si impone  [di PRO i fare  il suo dovere] 
Gianni himself compells  to-do the his duty 
Conclusion: A-movement may not apply acr oss a coindexed anaphor: *[NP i ... sii  ti ]. 
Rizzi argued that any parse of this se quence is bound to vi olate either the -criterion (an 
argument with no  -role) or the Chain Condition (two -roles in a chain). The argument 
was taken to show the reality of A-movement. 
Note : Later work restated the generalization without recourse to A-movement. Can you 
think of a possible formulation? 
Raising to Subject 
(19) 	 Raising vs. control : Raising predicates dont impose any thematic restrictions on 
their surface subjects , control predicates do. 
a. 	 John seemed to be a great linguist. 
b. 	 There tended to be  a lot of discussion. 
c. 	 Headway is likely to be made soon. 
d. 	 John wanted to be a great linguist. 
e. * There tried to be a lot of discussion. 
f. * Headway is anxious to be made soon. 
Baltin : Controllers must be animate. 
Note : This is almost true. A few contro l verbs allow inanimate controllers. 
g. 	 The bad news 1 managed [PRO 1 to break our spirit]. 
h. 	 I forced the car 1 [PRO 1 to stop]. 
i. 	 This knife 1 serves [PRO 1 to cut cheese only]. 
(20) 	 Some properties of raising 
a. 	 No complementizer is allowed in a raising complement (in contrast to  
  control complements). 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Conclusion: Rationale clauses can only modify events/states that can be conceived as the 
product of a purposeful causer  which may, but need not, be realiz ed as a grammatical 
argument.  
A-movement and theories of linking 
Baltin points out an important implication between ones views about A-movement and 
ones views about argument li nking (the mapping from lexic on to syntax). If linking is 
maximally simple, syntax must be non-trivial.  Conversely, if linking is more complex, 
syntax can be trivial. 
a. 	 They arrested John. 
b. 	 John was arrested. 
On a maximally simple linking theory, there is just one relevant rule:  
Theme  direct object (Bakers UTAH is very relevant here). The occurrence of John  as 
a subject in (b) must be therefore syntactically  derived  by A-movement. On a more 
complex linking theory, there would be two (context-dependent) rules: theme  direct 
object, theme  subject, operating in the active and the passive contexts, respectively. 
No need would then arise to move John to its subject position in (b)  it would simply 
be base generated there. 
There is no a priori choice between le xicalist and syntactic  approaches. Very 
often, people side with the theo ry that accords with their pr ior notion of how labor ought 
to be divided between syntax and the lexic on. But empirical arguments can be brought to 
bear, and we will see that the movement approach has significant merits to it. 
Passive 
(7)	 Not all passives involve transitive verbs (likewise, not all transitive verbs 
passivize; see Perlmutter &amp; Postal 1984) , nor do they always involve movement: 
a. In de zomer wordt er hier vaak gezwommen. Dutch 
In the summer it is swum here frequently 
b.  stato messo un libro sul tavolo. Italian 
Has been put a book on the table 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
i. Giovanni ne 1 invitera [molti t 1]. transitive 
John of-them will-invite many 
ii. Ne1 arriveranno [molti t 1]. unaccusative
  Of-them will-arrive many 
iii. * [Molti t 1]2 ne1 arriveranno t 2. 
iv. * Ne 1 telefoneranno [molti t 1]. unergative
  Of-them will-telephone many 
Unergative postverbal subjects are VP-adjoined, hence islands for ne-
extraction (contra Baltin, lack of  c-command cant be at stake). 
Unaccusative postverbal subjects are V-complements, allowing ne-
extraction. Its unclear why (iii) is bad  remnant movement should be 
able to reconstruct, and the French counterpart ( en-extraction) is OK. 
(14)	 A lexicalist alternative : Role &amp; Reference Grammar (RRG), [59]/[62]. Baltin
 criticizes these statem ents as unsatisfactory, especially the one about ne-
cliticization, which seem s unconnected to any other grammatical  principle. 
More Evidence for A-movement 
In Japanese, a numeral quantifier must be ad jacent to (in mutual c-command with) the 
noun it modifies (Miyagawa 1989). 
(15) 	 Transitives 
a. 	 Taroo-ga hon-o 3-satu  katta 
Taro NOM book-ACC 3-cl bought 
b. 	 * Gakusei-ga  hon-o 2-ri katta 
student-NOM book 2-cl bought 
c. 	?* Kodomo -ga [kono kagi]-de 2-ri doa-o aketa 
child-NOM this key-by 2-cl door-ACC opened 
A quantifier can only be seperated from a derived  subject (Q-float). 
(16) 	 Passives
 a. 	 Kuruma-ga  doroboo-ni 3-dai  nusum-are-ta. 
car-NOM thief-by 3-cl steal-PASS-Pst 
b. 	 Kinoo, gakusei -ga [ano otoko]-ni 2-ri koros-are-ta. 
yesterday student-NOM that man-by  2-cl kill-PASS-Pst 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
d. Nominative subjects of transitive verbs. 
e. Nominative subjects of unergatives. 
f. Nominative subjects of adjectival passives. 
This partition is neatly captur ed by the generalization that only deep object  may 
shift to genitive under negation. Baltin points out that under a lexicalist theory, 
both the subjects of verbal  and adjectival passives are deep subjects, hence no 
contrast is expected w.r.t. the genitive of negation. 
(10)	 Baltins argument based on the placement of the predicate modifiers all/ever is 
problematic. It invokes a notion of synt actic predicate which is found nowhere 
else, adjunction to X, and PRO in [Spec,VP]. Even under his assumptions, 
[40]/[41] do not argue for an embedded A-trace, since the to-projection could be 
a predicate without it. 
Unaccusatives 
(11) 	 Baltin : i) absence of distinctive verbal morphology (as opposed to passive); ii) 
absence of any thematic role other th an the one assigned to the complement. 
Note : (i) is of course an acc ident of English; many, pe rhaps most languages have 
 distinctive unaccusative morphology (interestingly, often reflexive). 
(12) 	 Under a movement analysis, intransitiv e verbs fall into two classes  unergatives 
and unaccusatives  that differ not only in  their core meaning but also in their 
syntax. By contrast, a lexicalist analysis  would locate the differences between the 
two classes strictly in their semantics,  since neither involves movement. To the 
extent that some data can only be explained by recourse to a syntactic 
difference between the two classes, the movement approach is supported. 
a. 	 [IP DP [ VP VInt ]] unergative
 b. 	 [IP DP 1 [VP VInt t1 ]] unaccusative
 Note : Actually, there is also A-movement in (a), from [Spe c,VP]. Disturbingly, 
although everyone assumes it, there is little factual evidence for it. 
Baltin also notes that a relational theory  of linking cannot derive the contrast in 
(a-b). In such a theory, thematic prominence implies syntactic prominence; a 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Thus, the universal aspects of passive seem to be i) special morphology on the 
verb, ii) suppression of the external argument. Movement is not one of them. 
How is the postverbal DP licensed? Belletti (1988) claimed that it receives 
partitive case in situ. GB theory invoked an indexing mechanism that allowed 
Infl to assign nominative case to postverbal subjects. In Minimalism, Agree  is 
doing the work. 
(8)	 Adjectival passives 
The subject of an adjectival passive must  be an argument of the passive predicate, 
unlike in verbal passives ( un- selects an adjective): 
a. 	 The bed was unmade. 
b. 	 Headway was (*un)made. 
c. 	 John was unknown. 
d. 	 John was (*un)known to be the murderer. 
On the classical analysis, adjectival passives are formed in the lexicon while 
verbal passives are syntactically derive d. The lexical source of adjectival passives 
explains two facts at once i) they involve category change (V A), something that 
syntax never does; ii) they must a pply to thematically related items.  
Lexicalist theories can explain why ve rbal passive is possible in (b,d) by 
defining it over grammatical relations (objec t, subject, 2, 1) rather than argument 
structure. This would turn those relations to lexical features. But then it is not 
entirely clear why properties (i) and (i i) cooccur; what excludes a passive rule 
which would apply to grammatical relations and change V to A? The absence of 
such a rule is an argument for keepin g the lexicon-syntax distinction.    
The genitive of negation in Russian 
(9) 	 In the context of clausal negation, the following arguments optionally surface 
with genitive case:
 a. 	 Accusative objects of  transitive verbs. 
b. 	 Nominative subjects of verbal passives. 
c. 	 Nominative subjects of unaccusatives. 
The following arguments cannot shift to genitive in the context of negation: 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
theme is projected above a goal, but if  there is no goal, the theme would be 
projected where the goal was (complement to V), see [42]/[43]. Baltin claims that 
this will obliterate the contrast between (a) and (b)  but will it?
  Typically, unergative subjects are agents, unaccusative subjects are 
themes. A relational linking theory can still draw the necessary distinction by 
requiring that the external  argument always be proj ected above V, while all 
internal arguments be projected below V. The real challenging cases are theme-
unergatives ( The torch glowed in the dark ); how do we make sure that they are 
linked differently from theme-unaccusatives (e.g., fall, open)? 
Diagnostics 
(13) 	 Aux-selection in Italian 
a. 	 Transitives and unergatives select avere  have in the perfect tense;  
passives, unaccusatives and raising verbs select essere  be; see [44]-[48]. 
The generalization (following Burzio) is that avere  goes with deep subject, 
essere  with derived subjects. 
  N o t e : Reflexives also select essere , see [49], which led people to propose  
that they too involve derived subj ects. But there is much independent  
  evidence against the unaccusative analys is of reflexives. We can settle for  
a one-way implication: derived subject  essere. 
Problem : Unaccusative/passive verbs with postverbal subject also select 
essere  [54]. Solutions : i) An abstract CHAIN relation between the 
postverbal subject and Infl  (or its Spec) licenses essere ; ii) Aux-selection 
is fixed at the lexicon  essere  is picked whenever some arity-reducing 
operation took place (whenever the ex ternal argument is suppressed, 
eliminated, or equated with the internal argument). 
b. 	 Ne-cliticization : Ne is a pro-form clitic replaci ng partitive complements of 
nouns. Belletti &amp; Rizzi (1981) proposed that ne is extracted from the 
direct object position a nd attaches to Infl. Again, the class of verbs 
allowing ne-cliticization from their subject  is exactly that selecting essere 
 namely, those with derived subjects.  
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
a. John watched  John watched himself 
b. * [IP John 1 [VP watched t 1]]. -criterion violation 
c. * [IP John 1 [VP t1 watched t 1]].  Chain Condition violation 
d. 	 * [IP John [ VP t1 believed [t 1 to appear that it would rain]]] . 
Chain Condition violation 
Note : If case-assignment by believe  is obligatory, (d) violates both -uniqueness 
and case-uniqueness. 
(5) Some A-movements target non-case positions: 
a. John 1 is believed [ IP t1 to be likely [ IP t1 to [ VP t1 win]]]. 
Some A-movements move PPs, which need no case: 
b. [Under the rug] 1 seems to be [ IP t1 the only place I havent searched]. 
If the cases under (2) are indeed genuine  A-movements, then the EPP feature at 
[Spec,IP] is also not a defining characteri stic of A-movement. So what are we left 
with? Perhaps a negative characterization: A-movement applies to arguments and
 targets non-operator  positions (not [Spec,CP], not adjoined). 
While were picking on Baltins errors 
(6) a. * The boat sank to collect the insurance. 
b. The boat was sunk to collect the insurance. 
Baltin cites the common wisdom; the contrast is due to the fact that i) PRO must be 
controlled by an argument (possibly implicit) ; ii) the external argument is implicit in 
passives, eliminated in unaccusatives.  
(c,d) show that (i) is false (for rationale  clauses); (d) shows that the trouble in (a) 
is orthogonal to control. 
c. Grass is green to promote photosynthesis. 
d. The shopwindow has a big sale sign in it (in order) to attract customers. 
e. * The ship sank (in order) for the owner to collect the insurance. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
b. 	 The semantic characterization of the class of raising predicates is very  
tricky  perhaps there isnt any. Ne arly synonymous pairs contrast, e.g.,  
likely-probable, sure-confident . 
Raising to Object (ECM) 
(21) 	 The mainstream of EST and GB reje cted the idea of raising to object. 
a. 	 John believes [ IP her to be clever]. ECM 
b. 	 John believes her 1 [IP t1 to be clever]. RtO 
There is no question that the medial DP is the thematic subject of the embedded 
clause; the issue is how to capture its syntactic behavior as a matrix object (case, 
passive). Chomsky argued that i) object  positions are sub categorized, ii) all 
subcategorized positions are -marked, iii) chains can only bear a single -role. 
RtO would then amount to a violation of the Chain Condition. 
Recently there have been attempts ( by Lasnik) to revive the classical RtO 
analysis without infringing on the Chain C ondition. The idea is that the medial DP 
indeed raises overtly to th e matrix clause, but not into  a thematic position, rather 
into [Spec,Agr o/v], to check case.  
Evidence for RtO 
(22) 	 Matrix adverbs may intervene between the medial DP and the infinitive. 
a. 	 I believe John [with all my heart] [to be a fine person]. 
b. * I believe [John with all my heart is a fine person]. 
(23) 	 The medial DP has ma trix scope by binding tests. 
a. * Mary believes him 1 [to be a genius] [even more fervently than Bob 1 does]. 
b. 	 Mary believes [he 1 is a genious] [even more fervently than Bob 1 does]. 
c. 	 The D.A. proved the defendents 1 [to be guilty] [on each others 1 trials]. 
d. * The D.A. proved [that the defendents 1 were guilty] [on each others 1 trials]. 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
A-movement 1 seems t 1 to be real 
Idan Landau 
Canonical examples 
(1) 	 a. Passive
  The door 1 was opened t 1. 
b. 	 Unaccusative
  The door 1 opened t 1. 
c. 	 Raising (to subject)
  M a r y 1 appears [ IP t1 to be confused]. 
Controversial examples 
(2) a. 	 Local scrambling (Japanese, Hindi). 
b. 	 Object shift (Scandinavian languages). 
c. 	 Possessor raising (Hebrew, Korean). 
d. 	 ECM/Raising to object. 
Definitions 
(3) 	 a. Baltins definition [p.226] 
Movement of an element to what is known as an argument position  
roughly, a position in which an elemen t can be base generated and bear a  
crucial semantic role with respect to the main predicat e of the clause. 
b. 	 Classical Definition
Movement of an argument to a case position. 
Both definitions are problematic.  
(4) 	 In fact, A-movement never  targets a position in which an  argument can be  base-
generated. This follows from the Chain Condition (Chomsky 1986), which 
dictates that a chain bear exactly one -role, assigned at its tail. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
c. 	 * [Tomodati no  kuruma]-ga  2-ri nusum-are-ta 
friend-GEN car NOM 2-cl steal-PASS-Pst 
(17) 	 Unaccusatives
 a. 	 Doa-ga [kono kagi]-de 2-tu aita. 
door-NOM this  key -by  2-cl opened 
b. 	 Kinoo, tekihei -ga [ano hasi]-o 2-3-ni watatta. 
yesterday enemy-soldiers- NOM that bridge-A CC 2-3-cl crossed 
c. 	 Gakusei -ga ofisu-ni 2-ri kita. 
students-NOM  office-to 2-cl came
Conclusion : The floated Q associates with the tra ce of the subject. Its difficult to see 
how a lexicalist theory would d eal with these word order effects in a principled way. 
(18) 	 Derived subjects cannot bind the reflexive si  in Italian (Rizzi 1986). 
Transitives 
a. 	 Paolo affider Gianni a se-stesso]. 
Paolo will-entrust Gianni to himself 
b. 	 Paolo si  affider Gianni.
Paolo to-himself will-entrust Gianni
 Passives 
c. 	 Gianni -stato affi dato  a se-stesso]. 
Gianni was entrusted to himself 
d. * Gianni si  -stato affidato. 
Unaccusatives 
e. 	 Il ladro e il poliziotto sono caduti l'uno addosso  all'altro. 
the thief &amp; the cop have fallen one on-top-of the other 
f. ?* Il ladro e il poliziotto si sono caduti addosso. 
Raising 
g. 	 A se stesso, Gianni non sembra fare  il suo dovere. 
to himself  Gianni neg seems  to-do the his duty 
h. 	 * Gianni non si  sembra fare il suo dovere. 
Gianni neg to-himself seems  to-do the his duty 
8</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Control (PRO) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln14control/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 The binding properties  [5]-[6] 
a. The antecedent must be local (inside GC / CFC). 
b. The antecedent must c-command the anaphor. 
c. The antecedent cant be split. 
d. The anaphor gets only sloppy reading under VP-ellipsis. 
(29) Lebeaux : Only the dependency property is inherently linked with anaphors. The 
binding properties follow from a pa rticular mechanism of binding ( predication ). 
Concretely, local binding exhibits the binding properties, non-local binding 
doesnt. 
(30) Local binding 
Lebeaux sets up the definitions [6]-[7] su ch that the domain of local binding for a 
lexical anaphor is the minimal NP/S cont aining it, whereas for PRO (a nonlexical 
anaphor) its the minimal NP/S containing the nonfinite clause. 
(31) Local binding 
a. John saw himself in the mirror. Binding domain = matrix S 
b. John tried [PRO to leave]. Binding domain = matrix S
 Non-local binding 
c. John knew that [there were [pictures of himself] inside]. 
d. John told Mary that [[PRO leaving early] would be a mistake]. 
(32) Nonlocally bound reflexives may take non-commanding or split antecedents, and 
allow strict readings under VP-ellip sis [10]; same for non-locally bound PRO 
[11]. 
Note : Some OC contexts allow sp lit antecedents, cf. (10b).  
Lebeaux : Since all occurences of PRO are anaphoric (dependent), but some show 
binding properties (OC) and others dont (NOC), the binding properties cant be 
inherent to PRO.  
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Non-Arguments for PRO 
(2) 	 Understood Coreference  (Haegeman 1994) 
a. 	 Poirot 1 abandoned the investig ation [in order PRO 1 to save money]. 
b. 	 Poirot 1 abandoned the inves tigation [without PRO 1 giving 
an explanation]. 
Problem : Predication can achieve the same effect. There is no obvious entailment 
from understood coreference to syntactic representation. Compare: 
c. 	 John ate the meat raw. 
d. 	 John 1 underwent an operation (on him 1). 
e. 	 We entered the room 1. The walls (of it 1) were covered with blood. 
(3) 	 Together  (Haegeman 1994): Requires a local plural NP in an A-position.  
a. 	 I saw the boys/*boy together. 
b. 	 [PRO to leave together] would be stupid. 
Problem : The local NP can be the controller, not necessarily PRO. This is 
possible in (b), with an implicit controller ( stupid of X ), though not in cases of real 
arbitrary control (... would insult Mary ). 
(4) 	 Binding : The infinitive behaves like a bi nding domain (GC), hence contains  
 a subject. 
a. 	 John 1 wanted [PRO 1 to talk about himself 1/*him 1]. 
 Problems : i) The argument is invalid. If the infinitive is a binding domain, then 
the contrast in (a) follows. But not vice versa: The contrast in (a) could also 
follow from the fact that the infinitive lacks  a subject and the binding domain is 
the whole matrix. ii) It needs to be  shown, independently, that condition A 
requires a syntactic and not an implicit bi nder (true, but not trivial, and false for 
conditions B &amp; C). 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Agent Control 
(24) a. * John was promised (by Mary) [PRO to leave]. 
b. It was decided [PRO to leave]. 
c. The game was played [PRO wearing no shoes]. 
(25) 	 Rationale Clauses 
a. 	 The boat was sunk [PRO to collect the insurance]. 
b. * The boat sank [for the owner/PRO to collect the insurance]. 
c. * The ship was sunk to become a hero. 
d. 	 Grass is green to promote photosynthesis. 
Lebeaux (1984) 
(26) 	 Main idea  
a. 	 All types of PRO are anaphoric, including so-called PRO arb. 
b. 	 The differences between locally bound lexical anaphors and PRO in NOC 
are not due to their different cons titution (both are an aphors), but due to 
the different mechanisms of anaphor binding.   
(27) 	 Long Distance (LD) controlled PRO is not a pronoun
 a. 	 His 1 / *PRO 1 having shaved already shows th at Mary arrived more than 5 
minutes after John 1 did. 
The antecedent of PRO must comma nd it (i.e., the first S dominating the 
antecedent dominates PRO).  
(28) 	 Narrowing down anaphorhood 
Properties of anaphors are of two different types. 
The dependency property
An anaphor is referentiall y dependent on an antecedent. 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
PRO arb is locally bound by an operator / PRO arb is an A-bar anaphor 
(33) a. [PRO x making a large profit as a slum landlord] requires 
[ P R O x exploiting the tenants]. 
b. [PRO x to know him] is [PRO x to love him]. 
The interpretation of the two PRO arb subjects is linked, even  if pragmatics prefers 
otherwise: 
c. * [PRO x becoming a movie star involves [PRO y recognizing you]. 
Lexical subjects need not be linked: 
d. 	 His getting up on time will requi re her setting the alarm clock. 
(34) 	 Since neither PRO binds the other PRO,  they must be both variables bound by the 
same operator  with universal/generic force. PRO arb is similar to the indefinite 
pronoun one . 
a. x / Gen x ((PRO x making a large profit) requires (PRO x exploiting the tenants)). 
(35) 	 Important note: The universal operator is  associated with necesseity predicates  
require, entail, involve . When the predicate doesnt imply necessity, the linked 
reading disappears. 
a. 	 [PRO x going to the movies] beats [PRO y staying home and  
  eating popcorn]. 
(36) 	 Linked readings obtain in clausal contexts, where PRO exists, not in nominal 
contexts. 
a. 	 PRO winning games requires PRO losing games. 
(winner of some games = loser of some games) 
b. 	 The winning of games re quires the losing of games. 
(If someones wins, someone (else) must lose). 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
b. 	 Strkarnir vonast til [a PRO lei ast ekki llum   skla]. 
  the boys. NOM hope for to PRO. DAT bored not all. DAT in school 
The boys hope not to be all bored in school 
Distribution of PRO 
(12) 	 *PRO in case positions. 
a. * John invited PRO. 
b. * John talked about PRO. 
c. * John said that PRO can leave. 
d. * John believed PRO to be intelligent. 
e. * [For PRO to leave abruptly] would be impolite. 
(13) 	 *PRO in governed but caseless positions. 
a. * There was invited PRO. 
b. * A picture PRO. 	 (cf. a picture *(of) Mary) 
c. * Johns belief PRO to be innocent. 
d. * It is likely PRO to be angry. 
e. * John was proud PRO (cf. ...*(of) Mary) 
Conclusion: PRO is ungoverned. [Chomsky 1981] 
(14) 	 The PRO-Theorem  [Chomsky 1981] 
Condition A: An anaphor must be bound in its local domain. 
Condition B: A pronoun must be free in its local domain. 
The local domain includes a governor and a subject.  
PRO is [+anaphor,+pronoun]. 
 ------------------ ------------------ ----------------- ---------- -------- 
  PRO has no local domain  
PRO (in OC) has a subject 
 ------------------ ----------------- 
 PRO is ungoverned 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(48) a. In a structure [... X ... [ it  Aux Pred Y [ S PRO to VP]], where Y and S 
are arguments of Pred: 
    i) If Pred is ps ychological, Y must control PRO. 
   ii) If Pred is non-psychol ogical, either X or Y may control PRO. 
b. In a structure [... X ... [ S [S PRO to VP] Pred... Y] ], either X or Y may  
 control PRO. 
In short, LD-control is susceptible to intervention only in ex traposition, and only 
when the intervener bears an experiencer -role. 
(49) Outline of the account : In extraposition, at the rele vant level where control is 
established, an experiencer controller will c-command the infinitive but a 
theme/goal controller  will not.  Hence, OC is linked to experiencers. In 
intraposition, no clausemate argument c- commands the infinitive, hence NOC. 
Note : In the book I assumed that the relevant level is already established at DS, 
now I believe that the experiencer c- commands the infinitive only at LF. 
(50) A substantive correlation: The goal/theme object may fail to to c-command the 
infinitive only if the latter is adjoined  to VP. But adjuncts are islands. So we 
expect a correlation be tween NOC and islandhood. 
(51) a. It would kill the workers 1 [PRO 1 to build this dam]. 
b. What 2 would it kill the workers 1 [PRO 1 to build t 2 ?] 
c. It would kill the forest [PRO arb to build this dam]. 
d. * What 2 would it kill the forest [PRO arb to build t 2 ?] 
(52) a. Hillary thinks it damaged Bill 1 [PRO 1 to talk about himself on the 
Dave Letterman show]. 
b. Thats the talk show 2 that Hillary thinks it damaged Bill 1 [PRO 1 to talk 
about himself on t 2 ] . 
c. Hillary 1 thinks it damaged Bill [PRO 1 to talk about herself on the 
Dave Letterman show]. 
d. * Thats the talk show 2 that Hillary 1 thinks it damaged Bill [PRO 1 to talk 
about herself on t 2 ] . 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(15) 	 Problems for the PRO-Theorem 
i) 	 Under Chomskys (1986), the local domains of anaphors and pronouns can be 
different. In (a), the object DP is the minimal CFC with a governor in which the 
pronoun can be free, but in (b) the entire  clause is the minimal CFC with a 
governor in which the anaphor can be bound. We therefore expect PRO to be 
possible there, simultaneously satisfying c onditions A and B. But it is not, see (c). 
a. 	 They 1 like [ DP their 1 pictures]. 
b. 	 They 1 like [ DP each others 1 pictures]. 
c. * They 1 like [ DP PRO 1 pictures]. 
ii) 	 The exclusion of [-Agr] Infl from th e class of governors is completely  
ad-hoc, voiding government as a structural relation. 
iii) 	 If PRO is caseless a nd the Visibility Condition of Chomsky (1981) obtains, 
then PRO violates the -criterion. On the other hand  why should the 
Visibility Condition obtain, anyway? 
iv) 	 If PRO is caseless, and NP-movement is case-driven, then we fail to account for 
John wanted [PRO to be elected].  However, NP-movement may be driven by the 
PRO-theorem as well, or  more likely  by the EPP.  
v) 	 As we have seen in (11), PRO is case-marked (hence governed) in some 
languages. 
Referential properties of PRO 
(16) Weather- it &amp; extraposition- it vs. there -expletive. 
a. 	 Sometimes it 1 rains without [PRO 1 snowing]. 
b. 	 It bothered John [PRO without actually offending him] that he  
  wasnt elected. 
c. 	 There occured three more acci dents without [there/*PRO being 
any medical help available on the premises]. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
If PRO arb is an anaphor, what is its binding domain? 
(37) 	 The binding domain of PRO is the mini mal NP/S containing the nonfinite clause.  
a .	 *  [ BD [PRO x winning the trust of the populace] requires [PRO y having to 
serve in the army]].  
b. 	 [BD1 [PRO x winning the trust of the populace] requires that  
[BD2 [PRO y having to serve in the army] be abolished]]. 
Unifying LD and arbitrary control 
(38) 	 In general, NOC comprises of either long-distance or arbitrary control. If no 
controller is available in th e binding domain of PRO, then  either LD or arbitrary 
control is allowed. Since the choice be tween them is not grammatical, Lebeaux 
suggests to unify both cases. 
(39) a. Closure: If PRO is unbound in its binding ca tegory, adjoin a null operator 
Op to the binding category and coindex it with PRO. 
b. Operator interpretation : Op may be coindexed with a grammatical 
antecedent or a discourse referent. Otherwise, Op is generic.  
See examples [35]-[38].  
(40) 	 Problem : (39a) predicts that a local potential anteced ent rules out NOC. But 
weve seen examples like (a), where that is possible.  
a. 	 Mary realized that it woul d help John [PRO to speak about
 himself/herself/oneself]. 
b. 	 Mary realized that [PRO speak ing about herself/ himself/oneself]  
  would embarrass John. 
Solution : Maybe John  in (a) doesnt c-command the extraposed clause.  
Notice that the operator in (b) would c-command John, violating [43]. 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(41)	 Prediction : Interrogative complements should fall  under OC if a matrix controller 
is avaialble. Paradox : Arbitrary control is allowed, LD control isnt. 
a. 	 Mary said that John wondered 
[how PRO to introduce himself/oneself/*herself]. 
Landau (2000: Chapter 1): The basics 
(42) What classifies a construction as OC? 
a. Classical answer: Whether or not PRO is obligatory. 
b. Alternative answer: Whether or not PRO is obligatorily controlled. 
 OC may obtain even if PRO altern ates with a lexical subject (e.g., prefer). 
(43) Two types of OC: Exha ustive vs. Partial control 
(We thought that...) 
a. The chair 1 preferred [PRO 1+ to gather at 6]. 
b. Bil1 regretted [PRO 1+ meeting without a concrete agenda]. 
c. Mary 1 wondered [whether PRO 1+ to apply together for the grant]. 
(cf... * to apply as partners). 
(We thought that) 
d. * John 1 managed [PRO 1+ to gather at 6]. 
e. * The chair 1 began [PRO 1+ meeting without a concrete agenda]. 
f. * Mary 1 is able [PRO 1+ to apply together for the grant]. 
(44) EC-infinitives 
a) implicative (dare, manage, forget, force ...) 
b) aspectual (begin, stop, continue...) 
c) modal (able, capable, need, must...) 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 PC-infinitives
 a) desiderative (want, prefer, decide, demand...)
 b) interrogative (wonder, ask, guess, inquire ...) 
c) factive (hate, regret, dislike, shocked ...) 
d) propositional (believe, imagine, say, declare ...) 
(45) 	 Question : What distinguishes EC- from PC-infinitives? 
Answer : The absence or presence of tense  (Landau 2000). 
EC-infinitives are untensed, PC-infinitives are tensed: 
a. * Yesterday, John managed to solve the problem tomorrow. imp. 
b. * Yesterday, John began to  solve the problem tomorrow. asp. 
c. * Yesterday, John was able to solve the problem tomorrow. mod. 
d. 	 Yesterday, John hoped to solve the problem tomorrow. des. 
e. 	 Yesterday, John wondered how to solve the problem tomorrow. int. 
f. 	 Today, John regretted having so lved the problem last week. fac. 
g. 	 Oggi Gianni crede di avere offeso Maria la notte scorsa. prop. 
today John believes to have offended Mary the night last 
Today, John believes to have offended Mary last night [Italian] 
(46) 	 Outline of the account : OC is Agree  between a matrix controller and the 
embedded [Agr] or PRO. The C head of of PC infinitives is associated with [+T], 
and derivatively, [+Agr]. This [+Agr] is th e target of partial control. Because it 
bears no specification of Semantic Pluralit y, it allows the controller and PRO to 
differ on that feature. In EC, it is PRO whic h is directly contro lled (C bearing no 
[T] or [Agr]), hence it must match the semantic plurality of the controller. 
Super-Equi 
(47) 	 a. Mary knew that it disturbe d John [PRO to perjure himself / *herself]. 
b. Mary knew that it damaged J ohn [PRO to perjure himself / herself]. 
c. Mary knew that [PRO to perjur e himself / herself] would disturb John. 
d. Mary knew that [PRO to perjure himself / herself] would damage John. 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
c. 	 John 1 ubedil Mary 2 navestit svoju *1/2 sestru. 
  John persuaded Mary. ACC to-visit SELF s sister. ACC
John persuaded Mary to visit selfs *1/2 sister 
(9) 	 Dative control + binding of embedded anaphor unbindable by a dative.
 German  (Wurmbrand 1998) 
a. 	 weil der Hans der Maria sich 1/*2 auf dem Photo zeigte. 
  since the John- NOM Mary- DAT SELF in the picture showed 
  since John showed Mary himself / *herself in the picture 
b. 	 Sie hat dem Hans erlaubt [PRO 1 sich 1 den Fisch mit Streifen 
vorzustellen]. 
  She has John- DAT allowed PRO SELF the fish with stripes to-imagine 
She allowed John to imagine what the fish would look like with stripes 
(10) 	 Split antecedents .     [Koster &amp; May 1982] 
a. * John 1 suggested/showed Mary 2 to each other 1+2. 
b. 	 John 1 suggested to Mary 2 [PRO 1+2 to help each other 1+2]. 
(11) 	 Case concord with quirky subjects. 
Icelandic (Sigursson 1991, ex.8) 
a. 	 Strkana vanta i alla  sklann. 
  the boys. ACC lacked all. ACC.PL.MS  in the school 
The boys were all absent from school 
b. 	 Strkarnir vonast til [a PRO vanta ekki alla  sklann]. 
  the boys. NOM hope for to PRO. ACC lack not all. ACC in the school 
The boys hope not to be all absent from school 
c. 	 Strkana leiddist llum   skla. 
  the boys. DAT bored all. DAT .PL.MS  in the school 
The boys were all bored in school 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
b. Mary 1 thought that John talked *(to her 1) about herself 1. 
c. Mary 1 thought that John said (to her 1) [PRO 1 to wash herself]. 
d. John never talked (*to her 1) about Mary 1/her 1. 
(5) 	 Theta Criterion : Every -role must be assigned to an argument. 
Problem : Implicit arguments satisfy this cr iterion, why must PRO be projected? 
(6) 	 EPP: The subject must be projected. 
Problem : The reasoning is circuler. The claim that the EPP is exceptionless in 
itself assumes that null subjects can satisfy it. But if they cant, then the EPP is 
violable. One cannot motivat e the existence of PRO on the basis of a principle 
whose status crucially relies  on the existence of PRO.  
Genuine Arguments for PRO 
(7) 	 Predication  (Haegeman 1994): Secondary re dicates require a local  
 syntactic subject. 
a. 	 [PRO to arrive exhauste d at a party] is terrible. 
b. 	 John ate *(the meat) raw. 
c. * Dinner was served angry at the guests.  [cf. ... PRO wearing aprons]. 
d. 	 [PRO to serve dinner angry at  the guests] is not a good idea. 
(8) 	 Object control + embedded subject-oriented anaphor.
 Russian  (Natalia Strahov, p.c.) 
a. 	 John 1 otpravil Mary 2 k svocj 1/*2 sestere. 
  John sent Mary. ACC to SELF s sister. DAT
John sent Mary to selfs 1/*2 sister 
b. 	 John 1 otpravil Mary 2 navestit svoju 1/2 sestru. 
  John sent Mary. ACC to-visit SELF s sister. ACC
John sent Mary to visit selfs 1/2 sister 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(17) PRO arb is [+human].      [Chomsky 1981] 
a. [For coffee prices to fall in August] is very unusual. 
b. [PRO to fall in August] is very unusual. 
(18) Semantic plurality in partial control. 
a. John told Mary that he wanted to meet (*each other) at 6. 
b. John told Mary that he wanted  to work together / *become partners. 
(19) De se  / de re . 
a. The unfortunate expects that he will get a medal. 
b. The unfortunate expects [PRO to get a medal].             
Implicit Control 
Dative Control (and locality effects) 
(20) a. Mary 1 said it was difficult [PRO 1 to get herself a visa]. 
b. * Mary 1 said it was difficult for Bill 2 [PRO 1 to get herself a visa]. 
(21) a. * Mary knew that it had been decided (by John) [PRO to behave herself].  
b. Mary knew it had been prohibited [PRO to reveal herself in public]. 
(22) Omissibility of Controllers 
a. John recommended *(to us) to leave. 
b. Gil himlic (lanu) laazov.  Hebrew 
(23) Apparent Arbitrary Control (Williams 1980, Bouchard 1984, Huang 1989) 
a. John said (*to Mary) [PRO arb to behave oneself]. 
b. It is fun [PRO arb to eat ice-cream]. 
c. Gen x [it is fun for x  [for x to eat ice-cream]]. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
How PRO to control PRO? 
Idan Landau 
Distribution of Infinitives/Gerunds 
(1) 	 V/A-Complement 
a. 	 John promised Mary [PRO to leave early]. 
b. 	 John persuaded Mary [PRO to leave early]. 
c. 	 John wondered [when PRO to leave]. 
d. 	 Mary considered [PRO leaving early]. 
Sentential Subject/Intraposition 
e. [PRO to eat/eating t oo much lettuce] is not healthy. 
f. Mary realized that [PRO speak ing of herself/himself] would embarrass John. 
Extraposition 
g. 	 Mary realized that it embarrassed John [PRO to speak about  
  himself/*herself]. 
h. 	 Mary realized that it helped John [PRO to speak about himself/herself]. 
Adjunct 
i. 	 John resigned after [PRO delivering his speech]. 
j. 	 Mary 1 helped us 2 without [PRO 1 being rewarded/*PRO 2 rewarding her]. 
Rationale/Purpose Clause 
k. 	 John brought the book (in order) [PRO  to read it on the flight]. 
l. 	 John brought the book (*in order) [PRO to read on the flight]. 
Infinitival Relative 
m. 	 Something [PRO to eat] would be nice now. 
N/P-complements 
n. 	 We were told about the decision [PRO to evacuate the island]. 
o. 	 I read a story about [PRO falling in love with a foreign girl]. 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Unaccusativity (cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln9process_unacc/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(7) 	 Main results [Table 1, p. 13]
 a. 	 Priming : After the head (position 1) for all verb types; in position 3  
(750 ms after the verb) only for no n-alternating unaccusatives and some 
alternating ones. 
b. 	 No priming : In position 3 for unergatives, and some alternating 
 unaccusatives. 
c. 	 Decay in activation : In position 2 for all verb types. 
(8) 	 Variable behavior in  the alternating class
 a. 	 Priming (like non-alternating unacc.): dry, sink, open, bounce, 
 freeze, grow . 
b. 	 No priming (like unerg.) : crack, swing, shut . 
c. 	 Unclear pattern : close, cook, break, roll, spin, move. 
(9) 	 Possible explanation for the unruly verbs 
a. 	 Alternating verbs have homonym ous transitive variants. Perhaps the 
parser is misanalysing the unaccusative verb as a transitive (so no gap is 
expected), and only retracts at a po int beyond those tested for priming. 
 Prediction : The irregular pattern will disa ppear in a language where the 
transitive and the incohative vari ants are morphologically distinct.  
b. 	 Gradient unaccusativity: The verbs in (8a) typically take patient subjects, 
those in (8b) typically take agent su bjects, and those in (8c) take the two 
types of subjects with equal freq uency. Preliminary database search 
confirmed this hypothesis.  
  N o t e : It is still not clear how the fact that crack usually takes an agentive 
subject (assuming thats true) forces an unergative analysis even when the 
subject is inanimate (as must have been  the case in this study). Whats the 
 linking rule? 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(3) 	 Earlier Findings 
a. 	 If the target word is semanti cally related to the prime word (e.g., ballet ), 
priming occurs (easier/faster lexical access). 
b. 	 The target can be primed not only by  the actual prime word, but also by 
its trace. This was a classical argument for movement. 
c. 	 Priming in NP-chains is dela yed (relative to A-bar chains).  
(4) 	 Classifiying unaccusatives 
Non-alternating unaccusatives were identified by ability to occur in there -
construction, lack of a tran sitive variant and lack of passive [9]-[11]. Alternating 
unaccusatives were identified by the pr esence of a homonymous transitive 
variant, occurrence in passive and blocking of resulta tives [12]-[14].  
 Note 1: Its unclear what is tested by the there -construction. Friedmann et. al. note 
that the restrictions on this constructi on are very subtle and context sensitive 
(Levin &amp; Rappaport 1995). Actually, some  alternating unaccusatives allow it 
(begin , continue ). 
 Note 2 : Its unclear how resultatives are relevant. [14] is bad not because roll is 
alternating, but because it is ambiguous be tween unaccusative and unergative, and 
animate subjects favor the latter. In f act, many alternating unaccusatives take 
resultatives (The river froze solid ), while some nonaltern ating unaccusatives dont 
(She arrived breathless ). 
(5) 	 Classifiying unergatives
 i) ungrammatical in there -construction; ii) un grammatical with resultatives or 
reflexive objects, unless both occur together [15]-[18]. 
Note : Again, the resultative test is just a necessar y, not a sufficient condition. 
(6) 	 Examples  [19]-[20].  
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(10) 	 Conclusions 
a. 	 The Unaccusative Hypothesis is strongly confirmed. 
b. 	 The reactivation delay in A-chains , compared with A-bar chains, is 
probably due to the different cues the parser has for the existence of 
movement. In A-bar chains (quest ions, relative clauses), the cue  wh 
word or complementizer  is available very early; in A-movement, the cue for movement is only the ve rb itself (indicating the -role of the subject). 
c. 	 (My own): In retrospect, the pa rtition between alternating and non-
alternating unaccusatives wasnt illuminating, given that some of the 
alternating verbs, (8a), are indis tinguishable from nonalternating ones. 
Moreover, this fact alone rules out the proposal in (9a). Further studies 
will have to look more carefully at the semantic components of classes 
(8b,c). It is crucial to  conduct comparable experiments in languages where 
morphology doesnt confuse the parser. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Processing Evidence for the  Unaccusative Hypothesis 
Idan Landau 
(1) What can on-line processing teach us  about the structure of unaccusatives? 
       Unaccusatives  Unergatives 
  Non-alternating    Alternating 
arrive, vanish break, open smile, chirp 
The Unaccusative Hypothesis claims that unaccusatives are derived by NP-
movement from the object position, wher eas the subject of unergatives is 
underived. Occasionally it has also been cl aimed that in fact only the subject of 
non-alternating unaccusatives is derived; according to this view, alternating 
unaccusatives and unergatives ar e syntactically identical.  
The study uses Cross Modal Lexical Primi ng, a measure that is sensitive to the 
reactivation of antecedent arguments.  
If the single argument of unaccusati ve verbs is base generated in 
object position, and is displaced to subject posi tion through NP-
movement, then we should observe  activation of the argument in 
the object position; we should not observe activation of the subject 
NP in the object poistion of  unergative verbs (p. 4).  
(2) Cross Modal Lexical Priming 
A word presented after a semantically related word is accessed more easily/quicly 
than when it appears after an unrelated word. 
The reactivated word, in the trace position, is used as a auditory prime for another 
word, presented visually. So sentence [8] is presented aura lly, and at certain 
points a letter sequence is presented visu ally. The subject has to make a lexical 
decision (word/non-word) for the visu ally presented letter sequence.  
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Phrase Structure (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln2ho_fukui_01/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Relational Grammar and Lexical-Functional Grammar (cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln11ho_lfg/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Relational Grammar and Lexical-Functional Grammar (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln10rela_grammar/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
c. Multiple 2-advancements actually exist  as in Locative/Instrumental  
advancement in Kinyarwanda [5 ]-[7], with the structure [8]. 
Diagnostics of 2: No preposition, undergoes passive, relativization, 
reflexivization, clefting and determin es object agreement (in object drop). 
Note : None of these properties is derived in any deep sense from 2-hood (which is 
a primitive property). Moreover, their clustering  is equally accidental in RG. 
(4) Given that the ATL is too strong, a restricted version is proposed: 
1-Advancement Exclusiveness Law 
A clause contains at most a single 1-advancement. 
GB/Minimalism analogue: Raising to subject occurs at most once in a clause.  
Are multiple subjects ruled out in general? 
(5) Notation 
Stratal diagrams can be converted to RNs,  where the history of each element is 
highlighted. Nominals that undergo adva ncement or demotion head parallel arcs, 
each labeled with the st ratum at which the nominal bears the arcs GR. For 
example, passive [15], Rt O [16], extraposition [17]. 
(6) Ruled out by 1-AEX : double passive/unaccusative [19] a nd passive of raising [20].   
Empirical Consequences 
(7) 	 In Cebuano, either the theme or the goal of write  can be passivize d; [22]-[23]. But 
if the theme is passivized, the goal cant be also passivized (putting the theme en 
chmage); and if the goal is first promoted to 1, the theme cant do the same [24]-
[26]. This is impossible re gardless of the voice mor phology on the verb. The same 
restriction was reported for other languages as well. 
(8) 	 In English, obliques expressing cost can be promoted to 1, as in (b), but the result 
cant be passivized (d): 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
The Unaccusative Hypothesis 
The traditional notions of transitive/intransitive verbs can be reconstructed using RG 
strata. It then becomes clear that more possibi lities exist then just a binary distinction.  
(11) a. A stratum contains a 1-arc and a 2-arc. transitive 
b. A stratum contains a 1-arc and no 2-arc. unergative 
c. A stratum contains a 2-arc and no 1-arc. unaccusative 
The Final 1 Law requires the final stratum of every basic clause to contain a 1 arc 
(EPP). Therefore, option (c) cant be  realized by a final stratum.  
(12) 	 The Unaccusative Hypothesis 
The initial stratum of some basic cl auses contains a 2-arc but no 1-arc. 
[48] shows that simple unaccusative clauses contain 1-advancement, whereas 
simple uergative clauses dont. This fo llows from the UH and the Final 1 Law. 
Note : Actually, unccusative clauses dont ha ve to contain 1-advancement. Why? 
To the extent that we find syntactic phenomena that are sensitive to non-final 
relations, and they treat the 1 of certain intransitive verbs as if it were a 2, the UH is corroborated. 
(13) 	 Passive vs. Unaccusative 
a. In unaccusatives, the input to 1-advancement is an intransitive stratum. 
b. In passives, the input to 1-advancement is a transitive stratum [50]. 
(14) 	 Universal Alignment Hypothesis There exist principles of universal gr ammar which predict the initial relation 
borne by each nominal in a given clause from the meaning of the clause.  
 If exist  is unaccusative in English, its semantic counterparts are also 
unaccusative in every other language.  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Impersonal passives 
These constructions are formed from an unergative or transiti ve source. A dummy 
(expletive) is inserted as a 2,  putting the initial 2 (if there is one), and then advancing to 
1, putting it en chmage [68]. 
(21) 	 Prediction : Since impersonal passives involve 1-advancement, they will be 
incompatible with an unaccusative verb (which also involves 1-advancement).  
Dutch: unergatives [70]-[88], vs. unaccusa tives [89]-[105]; ambiguous verbs 
allow impersonal passives only under the agentive readi ng (syntactically 
unergative) [107]-108]. The discussion of  the German example [109], with the 
verbs bleed  and die, shows that there is considerable flexibility in verbs 
meanings; many verbs can shift from  unaccusative to unergative syntax, 
depending on how much control ove r the action the subject has.  
 perhaps, then, the unaccusative/unergative  distinction is not lexically encoded, 
but contextually determined (core verbal meanings are underspecified). 
(22)	 Prediction : Since both impersonal passive s and Inversion involve  
1-advancements, they will be inco mpatible. See [113] vs. [114]-[115]. 
(23) 	 Some Inversion construc tions, after demoting the initia l 1 to 3, advance it to 2. 
The original 2 was advanced to 1, so we get a final transitiv e stratum [118]-[119]. 
The 1-AEX predicts that this transitive may not be passivized, since it is already 
derived by 1-advancement. The facts b ear out this predic tion [120]-[123].  
Note : In GB/Minimalism, escape/elude fail passive for two reasons: i) they lack 
an external argument; ii) the object is in fact a hidden oblique, and null 
prepositions cant be stranded in pseudopassive.  
a. 	 The reason for that escapes from me.  
b. * I1 am escaped from t1 by the reason for that. 
c. 	 John wrote to me. 
d. * I1 was written to t1 by John. 
What would be the RG analogue of (ii)? 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Relational Grammar and the Limits of Advancement 
Idan Landau 
(1) 	 Some ground rules 
a. 	 The Hierarchy of Grammatical Relations: 
1 (Subject) &gt;&gt; 2 (Direct Ob ject) &gt;&gt; 3 (Indirect Object)  
  &gt;&gt; Nonterms (Oblique, Chmeur) 
b. 	 Any stratum (= level of grammatical representation) contains at most one  
instance of each GR (Stratal Uniqueness Law).  
c. 	 Nominals can travel up the hierarchy ( advancement ) or down ( demotion ). 
d. 	 If X bears a specific GR and Y is ad vanced to this GR, X is put en  
chmage (becomes a Chmeur). 
e. 	 Well-formedness conditions can be defined over a single stratum or the  
entire set of strata associated with a sentence (its derivation).  
Can there be multiple advancements to the same GR in a sentence? 
(2) 	 Advancee Tenure Law (ATL) 
An advancee cannot be placed en chmage by an advancement.  
Note : An advancee can still be put en c hmage by expletive insertion [4].  
injured+en many workers  expl. (il) 
 Initial Stratum P 2 
Intermediate Stratum  P 1 
Final Stratum P Cho 1 
(3) Against the ATL 
a. Most of the impact of the ATL is to rule out multiple 1-advancements.  
b. The rare cases of multiple 3-advancements are independently ruled out. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
a. Melvin bought a lot of heroin for five dollars. 
b. Five dollars bought a lot of heroin in 1827. 
c. A lot of heroin was bought (by Melvin) for five dollars. 
d. * A lot of heroin was bought by five dollars in 1827. 
(d) is ruled out because its deri vation involves two 1-avancements [31]. 
(9)	 Question : Why do we analyze five dollars  in (b) as an advancee (derived subject)? 
i) five dollars  bears the same semantic role in (a) and (b); ii) the linking rules, 
mapping the arguments of buy to GRs, are the same in (a) and (b).  Either (a) or 
(b) is derived. iii) Plausibly, it is the oblique relation that reflects the initial 
mapping of cost NPs (not an agent/causer).  (b) is derived from (a). Notice 
that RG operates on the assumption that semantic roles are uniformly mapped to 
the syntax  Universal Alignment H ypothesis (very similar to UTAH).  
More support: [34]-[38]. No te: Whats not explained is why certain nominals can 
and others cant be the first 1-advancee: 
a. 	 1939 found the US on the brink of disaster. 
b. * The US found (by) 1939 on the brink of disaster. 
c. * The brink of disaster found the US by 1939. 
(10)	 No multiple passivization 
Given that either argument of write  can be passivized [39b]/[40b] (using P-
stranding), it is not obvi ous what rules out applying one passive after the other 
[40c,d]. Same for pay [41]-[42]. 
 GB/Minimalism : All the bad cases involve passiv ization of a verb without an 
external argument. The ultimate challenge, for both frameworks, is to characterize 
the notion of external argument (initial 1) in such a way that it will exclude all the subjects in [33a]-[38a].  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(15) Unergative predicates [52] 
a. Willed/volitional acts, including manner of speaking verbs. 
b. Certain involuntar y bodily processes.  
(16) Unaccusative predicates [53] 
a. Adjectives describing size, shape,  weight, color, smell, state of mind. 
b. Predicates whose initial 2 is a Patient. 
c. Predicates of existence and happening. 
d. Involuntary emission of stimu li that impinge on the senses.  
e. Aspectual predicates.  
 f. Duratives. 
 Fn. 13: Verbs of motion are ambiguous.  
Note : This classification is very close to Levin &amp; Rappaports, except that L&amp;R 
classify emission verbs with unergativ es (in fact, with (15b)). The major 
difference is that L&amp;R didnt discuss adjec tives, and in fact, its unclear why P&amp;P 
take them to be unaccusative.  
A major prediction : Unaccusative verbs will not have any passive variant (personal, 
impersonal, pseudopassive), since that will i nvolve two 1-advancements, in violation of 
the 1-AEX. 
(17) No unaccusative pseudopassives 
Unergatives 
a. The bed was slept in by the Shah. 
b. The bridge was skied u nder by the contestants.  
c. The package was stepped on by a camel. 
Unaccusatives 
d. * The bed was torn in by the underwear. 
e. * The bridge was jammed under by the canon. 
f. * The package was accumulate on by dust. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(18) 	 Ambiguous verbs 
a. 	 Ted slid into the closet. unergative 
b. 	 The soap slid into the closet. unaccusative 
c. 	 The closet was slid into by Ted. 
d. * The closet was slid into by the soap. 
Also : sit, lean  (maintain position vs. simple location) [59].  
(19) 	 The problem isnt any requirement that the initial 1 of passive be animate or an 
agent. English has no such requirement [60]. 
a. 	 That hypothesis was refuted by the data. 
b. 	 The danger of forest fires was increased by the drought. 
c. 	 The house is surrounded by tall elms. 
Inversion 
(20) 	 Inversion is a construc tion is which an initial 1 (u sually an experiencer) is 
demoted to a final 3, while an initial 2 advances in its place to final 1. See [61]. 
P&amp;P predict that Inversion c onstruction will not passivize. 
a. 	 I was spoken to by that girl. 
b. * I was mattered to by that girl. 
More inversion verbs: seem, appear, belong, occur, happen, dawn.
 Note : P&amp;P point out that the lack of passives follows from the advancement-to-1 
part of Inversion, not from the demotion-to-3.  In other words, given only the 
1AEX, verbs like matter  could either be initially unergative or unaccusative.  
By contrast, on the GB/Minimalist account, matter doesnt passivize 
because it has no external argument. The notions external argument  and initial 1 
are nearly co-extensive. Therefore, it is possible to test, empirically, which 
analysis is superior. How? 
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Binding Theory (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln4ho_lasnik_89/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Passives (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ho_bjr_89/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Unaccusativity (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln7unaccusativit/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
4 resultative XP is VP-internal (being sele cted and restricted by V), hence it cannot 
c-command the subject; hence, only di rect objects can ente r the resultative 
construction.   
 
 UL&amp;Rs Critique U: 
  Secondary predication doesnt always re quire the predicate to  c-command the NP. 
Depictives are VP-internal, but still can be associated with the subject. 
 
UNote U: Its unclear how to reconcile this statement with L&amp;Rs example: 
  a. Jason wiped the table tired and Mary did so wide awake. 
 (19) 
UAspectual analysis U 
 
 Resultative predicates (RP) modify th e end state brought about by an eventive 
verb, in case the verb specifies such a state (accomplishment; destroy ), or simply 
specify that state, in case  the verb doesnt (activity; wipe ).  
 
 a. The blacksmith pounded the metal.             no implied change of state 
 b. The blacksmith pounded the metal flat.        implied change of state  
   Middles require COS predicates, explaini ng the obligatory presence of RP below: 
 
 c. Metal pounds *(flat) easily. 
 (20) The COS Linking Rule  
 An NP that refers to the entity th at undergoes the change of state in the 
eventuality described in the VP must be  the direct object of (governed by) the 
verb heading the VP. 
   Given that RP is predicated of the argument that undergoes change of state, 
and that this argument is linked to th e direct object position, the DOR follows. 
  
UL&amp;R U: In addition, this NP mu st be in the appropriate  structural relation  
presumably mutual c-command  with the resultative XP (p. 51). 
 
This is, as far as I can see, a redundant stipulation.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
9 (33) Whats the difference betw een the two types of verbs? External vs. internal 
causation . With alternating unacc usatives, the event is brought about by some 
causer external to the subject. With unerg ative verbs, the event is brought about 
by some inherent property of the subject; in  agentive verbs, this is the will of the 
agent, but agentivity is not necessary for unergativity. Cf. verbs of emission: 
flash, glow, ring, buzz, stink, bubble, ooze.  
  
  Since individual-level adjectives denot e intrinsic properties that normally 
cannot be externally caused, deadjectiv al verbs that display the causative 
alternation are formed only with stage level adjectives: 
 
 a. clear, dry, warm. brighten, deepe n, moisten, soften, tighten, widen,   
  smarter  (= make someone well-dressed, not make someone intelligent).  
   subtle semantic contrast s, traceable to external vs . internal causation, explain 
why some verbs are subject to alternations and others dont: 
  b. The ladder leaned against the wall / I leaned the ladder against the wall 
 c. The surly youth slouched against the wall / *I slouched the surly youth 
 against the wall. 
 
(34) 
UA constraint on detransitivization U 
 
 a. The baker/knife cut the bread / *The bread cut 
 b. The terrorist murdered the se nator / *The senator murdered 
 c. The wind cleared the sky / The sky cleared 
 d. He cleared the table / *The table cleared 
  An event which can come about without the intervention of a volitional agent 
allows an unaccusative variant. The decisi on on such matters is sensitive to our 
world knowledge about the event/entity  denoted by the verb/argument.  
 
(35) 
UVerbs of existence / appearance / position U: exist, flourish, appear, emerge, arise , 
sit, stand . These verbs are not derived from any causative variant, but are clearly 
unaccusative (apparent causatives are de rived through a different process).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
7  Why can the event in (a) have two delimiters  the inherent one, broken state, and 
the RP open   but the event in (23b) not? L&amp;R: open  in (a) modifies the broken 
state, hence doesnt count as an independent delimiter. Breathless  in (23b) does 
contribute a new delimiter, which cl ashes with the one inherent in arrive .  
 UNote U: This asymmetry seems quite arbitrary.  
 
(27) UStatives are incompatible with RP  
 
 a.      * Carla remained in the country bored. 
 b.      The botanist sniffed/*smelled the moss dry.      
 
UL&amp;R U: There is no such thing as a delimited state. Since RP create a delimited 
event out of an undelimited one ( activity  accomplishment ), when they combine 
with statives the output doesnt fi t into any known eventuality type. 
 
UAgainst purely semantic accounts  
 (28) Van Valin (1990) claims that unaccusativ ity is purely an aspectual distinction. RP 
must be predicated of the Under goer role (the argument of the 
BECOME predicate 
in conceptual structure), and this role is only present in accomplishments and 
achievements. Unergative verbs are aspect ually activities, which provide no slot 
for an Undergoer argument, hence their incompatibility with RP.  
 (29) 
UQuestion U: Why is a fake reflexive necessary  to license RP with unergatives? 
 UV.V.s answer U: The fake reflexive is an aspectual shifter, turning activity into 
accomplishment. 
 UR&amp;Ls reply U: This doesnt explain why such a fake reflexive is not needed to 
license RP with transitive a nd unaccusative activity verbs: 
  a. The blacksmith pounded the metal flat. 
 b. The curtain rolled (*itself) open on the court.  
 
UNote U: How do R&amp;L force the fake reflexive with unergatives and exclude it with 
transitive and unaccusative verbs? Becau se the single argument of unaccusatives 
undergoes a change of state (the COS argum ent), it is linked to the object position 
and licenses RP. And because the single argument of unergatives doesnt undergo 
a change of state, it is linked to the subject position and doesnt license RP.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
Unaccusatives, Resultatives, and the Richness  
of Lexical Rep resentations 
 
Idan Landau 
 
 
(1) Definition
 A resultative phrase is  an XP that de notes th e state achiev ed by the referent of  
 the NP it is  predicated  of as a result of the action denoted by the verb in the  
 resultative construction. 
 
(2) The Direct Object Res triction (DOR) 
 A resultativ e phrase m ay be p redicated  of the imm ediately postverbal NP, but 
 may not be predicated of a subj ect or of an oblique com plement. 
 
Distribution 
 
(3) Selected object of tran sitive
 a. It soaks all your fine washables  clean. 
 b. He kissed them alive . 
 
(4) * Subject of unergative
 a.      * Dora  shouted hoarse . 
 b.      * The officers  laughed helpless . 
 
(5) *Oblique object
 a.      * John loaded the hay into the wagon full . 
 b.       The silver sm ith pounded (*on) the metal flat .  
 
(6) Nonthem atic object of unergatives  
 a. Dora shouted herself  hoarse .    fake re flexive 
 b. The officers laughed themselves  helpless.  fake re flexive 
 c. The dog barked him awake . 
 d. Sleep your wrinkles aw ay. inalienable possession  
 
(7) Unselected object of a transitive  
 a. She cooked them into premature death .  unspecified object  
 b. He drank himself silly .     unspecified object  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 c. a wiped-clean table / *a  drunk-dry teapot       adjectival passive  
 d. He felt rubbed raw. 
 
cf. e. The baby was ticked aw ake by the loud clock 
 
 Note : How can (c-d ) satisfy the DOR? See (20). 
 
(15) Real argum ents can occu r as of-NP inside nom inalizations, fake one cant. 
 
 a. The watering of tulips flat is a crim inal offense in Holland. 
 b.      * The drinking of oneself sick  is comm onplace in ones  freshm an year. 
 
(16) Extraction of real arg uments from  a wh-island produces a m ild subjacen cy 
 violation; extraction of fake argum ents produces a stronger E CP violation. 
 
 a.      ?  Which people do you w onder whether he punched senseless? 
 b.    ??  Which neighbors do you w onder whether the dog barked awake?  
 
Conclusion : The resu ltative con struction doe s not change th e argum ent struc ture of  the 
base verb. 
 
(17) Syntax  SC or not
 
 a. [VP V NP Pr edR] 
 b. [VP V [SC NP Pred R]]  
   
 Intuitive ly, (a) is suitable f or the cases where NP is an argum ent of V and (b) for  
those where it isnt. If (b) is adopted, the DOR has to be m odified so as to 
subsum e SC-subjec ts; alte rnative ly, rais ing to  objec t sho uld be adopted. L&amp;R 
remain neutr al on the syn tactic ana lysis; th eir interest is in argum ent structure. 
 
Explaining the DOR 
 
(18) Against the mutual c-command account
 
 William s and others hav e proposed  that predication requires  mutual c-co mmand 
between the NP and the predicate. This immediately rules out secondary 
predication with oblique objects (introduced  by P). It is a lso assum ed that the 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
Linking Rules 
 
(36) Immediate Cause Linking Rule  
 The argum ent of a verb that denotes the im mediate cause of the eventuality 
described by that verb is  its ex ternal argument. 
 
 [the subject of : agentive  verbs, inte rnally caus ed intrans itives (verbs of em ission, 
maintain spa tial position) , extern ally caused trans itives] 
 
(37) Directed Change Linking Rule 
 The argum ent of a verb that corresponds to the entity  undergoing the directed 
change described by that verb is  its d irect interna l argum ent. 
 
 [the object of COS verbs; the su bject of directed motion verbs] 
 
(38) Existen ce Linking Rule  
 The argum ent of a verb whose existence is asserted or denied is its direct internal 
argum ent. 
 
 [the subject of: verbs of existence/ap pearance, simple spatial configuration] 
 
(39) Default Lin king Rule 
 An argum ent of a verb that does not fa ll under the scope of the other linking rules 
is its direct internal argum ent.  
 
 [the subject of: non-di rected m otion verbs] 
 
(40) Rule ranking  
 
 Directed Change, Existence &gt;&gt; Immediate Cause &gt;&gt; Default  
 
 For exam ple, if V involves both internal  causation and directed change, directed 
change prevails and the ve rb is unac cusative (I talian arrossire  blush, an d cadere  
fall  even when used agentively!). Likewise, exis tence prevails over immediate 
cause, m aking V unac cusative (Italian riman ere rem ain, even when used 
agentively). However, if V involves intern al causation and non- directed change, it 
will be unergative (e.g., run vs. roll).    
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
8   But how different is it than V.V.s account? Weve seen that whats 
crucial for L&amp;R is the fact that the RP  is associated with the COS argument; 
whether this argument is proj ected as object or subject is  not, strictly speaking, 
relevant to the licensing of RP (recall the adjectival passive facts). So V.V. could 
easily respond that pound  and roll provide an Undergoer ro le (even if they are 
activities), and this renders unnecessary the fake reflexive. 
 
(30) L&amp;R claim that V.V. also fails to account for the fact that fake objects are 
excluded with unaccusatives. V.V.s sugge stion (again, invoki ng aspect) doesnt 
work for cases like: 
 
 a.      * The boulders rolled the hillside bare. 
 b.      * The rice slowly cooked the pot black.  
 But again  what was L&amp;Rs account? They  ruled out these examples by Burzios 
generalization. Does BG entail a syntactic account of unaccusatives (the point that 
L&amp;R are trying to make)? It seems th at the following two statements are 
consistent: i) no Actor  no accusative case (RRGs BG); ii) the subject of 
unaccusatives is underived. In other words  the lack of accusative case for the 
fake object doesnt, in and of itself, demonstrate that  the subject is derived.  
 
 A brief outline of L&amp;Rs linking theory  
 (31) 
UThe causative alternation U 
  
 a. He opened the door / The door opened 
 b. She broke the glass / the glass broke 
  
UL&amp;R U: The lexical conceptual structure of th e unaccusatives is the same as that of 
the transitives; namely, a bi-eventive st ructure (x CAUSE y BECOME z). It is 
only at the level or argument structure (the input to syntax) that the Causer 
argument is eliminated in unaccusa tives of the alternating type. 
 (32) 
UUnergative verbs dont alternate U 
 
 a. Mary shuddered / *He shuddered Mary / He made Mary shudder 
 b. Mary smiled / *He smiled Mary / He made Mary smile.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
6 (24) URP as delimiters U 
 
 Some verbs encode  an end point ( delimited, telic ); others dont ( undelimited, 
 atelic ). The in/for X minutes  test distinguishes the two types. 
  a. Mary ate grapes for/*in an hour. 
 b. Mary built the  house in/*for a year.  
 An object specifying quantity or a goal PP delimit the event: 
  c. Mary ate a bunch of grapes in/*for an hour. 
 d. Mary pushed the cart (to the shed). 
  RP are similar  they can delimit events: 
 
 e. The waiter wiped the table in/for two minutes. 
 f. The waiter wiped the tabl e dry in/*for two minutes. 
  (25) 
UProposed constraint U: An event may have at most one delimiter. 
 Verbs of inherently directed motion are achievements , encoding an inherent 
delimiter.  the lack of resultativ e reading in (23b). The on ly delimiters allowed 
are those further specifying the inherent one: 
 
 a. We arrived at the airport. 
  Objects of transitives describing inherent ly directed motion are also bad with RP: 
  b.     * Mary took/brought Bill breathless.  
 More evidence for competition for the delimiter slot: 
  c. We ran the soles off our shoes (*into the town). 
 d. We ran (*the soles off our shoes) into the town. 
 (26) Unaccusatives with inherent non-locational end state do allow RP: 
  a. The bottle broke open.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
  
Note : These fake objects cant ap pear on their own (* Dora shouted herself, *The dog 
 barked him, *He drank himself ).  
 
(8) Subject of passive
 a. The floor  has been swept clean . 
 b. She was shaken awake  by the earthquake. 
 
(9) Subject of u naccusative
 a. The river  froze solid . 
 b. The curtain  rolled open  on the court. 
 
(10) Subject of middle
 a. This table  wipes clean easily. 
 b. This pumpkin  cuts to pieces easily. 
 
(11) *Fake-objects of unaccusative
 a.      * The boulders rolled the hillside bare . 
 b.      * The river froze itself  solid.  
 
(12) Explanation : In all the good cases, th e resultative is  predicated of the underlying 
 direct object, whether selected by the ve rb or not, as predicted by the DOR. I n 
 (4) it is predicated of an underlying s ubject, in (5) of an  oblique object. The 
 problem  with (11) is orthogonal  un accusatives dont license direct objects 
 (Burzios generalization).   
 
(13) A potential objection to DOR : Perhaps the rele vant ge neralization is sem antic 
 after all; for exam ple  resu ltativ es can only be predicated of bare internal 
 argum ents. The im plication would be that the  fake objects  in (6)-(7 ) are in fact 
 genuine argum ents of the unergative verb. In other wo rds  the argum ent stru cture 
 of unergatives is expanded in the resultative construction. 
  
That cant be true 
 
(14) Real internal argum ents can be externalized, fake ones cant. 
 
 a. This m etal pounds flat easily.    middle  
 b.      * This baby ticks awake easily.  
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 Note : If the COS argum ent happens to be ex ternal, the D OR will not hold; f or 
exam ple, in adjectival passives: 
 
 a. a wiped-clean table / *a  drunk-dry teapot       adjectival passive  
 b. He felt rubbed raw. 
 
(21) A crossling uistic puzzle : If the fake object of an unergativ e is not an argum ent 
 of the verb, why is it licensed in  som e languages but not in others?  
 
 a. The soprano broke / sang the glass wines to pieces. 
 b. zameret ha-sopran shavra / *shara et kosot ha-yayin li-rsisim .        Hebrew  
  singer the-sopran broke / *sang ACC  glasses the-wine to-p ieces 
 
(22) Comment: Does the argum ent from resultative constructions support a syntactic  
analys is of unaccusatives ? L&amp;R seem to believe it does:  
 
 If the s ingle argum ent of an unacc usativ e verb  were a D-s tructure 
subject, then this argum ent woul d not m eet the requirement that 
the argum ent undergoing a change of state be a direct object or 
governed by the verb. For the sa me reasons, the COS Linking Rule 
would be violated if a resultativ e phrase were predicated o f this 
argum ent directly (p.52).   
 
 Response : One can accept the generalization th at RP are predicated of the COS 
argum ent without  accepting the COS Linking Rule . While there m ay be good 
reasons to adopt this rule, the licensing of resultatives is not one of them .  
 
Semantic r estrictions 
 
(23) The DOR is only a neces sary, not a s ufficient con dition for th e occurrence  of a RP 
 with an unaccusative verb. Some unaccusatives resist RP. 
 
 a. Carla rem ained in the country bored.  stative  
 b. Willa arrive d breath less.    inheren tly directed motio n 
 
  The secondary predicates here  only have depictive readings. 
 
 
5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Head Movement (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ho_head_mvt/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT/, F all /2/0/0/3 /9d/. /* L a maison est autr e /`The house is other/'e/. L/'autr e maison /. /. /. vs/. /* L a maison autr e /. /. /.Where do es N raise to/?/(/5/3/) Un gr os c amion r ougeA big truc k red
/(F renc h/)/(/5/4/) a/. /[DP
Il mio Gianni /]The m y Gianni/`My Gianni/'
/(Italian/)b/. /* /[DP
mio Gianni /]c/. /[DP
Gianni mio /]/(/5/5/) hu ir/-r ag /
 gel il/-kbirbrother the/-man the/-big/`the man/'s big brother/' // /`the big man/'s brother/'
/(Maltese/)/(/5/6/) b eyt ha/-i
Rha/-go dolhouse the/-man the/-big/`the man/'s big house // /`the big man/'s house/'
/(Hebrew/)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Psych Verbs (cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln17psych_pesets/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>25</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 i. The news cheered Sue *(up) about her plight. 
 h. The article r eally p issed Bill of f at M ary. 
 
(20) A triv ial so lution : Perhaps the distinctions am ong Causer, Target and Subject 
Matter, although sem antically real, are them atically invisible. In other words, -
theory is too coarse-gra ined to distinguish among them, but still bans the 
cooccurence of two nondistinct -roles (Them atic Diversity ). Com pare: 
 
 a.     * John ate the egg the candy.  
 
 Egg is a natural kind, candy  is an artifact. That distinction, although crucial in 
other cognitive dom ains, plays no role in  syntax. Both objects count as them es, 
and the sentence violates Them atic Diversity.  
 
 Pesetskys response: i) Denying a them atic distinction betw een Causer and T/SM 
eliminates  the them atic solution to  the linking problem , and forces a syntactic 
solution  (unaccusativity), which was  shown to  be false.  ii) On the s implest view , 
if Causer is nondistinct from  both Target  and S M, then the latter two should be 
also m utually nondistinct. But in fact they can cooccur: 
 
 b.  Sue is angry  with Bill ab out the pa rty. 
 c. John is irritated at Mary about the m istake. 
 
Enter z ero morphmes 
 
(21) ObjExp verbs are sem antically and morphologically com plex. They arise from  a 
combination of a SubjE xp bound root and a cau sative affix: annoy  = cause X to  
be annoyed. annoy : [[be-annoyed]-CAUSE]  
 CAUSE is overt in Japane se; in English its m ostly covert, but som etimes overt: 
 
 - en (frighten, sadden ); en- (enrage, embitte r); -ify ( terrify, h orrify).  
 
(22) Zero m orphology, adding sem antic com plexity, is also involved in a restriction on 
argum ent expression in suggestiv e predicates (Higgins 1973): 
 
 a. John was angry at the guests. 
 b. Johns tone was angry (*at the guests). 
 c. John was nervous about the exam . 
 d. Johns behavior was nervous (*about the exam ). 
 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 a.     Odd noises were contin ually s caring / ??  depressing Sue. 
 b.     Sue was continually being scared / ?? depressed by odd noises. 
 
 In fact, the progress ive isnt a great test  for (no n-)stativity, because clearly stativ e 
verbs ac cept it: 
 
 c. Karen is finally understanding this proof. 
 d. Donald is finding your accusations ludicrous. 
 
 This spec ial interp retation ( intermediate evaluation)  isnt com patible with 
passive, for som e reason: 
 
 e.    ?? This proof is fi nally being understood by Karen. 
 f.      * Your  accusations are being found ludicrou s by Donald. 
 
 Notice tha t the verbs in  (c-d) a re not unaccusative. The fact that their passives 
appear to be stative (and hence, adj ectival) underm ines the argum ent that the 
contras t in (a-b) is due to unaccusativity. 
 
(8) More evidence 
 
 Disam biguation by much  
 a. In those d ays, Bill wa s often bein g (*m uch) frightened by one thing o r another. 
 
 P-selec tion 
 a. Sue was continually being scared by/*of sudden noises. 
 b. Sue was continually being annoyed by/*with sounds from  the cellar. 
 
Verb raisin g in Dutch and class II passives 
 
(9) In the perfect tense, V and Aux m ay opti onally invert. This is  possible also with 
stative (SubExp) verbs, and in the passive. 
 
 a. dat Jan zijn vader nooit echt gekend heeft / heeft gekend 
  that Jan his f ather never really known has / has known 
  that Jan has never really known his father 
 
 b. dat hem  de P.C. hooft-prijs to egekend werd / werd toegekend. 
  that to-him  the P.C. Hoof t prize awa rded was / was awarded  
  that the P.C. Hoof t prize was awarded to him  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
from  the verb. But stru ctural accus ative would  violate BG. ii) If the T heme is an 
argum ent of the verb and Exp is the subject  of a sm all claus e, the latter doesnt c -
command the for mer even at DS.  
 
(12) Japanese analogues are morphologically com plex, with a CAUSE m orphem e. 
 
 a. John-ga zibun 1-no kurum a-o kowas ita koto-ga Mary 1-o odorok-ase-ta. 
  John. NOM  self.GEN car.ACC broke f act.NOM  Mary. ACC surprised- CAUSE-past  
  The fact that John broke herselfs car surprised Mary 
 
 Moreover, the Them e  really a cause r  behaves like an underived subject 
accord ing to  Miyagawas (1989) test; it doesnt strand floatin g quantifiers.  
 
(13) Backward binding generalization 
 A Causer argum ent of a predicate m ay behave as if c-comm ande d by an 
argum ental DP governed by the predicate. To be continued 
 
(14) True unaccu sativ e ObjExp verbs: Class III
 
 These verbs  select essere , for m no passives (verbal or adjectival), and their 
postverbal subjects m ay launch ne-cliticization (like una ccusativ es, an d unlike 
unlike c lass II) : 
 
 a. Ne1 sono piacuti a Maria solo due t 1. 
  of-them  pleased to Maria only two 
 b.      * Ne 1 hanno preoccupato Gianni solo due t 1. 
  of-them  worried Gianni only two 
 
(15) Following B&amp;R (and P&amp;P 1984), Pesets ky adm its that accusative case is 
compatible with unac cusativity. A f ew ObjExp verbs,  which ar e sup erficially 
trans itive, are in fact und erlyingly un accusative. 
 
 a.      * W e were escaped by Sm iths nam e for som e reason. 
 b.      * Panini was eluded by the correct generalization. 
 c.      * Mary wasnt appealed to by the play. 
 d.     * John was m attered to by this. 
 
 
 
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
(4) Only verbal passives can host clitics in reduced relatives. 
  [ex. (14) in B&amp;Rs handout] 
 
 Pesetsky : The by-phras e cant cliticize to any passive participle in a reduced 
 relative; theres nothing special about class II verbs. Since one cant deny that the 
 other verbs have verbal passives, the ba n on cliticization here  cant m otivate an 
 adjec tival analysis for class II passives.  
 
 a. la sola perso na che ne  s tata u ccisa. 
  The only person that by-it was killed 
 b.      * la sola persona uccisane. 
 
(5) Only verbal passives allow the auxiliary venire com e 
 [ex. (15) in B&amp;Rs handout] 
 
 Pesetsky : venire  diagnozed eventive predicates, not verbal ones. Class II verbs 
 vary in their degree of toleranm ce to  eventiv e readings; som e are perfect.  
 
 a. Gianni venne spaventato da questa prospettiva alle cinque. 
  Gianni cam e frightened b y this perspective at five 
 
(6) Class II p assives in Eng lish: Can or must  be adje ctiva l? 
 
 Modifiers like very/much  selec t the adjec tival passive: 
 
 a. The idea was m uch dicussed in the 70. 
 b. We (*m uch) discussed the idea in the 70. 
 
 Adjectiv al passives are s tative; s tatives are incompatib le with the progr essive: 
 
 c. The book was still being (*very) abridged when the order cam e through to 
  publish it in its en tirety. 
 
(7) Some class II ve rbs (depress, worry, bore)  are stative alread y in the active, hence 
their incom patibility with the progressive in the passi ve is uninform ative about 
their V vs. Adj status. Other verbs ( scare, alarm, shock ) clear ly have event ive  
hence, verba l  passives: 
 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
   
 Adjectiv es never raise: 
 c. dat Jan de hele dag boos was / *was boos. 
  that Jan the whole day angry was / *angry was 
  that Jan was angry the whole day 
 
 Crucially, passives of class II m ay raise (the by-phrase forces the verbal passive): 
 
 d. dat ik door het college geboeid werd / werd geboeid. 
  that I by the classes fascinated became 
  that I got fascinated by the classes 
 
(10) Class I I doesnt a llow a ribitra ry pro, a diagnostic of external argum ents  
 [ex. (10) in B&amp;Rs handout] 
 
 Pesetsky : arbitrary pro (of the existential kind) requires an agent, not an  extern al 
argum ent. Therefore, its com patible  with an agentiv e unaccusative and 
incom patible with a non agentiv e transitive (de spite the exter nal argum ent). 
 
 a. Sono vinuti a riparare il lavandino. 
  Som ebody cam e to fix the sink 
  [Note: essere  and ra tionale clause]  
 
 b.      * Ieri hanno ricevuto una telefonata. 
  They received a phone call yesterday 
  [Note: avere  and nonagentive verb] 
 
Backw ard binding and causatives 
 
(11) Backward binding is licensed not onl y by ObjExp verbs, but by any causative verb 
(explicit or not): 
 
 a. Each others supporters worried Freud and Jung. 
 b. Pictures of each other make us happ y. 
 c. Pictures of him self give John the creeps. 
 d. Each others criticism s forced John and Mary to confront their problem s. 
 e.      ?   Each others stupid remarks eventually killed John and Mary. 
 
 Problem s for B&amp;R : i) E xp is the causee in (b,c), which is not an argument of the 
verb. If inherent case depends on -marking, Exp cant get inherent accusative 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Causer, Target, Subject Matter 
 
(16) If the unaccusativ e analysis fails fo r most ObjExp verbs, and if UTAH is valid, 
then we m ust refine our them atic analysis. 
 
 a. Bill was ang ry at the article in the Tim es.  Target of E motion  
 b. The article in the Tim es angered Bill.   Causer  
 
 Pesetsky: ( b) is approp riate even if  Bill thinks the article is splendid the article 
does caus e Bill to be an gry, and pos sibly angry at som eone or som ething, but h e 
is not necessarily angry at the article itself. 
 
(17) T/SM  Causer ;  (Causer  T/SM) 
 
 a. John worried about Marys poor h ealth, but Marys poor health ddsnt 
 worry John.  [contradiction] 
 b. Marys poor health worried John, but John didn t worry about Marys 
 poor health.  [noncontradiction] 
  (Johns could worry about the possibility of an epidem ic) 
 
(18) Thematic h ierarchy : Causer &gt;&gt; Ex perien cer &gt; &gt; Target/Subject Matter 
 
 Thats  the solution to the linking prob lem, without invoking unaccusativity. 
 
The T/SM restriction 
 
(19) Although Causer and T /SM are sem antically distinct, they cant cooccur: 
 
 a.    * The ar ticle in the Times angered Bill at the governm ent. 
 b.    * The Chinese d inner satisf ied Bill with h is trip to Beijing . 
 c.    * Som ething Bill h ad said both ered Mary ab out her f uture. 
 d.    * The distant rum bling fri ghtened Mary of another tornado. 
 
 Crucially, the intended m eaning is perf ectly intelligib le, and in f act render ed 
gramm atically with pe riphrastic cau satives: 
 
 e.   The article in the Tim es made Bill angry at the go vernm ent. 
 
 Verb  particle psych verbs are also  exempt from the T/SM res triction : 
 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 Note : In the res t of chapter  3 Pe setsky argues, following Fabb (1988), that 
Myerss generalization is epiphenom enal (and indeed, violated by the suffixes  er 
and  able) and that the relevant generalizations  constrain the type of affixes that 
can attach to CAUS  rather than CAUS  itself. He devises a com plex system  where 
each nom inal suffix is lexically as sociated  with  distribu tional restrictio ns. The 
fact that zero m orphemes, including CAUS , disallow further a ffixation is thereby 
decom posed into m any sm aller fact s about specific nom inalizers. 
 
What about the T/SM restriction? (fragments from chapter 6) 
 
(27) The gist  
 
 a.    * The ar ticle in the Times angered Bill at the governm ent. 
 
 i. VP-structu cre is a cascad e. 
 ii. Causer is generated as the lo west argum ent, introduced by CAUS. 
 iii. CAUS is an af fix that must attach to V. 
 iv. In the cascade of (a), CAUS and V are separated by P ( at). 
 v. The structu re violates either the Head Movem ent Constrain t or the Stray 
 Aff ix Filter. 
 
(28) Evidence for cascades: C- command &amp; coordination  
 
 a. John spoke to Mary about these people 1 in each others 1 houses. 
 b. Mary danc ed in no city with any pro minent citiz en. 
 c. Sue will speak to Mary about [linguis tics on Friday] and  
  [philosophy on Tuesday]. 
 
 Chapter 5 of Zero Syntax  provides am ple evidence for right-branching VP 
struc tures all the way to the bot tom. System atically, righ tward  downward.   
  Prepositions (about  in (a), in in (b)) are usually ignored for c-comm and. 
Pesetsky p roposes to  take them  seriousl y. Bu t if prepos itions are vis ible to c-
command, the only way they wont interfere in  (a,b) is if they are detached from 
their objects . This will also allow tw o DPs to  share a prepos ition, as in (c). Thats 
the m otivation to  cascades.  
  Obviously, cascades destroy constitue ncy relations that are considered 
vital for -marking and for m ovem ent. As t o -marking, Pesetsky devises a 
system  where a head can select either its s ister or the Spec of its sister. As to 
move ment, Pesetsky assum es that parallel to th e cascade s tructure, a traditional 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Psych Verbs and Zero Syntax 
 
Idan Landau 
 
 
(1) The Linking problem  (not again) 
 
 a. We puzzled over Sues rem arks. 
 b. Sues rem arks puzzled us. 
 
 Remember the 3 options: i) (a) and (b ) are them atically identical,  one is 
 syntactically derived (B elletti &amp; Rizzi 1988); ii) (a) and (b) are thematically 
 distinct, neither is synt actically un derived ; iii) (a ) and (b) are th ematically 
 identical, neither is syntactica lly underived (abandons UTAH).  
 
 Pesetsky : (i) is the corr ect appro ach. 
 
Against the unaccusative analysis 
 
(2) The unaccusative analysis involves two assum ptions: 
 
 a. The subject position of ObjExp verbs is nonthem atic. 
 b. The subject of ObjExp verbs is moved from  an object position. 
 
 Pesetsky : Property  (a) only hold s for a sm all subset of ObjExp verbs. Property (b) 
 holds for all of the m. Does that im ply that som e ObjExp verbs involve move ment 
 to a -position?  Unfortunately, yes. 
 
(3) Are psych p assives of class II n ecess arily adjectival? 
 
 Recall that B&amp;R had to  make this clai m, since unaccusativ es dont have verbal 
 passives. Pesetsky argues: 
 
 a. Class II verbs do have verbal passives.  
 b. Many unaccusatives dont have adjectival passives (so its not clear why  
  class II verbs should).  
 
  i. departed travelers, a fallen leaf, drifted snow. 
  ii.       *an already occu rred event, * recently gro wn interes t,  
            *a frequently paused m achine, *often stunk paint. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 Pesetsky : If these facts fall togeth er with the T/SM rest riction, then Them atic 
Diversity has nothing to offer;  the subject and ob ject in  (b,d ) clearly b ear distin ct 
semantic roles.  
 
 Bill was ang ry ; Bills m anner was [angry +SUG] (sugges ted anger).  
 
On the reality of bound psych roots  
 
If annoy  = annoy+CAUS, we  expect to find annoy in other, noncausative 
environm ents. The evidence com es from nom inalizations. 
 
(23) Class II verbs dont have causati ve nom inalizations (Lakoff 1970). 
 
 a. Bills contin ual agitatio n about the exam  was silly. 
 b. Marys constant annoyance about /at/with us got on our nerves. 
 c.      * The exam s continual ag itation of  Bill was silly. 
 d.      * Our constant annoyance of Mary got on our nerves. 
 
 Note : These are not result nouns, but argum ent-taking nouns, that sim ply lack any 
causative fo rce. The question is why. If annoyance  is directly derived from  annoy , 
why is it not causative?  
 Answer : annoyance  is not causativ e because it is directly derived fro m the root  
annoy, which is itself not causative. Thats  evidence for the real ity of this root. 
 Question : Why cant [ annoy+CAUS] be the input to nom inalization?  
 
(24) More im possible nom inalizations 
 
 a. your anger / your rem arks were angry / *your rem arks anger 
 b. her optim ism / her expression was optim istic / *her expressions optim ism  
 
(25) The (im )possible nom inalizations have the following for m: 
 
 a. [[[SubjExp-predicate V](*CAUS)] nom inalize r] 
 b. [[[SubjExp-predicate A](*SUG)] nom inalizer] 
  
(26) Myers s gen eraliza tion 
 Zero-derived words do not perm it the affixation of  further derivational 
morphem es. 
 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
left-branching structure exists (layered syntax), which is targeted by movem ent. 
In effect, ev ery sentence has a dual life  layered or cascade.  
 
(29) Important claim : The Ca user introduced by CAUS is the low est argum ent. 
 
 Analogy:  a. Sue yelled out of frustration. 
   b. John died of consum ption. 
 
 Since CAUS is a verbal affix, it m ust raise to V . Movem ent of CAUS is blocked 
by any intervening n on-affixal P (recall that prepos itions do intervene in  
cascades), and skipping P is blocked by the Head Movem ent Const raint. See 
structure [513], p. 1999.  
 
(30) More evid ence: Oherles effect 
 
 a. Interviewing Nixon gave Mailer a book. 
 b.      * Interviewing Nixon gave a book to Mailer. 
 
 The causative sense involves affixation of CAUS to give, blocked in (b) by the 
intervening to. Independen t eviden ce for the pres ence of C AUS in causativ e 
double object verbs comes from  the (now fa miliar) lack of nom inalization s: 
 
 c. Bills /*our efforts gift of a new building 
 d. Sues/*the sm iles rental of the apartm ent 
 
Residue: Backw ard binding  and thematic subjects 
 
Because the Causer in class II o riginates be low the Exp, backwards bind ing is explained ; 
just like in B&amp;Rs analysis, condition A is  satisfied at DS. Mo reover, any causer will 
have this property, not just in class II predicates.   
 
(31) A paradox : Pesetsky has destroyed the unaccus ative analys is. He now seem s to 
resurrect it to account f or backward bi nding and the T/S M restriction (both of 
which require a low, internal Causer).  
 
 Solution : CAUS has an identical counterpart  on V, which projects an external 
Causer (see ex. [530], p. 209). CAUS affi xation is an instan ce of checking. 
Movem ent of the Causer from  one -position to another is  licensed because the 
two -roles are identical.               
10</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Psych Verbs&#160; (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln16psych_b_r/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 
(10) Class I a llows aribitra ry pro, class II doesnt. 
 
 a. Evidentem ente, in questo paese per anni pro hanno tem uto il terrem oto. 
  Evidently, in this country peopl e feared the earth quake for years. 
  
 b.      * Evidentem ente, in questo paese per anni pro hanno preoccupato il governo. 
  Evidently, in this country peopl e worried the gov ernm ent for years. 
 
Causative constructions 
 
(11) Burzio (1986) has show n that derived subjects aren t possible under the causative 
construction. 
 
 a. Gianni ha fatto telefonare Mario. 
  Gianni m ade m ario call. 
 
 b.      * Gianni ha fatto essere licenziato Mario. 
  Gianni m ade Mario be fired. 
 
 Classes I an d II dif fer in this r espect  class II is  unaccusativ e:  
 
 c.      * Questo lo ha fatto preocc upare/comm uovere/attrarre  ancora pi a Mario. 
  this him  has m ade worry/move/attract even m ore to Mario 
  This m ade Mario worry/m ove/attract him  even more 
 
 d. Questo lo ha fatto apprezzare /temere/amm irare ancora pi a M ario. 
  this him  has m ade estim ate/fear/adm ire even m ore to Mario 
  This m ade Mario e stimate/fea r/adm ire him even m ore 
 
(12) Problem s
 
 Burzio as sumed that ca usativ e complem ents tha t assign da tive case  to th e exte rnal 
argum ent are full clausal projections. The embedded VP undergoes leftward 
move ment past the subject, giving rise to the V OS word or der. If the subject is 
derived, as with passive and unaccusativ e verbs,  the unbound trace in th e fronted  
VP yields ungramm aticality (irre pairable by reconstruction).  
  However, subsequent work (e.g., Guasti 1996, 1997) has established that 
the causativ e com plement is in fact subc lausal, lacking all f unctional projections 
where Aux/Neg/Tense are licens ed. If no movement to [Spec,IP] is involved in 
causative complem ents, then (11b,c) rem ain unexplained.  
 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 Landau (2002) : Causative form ation involves case alternations. In particular, the 
original case of the embedded direct object is suppresse d, and instead it is 
assigned s tructural accu sativ e case b y the m atrix causative v erb. If the case of the 
Exp. is obliq ue, this p rocess will b e blocked and the case alternation fail.   
 
Passive 
 
(13) If class II is  unaccusativ e, it sho uld not give ris e to pass ive (The 1AEX Law). 
Apparent class II pas sives m ust theref ore be adjectival (not derived by NP-
move ment).  
 
(14) Only verbal passives can host cl itics in reduced relatives (why?). 
 
 a. La notizia che gli  stata com unicata / ignota 
  The news that was communicated/unknown to him  
 
 b. La notizia com unicatagli / *ignotagli 
  The news communicated / *unknown to him  
 
 A da-phrase can be pronom inalized by the clitic ne, but not in a reduced relative 
of class II v erbs.  The passiv e particip le in th e reduced re lative is adje ctival  
There is no verbal passive for class II. 
 
 c. La sola persona che ne  affascinata.  
  The only person that is fascinated by it. 
 
 d. La sola persona affascin ata da questa prospettiva.  
  The only person that is fascinated by this perspective. 
 
 e.       * La sola persona affascinatane.  
  The only person that is fascinated by it. 
 
(15) Only verbal passives allow the auxiliary venire com e.  
 
 a. La porta /viene chiusa alle cinque. 
  The door is/com es closed at five [stative/eventive] 
 
 Class I pas sives are bu t class II arent com patible with venire : 
 
 b. Gianni viene tem uto / *preoccupato da tutti. 
  Gianni comes feared / *worried by everyone. 
 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
Psych Verbs and Unaccusativity 
 
Idan Landau 
 
 
(1) Class I: Exp NOM  Th ACC  
 a. Gianni tem e questo 
  Gianni fears this 
  
 Class II: Th NOM  Exp ACC  
 b. Questo preoccupare Gianni 
  this worr ies Gianni 
  
 Class III: Th NOM  Exp DAT 
 c.    i. Questo piace a Gianni. 
       ii.  A Gianni piace ques to. 
 
(2) The Linking Problem : The sam e -roles appear to be linked to different structural 
position s (but are they the identica l -roles ?). Note tha t the patte rn in (1 ) poses a 
problem  both for UTAH and for RUTAH.  
 
(3) Structu ral claim  of Belletti &amp; Rizzi (1988): Exp. Is al ways generated abo ve Th.  
 
 a. [S Gianni [ VP teme [NP questo]]]. 
 b. [S ec [ VP [V preoccupare/piace [ NP questo]] [ NP/PP (a) Giann i]]]  
 
 Surface order in (b) is derived by NP- movem ent to the su bject pos ition, as in 
passive/unaccusative derivations. In both (a) and (b), V -marks Th. And [V+Th] 
-marks the Exp. 
 
 B&amp;R : If we have independent evidence fo r (3b), then RUTAH is strongly 
supported; why would otherwise language learners bother to postulate underlying 
structures th at rev erse S -structures ?     
 
(4) Whats the role/locus of -theory in the gramm ar? 
 
 a. Grammatical pro cesses  may refer to sp ecific -roles (Aget, Patient, 
 Experiencer, etc.).   
 b. Specific -roles are only releva nt for the initial pro jection of argum ents 
 into DS. Beyond that, the gramm ar only refers to the distinction between 
 them atic/no nthem atic p osition s. Apparent sens itivity  to spec ific -roles is  
 an epiphenom enon of their differe nt structural realizations.   
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 
 b.      * A Giorgio, la gente non lo conosce. 
  to Giorgio, people not him  know 
 
 Other verbs, like inter essare interest, take eith er an  accusative or a dativ e Exp. 
 
(31) Comment
 
 B&amp;R de monstrate that Exp. objects arent  canonical objects. Their observations in 
fact extend to m any other languages. Their account posits two independent 
differences between canoni cal objects and Exp.: 
 
 a. Exp. is a second object (sister of V).  
 b. Exp. bears inherent case. 
 
 Notice that (a) and (b) are logicaly indepe ndent, which is a fl aw in the analysis. A  
natura l ques tion then arises: Is on e of the m superflous?  Can we explain all psych 
effects by reference to either (a) o r (b)? 
 
Class III verbs 
 
(32) Class III verbs select a dative Exp., the auxiliary essere , and surface in two word 
orders: 
 
 a. A Gianni  sem pre piaciuta la m usica. 
  to Gianni is alwa ys pleased the m usic  
 b. La m usica  sem pre piaciuta a Giann i. 
   Music always pleased G ianni 
 
 B&amp;R (1) : Perm utability of the dative fo llows from  case theory. Althoug h 
inherent case is assigned at  DS, it must be licensed at SS by a governing head. In 
the case of a dative, the governing head is the preposition a, so m oving the PP 
doesnt d isrupt case licensing. But an  accusativ e Exp. will be ungovern ed after 
move ment, hence it cant perm ute with the Them e. 
 
 Notes : i) A-bar m ovem ent can m ove accusa tive NPs (B&amp;R: vari ables can satisfy 
governm ent for case); ii) B&amp;R predict fr ee A-m ovem ent of PPs in any language. 
Thats m assively disconfirm ed. In fn. 33 they exclude preverbal dative Exp. i n 
French by the null subject param eter, that  doesnt allow rightward assignm ent of 
nominative case to the Them e. That still allows  impersonal dative sub jects (To-
me is cold).    
 
 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
(8) Comm ents &amp; problem s 
 
 a. B&amp;R are c orrect to po int out that  psych effe cts disappear in agentive 
 contexts. Thats a system atic patt ern that m any proposals ignore. W hats 
 special about psych verbs isnt inhere nt to the experiencer, but m ust be  
 due to the T h-Exp relation (as oppos ed to the Agent-Exp relation).  
  
 b. Still, senten ces lik e (7c) are m arginal even when no focus is placed on th e 
 anaphor and care is taken to guarantee nonagentivity. The exa mples are 
 worse with s tative verb s. 
 
  i. John and Mary accidentally startled each other in the dark. 
  ii.      * John  and Mary rather concerned each oth er in their y outh. 
 
 c. What about class III? Contrary to B&amp;Rs prediction, anaphor ic clitics are OK: 
 
   i. Gianni si piace. 
   Gianni likes himself. 
 
  Landau (2002) : si abso rbs accus ative/dative cas e, but no t oblique case.  If 
 Exp. In class II bears oblique case  (masked as accusative), then the  
 contras t with class III fo llows.  
 
Arbitrary pro 
 
(9) On the nonreferential reading, 3pl pro in Italian takes an  arbitrary  read ing. This is  
possible with deep subjects, but not with derived ones. 
 
 a. pro hanno telefonato a casa m ia 
  Somebody called m y place 
 
 b. pro hanno visto Gianni in giardino. 
  Somebody saw Gianni in the garden. 
 
 c.      * pro sonno arrivati a casa m ia. 
  Somebody arrived at m y place. 
 
 d. * pro mi sonno sem brati m atti. 
  Somebody sem d to m e crazy 
 
 B&amp;R : Assum ing that In fl -marks the subject (via inh eritence from  VP) , we can 
say that  pro in subject position can have arb interpretation when the licen sing 
Infl -marks it.   
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
(33) Exp. in (32a) is a subject, not a topic  
 
 a. Exp.-V-Th. Is the unm arked word order in class III. 
 b. Preverbal E xp. doesnt create a brrier, preverbal Ind. Obj does. 
 
  i)      ??  I libri ch e a Gianni ho dato sono questi. 
   the books that to Gianni I gave are these 
   
  ii) I libri che a Gianni  sono piaciuti sono questi. 
   the books that to Gian ni are pleased are these 
 
 c. Preverbal E xp. can be a negative qua ntifier, dislocated Ind. Obj cant. 
 
  i)       * A nessuno gli hanno detto di andare al diavolo. 
   to nobody to-him  they said to-go to hell 
 
  ii)      ? A nessuno gli piace esser m andato al diavolo. 
   to nobody to-him  pleases to-be sent to hell 
   [marginality  due to clitic-doubling of  an A-position) 
 
Lexical rep resentation s 
 
(34) A verbal lexi cal entry co ntains : 
 
 a. Unordered -grid. 
 b. Marking of the external argum ent (underscore). 
 c. Case-grid (inherent case only). 
 
(35) Mapping principle : Exp. is projected higher than Them e. 
 
Psych verb entries 
 
(36) a. teme re:  -grid      [Exp, Theme] 
    Case-grid [      ,         ] 
 
 b. preoccupare :  -grid      [Exp, The me] 
    Case-grid [ ACC,        ] 
 
 c. piacere :  -grid      [Exp, The me] 
    Case-grid [ DAT,        ] 
 
 These entries derive the desire d DS, given the m apping in (35). 
 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 B&amp;R advocate (b), which is indeed mo re desireable on restrictiveness grounds. 
 
(5) Argum ents for structu re (3b): i) Th e subject of class II/III verbs behaves like a 
derived subject; ii) The object (E xp.) in class II verbs doesnt behave like a 
canonical direct object. 
 
Anaphoric cliticiz ation 
 
(6) Deep subjects can bind anaphoric  clitics, derived subjects cant.  
 
 a. Gianni si  fotografato. 
  Gianni himself photographed 
 
 b.      * Gianni si  stato affidato. 
  Gianni to-him self was entrusted 
 
 c.      * Gianni si sem bra sim patico. 
  Gianni to-him self see ms nice 
 
 Explanation : All possible parses of [NP i  si i  t i ] violate the Chain Condition. 
 
(7) Class I allows anaphoric cl iticization, cla ss II doesnt. 
 
 a. Gianni si amm ira. 
  Gianni himself admires 
  
 b.      * Gianni si comm uove. 
  Gianni himself moves 
 
 [Note that (b) is OK under the non-psych reading, or the inc ohative psych reading 
Gianni got moved about som ething]. 
 
 Full anapho rs are m arginal: 
 
 c.     *? Gianni preoccupare se stesso. 
 
 B&amp;R : Stress obviates the intervention of  the anaphor. Focused anaphors becom e 
binding visible only at LF, hence w ouldnt disrupt chain for mation (which 
applies at SS). Of course, si cant b e stress ed. Furtherm ore, agentiv e readings are 
expected to be OK, since the agent is generated above the E xp; see [17].   
 
 
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
(16) Some class II verbs do not have regular participial form s, as in  (b), an d instead  
have only irregular adjectival form s (c) 
 
 a. Le sue idee m i stufano/stancano/entusiasm ano. 
  His ideas tire/excite me 
 
 b.      * Sono stufato/stancato/ entusiasm ato dalle sue idee.   
 I am tired/ex cited by h is ideas 
 
 c. Sono stufo/stanco/entus iasta dalle sue idee.    
 I am tired/ex cited by h is ideas 
              
 B&amp;R : According to the Blocking Principle, an irregular form blocks the regular 
form. Since the irregular for m is una mbiguously adjectival, the blocked participial 
form must also be adjectival, o therw ise no com petition shou ld arise. This implies 
that the verbs in (16) have no verbal passives. 
 
(17) Some psych passives resist the regular da-phrase and only occur with special 
prepositions. The occurrence of idiosync ratic preposition s is a ha llmark of  
adjectival passives, which are lexically derived (cf. amused by/at  X). 
 
 a. Gianni  in teressato a/* da Maria. 
  Gianni is interes ted to/*by Maria  
 
 b. Gianni  appassionato di/*dalla poesia. 
  Gianni is fond of/*by poetry 
                     
 Note : Argum ents (16)-(17) are indeed conclusive, but apply to a s mall subset of  
class II verbs. One needs m ore general argum ents.  
 
Backw ard binding 
 
(18) Its an old  observation that an exp eriencer object can b ind in to the them e subject, 
in apparent violation of the c-command requirem ent on binding: 
 
 a.   Questi pettegolezzi su di s pr eoccupano Gianni pi di ogni altra cosa. 
       These gossips about him self worry Gianni m ore than anything else 
 
 b.* Questi pettegolezzi su di s descrivono Gi anni m eglio di ogni biografia ufficiale. 
       These gossips about him self descri be Gianni better than any official biography 
  
 Given structure (3b), the puzzle of (18a) is solved: Condition A is m et at DS, 
where the E xp does c-comm and the Th. Sim ple transitives, like (18b), cant avail 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
(37) Towards a deeper exp lanation : Why do we find only these options?  
 
 A. W hy cant th e Them e in cla sses II and III b e externa l? 
 B. W hy cant the Exp in cl asses II an d III be exte rnal? 
 C. W hy mus t the Exp in  class I be ex ternal? 
 
(38) Answer to (A) : The ext ernal argument  is the highest on the -hierarchy. An 
external Them e would be them atically higher than Exp., in violation of (35). 
 
(39) Answer to (B) : An exte rnal a rgument is not go verned by V (its VP-external). 
Inherent case is assigned by V under gove rnment. Given that Exp bears inherent 
case in classes II and III, it m ust be internal.  
 
 Note : i) If external argument s are gener ated inside VP, then theyre governed by 
V; ii) B&amp;R  dont address the m ore funda mental question  why must Exp in 
classe s II an d III be ar inherent case ?  
 
(40) Answer to (C) : One argum ent in class I m ust get structural accusati ve case ( since 
no inherent case is lexically specified) . By Burzios generalization, the other 
argum ent must be external. It  has to be Exp, given (35). 
 
 Note : B&amp;R m anage to reduce all the syntactic differenc es between  the thre e 
classes to minim al stipulations about th eir Case grids. The next obvious question 
to ask is  can these stipulations be derived from  som ething deeper?  
 
(41) Question : Why are psych effects gone with agentive verbs?  
 Answer : Agent is intr insic ally ex terna l, so Exp will be intern al, and BG 
guarantees that structu ral case is ava ilable for it. But what excludes  inherent case 
on an agentive class II/III verb ? And do B&amp; R assum e two dif ferent lex ical entries 
for agentive and non agentive uses of the sam e verb, with different Case grids?  
 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 
 b.     ?? Que sto fatto ne preoccupa molti. 
   this fact of-them  worries m any 
 
(25) Problem  1: If the accusative case o n the Exp. is standard structural case, its not 
clear why it cant b e assigned to th e Th eme, allowing the Exp to rais e to the  
subject: 
 
 a. Questo 1 preoccupa t 1 Gianni. 
  This worries Gianni. 
 
 b.      * Gianni 1 preoccupa questo t 1. 
  Gianni worr ies this 
 
(26) Problem  2: Class II verbs assig n accusativ e case, but are shown to be 
unaccusativ e. Thats a v iolation of Burzios generalization. 
 
(27) Solving both problem s at once:  The case of the experiencer is inherent ! 
 
 a. Inheren t case is asso ciated with a -role. If Exp. bears inherent case in 
 virtue of its -role, this case cant be suppre ssed (the Projecti on Principle). 
 (25b) would then involve a doubly case-m arked chain.  
 b. Burzios generalization applies to structural  accusative only. 
 
(28) Consequences
 
 a. Seperation of morphological from abstract (structura l) case; not all 
 accusatives are alike (e.g., quirky accusatives in  Iceland ic, accusative  
 prepositional objects in Germ an).  
 b. Classes II and III are brought together ; in both Exp. bear s inherent case  
 (ACC or DAT).   
 c. Revision of Aux-selection rule 
  Old rule: No external argum ent  essere  
  New rule: Capacity to as sign accus ative (inheren t or stru ctural)  avere   
 
(29) More evid ence for inherent case
 
 Beninc (19 86): W hen dislocated, the Exp. of class II verbs can surf ace as a 
 dative  as sociated with an accusative cl itic. This option  is not av ailable fo r 
 standard accusative objects , as in class I verbs: 
 
(30) a. A Giorgio, questi argomenti non lhanno convinto. 
  to Giorgio, these argum ents not him -have convinced 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
them selves of this solution, since the prom inence relation between their 
argum ents is not reversed from  DS t o SS. 
 
 (19) Where does binding theory apply?  B&amp;R: Anywhere (at least, condition A). 
 
 a. Each others 1 remarks annoyed John and Mary 1. 
 b. They 1 seemed to each o ther 1 t1 to be inte lligent.  
 c. Which picture of him self1 do you think that Bill 1 likes t 1 best? 
 
 (a) shows that condition A can  apply at DS. (b) shows th at it can apply at SS. (c) 
was taken to show that it can apply at LF  (after reconstructi on), but (c) can now 
be reanalysed as (a), nam ely, DS satisf action of condition A (before m ovement).  
 
 Note 1 : We have seen more sophisticated argum ents, in Lebeaux (1998), that 
condition A applies only at LF (the trapp ing effect). Still, the influential idea  
that inte rpretive cond itions can apply  derivationally originates in B&amp;R.  
 
 Note 2 : With copies (instead of traces), no appeal to DS is necessary. 
 
 Note 3 : Backward binding in fact defies a st ructural account (s ee first handout).  
 
(20) Conditions B &amp; C apply at SS . 
 
 DS satisfaction of conditions B/C isnt enough: 
 
 a.      * Him self1 worries John 1/him 1. 
 b. DS: [S ec [ VP [V worries himself1 ] John 1/him 1]].  
 
 The anaphor is bound at DS, and the na me/pronoun is free. Therefore, the S S 
violation at (1) is sufficient to m ake the sentence ungram matical. See also: 
 
 c.      * He 1 seem s to hi m1/Bills 1 sister [t 1 to be the best]. 
 
(21) Do conditio ns B &amp; C apply also at DS? Oblig atory reconstruction sugges t so: 
 
 a.    ?? [W hich picture of John 1]2 did he 1 like t 2 ? 
 b.     * Mary, [Johns 1 picture of whom] 2 he1 likes  t2, is very pretty. 
 
 B&amp;R indicate that if these are repres entative, then conditions B &amp; C m ust be  
satisfied both at DS and at SS. Today, we  would say that they apply everywhere. 
But recall the annoying contrast betw een A-move ment, which obviates these 
violations, and A-bar m ovement, whi ch doesnt. 
 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
 
 c. [Bills 1 sister] 2 seem ed to him 1 [t2 to be the best]. 
 
The experiencer is not a canonical object 
 
(22) Direct objects are transp arent to extraction, Exp isnt. 
 
 a. Il cand idato di cui quest a ragazza app rezza i sos tenitori. 
  the candidate of whom  this girl likes the supporters 
 
 b.      * Il candidato di cui quest a prospettiva im paurisce i sostenitori. 
   the candidate of whom  this perspective frightens the supporters 
 
 B&amp;R : This is rem iniscent of the islandhood of postverbal subject s of transitive 
and unergative verbs, and adverbial NPs: 
 
 c. Il rag azzo d i cui am avi la sorella. 
  the boy of whom  you-loved the sister 
 
 d.     ?? Il ragazzo di  cui to am ava la sorella. 
  the boy of whom  you contacted the sister 
  (The boy whose sister contacted you) 
 
 e.      * Il m ese di cu i Gia nni  to rnato  la pr ima settim ana. 
  the m onth of which Gianni cam  back the first week 
  (The m onth (on) the first w eek of which Gianni cam e back) 
 
(23) Barriers -type analys is  
 
 [ IP NP 0 [I [I  I [VP [VP V NP 1 (obj) ] NP 2 (subj) ]] NP 3 (adv)]]  
 
 Extrac tion f rom NP 1 crosses no barriers (it is L -marked); 
 Extrac tion f rom NP 2 crosses one barrier (NP 2); 
 Extrac tion f rom NP 3 crosses two barriers (NP 3 and IP); 
 Extrac tion f rom NP 0 crosses two barriers (NP 0 and IP). 
 
 The system  derives the reported 3-way distinction between (22c,d,e)! 
 [I ignore further refineme nts introduced by B&amp;R to distinguish (22d) from  other 
cases where crossing of a singl e barrier is accep table].  
 
(24) Weaker contrasts with ne-extraction (why? ). 
 
 a.     *?  Questo fatto ne preoccupa il presidente. 
  this f act of -it worrie s the presiden t 
8</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Case and Licensing (cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln13case_stackin/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Yoon (following Lasnik) : "Enlightened Greed" allows overt movement triggered 
by the target. Importantly, once strong Greed is abandoned, CUC does not follow 
anymore and multiple case is allowed. 
Note : This is in fact the modern view, which rejected Greed altogether. Still, 
multiple case is ruled out by Chomsky as case checking makes DPs "invisible" to 
further attraction. Chomsky discussed stru ctural case  perhaps inherent case is 
constantly visible (allowing the raising of Korean DAT NPs and Icelandic quirks). 
(25) Is case stacking optional ? [64] 
True optionality is problematic in economy-based grammar. Yoon argues that the choice between DAT or DAT-NOM is free since they proceed from different 
numerations (different case affixes).  
(26) Summary 
Multistratal derivational theories lead us to expect that multi-membered chains will 
have properties that set them apart from single-membered chains. Multiple case is exactly such a property. (Note: This  is compromised by [42e, 54, 55]). 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>b. Cuzco Quechua : Structural+Structural is possible. [8] 
Explanation : There is only one morphological slot for structural case in Korean.  
 Arguments : i) Other affixes compet e for this slot [29,30]. 
       ii) Honorific NOM can stack with simple NOM [31], since the former  
   occupies the slot of Inherent case (even though its  structural).  
Case resolution strategies 
(13) I-case must be realized.
 Icelandic [33]: S-case is suppressed ; Korean  [34]: S-case cooccurs with I-case. 
Yoon claims that the difference reflects a difference in the number of available 
case-slots; obviously, this cl aim requires independent support. 
 A potential counterexample [35] is dismissed; it is not DAT which is suppressed, 
but rather the psych predicate c-selects an  NP instead of a PP [fn. 8] (presumably, it 
is P that assigns DAT, not V). But if DAT is tied to the -role experiencer, it should 
be ineliminable. And why can't Icela ndic verbs c-select an NP in [33]?
 Note : Yoon's analysis of Icelandic quirky subj ects assumes that they always bear 
two cases, from which morphology chooses to spell out one.  
(14) Competition between two S-cases
 Korean : The higher S-case wins. 
 Argument : Embedded NOM subjects can corefe r with the matrix subject, but 
ECM ACC subjects cannot [ 36]. Yoon concludes that the former occupy a lower 
position, hence the lower case  (NOM) can only be realized in the lower position 
of the chain.
 Note : Actually, [36] doesnt show what its  supposed to  namely, that when two 
S-cases compete in Korean, the higher one  wins. For this to be shown, Yoon must 
demonstrate that NOM cant be realized  in the high position of the A-chain in 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Case Stacking and the Chain Condition 
Idan Landau 
(1) 	 The Chain Condition  (Chomsky 1986) 
In a maximal chain C={ 1, ,  n}, n occupies its unique -position and  1 
its unique case-marked position. 
TUC  Theta Uniqueness Condition ; CUC  Case Uniqueness Condition 
(2) 	 TUC is deriveable on the GB assump tion that all D-structure positions are 
thematic, and the -criterion. In fact, within minimalism, it is not clear how one 
can justify TUC; it doesnt seem to follo w from any property of the semantic 
interface. Brody (1993) proposed to  abandon TUC in the face of easy-to-please 
constructions; Hornstein proposes to aba ndon it for simple cases of obligatory 
control. 
Is CUC derivable? 
(3) a. Visibility doesn't entail CUC. 
b. Government entails CUC only with 2 stipulations: i) Only one chain  
member is governed by a case assigner; ii) this member is the head of 
 the chain. 
c. Without (b-i,ii), case uniqueness is lost. If government is  unique, all that  
is required is that a chain ha s at least one case position [p.108].  
(4) 	 Case stacking in Korean 
A subject (usually experiencer) appear s either with a dative/locative case, 
nominative case, or both [2]-[4].  
The nominals in these examples pass standard subject tests  passivization (under 
ECM verbs), triggering subject honorific agre ement, and binding of anaphors [5].  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>(22) 	 Apparent evidence for CUC 
[56,57]: Yoon claims that they violate ot her principles as well, hence can't be 
taken as evidence for CUC. But what "oth er principles"? Condition A is no longer 
relevant for NP-traces, the ECP is satisfied in both.  
(23) 	 [58a,59a]  Yoon admits a problem: They are allowed by RCC, excluded by 
CUC. 
a. 	 It seems to/strikes John that Bill is a jerk. 
b. * John 1 seems to/strikes t 1 that Bill is a jerk. 
 Yoon's account : Associate CPs have features to check, and in (a) they do it by 
covert LF raising to the expletive it. In (b) the checking position is taken by John. 
Note : If CPs do have features, then presumab ly they can be checked by I that had 
already checked against it, an expletive with 3rdSg. But then why should it be 
impossible when the first checking is against John ? 
[62,63] show that [58b,59b]  are OK in Korean.  
Notes : Two parametric differences are needed  to allow that: (i) Korean has no 
expletives; (ii) Korean CPs have no feat ures to check (to allow [62c]). This 
cooccurence seems accidental. Notice al so that the Minimal Link Condition 
should block [62c], given [62b]. 
 Prediction : [62c] should be impossible with case stacking on John. 
(24) 	 Making RCC compatible with minimalism
 The problem : If overt movement must be self-serving (strong Greed), once a case 
position has been reached, no overt movement can take place from it, since the 
DPs only need  case checking  ha s been fulfilled (Last Resort). 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Examples: [9]-[12]. Notice that RtO affects word-order; sometimes it even leaves a 
resumptive pronoun [14].  
(7) 	 Analysis of finite ECM : [Spec,CP] is an A-position, to which matrix ACC is 
assigned [15]. Due to locality (Subjacen cy), [Spec,CP] cant be skipped; due 
to the ban on improper movement, it cant be an A-bar position.  
Note : We still lack an account of why stacking of NOM-ACC or ABS-ERG is 
not attested. The answer will be  morphological, not syntactic. 
(8) 	 CUC violations in A-bar movement  [16,17]. 
(9)	 Possible alternatives to multiple case assignment 
a. 	 Optional NOM assignment in finite ECM (governed by economy). 
b. 	 There are two chains with unique cases, not a single chain with two cases. 
c. 	 CUC only applies to structural case (so stacking inherent+structural is OK). 
(10) 	 Against (9a)  [p.123, top] 
a. 	 In case stacking, the optional ity must have been suspended.  
  N o t e : Stacking is optional, whats the problem?  
b. 	 If the optionality is due to economy, Last Resort predicts that the realized 
case in an A-chain must always be th e one assigned to the head position. But 
in fact, in Farsi and Tongan the case of the tail position is realized (on the
 head position). 
(11) 	 Against (9b) 
(9b) entails control, not raising. But thematic independence refutes that. [19] 
Against (9c)  a morphol ogical filter on stacking 
(12) 	 a. Korean :  Inherent+Structural, *Str uctural+Structural  [28] 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>RtO. But all that [36a] shows is that NOM can be realized in the low position 
(presumably, the high position would be  ruled out by condition B).    
(15) Preservation of lower S-case : 
Farsi [37]; the evidence is very indir ect. Yoon assumes that NOM is assigned in 
the matrix clause even in the absence of agreement. But its equally plausible that 
NOM is not assigned in the matrix, so no case resolution is needed.  
Tongan [38]; Again, its possi ble that ABS is not assign ed in the matrix clause. 
Moreover, if ERG is inherent case (as some have suggested), this falls under the 
the I-case vs. S-case scenario.   
Turkish [39]; The lower case can be  overwritten only if its morphologically 
null. 
(16) Conclusion: Yoon concludes that there are no UG principles of case resolution 
when two S-cases compete on the same NP. But weve seen that the evidence for 
preservation of the low S-case in (15) is very weak. In fact, the evidence for high 
S-case wins is much stronger, and could ex plain all the facts, if we assume that 
one S-case isnt assigned in the cases of Farsi/Tongan/Turkish. 
(17) Two I-cases  [40] 
Navely, that should violate uniqueness of -role. Yoon allows instead "multiple 
-relations", or treating the composite case marker as a single marker.  
(18) Revised Chain Condition (RCC)  [41]
 C={ 1, , n} is an A-chain iff C is the maximal sequence that each member of 
C bears the same index and: 
(i) n has a unique -role. 
 (ii) For i, 1  i  n, the Case of I is determined by a unique (Case-)governor. 
RCC and CUC yield the same predictions for [42b-e]. They only differ on [42a],  
ruled out by CUC but allowed by RCC. The evidence section 2 favors the latter.  
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Note : Yoon notes [fn. 6, 8] that the stacked NP is interpreted as a focus, which is 
why it is preferred with the marker  man only. He assumes that NOM can be 
assigned either in [Spec,VP] or in [Sp ec,IP]; the latter position gives rise to 
exhaustive focus. One may raise the doubt  of a misanalysis. Schtze (1997) in 
fact argued that the Nominative (and A ccusative) suffix is ambiguous between a 
case marker and a focus marker. In stacked nominals, it is only a focus marker 
(so, strictly speaking, case st acking doesnt exist).   
(5) 	 Following Belletti &amp; Rizzi (1988), Yoon adopts an unaccusative analysis of  
psych constructions [6]. The experiencer /locative is generate d as a VP-internal 
argument (higher than the theme). It is assigned DAT/LOC in situ, and then raises to [Spec,IP], where it is assigned NOM; The CUC is violated. 
Note : Nothing in the proposal hinges on the unaccusative analysis of psych verbs.
Even if the experiencer/locative NP is generated as an external argument in 
[Spec,vP], it could be assigned DAT/LOC in that position. 
 Problem 1 : How can NOM be suppressed, as in [2b]-[4b]?
 Answer [fn. 8] : Structural case markers can be optionally dropped.  
 Problem 2 : How can DAT/LOC be suppressed, as in [2c]-[4c]?
Answer [fn. 8] : The experiencer/locative is optiona lly selected as an NP rather 
than a PP. Huh?
(6) 	 Case stacking in Cuzco Quechua : 
A subject of a nominalized complement bears GEN. Raising-to-Object stacks ACC on top of GEN [8]. 
Finite ECM/RtO 
In several languages, an  NP raises from the subject positi on of a finite complement clause 
to the matrix object position. Th e lower position is is typica lly assigned NOM, the higher 
one ACC. The nominal surfaces with only one  case marker (no visible stacking), but 
given simple assumptions, must be assumed to be doubly case-marked. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Note : The RCC preserves the uniqueness of government per position. But if the 
same head can assign two cases, as in  [42e], double case-marking is possible 
without movement; see [54, 55]. 
(19) 	 RCC predictions 
a. 	 Stacking [48]: There is indirect ev idence (from focus, fn. 8) that the  
  DAT-NOM DP moved (string-vacuou s), so the two cases come from
  two governors. 
b. 	 Finite ECM: If the ECM subj ect moves overtly to the embedded 
[Spec,CP], then its ACC and NOM ar e assigned by differe nt governors.  
(20) 	 Bottom line of section 3.2.3 
In a configuration: [ XP X0 [YP ZP [ Y Y0 WP ]]], both Y (the internal head) and X 
(the external head) are potential  governors of the speci fier ZP. Yoon defines 
head-government in such a way that the following result holds: Y governs ZP iff 
it assigns some feature to it (e .g., case); otherwise, X governs ZP. 
(21) 	 A contrast between Korean &amp; Cuzco  [51] 
While ECM subjects in verbal comple ments in Korean get ACC or NOM (see 
[9a]), in nominalized complements they get GEN or NOM but not ACC. 
However, in Cuzco Quechua they can get ACC, as well as GEN.  
Explanation : Korean nominalized C assigns GEN, blocking external government 
by ACC-assigning V [52]. In Cuzco, GEN is assigned by I, so [Spec,CP] is visible 
to external government [53]. There's al so morphological evidence for this. A 
cogent argument! 
Note : The Korean data appear to support the standard CUC (the lower GEN is 
preserved, the higher ACC isnt assigned); but a closer analysis reveals that the 
higher ACC had no chance of being assigned, due to lack of government. The case is different, of course, with verbal complements, whose subject is visible to 
external government (getting ACC).  
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Minimalism (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ln18recent_minim/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>26</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Recent Minimalism: Chomsky (2000, 2001) 
Idan Landau 
Minimalist Inquiries 
(1) 	 Caveat (apply profusely) : The proposals are very tenta tive. Minimalism is still a 
program, not a theory. Everything we know  about language argues against it. The 
questions that we pose are proba bly premature, if not meaningless. In short, this is 
all crazy, so lets do it. 
(2) 	 The minimalist question: How close does language come to optimal design? To 
what extent minimal design specifications derive the properties of UG? 
Therapeutic value: Minimalist methodology urges you to get rid of 
technological solutions, unnatural co ncepts and stipulations (examples: 
goovernment, Agr projections).  
But remember : Caution is in order in appeali ng to such considerations. Given 
some empirically supported conclusion, it is  often possible to construct plausible 
conceptual grounds for it, and for alternatives. 
(3) 	 Perfect design is not perfect usability. Language ma y approach a perfect design, 
in that its properties are almost fully re ducible to interface c onditions. But actual 
expressions may often be unusable, due  to memory and parsing limitations 
(garden path, central embedding). So the no tion that language is almost perfect 
in some biological sense is quite different  from the tradtional functionalist mantra 
that language is well-d esigned for communication. 
(4) 	 The strongest minimalist thesis: Language  is an optimal solu tion to legibility 
conditions. 
If true, then just by knowing the le gibility conditions, and what an optimal 
solution to them would look like, we would be able to derive all linguistic facts 
(acquisition, processing, neurology, etc.). The proposal is odd evidence does 
not come with a mark: I do or do not bear on reality.  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(32) 	 On Case: Structural case is demoted in significance. Its a reflex of agreement, 
not the trigger, serving to activate the goa l. [note: one can sense some uneasiness 
here; the picture is bound to change]. 
Defective intervention effects (DIE) 
(33) 	 Wh-island 
a. *[CP C[Q]  [ CP wh1
[Q,WH ]  wh2
[Q,WH] ]] 
[Q] is uninterpretable on C, interpretable on wh-phrases, [WH] is uninterpretable 
on wh-phrases, making them active (like case in A-movement). wh1 in (a) has 
checked off its [WH] feature, so its inac tive; but it still blocks Agree between the 
matrix C and wh2. 
Note : Its not clear why both [Q] and [WH]  are needed (the notion of active 
becomes a complication). More puzzling  doesnt the failure of long-distance 
Agree in (a) simply follow from the PIC? 
(34) 	 A-movement / Expletive-Associate 
a. * [John 1 to seem [ t1 is intelligent]] would be surprising. 
b. * We hoped [PRO 1 to be decided [ t1 to be killed at dawn]]. 
c. * This book 1 seem [t 1 to read 2 [t1 never [any students t 2]. 
(a) involves raising out of a finite clause into an infinitive. (b) involves raising of 
PRO from one control complement to anot her. (c) involves OS feeding movement 
to subject position and then raising. 
In all these cases, the boldfaced po sition is inactive, case being checked 
there. So it cant move to (o r agree with) the higher probe.  
 Alternative explanations : (a) violates the requirement that clausal subjects (with 
lexical subjects) be introduced by an overt  C; (b) could be ruled out by whatever 
blockes reflexive readings for passive (PRO is coindexed with the implicit 
decider). 
(35) 	 a. * There seem  [several people are friends of yours]. 
b. * There were decided [PRO to stay with friends ]. 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
The particple lacks [person], but can still Agree with DP on [number,gender]. 
DPs case is still active, its -features are interpretable and not deleted, so it can 
further Agree with T. This gives rise  to French participle agreement.  
(29) 	 [TP T [ VP seem  [TP Tdef [vP DP v [ VP V ]]] 
Tdef must have some minimal uninterpretable feature; lets say [person]. Thats 
the probe for successive cyclic movement through this position, or expletive 
merge (so there  also has uninterpr etable [person]). 
(30) 	 Consequences 
a. 	 Uninterpretable features can only delete in one fell swoop. So whenever 
X and Y Agree, and X has a subset of the uninterpretable  features of Y, 
Xs features delete, but Ys features survive.  
 i) an expletive cant delete the fe atures of nondefective T, but its own 
[person] feature is deleted. ii) T def allows, but standard finite/control T 
doesnt allow, successive cyclic movement.   
b. 	 Dissociation of checking from dislo cation: Agree and movement to Spec 
are independent (cf. Icelandic quirky subject satisfying E PP together with 
long-distance nominative satisfying  Agree). Therefore, the notion of 
checking domain is eliminated (the  only domain relevant for Agree is 
defined in (27)). 
c. 	 More generally  the Spec-h ead relation has no special status. 
Note : Still, it is universally true that agreement+movement is richer than 
agreement in-situ (French participial ag reement, Arabic VSO/SVO agreement, 
etc.) Thats a mystery under the radica l dissociation between Agree and EPP 
(recognized in DbP, fn. 39). 
(31) 	 On Greed: The original Greed of Chomsky (1993) was motivated by features of 
the goal. It also involved look-ahead. Lasnik s Enlightened self-interest allowed 
Greed to be motivated by either goal or  probe. The current version holds that 
features of the probe must be deleted  Suicidal Greed.  
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
b. 	 John v0 expects.sg there to have been caught. ACC several fish. ACC. 
The matrix T/v agrees in -features and Case with several fish ; the participle 
caught  agrees in [number,gender,Case]. 
  The single strong phase is the matrix CP, hen ce all checked features 
persist until the entire sentence is finished. 
 For (a) : Prt= caught ; DP= several fish ; 
i. Agree (Prt,DP)  
[person,gender] of Prt valued and de leted; Case of neither is valued. 
ii. Agree (T,Prt) 
Case of Prt is still active; it is valued (Nom) and deleted; -features of T 
unvalued because Prt is -incomplete. 
iii. Agree (T,DP) 
Case of DP is valued and deleted; -features of T valued and deleted. Prt 
does not intervene because its -incomplete. 
Real English facts 
(5) 	 Puzzling word orders 
a. * There was placed a large book on the table. 
b. 	 There was placed on the table a large book. 
c. 	 There was a large book placed on the table. 
In most Germanic languages  the facts are reversed.  
(48) 	 English Thematization/Extraction (Th/Ex) 
At PF, move DO to the left (or right) edge of vP.  
Evidence that Th/Ex is phonological 
(49) 	 Th/Ex has no semantic effect (unlike OS), e.g., specificity. 
(50) 	 The NP that undergoes Th/Ex, whether to  the left or right, is inaccessible to 
syntactic operations, like wh-movement. 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Note : PIC derives Subjacency in a strong form. Movement must proceed 
successive cyclically, leaving a copy at the edge of every intervening transitive vP 
or CP. 
 By the end of a phase, all the uninterp retable features in its domain must be 
deleted (because later operations  wont have a chance to do so). 
Relations and Chains 
(20) 	 Imperfection in language de sign could be i) ill usory, ii) real and irreducible, iii) 
real but reducible to some optimal solution. 
(21) 	 Illusory imperfections: DS, SS, gove rnment, indices, X-bar levels, traces, -
operators. Lets assume none of this exists in derivations or LF/PF representations. 
(22)	 Reducible imperfections 
a. 	 A chain is a set of occurrences  of a single item. Occurrence of  is 
defined as the sister of . All properties of chains follow from independent 
principles (so  no Chain Condition). 
b. 	 Feature chains dont  exist (how can we defi ne sisterhood or c-command 
for features? Too much of a headache).  
c. 	 Merge provides two relations: sist erhood (between the objects merged)  
and immediate containment (between the the output and the inputs). The 
transitive closure of immediately contain is contain; the transitive 
closure of sister is identity; and sister of contain is c-command.   
d. Modified lexical items  (heads with  deleted  features) preserve  their 
 configurational relations. 
e. Adjunction? L-marking? 
Irreducible imperfections 
(23) 	 The Inclusiveness Condition 
No new features are introduced by C HL. 
The phonological component massively violates inclusiveness (by adding 
prosodic structure, narrow phonetics). Perhap s the source of th ese imperfections 
(the sensorimotor system) and the abundance of evidence allows this situation. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(24) 	 Inclusiveness + FI: Inclusiveness hold s of narrow syntax, and each feature has 
either a PF or an LF interpretation 
The most interesting reducible imperfection 
(25) 	 a. Lexical items have  uninterpretable features. 
b. 	 Language diplays dislocation. 
Perhaps dislocation is in fact required by the thought system. That  system requires 
dissociation of argument-structure ( -roles) from information-structure (topic, 
focus). If this is a bare output cond ition, then (25b)  no t found in any other 
symbolic system  is not an imperfecti on. We might take then (25a) to be the 
mechanism  by which (25b) is realized, and th erefore, also not an imperfection. 
The mechanism of dislocation 
(26) 	 [TP T [be elected an unpopular candidate] 
The probe  T has uninterpretable -features (+case) and se lectional EPP feature. 
The probe looks for a matching goal, in this case an unpopular candidate. The 
goal has interpretable -features and uninterpretable case. 
Structural case is what makes the goal active, by enabling the selection of the 
pied-piped category to be merged.  Case-checking renders a DP inactive, hence 
inaccessible to Agree/Move. Structural case is lexically valued on T, syntactically 
valued on DP; the reverse holds for -features. 
(27) 	 Conditions on Agree
 a. 	 Probe-goal matching (  no V/N/D-features in checking). 
b. 	 The goal is active. 
c. 	 The goal is in the domain of the probe (c-command).  
d. 	 There is no closer goal (up to equi-distance). 
(28) 	 [TP T [ PrtP Participle [ VP V DP]]] 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
c. * There seem  [that it was told friends  [that its raining]]. 
The Agree relation is blocked by the embedded subject, though its inactive (DIE). 
Notice again, Chomsky assumes that the PIC doesnt apply here.  
(36) 	 Interveners must be complete chains. 
Icelanglish 
a. 	 me.DAT 1 thought .pl [t 1 [they.NOM .pl be industrious]]. 
b. * me. DAT 1 seem .pl [t 1 [John. DAT to like horses. NOM .pl]]. 
t1 doesnt block agreement with the embe dded nominative, because its only part 
of a chain; but John. DAT does block it since its the entire chain. 
(37) 	 DIE argue against Move as distinct fr om Agree+Merge. The closest target that 
can check of the case feature of the associate is the matrix T; the fact that its too 
far can only be accounted for by an Agree-based theory. 
Cyclic Spellout 
(38) a. Deleted features persist to the end of the phase. 
b. Every phase is a spellout cycle. 
c. The former distinctions between  overt, covert, and phonological cycles  
collapse. There is a single cycle in the grammar. 
d. Apparent countercyclic covert  movement is cyclic Agree.  
Note : Covert movement is needed besides Agree, to account for QR, ACD, etc. 
(39) 	 Cyclicity follows from minimal sear ch; operations can only access full syntactic 
objects, attending to the n eeds of their heads.  
Derivation by Phase 
(40) 	 To make the distinction between interpretabl e and uninterpretable  features visible 
throughout the derivation, we assume that  uninterpretable f eatures enter the 
derivation unvalued. They are valued by Agree, deleted from narrow syntax but 
available to spellout.  
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
e. 	 In OS languages, Int is available in-situ for objects not at the phonological 
border of v*P; by the reasoning in (b), they may not shift; (56e). 
(58) 	 Note : Countercyclicity is not entirely elim inated. Evaluation applies at the next 
strong phase; so whether or not Obj is at the phonological border of v*P is known 
only when the CP phase is reached (e.g., V-topicalization). 
(59) 	 OV languages (German, Dutch): They are OS languages, but (55c) always 
applies, hence OS (scrambling)  doesnt depend on V-raising.  
Romance: Non-OS languages. 
(60) 	 A problem : OS applies in (a), although the in -situ subject separates the (base) 
object from the phonological border of v*P: 
a. 	 there read it 1 never [ v*P any students t read t1]. 
Solution : The principle Something must escape a transitive v*P licenses an
EPP-feature on v*. 
Note : Perhaps the subject has raised outside v*P.  
More phonologiocal movements 
(61) a. Th/Ex. 
b. Disl. 
c. Head movement. 
(62)	 Oddities of head movement 
a. 	 Why head? Why V-to-T and not VP-to-T? Why T-to-C and not TP-to-C?
 b. 	 Its countercyclic. 
c. 	 The head doesnt c-command the tail (on the simplest assumptions). 
d. 	 Its unclear how to identify o ccurrences of the head (in a chain). 
e. 	 Its not iterable  (successive-cyclic). 
f. 	 Its intact in aphasics (unlike A-chains).  
 Chomsky: All of these properties naturally fall out if head movement is 
phonological and applies to affixal elements. 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(13) 	 a. [ CP C [ TP T [ VP likely  [TP Tdef [vP XP [ vP Subj [ v v [ VP V Obj ]]]]]]]] 
There is likely to be a proof discovered. 
there  raises from the lower [Spec,T def] to the higher [Spec,T]. 
b. 	 [CP C [ TP T [ vP Subj [ VP expect [ TP Tdef [vP XP [ vP Subj [ v v [ VP V Obj ]]]]]]] 
I expected there to be a proof discovered. 
there  cant raise from the lower [Spec,T def] to the higher [Spec,T], since 
the matrix external argument intervenes in [Spec,vP] (MLC).  
Merge over Move 
(14) 	 a. * There is likely [a proof to be dicovered]. 
b. 	 There 1 is likely [t 1 to be a proof discovered]. 
c. 	 A proof 1 is likely [t 1 to be a proof discovered]. 
d. 	 [TP Tdef [be a proof dicovered]] 
At stage (d), either Move of a proof  or Merge of there  can satisfy the EPP feature 
of T def. Both involve Agree, but Move also  involves pied-piping. Merge wins 
by economy when there  is in the numeration.  
e. 	 John expected [a proof to be discovered]. 
f. 	 John expected [there to be a proof discovered]. 
g. * John 1 expected [t 1 to be a proof discovered]. 
At stage (d), either Move of a proof  or Merge of there  can satisfy the EPP feature 
of T def. Both are possible since there need not be in the numeration. (g) is ruled 
out not by economy, but by Merge-Theta  (11). 
Control CPs 
(15) 	 Chomsky : Like finite CPs and unlike raising/ECM TPs, control CPs assign case 
to their subject, can sometimes app ear as root expressions, and enjoy 
distributional freedom. Therefore: Control T is nondefective, control C 
introduces a phase. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
(16) 	 Note : Chomsky relies on an old observation by Rizzi: 
a. 	 What did John promise? To help Mary. 
b. * What did John seem? To be angry. 
But while its true that no raising comp lement can be separated, it is very not 
true that every control complement can: 
c. * What did John persuade Mary? To help him. 
d. * What did John condescend? To help Mary. 
In fact, the bad cases  are ruled out because what  has no case. If the control verb 
has no accusative case to assign to the infi nitive  either b ecause it is already 
assigned, or because the verb is unaccusativ e  a separated infinitive is ruled out.  
(17) 	 Merge over Move predicts, incorrectly, that proofs  cant be raised in (a), since 
there  could be merged from the numeration. 
a. 	 There is a possibility [tha t proofs will be discovered].  
Solution : The numeration is also cyclic, broken into separate phases . When the 
embedded T is reached, there is not yet in the numeration, so movement isnt 
prevented. Thats more evidence for constraints on operative complexity. 
Whats a phase? 
(18) 	 Phase   a propositional unit, vP or CP. Actually, Chomsky restricts phases to 
units headed by a core functional category with -features. So phases are CPs, 
finite or control, and transitive vPs. TPs and unaccusative/passive vPs/VPs are not 
phases. 
(19) 	 Phase Impenetrability Condition (PIC) 
In a phase  with a head H, the domain of H is not accessibe to operations 
outside , only H and its edge (=specifiers/ adjuncts) are accessible to such 
operations. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
a. [Susan T comp seems [ TP Susan T def to be Susan  sleepy ]] 
Move (1) : Tdef has uninterpretable [person], Susan has Case, both active: they Agree. 
[3rd person] of Susan values [person] of T def. 
Susan's -features are complete, so T defs features delete. 
Tdefs features are incomplete, so Susan's Case feature remains. 
EPP forces movement to [Spec,TP]. 
Move (2) : Tcomp has uninterpretable -features, Susan has Case, both active: they Agree. 
[3rd person,+Sg,+Fem] of Susan values [person,number,gender] of T comp. 
Both sets of -features are complete, so all un interpretable features delete.
 Note : The status of Case is unclear. It makes a DP active. Chomsky maintains 
that T/v have no Case feature, but its assigned a value under agreement. Whats 
the source of the value (Nom, Acc) if not T/v? 
Cyclic spellout 
(41)	 Cyclic spellout applies to strong phases (transitive vP, notated v*P, or CP). 
Earlier phases can be forgotten, being in accessible to syntax (because of PIC) 
and phonology (because of cyclic spellout). 
(42) 	 Simplest assumption: Head s of chains are pronounced.  
Note : Thats probably too simplistic. First, there is covert move ment (not Agree); 
second, there are cases of multiple pronunciation of chain positions. 
Generalizing from spellout 
(43) 	 A strong phase is interpreted/eval uated at the next (higher) strong phase. 
Note : Chomsky probably means that the head/edge of a phase are 
interpreted/evaluated at the next level.  As regards LF, however, long-distance 
vasriable binding must be able to look at units larger than phases: 
a. 	 Every boy 1 heard the rumor that his 1 mother came from Mars. 
Dividing labor between PIC and Inactivity 
(44) 	 PIC of MIF is weakened  in DbP to strong phases only. 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
If HP is a strong phase a nd ZP the minimal strong phase  above it, then the domain 
of H is not accessible to operations at ZP; only H and its edge are.  
(45) Consequences
 a. [CP C [ TP T [v*P v* [VP V DP ]]]] 
b. [CP C [ TP T [v*P v* [TP  DP  ]]]] 
c. [CP C [ TP T [vP v [ VP V [ CP  DP  ]]]] 
(a) and (b) represent local and long-distance agreement with a nominative DP 
(possibly part of Move). (c) represen ts agreement across CP. All cases are 
licensed by the PIC, since the domain of a strong phase (v*P or CP) is accessible 
to all probes up to the next higher st rong phase. If ungrammatic al, these cases are 
ruled out only because DP, or an intervener, is inactive. That clarifies (34)-(35) 
above, though not the wh-island (33). 
d. * There seem  [that it was told friends  [that its raining]]. 
e. * me. DAT 1 seem .pl [t 1 [John. DAT to like horses. NOM .pl]]. Icelanglish 
(46) Maximize matching effects. 
This principle has the effect of Earline ss, or strong features. Feature checking and 
deletion must proceed in maximal chunks. 
a. There is likely to arrive a man. 
b. * A man is likely there to arrive. 
When there  is in the embedded [Spec,TP], Agree (T matrix,there ) takes place, 
activated by [person], before Agree (T matrix, a man). Maximize Match requires 
EPP-checking as well, so there  moves, blocking (b).  
Note : Does DP have an EPP feature? If not , how is Match relevant? Further, (b) 
could be ruled out if raising/ECM cl auses lack EPP (see idea in  (Error! 
Bookmark not defined. )). 
More Icelanglish 
(47) a. There T0 seem.pl to have been caught. NOM. pl several fish. NOM .pl. 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
a. * How many packages did there arrive in the mail? 
b. * What did there arrive in  the mail [several packages of __] ? 
c. * What are there [books about __] being sold (in Boston these days)?
 This is not a property of expletive constructions generally: 
d. 	 How many packages are there in the room? 
e. 	 What are there [several packages of __] in the room? 
(51) 	 Still, the trace of the associate is visible to Agree (getting Nom case) and to 
interpretive conditions, like binding. Exactly  what part of Move is incompatible 
with the trace of Th/Ex? 
a. 	 Not Merge, since other null elements (pro, PRO) can Merge. 
b. 	 Not Agree, since the associate agrees with T. 
c.   A trace cant pied-pipe (pro/PRO are heads, need not pied-pipe). 
d. 	 Further, perhaps an inactive tr ace resists Match, explaining (36).  
Chomsky notes that the dependence of pi ed-piping (hence, Move) on the presence 
of phonological features is suboptimal; narrow syntax shouldnt care about 
these matters (the issue goes back to the status of special conditions on ecs). 
Object Shift 
(52) 	 Assuming PIC, wh-movement of the object must proceed through the OS position 
even in English, even if the object can surface in that position only in Scandinavian languages: 
a. 	 Guess [ CP what 1 [TP John 2 T [ vP t1 [vP t2 read t 1]. 
(53) 	 Why is OS barred in English? Po ssibly, the shifted object would produce a 
defective intervention eff ect between T and Subj. But why should this be 
restricted to Move, and not Agree (the latter obtaining in (52a)? Moreover, in 
Icelandic DAT-V-NOM constructions, the dative subject raises past the shifted 
object that agrees with T. 
 OS is only allowed in English if followed by further movement of the object. 
Or, Agree (T,Subj) depends on the outer Spec,vP being empty. Countercyclic !! 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Holmbergs Generalization 
(54) 	 OS cant apply across a phonologically vi sible category  V, particle, indirect 
object  except adjuncts. 
Holmbergs account assumes that OS is triggered by semantic properties of the 
object (specificity, old information; Choms ky calls this Int ) but conditioned by 
phonological edge. This kind of interaction runs against the spirit of DbP, and 
also doesnt extend to invisi ble OS, as in (52a).    
(55) 	 Chomskys account 
a. 	 UG: v* is assigned an EPP featur e (allowing OS) onl y if that has a 
semantic effect on the outcome (optional rules are outcome-dependent). 
b. 	 UG: The EPP position of v* is assigned Int. 
c. 	 In OS languages: At the phonologica l border of v*P, XP is assigned Int 
(the opposite of Int, namely, new information).  
(56) 	 English
 a. 	 Guess [ CP what 1 [TP John 2 T [ vP t1 [vP t2 read t 1]. 
b. * They had it 1 never [ v*P thave t1]. 
Icelandic 
c. They read it 1 never [ v*P tread t1]. 
d. * They read never [ v*P read it]. 
e. * They have it 1 never [ v*P read t 1]. 
(57) 	 a. Wh-question has a semantic effect, so  v* may be assigned EPP, allowing 
invisible OS in all languages, whether or not Obj is at the 
phonological border of v*P; (56a). 
b. 	 In non-OS languages, In t is available in -situ for all obje cts; OS isnt 
necessary to obtain this reading, hence its blocked (no EPP-assignment to 
 v*); (56b). 
c. 	 In OS languages, Int is unavailable for objects at the phonological border 
of v*P; OS has a semantic e ffect, so its allowed; (56c). 
d. 	 In OS languages, objects at th e phonological border of v*P are assigned 
Int; if the object is intrinsically specific, the result is deviant; (56d). 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
Operations 
(8) 	 Merge (indispensible in any symbolic system): Merge ( ,)  K(,) 
Agree (specific to language) between a lexi cal item and a feature in its domain. 
Move = Agree + Pied-piping + Merge (pied piping determines what projection of 
the agreeing feature is actually moved).   
 Economy : Agree preempts Move (replacing Procrastinate). 
Core functional categories: v, T, C 
(9) 	 v: expresses transitivity, selects V, has -features (object agreement), selects 
external argument, has optional EPP f eature (second Merge) for object shift. 
T: expresses tense/event structure, has -features (subject agreement), obligatory 
EPP feature. If selected by C, it has a full set of -features, whether expressed 
(finite) or not (control). If selected by  V (raising/ECM), it has only a subset of -
features (only [person]?), hence defective. 
C: expresses force/mood, has -features, optional EPP feature (for wh-phrases) 
(10) 	 [vP XP [ vP Subj [ v v [ VP V Obj ]]]] 
XP is the object-shift pos ition. It cant be filled by Merge of an argument, 
because 
(11) 	 Merge-Theta
 Pure Merge in -position is required of a nd restricted to argument.  
Consequence : No movement to a -position . Chomsky hints that this is implicit 
in Hale &amp; Keysers view of argument  structure, but its not clear how.  
(12) 	 [TP T [vP XP [ vP Subj [ v v [ VP V Obj ]]]] 
The object may raise to the XP position (a s in Icelandic) or not; the subject may 
raise to [Spec,TP] or not; if not, an expletive is merged in [Spec,TP].  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Syntax, 24.951, MIT, Fall 2003 
How do we know what the legibility conditions are? We must understand the 
external systems. But they are not well understood. Progress in understanding 
them goes hand in hand with progress in  discovering the languafe systems that 
interact with them.  
Derivationalism 
(5) 	 Strong derivational approach : There is no final representation, everything in 
computed dynamically (Epstein et. al.).  
Weak derivational approach : Some operations are cyclic, but others apply at the 
interface to the entire  expression (Chomsky). 
 Representational approach : No derivations, all conditions apply to to LF/PF 
representations (Brody). 
 Chomsky: Its not clear that th e issue is real. But le ts suppose it is. On the 
derivational approach, we might expect to discover principles of least effort, 
eliminating superflous elements/ operations, licensing only non-vacuous 
operations; local search for computation (locality of movement); and local 
determinability (no look ahead).  
(6)	 Actual complexity is not mathematical complexity. Suppose automobiles lacked 
fuel storage, so that each one had to carry along a petroleu m-processing plant. 
That would add only bounded complexity, but would be considered rather poor 
design. Something similar might well be true for language. 
General language design 
(7) 	 F  the universal set of linguistic features 
[F]  the subset of F operative in a language L. 
Lex  the lexicon of L, assembled from [F] 
LA  the lexical array used in a given derivation 
 Assumptions : L makes a one-time choice of [F] from F, a one-time assembly of 
Lex from [F], and a one-time choice of LA from Lex (recall the fuel plant). 
Moreover, derivations have no access to unpackaged free-floating features.   
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Minimalism (cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-951-introduction-to-syntax-fall-2003/resources/ho_mplt1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>27</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
