<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/6-912-introduction-to-copyright-law-january-iap-2006/</course_url>
    <course_title>Introduction to Copyright Law</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Legal Studies</list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>LexisNexis&#174;; 1976 Copyright Act</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/6-912-introduction-to-copyright-law-january-iap-2006/resources/lexis_intro/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to Researching Legal Materials
1. Sources of legal materials 
 Bills  Laws  United States Statutes at Large  United States Code 
 Litigation  Published opinions  Reporters 
 Federal Register  Code of Federal Regulations 
Law review articles  
 State codes, cases, regulations 
 Treaties (sometimes have domestic force of law) 
 Other countries laws and courts, United Nations, municipal ordinances, etc. 
2. How to read and write citations 
Type of Material 
Bill in Congress 
Federal statute 
United States Code 
Supreme Court 
Appeals court 
District court 
Pending case Example Citation 
Communications Decency Act of 1996, S. 652, 104th Cong. tit. V (enacted) 
Communications Decency Act of 1996, Pub. L. No. 104104, tit. V, 110 Stat. 56, 133 
Communications Decency Act of 1996  509, 47 U.S.C. 230 (2000) 
Reno v. ACLU, 521 U.S. 844 (1997)
Zeran v. Am. Online, Inc., 129 F.3d 327 (4th Cir. 1997)
Zeran v. Am. Online, Inc., 958 F. Supp. 1124 (E.D. Va.), a d, 129 F.3d 327 (4th Cir. 1997)
Recording Indus. Assn of Am. v. Mass. Inst. of Tech., No. 03MS265 (D.D.C. led Aug. 1, 2003)
3. How to nd legal materials 
MIT has a networkwide subscription to a limited version of the LexisNexis database, known as LexisNexis 
Academic. It contains a large library of news materials, Lexiss commercial annotated edition of the United States 
Code and the Constitution, similar state materials, Congressional bills and federal statutes starting from 1989, the 
Congressional Record , the Federal Register, the Code of Federal Regulations, and virtually every published decision 
of a federal or state court that you could nd in a law library. 
To begin, go to http://web.lexisnexis.com/universe and click Legal Research. 
	To get a decision by name: Get a Case, then enter the names of the parties. 
	To get a decision by citation: Get a Case, then enter the citation. 
	To get a section of the United States Code : Federal Code, then Guided Search, and search by Cite as 
follows: to get 47 U.S.C.  230, enter 47 USCS sec 230. 
	To get a public law: Congressional, then Laws, then Laws by Number. 
	To get a Congressional bill: Congressional, then Bills, then Bills by Number. 
Most of the search forms also let you search by contents as well as citation, and there are lots of materials available 
in addition to the above. Dont be afraid to explore! 
4. Structure of the federal court system 
Civil and criminal cases start at a federal district court in front of a single trial judge appointed for life 
by the president. All of Massachusetts is in one district, the District of Massachusetts (D. Mass). There are 
courthouses in Boston, Worcester, and Springeld that house the United States District Court for the District 
of Massachusetts . 
The losing party can usually appeal a nal judgment or order to a threejudge panel of a federal appeals 
court. The federal court system is organized geographically into 12 circuits, each with a court of appeals. Cases 
from our district court are appealed to the United States Court of Appeals for the First Circuit. There are 
also some specialized appeals courts, like the Federal Circuit Court of Appeals, which hears all patentrelated appeals. 
There are six active judges on the First Circuit Court of Appeals (the smallest in the country), but only three 
randomlyselected judges on a panel. If a majority of active judges on the court vote to allow it, a case can be reheard 
by a federal appeals court sitting en banc, usually the entire court. This happens rarely. 
Finally, a losing party in a federal appeals court or a state supreme court can le a petition for certiorari with 
the Supreme Court of the United States in Washington, D.C. Unlike a direct appeal, the Supreme Court is not 
required to hear your case and in fact only grants cert for about one percent of requests. 
Federal courts have jurisdiction to hear cases involving federal laws, like copyright (Recording Indus. Assn of 
Am., supra ) and deprivation of civil rights (Reno v. ACLU, supra ). They also have jurisdiction to hear some cases 
arising under state laws, when the value of the dispute is more than $75,000 and the parties are in dierent states: 
a diversity case (Zeran, supra ). States own court systems hear the rest of the cases. Most states have systems 
similar in structure to the federal government.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos>
        <video>
          <video_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/6-912-introduction-to-copyright-law-january-iap-2006/resources/lecture-1-introduction/</video_url>
          <video_title>Lecture 1: Introduction</video_title>
          <transcript/>
        </video>
      </videos>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Software Licensing; DVDs and Encryption</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode17/usc_sec_17_00000512----000-.html</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos>
        <video>
          <video_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/6-912-introduction-to-copyright-law-january-iap-2006/resources/lecture-2-lexisnexis-and-1976-copyright-act/</video_url>
          <video_title>Lecture 2: LexisNexis and 1976 Copyright Act</video_title>
          <transcript/>
        </video>
      </videos>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Copyright Applied to Music, Computers; Napster&#174;; Peer-to-Peer File Sharing</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://www.copyright.gov/title17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos>
        <video>
          <video_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/6-912-introduction-to-copyright-law-january-iap-2006/resources/lecture-3-copyright-applied-to-music/</video_url>
          <video_title>Lecture 3: Copyright Applied to Music</video_title>
          <transcript/>
        </video>
      </videos>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
