<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/</course_url>
    <course_title>Introduction to Observational Physical Oceanography</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Earth Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Internal Waves (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_17n/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>2
122 2 2
222) (
/', ,1)] sin() cos()[,,( ),,( ,,
f Hg awherelk whereakat lykx it lykx hvu ehvu hvut lykxi
=+ =+=+ + + = +
 
 
 
A smaller radius of deformation, a, means, am ong other things, that 
aroclinic scales are much smaller th an barotropic scales: the adjustm ent 
h a column of upper laye r fluid is released and allowed to 
djust to the rotation of the earth will yield a m uch narrower geostrophic 
current and a smaller scale for the slumping of t he interface in the upper 
layer. Whether Poincar (or internal/in ertial gravity) wav es or Rossby waves 
are long or short com pared to the ra dius of deformation will be greatly 
affected: m ost of these that were s hort for barotropic m otion will be long 
for barocli nc waves. The frequency gap between the lowest frequency 
ternal wave and the highest frequency internal Ro ssby wave will be much 
till the 
al 
  
d 
rovided the best view of these ba roclinic waves because though the 
s by 
iscuss. 
 at signals 
ed, 
 be b
problem  in whic
a
in
larger, because the lo wer lim it for the fo rmer is the sam e as before (s
inertial frequency) but the upper lim it for the latter is m uch smaller: intern
Rossby waves have m uch longer periods th an their barotropic counterparts.
 
For example, we estimated earlier that the m inimum period (maxim um 
frequency) of a bartopic Rossby wave wo uld be 3.6 days. For the baroclinic 
case just considered,  this woul d becom e 360 days. In other words, we woul
expect no propagating baroc linic Rossby waves to have  a period shorter t han 
about a year! 
 
Baroclinic m otions can have larg e am plitude displacements of the 
pycnocline: of 100m. Thes e can be s een at the ocean surface, although 
reduced in am plitude by a factor of / . The satellite altimeter has 
p
amplitudes be small (10 cm ), the peri ods are long and thus easily sam ple
the 10 day repeat orbit of the Topex- Poseiden altimeter. In a p aper by 
Chelton and Schlax (Science, 1996). Th ey showed a space-time series of 
altim eter variability at selected latit udes in the North P acific Ocean, which  
we will now d
 
In the diagram  at the right, altimeter data  have been filtered to look
having periods between 0.5 and 2 yrs. Fo r the three years of data display
surface highs (depressions of the pycnoclin e) and lows can be seen to</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Internal Waves 
 
We now exam ine internal waves, for the case in which there are two distinct 
layers and in which the lowe r layer is at rest. This is an approximation of the 
case in which the upper layer is m uch thi nner than the deeper layer, but this 
makes the dynam ics much simpler. The linearized equations of m otion (for 
small perturbations) are as before , but now for the upper layer only: 
 
0] [,,
1 1
111111
=++= += 
yv
xuHtHyhg futvxhg fvtu
 
 
where H1 is the total thickness of the upper layer. The upper surface, h, is 
free to m ove vertically, as is the botto m of the upper layer. Recall before that 
in this case, ther e can be no pressure gr adients in the lower l ayer (layer  2) if 
it is to remain at rest. If perturbations to  the internal layer interface are small, 
and its depth is otherwise at a constant H01, then the vanishing of pressure 
gradients at any depth in the lower layer, z = -z 0, requires the following: 
 
   
/ /) ( 0)), ( ( ) ( ),,(
1 1 1 2 1 2,1 01 0 2 1 01 1 0
=   = +  +++ =
h hh Pand h H zg hh Hg zyxP
yxz
 
 
Upward  displacemen ts of the free su rface m ust be accom panied by 
downward  displacements of the interface to prevent pressure gradients in the 
lower layer. We have defined the disp lacements of the interface so that a 
downward  displacement of the inte rface is equivalent to a positive  value of 
h1. The reason for this will be apparent  shortly. Sinc e the density difference 
is going to be a s mall co mpar ed to the density of the surface lay er 
(/&lt;&lt;1 ) , changes in the free surface ar e going to be s mall co mpared to 
those of the interface. Thus, in the third equation above, we can ignore 
variations in the surface height co mpar ed to changes in the interface h eight. 
When we now substitute this approxim ation for h and H1 into the above 
equations we obtain:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>. ',0] [,', '
1 1
0111
111
11
=++= += 
ggwhereyv
xuHthyhg futvxhg fvtu
 
 
Note that t hese ar e exactly  the equations for a homogeneous fluid of uni form 
density with two exceptions: the wate r depth now becomes the mean depth 
of the upper layer ( H  H01) and the gravity term be comes a r educed gravity 
(g  g). Thus all of the previous types of surface waves can b e 
immediately taken over for int ernal wa ves with these two differences in 
mind. The small differences make som e substantial changes in the properties 
of these waves. Consider two quantities which were im portant for all of the 
surface waves: the shallow water phase speed c and the Rossby Radius of 
deform ation, a. These will tak e on different numerical valu es. We n eed to 
first estimate so me b asic quantities, such  as the den sity ratio and the m ean 
interface d epth. For this, we will use tw o stations from either si de of the 
).  
 
 
 
 
 Gulf Stream (they were used in  one of the homework problems</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>In the above figure, two hypothetical cases for dividing up the water colum n 
to two layers have been maded. In the first, the station (#65) i s south of the 
ulf Stream in a thick layer of subtropical m ode water (Eighteen Degree 
ater). We have used a surface density appropriate for what m ight be found 
 winter and a pycnocline depth of 750m. The stations were occupied in 
e see that the phase speed has been reduced from  200 m /s to 2-3 m /s and 
the radius of deform ation is reduced from 2000km to 20-30km (for a value 
of f  of 10-4 s-1.) While this change in two of the key parameters governing 
wave m otion is two orders of magnitude , there is n o qualitative difference in 
e types of waves or their dispersion relations. We will br iefly review this 
Kelvin waves: 
 in
G
W
in
Septem ber when the seasonal pycnocline is  fully de veloped. In the second, 
we used a shallower pycnocline (200m ) but a larger density ratio (2x10-3). 
The phase speed and radius of  deformation are given by: 
 
2
012 2 2012
/ ' /,'
f Hg fc aHg c
= ==
  
 
W
th
now. 
 
Internal gravity/inertial waves: 
 
22 2 2
(,
kwhere c f
+ =
 
2 2 2), ( &amp;),, andl k l + =  
12'Hg c=
 
1222 22 2
2) (
',,0, ))(),((),(
Hg cwherelcgivingh hexvxh vht lyi
====

 2 2t y  c
 
Rossby waves:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>propagating to the west, m ost clearly in 
the west ern part of the Pacific.  These 
have phase speed of  order 10 cm /s and 
are consistent with speeds of the lowest 
mode baroclinic Rossby wave (sim ilar 
to our approxim ation above). While the 
hase speeds seem slightly faster than 
 
g-
he 
 
tion is 
hase 
a2), 
es w
ve
reas 
 not th
 
 in 
 
ace 
 
nd occasionally break. A good descripti on of these can be seen in a paper 
by Haury, Briscoe and Orr (Nature, 1979),  which will be discussed in class. p
expected,  and this has been a focus of
much debate in the literature, th e 
evidence f or the existence of th ese 
waves and their im portance to lon
term variability in the ocean is 
undispute d. Also evident is the 
evidence t hat baroclinic wav es 
propagate faster towards the equator. 
This can be understood in terms of t
variation of the radius of deformation 
with latitude: in the tropics, where f is
smaller, the radius of deforma
larger than in m id-latitudes. Since long 
Rossby waves propaga te have a p
speed that is proportional to the square 
of the radius of deformation ( cp = 
as one app roaches the equator, wav
than at higher latitudes.  At 21N abo
to cross the do main plotted, whe
39N. Of course the time series is
see this.  
 
Internal waves are responsible for m uch
open ocean observat ions. This can be deduced by the relationship between 
observed horizontal and vertical velocities and how  they depend upon 
frequency. In shallow water, such as Massachusetts Bay, internal waves
the seasonal therm ocline (pycnocline)  are generated by tidal flow over
Stellwagen Bank an d can produce a visi ble signature at  the ocean surf
(due to surface convergences an d divergences and their effect  on surface 
waves) and substanti al mixing at the oc ean bottom. In fact, they can be a
major source of nutrient supply to the upper ocean as these steep waves m ix ill take a shorter time to cross a basin 
, it will take about 4 years for a wave 
it will take ap proxim ately 10 years at 
at long and we have to extrapolate to 
of the high frequency variability in 
aImage removed due to 
copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Another Wrinkle on Observations of the Abyssal Ocean: Geothermal Heating&#160;and Hydrothermal Vents (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Another wrinkle on observations of the Abyssal Ocean: Geothermal Heating 
&amp; Hydrothermal Vents 
 
 
 
Models of Magma injection at Ridge Spreading Centers lead Geophysicists 
to expect a heat flux out of the ocean  bottom that exceed ed observations of 
diffusive heat flux made w ith probes placed in sediments. This missing heat 
flux (of order 0.1-1 w m-2) lead some to speculate that it might be 
hydrothermal: involving oceanic water ci rculating within the earths crust 
and being injected into the ocean like hot 
springs. 
 
Indeed, these hot springs were 
discovered by the Alvin submersible (see 
figure at right) in th e Pacific Ocean with 
black fluid, filled with dark mineral 
particles, emergi ng from vents at 
temperatures of 350oC. The chemical 
signature of these vents can be traced 
over 2 thousand km. across the Pacific as 
was first demonstrated by in paper by Lupton and Craig (Science, 1981) using 
an isotopes of helium (
3He, 4He) which 
are emitted from the earth at vent sites.  
 Image removed due to 
copyright concerns.Mild-Ocean
Ridge
Heat FlowIs this due to hydrothermal circulation?Actual measurements of heat flow
Distance away from ridgeTheoretical curve of heat flow:
What scientists predictedHeat flow through the seafloor</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Because the emitted fluid is so hot, it is buoyant and quickly rises from the 
bottom . These buoyant plumes can rise  up to a few hundre d meters above 
the sea floor, where their buoya ncy is fi nally lost due to entrainment of 
surrounding fluids. From  laboratory &amp; at mospheric studies of these (spurred 
on no doubt by a need to know how high to make smoke stacks in cities) the 
rise height  can be related to envir onmental variables such as the background 
statification and the initial buoyancy (e .g. heat) flux from  the plume. During 
the plume rise, entrainmen t will draw surrounding fl uid int o the plum e and 
rotation effects will be seen (as in a hu rricane). Similarly, at the level wh ere 
the plume rise stops, fluid will spread away from  the center again feeling 
rotation (Speer &amp; Rona, JGR, 1989). Th is produces a cyclonic lower level 
flow and an anti-cyclonic flow at plum e height (bot h of which have been 
observed: Joyce et al., GRL, 1998). A series of these plumes located along a 
Ridge Crest or in an Axial Valley, may be largely responsible for the 
existence of anticyclonic m ean curre nts which flow along oceanic ridges 
(Helfrich et al., GRL, 1998).  
 
On a l arger scale, these plumes ofte n influence tem perature, salinity, and 
tracers far from their source. Th e best st udied cas es (East Pacific Rise, Juan 
de Fuca Ridge) have a nomalies extending westwa rd over a thousand km . 
The WOCE one-time hydrogra phic surve y included tracers such as deep 
helium , which have been used (Lupton,  JGR, 1998) to m ap out these helium  
plum es from Ridge venting 
sites. A north/south section 
across the Pacific Ocean 
(line P17, see figure at right) 
really consisted of multiple 
legs, which have been 
joined t ogether to look at 
a large-scale view of these 
plumes. The sources for the 
observed plumes (see color 
figure below) are from the 
East Pacific Rise (EPR) w
local maxima at 12S and 
8N, and Juan de Fuca (JdF)
Ridge, located just to the 
west of the NW US  coas
with a maximu m at 42N. 
The heliu m ano malies ar e ith 
 
t, Image removed due to
copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>still detectable far (in the case of th e EPR) from  their sources. These m us
have been advected b y mean flows in the abyssal Pacific Ocean. Lupto
makes the case that mean flows at the depths of t he plumes are consisten
with what is known about the deep circ ulation of t he Pacific as deduced by
Reid (Progress in Oceanog., 1997). t 
n 
t 
 
 
   
 
Stommel (Earth &amp; Plan. Sci. Lett., 1982)  explained the westward m otion of 
plum es in term s of the effect which causes te mperature ano malies to 
move westward from their source. Th ese plum es are im portant features in 
understanding how regions of deep wa ter m ass formation influence their 
local surroundi ngs. While their m otion is influenced by the effect &amp; 
Rossby wave propagation, which we will  study shortly, the spread of tracers 
such as helium  is mainly due to deep currents. Since mean flows in the deep 
interior of the ocean can be very sma ll, indirect (tracer) m easurements m ay 
be the best way to learn som ething a bout t hem. The vertical spreading of 
plum es may also be related to v ertical  velocities/m ixing in the abyssal ocean 
as well. Below the sea surface, 3He is not a conservative tracer. Its 
concentration will increase because of the radioactive decay of tritium  in 
seawater. At the surface, it outgases into  the at mosphere. Thes e effects n eed 
to be considered in any serious ci rculation budgets involving this tracer. 
  
 
 Image removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ekman layers, Friction&#160;and Geostrophic Flow (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_4n/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Notes on the  Geostrophic Balance 
 
 
Consider the diagram at  the 
right. The ocean consists of two 
density layers of uniform  
density 1 &amp; 2. The height of 
the free su rface is gi ven by 
h(x), that o f the interface by 
H(x) and o f the flat lower 
surface H 0: it neednt be the 
ocean bottom, only a level 
surface. We will use the 
hydrostati c relation to 
determ ine the pressure on the 
lower surface. It is given by the following: Z=0 Z=h 
Z= -H
Z= -H 0 1 
2 
 
) ( ) ( ) (0 2 1 0 H H g Hhg H zP  + + = =    
 
If at this surface ther e is no horizontal pressure gradient, Px = 0 and we get 
the followi ng (after canceling out g, which appears in both term s): 
 
1 22 1
,, ) ( 00
1  
 = + ==
where H horH H h P
x xx x x x
 
Since / 1 &lt;&lt; 1,  the interface thickens and d eepens much more than the 
free surface rises. For the Gulf Stream , the above picture is what one would 
see standi ng near Cape Hatteras and l ooking to the east. The s urface rises 
about 1 meter across the Gulf Stream  due to the strong flow at the surface, 
but this flow decays rapidly with depth. The density contrast across the 
pycnocline makes /1 ~ 2x10-3 so the pycnocline slopes down to the south 
(right) about 500m  across the Gulf Stream . Of course, the above situation is 
only an idealization of the actu al situation (the class will have a ho mework 
problem  using real data), but this illu strates the degree to which the density 
field can com pensat e for a non- level free surface expression.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Ekman layers, friction &amp; geostrophic flow  
 
The ho mework problem  (pucks_on_ice) illustrates several important points: 
 
1. Particles move perpendi cular to the applied force, to the right in the 
northern hem isphere, to the left  in the sout hern hem isphere 
2. Particles do not m ove steadily but oscillate with an inertial frequency, 
equal to 2 sin(), where  is the latitude 
3. After the external force is r emoved, particle motion  decays except 
when close to the bum p where th ey continue to rotate around the 
bump with high elevation on the right (left) in the northern (southern) 
hemisphere 
4. Due to friction, particles near the bum p slowly slide down the slope 
 
Point 1 is an illustration of Ekman lay ers in the ocean. A force (wind stress) 
pushes them at right angles in the rotating system. One m ight wonder how it 
is possible in such a world to driv e from California to Seattle: one would 
have to head westward in your car (tow ards the Paci fic Ocean) to get there! 
But in fact, friction for autom obiles is  rather large: the tires co nstantly 
impeded m otion except in the direction the car is pointed. So dont t ry this 
experiment!</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>(0) ()()
(0) ()()g
p
g
pDpfvpx xx
Dpfupyy   =  =+  
  = = +   y 
 
where we have used the definiti on of geopotential presente d earlier in term s 
of dynam ic height and also made us e of the fact that there is no horizont al 
variation of one of the term s in th e definiti on of geopotential which is 
proporti onal to the reference specific volume anom aly 0 .  he last pair of 
equations can be further sim plified recognizing that for p = 0  , D = 0 , thus  
 
ypDpu ufxpDpv vf
g gg g
= =  
)()]( )0([)()]( )0([
 
 
This is the form  of the geostrophic equations m ost comm only used since the 
gradient of geopotent ial at the free surface is not easily measured. It 
expresses how velocity will change with pressure based on horizontal 
gradients of dynam ic height. Without  any other inform ation, on cannot 
determ ine the geostrophic velocity at a point, onl y its variation with pressure 
(or depth):  there is an unknown constant , which can be de termined by fiat: 
[saying that the velo city at some refere nce pressure m ust be zero] or by other 
means [such as equating the veloc ity at some depth with direct 
measurements of velocity and then re quiri ng that measured velocity to be 
geostrophic]. [reference for s ome of this is Fofonoff in The Sea , Vol. 1]. In 
a later homework problem, we will ca lculate geostrophic currents using 
actual oceanographic data. Use of the above pair of equations will be 
essential  as well as understandi ng how to  use the co ncept of a deep 
reference pressure as a level of no m otion.  
 
On an f-plane, contours of constant  dynam ic height are equivalent to 
stream lines of the geostrophic flow re lative to so me assumed level of no 
motion. While this is a convenient f act and of m uch use in exam ining 
spatial m aps of dynam ic height from  hydrographic data, one must always be 
aware of t he limitati ons of this approximation. Because f can vary with 
latitude, this approximation breaks down for whole ocean b asins.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Frictional or Ekman layers can exist near the ocean bottom as well. This was 
also illustrated in the homework problem  as the pucks slowly slid down the 
sloping topography because of friction.  The main motion of the pucks was 
clockwise around the topographic bump. This reflects the geostrophic 
balance  between motion and the slope in surface elevation. Since frictional 
coupling is again strong when there is flow in near contact with the ocean 
bottom, this ageostrophic (non-geost rophic) motion, again deflects the 
trajectories of particles n ear to the bottom to the left of those further away 
from the bottom. This creates a spiral  in the opposite direction with net 
frictional flow to the left of the overl ying fluid (in the N. hemisphere). A 
similar result is obtained for geostro phic flow around a dimple. Near the 
bottom, friction upsets this balance a nd there is again a flow down the 
pressure gradient and a turning of the flow to the left of the interior motion.Image removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>We will now look at the equations e xpressing the geostrophic balance for 
baroclinic m otion. In our grand equa tions, we can wr ite the balance for 
geostrophi c motion [ (u,v)=(ug,vg)] as 
 



=

= 
ypfuxpfv
gg

 
 
where we have noted that the pressure  gradients in (x,y) are calculated on a 
constant geopotential surface f or clarity . Now recal l from  the definition of 
geopotential surfaces  that there is no ch ange in potential energy as a particle 
is moved in a surface of constant , and that (p(x,y),x,y)  explicitly depends 
on pressure as well as horizontal position.  We can u se this to make a ch ange 
of variables in the above. For exam ple, if  
 
, ,,
,, ,(( ,),,),
.
,0 ,
/.py xy px
yp y xypx yxythen
p xypx y
For y
pp
xx x p 


=
     = + +      
=
       =           
 
  
So we can write 
 
,
,/
/.pp xy
px yp
xx p
p
yy p

       = =         
       = =          px
y  
And our geostrophic balance becomes</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The variation of the particle m otion with  ever-increasing fricti on is shown in 
the figure above. As friction is increased  (relative to f ) the particle m oves 
more in the direction of the applie d force (blue arrow). The osci llation 
amplitude also decreases. In th e lim it in which friction is m uch larger than f , 
the m otion is in the direction of the applied force. 
 
The dynam ics behind the Pucks on Ice problem  is all contai ned in the 
equation for the change in m omentum  of a particle of mass m moving in a 
rotating system  about  a frozen, bum py su rface h(x,y) under the action of a 
body force, F and weak friction r . As we have seen, when friction is 
weak enough (in one lim it discussed above ), the pucks can do some things 
that are initially surprising when the body force is switched on and then off 
after a short time (3 days in the probl em). The dynam ical balance is given as G
() () ()() ()[2 ]
12 3 4dvmv mrvmghdt+ =  +JGGG JG
 5F
 
Each of the term s has been num bered to facilitate some discu ssion. One 
feature of the solution is that shortly  after the body force is either switched 
on or off, particles undergo osc illations in a circle. This oscillation is an 
inertial oscillation and is characterized as a balance betwee n term s (1) &amp; (2). 
Inertial oscillations: terms (1) &amp; (2) 
 
For those particles near the bum py topogr aphy, their m otion will be such as 
to move with velociti es that have the high topography on their right (i n the 
Northern Hem isphere, left in the S. He misphere). This balance is called the 
geostrophi c balance. 
Geostrophic flow: terms (2) &amp; (4) 
 
Under the action of the body force, partic les will m ove at right angles to the 
force, to the right in the N. hemisphe re (left in S. Hem isphere). This is 
represents a balan ce between term s (2) and (5) and is the fundamental 
balance in the wind-driven, Ekman tr ansport (after V. Walfrid Ekman). 
Ekman flow: terms (2) &amp; (5) [&amp;(3)] 
 
Weak friction will modify all of the above, and in the problem, the above 
balances are never exactly foll owed, onl y approxi mately, in different regions</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>and at different times. Yet these bal ances lie at the core of wind-driven 
motion in the ocean. In all of these cas es, the Coriolis fo rce (2) is central. 
 
Ekman flow in the ocean  
 
Now consider a non-frozen ocean forced  by an applied wind stress in the 
direction of the blue vector. For the su rface layer, turbulence is large and the 
effective friction is large: so a partic le will move downwind but slightly to 
the right (in the N. hemisphere, which we will assume in what follows). The 
layer below, which is causing the drag on the surface layer then wants to 
move too. It will move to the right of the overlying surface layer for the 
same reasons. This continues in the vertical until the turbulence, which 
couples the layers in the water column , eventually dies away and there is 
no subsequent motion. The resulting ve locity vector looks like a spiral: 
going from slightly downwind but to th e right of the wind, rotating to the 
clockwise and decaying with increasing depth. This was first pointed out by 
Ekman with a very simple model of the frictional coupling in 1905, and 
convincingly demonstrated in the ocean by Price, Weller and Schudlich 
(Science, vol. 238, pp 1534 -1538) in 1987. The net transport in this 
frictional layer is almost exactly to th e right of the stress as predicted! We 
call this surface layer of wind stress infl uence the Ekman layer. In the figure 
below, we can see this almost exact ba lance of net transport integrated over 
the surface Ekman layer, which is a bout 25m depth, and the wind stress, 
such that the net transport is the right of the wind stress (in the N. 
Hemisphere).</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction to &#8220;Waves&#8221; and Time Dependent Motion (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_16n/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>In the above, we have scaled the hor izont al wavenum bers by the radius of 
deform ation, and the frequency by the in ertial frequency. We  have chosen a 
couple of wave m odes of each t ype by setting the scaled meridional 
wavenumber ( la) to be 0 or 1.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>gH cwherelcgivingth
yhcexvxh vht lyi
====
222 222
22
2) (
,,0, ))(),((),(

 
 
Because the dispersion relation is quadr atic, there are two possible roots: one 
with a wave propagating to the north ( c &gt; 0 )  and one with the wave 
propagating to the south ( c &lt; 0 ). However, we will see that only one of these 
two roots is possible. The potential vortic ity equation, as before reduces to 
 
yvfth
Hf
xv
t yu
xv
t torth
Hf
t H hHf
dtd
zz z
==
=


==++
 ], [10] [
 
 
Where we have made us e of the fact that  u = 0, and the continuity equation 
(third equation at the bottom  of the prev ious page). We can  substitute in the 
above wave structure for ( h,v ) and get a very simple equation for the 
unknown structure in the x direction 
 
.0= vcf
xv
 
 
If a wave is propagating to the north ( c &gt; 0) in the northern he misphere, the 
has a solution exponentially grow s for positve values of  x  and 
exponentially decays for negative values of  x . We reject any solution which 
grows to be infinite as unphysical leaving only one choice for the direction 
of propagation of a Kelvin wave: w ith the coastline at its right (in the 
northern hem isphere). Im agine a square  basin in which a Kelvin wave is 
propagating around the bounda ry. In each  hemisphere it can propagate in 
only one direction: with the coast on its right (left) in the northern (southern) 
hemisphere. This particlar type of wa ve can exist at fre quencies below the 
local inertial frequency and is a special so rt of gravity wave in this regard. 
The scale at which the wave decays  away from  the boundary is the Rossby 
radius of deformation The other class of waves which exist at subinertial</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>We will ignore  the variation of the Coriolis paramet er at this time co mpared 
to other, larger term s, making this  equation reduce to a sim ple relation 
between surface elevation and vorticity for a fluid where potential vorticity 
is constant: 
 
),(], [
0 00 0
yxhhwherehhHfhHf z z
=+ = + =  
 
 
Gill m akes the point in his book that historically, the shallow water wave 
equations in a rotating system were solved many decad es before Rossby 
noticed that a non-zero constant represen ting som e initial vorticity or surface 
elevation was an i mportant factor. We  will see what  this does in what 
follows. Next, take the x-derivative of  the u-m omentum  equation and the y-
derivative of the v-mome ntum equation to get 
 
2122
2202
02
22
22
][,0 ,0),,(
gH cwhere fforthh coryxhf fH hfthh c
Hz
H
= =+ = = ++  
 
 
We have made use of the continuit y equation in deriving the above wave 
equation for the surface elevation. The quantity, c , has units of velocity and, 
for the case of no rotation, is the phase  speed at which an initial disturba nce 
will propagate. 
   
Consider the non-rotating  case at 
the right. The ocean  surface to the 
left of the origin (taken to be the x-
axis) is initially high and the surface 
to the right of the origin is low. As 
time develops, the interface will 
flatten as fluid m oves from  left to 
right and t he regions of high and 
low water will beco me separated as 
each side propagates as a wave to 
the right and left (at speed c ).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>In shallow water, of de pth 100m, the phase speed, c, takes on values of 30 
m/s. For waves of semi-diurnal tidal period (  12 hrs.) the wavelength,  = 
c , in the direction of propagation is approximately 1300 km. A quarter 
wavelength is approximately 300 km. A large bay, like the Bay of Fundy, 
has a length and depth such that a quarter wavelength of a free wave can 
fit in it. In this case, forcing at the opening of the bay can be amplified by 
what is called a  resonance , much like an organ pipe  can be forced to make 
an acoustic tone of wavele ngth 4 times the length of the pipe. In this case, 
weak forcing at the opening can cause a large  response. Tides in the Bay of 
Fundy reach maximum amplit udes in the head of the bay of 16 meters and 
are among the largest in the ocean. St rong currents flowing into the Bay 
form hydraulic bores which are impressive to see.  
 
 
 
 
 Image removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>experiment in POLYMODE in the late  70s (J. Price &amp; T. Rossby, JMR, 
supp. to vol. 40, 1982).  
A number of SOFAR floats were releas ed at a depth of 1300m in the sound 
channel near 31N, 70W in the N. Atla ntic. Over a period of 9 weeks about 
12 of the 18 floats took part in a textbook example of a Rossby wave 
oscillation. This is shown in the next figure (below).  
 In this case, the authors have account ed for (weak) variations in the bottom 
bathymetry which give a slight tilt to the lines of constant f / H, which are 
dashed in the above figure (with per cent changes from a reference). As the Image removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>frequencies is Rossby waves,  which we will consider  next for m id-latitudes 
only, due to lim itation on our availabl e time. However, it should be noted 
that the Kelvin wave can ex ist at the equator. When f = y (near the 
equator), this wave can only propagate from  west to  east along the equator in 
either hemisphere, but not across it. The Kelvin wave is discussed in the text 
of Ocean Circulation  in section 5.3.1, although one can get confused by the 
discussion because at some poi nts the text is describing internal  Kelvin 
waves, not barotropic  or surface  Kelvin waves as we have just covered. 
Internal Kelvin waves will be discussed in a later section. We now turn to 
Rossby waves, in which vorticity is the dom inant restoring force, not 
gravity. 
 
Mid-lati tude Rossby Waves 
 
Looking down at the surface of  the ocean (see figure) consider a thick, bl ack 
line of displaced fluid as shown. We h ave drawn so me si mple lines of 
constant planetary 
vorticity   ( f / H ) 
which represent 
variations either due 
to changes in 
latitude or to 
changes in wat er 
depth. We are in the 
northern hem isphere 
because in the 
southern 
hemisphere, shallow water would be equivalent to the south  and vice versa 
for deep water. In the absence o f external forces or friction, potential 
vorticity m ust be conserved, so particle s on the line that have been displaced 
to the north m ust develop anticyclonic (negative) relative vorticity and those 
to the south cyclonic (positive) relativ e vorticity. This is represented by the 
circles with arrows, showing the flow co nsistent with this relative vorticity. 
What will happen to this syste m? If vor ticity conservation acts as a restoring 
force, it should try to m ove this stru cture back towards zero. Looking at the 
crest on the left, the circulation will tr y to drag down the fluid line to the 
right of the crest and drag up the fluid lin e to the left of the crest. Looking at 
the trough to the right, fluid m otion will try to push up the trough to the right 
and pull it down to the left . The net result of the pushing and pulling is the 
dashed curve, which indicates that th e initial disturbance has m oved to the  North/Sha llow
South/Dee p</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>west or equivalently,  moved with th e shallow water on the right. For a 
southern hem isphere, the wave would still m ove to the west but it would 
also m ove with shallow water on its left. The restoring force of potentia l 
vorticity c onservation thus acts to prod uce westward m otion of a disturbance 
over water of constant depth. This is called a Rossby wave. In cas es in 
which variations of topography dom inate over variations of latitude, it is 
called a topographic Rossby wave. We wi ll exam ine how fast this wave 
propagates and what are its propertie s for a case of constant depth. 
 
The equations of m otion should look fa miliar as they have been used for 
each of the types of waves di scussed up until now. They are: 
 
.0] [,,
=++= +=
yv
xuHthyhg futvxhg fvtu
 
] [10] [ vth
Hf
t H hHf
dtdz z
 +=++ 
 
We are going to look for waves with frequencies mu ch less than the local  
inertial frequency, unlike gravity waves. In  this case, we will want to neglect 
the acceleration terms on th e momentum equations com pared to the coriolis 
terms. We call this approxim ation quasigeostrophic . Thus 
 
1)/()/(,)/(,)/(&lt;&lt;  
xhgtu
futv
fvtu
 
 
The PV equation (last one) will be us ed without any approxim ations. With 
these assum ptions, we can obtain a single equation in a single unknown (a 
wave- equation), which we will write  down for the surface elevation, h .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>0   0] [  )0 (0  
= + =++= + = += = =  =
Hvilhiyv
xuHthhgl ufviyhg futvk hgk vfuixhg fvtu

 
 
Note that even though the x-wavenumber  is zero, t he x-veloci ty is not 
because of rotation. The energy flux term s are the important ones to consider 
here. W aves are weakly dissipated (by bottom  friction) and energy, averaged 
over a wavelength is conserve d. This means that the energy flux is constant 
in the y-direction (recall that the wave is pr opagating in this direction). This 
flux, Fy, averaged over a wavelength can be  written using the above relations 
as: 
 
1 )/( , )/(2 2 2&gt;&gt; &gt; &lt; &gt; &gt;=&lt; &gt;=&lt; &lt; f for h gc l gh gHvh Fy      
 
So as the wave slows down as it gets into shallow water (since c2=gH ) it 
must have a constant energy flux and thus its am plitude goes up. The root 
mean square (rm s) am plitude g oes as the   th power of the depth according 
to 
 
4/1 2/1 2) (  &gt; &lt; H gc h hrms   
 
Imagine a 1 meter am plitude wave at the site of generation in 4000m  of 
water. When this wave gets into shallow water ( e.g. H= 4 m), its rms 
amplitude is 5.6m . And the peak am plitude may be a few ti mes larger than 
the rm s. That is why tsunam i warnings send residents to highe r ground. It is 
also why storm  surges, with amplitudes of 50 cm  in the deep ocean (due to a 
low pressure in a hurricane of about 50  mbar) can become significant at the 
shoreline. When ocean swe ll propagates into shallow water, it can be studied 
within the approxim ation of shallow water which we have made. Thus, 
this am plitude am plification above also  applies to ocean swell and explains 
wave steepening near the shore; it cannot explain breaking, which m ust 
include non-linearity and dissipation.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>gravity  approxim ation that will allow us to skip lots of math already co vered 
by the surface wave discussion.  
 
Long [hydrostatic] surface waves 
 
The equations of m otion we have deri ved for a shallow layer of constant 
density are, ignoring external forces and friction 
 
 
yvxut dtdwhere hHvyhHux thyhg fudtdvxhg fvdtdu
++= ++ ++= +=
,0)] ([ )] ([,,
  
 
We will be linearizing these (valid for small perturbations) about a state of 
no m otion over a flat bottom  (or nearly fl at). This will sim plify the above to 
the following: 
 
.0] [,,
=++= +=
yv
xuHthyhg futvxhg fvtu
 
 
We will also be m aking use of the pot ential vorticity equation in a linearized 
form , so lets write that down as we ll (it can be derived from  the above 
three). 
 
] [10] [ vth
Hf
t H hHf
dtdz z
 +=++</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Returning now to the 
case of a l ong surface 
wave propagating to 
the south ( x-
wavenumber, k =0), 
we can see from  the 
above that the ratio of 
the velocity in the x-
direction to that in the 
y-direction is 
proportional to ( f / ), 
and that the two are 
out of phase by 90o. If 
we integrate the 
velocity to track what 
a particle of fluid will 
experience during one 
cycle of th e wave, we 
get the plot at the right. Particles will undergo an elliptical orbit with the 
major axis aligned with the direc tion of wave propagation. For high 
frequencies (com pared to the inertial frequency) the ellipse will be narrow, 
with m ost of the displacements in north /south direction in which the wave is 
propagating. As the frequency approach es the inertial frequency, the orbits 
becom e more circular, until at the iner tial frequency, the orbits are a perfect 
circle, m uch like our old pucks on ice model . Whether the wave is 
propagating from  north to south or south to north, the direction of rotation is 
always clockwise for the northern he misphere. We see for this sim ple 
exam ple that the horizontal velocity is never zero due to rotation. At very 
high frequencies, the m otion becom es two dimensional in the direction of 
propagation, with horizontal and vertical  velocities only in this plane. We 
cannot tell which direction the wave is  propagating from  a plot of the two 
horizontal velocities. To do this, we need to look at the phase of the 
horizontal velocity com pared to the ve rtical displacement of the free sur face. 
The relation between the frequency and the wavenum ber of waves is called 
the dispersion relation. For long gravity waves, this is sim ply the following:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>2 2 22 2 222 2 222 2 2
/), (), 1(,
fc aandl kwhere a forc f
+ + =+ =
  
 
 
recall that a  is the Rossby radius. Thus, it is for wavelengths that are short 
(wavenu mbers that are large) compar ed to the Rossby radius that rotation 
becom es unim portant. The m inimum freque ncy is the inertial frequency, but 
there is a class of gravity wave for which there is no lower frequency lim it: it 
is a Kelvin Wave, which we will exam ine now. 
 
Kelvin Waves 
 
In the case that waves are propagating next to a solid boundary, it is clear 
from  the above that even if the boundary is parallel to the direction of wave 
motion, there will be a velocity into the boundary. If this boundary is the 
western boundary of an ocean basin, say at x = 0 in a recta ngular ocean, we 
can get a class of waves that satisfy th e condition that there be no flow into 
the boundary: just set u to be zero everywhere  in the wave equations.  
 
.0 0] [,,
=+=++== +==
yvHth
yv
xuHthyhgtv
yhg futvxhg fvxhg fvtu
 
 
This wave propagates in the y-directi on with a phase speed c as before, but 
has no velocity in the east/west direction. 
 
From  the above equations one can imme diately see that the dynam ics in the 
x - direction (norm al to the boundary at x = 0) are geostrophic, with slopes 
in the free surface bal anced by p ressure gradients. As before, we can 
eliminate variables to get a sin gle wav e equation for the free s urface, h , 
which we can write as follows:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>out quickl y: if an earthquake near the Al eutian Island arc causes a rise in sea 
level locally, this will arrive at the Hawaiin Islands in about 2 hours. Of 
course, once the wav e gets into sha llow water, it will start to slow down 
since the p hase speed  depends on the squa re root of t he local depth, but at 
this poi nt another important thi ng happe ns: the wav e amplifies. In order to 
see this, we need to look at the energetics of these surface wav es. 
 
If we m ultiply the x-momentum equation by Hu and the y-m omentum 
equation by Hv and add them  together, the Coriolis term s drop out and we 
get an equation for t he kinetic energy of the waves: 
 


+=
+
yhHvxhHug v uHt  ) (21 2 2
  
 
The quantity in brackets on the left ha nd side is the kinetic en ergy of the 
wave m otion. The potential energy of  the wave m otion is obtai ned by 
multiplying the continuity equa tion by gh to give 
 


+=


yHvhxHuhg ght 2
21 
 
If we add these two equati ons, we get the total ener gy of the wave m otion: 
 
hugH Fand gh v uH EwhereyF
xF
tEy x
GG
 
=
+
+ =++
,21) (21,0
2 2 2 
 
If we i magine that we averag e the wave over one wavele ngth, we get an 
average value for the total energy a nd energy flux. W e will denote this 
average by &lt; &gt;. No w to simplify things, suppose the wave is propagating 
in the negative y-direction (southward from  the Aleutians towards Hawaii) 
and its frequency is m uch higher than the inertial frequency, the relationship 
between the vertical motion at t he surface ( h) and the horizontal velocity, 
(u,v), is readily given by the above equations:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Introduction to waves and time dependent motion (12.808) 
 
One aspect of observational physical oc eanography not treated in the course 
thus far is time-dependent motion. This  can be considered to be of two 
types: forced  [such as the annual cycle of mixed layer deepening/shoaling, 
and tidal forcing] and free [natural modes of oceanic response]. Since how 
the ocean responds is not unrelated to how it wants to respond, we will 
consider the natural modes first. Natural time-dependent modes most obvious are waves. Many types of thes e are familiar to everyone: the ocean 
surface rises and falls due to natural fluctuations that are not locally 
generated, but arise from distant fo rcing. Long swell is a good example. 
When the surf is up is when waves generated by distant storms arrive at 
local beaches. They have traveled thousands of km. from their point of origin. Other types of surface waves are a tsunami, a disturbance caused by 
sudden shifts in the earths bathymetry [e.g. earthquakes], or a storm surge, 
caused by rapid, large-scale shifts  in surface pressure [hurricanes 
approaching the coast]. We will begin with these long, low frequency waves. 
An essential characteristic of these motions is that they are hydrostatic : 
vertical acceleration in these waves are a small fraction of gravity. While 
limiting, there is still a rich pantheon of wave motion contained within this 
class of wave. It includes the following: 
 
 Long gravity waves 
 Mixed gravity/inertial waves 
 Kelvin &amp; edge waves 
 Vorticity waves [i.e. Rossby waves] 
 
The latter contains waves that exist over flat bottoms and those which rely 
on variations in bottom topography (top ographic Rossby waves). Under each 
of the above categories, there are wave s that have their maximum vertical 
displacement at the ocean surface &amp; ar e insensitive to the ocean stratification 
[surface waves] and those which have  their maxima in vertical motion 
within the water column with little vertical motion at the free surface 
[internal waves]. We will try to treat both of these. We will see that some 
waves exist in the absence of rota tion, others depend upon rotation, and 
yet others depend on variation of th e rotation rate with latitude. We will 
make this introduction as simple as possible by considering most of the mathematics for a homogeneous density ocean [no stratification], but will 
show that each of the internal wa ve counterparts has exactly the same 
dynamics but with a apparent gravity that is much reduced. It is this reduced</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>This condition is call  non-dispersive . With rotation, this changes. To 
better see this, we n eed to consider  how individual waves of a given 
frequency and scale propagate . It is customary to consider a sinusoi dal wave 
as a test case, recognizing that we  can always sum  up many indivi dual 
waves to solve a given problem. Consider  a wave of the foll owing structure: 
 
)] sin() cos()[,,( ),,(,,) (t lykx it lykx hvu ehvu hvut lykxi + + + = + 
 
The quantity   is the frequency of the wave and the x-wavenum ber k =2/x 
is inversely related to the wav elength in the x-direction. If, for exam ple, 
waves are only propa gating in t he x-direction, as in our exam ples above, 
then the y-wavenu mber, l , would be zero (an infi nite wavelength in t he y-
direction: or constant in y). If we insert this test wave into the equations, we 
get the relationshi ps of the wave vari ables (shown above with carats) to one 
another. If we substit ute this form into the wave equation (i gnoring the 
constant term depending on h0(x,y) as we are now tal king above the waves) 
we g et the following: 
 
) ( &amp;),,(,
2 2 222 2 2
l k lkwhere c f
H HH
+ = + =
   
 
The quantity H is the horizont al wavenum ber in the direction of wave 
propagation. This equation relating freque ncy to wavenum ber is called a 
dispersi on relation and is im portant for the study of wavem otion. We see 
that the lowest  frequency of surface gravi ty waves i s the inertial  frequency 
and that inertial waves ar e a speci al case in which the horizont al 
wavenumber is zero (infini te wavelengt h). We can  also see t hat for waves 
with frequencies that  are much larger than f ,  
 
2 222 2
,,
f for cor c
HH
&gt;&gt; 
   
 
 
We define the wave phase speed as the ra tio of the frequency to 
wavenumber and we see that for this lim it, the wave speed is identical to c. 
In this lim it, all wav elengths travel at the same speed, which we h ave 
estimated above to be 200 m /s for water of 4000m  depth.  This is pretty fast: 
a wave co uld cross an ocean of  width 4000 km (like the N.  Atlantic) in a 
little m ore than 3 hours! This is why ts unam i warnings are important to get</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>floats reach their maxim um northern excursion, t hey develop anticyclonic 
vorticity, which is clearly indicated in upper right 2 panels. At their 
southernmost extr eme, cyclo nic vortic ity is also cl ear (see th e 20 June 
panel). The authors estim ate a period of  about 61 days, a wavelength of ca. 
340 km . And a direction of propagati on towards 300 degrees true. What is 
amazing in an exten ded timeseries is that after the p eriod shown in the 
figure, there is little evidence for thei r presence. Th e interlude of their 
passage was brief! While the crests of  these waves were propagating to the 
WNW, their energy was actually propaga ting to the east, away  from a likely 
source in the Gulf Stream. Were there an altim eter, it m ight have been 
difficult to track them because of their small scale and the small signal at the 
ocean surface (sever al cm. amplitude). Bu t as we s hall see l ater, these waves 
can be tracked from  space. We haven t talked about energy propagation 
since our discussion of long surface grav ity waves, but for Rossby waves, it 
is fairly com plicated and beyond the scope of this course. Simply said, 
energy propagates wi th somethi ng called t he group velocity  which is defined 
as follows: 
 
2 2 22
) (1),, (
al kkawherel kck g
+ +=
= 
 G
 
 
We will plot this dispersion diagram  below including all the types of waves 
discussed t hus far. It is conventi onal to onl y plot posi tive frequencies, but 
allow wavenum bers to have either si gn. We have constructed one such 
diagram based on a waves c ourse (12.802) taught by Dr. Joe Pedlosky. It 
shows the inertial/gravity (also calle d Poincar waves) dispersion diagra m 
together with Kelvin and Rossby waves that are propagating at m id-
latitudes: all waves are ba rotropi c. Notice that Rossby waves exist onl y on 
one side (negative) of the wav enumber axis for positive frequencies. Also, 
Kelvin waves m ust propagate with the coast on their right (in the N. 
Hem isphere). Thus the Kelvin wave on the right (l eft) side of the diagram 
must be propagating to the east (west)  with a side boundary on its right.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Eventually, there will be a flat i nterface in the field of view but the fluid will 
still be m oving from  left to right as the far field adjusts to the initial 
disturbance. This is an exam ple of waves in a non-rotating syst em.  
 
The cas e for a rotating system  is very different, as illustrated in the next 
diagram (at right). Here we have th e same initial condition, but as the 
interface adjusts, a steady, geos troph ic flow develops at the ini tial 
disconti nuity. A wave signal 
propagates away as before (with a 
slight ly different phase speed as we 
will see shortly). But behind it there is 
no u-com ponent of velocity as in the 
previous c ase and the surface does not 
beco me flat. Instead, a v-co mponent 
of flow (out of the page for the 
northern hem isphere) is left behind. 
This stead y flow is a solution to the 
steady part of the wave equation for 
a rotating system , which m ust satisfy 
the following: 
 
   
fcf gH awhere eaf gh vuxfor e hhxfor e hhthenx h yxhiforyxhf fH hfh c
axaxaxz
H
/ /, ) / (00 ], 1[0 ], 1[), sgn( ),(),,(
/
0/
0/
00 002
02 2 2
= ==&lt;  =&gt; + === = + 

  
x
v 
 
The quantity a , has units of di stance and is called th e Rossby Radius of 
Deform ation, after Carl Rossby who first solved the problem  of geostrophic 
adjustm ent. In order to put some real  num bers into the above, consider an 
ocean of d epth 4000m. In this case the p hase speed  c = sqrt( gH) = 200 m /s, 
and with a value of f = 10-4 s-1, we g et a = 2000 km . The waves that spread 
out from  the origin have a permanent shape in the non-rotating case:  they do 
not change shape. This is becau se all wavelengths move at the same speed.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>22 2
2
2
2210Hhhaatx
cg Haff + =
=,where
 
 
You will notice that unlike the other wav e equations so far, this one is only 
first order in time (only one time derivative). Again, we will look for 
wavelike solutions and use the above to get a dispersion relation between 
frequency and wavenum ber: 
 
. ,1)] sin() cos()[,,( ),,( ,,
2 2 2
222) (
lk whereakat lykx it lykx hvu ehvu hvut lykxi
+ =+=+ + + = +
 
 
 
Only westward phase speeds are possible  in this solution since  / k &lt; 0. 
These are the Rossby waves pictur ed in the above diagram . For 
wavenu mbers much s maller th an the radius of deformation, a (very long 
wavelengths), the second term in the above denom inator is small and the 
Rossby waves are non-dispersi ve: they all have the sam e westward phase 
speed independently of wavenum ber. In fact, they only prop agate to the west 
with no north/south wavenumber. For wavenu mbers mu ch larger than the 
radius of deformation, of deformati on (short waves), phase speed actually 
decreases with increasing wav enumb er. At the radius of deformation, these 
waves attain their maxim um frequency, which we will now estimate. Tak e ( 
k , l ) = ( a-1, 0 ), making  ka = 1.  We will now insert some typical values 
for the remaining variables to see what we h ave.  
  
days sx s xmx a ms xaaka
6.3 1014.3 /2 102, 102 ;)( 102.2/1
5 1 56 1 11222
 = =  = = =+=
  
  
 
This is not m uch greater than the local  inertial period for m id-latitudes (ca. 1 
day), bringing our quasigeostrophic assum ption into question, but this 
frequency is meant to represent the largest frequency possibl e. What is 
actually observed in lower in frequenc y than this upper lim it. We will 
illustrated this with some real da ta taken during the local dynam ics</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Global Hydrographic Climatology (PDF)
Supporting Files
atlas_test.m (M)
ghc_Ni.mat (MAT - 21.1 MB)
ghc_Oxkg.mat (MAT - 21.1 MB)
ghc_Ph.mat (MAT - 21.1 MB)
ghc_pr.mat (MAT - 63.4 MB)
ghc_Sil.mat (MAT - 21.1 MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/gbl_hgpc_atlas/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>WOCE hydrographic Atlas, fig. 3
It is oft en common to 
plot properties on density 
surfaces, in order to see 
water mass structure. We 
have used neutral density 
surfaces for this exercise. 
Neutral surfaces will vary 
for a fi xed pressure 
because of geostrophic
flow in the ocean. At the 
right are plotted neutral 
density at the surface and 
at 1000 dbar.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>WOCE hydrographic Atlas, fig. 2
At the right, I have plotted 
the temperature and salinity 
at a pressure of 1000 dbar. 
Note the large saliniti es in 
the North Atlantic and NW 
Indian Oceans: these are 
due to outflows from the 
Mediterranean and Red 
Seas, respecti vely. The 
Arctic Ocean appears to be 
cut off from the rest of the 
ocean because 1000 dbar is 
below the sill depths for the 
Bering Straight and the 
Iceland/Faroe Ridges.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>WOCE hydrographic Atlas, 1
As a re sult of the World Oc ean Circulation Experiment ( WOCE ), a 
hydrographic survey of the world oceans occurred from 1990-1998. 
These data were unprecedented in terms of the global coverage and 
quality. They were subsequently used by a group in Ha mburg (Goruretski
&amp; Koltermann, BSH Tech. Ret. 35/2005)  to regionally correct previous 
cruise data, and produce a Global Hydrographic Climat ology [GHC] of 
gridded hydrographic data [half degree of lat/lon] at 45 standard depth 
levels for the world oceans. Spatia l averaging ranged from 50 to 700 km 
scales, with smaller scales near boundaries and where available data 
density allowed. While nutrients an d oxygen we included in the gridded
Atlas, we will be using just temper ature, salinity, and neutral density 
(Jackett &amp; MacDougall, JPO 1996). And si nce we want a tool for global 
calculations, we will subsample the half degree climatology to every 
whole degree of lat/l on[reduction of  file sizes by a factor of 4].</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>WOCE hydrographic Atlas, fig. 4
At the right salinity has been 
plotted following the neutral 
density surface 27.95. This 
surface is one which can 
charact erize the classical 
Labra dor Sea Water . One 
can see this level to be 
shallow in the Lab Sea and to 
have its lowest salinities 
locally there. The layer 
obviously comes near or to 
the surface in the Southern 
Ocean, where low salinities 
are also imprinted.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>WOCE hydrographic Atlas, fig. 1
To begin with, we select 
the temperature (upper) 
and sal inity (lower) values 
at the ocean surface and 
plot their global 
distribution. White values 
are generally over land 
but in other figures at 
greater pressures, they 
will be where the pressure 
level does not exist i n the 
data file. Bathymetry 
contours (black lines) are 
plotted at 1, 3, and 5 km 
depth.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>WOCE hydrographic Atlas, fig. 8
Finally, we plot a 
/S diagram for 
data along the 
170W section 
from the previous 
figure. We have 
coded the points to 
contrast those in 
the polar regi ons 
from the central 
Pacific. In the 
former, one can 
see near surface 
waters at or very 
close to the 
freezing point.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>WOCE hydrographic Atlas, fig. 5
At the right, we have plotted 
pressure (top) and sal inity 
(bottom) on the neutral density 
of 27.3. This density is one 
which rises to the surface 
(outcrops) in the Southern 
Ocean and is a good level for 
tracing propert ies of Antarctic 
Intermediate Water (AAIW). 
We can also see effects of the 
Red Sea and Med Outflows. 
Note how this display shows a 
much broader salty Med 
tongue than on the 1000 dbar
pressure level.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>WOCE hydrographic Atlas, fig. 7
Other neutral layers are plotted 
with the atlas_test program. For 
now, we move on to a different 
display. Here we select a particular 
longitude (190 or 170W) and plot a 
vertical section from south to 
north across the central Pacific 
Ocean. We have calculated 
potential temperature and plotted it 
(bottom) and salinity (upper). Note 
the outcropping of cold water in 
the Southern Ocean and the 
appearance of intermediate waters 
of low salinity in both the Southern 
Ocean ( AAIW ) and North Pacific 
(North Pacific Intermediate 
Water : NPIW ).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>WOCE hydrographic Atlas, 2
Because we want a tool for calculati ons, the origi nal depth levels were 
resampled or interpolated onto pressu re levels (in decibars) so that 
standard calculations for potenetia ltemperature, potential density, 
geopot ential anomaly [dynamic height] could be easily made with our 
MATLAB routines. Each of the gridded data arrays are padded with NaNs
where no data are available [over la nd or below the local ocean water 
depth/pressure]. Each array is thr ee dimensional with latitude, longitude 
and pressure the three independent variables. Thus salinit y, 
(dataS_pr(171x360x45) has 171 lati tudes [-80:90],  360 longitudes [0:359] 
and pressures [variable 1:45]. Lo cal bathymetry is provided by the 
MATLAB topo one degree file. The MATLAB script  atlas_test.m  
was used to create all of the following fi gures. It, as well as the data file 
[GHC_pr] can be found in the course notes under  GHC Files.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Large Scale Thermohaline Circulation: Some Thermodynamics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_9n/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>This looks deceptively sim ple for salin ity until we realize that at the ocean 
surface, th ere is a net  velocity because of an i mbalance bet ween 
Precipitation, P, and Evaporation, E. A positive vertical velocity is one in 
which the sea surface is m oving upw ards because of a net freshwater 
addition: t hus at the free surface, w = (P- E). As we will soon see, the salinity 
flux at the free surface is given by - (P-E)S .  
 
Consider a colu mn of fluid extendi ng from the free surface to the ocean 
bottom . If we integrate the potential te mperature and salinity equations i n 
this fluid colum n, we will get th e following expressions: 
 
]]
]] ) ( ) ( , H z hz where Sw StSdzQ wC Q QtCdz
h
Hh
H vh
Hh
Hh
H p e v ph
H
= =   =  + =
 
 


     
 
 
We hav e lumped for the mo ment all of the divergences due to horizontal 
flows into a couple of term s, Qv and Sv. [we will return to these later, dont 
worry!]  We have also explicitly writte n down an internal heat source term 
depending on the evaporation. Ignori ng the heat flux through t he ocean 
bottom  due to geotherm al heating: Q(z=-H)  and writing the vertical velocity, 
potential tem perature and salin ity in two parts: w=&lt;w&gt;+w , etc., wh ere the 
brackets refer to the average p roperty and the prime represent s the 
fluctuations, the above can be re-written: 
 
]
]h
H vh
Hh
H p p e v ph
H
S w hzSw StSdzhzQ w C hz w C Q QtCdz



&gt; &gt;&lt;&lt;&gt;= &lt;&gt; =&lt;&gt;&lt;&gt;= &lt;&gt; &gt;&lt;&lt; &gt;= &lt; &gt; &lt;+&gt; =&lt;&gt;&lt;

     
) ('') ( ) (''
 
 In the above we have ignored small sp atial variations of densi ty and heat 
capacity and conside red only the ba lance for the &lt;av erage&gt; quantities. 
Turbulent fluxes or heat w ill produce an average product &lt;w&gt; that is 
non-zero; this need not be the case for salinity because salt is n ot transferred 
across the air-sea boundary [we will ignore this &lt; wS&gt; ter m]. We can 
define the turbulent sensible heat flux as &lt; Qh&gt;  -Cp&lt;w&gt; and if we</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>The salinity equation does not show a ( P-E) term at the surface, but 
remember that the integration is from the bottom to the top of the ocean and 
that the upper surface may not be stea dy or even if it is, there will be 
divergence in the horizontal volume flux (contained in Sv) that is required to 
balance ( P-E) at the surface. We have rewritte n this equation in terms of ( P-
E) by defining a global average salinity, S0 and relating the horizontal 
divergence of the volume transport to ( P-E) at the surface. The salinity 
balance is very sensitive to ocean advection: there being no other terms that 
force it! It is the salinity balance that is used to estimate the freshwater 
transport of the ocean in climate calculations. 
 
We could have been fa ncier and also derived horizontal eddy flux terms 
(proportional to &lt;u &gt;, &lt;uS&gt;) for heat and salt, but this would not 
materially add to the above  material since this argument is similar to the 
vertical eddy flux discussion just pres ented. This decomposition into small-
scale, random fluctuations and an en semble average stat e lies at the very 
heart of eddies &amp; parameterization of  turbulence. Also, we might mention 
that one can consider areas of rainfa ll as adding volume (or mass) to the 
ocean surface at one temperature, a nd areas of evaporation as areas of 
decreasing volume at a different  temperature. This gives rise to another flux 
term proportional to &lt;w (z=h)&gt;  at the ocean surface  that is slightly 
different than the turbulent sensible  flux used above. Even if on average 
w=(P-E)=0 , there can be a net heat flux due  to small-scale variations of 
rainfall/evaporation that ar e correlated with temperat ure differences [rainfall 
in the tropics is colder than the surf ace water/air temperature]. This is a way 
that freshwater flux can affect the heat balance, not just the salt balance, 
which is thru the term which we ignored above: &lt; wS(z=h)&gt; . In the tropics, 
this rainfall heat flux can become impor tant and must be considered to get 
the net heat balance correct. 
 
The above heat and salt e quations govern the large- scale thermodynamics of 
the ocean. In a steady-state, the left hand sides of each must vanish making a 
balance among the various surface flux terms as presented in the text, 
including ocean heat transport dive rgence. An active freshwater cycle 
involving ( P-E) may balance globally, but not locally, and must therefore 
require ocean advection since there ar e no salt fluxes across the air-sea 
boundary.  
 
Because of strong seasonality in surf ace forcing, there may be large local 
changes in heat (heat storage) that ar e released locally during winter. A heat</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>One can see that  replacing ice in the arctic  ocean with open water will 
greatly increase the am ount of shortwave radiation entering the  ocean, thus 
warm ing the ocean further. However,  cloud form ation will be increased, 
which acts as an absorber of longwave (infrared) radiation, but also reflects 
shortwave radiation. So the response is  com plicated, but generally there is a 
positive feedback [which means a perturbation can be am plified] .  
 
The earth radiates back to space at long wavelengths. The am ount depends 
on the 4th power of the temp erature, T, a nd is a function of the emissivity. 
Black bodi es (perfect radiators and abso rbers) have an em issivity of 1. A 
perfect ref lector has an emissiv ity of 0. The emissiv ity over the ocean is a 
function of its roughness and m icrow ave sensors looking down on the ocean 
must take this int o account before esti mation of ski n temperature. In fact, 
microwav e emissions from  the ocean  tell us som ething about both 
temperature and roughness (related to stress), and it is possible to estimate 
wind stress and skin temperatur e at the same time! We say skin 
temperature because m ost of the long wave radiation is em itted/absorbe d 
within the upper cm  of the ocean su rface. Shorter wavelengths penetrate 
deeper, wi th blue light reaching depths  of 100m  in cal m, clear wat er. In 
general, sh ortwave radiation is absorb ed in the upper ocean  according to the 
optical properties of the ocean, wh ich can be dependent on biol ogical 
productivi ty. Thus, a careful heat budget of the ocean m ust take into account 
the biology! 
 
The Greenhouse Effect  [After Gill, 1982] 
 
Consider the following sim ple model of the earth.  
 
  
I 
I I (1-e)U
UB
B
Groun dGlassShortwaves Longwaves</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>There is an incident energy flux per unit area due to shortwave radiation 
with an intensity I. This radiation passes thru th e glass [atm osphere] and hits 
the ground, wher e it is all absorbed. The outward flux due to radiation of the 
earth as a black body [e missivity of 1]  is U = T4. A fraction of this energy, 
e, is absorbed by the glass, whi ch then causes the glass to heat up and radiate 
like a black body, and am ount B. In both the region below and above the 
glass layer, the net radia tion m ust balance giving 
 
4(1 ) ,
/(1 /2)gI eU BUB
withT U I e = +=
==  
Thus, the ground tem perature can be increased (up to 19%: for e = 1) over 
the case in  which there is no glass ( e = 0). Try putting in a test value, say e = 
0.1, and solving for t he ground tem perature with the solar flux value given 
above and the numerical value for the constant  . The result is 284 oK, or 
11 oC, which is fairly close to the m ean tem perature of the ground on t he 
earth.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>balance that has large seasonality in flux es and local storage is characteristic 
of most areas of the o cean away from strong horizontal flows. In these 
regions, a 1-D mixed layer model may work quite well in explaining most of 
the seasonal changes of heat and salt.  Ocean advection can upset this 1-D 
balance and, in fact, is required to balance significant seasonally-averaged 
fluxes of heat and freshwa ter at the ocean surface. 
 
 
Some issues about radiation 
 
All bodies radiate energy at a rate equal to T4, where  is the emissivity, 
 is a constant (=5.7x10-8 W m-2 K-4), and T is absolute temperature (oK). 
This is called Stephans Law. For light, energy is proportional to frequency, 
so the sun, which has a surface temperature of app. 6000 oK radiates with 
more energy at higher frequencies (s horter wavelengths) than the earth, 
which has an absolute temperature of about 284 oK. The average radiation 
received at the mean radi us of the earth from the sun (called the solar 
constant) is 1.368x103 W m-2, and that received on average at the outer edge 
of the earths atmosphere is this value divided by 4: 344 W m-2. This varies 
over the course of the year because the earths orbit is an ellipse. Presently, 
earth is closest to the sun in the sout hern summer, but this situation changes 
with time (and with a period of app. 23000 yrs.). Not all of the short wave 
radiation reaching the outer atmosphere gets to the surface of the earth. Over 
the ocean, about half is reflected by clouds, absorbed by the atmosphere, or 
reflected from the ocean surface. Th e percent reflection is called the albedo , 
had it varies widely with the surface properties. Below is a table with 
different albedos for different surfaces. 
 
 
 
Surface Albedo (%) 
Snow Up to 90 
Desert sands 35 
Vegetation 10-25 
Bare soil or rock 10-20 
Built up areas 12-18 
Calm water 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>The L arge Scale Therm ohaline Circulation: som e 
therm odynamics  
 
Thus far, we h ave dealt w ith mechanical forces on fluids suc h as friction and 
wind stress. The consideration of extern al forces i n the ocean must include 
exchange of heat an d freshwater at th e ocean surface. This is a co mplicated 
phenom enon and far beyond this course. In  fact, there is very little written 
about this in the literature co mpared to  mechanical f orcing because it is s o 
hard! Interested readers can refer to the Gill and Batchelor books referenced 
at the beginning of the course. We  will write down some large-scale 
equations t hat approximate the ther modynam ics needed for our purposes. 
 
Conservation of internal energy and sal inity 
 
Conservation of internal energy or entrop y eventually leads to an equation of 
the following form : 
 

+= + = )( ) (  utC sources QdtdCp z pG   
 
where Cp is the heat capacity at  constant pressure,   is the potential 
temperatur e, and the (internal) sources are due to phase changes in the fluid 
(condensation, evaporation, freezing, etc.).  Qz is the vertical divergence o f 
the heat flux written so that if is positi ve, m ore heat leaves the top of the 
ocean at th e surface t han enters the bottom of the ocean layer and the 
potential temper ature must decr ease. Near the ocean surface, Q has many 
components due to shortwave radation ( Qs), longwave or back radiation 
(Qb), turbulent sensible ( Qh) and latent ( Qe) fluxes, as described in the Ocean 
Circulation text. But in the equation above, the only fluxes considered are 
due to radiation , the turbulent fluxes co me fro m other considerations, which 
we will ex amine soo n.  
 
Similarly, we can write the conservation of salinity as 
 
 

+== )( 0 SutS
dtdS G</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Tidal Forces (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_15n/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>We will now investigate some aspects of free waves: waves which naturally 
occur on and below the ocean surface.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Tidal forces 
 
Before we look at free waves on the ear th, lets first exam ine one class of 
motion that is directly forced: astr onom ic tides. Here we will briefly 
consider some of the tidal generating forc es for 2-body systems.  
 
x
r2 r1 m1 m 2
 
Consider the two masses in the diagra m above. Each of these two m asses, 
denoted by m 1 &amp; m 2, rotate about one anothe r and under the action of 
gravity are in a stable binary orbit.  The center of rotation is on a line 
between the two masses at a position denoted by x. Th e force balance on 
these two point m asses is given as: 
 
gg
Frvm
rvmrmGmF
===
22
22
12
11221,
 
 
The first is the gravitational force of attraction ( G is a universal constant) 
and the second is the orbital balance re flecting a balance between centrifugal 
force and gravity, which m ust be in ba lance for a stable orbit. The total 
distance between the two masses having velocities v is denoted by r. If the 
rotation ra te is given by , then the above can be rewritten as 
 
22 1122
2
22
22
12
1
12
11,
rmrmF r mrvmr mrvm
g
== = =  
 
 
The second allows us to calculate the center of m ass, where the center of 
rotation lie s knowing the masses. For th e case of the earth and m oon, we 
have the following:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>speed of a surface gravity wave. Friction will cause the earth t o drag the tidal 
bulge in the direction of the rotation cau sing a torque that acts to slow down 
the rotation of the earth at a rat e of ca. 2.3 m s/century. A further interesting 
fact is that the solid earth has tides as well: equilibrium  tidal displacemen ts 
of the soli d earth can actually reduce the fluid tides by about 30%.  
 
Since the earth is not water co vered, the equilibrium tide is n ot observed. 
stead, the detail and shape of the continental boundaries play a major role 
des 
2 would 
e the corresponding solar semidiurnal) tide will be show n in class. The In
in determ ining the actual tidal respons e to forcing. So does the wavelike 
nature of the long surface wav es. In many parts of the ocean, forcing is 
within the frequency band where freel y propagating wave s can exist and 
thus the resulting patterns if tidal flow are related to natural standing m o
of long wavelength surface waves and can vary considerably with the 
frequency characteristics of th e various tidal com ponents. 
 
An exam ple of a global tidal model for the M 2 (lunar sem idiurnal: S
b
Topex-Poseidon altimeter has been su ccessfully used to im prove global 
models of tides beyond previous studies li ke the one shown. 
 
 
 
 Image removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>degrees from  the plane of its rotati on about the sun. The moon rotates 
around the  earth (in 27.32 days) in an orbit that is tilted 5 degrees from
ecliptic plane: thus the declination of  the m oon can vary between 0 to 28 
degrees over tim e. If, for exam ple, the moon is directly above the equator,
then north is up in the above figure and while the earth rotates, there will be
two high equili brium  tides per lunar day with a period of 12.42 hours: a 
lunar sem idiurnal tide. If, however, th e moon is at its m aximum declinati
and found above a latitude of 28 degrees, there will be only one high tide 
per lunar day (24.84 hrs.) at the latit ude of the sub-lunar point: a lunar 
diurnal tide.  
  the 
 
 
on 
he solar and lunar tides can reinfor ce one another during periods of a new 
  
s T
or full m oon. This is when the sun and moon are in line. In the figure 
below, I have plotted two sinusoidal fluctuations ha ving am plitudes of 1
(0.5) m eter and periods of 12.42 (12) hrs, representing the semidiurnal tide
of lunar (solar) origi n. The pattern ha s a maxim um or spri ng tide when the 
two are in phase or anti-phase and a w eak or neap tide wh en they are 90 or 
270 degre es out of phase.   
 
At a latitude of 45N/S, the speed at which  the equilibrium  tide propagates as 
the earth revolves is quite large, over 300 m s-1. This is faster t han the phase</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>m rm mkg m
eme me
8224
10*8.310*228.110*983.5
===

 
 
With these we can calculate that the di stance fro m the center of the earth to 
the center of rotation of the earth-m oon binary system is 4500 km , within the 
earth (since the earth s mean r adius is 6371 km). No w we are i nterested in 
the details of the forces relative to the cent er of mass of the eart h due to 
another mass, be it the m oon or the ea rth. So consider the picture below: 
 
   
R 
a b 
P 
 
The distance fro m the center of the eart h (on the left) to the other mass is P 
(~60R) . At the points a, b, we are interested in the gravitational forces on 
particles of unit mass due to the other m ass (of mass m). We also note that 
the two are in orbital balance, so that the centrifugal force, Fc, for every 
particle on the earth is prescribed by the orbital balance given above for 
point m asses. Thus the force balance per u nit mass for particles directly 
under the other mass but on either side of the earth is as follows: 
 
3 2 23 2 2222
2) (2) () () (
PGmR
PGm
RPGmF FPGmR
PGm
RPGmF FPGmFRPGmFRPGmF
c bc acba
+===+==</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The force balance between gravity  and centrifugal forces wil l be 
unbalanced except at the center of m ass of the earth and will lead to 
resulting force that is to the right at point a and to the left at point b. Thes e 
forces relative to the center of mass are given for these two points above:  
Fa,b  F c. These forces are equal and opposite , are proporti onal to the m ass of 
the external body, and 
depend on the inverse 
cube of the distance. 
The net effect on the 
surface of the earth i s 
shown in t he figure 
below. This is taken 
from  the book by 
Knauss an d, to my 
dism ay, has the m oon 
on the left, not the 
right as pl otted above. 
Although the sun has 
a mass that is larger 
than the moon by a 
factor of 2.5x107 , 
because the distance 
between the earth/sun 
is about 400 tim es 
that of the 
earth/m oon, the 
effective ti dal forces 
are larger for the m
are weak com pared to local gravity (1 part in 9 m illion) but the horiz
components of the force will drive pressu re gradients that will force fluid to 
move laterally. The force im balance will cause, on a wa ter covered glo
the surface to deform into an ellipso idal shape which, under a theory of 
equilibrium tides, 
shoul d cause a bulg
on either side of the 
earth of about 55 cm 
due to the lunar 
forcing. Recall that 
the earth rotates abou
an axis which is 2
oon than the sun by ab out a factor of 2. The tidal forces 
ontal 
be, 
e 
t 
3.5  
moon 
or sun</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Stress in the Ocean (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Munk solved the above neglecting the bottom friction term  (proport ional to 
r) but retaining horizontal fricti on (proportional to Ah) 
 
Because there are no w four  x-derivitives to the stream function, the western 
boundary current is even sharper and more intense than Stommels, which 
had 2 x-derivatives. As we indicated ea rlier, the interior Sverdrup Balance 
holds i n the interior of the basin,  but in the boundary near the western 
boundary, a different dynam ical balance must be present. We can determ ine 
the width of the western boundary current  in each of the two models very 
easily, without actually solving the pr oblem. In each m odel we have the 
following approxim ate balance near the western boundary, where things 
change rapidly in the x-direction: 
 
 
widthwbcs MunkAx Awidthwbcs Stommelrx r
h
m x xxxxhs x xx
' , 0' , 0
3/1

+
+

 
 
Time-dependent &amp; non-li near numerical  models of the ocean circulation 
using eithe r bottom  or lateral friction m ust be able to resolve the structure of 
the wbc. The above spatial scales fo r the two types of boundary currents 
becom e important m inimum scales re quired for numerical ocean m odels. 
 
This co mpletes the extra notes on th e wind-dri ven circulation. Further 
discussion will center around the textbook until we m ove on to other parts of 
the ocean.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Our dynam ical equations have already in corporated one of these body forces 
into them : it is the third com ponent of  each of the above shear stresses. 
Consider the vertical integral of one of  these three f orces (say the first one). 
 
) ( )0 ( ] [0
H z z dzydzxdz dzFx
Hx x x x
zx
yx
xx==++++= 
     
 
The approximation is because we are taking H to be a constant depth level 
and assu ming the surface to be flat (or its variation h to be s mall co mpar ed 
to the depth of the ocean). Consider now  the last two  terms in t he above. The 
last one is proporti onal to the stre ss on the bottom  and the preceeding one is 
due to the stress on t he top or free surface. If we write the bottom  stress as 
 
ru H zzuA H zz x   ==== ) ( ) ( ,   
 
we see that we can now associate this term with the sim ple bottom  friction 
we have retained from our pucks on ice model. It is this term that plays an 
important role in the Stommel m odel fo r the western intensification of the 
wind-dri ven gyres. As for the wind driv ing, this is the just the surface 
component of the stress x(z=0). For the Sverdrup balance, we obtained the 
following equation 
 
)0 (1 1), (1
====
z Fdz dzvorF vh
 
G GK
 
 
where we have again ignored  spatial variations of h,H , set the stress at the 
bottom  to zero and ignored the  horizontal  com ponents of the stress as well. 
As you will recall, this was the assum ption inherent in the Sverdrup balance, 
that we could ignore bottom  stress or  the frictional term proport ional to r. 
The above statement of the Sverdrup balance is m ore general that the 
previous one because we have explic itly included the surface wind stress and 
we have NOT made the assumption that the velocity v is constant with 
depth. So the Sverdrup balance can be applied to the vertical integral of 
wind-dri ven currents (including the baro clinic velocity) and subject to some 
requirements on the levelness of the ocea n depth, is a useful description of 
wind-driven, frictionless (except for the surface lay er) flow. Note that i t does</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>include the wind driving and therefor e the dynam ics of the surface Ek man 
layer.  
 
Geostrophic and Ekman components  of the Sverdrup Circulation 
 
The Sverdrup balance is a vertical integral of the sim plified p otential 
vorticity e quation. Lets step back now and look at what velocities m ake up 
this balance. We will be using the m ore general equations fo r baroclinic flow 
here, which you will recall are the following: 
 
zwyvxut dtdzw
yv
xugzpFrvypfudtdvFruxpfvdtdu
yx
+++=++=+=++=
,0,101,1
  
 
 
We could now insert the form of the body force derived above and we would 
have the full turbulent equations used  in large-scale physical oceanography. 
But here we are interested in the Sver drup balance, which is for a steady, 
linearized ocean, wit h wind forcing but otherwise no explicit friction. So the 
above become</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Stress in the Ocean  
 
The treatment of stress and strain in fluids is co mplicat ed and somewhat 
beyond the scope of this cla ss. Those really interested should look into t his 
further in Bat chelor, Introduction to Flui d Dynamics , given as a reference at 
the beginning of the class. The scali ng up of turbulent stresses to oceanic 
scales is even m ore esoteric. Here we  will m erely summarize what is known 
about the form  of the body force, F , for oceanic flows. It involves a tensor 
with three co mponents of stress for each o f the three m omentum equatio ns. 
 
[]
[]
[]z
zz
yz
xzy
zy
yy
xyx
zx
yx
xx
FFF

++=++=++=
 
 
The notation is that the superscript re fers to the stress direction of the 
component and the subscript re fers to  the derivative of the component. The 
relationship of stress to strain (fluid response) can be com plicated. For fluids 
like water and for scales typical of those we will be discussing in this class, 
it can tak e on the following form : 
 
ji
i
jxuAj
=  
 
where Aj is a constant known as the eddy viscosit y. For fluids that are 
shallow relative to their widths, these three assu med constants (Ax, Ay, Az) 
are not the same: the vertical com pone nt is m uch smaller than the two 
horizontal com ponents, which are usually (not always) assumed to be equal. 
If we insert this definition into t he above equation for the vector body force, 
we can get the following relationship (where Ax=Ay=Ah) 
 
  
[ ]
[]
[]zzz
yyh
xxh zzzz
yyh
xxh yzzz
yyh
xxh x
wA wA wA FvA vA vA FuA uA uA F
++ =++=++=</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>,0,101,1
=++=+=++=
zw
yv
xugzpypfuxpfv
y
zx
z



 
 
 
Suppose we write the velocity com ponent s as the sum of a geostrophic part 
and an Ekman part with superscripts denoting t hese. The first two equations 
beco me 
 
z ypfu fu fuz xpfv fv fv
y
e gx
e g
+==+==



1 11 1
 
 
We hav e already  looked at the geostrophi c bala nce. Now we look furthe r at 
the Ekman balance, integrating the Ekman balance between the free surface 
(z=0) and a depth at the base  of the Ekman layer (z = -Z e). 
 

====

+====

fzZ zwyv
xudzfzdzvfzudz
h eee ex
ey
e
)0 ( 1) (,)0 (,)0 (


G 
 
In the first  two equations above , we se e that the integrat ed Ekman transport 
is to the right of the applied wind stress.  In the third,  we see that there is a</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>horizontal divergence of the net Ek man transport which will produce a 
vertical velocity at the bottom  of the Ek man layer (the vertical velocity at the 
surface bei ng zero). These expressions ar e not valid at the equator where the 
Corilios parameter v anishes! The vertical  velocity is such that there is 
sinki ng with subt ropical gyres and upwelling within subpolar gyres, 
irrespective of hem isphere. 
 
Now if we know the inte grated Ekm an transport and we also know the 
vertically integrated Sverdrup trans port, then the vertically integrated 
geostrophi c transport  must just be th e difference between the Sverdrup and 
Ekman transports, since by definition, vs=vg+ve.  Some investigators have 
used this constraint t o help determ ine the unknown referenc e level velocity 
for geostrophic m otion, but this is onl y as good as the assum ptions behind it. 
In fact, you will be exam ining this in one of your next hom ework proble ms. 
The fact th at there ar e large  difference between th e actual and Sverdrup 
volum e transports in the Gulf Stream  (150 vs. 30 Sv., respectively) shoul d 
make one approach this method with  caution! We will be seeing this 
difference later. 
 
Munk s gyre vs. Stommels gyre 
 
Munk (1950) produc ed another m odel of the N. Atlantic wind-driven 
circulation and explained its westward  intensification using a different 
friction model than Stommel. Instead of vertical friction as co ntained in the 
frictional parameter, r opposi ng the m otion, Munk used a horizontal eddy 
viscosity. We will not go into this m odel, as it also required a positive  to 
have the Gulf Stream stronger on th e western boundary. We will just write 
down the linear vorticity balance with both  frictiona l term s. 
 
1() ( )  [ (0) (hy
xxxxy yyy xxy y x x y Ar z    + +++===0)]xz  
 
Here we h ave replaced the body force wi th the wind stress at t he surface and 
the streamfunction is now the vertical integral of the previous 
stream function:  
 
= =y x dzu dzv  &amp;</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Observations of the Gulf Stream in the N. Atlantic (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Observations of the Gulf  Stream in the N. Atlantic  
Florida Strait Transport 
 
Probably the best &amp; most continuous r ecord of ocean transport is in the 
Florida Strait where cable measuremen ts between the coast of Florida 
(Miami) and the Bahamas (Bimini) have been calibrated (Baringer &amp; 
Larsen, 2001, GRL, 3179-318 2). The time series started in 1982 and in the 
above reference is reported through 1998 . Daily estimates of Florida Current 
transport have been examined over the course of many years (fig. 2, below) 
and clear interannual variati ons have been detected that are related to the 
strength of the wind-driving in the N. At lantic (the NAO Index is used in the 
figure, see Ocean Circulation te xt, p. 139 for NAO schematic).  
 
Image removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Streamwise averaging makes for a shar per flow (compare the middle panels 
of the above two figures) and for an in teresting result from the flow at right 
angles to the section (lower right panel), which now shows inflow into the 
Gulf Stream from both sides, amounting to a downstream increase of transport of about 15 Sv. per 100 km of distance downstream. The total 
transport of the flow in the upper 2000m is approximately 88 Sv and 94 Sv 
for the whole water column. We can see that this transport far exceeds the expected Sverdrup return flow and transport in the Florida Straits. Inflow from either side of the Gulf Stream is  a consequence of two counter-rotating 
gyres on either side of the current. Th ese are called re-circulation gyres as 
flow is confined to regions on both th e north and south sides of the Gulf 
Stream. 
 
Before we get to these, another long  timeseries of Gulf Stream flow was 
made at 68W, further downstream fro m Hatteras section above (at 73W), 
this time using moored instrumentati on, not probes droppe d from research 
vessels. Data were examined in a si milar manner (defining a streamwise 
coordinate system) and the results published by Johns et al. (1995, JGR, C1, 
817-838). Over two years of records were obtained betw een June 1988 and 
August 1990. An amazing figure (see their fig. 9) shows that the structure seen at Hatteras is reproduced furt her downstream with the width of the 
current similar at both locations ( 160 km). However, the maximum surface 
flow has increased and the depth extent of the current increases and is seen 
all the way to the ocean bottom (&gt;4000m).  The total transport at this 68W 
section was 113 Sv, approximately 20 Sv. larger than at 73W.  
 
Further downstream (between 60-65 W) the Gulf Stream reaches its 
maximum transport of about 150 Sv. and then starts to decrease transport. 
The flows feeding this transport cha nge are not wind-driven but a non-linear 
phenomenon, due to the fact that the Rossby Number becomes significant in 
the Gulf Stream and both steady and tim e-dependent flows can contribute to 
the circulation; these lie outside the simple dynamics we have considered 
thus far. The presence of strong eddi es in the region is one mechanism for 
making the mean flow larger. In fact much of the transport structure shown 
by schematically by Hogg (1992, Deep -Sea Research, 39, 1231-1246) might 
be considered to be eddy-driven .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>have been made with cable voltages,  since the Lo rentz force of a ch arged 
particle moving thru the earths m agnetic field will be a right angles to the 
magnetic field. An upward com ponent of the m agnetic field will deflect 
positi ve ions to the right of the flow and negative ions to the left, m aking for 
a potential difference across the flo w, which can be measured using 
subm arine telephone cables (not used a nymore!). Some corrections need to 
be made for the electrical resistivity  of the ocean bo ttom, but once made, 
cable measurements provide the most c ontinuous measure of water transport 
in the ocean. 
 
Cape Hatteras transport of the Gulf Stream  
 
Halkin and Rossby (1985, JPO , 1439-14 52) made 16 repeated sections 
between Sept. 1980 and May 1983 across the Gulf Stream  just as it left the 
coast at Cape Hatter as. They used an instrument (P egasus) which was 
essentially an acoustically-tracked pr obe which measured temperature and 
pressure and whose tracking yi elded hor izontal velocity. At s ome pre-set 
depth, the instrument releases a we ight an d returns to the ocean surface 
where it is recovered and re-deployed by a ship at another site . The work 
shows several things: the im portance of  streamwise averaging, the total 
volum e transport of t he upper 2000m , and the inflow into the Gulf Stream 
which increases its transport down stream . The figure below shows the 
stream wise av eraging scheme schematic ally (we will discuss it in class). 
   Image removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>A streamwise coordinate system was used to simulate the Gulf Stream 
structure irrespective of the angle of the current to the section and 
irrespective of the location of the velo city maximum at different locations 
along the section. The meas ured mean velocities and temperatures are shown 
in the next figure followed by a plot of  the mean properties in a streamwise 
coordinate system. 
 
 Images removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>This transport is one main benchmark  against which all numerical models 
of the ocean can be judged: do they get the transport correct or not? Do they 
get the same temporal variability? Do they get the correct seasonal cycle? 
The transport is seen to vary seasonally (see fig. 3, above reference, below)  
There is a suggestion of a different annual cycle in the first half of the record 
compared to the second half . The range of the annual cy cle (2-3 Sv.) is about 
the same as the range of interannual ch anges. The mean va lue (32.2 Sv.) is 
somewhat larger than we would expect  from the Sverdrup transport at this 
latitude (26N, homework prob lem). The discrepancy can in part be related to 
the fact that some water flowing th ru Florida Strait is from the South 
Atlantic and is required by the thermohaline circulation, which we will 
discuss in a later part of the course. The failure of the mid-latitude Sverdrup 
balance is more apparent as Cape Ha tteras is approached, as shown in 
another classic study. The transport measurements in the Florida Strait Image removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>In the above figure (taken from Hogg), these two re-circulation gyres are 
shown on either side of the Gulf St ream. To the north, the Northern Re-
Circulation Gyre (NRG) is confined by the topography to lie between the 
Slope Water northeast of Cape Hatteras to the tail of the Grand Banks. To 
the south of the Stream, a Southern  Re-Circulation Gyre (SRG) often 
ascribed to Val Worthington (Worthington Gyre or WG) is less confined but situated in the northern Sargasso S ea. The NRG circulat es in a counter-
clockwise direction and the SRG rota tes clockwise. These gyres have a 
strong barotropic as well as baroclinic signature: they extend from the surface to the ocean bottom. Although best  defined in the N. Atlantic, they 
are present, with some variation, near strong western boundary currents in 
all the ocean basins and their exis tence has been linked to strong eddy 
motions which act to generate them. In this instance, eddies can act not only 
to dampen mean currents , but also force them!  
 One important type of eddy found in the region of the Gulf Stream is a Gulf 
Stream ring, called that because a ring of Gulf Stream flow forms a meander 
which pinches off into large eddies on either side of the flow. Typically, 4-6 
of these are formed each year in the region of the Gulf Stream and they can 
persist for months to in excess of a year. Those found to the north of the 
Stream (warm core rings) have shorter lif etimes than the cold core rings to 
the south. Image removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rotation 101: Some Basics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>drdhthatg recognizinrg drdhor r g = =+    tan , ,0 tan2
2
 
 dh  
 
 dr
 
So the answer to part  (1) of the problem  is that the shape is a parabola, the 
soluti on being 
 
22
02rghh+=  
 
where h0 is a constant. The answer to pa rt (2) requires the use of some 
trigonom etric identit ies as well as  using the above answer for tan . It can  be 
easily  shown (this is often written and it is usually not that easy) that  
 
22 22 1/2 2 2[1( /)]/[1( /)] [1( /)] gg rg rg g rg =+  + = +1/2
 
 
Centrifugal force can be subsumed into  a revised definiti on of gravit y 
which is acting on a curved, parabolic surface. For a rotating surface in 2 -d 
this varies with radius, increasing out ward. So if you want to weigh less , 
move to the center of the surface! 
 
Many rotating surfaces on which things are placed and on which laboratory 
experiments are done already have this  parabolic shape. If one saw such a 
surface in the lab an d wanted t o know wh at was  the correct rotation rate in 
which a particle would be at rest, one could (hard way) figure out the 
quadratic ter m of the surface or (easy way), drop a marble on the non-
rotating surface and figure out its peri od of oscillation. This will now be 
shown. Newtons second law for forces ac ting in the radial direction parallel 
to the surface is</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Rotation 101 (some basics) 
 
Most students starting off in oc eanography,  even if they have had som e fluid 
mechanics , are not famili ar wit h viewi ng fluids in a rotating re ference frame. 
This is essential in order to underst and large scale, low frequency dynam ics 
of the ocean. So we m ust return to som e basic about rotating dynam ics. 
 
Consider a dish that is curved as 
shown and which is rotating at a 
rate  about a vertical axis. Only 
gravity, also vertical, is acting. A 
particle of mass m is resting on the 
surface. (1 ) What shape does the 
surface have to be in order that 
there are no net forces on the 
particle: can it be at rest in the 
rotating frame? (2) What is the 
apparent gravity acting norm al to 
the surface? 
 -gcos 
-gsin 2rcos 
-2rsin  
-g2r 
 
In a rotating frame, there is a 
centrifugal force acting outward 
from  the axis of rotation and 
gravity acting downward. We 
deco mpose these two forces into 
ones acting paralle l (a) and normal 
(b) to the surface 
 
0 cos sin2= +    r m mg
   
 
 
2 cos sin mg mr mg    =  
 
where  is the apparen t gravity. For the case in which  &lt;  /2 the first 
relation (balance par allel to surface) b ecomes g</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>simply rep resented by a linear drag for ce acting on the whole particle. So we 
will m odify the above equation to the following: 
 

=+ =+
2] 2 [
iiF vmr vdtvdm 
 
where r is a co efficient of fricti on proportional to stickiness of the 
contact between the par ticle and the surface.  
 
Now we will add another force. S uppose that there are bu mps in the 
surface: it is not flat. [Recall that we have already accounted for a slow 
curvature due to the centrifugal for ce.] If the topogra phy of the surface is 
represented by h, then this force is just -gh . Wher e the sy mbol   is the 
gradient operator which is a vector s horthand the slope of the surface in t he 
x- and y- directions: ( x,y)h. This was already introd uced earlier when we 
figured out what the equ ilibrium shape o f a rotati ng surface must tak e. So 
our equati on of m otion then becom es: 
 

=+  =+
3] 2 [
iiF h mgvmr vdtvdm 
 
Any rem aining forces on the hockey puck (i  3) are left for the present an d 
simply written as F. If we write the above vect or equation in its com ponent 
form , it becom es: 
 
mFrvyhg fudtdvmFruxhg fvdtdu
yx
+=++= ,
 
 
where f  2, and we have divided through by the mass, m.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>We will illustrate some of the dynami cs of the above balances with a 
homework problem: pucks_on_ice . We use ice to illustrate, in part, what 
permanent bumps on the surface will do pa rticles. In fact, in a fluid, there 
are no permanent bumps on a free su rface unless they are maintained by 
forces. We will later see that these can be maintained by something called 
the geostrophic force balance, in which steady flows are required to 
balance permanent bumps or dimples on the free fluid surface.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>r gr gdrdhgdtrd2 2
22
)/ ( = = =  
 
 
This reflects the force balan ce that makes a particle roll down t he slope and 
accelerate under the action of gravity. Bu t we know what the expression for 
the slope ( dh/dr ) must be from  before and inser ting t hat above we see that  
r = a sin(t) + b cos(t) is a solution, where a a nd b are arbitrary constants 
that can be used to satisfy the initial conditions. So the frequency of 
oscillation,  is the same as the period of rotation used to construct the 
surface! 
 
   
g  
Now consider a rotating, self-gravitating sphere 
shown at the right. Gravity acts toward the center 
of the sphere but since it is rotating, there is a 
centrifugal force acting outward from  the rotation 
axis on the fluid. What shap e does it take if there is 
no m otion in the rotating fram e? What does 
rotation do to apparent gravity?  We will discuss 
this is class, but not actually solve this problem 
 
 
Coriolis Acceleration/Force 
 
We hav e examined what shap e a rota ting surface must tak e in order for a 
particle to reside on it without m otion: it is paraboli c. Now consider what 
happens when, in this rotating fram e of reference, there is m otion. The 
exam ple we will use is taken from a program (coriolis.m ) written by Jim  
Price to illustrate what happens when a particle, say a hockey p uck, is given 
an initial velocity and afterwards m oves without any external forces (other 
than gravit y &amp; centrifugal forces, that is). So the surface m ust be relatively 
slick (ice) so that friction is weak and can be ignored. We will look at the 
motion of the particle in two referenc e frames: one an inertial fram e (non-
rotating) and the other the reference frame rotating with angular velocity 
 about an axis parallel with gravity. In  the inertial frame, the particle will 
move in the direction given by the initia l velocity. But as we h ave alread y</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>shown, it will be stopped by the parabo lic surface and w ill oscillate with 
frequency . In the rotating fra me, it will be seen to m ove in a circle, 
coming back to its initial position after ha lf a rotation cycle: its frequency of 
oscillation is 2 . This circular m otion is caused by the reference frame 
rotation under the particle. In this ro tating fram e, we can account for this 
motion by adding an acceleration to the particle equal to 2  x v, wher e the 
accel eration is at right angles to the both the relative velocity vector v, and 
the rotation vector . ere we use bold face as i ndicating a vector, which is 
also denoted by an arrow over the letter,  as below. This accel eration, if 
multiplied by the m ass of the particle, is equivalent to a force d irected to the 
right of the particle if  is as shown (counter-clockwi se), and to the left of 
the particle m otion if  is in the opposite direction. This fictitious force is 
one of the m ost important ones in ocea nography! It arises solely because we 
(and the oceans) are confined to a rotating earth.  
 
Try running the m -file coriolis.m  written by Jim  Price. It illustrates the 
views of a particle on a parabolic surface s een in an i nertial (non-
accel erating) reference frame and in the reference frame of the rotating 
system . In the form er, a particle w ill undergo an oscillation about the center 
of the paraboloi d, with a frequency , as we showed above. When it is 
halfway through its oscillation, the ro tating reference frame  is now halfway 
rotated about the axis of rotation, so th e particle is at the same positi on in the 
rotating frame as it had initially! In th is reference frame, the frequency of 
oscillation is 2 , or twice that in the iner tial frame. Notice also how the 
particle ap pears to move in a circle  in a clockwise fashion due to the 
fictitious coriolis force. In the rotati ng frame, if (x,y) is the position of the 
particle and (u,v) its velocity, Newtons second law can be written: 
 

==+
1] 2 [
iiF vdtvdm 
 
where the external forces  are represented on the right hand side. We will 
now consider one special type of exter nal force: friction. Friction acts to 
impede th e motion of the hockey puck. We have all observed that friction 
will eventually act to bring m oving thin gs to rest. The sim plest form  that 
friction can take refl ects the f act that it acts in proportion to the mass of the 
particle and is opposi te to the velocity  of the particle. It acts only on the 
point(s) of contact b etween the partic le an d the surface, but can  be most</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rotation 101 (cont.): Effects of Rotation on a Sphere: f- and &#946;-planes (PDF)
Earth&#8217;s Gravity Field and Sea Level (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_3a/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>0 ,0, ,0)]( )( )([3 2
 =++= = + +  +
Laszw
yv
xuorL V where w v u LtV
 
 
since by definition, we have a fixe d volume of fluid in the cube and L is 
constant on all sides of the cube. So fo r future reference,  the grand set of 
equations which can account for vertical variations in the flow (and for the 
case in wh ich there i s no vertical  flow variation) now becom e 
 
zwyvxut dtdzw
yv
xugzpFrvypfudtdvFruxpfvdtdu
yx
+++=++=+ = ++ = 
,0,101,1
  
 
 
We have now four equations for the five dependent variables ( u,v,w,p, ) 
subject to external forces which  have not yet been further defi ned at this 
stage. The frictional force, r,  is subtle in that it is expected to be large near 
solid boundaries of the fluid and near  the ocean surface where turbulence 
levels are large and can act to oppose or  create m otion. The usual m ethod for 
understanding of fri ction would take us too far into fluid dynam ics. For the 
present, understand that friction is im portant where lateral stresses applied at 
boundaries of the fluid can force the m otion of the fluid, such as the top 
[where we have wind stre ss forcing the ocean] , and on the bott om and sides 
of the ocean, where lateral stresses act to im pede the m otion of the fluid. The 
5th equation (m issing above) prescribes how  density is affected by advection 
&amp; external forces. We will be dealing wi th this later. For now, consider it 
prescribed!</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Rotation 101 (cont. ): Effects of rotati on on a sphere: f- and -planes 
  
We will follow the convention of many before us and try to sim plify the 
effects of the curvature of the earth on the dynam ics of particles in this 
rotating system . An approxim ation is  made in which  the position of a 
particle in a spheri cal geometry  (,,r) is expressed in term s of cartesian  
variables (x,y,z) for small excu rsion from  a reference point. 
 
Consider the following figure. 
  
(0,0,r0)=(x0,y0,z0)
0 0 r0 On the surface of the 
sphere, we choose a 
reference point at a 
longitude, latitude, and 
radius denoted by the 
coordinate ( 0,0,r0), with 
the Cartesian coordinates 
of (x 0,y0,z0). For small  
distances from  this point, 
we can wr ite the 
following: 
 
 
0 00 0 00 0 0 0
') ( ') ( cos '
rr zzzr yyyr xxx
= = = = = =

 
 
Gravity is in the radial or z direction and the rotation vector , velocity v, 
and Coriolis accel eration 2   x v have the following com ponents: 
 JG
(0,cos,sin),
'' '(,,)( , ,)
2 (2 cos 2sin,2sin,2cos)dxdy dzvu vwdt dtdt
vw v u u
 =  
==
 =    G
JGG</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>First of all , we m ust recognize that horizontal  gradie nts of pressure will act 
to cause horizontal  acceleration of the fluid, s ubject to the presence of the 
Coriolis force. Recall that we have  employed a hydrostatic balance in the 
vertical in which vertical gradients of  pressure are bala nced by gravity. So 
the additional equation is the hydrosta tic balance, which states that 
 
0= =zpgdtdw 
 
In the event that the hydrostatic bala nce is upset, there will be vertical 
accel erations of the fluid.  
 
The next m odification to the equations of  motion is that we need to replace 
horizontal variations of the ocean su rface, with horizontal variations of 
pressure, as these can now vary in the vertical away f rom the ocean surface. 
So we hav e 
 
yp
yhgxp
xhg

 1,1
 
 
Next, we must reco gnize th at the advecti ve derivativ e must include vertical 
velocity and a  z  derivative. Thus 
 
zwyvxut dtd
+++ 
 
Finally, the last equation of t he earlier group, also known as the continuity 
equation, expresses the fact that flow s into a control box m ust be balanced 
by flows out of the volum e or change s in the free sur face. Away from the 
free surface, this m ust now be m odified  by considering a sm all cube of side 
L within the fluid. The volume flux acr oss the six faces of the cube now 
beco mes</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Because vertical velocities are m uch smaller than horizontal velocities for 
large-scale, low frequency moti on, a nd because th e basic balance in the 
vertical is hydrostati c, the last e quation above can be  approximated as 
 
 
sin2),0,, ()0, sin 2, sin 2( 2
=  =
fwhere fufv u v v
 
 
the Coriolis parameter, f , is the vertical com pone nt of the rotation vector. 
This approximation will shaky in high latitude regions where v ertical 
convection in winter can create large vertical velo cities and at the equator 
where l arge zonal currents can aff ect the h ydrostatic balance.  
 
One problem  with the Coriolis parame ter above in trying to understand the 
simplified physics of the ocean is that it is not a constant [ sin  varies wit h 
latitude]. In the problem s we will consider  in this course, the ocean basin can 
be considered sm all enough so that loca lly, some further sim plifications can 
be made. We will consider two exam ples called th e f-plane  and  
plane  approxim ations.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>So we now have the following equati ons of motion for a fluid ocean of 
uniform  density: 
 
yvxut dtdwhere hHvyhHux thFrvyhg fudtdvFruxhg fvdtdu
yx
++= ++ +++= ++=
,0)] ([ )] ([,

 
 
For fluids, we can eit her track p article motion [Lagrangian form ulation] or 
look at force balances at a position,  while different particles flow by 
[Eulerian form ulation]. Thus far, we have done the form er, but not using any 
fluid dynam ics. When one does, the time derivatives take on different 
meaning in the two form ulations. This is given in the last of the above 
equations, where a time d erivative follo wing a particle beco mes an advective 
derivative at a point (x,y) in the Euleri an formulation. This reflects the f act 
that at a point, there can be changes in  time b ecause of extern al forces and 
because different particles with  a diffe rent history are streaming by the point 
of observa tion. As far as any mathematic s needed fo r the rest of this course, 
the difference is immaterial  since we will be looki ng at sim ple linearized 
versions of the above equations. Yet we  will be using them to understand the 
dynam ics of m id-latitude gyres, the de ep tropics and equator, and time 
dependent m otions such as tides, Ross by, and topographic waves, in which 
we consider the whole water colum n respondi ng as one with no density 
variations in the vertical. Motions of this nature have been called 
barotropic  and are an im portant part of the ocean circulation. 
 
However, we know t hat density does va ry in the vertical and that ocean 
currents are not uniform with depth. The pa rt of the velocity field that varies 
in the vertical is known and the  baroclinic  velocity, and our equations 
need to be slightly modified to ac count for this component. We will now 
briefly discuss what needs to be m odifi ed in our set of grand equations for 
the baroclinic flows.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Fluid equations for barotropic and baroclinic flows 
 
Thus far we have dealt with soli d objects moving around on a solid surface 
with little or no fluidity. But in fact we have almost derived all of the 
equations needed for the study of a laye r of fluid of uniform density on the 
surface of the spherical earth! There is  one last item need ed to make the 
transition from pucks on ice to the genera l circulation of the ocean: it is that 
bumps on the surface of a fluid will not stay there: motion will be away from 
the bump and its surface expression w ill vanish unless sustained by some 
force.  
 
For those of you with no experience in fl uid dynamics, this may appear to be 
a formidable hurdle to overcome. We have  tried to make this as painless as 
possible: starting with pucks on a frozen ocean, yet ending up with the 
equations physical oceanographers use to understand their observations. For 
those with fluids in their past, this may seem less rigorous than the 
traditional method of derivation of the Navier-Stokes equati ons for a rotating 
fluid. In this course, we will not be trying to solve the complete sets of fluid 
motion in either the barotropic or baroc linic limits. In fact, this is impossible 
as non-linearity and time dependen ce due to turbulence precludes any 
general solution. So dont worry about  solving them! We will simplify them 
for particular problems, however, a nd want them exposed now for later 
reference. 
 
Consider the following diagram. 
 
A layer of fluid of density  lies over a sloping bottom (z=-H) and a free 
surface. Because of a bump of fluid on  the surface, there will be pressure 
gradients created that try to force th e underlying fluid away from the surface 
bump. In the lower panel, we consider a column of fluid of sides L x,Ly and 
height H+h (the total depth of the fluid). 
 
Fluid can escape the box by flowing thru the imaginary sides, but not 
through the bottom, which is solid. Be cause fluid can leav e the box, the free 
surface level can change. Here we do a mass (or volume balance) for the 
box, whose volume, V is  L x Ly(H+h).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>z = 0 z = h 
z = -H Fx = -ghx 
h
Lx Ly 
 
 
 
 
=  net loss of flui d in x-dir.  
)] ([ ) ( ) ()] ([ ) ( ) (
hHv L hHvL hHvLhHu L hH uL hH uL
x back x front xy lhs y rhs y
+ = +  ++ = +  +
= net loss of flui d in y-dir., 
 
where lhs refers to the left hand side of the box. This net loss of flui d must 
be balanced by a change in vol ume. So we can write a volum e balance as 
follows (first sim plifying by letting L x=Ly=L): 
 
0)] ([ )] ([0 ,0)) (( )) ((,0 ))] (( )) (([
2
= ++ ++ =+ ++ +== + + + +
hHvyhHux thLasorLhHv
LhHu
ththusthLtVhHv hHu LtV</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>We now insert into t he above the fact that  =  0 + , where  &lt;&lt;1, &amp; use 
the trigonometric identity for sin(a+b)=sin( a)cos( b)+cos( a)sin( b). Now as 
seen in the above figure, for small a ngular changes (expressed in radians) 
from  the reference latitude, cos() ~  1 &amp; sin( ) ~  .  
 
Thus for t he vertical com pone nt of the rotation vector, f , we get the 
following: 
 
0
00 0
0
002cos2sin( ')2sin (
')
,frr
fy where
nd0 
= +  + 
=+
 
00
00 02sin
(2co /s),a f
r
 

 
An  f-plane  approximation assum es that th e vertical com ponent of the 
rotation ve ctor is constant. The -plane  approximation assumes that f  is 
constant unless its y-deriv itave is taken, in which df/dy  is replaced by 
another constant equal to .  
 
The ho mework problem  pucks_on_ice is done on an f-plane; our work on 
the wind-driven circulation will require use of the -plane. Th e following 
material will be need ed when we begi n the section on the ocean circulation, 
chapter 3 i n the text.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Equatorial Twists to Mid-Latitude Dynamics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>used to forecast the occu rrence of El Nio and its opposite extreme, La Nia. 
Access to these data can  be found on the web at: 
http://www.p mel.noaa.gov/tao/  . An array of m oorings is in pl ace in the 
Pacific as shown below: 
 
 
All of the blue dots represent surf ace m oorings with at mospheric boundary 
layer and s ubsurface temperatur e and ve locity measurement. On select ed 
locations on the equator, m oored ADCP  (acoustic Doppler current profi lers) 
collect current profiles in the u pper o cean. All of the data are t elemet ered 
back and can be accessed in realtim e. For exam ple, one can see the wind 
anomalies from the mean seasonal cycl e and SST (sea surface temp erature) 
from  8 October 2002 (below). Winds are blowing towards a SST maximum  
in the west ern tropical Pacific and cold SS Ts can be seen in the east. This is 
close to the normal condition since the ano malies are weak.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>EUC), call ed (z=z 0) can be written down without knowledge of the friction 
parameter. 
  
   orhzhg zz zuzrxx,) ( ) ( )()( 00 1 0 0 0   = = =  
 
It is merel y the depth where th e surface s tress exact ly balances the 
horizontal pressure gradient . This can be solved for z0  and estimated readily 
from  data. As you will recall fr om an ear lier discussion, the variation of 
surface el evation h is m uch smaller than th at of the upper layer depth H by a 
factor of / . So we could also sim plify th e above even m ore by replacing 
1hx by Hx and using a figure such as fig. 5.4 (p. 148 of 2nd ed. textbook). 
Lets try putting in some nu mbers and seeing what we g et. From  the above, 
we can solve for z 0.  
 
00 0
2
6
0() /, |/|1
0.04 /,
0.5 /9000 0.56 10,
74,x
x
x
xzz zghforhz
ntm
h m km thus
zm

 = &lt;&lt;

=  

,
 
 
which is indeed m uch larger in magn itude than the s ea surface elevation. 
This depth separates the westward flowing South E quatorial Current on the 
equator from  the eastward flowing Equa torial Undercurrent. It is not a bad 
estimate looking at the upper panel of fig. 5.5 in the text. 
 
Observations of the Equatorial Ocean 
 
 Because of the legacy of the Tropi cal Ocean, Global Atm osphere (TOGA ) 
Program , we have learned a great deal  about equatorial dynamics and the 
reasons for changes i n the equatorial ci rculation. One such  change, in wh ich 
the trades weaken signifi cantly across the Pacific Ocean, the t hermo cline 
slope is greatly reduced fro m west to eas t, and the upwelling of cold water in 
the east ern Pacific Ocean is ter minated, is something called El Nio. This is 
discussed i n the text. Because of th e dem onstrated human dimension of 
these changes, mainly due to changes in tropical precipitation, a real time 
monitoring system  has been maintained  in the tropical Pacific with data 
employed in som e predictive models of  equatorial dynam ics than can be</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The EUC occurs at a depth where hor izontal pressure gradients (higher 
pressure on western sides of the basi ns due to west ward wind stress at t he 
surface piling up water) drive an eastward fl ow at depth. It also can apply to 
the meridional (north/south) flows: at the surface, where wind stress is 
blowing to the north across the equato r, there is a surface flow i n the 
direction of the wind (Sout h Equatorial Current, SEC), but at depth, pressure 
gradients may drive an opposi ng flow to the south. Indeed, there is evidence 
for m ean meridional slopes of t he sea surface across the equator, with 
generally higher sea surface hei ght to the north as a consequence of positive 
meridional wind stress at the equator. R ecall that the ITCZ is, in the m ean, 
located to the north of the equator.  
 
The second equation above has been us ed to calculate a geostrophic zonal 
velocity AT the equator. (Jerlov, 1953,  Tellus) was the first explore this 
balance. It can be m ost sim ply stat ed by neglecting the effects of friction 
(proportional to r ) as follows.  
 
Let u = ug + uf. In the second m omentum e quation above, we now have  
 
y
z yf gp u uy   += + + ) (  
 
If we take the y derivative of both si des of the above and evaluate it at the 
equator (y=0), this equation be comes 
 
y
yzfyyg
up u
 
+= += +
 
 
This balance assu mes that 
 
y
z yp+=0  
 
and that uy is finite. The first of these th ree equations is often used to 
calculate  geostrophic flow at th e equator, but the additi onal two 
constraints are usually ignored. This is discussed furt her by Joyce (right, 
thats me!, 1988, JPO). A recent (a s yet unpublished) study of Sverdrup 
dynam ics in the equatorial Pacific by Kessler can be found on t he web at 
http://www.p mel.noaa.gov/~kessler/kjm01-abstract.htm l</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Equatorial Dynam ics 101 
 
To examine the zonal m omentum balan ces at the equator, we will use the 
simplified dynam ics contained in  
 
x
z xp+=0  
 
Consider the figure at the right, 
which we already have used in 
previous notes. If we think of 
ourselves l ooking at the 
equatorial Pacific Ocean (for 
exam ple) from  a point in the 
northern hem isphere, the sea 
surface slopes upwards to the 
west under the trades and the 
pycnocline underneath slopes 
oppositely so as to make for no 
or reduced pressure gradients at depth.  In the upper layer, which can be in 
motion, we have px=1ghx. This is constant throughout the upper layer since 
the density is assum ed constant. If we  integrate the above equation from  the 
free surface to a depth z with in the upper layer, we obtain Z=0 Z=h 
Z= -H
Z= -H 0 1 
2 
 
1
10( ) ( ) (),
() ()(), () ,
()() ( ) ( )xx
x
x
x
xghzh zh zbut
zrzuzwhererzisthefriction parame terthus
rzuz zh ghzh 

=  + =
=
==   
 
If we knew som ething about r(z), we could sol ve for the zonal current 
variation with depth using the last of  the equations above. Near the surface 
(z=h), the second term on the right of the last equation is small and the flow 
is in the direction of the surface stress (to the west since x(h) is negative on 
the equator). This is the westward SEC.  In this simple m odel, the vertical 
integral of the zonal flow m ust vani sh since ther e is no source for inflow 
from  the sides or thru the bottom of th e upper layer. Near  the bottom  of the 
upper layer, r(z) becomes small, z approaches  H, the second term  on the 
right is larger than the first and the flow beco mes positive (and possibly 
large). Thi s is the EUC. The d epth of  no zonal flow (between t he SEC an d</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Equatorial tw ists to mid-latitude dynamics 
 
As we saw for Stom mels or Munks wind-driven gyres and for Sverdrups 
balance, there was no par ticular problem  with the equator. In fact, Stommel 
solved his gyre for no rotation of the earth  at all. But we do n eed to retu rn to 
the barotropic potential vorticity bala nce and discuss one aspect (involving 
linearization) that is different i n equatori al dynam ics. 
 
The wind-driven m odels of Stomme l and Munk em ployed a linearization 
invol ving a small param eter, the Ro ssby num ber, which we need to re-
consider. Recall 
 
1]/[ ,1]/[],[])/(1)/(1][[] [][][]/[][
00 0 00
&lt;&lt; &lt;&lt; ++++
Hh and fLu RifHf
HhfLu
Hf
hHfH Hh hLuf f

   
 
Clearly near the equator, f  beco mes arbitrarily small and this definition of 
the Rossby num ber leads one to suspect  that the flow cannot be linear. 
However, we can fix this by r ecognizing that for steady flows: 
 
,
2
2
00 0
2
0;[ ]
[/ ]
[] ( )[][1(/
1( / )[ ][] [ ][] ,1( /)
[/ ]1, [/]1y
xy
xy
Efy f
uL
d)] f vu v u uLdt
df u uL uifdtHh H hH H
R uL and hH 

    
  
=

+= + +  +
++++
&lt; &lt; &lt;&lt;  
 
For equatorial dynami cs a new parameter RE must be small for the flow to be 
linear in the same sen se as for mid-latitu des. This is somewhat less stringent 
than for mid-latitudes. Try putting so me values into the two different</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Data ar e somewhat  more difficult to a ccess, and often have  gaps due to 
mooring failure or damage from vandalis m. The array is still considered a 
pilot array, and there are ongoing disc ussions to make additions/changes. 
But co mpared to the rest of the ocean, the Pacific a nd Atlantic tropics are in 
MUCH b etter condition for data availability from  in situ  instrumentation.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Rossby num bers and see which one is larger. Recall the definition of . At 
the equator it has a value of approxim ately 2x10-11 (ms)-1. 
 
The equations of m otion near the equato r can be written using the equatorial 
-plane as follows:  
 
zwyvxut dtdzw
yv
xugzprvypyudtdvruxpyvdtdu
y
zx
z
+++=++=+= ++= 
,0,101,1



 
 
Steady, linear flow n ear the equator dem ands that term s with ( d/dt) are set to 
zero. The first two equations the n reduce to the following: 
 



y
zx
z
rvypyuruxpyv
+= ++= 
11
 
 
At the equator, the left hand sides of  both of the above m ust vanish. This 
results in a balance in  which ver y near the surface, wh ere the pr essure 
gradient is sm all, the currents are down- wind. Where the press ure gradient is 
larger than the wind forcing, the curre nts are then down-pressure gradient. 
While Stommel (1960, DSR) seem s to ha ve been the only one to explore this 
for the case in which  the wind stress is zonal and uniform  with  latitude, this 
balance lies at the heart of the descrip tion of surface and subsurface flows at 
the equator, and the sim plified explana tion for the equatorial undercurrent 
(EUC) in Ocean Circulation . We will look further along these lines shortly.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Other data can be seen showing the changes in SST and in surface dynamic 
height on t he equator, the la tter co ming from th e mo orings. 
 
 
In addition to the seasonal cycle of SST  on the left, one can see interannual 
changes in the dynam ic topography at the sea surface (relative to 500 db) 
showing a large reduction in the sea surface h eight across the Pacific 
between, say, Marc h 2001 and Sept. 2002.  
 
A similar but less extensiv e array is in place in the tropical Atl antic, called 
PIRATA ( http://www.p mel.noaa.gov/pi rata/images /pirata.gif  ). The mooring 
array is shown next.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Wind-Driven Circulation: Stommel&#8217;s Gyre&#160;and Sverdrup&#8217;s Balance (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>In the first figure (above) , we show some global maps of wind curl from 
these two climatologies (based on ship observations over many years).  
Regions of negative (positive) curl ar e subtropical gyres in the northern 
(southern) hemisphere. We are not intere sted in the differences in these two 
climatologies at this point: you can read all about this in the paper on the web at http://www.soc.soton.ac.uk/JRD/ MET/PDF/SOCHR.pdf  . What we 
are interested in here are the patterns a nd in the zonal integration of the curl 
field to produce a volume transport streamfunction following the Sverdrup Balance, which is shown below (a lso from the same reference). Image removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>The interior region i s one that Sverdr up studied in 1947 and the balance of 
these two term s has become known by his nam e: The Sverdrup Balance. If 
we re-write this balance slightly, its value will become m ore apparent. 
 
 
) (H), (1
0F dx v dxdzorF
h
xh x
KK
 = =
 
 
 
If we integ rate the first equation across a basin from  east to west at any fixed 
latitude (y=constant) and th en m ultiply by the depth of the fluid, we ob tain 
an estimate (second equation) for the interior wind-driven transport across 
the basin in the m eridional dire ction. Th e direction of this transport depends 
on the sign of the curl of the forcing, F. In the case of the Stommel forcing, 
the curl of the forcing is negative and t hus the interior flow is to the south. 
So we can then estimate, using knowle dge about the forcing, what the wind-
driven circulation m ust look li ke. Whatev er interior flow is demanded by the 
Sverdrup balance must then be returned  in the wbc as a boundary layer flow.  
With knowledge about the wind stress and its curl, one can make direct 
estimates of the wind-dri ven flow us ing the Sverdrup Bal ance. Below we 
have extracted two figures from  a ma nuscript written by Josey, Kent, and 
Taylor (JPO, subm itted) that discusse s wind stress from  a couple of well-
known climatologies (He llermann and Rosenstein , JPO, 1983; and Josey, 
Kent &amp; Taylor, 1998,  from  Southam pton Oceanogaphy Centre [SOC]).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>The Sverdrup circulation is construc ted by beginning the integration of the 
wind curl at the eastern boundary of all oceans and requiring that there be no 
flow into the ocean through/from the eastern  boundary. You will see that 
there is a lot of flow into and out of the boundary on the western  sides of the 
ocean basins. This is because we need  western boundary currents to return 
the wind-driven flow in these regions and they are not part of the dynamical 
balance. Finally, note that  while assumptions of geostrophic motion break 
down at the equator, there is nothing in the Sverdrup Balance that breaks 
down there. So unlike circulation ma ps inferred from dynamic height, maps 
of the Sverdrup circulation can be us ed to infer wind-driven circulation on 
and across the equator.  
 
Compare the subtropical gyres in the N. Atlantic and N. Pacific. The winds are similar in the two basins and so ar e the wind stress curls. But because the 
N. Pacific is nearly twice as wide z onally as the Atlantic, the Sverdrup 
transport (which is the zonal integral of the wind curl) is nearly twice as 
large. The two wind climatologies used  above are quite different in the 
Southern Ocean. Problems there are largely because there are so few ship 
observations in that part of the ocean . Another problem is because there are 
no continental boundaries over the latit ude zone defined by Drake Passage 
(between S. America and the Antarctic peninsula). Therefore we cant define 
a zonally-integrated Sverdrup Balance  there as there are no eastern or 
western boundaries to start from and end at! 
 
Before we return to the N.  Atlantic subtropical gyre, one further digression 
is needed. We have been rather vague about how the body force, F , is 
actually related to the wind stress. We ha ve also been rather vague about the 
nature of the frictional force. As thes e are two of the three terms in the wind-
driven theory of Stommel, it is proba bly appropriate to spend some time on 
this now. They are both related to the way that stress is transferred between 
fluid particles in the ocean. Once we have done this, we can also briefly 
discuss Munks (1950) paper on the wind-driven circulation and how it 
differs from Stommels.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Wind-Driven Circulation: Stomme ls gyre &amp; Sverdrups balance 
 
We begin by returni ng to our system of  equations for flow of a layer of 
uniform  density on a rotating earth.   
 
yvxut dtdwhere hHvyhHux thFrvyhg fudtdvFruxhg fvdtdu
yx
++= ++ +++= ++=
,0)] ([ )] ([,

 
 
We recall t hat z = -H is the bottom of the fluid layer and z = h  is the free 
surface. F or simplici ty, we will  define D to be the total depth of the fluid: D 
= H+h . Because the bottom  of the fluid is not changing in tim e, we can 
replace the time rate of change of h in the third equation with the time rate of 
change of D. Next we define v orticity. 
 
An im portant fluid property associated with shearing and rotating elem ents 
of motion is vorticity, . It is defined as follows: 
 
v   
 
It is a vector, but we will be consid ering here the vertical component of 
vorticity, which is 
 
) (yu
xv z
=  
 
This quantity depends on the shears in th e flow, not the flow itself. We will 
see that is an im portant quantity in a moment. But first note in the above 
equations t hat momentum  can change following a fluid particl e because of 
external forces, fricti on and pressure gradi ents. The latter element of non-
conservation can be re moved by considering vor ticity because if one 
differentiates the second equati on above  by x, the second equation above by</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>y and then subtracts them , the term  asso ciated with pressure gradients can be 
eliminated. We will not derive the following equation here, but you can do 
this on your own [in fact it may be a new homework exercise], but by using 
the above procedure and the definiti on for vorticity, and all three of the 
above equations, we can obt ain the following without any assum ptions about 
the Coriolis parameter being constant (except in time!): 
 
) (1) (1] [ FD DrF FD Dr
Df
dtd
hx
yy
xz G
 + =  + =+
 
 
In the absence of friction or external forces, the quantity [(f+)/D] is 
conserved, where we have  now dropped the subscript  v for vertical, which 
is assumed. This quantity is called potential vorticity  and is one of the 
fundam ental properti es used in physical  oceanography. It can be changed by 
friction and by a curl of an external fo rce (e.g. wind stress) but otherwise is 
remains constant. It is so im portant, that it is even known by the cartoon 
character  Dilbert (see figure s hown in cl ass). It states that, in the absence 
of external forces (or friction), fluid will tend to follow contours of constant 
depth in the ocean. Since depth varia tions occur m uch m ore rapidly that 
variations of the Coriolis parameter, fluid parcels can cross depth contours 
only by developing a  substantial relative vorticity. 
 
Concept o f lineari zation: 
 
If the equations are exam ined, not all te rms are al ways of the same size. We 
have already recognized that overall, friction will be small and for m any of 
the flows the basic balance will be ge ostrophic, for exam ple. Because the 
equations are non-linear, this makes solu tion very di fficult. SO if some of 
the sm all term s are the non-linear ones, ignori ng them  can allow us to obtain 
a solution! Consider the quantit y potentia l vorticity, for exam ple. It contains 
quantities which have different magnit udes. We will now look at som e of 
these ter ms [this exercise is cal led scaling]. 
 
We can denote the scale of a quantity by square brackets:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>) (1  ) (x
yy
x x yy xx F F r  = + +    
Stommel u sed a sim plified form  of the external forcing as well: is was a 
sinusoidall y-varyi ng body force in the x -direction, but varying only in t he 
y direction. At this stage, one  can associate this roughl y with a 
meridionally-varyi ng zonal wind stress. If this force is given by  
(Fx,Fy)=((-a/b)cos( y/b ,0) , using Stom mels notation, then the above 
beco mes 
 
y/b) sin(a ) (     = + +x yy xxr  
 
This is the equation Stommel solved which showed the different types of 
flow depending on t he rotation (or non-rota tion) of t he earth, and due to the 
earths curvature. The so lutions are shown in the textbook on p. 94. We will 
discuss this in class. Because  is always positive, the intense western 
boundary flow is always  on the western boundary. If the wind stress is 
reversed, the sense o f rotation of the flow will be reversed but the strong 
boundary flow will be to the south along the western boundary.  This is what 
we would expect in the subpola r gyres (to the north of the subtropical gyre 
Stommel considered.  This general result explains a lot about the structure of 
the wind-driven circulation in both hemispheres. You m ight think through 
what happens in the sout hern hem isphere where f  is negative (but NOT ). 
 
Sverdrups balance 
 
If we exam ine Sto mmels solution for th e flow in the case of rotation on a -
plane on p. 94, lower left, we see that except for the region near the wester n 
boundary of the basin, where the flow is strong and to the nort h, the flow 
everywhere else is zero or to the south.  We can think of this interior regi on 
as som ehow having different dynam ics than the wes tern boundary current 
(wbc) region. If one looks at the previ ous equation for the stream function of 
the flow, we s ee three t erms: one proportional to fr iction, one having , and 
a third with the forcing. The first term  beco mes important near the western 
boundary where gradients in t he stream function are large. Elsewhere friction 
is less i mportant because gradients of the stream function (actually second 
derivatives!) are s mall. So one might imagine an interior  region in which the 
second two term s are im portant and a boundary layer  region in which the 
first two term s are important, the forc ing there having no strong variation.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>In case you are wondering about the units in the second figure, they are in 
Sverdrups (1Sv = 106 m3/s, also named after guess who?). As a point of 
comparison, the Amazon river, which tran sports the most water of any river 
in the world, has a mean volume tran sport of 0.3 Sv. So the wind-driven 
flow drives transports in the ocean th at are a hundred times larger than the 
Amazon outflow. As we will see later, the actual transports in wbcs are 
substantially larger than what is an ticipated by the Sverdrup balance. But 
this is not going to deter us &amp; we w ill not throw out this valuable tool for 
understanding the wind-driven circulation. 
 Image removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>1]/[ ,1]/[],[])/(1)/(1][[] [][][]/[][
00 0 00
&lt;&lt; &lt;&lt; ++++
Hh and fLu RifHf
HhfLu
Hf
hHfH Hh hLuf f

 
 
The quantity R, is cal led the Ro ssby Number a nd is a ratio of the relative 
vorticity,   to the planetary vort icty, f. For m ost velocities and for m ost 
horizontal length scales we will use in  the course, this is a pretty good 
approxim ation (e.g. R&lt;&lt;1). If the total dept h of the fluid is m uch larger than 
the free su rface elev ation ch anges, then th e second approxim ation is good as 
well. In this case, potential vorticity sim plifies to ( f/H) which, in the absen ce 
of other forces, m ust be conserved. Wh at this means is that the fluid must 
always flow along lines of constant ( f/H). For an f-plane, this means that 
fluid cannot cross depth contours wit hout some external force operating. 
This is a p retty powerful statement! 
 
Now we will look at Stommels (1948) exam ination of wind-driven gyres. 
We have already derived everythi ng we need. We will use the above 
linearizations to sim plify the potentia l vorticty (PV) equation. His m odel 
was for an ocean of constant depth, so this sim plifies things even m ore. 
Since H is constant and f varies with latitude (y-direction), this means that 
PV conservation requires that fluid can flow only east/west NOT north/south 
unless there ar e external forces. This is now 
 
) (1) (), (1] [
x
yy
x y xx
yy
xz
F F uvr vscaling afteror F FD Dr
Df
dtd
   = + =+

 
With const ant depth, ( ux+vy=0) and we can write the second equation above 
in term s of a stream  function  : (u,v) = ( y,x)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Thermohaline Circulation (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>The Thermohaline Circulation 
 
The diagram at  the right is meant 
to represent the ocean as two 
layers: and upper layer largely 
driven by t he winds but having 
localized r egions where the l
layer water m ass is form ed by 
air-sea interaction.  These 
localized s ources, S, are in high 
latitudes such as the northern N. 
Atlantic and the Antarctic. The 
return flow consists of weak 
upwelling everywhere else in the 
ocean. Since the upper layer is ion contact with the at mosphere, its 
properties are constantly forced to so me specified surface v alues. If the d eep 
water is n ot going to eventually fill up the basin, it m ust be returned to the 
surface val ues. If this is done by downwar d turbulent diffusion from  the 
upper to lower layer, a balance can be reached when the weak upwelling 
balances:  this vertical diffusion. This  is the basic in terior balance later 
envisioned by Munk (1966, Deep-Sea Re search, see below). The source/sink 
flows represent water m ass forma tion and Stommel (1958, Deep-Sea 
Reseach) and Later S tommel and Arons (see Warren summary in Evolution 
of Physical Oce anography) developed a globa l model for the horizontal 
circulation driven by these transform ations. As the two high latit ude sources 
are each of order 15-20 Sv., a d eep circ ulation of one sign develops in the 
lower layer which is exactly opposite to one which develops in the upper 
layer in response to t hese sources.   S 
 2,H21,H1 
ower 
 
The m odel is essentially one in which th e potential vorticity of each layer is 
conserved. The conservation of PV in each layer is given by t he following: 
 
2
22
221 11
11
11 1

Hr
Hf
dtdFcurlH Hr
Hf
dtd
=
++ =
+ r
  
 
where F is the body force (i.e. wind stress) at the upper surfa ce. Now in the 
interior, away fro m any sources, there is  an upward velocity of the interface</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Note that the upper layer  circulation (opposite to that plotted in the figure) 
will be such as to increase northward transports in Gulf Stream over wind-
driven dynam ics, but will decrease tr ansport of the Brazil Current, because 
the two flows are opposed.  The actual flows in the western boundary 
currents are, mu ch like those for th e wind-dri ven circulation, dependent 
crucially on the nature of the fricti onal dam ping with Stommel- and Munk-
type boundary layers. 
 
This thermohaline circulation is an in ternal m ode which vanishes if we 
average vertically over both layers. It  is ultimately tied to the interior 
balance reflected by Munks fam ous Ab yssal Recipies paper (referenced 
above- in 1966): the cold water inject ed into the deep layer must be 
converted to warm  water in the upper layer by diffus ive proc esses. This is 
often overl ooked, but  it is a central el ement of the theory . Numerical work 
with more co mplicat ed ther mohaline mo dels shows that this is indeed the 
case: the strength of the overturning circ ulation is proport ional to the am ount 
of small-scale vertical diffusion of  heat/salt/density in the ocean.  
 
How big is the vertical velocity driv ing the above? Warren estimates that for 
a lower layer thickness of 3 km, with total source strength of 34 Sv. of deep 
water formation, mean ve rtical velocities will be  approxim ately 1.5 x 10-7 
m/s, horizontal interi or flows of order 10-3 m/s and western boundary 
transports of order 10 Sv. [=107 m3/s].  
 
Abyssal Mixing 
 
If we m odel the vertical flux of salinity (for example)  in the deep water as a 
balance between v ertical a dvection and vertical m ixing, the latter is m odeled 
as an eddy-diffusivit y so that small- scale turbulent fluxe s of salinity are 
given by 
&gt; &lt; =&gt;&lt;&gt;= &lt; )( '' zSwzSSw     
where  is a vertical eddy diffusivity. If w e insert typical values for the 
vertical variation of salinity and the a bove estimate for the vertical velocity, 
we can get an estimate of the verti cal diffusivity required for an overall 
balance of the therm ohaline circulation:    10-4 m2/s, one of the canonical 
numbers in oceanography.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>which we will take to  be a constant = w0:  H1=H0
1 - w 0t, H 2=H0
2 + w 0t. If 
these are inserted int o the above, we can obtain a pair of equations for t he 
linearized vorticity of the layer [this fo llows what  we did for the wind-driven 
circulation]. These ar e: 
 
22 0 0
22111 0 0
111
  
r wHfvFcurl r wHfv
= + = +r
 
 
We will now integrate these ov er the la yers and use the definition of wind 
stress at the upper surface. Here pleas e note that while the cu rrent in each 
layer is uniform  with depth (or near ly so), the friction parameter is not: it is 
strong near the surface and bottom and perhaps ne ar the interface. The 
integration results in an av erage of the friction parame ter in each layer. Th is 
procedure assumes that the variable t opography of t he internal interface and 
bottom  can be ignored (i.e. flat). Thus we obtain the following: 
 
222 0 21111 0 11
  
  
 +=+  =
dzr fw vdzcurl dzr fw vdzr
 
 
We have something like the Sverdrup interior balance (ignoring frictiona l 
terms) for the upper layer, which is  augmented by an upwelling across the 
interface, while in the deep er layer, a circulation op posite to that in the upper 
layer is driven by the upwelling. This upwelling results in a poleward  
interior flow ev erywhere in the deep lay er and an equatorward  flow 
everywhere in the upper layer driven  by the therm ohaline mass exchange. 
The flow schematic in the book (fig. 6. 40, p. 240) is for the lower layer. 
What emerges from  the above balanc e is the im portance of western 
boundary currents in redistribut ion of th e required transport for the interior. 
The Stommel/Arons m odel has not been ve rified in detail for the interior of 
the ocean, but its inferen ces about the location and di rection of abyssal flows 
has been o ne of the few th eoret ical predictions made before  the observations 
of strong, deep wbcs were made which later support it!</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Some Physical Properties of Sea Water (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-808-introduction-to-observational-physical-oceanography-fall-2004/resources/course_notes_1b/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>hShort digression on pressure: 
 
Consider the diagram at  the right: 
 
 A column  of water o f density  and height h is resting. 
The column has a cross-sec tional ar ea A. The pressure 
at the top of the colum n is P t and at the bottom, P b. The 
Pressure at the bottom can be expressed as the total force 
per unit area on the bottom  surface or 
 
(p1)  P b = (Ah)g/A + P t = gh + P t ,  
 
where ( Ah) is the mass of flui d &amp; g is th e accel eration of gravity. For small 
changes in depth, h = - z, and  P b - P t = P, the abo ve equation can be written in 
differential form  as: 
 
(p2)  P/z = -g ,  
 
where we have inserted the sign conventio n that z is positi ve upward. This is 
known as the hydrost atic balance &amp; is one of  the m ost im portant relations in the 
ocean, wh ere for mo st low frequency cha nges, it is a reasonable approximation 
of the force balan ce in the vertical. 
 
For a column of s altwater with a density of 1025 kg/m3 that is 10 m  high with a 
gravity of 9.81 m /s2, using (p1) we get: 
 
P = (1025)(9.81)(10) ~ 105 Pa, 
 
which is the pressure at the bottom  of the at mosph ere. Thus, the weight of the 
entire atmosphere is equivalent to 10 m of seawater! Mercury, which has a 
specific gravity of 13.6, or a density of  13.6 times th at of pure water, wo uld 
produce the same pressure at th e bottom  of a colu mn that is: 
 sealed
h = 105 Pa / (13600 kg/m3) / (9.81 m /s2 ) =  0.754 m. 
open 
0.76m   
With a sea level pressure of 1.01  Bar, this would give 0.76m . A  
mercury-filled tube, sealed at on e end and evacu ated of air on that 
end, open to the atmosphere at th e other is called a manom eter and 
is one of the easiest ways of r outinely and accurately measuring  
atmospheric pressure.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Temperature 
 
Temperature is measured  in an absolute s cale (degrees Kelvin, oK) from 
absolute zero, a temperatur e of zero molecular motion. Other benchmarks  have 
been picked somewhat arbitrarily base d on properties of various substances, 
which are readily available and have some rather stable properties. The 
temperature scale used on oceanography is the Celcius scale (degrees C) such 
that: 
 
T = t + 273.15, where T is in oK and t is in oC.  
 
Temperature scales have changed ove r the years (in 1948, 1968 and most 
recently in 1990) as various benchmark values have been changed. For the 
oceanographic temperature range (-2 to 35 oC), temperature is now based on 
electrical resistance measurements of a pure platinum wire relative to the 
resistance at the triple point of water,  which is a temperature value at which 
solid, liquid and vapor phase s are in equilibrium at a standard atmosphere. 
Other benchmarks and the resistance ratios are given below: 
 
 Temperature oC Wr 
Triple point, mercur y -38.8344 0.84414211 
Triple point, water 0.01 1.00000000 
Melting point, Gallium 29.7646 1.11813889 
Freezing point, Indium 156.5985 1.60980185 
  
Wr=R(t90)/R(273.16 oK) is the resistance ratio of  pure platinum for the t90 
temperature scale relative to the tr iple point of pure water. For the 
oceanographic range, 
 
t90 = 0.010015 + 250.7140(Wr-1) + 9.71421(Wr-1) 2 
 
The difference between the old (1968) temperature scale (t68) and the new 
(t90) is small, basically showing that water now boils at 99.97 oC not at 100! It 
can be written as  
 
t90=0.99976*t68</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>The diagram at  the right is 
taken from Pickard &amp; 
Emery (who took it from  
elsewher e) and shows the 
classic picture of the 
difference between 
temperature and potential 
temperatur e over a deep 
trench (Mindanao). On t
left, temp erature incre
with depth and density 
anomaloy (using in situ 
temperatur e) decr eas
with increasing depth and 
suggest a tongue of
cooler water flowing to 
the left, over the sill at th
right. Pote ntial 
temperature and potential 
density anomaly (right 
panels) correctly show 
cooler deep water flo wing over the s ill and into the abyss with stable 
stratification above.  he 
ases 
es 
 
e 
 
Density 
 
Various different ways are used to desc ribe the den sity of seawater and its 
relation to the basic field variables of  temperature, s alinity and pressure.  
 
 =   1000 kg/m3 = (s,t,p)  density anomaly 
 
v = 1/  = v(s,t,p)    specific volume 
 
 = v(s,t,p) - v(35,0,p)   specific volume anomaly 
 
 = (s, ,p,pr)    potential density [2= (s, ,p,2000)]  
 
Usually density is plotted/exam ined at fixed pressures so that  is much more 
comm only than . The internationally use d equa tion of state of seawat er was Image removed due to copyright
concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.808 : Some Physical Properties of Sea Water  or, More than you ever 
wanted to know about the basic state variables of the ocean  
 
Salinity 
 
Various salt constituents in 1 m3 of seawater having (t, S) = (20, 35). Taken 
from Neumann and Pierson, Principles of Physical Oceanography , 1966, 
Prentice-Hall.   
 
Constituent Mass, kg Running Total, kg 
NaCl 28.014 28.014 
MgCl 2 3.812 31.826 
MgSO 4 1.752 33.578 
CaSO 4 1.283 34.861 
K2SO 4 0.816 35.677 
CaCO 3 0.122 35.799 
KBr 0.101 35.900 
SrSO 4 0.028 35.928 
H2BO 3 0.028 35.956 
 
Now, based on the equation of state (EO S-1980) for seawater, the density of 
seawater having this (t,S) value should be 1024.8 kg/m3. So the mass of salts 
divided by the mass of the water is: 
 
(35.956/1024.8) = 35.1, which should be 35 but seems a bit off!  
 
Salinity used to be based on chlorinity (Cl) since it was found that many of the 
above salt constituents had a constant ratio with Cl in seawater under a variety 
of values and locations (based on the Challenger Expedition samples). After 
later finding out that this was not univers ally true, a different, more accurate 
salinity scale was developed based on the electrical  conductance of seawater 
compared to a standard  solution of KCl at 15 oC. A practical salinity scale 
was agreed upon in 1978 (PSS 1978). Standards based on KCl are available for 
purchase and are made in batches every year and distributed to the 
oceanographic community. See Fofono ff (JGR, 90, 3332-3342, 1985) for a 
discussion of PSS78 (and EOS1980, below) . Salinity used to be reported as 
parts per thousand or o/oo (or grams per kg of seawater), but now has no formal 
units under the new salinity scale.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Most formulae for water properties (e.g . EOS1980, PSS1978) were distri buted 
before this tem perature ch ange occurred and to be fo rmally correct, they shoul d 
have their t90 tem peratures changed to the t68 scale before using them. 
 
In this course, we will usually use the symbol T to represent t90, unless units 
are specifically given as oK. 
 
Some representative profiles  of tem perature and salinity vs. depth are given 
below. The region of rapid temperature change with depth due to seasonal 
heating is called the seasonal therm ocline. It lies above a permanent 
therm ocline, which divides the uppe r and deep parts of the ocean. 
Images removed due to copyright concerns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Pressure 
 
Pressure is force/unit area acting on a surface. It has se veral units, with 
conventional units different in meteorology and oceanography. The Standard 
International (SI) units are based on th e MKS (meter-kilogram-second) and is 
the Pascal. 
 
1 Pascal = 1 newton/m2, where  
1 Newton = 1 kg m / s2, making 
1 Pascal =  1 kg / m s2 . 
 
Other units commonly uses are based on the Bar, where 
 
1 Bar = 105 Pascal 
1 mbar 10-3 bar = 102 pascal = 1 hectopascal, 
1 dbar = 10-1 bar = 104 pascal. 
 
Pressure at the bottom of the atmo sphere is 1.013 bar or 1013 mbar. 
Meteorologists commonly use millibars as  pressure units and oceanographers 
use decibars because the additional pre ssure under a layer of water that is 1 
meter high is approximately 1 dbar. We generally use gauge pressure , or the 
departure of pressure from atmospheric valu es at sea level. Just to make things 
more complicated, pressure is often quoted in terms of cm or inches of mercury 
in a manometer, where a st andard atmosphere (1013 mbar) will raise a column 
of mercury a height 76 cm. Pressure measuring instruments can generally be calibrated by adding fixed masses that depress a fluid column a known amount, 
given that one can independently measure or determine the local acceleration of 
gravity!</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Adiabatic  Lapse Rate &amp; Potential Tem perature 
 
If a layer o f fluid is com pletely m ixed, then when 2 parcels of fluid from  
anywhere in the layer are brought together  at the same pressure, their properties 
are indistinguishable. The parcels m ust all have constant entropy per unit  mass, 
. This is expressed therm odynam ically as follows: 
 
()
Tv
p T TCwhereCTvT
dpdTor dppdTTd
p
p 
 =
==
+
=
  
, ,,0
 
 
where T is temper ature (oK), v/T is the change in specific volume (inverse of 
density) with respect to tem perature, Cp is heat capacity at con stant pressure, 
and    is the adiabatic lapse rate , or rate at which tem perature will change in 
the vertical in an otherwise vertically m ixed layer of fluid. It  is often explained 
in term s of the com pressiblility of air or seawater, but as  you can see from the 
above, it does not directly come from  the com pressibility ( v/p), but from the 
change in volum e with tem perature.  
 
At the surface of the earth in the lower atm osphere a nd in the deep ocean, the 
following are approximate values for : 
 
Lower atmosphere: -10oC / 1000m  increase in height 
 
Deep Ocean:  -0.1 oC / 1000m  decrease in depth 
 
This is m ost comm on to those living near m ountains who can m ove upward to 
cooler temperatures by ascending the mountain even in a well-m ixed lower 
atmosphere. In the o cean it is m ost evident in the gradual increase in 
temperature with increasing depth in  the deep ocean. Because of the non-
conservative aspect of te mperature, we often use potential temperature , which 
is the temperature of a fluid parcel th at is m oved adiabatically from  an in itial 
pressure of p i to a reference pressure p r. It is expressed as follows: 
 
+=rp
pi dp t , wher e   is the lapse rate and t i is the initial tem perature.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>suggested by Millero and accepted in 1980 (EOS80). The density of air at 
atmospheric pressure is approxi mately 1.2 kg/m3, nearly a thousand times less 
than seawater. 
 
Sound Speed 
 
The speed of sound, c, in  a fluid is defined as: 
 
c-2 = ( /p), where the usual notation above  appli es and the change of 
density with pressure  (related to  the inverse of the com pressibility) is 
determ ined at constant entropy.   
 
Values of sound speed (t=15 oC, p = sea level) in air (340 m /s) and water (1500 
m/s) are quite different and c has the property that it increases with both t and p. 
In the ocean, because p increas es with depth and t decreases with depth, one 
often sees a sound velocity minimum  in the water colum n as sketched bel ow: 
 
1450 1500 1550 m /s 
depth 1000m  
2000m                    
            
            
            
          
          
         
         
           Sound velocity m inimum or 
sound channel : whale s use it f or 
long distance communication! 
 
 
In the following figure (taken from  Pickard &amp; Emer y) an exampl e of a sound 
velocity profile is given for a North P acific location in which (upper panel) 
temperature and salinity variations ar e plotted vs. depth (left), the sound 
velocity dependence due to tem perature and pressure (cente r) and the resultant 
sound speed profile (right) are indicated. In the lower panel(s), near surface and 
deeper effects of sound speed variation on propagati on of rays of sound are 
shown. Note how, in the lowest plot, so und tends to be cha nneled in a region 
defined by the sound velocity minim um. This sound channel enables long-
distance comm unication by whales, and ha s been exploited by oceanographers 
[and the military]  for some time.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Dynamic Height or Geopotential Anomaly 
 
Under action of gravity, a geopotential  , can be defined as the work done per 
unit m ass to m ove a particle a distance dz, where z is the direction of gravity. 
 
+= =
z
dzg zdzg d
00 )(,
    
Recalling the hydrost atic balance (from  the discussion of pressure), 
 
 
  =   = = =  =
PP PP
dp pDwherepD dp dp dp Pthusd gdz vdp gdz dp
000
000
)(),( )0( )0( )(, ;
  
 
D(p) is dynam ic height or geopotential anomaly and it contains all of the 
horizontal and vertical variations of de nsity in the fluid. The term proport ional 
to 0 is of little dynam ic consequence a nd the ter m at the ocean surface, 0, is a 
depth inde pendent part of the geopotentia l or dynam ic height that will need to 
be evaluated based on c onsiderations othe r than density (or specific volume 
anomaly). The MKS units for geopoten tial anom aly or dynam ic height are 
m2/s2, but comm on usage gives values of dynam ic height in dynam ic meters, 
which is equivalent t o 10 m2/s2. 
 
Heat Cap acity 
 
The am ount of heat needed to raise the tem perature pe r unit mass of a substance 
a temp erature T = 1 oK at constant pressure  is heat capacity, C p. Some typ ical 
values are as follows: 
 
Ocean wat er: Cp= 4.2 x 103 joules/ kg/ oK Cp=4.2 x 106 joules/ m3/ oK 
Air   C p= 103 joules/kg/ oK  Cp=1.2 x 103 joules/  m3/ oK 
Granite  Cp= 0.84 x 103 joules/kg/ oK Cp=2.3 x 106 joules/ m3/ oK 
 
If one m ultiplies the heat capacity tim es the density of each of the above Cp, 
one gets the third colum n, which is a measure of the heat cap acity of one m3 of 
the substance. 
 
Refer ence:  Fofonoff, in The Sea , Vol. 1: Physical Pr operties of Seawater .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
