<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/</course_url>
    <course_title>Justice</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>Ethics </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Harm Principle (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec05/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 5  The Harm Principle  
1. The fundamental  question in Mills On Liberty  
 
a. The scope of social and civil liberty, or  
 
b. The limits of societys legitimate authority over the individual  
 
2. Stages of progress in the struggle between Liberty and Authority  
 
a. Before advent of popular government: subjects against oppressive rulers  
 
b. After advent of popular government: individual against society  
 
3. Tyranny of the majority by way law and custom , and the need for a limit on interference  
 
4. The Harm Princip le 
 
a. A filter for reasons  we might invoke to justify coercion  
 
b. Harm to others is the only  reason that can  justify coercion  
 
c. Other reasons can never  justify coercion , e.g.: 
 
i. Paternalistic reasons  
 
ii. Moralistic reasons and reasons of propriety  
 
iii. Perfectionist reasons  
 
5. Implications of the Harm Principle  
 
a. Freedom of all thought and conduct not harmful to others  
 
6. Mills utilitarian justification of the Harm Principle  
 
a. Even when they dont harm  others,  people can  sometimes  act in ways that are 
harmful to themselves or distressing to others  
 
b. But we should not coerce them in these cases, because  
 
c. Consequences for human happiness will be  better if we use persuasion, not coercion  
 
d. Why ? Because  coercion stunts the development and exercise of our distinctive  
human faculties our individualityand this weighs much more heavily  
(contributes much more to happiness) than any benefits  gained  from restricting 
conduct that is not harmful to others</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Justice &amp; the Ghetto Poor (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec23/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>8. Shelby:  the constitutional essentials are denied to people who are born into ghetto poverty in the US  
a. The ghetto poor lack adequate access, through legal means, to a minimum income sufficient to 
meet basic needs  
i. The menial service jobs available to the ghetto poor pay wages too low to escape 
poverty 
ii. Ghetto schools are substandard; ghetto residents cannot acquire skills to get  higher -
paying,  high -skilled jobs  
iii. The ghetto p oor cannot afford to move to the affluent suburbs where the schools are 
better; and governments/cities tend  to subsidize housing  only in poor areas, not in 
affluent suburbs  
iv. Welfare payments are not  high enough for  families to live adequately  
v. Now that we lfare has been replaced with workfare, those who accept welfare benefits 
are compelled to work at menial jobs for poverty -level  wages  
b. When some among the ghetto poor turn to illegal sources  of income, they are routinely 
treated more severely by the criminal justice system than other citizens who commit similar  
crimes  
i. There is class bias in the punishments attached to similar crimes (e.g., punishment 
attached to selling powdered cocaine vs. crack cocaine)  
ii. There is racial discrimination in arrest, prosecution, and sentencing for property 
crimes and drug crimes  (e.g., rates of illegal drug use are similar among  blacks and 
whites  and yet blacks  are sentenced to prison  for illegal drug use  at several times the 
rate of whites ) 
c. Partly as a result of these violations of formal justice , there are significant racial di sparities 
in the suspension of basic rights  
i. Black men are ~6 % of the general population but account for ~ 30%  of the prison 
population  
ii. Felony disenfranchisement for black s is three  times the national average; one in 
thirteen blacks ar e barred from voting, one in eight black men  
9. Shelbys conclusions  
a. The basic structure of US society exceeds tolerable injustice in how  it treats the ghetto poor  
b. Therefore, when some among the ghetto poor refuse to work menial jobs or turn to crime for income, they do not thereby violate any civic obligations grounded in reciprocity  
c. This does not mean that no  criticism of the behavior of the ghetto poor is appropriate  
i. Like everyone else, the ghetto poor have natural ( non-civic)  duties  towards other 
persons  
ii. Like everyone else, the ghetto poor have a duty to support the creation of more 
thoroughly just institutions 
iii. These duties are incompatible with some  criminal attitudes and behaviors  
d. But it is a mistake to suppose that the ghetto poor should avoid deviant behavior because they 
have a civic obligation  of reciprocity  to play by the rules like everyone else; s ubmitting to the 
demands of unjust institutions is incompatible with the duty to respect oneself 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 23  Justice &amp; the Ghetto Poor  
1. What is a US ghetto?  
a. A predominant ly black, urban neighborhood , with a high concentration of poverty (40% 
or more of the population living below the official poverty line)  
2. Two problems associated with ghetto poverty  in the US  today  
a. Poverty that is  deep, chronic, and  intergenerational  
b. Behavior, on the part of some  ghetto residents , that deviates from accepted social norms  
i. Refusal to work legitimate jobs  
ii. Engaging in  crime (theft, drug -deal ing, prostitution) to make money  
3. Two historically common  responses to ghetto pov erty  
a. Criticism of the governments failure to fight poverty; calls for more assistance to the poor  
b. Criticism of the behavior/values of the ghetto poor; calls to punish  crime &amp;  end welfare 
dependency  on  the government/taxpayers  
4. What sort of criticism of the ghetto poor is appropriate ? Dis tinguish two kinds of criticism:  
a. Criticism of the behavior of  some among  the ghetto poor as imprudent  
b. Criticism of the behavior of some among the ghetto poor as  unreasonable  
5. Why think that deviant behavior in the ghetto is unreasonable? Consider the argument from reciprocity  
a. Society is a cooperative scheme for mutual advantage 
b. Those who benefit  from  the scheme have a civic obligation, grounded in reciprocity, to abide 
by the norms that make social cooperation possible  
c. Therefore, the ghetto poor are shirking their civic obligation s when they refuse to work 
legitimate jobs and turn to crime for additio nal income  
6. Shelbys criticism of this argument  
a. Civic obligations to do ones fair share arise when the social scheme is  just and one is  
receiving  ones  fair share  
b. Moreover, c ivic obligations to comply with the requirements of basic social institutions 
(e.g., to obey the law) are binding even in an unjust society, so long as the injustice s are not 
so serious as to be intolerable  
c. However, there is no  obligation to submit to  institutions that exceed the limits of tolerable 
injustice  
7. Shelbys proposed standard  for when injustice becomes intolerable  
a. An otherwise unjust society is minimally tolerable if the consti tutional essentials are secure  
i. The society formally grants the  basic rights and liberties of citizenship to all  
ii. These rights and liberties are impar tially and effectively enforced for all  
iii. Everyone has adequate access to a minimum income sufficient to meet basic needs  
1. Everyone has an adequate opportunity to develop his marketable abilities  
2. Everyone has an adequate opportunity to earn an adequate income  
b. Injustice becomes intolerable when even these constitutionals essentials are denied to some  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Utility of Speech (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec06/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 6  The Utility of Speech 
1. Mills project in On Liberty  
 
a. Mills concern : the  existence/threat  of social  tyranny, by way of law and custom  
 
b. Mills question : when does society have the moral right  to coerce the individual? 
 c. Mills answer : only when its necessary to prevent harm to others  (Harm Principle)  
 
2. The Harm Principle:  
 
a. A filter for reasons  we might invoke to justify coercion  
 
b. Permits coercion only to prevent harm to others  
 
c. Forbids coercion for any other reason (e.g., paternalistic, moralistic, perfectionist)  
 
d. Demands freedom of all speech  &amp; conduct -not-harmful -to-others  
 
3. Mills argument  for the Harm Principle : 
 
a. We should always do what will maximize happiness  
 
b. Allowing freedom  of all speech  &amp; conduct -not-harmful- to-others will maximize happiness 
 
4. Why does freedom of speech  maximize happiness?  Why not censor  unpopular or false doctrines ? 
 
a. Because censorship  of unpopular doctrines  can deprive everyone of the benefits of truth  (in 
science, politics, morals)  
 
b. Because c ensorship of false doctrines d eprives everyone of the benefit  of (being confronted 
with) falsehood : being intellectually active  
 
5. Why does freedom of  conduct -not-harmful -to-others maximize happiness?  Why not more coercion?  
 
a. Because the best happiest ways of living will  be discovered only if there is room for 
experiments in living and variety of characters  
 
b. Because freedom of conduct -not-harmful -to-others is necessary  for individuality one of 
the principal ingredients in human happiness whereas coercion stunts individuality</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Utility of Liberty (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec07/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>c. Accepting  even a good , suitable  character or custom  merely  as custom  does not deploy or 
develop a human beings  distinctive faculties  
 
d. Developing ones own  character , and living a life that is the product of ones own  reasoned , 
choices i.e. , individuality requires having the freedom  to depart from prevailing 
custom ; and individuality is one of the principal ingredients in human happiness  
 
6. Two potential objections to Mills argument:  
 
a. Are all restrictions on offensive  or hateful speech impermissible? Are they impermissible 
because they  pose a threat to a people being intellectually active ? 
 
b. Are all paternalist restrictions on conduct impermissible? Are they impermissible because they pose a threat to individuality ? 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 7  The Utility of Liberty  
1. According to Mill:  
 
a. We should never coerce anyone except to prevent harm to others (the Harm Principle)  
 
b. Not because everyone has an abstract right to do as he pleases so long as he doesnt harm others  
 
c. But because this will maximize  human happiness in the long -run ( Utilitarian justification)  
 
2. Why does freedom of expression  maximize happiness? Why not censorship of unpopular doctrines?  
 
a. Not because the pains and frustrations of those who are silenced  always ou tweigh the 
pains and frustrations of the offended majority  
 
b. But because the most important costs of censorship fall on the audience: the entire community  
 
3. What are the costs to everyone  of censoring unpopular beliefs and doctrines?  
 
a. Being fallible, censors will sometimes hamper progress by mistakenly censoring true , 
happiness -promoting beliefs and  doctrines  
 
b. Censorship of false doctrines  deprives everyone  of the benefit of (being confronted with) 
falsehood: being intellectually activ e, examining and appreciating the reasons for their 
own beliefs  
 
4. Why does freedom of tastes and pursuits maximize happiness? Why not enforce conventional 
norms and prevailing customs?  
 
a. Not because the pains of those who are forced to conform always outweigh the pains of the majority distressed by seeing unconventional conduct  
 b. Because the most important  costs of the despotism of custom fall on the entire community  
 
5. What are the costs to everyone  when conventional norms and prevailing practices are enforced?  
 
a. Prevailing customs may be based on misunderstanding of what makes people happy ; to 
discover the best customs/ways of living , there must be room for experiments in living  
 
b. Not every good  custom is suited to every character or  every person ; if (most) persons are to 
be happy, there must be great variety of characters , each  with their own supporting customs  
 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Markets &amp; Moral Desert (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 16  Rawls on Markets and Moral Desert  
1. Recall from last time: Rawls  principles of justice and the argument s for them  
2. Can Rawls Difference Principle be defended against the objection from moral desert?  
3. Consider Rawls account of how prin ciples of justice are justified  
a. The Method of Reflective Equilibrium  
i. Identify c onsidered judgments of justice  
ii. Look for principles that would account for and explain these judgments  
iii. If the principles do not fit with all of our considered judgments, then consider whether 
to revise the principles or modify some of the judgments  
iv. Continue in this way until equilibrium is reached  
b. The Original Position as an instance of the Method of Reflective Equilibrium  
i. The Original Position and its special features are supposed to model our  considered 
judgments concerning reasonable constraints on arguments for principles of justice  
1. The hypothetical contract : principles of justice must be justifiable to each 
person (compare Utilitarianism, which may require large individual sacrifices)  
2. The veil of ignorance : the mere fact that  a principle would assign greater 
benefit s to someone with your class origins or natural talents o r aims in life is 
not, by itself, a reason for  society to adopt that principle  
ii. The Original Position is supposed to yield principles of justice that account for our considered judgments in particular cases  and which  extend these judgments to other 
cases in ways that on reflection seem correct  
1. The first prin ciple requiring Equal Basic Liberties accounts for (e.g.) the 
considered judgment s that slavery and religious intolerance are unjust  
2. Fair Equality of Opportunity a ccounts for (e.g.) the judgment  that racial and 
sexual discrimination are unjust and that unequal life chances deriving from 
inherited class  positions are unjust  
3. The Difference Principle reflects (e.g.) the j udgment s that no one deserves 
greater rewards merely  because he was born with a scarce talent but that there 
is no reasonable objection to inequalities that make everyone better off  
4. Does Rawls theory move us closer to reflective equilibrium?  
a. What about the common sense precepts of justice?  
i. To each according to his contribution  
ii. To each according to his effort  
iii. To each according to his need  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>b. Rawls holds that his theory can properly account of  these precepts (47)  
i. Taken together, the precepts are contradictory  
ii. At the same time, none can plausibly be elevated into a first principle  
iii. Thus, they must be given a subordinate role and assigned appropriate weights  
iv. Rawls claims that his theory does this by calling for (43):  
1. Competitive markets  give weight to the precept to each according to his 
contribution  
2. A social minimum ( set to  accord with the Difference Principle , at the highest 
sustainable level) give s weight to the precept to each according to his need  
3. Inheritance and other taxes which (i) establish and maintain Fair Equality of 
Opportunity, and (ii) allow greater income to those who make the effort to 
develop and use their talents in ways that benefit the least advantaged give 
weight to the precept to each according to his effort  
5. Does Rawls Difference Principle really give the right weight to the precept s of contribution and 
effort?  
a. Why cant those who are more talented complain that they morally  deserve greater rew ards 
than what the Difference Principle allows  them ? (17, 48) 
i. Why dont people with scarce talents deserve to be rewarded for their unique contributions  even more generously than the Difference Principle would allow?  
ii. Why dont the more talented deserve even greater rewards than the Difference Principle would allow if they are willing to put in more  effort  than less talented people?  
b. Rawls answer:  
i. Under the Difference Principle, the more talented will  already  be benefit ed more than 
the less talented. Why should they be benefited twice over?   
ii. After all  
1. The more talented cannot claim to deserve greater rewards  for the unique 
contributions their scarce talents enable them to make: no one is more 
deserving merely because he was born more talented. The notion of desert 
does not apply here.  
2. But d oesnt greater effort  make one more deserving?  
3. Perhaps but the effort a person is willing to make is influenced by his 
natural abilities  and skills and the alternatives open to him, as well as  his 
more or less fortunate family  and social circumstances.  Since there is no way 
to discount the greater good fortune of those favored by nature and social  
background, the idea of rewarding desert is impracticable. ( 17, 48) 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Entitlement Theory (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>iii. A given distribution of resources is just if everyone is entitled to the resources 
they possess under the distribution  
 
4. Nozick on the (first) principle of just original acquisitio n: 
 a. How can one justly  come to own a previously unowned thing?  
 
i. By mixing ones labor with it?  
 
ii. By leaving enough and as good for others?  
 
iii. By not making others worse off through ones act of appropriation  
 
5. Nozick on the (second) principle of just transfers: 
 a. A transfer of resources involving force or fraud is unjust  
 
b. Why?  Because such a transfer violate s a persons ownership  of himself  and his goods , 
insofar as he no longer decides what he will do , or w hat will happen to his goods  
 
6. The (third) principle of rectification of injustice: 
 
a. Applies to cases of unjust original acquisitions and cases of unjust transfers  
 
b. Asks  what would have happene d if the unjust acquisition/transfer had not occurred  
 
c. Calls for  measures (e.g., restitution, compensation ) that return the victim to the 
condition in which he or she would have been if the injustice had not occurred  
 
d. But d oes not allow compensatory measures  that would violate  rights of unconnected 
third -parties  
 
7. What are the implications of the Entitlement Th eory for contemporary societies?  
 
a. According to the Entitlement Theory, is the current distribution of property just?  
 
b. Does the current distribution reflect historical injustices that haven t yet been rectified?   
 
i. Who are the present -day victims of historical injustice? Who are its beneficiaries? 
 
ii. Are the victims worse off than they would have been had the injustice not occurred?  
 c. If there are as -yet uncompensated  victims of historical injustice , what measures would 
be sufficient to compensate them ? 
 
d. Of these measures, which ones  may the state use without violating the  ownership rights  
of third parties (people who neither committed nor benefited from the injustice) ? 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 11  The Entitlement Theory  
1. Nozicks two central claims in Anarchy, State and Utopia  
 
a. The minimal state is the most extensive state that can be justified  
 
b. Any state more extensive than the minimal state violates peoples rights  
 
2. Nozicks argument against a more extensive, redistributive state  
 a. The typical  justification for a redistributive state rests on some patterned  principle  
 
b. But, patterned principles should be rejected, because  
 
i. liberty upsets patterns  
 
ii. taxation of income from lab or is on a par with  forced l abor  
 
3. Nozick s Entitlement T heory of distributive justice : 
 a. Nozicks Entitlement Theory  is not patterned, but historical : the justice of peoples 
holdings  i.e., whether what people have, they have justly   depends upon what has 
actually happened  
 
b. The theory consists of three principles  
 
i. First principle  specifies how unowned things can come to be owned  justly  
 
ii. Second principle specifies how (justly owned) things can be transferred justly  
 
iii. Third principle  says what to do about unjust acquisitions &amp; unjust transfers  
 
c. According to the theory:  
 
i. A thing  is owned justly if it was originally acquired justly &amp; always  transferred justly  
 
ii. A person  is entitled to the resources he or she possesses if and only if he or she 
acquired these resources through  
 
1. a just original  acquisition (as specified by the first principle) OR  
 
2. a just transfer (as specified by the second principle) OR   
 
3. as compensation for previous injustice (as specified by the third principle)  
 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Communal Norms (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec03/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>J U STICE  
Lecture 3  Communal norms  
1. Last time : 
 
a. The parts of the Principle o f Utility and the case for them  
 
b. Implications of the Principle of Utility  
 
i. A comprehensive (personal and political) morality  
 
ii. Legal protection for unpopular behavior where punishment unprofitable  
 
iii. Rights understood as  means to maximizing happiness  
 
2. Civil liberties : will they be secure if we accept utilitiarianism ? 
 
3. Bowers v. Hardwick  
 
a. Due Process Clauses guarantee a  fundamental  right to privacy , but 
 
b. Right to privacy does not extend to protection for homosexual conduct, because  
 
i. Argument A : no connection with family/marriage/procreation  
 
ii. Argument B: majoritys conviction is a rational basis for criminalization  
 
4. Lawrence v. Texas  
 
a. Right to privacy extends to protect ion for  matters of  sexual intimacy , because  
 
i. Argument A: the argument from autonomy  
 
ii. Argument B : majoritys conviction insufficient basis for criminalization  
 
5. How to weigh the majoritys antipathy towards unpopular private conduct ? 
 
a. View 1:  there are no fundamental rights, and antipathy always  counts for something  
 
b. View 2: majoritys antipathy counts only  where no fundamental right  at stake  
 
c. View 3: majoritys antipathy never  counts, even when no fundamental right at stake  
 
6. Benthamite utilitarianism and civil liberties  
 
a. Does Benthams view lead to the right result ?  
 
b. For the right reason ?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Revisionist Utilitarianism (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec04/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>6. Is the development/exercise of our faculties valuable only  because it brings us pleasure?  
 
a. Is it intrinsically  valuable to develop and exercise your faculties?  
 
b. To be a certain kind of person?  Actually to experience certain things?  
 
7. Mills distinct view of  the special importance of  liberties: 
 
a. Bentham:  
 
i. All pleasures/ pains  equal; none contributes more to happiness than any other  
 
ii. Civil liberties founded  on general value  of avoiding  pain (e.g. from  punishment ) 
 
iii. Civil liberties not founded on anything of  special  value  
 
b. Mill:  
 
i. Pleasures derived from  developing &amp;  using  our distinctive  faculties are better  
 
ii. Civil liberties are necessary for developing &amp; exercising our distinctive faculties  
 
iii. Civil liberties founded on special , higher  value of developing &amp; using  our faculties  
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 4  Revisionist Utilitarianism  
1. Last time  
 
a. How to weigh majoritys antipathy towards unpopular private conduct?  
 
b. Supreme  Court: majoritys antipathy doesnt count where fundamental rights at stake  
 
c. Bentham: no fundamental rights + majoritys antipathy always counts for something  
 
d. Does utilitarianism support  civil  liberties? For the right reason?  
 
2. Mills revisionist utilitarianism  
 
a. Measure of a just law/action is (still) its consequences, how much goo d it produces  
 
b. Pleasure is (still) the only thing that is good in itself, but  
 
c. Some pleasures are of higher  quality, cant be outweighed by lower  pleasures  
 
d. Civil l iberties are required to maximize the higher pleasures  
 
3. Mills distinction between higher and lower pleasures  
 
a. A life is better happier when it contains higher pleasures , even if  less satisfaction  
 
b. Higher pleasures are the ones preferred by (all or almost all)  competent judges  
 
c. Competent judges decidedly prefer ple asures that come from exercise of intellect 
 
4. Why are intellectual  pleasures better/higher  for everyone ? 
 
a. Some people prefer other  pleasures . Why should they defer to competent judges?  
 
b. Is Mills argument elitist?  
 
5. Why are intellectual  pleasures better/higher? 
 
a. Use of our intellectual faculties awakens a sense of our own dignity  
 
b. Sense of our own dignity produces a desire to develop &amp; exercise our higher faculties  
 
c. Once we have this desire, we can t be happy without  engaging our higher  faculties  
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Justice as Fairness (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
 c. As a method that yields principles of justice that account for our considered judgments  of 
justice  
d. The Original Position as an instance of the method of reflective equilibrium, not an 
alternative to it  
4. The two principles that Rawls thinks would be chosen in the Original Position:  
a. A preliminary statement:  
i. First  Principle : Each person is to have an equal right to the most extensive scheme 
of equal basic liberties compatible with a similar scheme of liberties for others.  
ii. Second  Principle : Social and economic inequalities are to be arranged so that they 
are both (a) reasonably expected to be to everyones advantage and (b) attached to 
positions open to all.  
iii. Priority Rules: First Principle takes priority over the Second Principle, and in 
applying the Second Principle the requirement that position s be open  to all takes  
priority over ensuring that socio economic inequalities benefit  everyone.  
b. How are we to understand the phrases  open to all and to everyones advantage in 
interpreting the requirements of the Second Principle?  
5. Three alternative interpretations  of the Second Principle : 
a. The System of Natural Liberty  
i. To everyones advantage = Principle of efficiency (Pareto opti mality)  
ii. Open to all = Non -discrimination (careers open to talent)  
iii. Institutional implications:  
1. Distribution of income and wealth determined by a free market  
2. Against a background of legally enforced non -discrimination  
3. And a constitutional political order  compatible with the First Principle  
b. Rawls objection to the System of Natural Liberty  
i. Since there is no effort to preserve an equality, or similarity , of social conditions 
except insofar as this is necessary to preserve the requisite background 
instituti ons, the distribution of income and wealth will be the cumulative effect of 
prior distributions of natural assetsthat is, natural talents and abilities as these 
have been developed or left unrealized, and their use favored or disfavored over 
time by suc h chance contingencies as accident and good fortune.  
ii. Intuitively, the most obvious injustice of the system of natural liberty is that it 
permits distributive shares to be improperly influenced by these factors so arbitrary 
from a moral point of view.  
c. The Liberal Equality interpretation  
i. Tries to correct for this by replacing careers open to talents with Fair Equality of Opportunity:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 
 1. There is n o
 information that can be used to estimate the probability of being 
in a given social position   
a. [Why not? This restriction on information intended to model a 
reasonable constraint on arguments about justice (?): the justice of a 
given way of assigning rights and goods to various social positions does 
not depend on the numbers of persons in those positions] 
2. It is possible to assure oneself of a satisfactory minimum by choosing the 
Two Principles  
3. The other alter natives all have potential outcomes one could not accept  
a. The agreement determines your entire life prospects and is final (no way to 
offset losses with future choices or gambles)  
b. The strains of commitment would be too great to bear under the worst 
outcom es possible under (e.g.) Utilitarianism  
c. Impossibility of agreeing to (e.g.) the Principle of Utility in good faith 
i. [Do these considerations apply with the same force to the choice of 
other plausible principles? Consider (a) Principle of Equal Basic 
Liberties with lexical priority, plus (b) Principle of Utility, constrained 
by a social minimum that is adequate but significantly below the 
maximum sustainable level] 
a. The larger reflective equilibrium argument: the Original Position and the Two 
Principl e
s it yields reflect reasonable constraints on arguments  for principles of justice ; 
and the Two Principles account for  our considered judgments of justice , and extend 
them in ways that on reflection seem correct  
i. The hypothetical contract : models the constraint that  principles of justice must 
be jus tifiable to each person (compare Utilitarianism, which may impose large 
individual sacrifices)  
ii. The veil of ignorance : the mere fact that  a principle would assign greater 
benefit s to someone with your class origins or natural talents or aims in life is 
notby itself a reason for society to adopt that principle  
iii. The first principle requiring equal basic liberties accounts for (e.g.) the 
considered judgment s that slavery and religious persecution are unjust  
iv. Fair Equality of Opportunity accounts for (e.g.) the judgments  that racial and 
sexual discrimination are unjust , and that unequal life chances deriving from 
inherited class  positions are unjust  
v. The Difference Principle reflects (e.g.) the judgments that no one deserves greater rewards merely because he was  born with a scarce talent but that there 
is no reasonable objection to inequalities that make everyone better off  
7. Does Rawls theory of justice move us closer to reflective equilibrium?  
Rawls, John. A Theory of Justice. Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2005. All rights reserved. This content
is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 
 JUSTICE  
Lecture 15  Justice as Fairness  
1. Rawls conception of society and  the role of justice  
a. As a cooperative venture for mutual advantage,  society is mark ed by  
i. An identity of interests: social cooperation makes possible a better life for all than 
any would have if each were to live solely by his own efforts  
ii. A conflict of interests : persons are not indifferent as to how the greater benefits 
produced by their collaboration are distributed  
b. A set of principles is needed  
i. For choosing among the variou s possible social arrangements which determine the 
division of advantages from social cooperation  
ii. To serve as a common  ultimate  public standard for adjudicating claims or 
complaints against the basic institutions of society  
c. These principles are the p rincip les of social justice  
i. They apply to the  basic structure  of society, or the way in which the major social 
institutions distribute fundamental rights and duties and determine the division of 
advantages from social cooperation  
ii. They regulate the choice of a polit ical constitution and the main elements of the 
economic and social system  
2. Principles of justice as the outcome of a fair agreement  
a. They are the principles that free and rational persons concerned to further their own 
interests would  accept in an initial p osition of equality  
b. The agreement is not an actual but a hypothetical agreement , in a hypothetical situation of 
equal liberty, where  no one knows his place in society, his class position or social status, 
 his fortune in the distribution of natural as sets and abilities, his intelligence, strength, 
and the like .  [T]he parties do not even know their conceptions of the good or their 
special psychological propensities. The principles of justice are chosen behind a veil of 
ignorance.  
c. This ensures that n o one is advantaged or disadvantaged  in the choice of principles by the 
outcome of natural chance or the contingency of social circumstance. Since all are similarly 
situated and no one is able to design principles to favor his particular condition, the principles of justice are the outcome of a fair agreement.  
3. The Original Position as a method of justification  
a. As a hypothetical choice situation that guarantee s a fair outcome  
b. As a theoretical device for modeling (making vivid to ourselves) reasonable an d widely 
accepted constraints on arguments for and against principles of justice</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
 1. those who are at the same level of talent and ability, and have the same 
willingness to use them, should have the same prospects of success 
regardless of their initial place in the social system, that is, irrespective of 
the income class into which they are born.  
2. Institutional implications: 
a. A framework of political, legal and social  institutions which , subject to 
the requ irements of the First Principle :  
i. prevents excessive accumulations  of property and wealth, 
detrimental to Fair Equality  of Opportunity  
ii. provides equal opportunities for education for all , regardless of 
family or class origins  
d. Rawls objection to Liberal Equality  
i. even if it works to perfection in eliminating the influence of social contingencies, it 
still permits the distribution of wealth and income to be determined by the natural 
distrib ution of abilities and talents, and this is  arbitrary from a mora l point of 
view. There is no more reason to permit the distribution of income and wealth to be settled by the distribution of natural assets than by historical and social fortune.  
ii. Moreover, Fair Equality of Opportunity can be only imperfectly realized in a market society at least as long as some form of the family exists . 
e. Democratic Equality Rawls preferred interpretation  of the Second Principle  
i. recognizes  this fact ( i.e., that Fair Equality of Opportunity can be  only imperfectly 
realized in a market  society that also has the institution of the family ) 
ii. and also mitigates  the arbitrary effects of the natural lottery itself  
iii. How? By replacing the Principle of Efficiency with the Difference Principle as the criterion for when social and economic inequal ities are to everyones advantage  
and thus permissible  
1. Difference Principle: Social and economic inequalities must be to the 
greatest possible  benefit of the least advantaged  group in society  
2. Inequality is permissible only if lowering it would make the working class 
even more worse off  
iv. Institutional implication  (in addition to Fair Equality of Opportunity) : A social 
minimum must be instituted and maintained  at the highest sustainable  level  
6. Rawls two arguments for his  Two Principles of Justice (the Democratic Equality interpretation)  
a. The argument from inside the Original Position: the Two Principles are the principles that would be chosen in the Original Position, a choice situation that guarantees a fair 
outcome  
i. The unusual conditions in the Origin al Position warrant use of the maximin rule 
(from the available alternatives, choose the alternative with the highest minimum)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Against Redistribution (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 10  Against R edistribution  
1. Last time:  
 
a. The rejection of u tilitarianism as a consequentialist  theory  of morality, justice and rights  
 
b. The non-utilitarian  account of rights: r ights as constraints  on the pursuit of worthy  goals  
 
c. The fundamental right not to be subjected to force and aggression  (e.g. to benefit others)  
 
2. Context for todays discussion  
 
a. Large and growing economic inequalities in America and other countries  
 
b. Disputes about the justice  of economic inequalities  
 
3. Utilita rianism supports redistributive taxation  in the direction of  more equality  
 
a. Because of the declining marginal utility of wealth  
 
b. So long as redistributive taxation does not reduce aggregate economic output/growth  
 
4. Nozicks two central claim s in Anarchy, State and Utopia  
 
a. The minimal state is the most e xtensive state that can be justified  
 
b. Any state more extensive than the minimal state  violates people s rights  
 
5. Nozicks argument against a more extensive , redistributive state  
 
a. Arguments  in favor of  a redistributive state typically invoke some patterned principle  
 
b. But a ll such principles have unacceptable implications (t hey require violating peoples rights ) 
 
6. Nozicks two main arguments for why all patterned principles are unacceptable  
a. Maintaining a pattern requires continual interference with peoples liberty to do what they 
please with what they own  
 
b. Maintaining a pattern requires redistributive taxation of income from labor, but taxation income from labor is on a par with forced labor: it gives others a property right in you, 
your actions, and your labor</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Classical Utilitarianism (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec02/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 2  Classical Utilitarianism  
1. The Pinto Affair  
 
2. Cost/Benefit Analysis  in law and public policy  
 
3. Two distinctions:  
 
a. Empirical vs. normative claims  
 
b. Theory  of society and politics  vs. theory of social and political morality  
 
4. Utilitarianism as a comprehensive  theory of morality  
 
5. The Principle of Utility, or the Greatest Happiness Principle  
 
6. The argument for the Principle of Utility  
 
a. Consequentialis t view of right action  (rightness is a function of consequences)  
 
b. Hedonist th eory of value  (what matters intrinsically is happiness, understood as 
pleasure and the absence of pain)  
 
c. I mpar tia lity  (everyones happiness counts equally)  
 
d. Sum- maximization  (what is to be maximized is the sum of happiness)  
 
7. Implications of the Principle of Utility  
 
a. Perfect altruism?  
 
b. Enforcement of m ajorit y likes and dislikes ? 
 
c. Dom ain of  c ivil liberties  (where punishment unprofitable ) 
 
d. Meaning of rights 
 
8. A note on Bentham</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Utility of Democracy (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec08/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>6. But mass participation can also have bad  consequences, since  at present the majority has  
 
a. Low technical competence  
 
b. Low moral competence  
 
7. These dangers of incompetence must somehow be addressed if popular government is to be 
justified by appealing to  its results  
 
8. Mill s proposal  
 a. No group should be permanently excluded from  political  participation: this would forgo 
the beneficial educative consequences of participation  
 
b. But,  a basic literacy and numeracy test should be required of all persons who wish  to vote  
 c. And, multiple votes should be given to persons of greater mental competence 
 
9. A potential objection to the  utilitarian justification of democracy  
 
a. It be wrong to give educated persons more votes even if  doing so  would have the best  results  
 
b. Therefore, the utilitarian justification of democracy is defective  
 c. And , the Principle of Utility itself  must be mistaken  
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 8  The Utility of Democracy  
1. So far:  
 
a. We have considered the Principle of Utility as the ultimate principle of justice  
 
b. We have explored some of its implications for the content  of laws and social practices  
 
c. But the Principle of Utility also has implications for the form  of government  
 
2. Utilitarianism as a theory of democracy  
 
a. Everyone should have rights of political participation, including the right to vote  
b. Not because there is an inalienable right to part icipate in collective decision -making  
 
c. But because popular government  has the greatest amount of beneficial consequences 
 
3. Why does representative government have better results than non -representative government?  
 
a. Influence on the content of laws: participation provides better protection against oppression  
 
b. Influence on the character of the governed: participation has important educative effects  
 
4. Mill on the  beneficial educative effects of participation  
 
a. Having the vote gives people the sense that the laws to which they are subject are 
changeable by them, not merely visitations of Nature or unchangeable obstacles  
 
b. Political discussion expands peoples thoughts beyond their daily tasks and wants; they are 
led to form opinions on larger matters of common concern  
 c. Participation in the exercise of public functions (voting, serving on a jury, holding a public 
office) develops the ability and desire to act impartially and to pursue the common good  
 
5. Government should be organized so as to enhance these beneficial educative effects, through e.g. : 
 
a. Opportunities for ordinary citizens to participate in the exercise of public functions  
 
b. Norms of open, public discussion by government officials and elected representatives  
 c. The Single Transferable Vote  
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rights as Side-constraints (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec09/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 9  Rights as side -constraints  
 
1. Ut
ilitarianism as a consequentialist theory of morality  
 
2. Some p roblem cases for consequentialist theories  
 
a. Th
e trolley problem  
 
b. The survival lottery  
 
3. Distinguish two different objections to u tilitarianism  
 
a. Ut
ilitarianism misunderstands what is intrinsically valuable  
 
b. Utilitarianism treats all rights as derivative, but some rights are fundamental 
 
4. Distinguish t wo ways of taking fundamental rights into account 
 
a. Non -violation of rights is taken to be a goal of action  
 
b. Non -vio
lation of rights is taken to be a side -constraint on action  
 
5. Consequentialist theories  must  treat non -violation of rights as a goal of action  
 
a. Wha
t if punishing the innocent leads to fewer rights violation?  
 
b. What if  killing civilians in war leads to fewer rights violations ? 
 
6. Non -co
nsequentialist  theories treat n on-violation of r ights as a side -constraint  on action  
 
7. Nozicks fundamental  libertarian side -constraint against aggression  
 
8. Co
nsequences of Nozicks libertarian  side -constraint  
 
a. Economic redistribution is unjust  
 
b. The only kind of state that can be justified is a minimal state</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Justice &amp; the Social Ethos (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>3. But,  
a. He cannot appeal to  moral  desert or entitlement  
b. He is supposed to  affirm the Difference Principle, and  hence  to 
believe  that inequality is just only if its necessary to benefit worst -off 
i. Is the inequality strictly  necessary, independently of his will?  
ii. Or is it necessary only because he will decide  to work less 
productively unless he is paid much more than everyone 
else? 
c. The two lesson s Cohen draws from t his critique:  
i. The difference principle can justify  inequality  only in a society where not everyone 
accepts th at principle  (p. 123)  
1. Unequal, higher  salaries for talented people are necessary to benefit the 
worst -off only when talented people refuse  to work for ordinary rewards as 
productively as they do for exceptionally high ones  
ii. A society that is just with in the terms of the Difference Principle requires  not simply 
just coercive rules , but also an ethos  of justice t hat informs individual choice s. (p. 123)  
1. If the talented are not  willing to work equally productively for an average 
wage, then the tax system will have to assign  them above -average  rewards in 
order to improve the position of the worst -off 
2. But then there will be inequalities that are not strictly  nece ssary to benefit 
the worst -off: after all, had the talented agreed to work equally productively 
for an average wage, the worst -off would be (even) better off  
3. Thus, there will be no inequalities  that are not necessary to benefit the 
worst -off only if both  the tax system  (etc) and the economic choices of 
talented people are appropriately influenced by the difference principle.  
6. The basic structure objection to Cohens critique  
a. The primary subj ect of justice is the basic structure of society: its major institutions  
b. Principles of justice constrain the choice of ( coercive ) institutions that comprise this structure  
c. Principles of justice do not constrain the individual choices that are left open by just institutions  
7. Cohens main reply to the basic structure objection  
a. The main reason  for focusing on the basic structure  is that its effects are so profound  
b. But, the ethos  of s ociety  also has profound effects on peoples lives  
i. The prevailing norms  and expectations  of family life  (e.g., who is expected to do the 
bulk of the housework)  
ii. The prevailing market ethos (e.g., how  socially acceptable it is for talented CEOs to press 
relentlessly for higher executive comp ensation at the expense of low- paid workers ) 
c. Therefore , principles of j ustice must  also  govern society s ethos  and (?) the individual  
choices that  constitute  and reinforce  this ethos  
Cohen, G. A. Rescuing Justice and Equality. Harvard University Press, 2008. All rights reserved. This content
is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.
Rawls, John. A Theory of Justice. Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2005. All rights reserved. This content
is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 19  Justice and the social ethos  
1. How can todays large economic inequalities be justified?  
a. Moral desert: the rich morally deserve their earnings?  
b. Entitlement: the rich are entitled to their earnings (through, e.g., voluntary transfers)? 
c. General utility: the system of inequality maximizes aggregate welfare? 
2. Rawls (and other egalitarian liberals) reject these justifications  
3. A di fferent argument for inequality  
a. The general version: an inequality is just if its necessary to benefit the worst -off 
b. The incentives  version: talented people will produce more than they otherwise would 
if, and only if, they are paid more than an ordinary wage, and some of the extra that they 
will then produce can be recruited on behalf of the worst off (Cohen, p. 119) . 
4. Rawls appears to accept both versions of this argument  
a. According to the Difference Principle,  an inequality is just if and only if its necessary to 
benefit the worst off [ if lowering it would make the working class even more worse off 
(Rawls, A Theory of Justice , 13)]  
b. Rawls thinks  that inequalities  do count as  fully just under the Difference Principle if they 
act as incentives for the talented wealthy (members of the entrepreneurial class ) to 
work harder/in  ways that raise the prospects of the laboring class (Rawls, A Theory of 
Justice , 13)  
5. G. A. Cohens critique of the incentives version of the argument  
a. The argument stated  
i. Inequality is just when it s nec essary to benefit the  worst -off 
ii. When the top marginal tax rate is 35%,  
1. the talented wealthy  produce more  than they would if the top rate were 
higher,  
2. As a result, the worst -off are better off than they would be if the top rate 
were higher. (Although the distance  between rich and poor might  be 
reduced under a higher  top rate, in absolute  terms  the worst -off would be 
even worse off under a higher rate.)  
iii. Therefore, the top  marginal tax rate should not be raised from 35  percent  
b. Cohens critique of the argument  
i. The argument might look  persuasive when stated in  impersonal form  
ii. But the argument cannot be offered by a talented rich person to a poor person  
as justification for giving greater rewards to the former  
1. Its the rich person who makes it true  that he will work less if taxes go up  
2. Therefore, the fact that he will work less is a good justification only if he 
can justify it  (analogy to the kidnapper: Cohen, p. 122, footnote 15)  
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Justice &amp; the Family (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-04j-justice-spring-2012/resources/mit24_04js12_lec18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>d. This leads him to neglect: (a) inequality of opportunity within  the family , (b) the threat 
that gender poses to the familys role as a school of justice  
5. Okin nonetheless claims that Rawls theory has the resources to overcome these two problems  
a. If knowledge of sex is to be exclude d by the veil of ignorance, then we must consistently 
take the relevant positions of both sexes into account in formulating [selecting] and 
applying principles of justice  
b. Okin implies that the same  two principles would be selected  in the Original Position , but 
that they should be understood to be inconsist ent with a gender -structured socie ty and 
traditional family rol es 
i. Rawls  second principle   requires that inequalities be both  [1] to the greatest 
benefit of the least advantaged  and [2]  attached to positions open to all . 
ii. This means that if any roles or positions analogous to our current sex roles 
including those of husband and wife, mother and father were to survive the 
demands of the first requirement, the second requirement would prohibit any 
linkage  between these roles and sex. Gender, with i ts ascriptive  designation of 
positions and expectations  in accordance with the inborn characteristic of sex, could no longer be   legitimate.  
6. Is that right?  
a. There should be laws to eliminate continuing gender discrimination in hiring, promotion , etc  
b. Social in stitutions should be arranged so that women are not disadvantaged simply 
because it is women who bear children ; thus , there should be  adequate paid maternity 
leave, among other things  
c. But the typical division of labor between husbands and wives including the division o f 
responsib ilities for housework and child rearingreflects deeply ingrained social  norms 
rather than merely  laws and formal institutions  
d. These social norms may  well  prevail even when social  institutions are arranged to permit  
and encourage a more egalitarian division of domestic responsibilities ( Consider  Swedish 
paternity leave policy  vs. uptake by fathers ) 
e. At the same time, the Equal Basic Liberties would seem to forbid mandating a more  
egalitarian  division of domestic  responsibility  
f. So, c an Rawls principles condemn all  objectionable  inequalities traceable to gender if 
principles o f justice govern  only the major  institutions or basic stru cture of society but 
not the prevailing attitudes  in society ? 
Okin, Susan Moller. Justice, Gender, and the Family. Basic Books, 1991. All rights reserved. This content is
excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse.
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.04J / 17.01J Justice
Spring 2012
 
  For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>JUSTICE  
Lecture 18  Justice &amp; the Family  
1. Continuing  substantial  inequalities between the sexes , for example  
a. Income inequalities between men and women  
b. Occupational segregation into male- dominated and female -dominated professions  
c. Under -representation of women in government and judicial offices  
2. Okins central claims in Justice, Gender, and the Family  
a. Many of todays  inequalities between men and women  reflect gender  the social 
assignment of different roles (identities, opportunities, duties ) to persons of diffe rent  
sexes  particularly in the traditional family, with its characteristic division of labor  
between husband and wife  
b. Gender and the family have been largely ignored by existing theories of justice  
c. This neglect is unacceptable , for three reasons : 
i. Women must be fully included in any satisfactory theory of justice  
ii. Equality of opportunity, not only for women but for children of both sexes , is 
undermined by the current gender injustices of our society  
iii. The family must be just if we are to have a just soci ety, since it is within the 
family that we first learn to be just  
3. The role  of the family in Rawls theory of justice  
a. The link between generations necessary for a just savings principle  
b. An obstacle to the full achievement of fair equality of opportunity be tween  social classes 
c. The first and most important school of moral development /justice  
4. Okins main criticism of Rawls  
a. Rawls appears to acknowledge that the monogamous family, as a major social institution, 
forms part of t he basic structure of society  
b. Thus, one might expect him to explain how his  principles of justice bear on this 
institution , and on the  internal justice of the family   
c. However, instead of telling us what is necessary to ensure that families are  just, Rawls 
simply assumes that families are just  
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
