<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/</course_url>
    <course_title>Language and Its Structure I: Phonology</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>Linguistics </list>
      <list>Phonology</list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction, course overview, vowels: articulatory description and transcription</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec01/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>nose/nasal passages; lowered velum: nasal consonant: ma vs. ba, nasal(ized) vowel: Fr. beau 
[bo] vs. bon [b#%] 
mouth/oral cavity: tongue and lips 
[3]. vowels 
&#8226;	vowels produced with unobstructed, open vocal tract and lowered jaw 
&#8226;	major articulator is tongue body that can be arched and moved forward and back 
(horizontal dimension) and up and down (vertical); lips may be compressed and pursed 
(rounded), which lengthens the vocal tract 
&#8226;	vowel space is combination of articulatory and auditory factors 
&#8226;	widest at high vowels and tapered at lower: high-mid-low, front-central-back 
[4]. International Phonetic Association (IPA) http://www.langsci.ucl.ac.uk/ipa/ 
&#8226;	founded in 1886 by leading phoneticians in France, England, Germany, and Denmark 
&#8226;	goal: uniform system of transcription system to represent phonemic contrasts in any 
language 
&#8226;	2008: 107 letters, 52 diacritics 
[5]. vocalic distinctions 
&#8226;	all languages have a height distinction (greater acoustic energy at F1) 
&#8226;	minimal vowel system: [i,u,a] Cl Arabic, Yupik Eskimo, Quechua (maximal dispersion) 
Arabic	 l[i]bs 'clothes' x[u]ms 'one-fifth'
h[a]ms 'whisper'
4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>[4]. Phonology: basic research questions 
&#8226;	what is the nature of the phonological representations composing lexical items and the 
computations that realize them as articulatory gestures? 
&#8226;	phonological analysis of a language asks 
i. sound distinctions that encode the vocabulary of a language; language&#8217;s sound system 
(phonemic inventory) 
nasal vowels: French beau [bo] vs. bon [b#%] cf. Au Bon Pain (oh bone pan) 
stress location: A'merica vs. Ala'bama vs. Tenne'ssee cf. Ameri'ca, Alaba'ma 
&#8226;	not all concatenations possible: phonotactic restrictions
act [kt] *atk (cf. Saudi Arabic fatk 'destruction'
apt [pt] *atp magt [makt] 'despise'
pray tray cray(fish)
play *tl clay
&#8226;	sounds altered on the basis of adjacent sounds and position in prosodic structure
hat-s [t-s] feel hair 'telegraph [&amp;, ', &#230;]
'
kid-s [d-z] leaf hair-y te'legraph-y [', &amp;, ']
kiss-es [-'z]
[5]. phonetics 
&#8226;	mapping of phonological categories to articulatory gestures and their acoustic and
perceptual correlates
Unit 1 
[1]. goals 
&#8226;	first-order articulatory description of speech sounds 
&#8226;	transcription in the IPA 
[2]. speech: moving body of air made audible by the vocal apparatus; sound source that is 
shaped/filtered by vocal tract 
&#8226;	air expelled from lungs into trachea (pulmonic egressive) 
&#8226;	larynx: a complex cartilage that contains vocal folds (cords) that sit across the glottis and 
can assume a variety of positions 
wide apart for normal breathing 
tightly closed for swallowing 
brought together (adducted) and set in vibration (phonation) by air passing through: s vs. z 
&#8226;	three supralaryngeal cavities (vocal tract) that modify/shape the airstream (PGG p. 142) 
pharynx/pharyngeal cavity; pharyngeal constriction: Arabic (, ) 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>[6]. vowels of General American (GA) and RP 
English 
Am Eng vowels: 
RP Eng vowels: 
Key words	 heed [i] food [u] feud [ju] 
hid ['] bird [,] hood [-] high [a'] 
hayed [e] bud [.] hoed [o] how [a-] 
head [&amp;] a(bout) [/] caught [#] (a)hoy [#'] 
had [&#230;] father [+] 
&#8226; low vowels have front-back distinction 
&#8226; high vowels have tense-lax distinction 
beat [i] [u] boot
bit ['] [-] book
tense vowels are longer (marked by colon) and more peripheral in vowel space 
6 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	proto-typical five-vowel system: [i,e,a,u,o] Spanish, Swahili, Hawaiian, Japanese (most 
common in Clements&#8217; survey) 
Spanish m[i]sa 'mass' m[u]sa 'muse' 
m[e]sa	'table' m[o]sca 'fly' 
m[a]sa 'dough' 
&#8226; proto-typical seven-vowel system: [i,e,&amp;,a,u,o,#] Italian, Yoruba 
Italian p[i]no 'pine' p[u]ro 'pure' 
n[e]ro 'black' r[o]sso 'red' 
b[&amp;]ne 'well' [#]ro 'gold' 
l[a]ma 'blade' 
&#8226;	Turkish [i,&amp;,y,oe,*,+,u,o,#]: most economical use of three articulatory dimensions: 
[&#177;high], [&#177;back], [&#177;round] 
k[i]l 'clay' k[y]l 'ashes' k[*]l 'hair' k[u]l 'slave' 
k[&amp;]l 'bald' g[&#339;]l 'lake' k[+]l 'stay' k[o]l 'arm' 
http://www.langsci.ucl.ac.uk/ipa/ 
&#8226;	French [i,e,&amp;,y,&#248;,oe,a,u,o,#,+] 
l[i]t 'bed' l[y] 'read' past.prt' l[u] 'wolf'
l[e]s 'the' pl. l[&#248;] 'the' masc.sg. l[o]t 'prize'
l[&amp;]d 'ugly' l[&#339;]r 'their' l[#]r 'during'
l[a] 'there' l[+]s 'tired'
5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>at surface level quality is basic property: shortened [i] is still distinct from [']; 
lengthened ['] is still distinct from [i] 
&#8226;	[e]-[&amp;] and [o]-[#] sometimes treated as tense vs. lax as well but based partially on 
phonological distribution: [',-,&amp;] (but not [#]) are barred from end of word 
&#8226;	according to L's chart, in AE [e]=[e'] and [o] = [o-] start at same point as [&amp;] and [#] 
but are distinguished by movement of tongue to periphery of space as a diphthong 
&#8226;	three central vowels: [,] is unusual sound; effect of rhotic; [/] of about, sofa only in 
unstressed position; wedge vowel of bud very similar to schwa except found in stressed 
position 
&#8226; in Am E [e] and [o] are realized with offglide
&#8226; off-glide-diphthongs: [a'], [a-], [#']; on-glide diphthong [ju]
[7]. in sum: 
&#8226;	five front and back vowels: [i,',e,&amp;,&#230;] vs. [u,-,o,#,+] 
&#8226;	three central and three diphthongs 
&#8226;	English vowels are a challenge for learners coming from a more restricted inventory like 
Spanish or Japanese 
7 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	a grammar is the linguist&#8217;s characterization of I-language and models the ability of 
speaker-hearer to assign a form and interpretation to a potentially infinite number of 
expressions 
&#8226;	a grammar is a computation over units of various types 
[3]. grammar&#8217;s architecture: 
[semantics] 
[lexicon] [syntax]
[phonology]
 [phonetics] 
&#8226;	lexicon: list of vocabulary items (morphemes)
grammatical features: noun vs. verb; singular vs. plural, etc.
semantic features: human, male vs. female, etc.
phonological features: vowel, consonant, bilabial, etc.
arbitrary association of sound and meaning:
&#8216;dog&#8217;: [d#g], [$a], [kalb], [inu], &#8230;.
[thu]: &#8216;two&#8217;, &#8216;too&#8217;, &#8216;to&#8217;,
[bo]: &#8216;bow&#8217;, Fr &#8216;beau&#8217;, Jp &#8216;stick&#8217;, &#8230;
&#8226;	syntax: items drawn from lexicon and organized into syntactic units which are combined 
and moved to form a sentence 
student bought the book 
the student has bought the expensive book 
the MIT student will have bought the expensive book written by the instructor 
Which booki did the student buy [ei]? 
&#8226;	sentence is interpreted by two components 
&#8226;	a semantic component specifies the grammatical aspects of interpretation 
&#8226;	a phonological component that contains rules that enhance and change the sounds in the 
items (morphemes) inserted from the lexicon to yield a Surface Representation [SR] 
&#8226;	a phonetic component that converts the sounds of the SR into articulatory gestures with 
measurable physical dimensions: e.g. 100 milliseconds duration for a vowel, 150 Hz for 
F0 (tone), etc. 
&#8226;	in deaf individuals sentence may be realized alternatively in the manual/facial gestures 
of sign language 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 
Lecture-1: Course outline, background; vowels: articulation and transcription 
[1]. course topics 
&#8226;	internal structure of speech sounds and their distributions as a function of adjacent 
sounds and their position in a word or phrase 
&#8226; organization of sounds into prosodic units: syllable, foot (stress), phonological word 
[2]. language as object of investigation 
&#8226;	19th century: language a product of historical cultural evolution: to understand a
language in its current state is to know how it developed from an earlier state
&#8226;	reconstruction of Proto-Indo-European (PIE) 
systematic sound correspondences among Indo-European languages
Grimm&#8217;s Law
PIE *p *t k *kw*bh
Sanskrit pa!da treta ka bhrater
Latin pe!s tres canis quod frater
English foot "ree hound what brother
Crowning achievement of 19th century linguistics; linguistics regarded as &#8220;queen of social 
sciences&#8221; 
&#8226;	early 20th century Ferdinand de Saussure: proper object of study is current synchronic 
state; sounds of a language form a system where the interpretation of a given element 
depends on the other elements it is in contrast with; very influential in 20th century 
European thought (e.g. semiotics) 
&#8226;	Structuralism: isolation and analysis of the distribution of units at various levels of 
analysis in a corpus of data: phonetic, phonological, morphological, syntactic; 
distinction of phoneme and allophone; [ph]in, s[p]in vs. Mandarin [ph]ai &#8216;row&#8217; vs. [p]ai 
&#8216;white&#8217; ; phonetically same sounds but in Mandarin they form a lexical contrast but not 
in English; emphasis on procedures of analysis of &#8220;objective&#8221; data 
&#8226;	Chomsky &amp; Generative Grammar 
&#8226;	language is tacit knowledge (cognition) of the individual speaker-hearer that has
developed from a language faculty present at birth as a biological endowment
&#8226;	linguistic data are a reflection of this knowledge and of interest (only) to the extent they 
help to elucidate it 
&#8226;	basic questions become: what is the form of this knowledge (Internal-language), how is 
it acquired, and used to speak and understand? 
1 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>American English dialects</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
Some images removed due to copyright restrictions. Please see: Labov, William, Sharon Ash, and Charles Boberg. 
"Atlas of North American English: Phonetics, Phonology and Sound Change."  Mouton de Gruyter, 2005. ISBN: 9783110167467.
New England
Stream
Pennsylvania Stream
Coastal South streamArea within which
log construction was
dominant in 1850
Westward settlement streams as shown by building material (Kniffen and
Glassie 1966, Figure 27). 
E
M
I
TI
TIMMI
Distribution of political cultures in North America, M = Moralistic;
I = Individualistic; T = Traditional (Kilpinen 2010, based on Elazar 1972, Figure 11). Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901 Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>   i. /hw/ and /w/ merger: whale vs. wail (map 8.1 
&#8226;	starts in 13th c.; noted for London in 1791 
&#8226;	distinction was alive in N.A. in most areas except Eastern seaboard 
&#8226;	now generally lost except for some speakers in the South 
  ii. /ohr/ vs. /  h r/ 
&#8226;	hoarse, four, mourning  vs. horse, forty, morning 
&#8226;	preserved in Eastern Mass, Maine; SC; Talahassee - Dallas
  iii. /iw/ vs/ /uw/ (map 8.3) 
&#8226;	loss of glide after coronals in NA 
&#8226;	some speakers still distinguish dew, lute  vs. do, loot (North Carolina), Talahassee -
Jackson
 iv. Mary /ey/ vs. merry  /e/ vs. marry /&#230;/ map 8.4 
&#8226;	three-way distinction maintained in NYC, Phil, Trenton NJ 
&#8226;	Mary and merry  merge while marry distinct in scattered areas of South and East 
&#8226;	distinction lost elsewhere 
v. Merger of /i/ and /e/ before nasals: pin and pen map 9.5  South 
Mergers in Progress
    Low-back merger of /o/ and /oh/ (map 9.1) 
&#8226;	hot, sock, Don, dollar vs. caught, talk, dawn, caller 
&#8226;	merger in West, Western Penn and Canada; maintained in South, Midwest, East 
5. Vowel Chain Shifts  Chain Shifts (Martinet 1951) 
&#8226;	vowels dispersed over acoustic space to maintain a margin of comfort 
&#8226;	drag chain: vowel shifts to occupy a space vacated by a prior movement: fronting of
[u] results in raising of [o] 
&#8226;	push chain: vowel x encroaches on space of y, which then moves to maintain contrast 
&#8226;	English short vowels are stable through history while long vowels are not (cf. GreatVowel Shift; divine *i:&gt;[aj], serene *e:&gt;[ij], profane *&#230;:&gt;[ej] vs. divinity [i], serenity [e], profanity [&#230;] 
&#8226;	generalizations on recurrent changes in the English vowel system: peripheral vowelsraise, lax vowels and the nuclei of diphthongs centralize and lower 
&#8226;	Inland North Area around Great lakes was basis for Kenyon &amp; Knott's (1953) 
 
Pronouncing Dictionary of American English
&#8226;	Broadcasting standard for mid 20th century 
&#8226;	most unmarked for General American speech 
&#8226;	Since then a large warping of the vowel space has occurred that has classic propertiesof a chain shift, termed Northern Cities Shift (NCS) 
&#8226;	First step: raising of [&#230;] (recall James Adamo of Detroit) (F1 &lt; 700 Hz) (map 14.4) 
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	Divides Illinois, Indiana, Ohio, Pennsylvania into northern and southern (downstate) 
regions 
&#8226;	Carver (1987) shows lexical isogloss for rural and agricultural terms (10.2) 
&#8226;	Correlates with different settlement histories (10.4) 
&#61656;	New England (Pilgrim-Puritan)/Yankeewhole parishes move as group; settle in towns; house located by roadside;stable: sustained contact 
&#61656;	Midland/Upland Southernersmovement of individual families; structure of rural neighborhoods based on kinship; house located by creek or spring in isolated areas; frequently move:intermitant contact 
10. Yankee vs. Upland Southerners: clash of attitudes, self perceptions and stereotypes:
Yankees: self-improvement, impose moral views on whole society; antislavery;
 busybody and meddling
Southerners: lean, lank, lazy

11. political cultures (Elazar 1972) [10.8] 
&#8226;	Moralistic: government should help people achieve good lives; government service ispublic service; community can intervene in private affairs if it serves communal goals 
&#8226;	Individualistic: politics is a business, dominated by parties; government should notinterfere in individual&#8217;s lives 
&#8226;	Traditional: hierarchical view of society; government is province of elites; preferenceto maintain status quo
12. strong correlation between county-by-county voting for 2004 Presidential race and the
 Midland-Inland Northern boundary
13. conclusion: &#8220;as long as these ideological differences persist, speakers may be more likely to align their productions towards those around them who share their own identity and word-view&#8221; 
4
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	Second step: fronting of merged [o, ah] to fill void: lockes sounds like lax (F2 &gt; 1450 
Hz) map 14.5 
&#8226;	Third step: lowering and fronting of [oh/] (also found more widely) to fill void 
&#8226;	Fourth and fifth (Eckert): e &gt; &#65533; , &#65533;&gt; o (14.8) 
6. Southern Speech
older features 
&#8226;	Preservation of contrasts lost elsewhere: whale=/= wail; dew =/= do 
&#8226;	Front glide /yu/ in dew, tune, Tuesday 
&#8226;	Fronting of back vowel in Vw diphthong: too, road, mountain 
&#8226;	Loss of contrast of pin  and pen; him and hem 
&#8226;	simplification of /ay/ diphthong finally and before voiced cons: high , side, time 
&#8226; drawl: breaking of /&#230;/ esp before nasals: pants [a-y- schwa] 
newer features 
&#8226;	/ay/ glide deletion generalized to all contexts in Central Texas and Inland South 
&#8226;	reversal of /ey/ and /e/ so that nucleus of bait  is lower and more central than bet which 
becomes higher and fronter [macon georgia] 
7. lexical differences   i. general term for carbonated beverage 
&#8226;	tonic   Eastern Mass 
&#8226;	coke South 
&#8226;	pop    Midwest, upper West 
&#8226;	soda (lower West: Nev, Az, CA)
  ii. roof 
&#8226;	shortened /u/: North Midwest to West: Columbus Oh Kansas City, Denver, Seattle,  Central CA
 iii. positive anymore (it's hard to find a job anymore
 ), needs+PPtcl (The car needs washed) 
&#8226;	Scotts Irish origin 
&#8226;	Upland South and Midland (map 21.3, 21.4) 
8. general points 
&#8226;	no significant effect of ethnicity; Telsur subjects origin (German, English, Scotts-Irish, Irish, Italian, Scandinavian, French, Polish) 
&#8226;	African American Vernacular English (AAVE) 
 
&#61656; Uniform dialect with minimal regional variation
&#61656; Stands apart from vowel shifts found in the atlas, esp in Northern Cities
9. North-Midland boundary 
&#8226;	Sharpest division in North American English dialectology 
&#8226;	Rapid spread of NCS in 30-40 years; extends east-west not north-south: Albany, 
Syracuse, Rochester, Buffalo, Cleveland, Toledo, Detroit, Chicago, Milwaukee 
&#8226;	Cities below line (Philadelphia, Pittsburgh, Columbus, Cincinatti, Indianapolis) do notparticipate and differ from one another as well 
&#8226;	Boundary has remained stable for a century; sound change originated in Western NY 
3
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 North American Dialects 
1. Atlas of NA Engl (Labov et al 2005, Mouton) 
&#8226;	Towns over 50K pop (68% of N.A.) 
&#8226;	Telephone survey: name, age, occupation, location, national ancestry 
&#8226;	Two speakers per locus point; c. 800 total 
&#8226;	Key words and free conversation 
&#8226;	Excludes AA and Latino speakers who have special dialect features that are 
differentiated by different geographical parameters 
&#8226;	Focus on stressed vowels; traditional transcription based on American Structuralist phonemicization and keywords 
SHORT LONG 
upgliding "ingliding"
Vy Vw Vh 
nucleus front back front back front back unrnd round 
high i u iy iw uw 
mid e &#65533;&#65533; ey oy ow oh 
low &#230; o ay aw ah 
SHORT LONG 
upgliding "ingliding"
Vy Vw Vh 
nucleus front back front back front back unrnd round 
high bit put beat suit boot 
mid bet &#65533;&#65533;&#65533;&#65533; bait boy boat bought 
low bat cot bite bout balm 
2. rhotic vs. nonrhotic 
&#8226;	r-vocalization develops in 18th century England; 
&#8226;	prestige variant for 19th and early 20th century American English on Eastern seacoast 
&#8226;	rhotic restoration after WWII; change from above 
&#8226;	vocalization retained as consistent rule in Boston, NYC, and scattered areas of south 
(Durham NC, Columbia SC, New Orelans) map. 7.1 
3. Mergers 
&#8226;	mergers expand at expense of distinctions (Herzog) 
&#8226;	hypercorrections 
1
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Syllables I: structure and syllabification</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text> 
      24.901 Syllable-1 
1. motivations for the syllable 
&#8226; phonotactic constraints: #tr, #str, *#tl, *#nt 
&#8226; environment for rule: 
Am&#233;rica M&#242;nt&#225;na
Nebr&#225;ska &#224;rc&#225;de
atr&#243;cious &#192;tl&#225;ntic
astr&#243;nomy &#224;rthr&#237;tic
&#8226; rules of epenthesis and deletion 
atom &#8776; atomic vs. rhythm &#8776; rhythmic
dam&lt;n&gt; &#8776; damnation, &lt;p&gt;neumatic &#8776; apnea 
2. syllable structure 
syll	 N" 
onset rhyme
N'
nucleus coda
 N
p e	 n p e  n 
3. structure-building rules:
 i.	 [-cons] -&gt; [-cons] ii. [+cons] V iii. V [+cons]
| | |
N N N
 | | |
N' N' N'
 | |
N" N" 
4. Tautosyllabic consonant clustering controlled by Sonority Sequencing Principle 
&#8226; onsets rise in sonority 
&#8226; codas fall in sonority 
&#8226; sonority hierarchy: vowels &gt; glide &gt; liquid &gt; nasal &gt; obstruents 
&#8226; subsidiary: fricative &gt; stop, voiced &gt; voiceless 
&#8226; corresponds to energy in lower regions of spectrum 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text> 
 
  Blevins (1995) segment
[-cons]
 [+cons]
[+low] [-low] [+sonor]
 [-sonor] 
[-high] [+high]  [-nasal] [+nasal]  [+contin] [-contin]
  [+voice] [-voice]  [+voice] [-voice] 
&#8226; left branch path has greater sonority than right branch path 
5. onset augmentation coda augmentation 
N" N'
 |  |
Cw Cx (where Cw &gt; Cy) Cy Cz  (where Cy &gt; Cz)
6. case study: English (Kiparsky 19981, Clements &amp; Keyser 1983) 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>    7. filters: avoid same place of articulation (recall Arabic) 
*N' *N"          *N" *N" 
/ \ / \  /  \ / \
         lab  lab         cor [+lateral]   -sonor  X         cor
  +contin         -anter
  +voiced
     *pw, *bw *tl, *dl *vr, *zw  *t&#8747;r, *&#8747;l 
8. 	special status of [s]
N" w y r l m n 
| sp - + + + - -
s C st - + + - - -
sk + + + + - -
9. codas: 
[&#61509;] [e:] [&#61509;] *[e:]
bell bale helm [ejlm]
hem aim elf [ejlf]
pep tape hemp [ejmp]
10. SSP 
helm
elf triumph dam&lt;n&gt;
help hemp
11. coronal edges: 
depth, apse, adze, act, fifth, apt : violate SSP 
wild, paint, fifths, sixths : violate length 
12. outstanding problem; suggested solutions 
&#8226; add by special rule 
&#8226; adjoin to syllable or highgrer constituent 
&#8226; leave unparsed 
&#8226; posit empty syllable nucleus 
13. medial vs. marginal clusters in Polish and the SSP 
&#8226; longer clusters 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>pstry [pstri] 'mottled', przestepstw [psetempstf] 'crime' g. pl. 
&#8226;	violations of SSP 
#NN, NN# mnozyc 'multiply', hymn 'anthem'
#LNV lnu 'linen' g.sg.
VNL# kreml 'Kremlin'
#SOV rtec 'mercury', lwy [lvi] 'lions'
VOS# mysl 'idea', rytm 'rhythm', teatr 'theater'
&#8226;	penultimate stress rule shows that these clusters are not syllabic: cf. komu'nizm 
&#8226;	Rubach &amp; Booj (1990) find that sonorant consonant violations of SSC licensed
only at word margin: #lsn is popssible but #sln is not; siostr 'sister' gen.pl' is 
possible but siosrt is not 
&#8226;	SSC controls word medial syllabification 
&#8226;	onset maximization: do.bry 'good' pa.t[s]ec 'look' are preferred parse while 
kon.takt 'contact' and par.tija 'party are only possible parses: ko.ntkt, pa.rtija are 
impossible 
14. mora subsyllabic unit of timing 
&#8226;	light syllables contain one mora and heavy syllables two 
&#8226;	in some languages ban on segments sharing the same mora 
&#8226;	Arabic dialects 
Egyptian 
'walad ki'taab 'kalb N 
'walad-i ki'taab-i 'kalb-i my N 
wa'lad-na ki'tab-na kal'b-ina our N 
'boy' 'book' 'dog' 
Mecca 
'walad ki'taab 'kalb
'walad-i ki'taab-i 'kalb-i
wa'lad-na ki'taab-ana 'kalb-ana
Palestinian 
'walad ki'taab 'kalb
'walad-i ki'taab-i 'kalb-i
wa'lad-na ki'taab-na 'kalb-na
4 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Prosodic morphology: reduplication and truncation</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec23/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text> &#8226;	Arabic broken pl (McCarthy &amp;  Prince 1990)
parse out a Trochaic foot at left edge and map to an Iambic foot
nafs rajul jaziir xaatam jundub UR 
{naf}s {raju}l {jazi}ir {xaa}tam {jun}dub parse trochee 
{nafaa}s {rajuu}l {jazii}ir {xawaa}tam {junuu}dub change to iamb 
{nufuu}s {rijaa}l {jazaa}ir {xawaa}tim {janaa}dib change vowels 
nufuus rijaal jazaa? ir xawaatim janaadib add residue 
6. OT model: Ideally prosodic morphology disappears as a special mo dule and arises from variable
ranking of independently motivated constraints on markedness, faithfulness, and alignment. 
&#8226;	Prince &amp;  Smolensky 1993.  Tagalog um-  infixation arises from ranking No- Coda1 above an 
alignment constraint Edgemost that enforces a p refixal realization of the affix: no special
circumscription required 
/um, gradwet/ No-Coda Leftmostness
um.grad.wet ***!
gum.rad.wet ***! g
&gt; gru.mad.wet ** gr
grad.wu.met ** gradw!
/um, aral/ No-Coda Leftmostness
 &gt; u.ma.ral *
a.u.ma.ral * a!
a.ru.mal * ar!
&#8226;	McCarthy &amp;  Prince 1993  Axininca Campa 
kawosi kawosi- kawosi &#8216;bathe&#8217;
koma koma-koma &#8216;paddle&#8217;
thaa&#331;ki thaa&#331;ki- thaa&#331;ki &#8216;hurry&#8217;
osampi osampi- sampi &#8216;ask&#8217;
osa&#331;kina osa&#331;kina- sa&#331;kina &#8216;write&#8217;
&#61656; full reduplication of base to mark morphological category: / base-RED/ 
1 The OT markedness constraints Onset (penalize syllables lacking a consonantal onset) and No -
Coda (penalize syllables containing a consonantal coda) define CV  as the opti mal syllable
(explaining why it is found in all languages and why V CV is canonically parsed V .CV) 
Onset No-Coda
CV
CVC *
VC * *
V *
5
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>&#8226; which phonemes of the base map to the reduplicant? 
e. shape transformation: the prosodic structure of the base is altered to mark a
morphological category 
Arabic broken plurals 
sg. pl. 
nafs nufuus &#8216;soul&#8217; 
rajul rijaal &#8216;man&#8217; 
jaziir- at jazaa? ir &#8216;island&#8217; 
faakih-at fawaakih &#8216;fruit&#8217; 
xaatam xawaatim &#8216;ring&#8217; 
jundub janaadib &#8216;locust&#8217; 
&#8226; what is shape of derived form? 
3. possible answers: 
&#8226; string transformations (e.g. Chomsky 1951);  now regarded as too powerful 
&#8226; Autosegmental Phonology: the C- V skeleton (Clements &amp;  Keyser 1982) 
Arabic templates; root and pattern morphology 
more examples 
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>&#61656;	RED is suffixal morpheme with morphosyntactic features but no fixed phonological 
&#61656; in output RED tries to maximize copying of the preceding base but this is restricted 
by the avoidance of hiatus formalized as markedness constraint Onset: penalizesyllables lacking a consonantal onset 
&#61656;	Onset &gt; &gt; Max- Base- Reduplicant 
/osampi- RED/ Onset Max
osampi- osampi **!
&gt;osampi- sampi * o
7. OT research program in Prosodic Morphology 
Template requirements are violable and determined by ranking
Templates integrated with alignment of M and P categories
Templates decomposed into constraints
AC:	 RED =  at least two syllables
Max-BR =  reduplication is total: copies all of what precedes RE D 
RED =  material from root 
root reduplicated form with 1 sg. prefix
kawosi no&#331;-kawosi- kawosi 'bathe'
kintha no&#331;-kintha- kintha 'tell'
tho non-tho- non- tho 'suck'
naa no-na-no-na 'chew'
&#61656; the RED morpheme prefers to copy material from root
&#61656; but this can be overridden to ensure that reduplicant has two syllables
/no&#331;-kawosi/ Root Max
no&#331;-kawosi= no&#331;-kawosi *!
-&gt;no&#331;-kawos i=kawosi no&#331;
/no-naa/ Disyll Root
&gt; no-naa-no-naa *
no-naa-naa *!
&#61656;	but when a prefix is missing (as in 3rd person) then the reduplicant is monosyllabic; no dummy syllable is inserted 
/naa+RED/ Dep Disyll
naa-naa
naaTA -naa-TA *!
&#61656;	Ranking:   Dep &gt; &gt; Disyll &gt; &gt; Root &gt; &gt; Max 
6
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>katab- a daras- a perfect
ya-ktub- u ya-drus- u imperfect
kaatib- un daaris- un participle
ma-ktab- a ma-dras- a noun of location
'write' 'study'
&#8226;	McCarthy 1979: consonantal radicals and vowel melodies map to C - and V -slots in template
analogous to how tones are mapped to tone- bearing units 
/a/ /au/ /ai/	 vowel melodies 
CVCVC CV-CCV C CVVCV templates 
/ktb/ /drs/ /md/	 radicals 
&#8226;	Moravscik 1978: survey of reduplication in 200+ languages; never clearly copies a syllable;
a paradigm like the following is systematically missing from survey: 
ta.pa ta.ta.pa
ta:.pa ta:.ta:pa
tap.ta tap.tap.ta
&#8226;	Marantz 1982:  reduplication specifies an affix characte rized in C- V templatic terms plus a
rule copying phonemes of the base and mapping them to the affixal template in phoneme -
driven fashion: 
CVC-CVCV UR 
| | | |
b a s a 
CVC-CVCV copy phonemes of  base 
| | | |
basa b a s a 
CVC-CVCV map phonemes to CV  slots 
| | | | | | | and delete unmapped segments 
b a sa b a s a 
4. McCarthy &amp;  Prince 1986: Prosodic Morphology Hypothesis 
&#8226;	templates for reduplication and truncation are specified in terms of natural units of prosody 
(mora, syll, foot) (cf. syllable templates); 
&#8226;	Prosodic Hierarchy: phoneme - &gt; Mora - &gt; Syllable - &gt; Foot - &gt; Prosodic Word 
3
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Prosodic Morphology 
1. morphology 
&#8226; the prototypical morphological operation is affixation to a base. 
&#8226;	usually the process applies independently of the phonology of the base:
   be- ing, hit- ing, comput- ing, backtrack- ing, prefix- ing. 
2. but sometimes the base must have certain phonological properties: otherwise the operation does
not occur. 
a. size requirements 
    English comparative affixes to &#8220;short&#8221; bases: red -er, yellow- er, *corrupt- er,
     *beautiful- er 
&#8226; how is size measured? 
b. truncations for hypocoristics 
P&#225;mela &gt;  Pam; El&#237;zabeth -&gt;  Liz; Sam&#225;ntha - &gt; Sam; prof&#233;ssor - &gt; prof 
&#8226; how small can the truncate be? 
&#8226; what portion of the base is truncated? 
c. infixation of affix inside base: 
Tagalog 	 aral um-aral &#8216;teach&#8217; 
abot um-abot 'reach'
salat s-um-alat &#8216;write&#8217;
sulat s-um-ulat 'read'
preno pr-um-eno 'brake'
gradwet gr-um-adwet 'graduate'
&#8226; where is the infix positioned? 
d. reduplication: some portion of base is copied to mark the morphological category 
Ilokano	 verb reduplicated verb no of copied phonemes
basa bas-basa &#8216;read&#8217; 3 
adal ad-adal &#8216;study&#8217; 2 
da.it da-dait &#8216;sew&#8217; 2 
takder tak-takder &#8216;stand&#8217; 3 
trabaho trab- trabaho &#8216;work&#8217; 4 
&#8226; what is the size and shape of the reduplicant? 
1
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>PW            PW
|
 /\
F
  F  F
 /\  /\ |
&#963; &#963;&#963; &#963;&#963; &#963;&#963;
       / \     / \     / \  |   /\    /\ / |\
 pa     me    la            e l  i   z a  b e th 
&#8226;	truncation minmizes the word while still satisfying requirement that it be a Prosodic Word:
project through Foot category. 
5. examples 
&#8226;	Japanese hypocoristics: trochee: H, LL 
name diminutive
ti tii-tyan
yoosuke yoo-tyan
taizoo tai-tyan
kinsuke kin-tyan
wasaburoo waa-tyan, wasa- tyan, sabu- tyan
&#8226;	Yupik vocatives: iambic:  H, LH 
name vocatives
&#593;&#331;ukagnaq a&#331; a&#331;uk
nipi&#610;ak nup nupix
kalixtuq kal kalik
q&#601;&#1241;tun&#610;aq q&#601;&#1241;t q&#601;&#1241;tun
&#8226;	Ilokano: red =  maximal syllable 
verb reduplicated verb no of copied phonemes 
basa bas-basa &#8216;read&#8217; 3 
adal ad-adal &#8216;study&#8217; 2 
da.it da-dait &#8216;sew&#8217; 2 
takder tak-takder &#8216;stand&#8217; 3 
trabaho trab- trabaho &#8216;work&#8217; 4 
4
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Alternations and derivations I</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec05/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>(2) mela mela-n 
wanka wanka-n 
ku$ka ku$ka-n 
$uka $uku-n 
kat!a kat!u-n 
$awa $awu-n 
$i#e $i#i-n 
pape papi-n 
tjempe tjempe-n 
wi"e wi"e-n 
(3) yalul yalulu-n 
mayar mayara-n 
wiwal wiwala-n 
karikar karikari-n 
yiliyil yiliyili-n 
(4) yukar yukarpa-n 
wulun wulunka-n 
wu"al wu"altji-n 
kantukan kantukantu-n 
karwakar karwakarwa-n mela-&amp; sea 
wanka-&amp; arm 
ku$ka-&amp; groin 
$uku-&amp; water 
kat!u-&amp; child 
$awu-&amp; wife 
$i#i-wu&amp; skin 
papi-wu&amp; father&#8217;s mother 
tjempe-&amp; mother&#8217;s father 
wi"e-&amp; interior 
yalulu-&amp; flame 
mayara-&amp; rainbow 
wiwala-&amp; bush mango 
karikari-wu&amp; butter-fish 
yiliyili-wu&amp; oyster 
yukarpa-&amp; husband 
wulunka-&amp; fruit sp. 
wutjaltji-wu' meat 
kantukantu-&amp; red 
karwakarwa-&amp; wattle sp. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>5. Serbo-Croatian oxytones 
a.	 masc. fem. neuter plural 
ml&#225;d mlad-&#225; mlad-&#243; mlad-&#237; young 
p&#250;st pust-&#225; pust-&#243; pust-&#237; empty 
zel&#233;n zelen-&#225; zelen-&#243; zelen-&#237; green 
t#&#233;st t#est-&#225; t#est-&#243; t#est-&#237; frequent 
bogat bogat-a bogat-o bogat-i rich 
rapav rapav-a rapav-o rapav-i rough 
&#8226; V -&gt; 'V / ___ Co# accent the final syllable of the word 
b.	 masc. fem. neuter plural 
deb&#233;o debel-&#225; debel-&#243; debel-&#237; fat 
posustao posustal-a posustal-o posustal-i tired 
b&#233;o bel-&#225; bel-&#243; bel-&#237; white 
m&#237;o mil-&#225; mil-&#243; mil-&#237; dear 
ts&#233;o tsel-&#225; tsel-&#243; tsel-&#237; whole 
&#8226; l ! o : l is found between vowels and o is word-final 
&#8226; alternatives 
A.l-&gt;o/___ # 
B. o -&gt; l / V __ V 
&#8226; l vocalization to a vocoid is common (cf. Engl field [fiod], It. piazza &lt; plaza 
&#8226; o-&gt; l is unprecedented 
&#8226; deriving [o] from a vowel also simplifies the analysis of accent 
/#debel#/ /#debel-a#/ 
deb&#233;l debel-&#225; final accent 
deb&#233;o -------- l-vocalization 
c.	 masc. fem. neuter plural 
ledan ledn-a ledn-o ledn-i frozen 
d&#243;bar dobr&#8211;&#225; dobr-&#243; dobr-&#237; kind 
j&#225;san jasn-&#225; jasn-&#243; jasn-&#237; clear 
s&#237;tan sitn-&#225; sitn-&#243; sitn-&#237; tiny 
m&#243;kar mokr-&#225; mokr-&#243; mokr-&#237; wet 
3
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>B.	[+cons, &#8211;sonorant] -&gt; [+voice] / V ___ V 
/klup/ /klup-i/ /trup/ /trup-i/ underlying representation 
----- klub-i ----- &#8727;trub-i intervocalic voicing 
&#8226;	rule B would have many exceptions and so analysis A is the better choice 
o!u 
sg. pl.
snop snop-i &#8216;sheaf&#8217;
"wup "wob-i &#8216;crib&#8217;
trut trud-i &#8216;labor&#8217;
kot kot-i &#8216;cat&#8217;
lut lud-i &#8216;ice&#8217;
sok sok-i &#8216;juice&#8217;
ruk rog-i &#8216;horn&#8217;
A. [+syll, &#8211;low, &#8211;high, +back] -&gt; [+high] / ____ [+cons, +voice] # 
/rog/ /rog-i/ /sok/ /sok-i/ /wug/ /wug-i/ /wuk/ wuk-i/ 
rug ----- ----- ----------- ----------- ----- o &gt; u 
ruk ----- ----- ----- wuk ----------- ----- final devoicing 
B. [+syll, &#8211;low, +high, +back] -&gt; [&#8211;high] / ____ [+cons, +voice] V 
/rug/ /rug-i/ /sok/ /sok-i/ /wug/ /wug-i/ /wuk/ wuk-i/ 
--- rogi --- ---- ---- wogi ----- ------u &gt; o 
ruk ----- ---- ------wuk ----------- ----- final devoicing 
*wogi 
&#8226;	once again analysis B with u &gt; o would have many unexplained exceptions so analysis 
A is the better choice 
&#8226;	final devoicing removes potential inputs to o &gt; u but o &gt; u nevertheless applies 
&#8226;	so o &gt; u precedes final devoicing 
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901	 Analysis of Alternations-1 
1. when stems and affixes are combined the resultant sound combinations often trigger sound 
changes that result in multiple realizations of the stem or affix. If the alternations are systematic 
then we posit a single underlying representation for the stem and affix and derive the various 
surface alternants by ordered rules. The study of alternations is a primary vehicle to discover the 
rules of the grammar. Certain general principles guide the analysis of alternations. 
2. given a ! b, analytic alternatives: 
i. /a/ is underlying and is changed to [b] in some context 
ii. /b/ is underlying and changed to [a] in the complementary set of contexts 
iii. both [a] and [b] derive from /c/ with two rules: c -&gt; a and c -&gt; b 
&#8226;	choice among the alternatives is guided by the simplicity and plausibility of the rules 
and the coherence of the overall analysis 
3. predictability: 
if one set of lexical items exhibit an alternation between sound [a] and sound [b] 
and another set has stable, non-alternating [a] then try positing /b/ as underlying 
the alternating set, with rule /b/ -&gt; in some context 
4. Polish nouns 
p!b, s!z, k!g 
sg. pl.
klup klub-i &#8216;club&#8217;
trup trup-i &#8216;corpse&#8217;
grus gruz-i &#8216;rubble&#8217;
nos nos-i &#8216;nose&#8217;
wuk wug-i &#8216;lye&#8217;
wuk wuk-i &#8216;bow&#8217;
A. [+cons, &#8211;sonorant] -&gt; [&#8211;voice] / ___ # 
/klub/ /klub-i/ /trup/ /trup-i/ underlying representation 
klup ------ ----- ------- final devoicing 
1
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Lardil 
Native Australian language; Morington Island, Gulf of Carpentaria; originally described by Ken 
Hale (1966,1973); later by Norvin Richards (200X). Largely extinct. 
Vocoids	 Consonants 
i	 u p t! t tj " k 
e	 a m n! n nj # $ 
y	 w l,r %,&amp; 
t! n!	 t, n = apical alveolar = laminal dental 
tj, nj = laminal alveopalatal stops " = retroflex 
t! t tj " 
coronal + + + + 
anterior + + --
distributed + -+ -
Nouns occur unsuffixed (marking absolute) and in various inflected forms depending on the verb 
uninflected nonfuture future gloss 
(1)	 kentapal kentapal-in kentapal-u&amp; dugong 
ket! ketar-in ket! river ar ! ar-u&amp;
miya&amp; miya&amp;-in miya&amp;-u&amp; spear
ya&amp;put ya&amp;putj-in ya&amp;put! snake
 -u&amp;
pir$en pir$en-in pir$en-ku&amp; woman
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>(5) t! t! t! urara urara$-in urara$-ku&amp; shark 
$alu $aluk-in $aluk-u&amp; story 
putu putuka-n putuka-&amp; short 
murkuni murkunima-n murkunima-&amp; nullah 
$awu$a $awu$awu-n $awu$awu-&amp; termite 
tipiti tipitipi-n tipitipi-wu&amp; rock cod 
t! t! t! older brother apu aputji-n aputji-wu&amp; 
mu$kumu mu$kumu$ku-n mu$kumu$ku-&amp; wooden axe 
tjumputju tjumputjumpu-n tjumputjumpu-&amp; dragon-fly 
(6) &amp;ilta &amp;il-in &amp;il-u&amp; neck 
ma&amp;"a ma&amp;-in ma&amp;-u&amp; hand 
"u&amp;"a "u&amp;-in "u&amp;-u&amp; excrement 
wunta wun-in wun-ku&amp; rain 
ka#"a ka#-in ka#-ku&amp; grass 
"era "er-in "er-u&amp; thigh 
yaka yak-in yak-u&amp; fish 
&amp;elka &amp;elk-in &amp;elk-u&amp; head </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	a ! &#248; 
&#8226;	alternatives 
A. syncope: a -&gt; &#248; / VC __ CV cf. gen&lt;e&gt;ral 
B. epenthesis: &#248; -&gt; a / C ___ [+sonorant, +cons] # (cf. cycle ! cycl-ic 
&#8226;	additional coherence: inserted [a] is skipped by accent rule 
/#dobr#/ /#dobr-a#/
d&#243;br dobr-&#225; final accent
d&#243;bar ------- epenthesis
d. epenthesis precedes l-vocalization 
masc. fem. neuter plural 
okr&#250;gao okrugl-&#225; okrugl-&#243; okrugl-&#237; round 
&#243;bao obl-&#225; obl-&#243; obl-&#237; plump 
n&#225;gao nagl-&#225; nagl-&#243; nagl-&#237; abrupt 
/#okrugl#/ /#okrugl-a#/ 
okr&#250;gl okrugl-&#225; final accent 
okr&#250;gal -------- epenthesis 
okr&#250;gao -------- l-vocalization 
e. summary: 
&#8226;	rules normally form a partially ordered set 
&#8226;	in this case from SC we have a total ordering since each of the three rules potentially 
affects the applicability of the other two 
final accent precedes l-vocalization
final accent precedes epenthesis
epenthesis precedes l-vocalization
4
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Phonological versus phonetic representations</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec04/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#8220;a voiceless stop becomes aspirated at the beginning of a syllable&#8221;
cf. [ph]a'cific, [th]er'rific, [kh]or'rupt
ra'[ph]idity, a['th]omic, a'[kh]oustic
&#8226;	[&#8722;contin, &#8722;voice] -&gt; [&#8722;spread gl] / 'V__V 
&#8226;	several rules of English phonology sensitive to intervocalic context V1___V2 where V2 is unstressed: 
cf. annual [nj] but annuity [n]; ve[ ]icle but ve[h]icular 
&#8226;	sC clusters are site of no contrast in [voice] (and [spread gl]): s[p]in, s[t]em, s[k]in, *zbin, *bzin 
&#8226;	unmarked default values emerge: [&#8722;voice] [&#8722;spread gl] 
&#8226;	there is one qualification to the statement that no minimal pairs exist for aspiration; this is true at 
the level of the word; but at the level of the phrase one must know where the word-boundaries 
fall to assign aspiration: cf. ice cream [kh] vs. I scream [k] 
&#8226;	the distribution of such features are plausibly parsing cues that allow the listener to locate word 
boundaries 
&#8226;	redundant features like aspiration and vowel nasality are commonly believed to enhance a 
phonemic contrast to aid in the recovery of the underlying form that allows the listener to enter 
the lexicon to interpret the sentence 
5.	vowel is lengthened before voiced consonant/ shortened before voiceless 
lap vs. la:b hit vs. hi:d buck vs. bu:g fuss vs. fu:zz
[&#230;] [&#230;:] [%][%:] [&amp;][&amp;:] [&amp;][&amp;:]
rope vs. ro:be heat vs. heed hake vs. Hai:g rice vs. rise
[o] [o:] [i] [i:] [e] [e:] [aj] [a:j] 
6. the phoneme /t/ has a variety of realizations (allophones) in English; 
[t] plain stem
[th] aspirated ten
['] retroflexed trip
[( ] flapped atom
[t?] glottalized hit, atlas
[)] glottal stop bottle
[ ] zero pants
[+coronal, &#8722;contin] -&gt; [+apical, &#8722;anterior] / ___ [r] /t/ -&gt; ['] 
[+coronal, &#8722;contin] -&gt; [+constricted gl] / in coda of syllable /t/ -&gt; [t?] 
3
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Kikuyu infinitive prefix 
2o-t,-,ra &#8216;to run&#8217; 2o-kuua &#8216;to carry&#8217; 
2o-koora &#8216;to root out&#8217; ko-ruya &#8216;to cook&#8217;
ko-oria &#8216;to ask&#8217; ko-m,0a &#8216;to know&#8217;
ko-h!ta &#8216;to be able&#8217; ko-ina &#8216;to dance&#8217;
ko-niina &#8216;to finish&#8217; 2o-kaya &#8216;to cut&#8217;
2o-t.uuka &#8216;to slander&#8217; ko-2aya &#8216;to divide&#8217;
Palauan Part of the analysis of any language is decomposing complex words into their constituent 
morphemes: in the simplest cases roots, suffixes, and prefixes. Examine the following paradigms to isolate 
the roots. What must the underlying lexical representation be? 
present future-1 future-2
m+3da-+b d+-+3ball d+3-obl &#8216;cover&#8217;
m+3te)+b t+)+3ball t+3)ibl &#8216;pull out&#8217;
m+3-et+m -+t+3mall -+3toml &#8216;lick&#8217;
m+3tab+k t+b+3kall t+3bakl &#8216;patch&#8217;
m+3)ar+m )+r+3mall )+3roml &#8216;taste&#8217;
m+3ses+b s+s+3ball s+3sobl &#8216;burn&#8217;
Tibetan numerals. This is a more tricky case of the same morphological parsing problem. Look for 
recurring forms to isolate the morphemes composing these numbers. What is the phonological rule that 
derives the surface form? 
d1ig &#8216;1&#8217; d1u &#8216;10&#8217; d1ugd1ig &#8216;11&#8217;
.i &#8216;4&#8217; d1ub.i &#8216;14&#8217; .ibd1u &#8216;40&#8217;
gu &#8216;9&#8217; d1urgu &#8216;19&#8217; gubd1u &#8216;90&#8217;
-a &#8216;5&#8217; d1u-a &#8216;15&#8217; -abd1u &#8216;50&#8217;
Interacting rules in two Bantu languages 
Lamba (Zambia) c4 = affricate [t.] 
Base Passive Neuter Applied Reciprocal 
c4 citwa c4 citila c4 &#8216;do&#8217; ita 4 itika 4 itana 
tula tulwa tulika tulila tulana &#8216;dig&#8217; 
c4 cetwa c4 cetela c4 &#8216;spy&#8217; eta 4 eteka 4 etana 
6
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>[3]. Even if a feature is not lexically contrastive in a language, phonological rules may introduce 
the marked value in particular contexts; sounds that bear the marked value are allophones 
(predictable variants) of the underlying phoneme 
two examples from English 
Example 1 
&#8226;	In French [&#177;nasal] encodes lexical contrasts in vowels: beau [bo] vs. bon [b!]"
&#8226;	English lacks such minimal pairs but it does have nasal vowels before a nasal consonant: cf. see [i] 
vs. seen [i]; "sew [o] vs. sewn [o]"
&#8226;	The French and English nasal vowels are phonetically comparable (identical) but have 
phonologically different status: nasality is assigned by rule in English but is contrastive in French 
French English 
/bo/ /b!"/ /so/ /so-n/ Lexical # Underlying Representation 
so"n [+syll] -&gt; [+nasal] / ____ [+cons, +nasal] 
[bo] [b!]" [so] [so"n] Phonetic Representation 
&#8226;	The nasal vowel in English [son] is thus an allophone of the oral phoneme /o/ while in French "
the nasal vowel is phonemic 
&#8226;	Psycholinguistic experiments show this difference is real: hearing part of a nasal vowel, English 
subjects expect a following nasal consonant while French (Bengali) subjects do not 
&#8226;	In English the oral ([-nasal]) and nasal ([+nasal]) vowels are in complementary distribution: 
nasal vowels occur before a nasal consonant and nowhere else while oral vowels appear 
everywhere except before nasal consonants 
Example 2 
&#8226;	In Mandarin [&#177;spread gl] encodes lexical contrasts: pha$ &#8216;to fear&#8217; vs. pa$ &#8216;father&#8217; 
&#8226;	In English voiceless aspirated and unaspirated stops are in complementary distribution; no such 
minimal pairs exist: [ph]in vs. s[p]in; aspirated stops occur at beginning of the syllable while 
unaspirated stops appear elsewhere; 
initial medial final
[ph]in [b]in ra[p]id ra[b]id la[p] la[b]
[th]ot [d]ot a[t]om a[d]am ma[t] ma[d]
[kh]ap [g]ap jac[k]et jag[g]ed pic[k] pi[g]
&#8226;	[&#177;voice] is contrastive in initial, medial, and final position as seen in the above minimal pairs 
&#8226;	text (and most literature) assumes that [&#8722;voice] is contrastive and aspiration is a redundant 
(enhancing) feature 
[&#8722;contin, &#8722;voice] -&gt; [+spread gl] / . ___ (C) [+syll] (dot = syllable boundary) 
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>/#t,nt-z#/ /#t,nd-z#/
t,nts ------- suffix voicing assimilation
------ t,:ndz vowel lengthening
t,ns t,:nz cluster simplification
10. typology of complementary distribution 
&#8226; one sound in restricted context, other is elsewhere case: e.g. flap in Am English 
&#8226;	more balanced distribution: vowel length and voicing of following consonant: lengthening or 
shortening? 
&#8226;	accidental complementary distribution: In English [h] is restricted to beginning of word or 
stressed syllable while [-] cannot begin a word or a stressed syllable 
&#8226;	whether two sounds are analyzed as variants of the same underlying phoneme depends on the 
simplicity of the overall analysis and the plausibility and naturalness of the rules; since [h] and 
[-] share no features in common it is implausible to derive them from the same underlying 
phoneme 
More examples (from Odden 2006) 
Kenyang (Cameroon). The velar stop [k] and the uvular [q] are in complementary distribution. What are 
the contexts where each occurs? Are there reasons for deriving one stop from the other? 
en!q &#8216;tree&#8217; enoq &#8216;drum&#8217;
eket &#8216;house&#8217; nt.iku &#8216;I am buying&#8217;
nek &#8216;rope&#8217; eyw/rek &#8216;sweet potato&#8217;
-g/q &#8216;knife&#8217; ek/q &#8216;leg&#8217;
ayuk name ku &#8216;buy&#8217;
kebwep &#8216;stammering&#8217; nk!q &#8216;chicken&#8217;
-k/p &#8216;money&#8217; k! &#8216;walk&#8217;
Gen (Togo) The liquids [l] and [r] are in complementary distribution. Which occurs in in a more 
restrictive context? 
a-!li &#8216;ghost&#8217; ago-glo &#8216;lizard&#8217; 
al! &#8216;hand&#8217; sra &#8216;strain&#8217; 
avl! &#8216;bait&#8217; edr! &#8216;dream&#8217; 
exl! &#8216;friend&#8217; hl, &#8216;read&#8217; 
-l! &#8216;write&#8217; 0ra" &#8216;be ugly&#8217; 
kl! &#8216;wash&#8217; tre &#8216;glue&#8217; 
mla &#8216;pound drum&#8217; zro &#8216;fly&#8217; 
l! &#8216;like&#8217; d1ro &#8216;hint&#8217; 
5
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>[+coronal, &#8722;contin, +constricted gl] -&gt; [&#8722;coronal] in casual speech [t?] -&gt; [)] 
[+coronal, &#8722;contin] -&gt; [+sonorant, +voice] / [+syllabic] ___ [+syllabic] (flapping)
&#8722;stress
7.	writer vs. rider and Canadian Raising (Joos 1942) 
[&amp;j] type tight tyke rice
[aj] time tide tie rise
[aj] -&gt; [&amp;j] / ___ [&#8722;voice] ( [+low] -&gt; [&#8722;low] / __ [&#8722;syllabic] [&#8722;voice] )
&#8722;cons
8.	write [*&amp;jt] ride [*ajd] 
writer [*&amp;j(+*] rider[*aj(+*] 
&#8226;	if we define phonemes solely by minimal pairs then [aj] vs [&amp;j] would be a phonemic contrast 
despite the predictable distribution of [&amp;j] 
&#8226;	analysis follows straightforwardly from two ordered rules that are needed anyway 
/*ajt/ /*ajt-+*/ /*ajd/ /*ajd-+*/ 
*&amp;jt *&amp;jt+* ------ -------- Canadian Raising 
---- *&amp;j(+* ----- *aj(+* flapping 
&#8226;	which features are contrastive can only be determined for the grammar as a whole 
&#8226;	opacity: the distribution of [aj] vs [&amp;j] cannot be discerned from the surface phonetic
representation: we must "undo" the flapping rule
&#8226;	expected result if the phonetic representation is derived from the underlying phonological 
representation by locally determined rules that apply without regard to their long-range, 
downstream consequences 
&#8226;	implication: the underlying form can only be recovered by knowing the rules, raising nontrivial 
learnability problems 
9. more opacity 
ten t[,:n] tent t[,nt] tend t[,:nd] 
ten-s t[,:nz] tent-s t[,ns] tend-s t[,:nz] 
vowel length and voicing of suffix depend on the /t/ vs. /d/ contrast in the cluster
but the stop is normally deleted medially in the cluster
4
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Phonological vs. Phonetic Representations 
1. reprise 
&#8226;	a speech sound is a particular combination of plus/minus choices for the distinctive features 
&#8226;	the features define natural classes for phonological rules and determine the grammatically 
controlled properties of the articulation and acoustics of the utterance 
&#8226;	most features are binary 
2. languages make different choices among the distinctive features to encode their vocabularies 
&#8226;	voicing ([&#177;voice] is not contrastive in Finnish but it is in English: (i.e. sue vs. zoo; Lacey vs. lazy; 
face vs. phase; no such pairs in Finnish; vowel length is contrastive in Japanese (e: &#8216;yes&#8217; vs. e 
&#8216;picture&#8217;) but not in Spanish 
&#8226;	one goal of the phonological analysis of a language is to determine which features are contrastive 
&#8226;	the sounds composed of contrastive features are called phonemes 
&#8226;	pairs of lexical items that differ by a single feature value are called minimal pairs 
&#8226;	they are good clues as to which features are contrastive in the language (but cf. writer vs. rider 
below) 
&#8226;	the contrastive (nonpredictable) feature values that distinguish one lexical item from another 
encode the lexicon 
&#8226;	predictable, redundant feature values are assigned by phonological rules when the lexical item is 
inserted into a sentence and enters the phonological component 
&#8226;	the phonetic representation thus has plus/minus specified for all relevant features, telling the 
vocal apparatus how to articulate the sound 
&#8226;	for most features there is an unmarked (default) value that represents the optimal state for that 
feature 
&#8226;	when there is no lexical contrast for a feature, the unmarked value normally appears phonetically 
(unless there is assimilation to a neighboring sound): Finnish stops are voiceless [-voice], Spanish 
vowels are [-long]; sonorant consonants are voiced; voiceless stops and short vowels are more 
optimal: they are found in most/all languages 
&#8226;	PGG Chapter 2 assumes that such noncontrastive features are [0F] in the lexicon and the
unmarked value is assigned in the phonology by default rules
&#8226;	Recent research challenges this assumption and would represent unmarked optimal value in the 
lexicon 
&#8226;	We will largely sidestep this question in this class 
&#8226;	Typologically some features are very common sites of contrast while others are less so or rare: all 
languages contrast [&#177;high] in vowels and almost all [&#177;back]; [&#177;nasal] is common while 
[&#177;retroflex] (cf. English bird) is rare; almost all languages have a dental stop and a nasal; most 
have an /s/; many contrast [&#177;voice]; while clicks are rare 
1
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>so-ka so-kwa so-keka so-kela so-kana &#8216;pay tax&#8217; 
pata patwa patika patila patana &#8216;scold&#8217; 
fisa fiswa fi.ika fi.ila fisana &#8216;hide&#8217; 
c4 ceswa ce.ika ce.ila c esa 4 4 4 4esana &#8216;cut&#8217; 
kosa koswa koseka kosela kosana &#8216;be strong&#8217; 
lasa laswa laseka lasela lasana &#8216;wound&#8217; 
.ika .ikwa .ic4 .icila .ikana &#8216;bury&#8217; ika 4
seka sekwa sekeka sekela sekana &#8216;laught at&#8217; 
poka pokwa pokeka pokela pokana &#8216;receive&#8217; 
kaka kakwa kac4 kacila kakana &#8216;tie&#8217; ika 4
fuka fukwa fuc4 fuc4 fukana &#8216;creep&#8217; ika ila 
Lomongo (Congo) 
Imper 1sg 2sg 3sg 1pl 2pl 3pl 
sa-ga nsa-ga osa-ga asa-ga tosa-ga losa-ga basa-ga &#8216;say&#8217; 
kamba -kamba okamba akamba tokamba lokamba bakamba &#8216;work&#8217; 
j4 njila oj4 ajila toj4 loj4 baj4 &#8216;wait&#8217; ila 4 ila 4 ila ila ila 
,na nj,na w,na ,na tsw,na j4 b,na &#8216;see&#8217; 4 w,na 
isa njisa wisa isa tswisa j4 bisa &#8216;hide&#8217; 4 wisa 
usa njusa wusa usa tswusa j4 busa &#8216;throw&#8217; 4 wusa 
ina njina wina ina tswina j4 bina &#8216;dance&#8217; 4 wina 
7
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Feature geometry</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>e.g, dog-[z] vs. cat-[sl where [F] = [voice] 
complete assimilation 
Arabic sun and moon letters 
?al-qamr 'the moon' ?aJ-anls 'the sun' 
?al-faras 'the horse' ?ad-daar 'the house' 
?al-kitaab 'the book' ?az-zayt 'the oil' 
?a]-harb 'the war' ?an-nahr 'the river' 
?al-ab 'the father' ?aO-8awb 'the garment' 
timing tier X,,, X 
f ""-....,, I 
[+cons] [+ cons] 
/ I 
[+ lateral] Oral 
Coronal 
lateral consonant of definite prefix is replaced by following coronal consonant 
[5]assimilation without delinking 
low tone spread in Buli: a high tone [A] becomes rising [g] after a low tone [A] 
mid tone [S] neither undergoes nor triggers the rule 
fi:k 'small' bag fi:k 'small lizard' 
zi 'millet' wi 25 'his millet' 
l2m 'meat' wA lam 'his meat' 
niim 'grind' niim z6 'grind millet' 
ci (I syllable tier 
[ +lo] [ + hi] tonal tier 
as a result of this rule the second syllable is associated with two tonal specifications: lo 
followed by hi which is a natural representation for a rise; similarly hi followed by lo 
associated to same syllable is a natural representation for a falling tone </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>[6] reduction deletion of part of tree without replacement 
reduction of unstressed vowels to schwa in English (Flem~zing 2004) 
Rosa's roses [a] .... [i] 
height difference but front-backness determined by coarticulation with adjacent 
consonants 
-delinking of [back] from unstressed vowel Dorsal 
t. 
debuccalization: s,f &gt; h; t &gt; ? [+.back] 
s-aspiration in Caribbean Spanish 
mes m~h 'month' , 
0' 
I 
Coda 
I 
[-tconsl meses [mes~hl PI 
after the rule the Glottal articulator becomes the major 
articulator to express [+continuant] 
[+contin] "Oral 
I 
Coronal 
* k &gt; ? in Hawaiian *kele &gt; ?ele 'black' 
,I+consl 
[-contin/] *Oral after the rule the Glottal articulator becomes the major 
1 articulator to express [-continuant] 
Dorsal 
[7] geminates 
* represent long vowel or consonant as one root node associated to two successive timing 
slots 
motivation: PBrnela Amanda Ram6:na 
Latin stress rule: heavy penult takes stress 
Heavy syllable: CVC or CV: Light syllable CV </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Feature Geometry 
--., o&amp;~Y,aclF, 
[I] In the early generative model the distinctive features formed an unordered bundle; research in 
the 1980's suggested that the features were organized into a dependency tree with the root node at 
the top and many features as leaves at the terminal nodes. Various intermediary levels of 
organization were also postulated. A new format for the formalization of phonological rules was 
also proposed based on this notation. It was hoped that this "feature" geometry would help to 
restrict the range of possible rules. We follow here the model proposed by Halle (1992). 
[2] major pieces of the structure 
* root node is location of major class features [cons] and [sonorant] that partition sounds 
into vowels vs. consonants and obstruents vs. sonorants 
various terminal features are the dependents of six articulators that are the principle actors 
in the production of speech: Labial, Coronal, Dorsal, Soft Palate, Radical, Glottal 
the articulators are grouped into a cavity specification where the constriction is formed: 
oral, nasal, pharyngeal 
certain manner (stricture) features more or less freely cross-classify the articulators and are 
off to side of the root node 
(3) [round] Labial [later] 
-&gt;- Coronal[dtstrib] 
[back] 
[high]* Dorsal 
[low1 [cons] 
[sonor] 
[nasal] Soft Palate Nasal 
I:",:: ,"? Glottal 
[voiced] 
terminal features articulator cavity stricture root 
[3] overview and motivation 
certain recurrent groups of features in rules of assimilation and reduction 
these groups are dominated by some node in the feature tree </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>lo:] [an1 
rhyme rhyme 
/ \ / \ 
timing tier X X X X 
\/ I I 
root node [-cons] [-cons] [ +cons] e 
rhyme 
I 
X 
I 
[-cons] 
* heavy syllable formally defined as having a branching rhyme 
geminate notation [oo] does not express fact that for rules of assimilation like umlaut long 
and short vowels behave the same (as a single segment) bevkb S ohh C tc: i-3 
5ahkii'i~Ij; nsxd-
[8] geminate integrity k.*wzb. T w-7 
rnBnnc,Lm 'fwengabl
geminate consonants parallel a cluster of two consonants for rules of syllable structure
-recall Italian f[a:].to but al.to and fat.to 
but geminates resist separation by rules of epenthesis (vowel insertion) 
Berber dialect of Guerssel (1978) inserts schwa to break up three consonant cluster (recall 
Tangale) ams 'rub' ass 'tie' 
amas-tan 'rub them' ass-tan 'tie them' "asas-tan 
X X X formal ban on crossing association lines 
Kolami vowel copy (Kenstowicz &amp; Pyle 1973) 
1sg. pres. 
suk-atun 
dakap-atun 
katk-atun 
melg-atun 
kink-atun iM-atun 
ad4-atun 
mind-atun 
poqg-atun 1 sg. past 
suk-tan 
dakap-tan 
katak-tan 
melek-tan 
kinik-tan 
it-tan 
at-tan 
min-tan 
poqk-tan imper. 
suk dakap 
katak 
meleg 
kinik 
ict 
a4 
mind 
POrJ 'whither' 
'push' 
'strike' 
'shake' 
'break' 
'tell' 
'thirst for' 
'bury' 
'bowl over' 
the linked structure in the homorganic nasal stop cluster like gk blocks epenthesis 
[+cons] [+cons] 
1 \I 
SP Dorsal </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>assimilation formalized as "spreading" of a tree node to the corresponding node in a neighboring 
segment; reduction formalized as the elimination of some tree node in the segment 
* segments linked to a timing tier of X slots that represent the linear order of speech sounds 
length/geminate contrast is represented as one root node of feature tree linked/associated 
to two successive timing slots 
[4] Assimilation types 
nasal assimilation: a nasal acquires the place features of a following (oral) consonant but 
not it's manner features like [lateral] or [continuant] 
Catalan (simplified) 
so[n] amics 'they are friends' 
bilabial so[m] pocs 'they are few' 
dental so[g] dos 'they are two' 
alveolar so[n] sincers 'they are sincere' 
palatal so[ii] [lY]iures 'they are free' 
velar so[g] grans 'they are big' 
rule [+cons] [+cons1 
/ """ .....,........I 
Nasal Oral Oral 
dotted line in rule denotes the spreading node; = denotes the delinked node 
* whatever articulator Oral dominates (Labial, Coronal, Dorsal) becomes the articulator for 
the preceding nasal 
* predicts no assimilation for a nasal preceding a pharyngeal or laryngeal consonant (cf. 
Sudanese Arabic p. 158 
regressive assimilation in general: node X acquires the same feature specification as node 
Y, losing its original specification 
X Y 
+'."".....&lt;....,.,,I 
[Fl [F] e.g. five but fif-th where [F] = [voice] and X and Y = Glottal 
progressive assimilation: node Y aquires the same feature specification as node X 
losing its original specification </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Phonetics III: suprasegmentals</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	level tones 
&#61656;	two-way contrast: Lingala (Bantu Congo)
mo-to&#769; 'head' lo-le&#769; 'tongue'
 mo 
mo-to 'person'	 mo-a&#769;si&#769; 'woman' 
mo-sisa&#769; 'vein' 
li-kolo 'leg' 
&#61656; three-way contrast:  Buli (Gur Ghana)
syu&#769;k 'path'
syu&#772;k 'navel'
syu&#768;k 'fish'
&#8226;	contour tones 
rise vs. fall Thai [Ladefoged CIP 10.4] 
high na:&#769; 'aunt' rise na:&#780; 'thick' 
mid na:&#772; 'field' fall na:&#770; 'face' 
low na&#768;: 'nickname' 
[9] register 
&#8226;	splits p itch space into an upper and lower region 
Cantonese [Ladefoged CIP Chapter 10 exercise G] 
high si 55 'poem' 
mid si 33 'to try' 
low si 22 'matter' 
extra low si 11 'time' 
mid rise si 35 'to cause' 
low rise si 13 'city' 
high fall si 53 'silk' [for many current speakers merges with 55] 
&#8226;	just as a vowel length contrast is o ften supplemented with a vowel quality contrast (e.g. 
Arabic) so a tonal height contrast is often accompanied by a laryngeal (voice quality) 
contrast so that breathy voice goes with lower tone 
[9] F0 used for intonation contours in English 
&#8226;	declaratives have falling contour 
&#8226;	yes-no have rise 
&#8226;	rise al so signals continuation, as in a list 
&#8226;	but these are just cross- linguistic tendencies; e.g. in Hungarian yes-no question ends in a fall 
4
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	#bra is a possible word initial cluster while #rta is not 
&#8226;	 syllabification parse here may be analogous to treating each syllable as if it w ere a word 
&#8226;	but if we get a consonant that is not permitted initially then syllabification goes against the 
Onset preference. Cf. Korean no velar nasal initially.  	V&#331;V is parsed V&#331;.V
tam can k*o&#331;
tam-i can-i k*o&#331;-i
'wall' 'cup' 'pheasant'
&#8226;	cf. English lam&#233;nt vs. le&#769;mon: [l&#603;] not possible word-finally; thus l&#603;.mon is not a good parse 
and [m] is perceived as ambisyllabic (straddl es syllable boundary and belongs to both 
syllab les) 
[4]. Stress: will discuss later: phonetic correlates include greater muscular energy (subglottal 
pressure) with increased pitch and duration 
[5]. Lengt h 
&#8226;	long vs. short vowels: Latin, Czech, German; ratio of duration contrast is 1.3 : 1 up to 2: 1 
&#8226;	long (geminate) consonant: Italian 2 to 3 times longer 
&#8226;	both long vowels and consonants: Hungarian, Arabic, Japanese, Finnish 
&#8226;	inherent duration of vowels: low vowel [a] is 2 0-25 ms. longer than high vowel [i] 
&#8226;	in a CVC syllable more time is required for tongue to move from consonant al constriction to 
open low target in CVC syllable 
&#8226;	global effects: 
&#61656; the number of segments in a syllable and the number of syllables in a word can 
decrease the length of the individual segments 
&#61656; phrase-final lengthening 
&#61656; tempo: faster tempo compresses longer segments (vowels) m ore 
&#8226;	Many languages avoid long vowel in closed syllable 
&#61656; Italian  lengthens stre ssed vowels of nonfinal syllable, but not when consonant in 
coda 
fate 'do' fat.te 'done' 
177 ms. 126 ms. D'Imperio &amp; Rosenthall 1999 
&#61656; Egypt ian Arabic non-final clo sed-syllab le shortening
baab 'door' beet 'house'
bab-na 'our door' bit-na 'our house'
&#61656;	English: keep, kept 
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#61656;	Cf. Hungarian, which retains contrast 
V C
hal 151 182 duration in ms
hall 177 272
a:l 285 172
ne:z 287 198
ne:zz 263 288
[6] tone: pitch  Fo 
&#8226;	gender: average of 130 Hz for adult males and 220 for females 
&#8226;	intrinsic F0: high vowels greater by c. 15 Hz (JN D for speech is 10 Hz) 
&#8226;	not clear why; speaker control to enhanc e height contrast ? 
&#8226;	after voicel ess obstruent F0 is 5-10 Hz greater (basis of tonogenes is); again appar ently under 
speaker control to enhance voicing contrast
 [7] tonogenesis 
&#8226;	in many Asian languages tones derive historically  from the phonemicizatio n of redundant F0 
differences that accompany voiced vs. voiceless obstruents in syllable onset 
&#8226;	F0 is typically 5-10 Hz higher after a voiceless obstruent as oppos ed to a voiced one 
&#8226;	in tonogenesis th e F0 difference is increased while the voicing contrast o n the consonant is 
decreased and event ually lost resulting in a tonal contrast 
&#8226;	prevalent in East Asian languages 
&#8226;	exam ple from Bei jing Mandar in 
&#8226;	tone 1 [55] High and tone 2 [35] Rise both go back to the same level pitch category (ping) in 
Middle Chinese 
&#8226;	the category split as a fu nction of the voicing of the onset consonant 
Middle Chinese Beijing Mandarin 
voiceless (yin) si si&#772; [55] 'poetry' 
po po&#772; [55] 'hillside' 
voiced (yang) zi si&#769; [35] 'time' 
bo po&#769; [35] 'old woman' 
Punjabi tones (Bhatia 1975)	 Hindhi Punjabi
ghor-a k&#242;ra 'horse'
dhol t&#242;l 'drum'
&#8226;	voiced aspirates devoi ce and deasp irate but with a low tone 
[8] lexical to nal distinctions 
3
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Phonet ics-3: syllables and prosodic (suprasegmental) features 
1. syllable 
&#8226;	no agreed upon phonet ic definition of syllable 
&#8226;	concept is inferred rather than perceived (Steriade 2000) 
&#8226;	syllab ic writing syste ms are ubiquitous vs. alphabetic 
&#8226;	suggests th at parsing speech into syllab les is easier than into phonemes (e.g. Japanese 
hiragana) 
&#8226;	many verse structures built on number of syllables (French alexandrine: 12 syllables divided 
by a pause (caesura) between 6th and 7th; Berber 12 syllable lines with heavy syllable in 
3rd, 7th, and 12th position (Dell &amp; Elmedlaoui 2002) 
2. internal structure: onset-rhyme (nucleus coda) 
&#8226;	structure preservatio n in spoonerisms: our dear queen -&gt; our queer dean b reak at onset.rhyme 
&#8226;	cross- linguistically rhyme is domain for poetic rhym e; rhym e books cruci al to recons truction 
of Chinese;
&#8226; open sy llable ends in a vowel and closed sy llable ends in a consonant
&#8226;	phonet ic definition in terms of chest pulses (Stetson) not confirmed 
&#8226;	peaks of sonority: sonority is roughl y the acoustic intensity of a sound with loudness being a 
primary auditory correlate. 
&#8226;	sonority h ierarch y: vowels (low,mid,high)&gt; glides &gt; r &gt; liquids &gt; nasals &gt; fricatives &gt; 
stops (voice d &gt; voiceless)  se e CIP 10.1 
&#8226;	corre lates with degree of opening of vocal tract 
&#8226;	no salient peaks lead to less robust judgm ents of syllable number: prism, file 
&#8226;	consonantal onset and cod a are fre quent sites of phonotactic restrictions (syllabic licensing): 
in English the velar nasal [ &#331;] is barred from the onset while in nonrhotic dialects [r] is 
banned from the coda 
[3] syllab le parsing 
&#8226;	given VCV other things being equal , V.CV pars e is preferrred 
&#8226;	Fujimura's (1978) exper iment
starts w ith cluster with different points of articu lation: apta, atpa, th en shorten
closure d uration to that of a single stop&#8212;but formant transition cues conflict: CV 
transitions predominate over VC
&#8226;	judgments of syllabic division are inferred rather than based on a direct phonetic percept. 
&#8226;	judgements based on possible word initial and word final clusters 
&#8226;	languages with no clusters at beginning and end of word will divide cluster:  CVC.CVC  (e.g. 
Korean). cf. English, Romance where V.CR (&#225;l.ge.bra) but VR.CV (al.b&#233;r.ta) 
1
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
Figure 10.1 The relative sonority of a number of the sounds of English.a a e e I u n m z v s d t k i lSonority
&#242;
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Alternations and derivations II</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec06/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>kubiga: luti &#8216;to hit with a stick&#8217;
kubiga: ngomi &#8216;to strike a drum&#8217;
kubiga rasa:si &#8216;to pull the trigger of a gun&#8217; 
kubiga $khe$gele &#8216;to ring a bell&#8217; 
&#8226;	analysis 
Word-final lengthening is word-level rule while pre-antepenultimate shortening is 
phrasal rule; requires phrase-final shortening (no length contrast here) 
Word level 
[kubiga] [ngomi] [rasa:si] [ku-re:bel-an-a] 
kubiga: ngomi: rasa:si: ku-re:bel-an-a: final lengthening 
Phrase level 
[kubiga: ngomi:] [kubiga: rasa:si:] [ku-re:bel-an-a:] 
-------------- kubiga rasa:si: ku-rebel-an-a: pre-antepenult shorten 
kubiga: ngomi kubiga rasa:si ku-rebel-an-a phrase-final shortening 
another paradigm 
nu:mba &#8216;house&#8217; sandu:xu &#8216;box&#8217; 
numba: nkulu &#8216;a big house&#8217; sanduxu: nzito &#8216;heavy box&#8217; 
[4] affixal allomorphy 
&#8226;	two (or more) shapes of an affix that cannot be related by a general rule; but the 
morpheme alternants are distributed according to natural phonological contexts 
English a ) an
an apple a car a well a use
an idiot a sin a yard a horse
cf. in America in Canada in Wellsley in Europe 
&#8226;	an appears before a vowel and a is the default (elsewhere) form 
Korean subject marker -ka ) -i, object marker lil ) il
noun son cip sul kho tali pata
nomin. son-i cip-i sul-i kho-ka tali-ka pata-ka
4
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	the depalatalization is inherited from the singular form by letting the rule of
depalatalization apply before the plural suffix is added
cycle-1 [desden'	 [desden' -ar] ]
des.de.n' des.den'
 ar syllabification 
-------------des.den coda depalatalization 
cycle-2	 des.den-es add plural suffix
des.de.nes (re)syllabify
&#8226;	In this example the cyclic suffixes of the plural are added to an independent word (the 
singular) while the non-cyclic suffixes are added to the verb stem, which is not an 
independent word; the same was true of the Italian example with clitic pronouns 
[4] syntax and a cycle 
&#8226;	In Chimwini (Bantu, Kisseberth &amp; Abasheikh 1974) vowel length is contrastive 
x-te:k-a &#8216;to load&#8217; x-tek-a &#8216;to fetch&#8217; 
x-ku:l-a &#8216;to extract&#8217; x-kul-a &#8216;to grow&#8217; 
ku-ba:ram-a &#8216;to talk&#8217; ku-balam-a &#8216;to promise&#8217; 
&#8226;	But long vowels are only preserved in a three-syllable window at the right edge of a 
word
ku-re:b-a &#8216;to stop&#8217;
ku-re:b-el-a &#8216;to stop for&#8217;
ku-reb-el-an-a &#8216;to stop for one another&#8217;
j(	 &#8216;jewel&#8217; x-sa:meh-a &#8216;to forgive&#8217; o:hari 
j( x-sameh-an-a &#8216;to forgive one another&#8217; ohari-je &#8216;her jewel&#8217; 
&#8226;	When words are combined into sentences two additional vowel length changes occur 
word-final vowel is lengthened 
ba &#8216;by&#8217; ba: noka &#8216;by a snake&#8217; 
kama &#8216;like&#8217; kama: mphaka &#8216;like a cat&#8217; 
kolko &#8216;than&#8217; kolko: mi &#8216;than me&#8217; 
the three-syllable window for long-vowels is actually over a syntactic phrase 
kubiga	&#8216;to hit&#8217; 
3
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>accus.	son-il cip-il sul-il kho-lil tali-lil pata-lil
'hand' 'house' 'wine' 'nose' 'bridge' 'sea'
&#8226; -i appears after a consonant and -ka after a vowel
&#8226; -il appears after a consonant and -lil after a vowel
&#8226;	choice of affixal shape promotes optimal CV syllable structure: avoid consonant clusters 
and vowel sequences (hiatus); 
[5] Lexical classes: rule applies only to a synchronically arbitrary class of lexical items 
English strong verbs 
&#8226;	default is -ed (weak verbs) with phonologically determined variants
want-id, comput-id, attribut-id
else: surfac-t, beep-t, drag-d,
&#8226;	strong verbs (c. 200) 
&#8226;	monosyllabic, Germanic origin 
&#8226;	some suffix &#8211;t: sleep, slep-t; leave, lef-t; 
&#8226;	most have root vowel change (ablaut)
lowering: sit-sat, ring-rang, swim-swam, eat-ate, choose-chose
backing: dig-dug, win-won, grind-ground, tear-tore
words move from strong to weak: shit, shat ) shitted; fly, flew ) flied out (baseball)
[6] Lexical strata: Japanese (Ito &amp; Mester 1995, 2003) 
&#8226;	Japanese vocabulary drawn from four different sources; each has dedicated rules or constraints 
&#8226;	Yamato (native) 
Rendaku (compound voicing) 
yu 'hot water' de-ru 'leave' hito 'person' hana &#8216;flower&#8217; 
toofu 'tofu' kuti 'mouth' hito-bito 'people' sono &#8216;garden&#8217; 
yu-doofu 'boiled toofu' de-guti 'exit' hana-zono 
&#8226;	Sino-Japanese (cf. English Latinate) 
All items underlyingly one syllable maximal size
Yamato Sino Mandarin
oto on yin &#8216;sound&#8217;
mitu san san &#8216;three&#8217;
gin yin &#8216;silver&#8217;
dai da &#8216;big&#8217;
in general S-J items resist redaku
koo-soku &#8216;high speed&#8217;
kooka keesatu &#8216;national police&#8217;
5
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>ri'pet-ere 'to repeat&#8217; maci'n-are 'to grind'
ri'pet -i 'you sg. repeat&#8217; 'macin-i 'you sg. grind'
ripe't-iamo 'we work' maci'n-iamo 'we grind'
ri'pete &#8216;repeat!&#8217; 'macina 'grind'
ri'pete#lo &#8216;repeat it&#8217; 'macina#lo 'grind it'
ri'pete#me &#8216;repeat for me&#8217; 'macina#me 'grind (for) me'
ri'pete#me#lo &#8216;repeat it for me&#8217; 'macina#me#lo 'grind it for me''
&#8226;	stress appears in a three-syllable window at the right edge of the word that excludes 
pronominal (clitic) pronoun suffixes 
&#8226;	stems are divided into those that stress the final syllable (paroxytone) and the prefinal 
syllable (paroxytone) 
&#8226;	if the stress of the latter class falls outside the three-syllable window, a default
penultimate stress is assigned
&#8226;	pronoun suffixes are more loosely attached to the stem and may appear before the verb 
in finite (tensed) clauses; inflectional suffixes like the infinitive and subject marking ones 
are tightly bound to the verb stem 
&#8226;	in some dialects (e.g. Neapolitan) the pronominal suffixes are counted as part of the 
stress domain 
[3] Rule applies in a cycle 
&#8226;	cycle: sensitive to inner structure before outer affixes added 
&#8226;	Spanish depalatalization of "ll" and n' (Harris 1982) 
bello 'beautiful' doncella 'lass' ella 'she'
beldad 'beauty' doncel 'lad' el 'he'
ll -&gt; l in coda of syllable 
doncel 'lad'
doncel-es pl. syllable parse is [don.ce.les]
a	 -ar don' 'lady' desden' 'to disdain' 
don 'sir' desden 'disdain' noun 
desden-es pl. (cf. desden''you disdain subj.) -es 
&#8226; the nasal of the plural desden-es is in the syllable onset and hence the wrong context for 
depalatalization 
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Alternations 2: Sensitivity to Morphological and Lexical Structure 
[1] in the examples discussed so far a rule's application is determined by neighboring sounds or 
its position at the beginning or end of the word or syllable. But in many cases phonological rules 
are sensitive to the morphological or lexical structure of the word. We survey some common 
types here. 
[2] Rule applies at a boundary between two morphemes 
Tangale (Chadic N. Nigeria) vowel elision 
possessive suffix
t!:"e 'horse' t!:"-d# 'her horse'
ta$a 'cow' ta$-wu 'their cow'
la$#r# 'donkey la$#r-g! 'your pl. donkey'
l%pra 'needle' l%p!r-"% 'your needle'
wudo &#8216;tooth&#8217; wud-no &#8216;my tooth&#8217;
associative
law# 'child' law Lak! 'Laku's child'
ara 'soup' ar k#nd# 'peanut soup'
verb
p#n-&amp; 'know' p#n-g# 'knew'
p#n-&amp; 'knows' p#n-d# 'knows her'
p#n-g# 'knew' p#n-!d-g# 'knew her'
timl-e 'hypnotize'	timul-go 'hypnotized'
timl-un-go 'hypnotized me'
&#8226;	Tangale has vowel harmony for [ATR]; suffixes agree with root 
&#8226;	Vowel elision: V -&gt; &#248; / _____ ] [segment] (delete the final vowel of a morpheme 
when followed by another sound) 
&#8226;	Epenthesis: &#248; -&gt; u / C __ C C (right-to-left to get minimal change and a valid CVC 
syllable parse 
3. rule applies within a domain delimited by certain affixes 
Italian stress and clitic pronouns 
1
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>&#8226; Mimetic (onomatopoeia) 
Canonical shape of two moras: 
kira-kira 'shining' poko-poko &#8216;hitting&#8217; koro-koro &#8216;rolling&#8217; *koro-goro 
&#8226;	Foreign (Western) loans 
fesutibaru 'festival' furutaimu 'full time' paati 'party' webbu 'web' 
kyampasu &#8216;campus&#8217; tento &#8216;tent&#8217; nama-kurimu &#8216;fresh cream&#8217; 
cf. nama-gome &#8216;uncooked rice&#8217; kome &#8216;rice&#8217; 
&#8226; Phonological constraints 
Yamato *p *NT *DD
Sino-Japanese *p _____ *DD
Mimetic _____ *NT *DD
Foreign ______ _____ _____
nihon ) nippon &#8216;Japan&#8217; present-future mi-ru nom-u 
yahari ) yappari &#8216;after all&#8217; past mi-ta non-da 
&#8216;see&#8217; &#8216;drink&#8217; 
webbu &#8216;web&#8217; 
6
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Phonetics I: acoustics of vowels, using Praat</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec08/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Phonetics-1 
1. sound results from pressure fluctuations in a medium which displace the ear drum to 
stimulate the auditory nerve 
&#8226;	air is normal medium for speech 
&#8226;	air is elastic (cf. bicyle pump, plastic bag, etc.) 
&#8226;	pressure fluctuations originate at a source that produce a wave in the medium that 
carries energy to the ear 
&#8226;	air particles do not move from the source to the ear--rather the energy is passed through 
the medium 
&#8226; oscillogram/waveform is a graphic (visual) representation of pressure fluctuations 
2. sound waves 
&#8226;	periodic: wave repeats at regular intervals (figure 2.1, page 3) 
&#8226;	frequency is number of repetitions per unit of time: f=1/T Hertz (Hz) is 1 cycle per 
second 
&#8226;	the perceived pitch of a sound depends on its frequency; at frequencies above 1,000 Hz 
equal increases in frequency are not  perceived as equal increases in pitch 1,000 &#8211; 2,000 
Hz ! 2,000 &#8211; 4,000 Hz 
&#8226;	speed of sound in air is c. 340 m/s; wavelength is speed (m/s) * period (T) 
&#8226;	amplitude is maximal displacement of wave above zero line and corresponds to 
intensity of sound; relation between amplitude and perceived intensity is not linear; the 
relative difference in perceived intensity is approximated by a logrithmic scale whose 
unit is the decibel (dB); change of 1 dB is JND; 5 dB is about twice intensity 
["]=13 dB, [s] = 17 dB, [i]=34 dB, [#]=40 dB 
&#8226;	aperiodic sounds have waves that do not repeat 
&#8226;	fricatives like [s] are aperiodic while vowels like [a] are periodic 
3. spectrum 
&#8226;	any complex wave can be analyzed as the combination of sinusoidal waves of different 
frequencies and intensities (Fourier Theorem); see fig. 4.1 
&#8226;	for a periodic sound like a vowel these are the fundamental frequency F0 and multiples 
of the fundamental known as harmonics or overtones 
&#8226;	the quality of a periodic sound depends on the relative amplitude of the harmonics 
&#8226;	these can be displayed in a power spectrum (fig. 4.2) 
&#8226;	examples from Ladefoged 1962: fig. 7.4 of vowel [$] 
&#8226;	note different frequencies but same overall shape of spectrum 
&#8226;	differences in vowel quality result from different vocal tract shapes 
1
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>a"
a'
b'b"0 -01 -02 -03Air pressure Air pressureTime in seconds
Fig. 2.1 Two sounds, one with twice the amplitude of the other.
3
100 200
Frequency in cps.
Fig. 4.2 The spectrum of the complex wave illustrated in fig. 4.1. 300Amplitude of component waveImage by MIT OpenCourseWare.
0 -01 -02
Time in seconds100 cps.
100 cps.
+
200 cps.
+
300 cps.
Complex
wave
Fig. 4.1 A combination of 100 cps., 200 cps. and 300 cps waves forming a
complex wave.200 cps.
300 cps.-c
x y
d
-g-ea
fbWave Analysis
Amplitude of component wave
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	they give rise to different spectra (e.g. figure 7.5) 
&#8226;	the perceived quality of a vowel can be adequately described by the relative location of 
the peaks in the lower part of the spectrum, termed formants 
&#8226;	most vowels are adequately characterized by the first three formants: F1, F2, F3 
&#8226;	fig. 8.2 (CIP) shows formants for eight AE vowels 
&#8226;	F1 primarily reflects vowel height in invrse fashion: greater F1 reflects lower vowel 
&#8226;	F2 reflects vowel backness as well as lip rounding: lower F2 reflects greater backing or 
rounding 
&#8226;	the science of acoustic phonetics models speech as the behavior of waves in various 
types of tubes (Ken Stevens 1998 Acoustic Phonetics, 6.541) 
4. spectrogram 
&#8226;	a graphic display of the components of a sound (e.g. figure 8.3) 
&#8226;	x-axis is time 
&#8226;	y-axis is frequency 
&#8226;	intensity of sound at a given frequency is indicated by gray scale: darker the wave the 
greater the intensity. 
&#8226;	narrow-band spectrograms give better resolution in the frequency dimension; striations 
are horizontal 
&#8226;	wide-band spectrograms give better resolution in the time dimension; striations are 
vertical 
&#8226;	formant chart 
o	origin in NE corner 
o	Bark scale* 
o	 lower part of spectrum has much more energy for vowel sounds 
* The scale ranges from 1 to 24 and corresponds to the first 24 critical bands of hearing 
(in Hz): 20, 100, 200,300,400,510, 630, 770, 920, 1 0801270, 1480, 1720, 2000, 2320,
2700, 3150 , 3700 , 4400 , 5300 , 6400 , 7700 , 9500 , 12000, 15500 . 
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
2890
2250
280400192025602490
1770
550 690166024903000
2000
1000
Hz
[ i ] [ I ]
FIGURE 8.2: The Frequencies of the First Three Formants in 
Eight American English V owel.3000
2000
1000
Hz2540 2540
880
5901100
7102380
2250
870
3101030
450
[ u ] [ A ][ Q ] 
[ &#141;  ][ W ]
4000
30002000
1000
Hz
4000
3000
2000
1000
Hz
400 ms 400 400 0 0 0 0 300[ i ] [ I ] [   ] [   ]
[    ]c[    ]u [    ] [   ]
Figure 8.3 A spectrogram of the words heed, hid, head, had, hod, hawed, hood, who'd as
spoken by a male speaker of American English. The locations of the first three formants are
shown by arrows.Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>2,000
1,000
Fig. 7.9 A spectrogram showing the frequencies of the first and second
formants of some of the English vowels as pronounced by the author.Heed Hid Head Had Hod Hawed Hood Who'd
5
1,000 2,000 3,000
1,000 2,000 3,000
1,000 2,000 3,000
1,000 2,000 3,0001,000 2,000 3,000
1,000 2,000 3,000
1,000 2,000 3,000
1,000 2,000 3,000Heed
Hid
Head
HadWho'dHoodHawedHodElements of Acoustic Phonetics The Production of Speech
Fig. 7.5 The positions of the vocal organs (based on data from X-ray photographs of the author) and the spectra
of the vowel sounds in the middle of the words heed, hid, head, had, hod, hawed, hood, who'd in the author's speech. 
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>0 500 1,000 1,500
0 500 1,000 1,500
0 500 1,000 1,500
0 500 1,000 1,500
0 .01
Time in seconds.02Elements of Acoustic Phonetics
a)
b)
c)
d)
Fig. 7.4 Wave forms and spectra for a synthetic vowel similar to the vowel [  ] as in
caught. (a) Effect of a single pulse on the resonating system; (b) pulses recurring at therate of 100 a second; (c) 120 pulses a second; (d) 150 pulses a second.
4
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7
3000 2500 2000 1500 1000 500
200
300
400
500
600
700
800
900
1000
1100
1200
1300
1400
1500 Hz
Figure 8.6 A blank formant chart for showing the relation between vowels. Using the information in 
Figures 8.3 and 8.4, plot the frequency of the first formant on the ordinate (the vertical axis) and the second formant on the abscissa (the horizontal axis).
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.8007006005004003002001000 1500 2000 2500
Figure 8.5 A formant chart showing the frequency of the first formant
on the ordinate (the vertical axis) plotted against the second formanton the abscissa (the horizontal axis) for eight American Englishvowels. The scales are marked in Hz, arranged at Bark scale intervals.i
uWI
e
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Constraints</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec07/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>[6] Phonotactic constraints: restrictions on the possible shapes of words 
&#8226;	Judgements of wellformedness (Halle 1962)
brick occurring
blick nonoccurring but possible
bnick nonoccurring but impossible
&#8226;	gradient judgments among nonoccurring 
bnick &gt; bdick, bzick 
&#8226;	is this judgment derived from exisiting lexicon or does it involve some UG prior/bias? 
&#8226;	Albright (2008) 
&#61656;30 monosyllabic nonwords 
&#61656;subjects rate on 7 point scale (&#8220;impossible&#8230;.fine English word&#8221;) 
&#61656;word pronouced to make sure proper stimulus elicited 
&#61656;a bias for rising sonority clusters obtained: bw &gt; bn &gt; bz,bd 
&#61656;one model for judging similarity to existing words (Generalized Neighborhood 
model) fails to distinguish among the unattested clusters 
&#61656;AA proposes model that invokes natural feature classes: bw and bn judged better 
than bz, bd because they fall under a generalized bl, br = [-contin]+[+sonorant] 
schema 
&#61656;But they also fall under [-contin]+[+consonantal] 
&#61656;Why is [-contin]+[+sonorant] better? Possible answer: greater perceptibility of 
stop cues 
[7] Constraints in Loanword Adaptation 
Mandarin Chinese (Hsieh et al 2009) 
&#8226;	CVC syllable but coda restricted to [w,j,n,!] 
&#8226;	[a] and [&amp;] in complementary distribution 
&#8226;	[an] and [&amp;!] but *[&amp;n], *[a!] 
&#8226;	English loans contain all four combinations of {&#230;,&amp;}+{n,!} 
&#8226;	In case of conflict what decides? 
English Mandarin 
[&#230;n] [an] anchovy an.chou 31/36 
[&amp;!] [&amp;!] Congo g&amp;ng.uo 5/7 
[&amp;n] [&amp;!] monsoon m&amp;!.xun 24/24 
[&#230;!] [an] tank tan.e 9/13 
5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	Blocks apocope rule 
mayar mayara-n mayara-" rainbow 
mela mela-n mela-" sea 
wi#e wi#e-n wi#e-" interior 
&#8226;	Triggers augmentation 
yaka yak-in yak-u" fish 
&#8226;	Grammar with simplest rules should allow the following derivations 
/ wi#e / /yak/
wi# ------- V -&gt; &#8709; / ___ #
wi#a yaka &#8709; -&gt; a / &#963; ___ #
&#8226;	Some notion of minimal departure from input to satisfy the constraint seems necessary 
&#8226;	Let asterisk denote a change, check denote no change 
/ wi#e/ *[&#963;]PW Apocope Epenthesis 
wi#e &#8730; &#8730; &#8730;
wi# * * &#8730;
wi#a &#8730; * *
/ yak /
yak * &#8730; &#8730;
yaka &#8730; &#8730; *
&#8226;	In the first case wi&#648;e has the fewest violations and so is best 
&#8226;	In the second case yak and yaka tie so we must prioritize the constraints so that *[&#963;]PW 
dominates Epenthesis or assigns a higher penalty 
&#8226;	Rendaku 
/siroto-kanKae/ Rendaku Lyman&#8217;s Law *NT
sirooto-kangae * &#8730; &#8730;
sirooto-gangae &#8730; * &#8730;
sirooto-gankae &#8730; &#8730; *
&#8226;	In order for sirooto-kangae to be the output Lyman&#8217;s Law and *NT must have higher priority 
(greater weight) than Rendaku 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Phonological Constraints 
So far we have introduced just one mechanism to express phonological generalizations: the rewrite 
rule in which a sound or sound sequence is altered on the basis of the phonological, morphological, 
or syntactic context. But there are many generalizations that are part of a speaker&#8217;s knowledge of 
language which are more properly expressed by constraints that state static generalizations over the 
lexicon, the surface output, or both. These constraints may trigger or block the application of 
phonological rules. 
[1]. Japanese native Yamato and Sino-Japanese vocabulary 
kak-u kusa sato
&#8216;write&#8217; &#8216;grass&#8217; &#8216;village&#8217;
kago kaze kado
&#8216;basket&#8217; &#8216;wind&#8217; &#8216;corner&#8217;
gake das-u buta
&#8216;cliff&#8217; &#8216;take out&#8217; &#8216;pig&#8217;
*gVg *dVz *bVd 
&#8226;	Lyman&#8217;s Law: two (or more) voiced obstruents are not permitted in a single stem 
&#8226;	A rewrite rule is not feasible since there is no unique output for a given input: a /gVg/ input could be 
transformed into a variety of outputs: kVg, gVk, kVk, gV!, 
&#8226;	Thus, we need a constraint on morpheme shape 
*[-sonorant, +voice] &#8230;. [-sonorant, +voice] 
[2] *NT 
&#8226;	The contrast between voiced and voiceless obstruents is suspended after a nasal in Yamato 
&#8226;	Only voiced obstruents are found
tombo kangae
&#8216;dragonfly&#8217; &#8216;thought&#8217;
&#8226;	Alternations where an underlying voiceless stop is voiced after a nasal 
1
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>striking contrasts 
&#61656;fluke &gt; fuluk vs. place &gt; pheisi and blonde &gt; pilan vs. blender &gt; phenta 
7 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	Conflict resolved in favor of phonetically more salient vowel over phonologically 
contrastive nasal place feature 
[8] Cantonese loans from English (Silverman 1993) 
6 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>[5] another motivation for constraints is that many rules can be interpreted as alternative repairs to 
the same illicit sound sequence or structural configuration 
&#8226; Cross-linguistic typology (McCarthy 2002) 
*NC$ avoid a nasal plus voiceless consonant sequence 
i. denasalization 
Toba Batak (Hayes 1986) 
/holom sa%tik/ &gt; holop sa%tik &#8216;somewhat dark&#8217; 
ii. nasal deletion 
Standard Malay Kelantan Malay 
pintu pitu &#8216;door&#8217; 
hampas hapas &#8216;husk&#8217; 
iii. voicing consonant
Japanese
Nonpast past
tabe-ru tabe-ta &#8216;eat&#8217;
sin-u sin-da &#8216;die&#8217;
yom-u yon-da &#8216;read&#8217;
typology 
NC$ [+nasal] -&gt; [-nasal] N -&gt; &#216; [+voice] -&gt; [-voice] 
Toba-Batak - + - -
K-Malay - - + -
Jap - - - + 
English + - - -
&#8226; In same language (aka &#8220;conspiracies&#8221;) 
Ilokano hiatus resolution (Hayes &amp; Abbad 1989) 
*V V 
High vowel devocalizes to glide 
Low vowel inserts a glottal stop since low vowel glide not possible 
Infin focus
gata! gata!-en &#8216;buy&#8217;
sa!it sa!it-en &#8216;cry&#8217;
babawi babawj-en &#8216;regret&#8217;
masahe masahj-en &#8216;massage&#8217;
maneho manehw-an &#8216;drive&#8217;
basa basa-?en &#8216;read&#8217;
saka pag-saka-?en &#8216;walk barefoot&#8217;
4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>tabe-ru sin-u nom-u
tabe-ta sin-da non-da
&#8216;eat&#8217; &#8216;die&#8217; &#8216;drink&#8217;
&#8226;	It appears that the rule of post-nasal voicing applies to satisfy the *NT constraint 
[3] redaku (sequential voicing) and Lyman&#8217;s Law 
&#8226;	The initial obstruent of the second (head) element in a compound is voiced if Yamato (cf. English 
mark-s-man, German Liebe-s-brief, etc) 
se &#8216;back&#8217; neko-ze &#8216;hunchback 
kaki &#8216;writing&#8217; yoko-gake &#8216;horizontal writing&#8217; 
tosi &#8216;year&#8217; hebi-dosi &#8216;snake year&#8217; 
sono &#8216;garden&#8217; hana-zono &#8216;flower garden&#8217; 
&#8226;	Lyman&#8217;s Law blocks rendaku voicing 
kado &#8216;corner&#8217; hito-kado &#8216;first point&#8217; 
sabi &#8216;rust&#8217; aka-sabi &#8216;red rust&#8217; 
tubo &#8216;jar&#8217; tya-tubo &#8216;tea jar&#8217; 
kurage &#8216;jellyfish&#8217; denki-kurage &#8216;electric jelleyfish&#8217; 
tokage &#8216;lizard&#8217; ao-tokage &#8216;green lizard&#8217; 
&#8226;	Redundant voicing after a nasal also blocks Lyman&#8217;s Law 
&#8226;	If voicing after a nasal assigned by a rule then Lyman&#8217;s Law holds over the output of that rule 
kangae &#8216;thought&#8217; sirooto-kangae &#8216;layman&#8217;s idea&#8217; 
&#8226;	Conclusion: rules controlling alternations can be blocked (e.g. rendaku) or activated (post-nasal 
voicing) in order to conform to a constraint (Lyman&#8217;s Law, *NT) that governs &#8220;static&#8221; generalizations 
of the lexicon 
&#8226;	Outstanding research problem: how do we formalize the relation between rules and constraints? 
[4] Lardil 
&#8226;	Minimal word requirement: all words at least two syllables in length 
* PW (Prosodic Word) 
|
&#963; (syllable)
2
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Sociolinguistic variables</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>9 F1F2
hN h Other O
iy
ey
i
e
ohowuw
h
th
sht
sk
kt
t
t
ktptdttbdgrthd
stptrdg g
dn sndzndn
k
o
Figure 4.9b V owel system of Chris Adamo, 13, Detroit8007006005004003002000 1800 1600 1400 1200 1000 800 600
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.
70
60
50
40
30
20
10
0
o oh e ^ QPercent advanced tokensMale Jocks Male Burnouts
Female Jocks Female Burnouts
Figure 13.7 Relations of gender and social class in the development
of the Northern Cities Shift in Belten High (from Eckert 1989b)
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	Jocks: middle class values, achieve goals by conforming to normative institutions
established by adults 
&#8226;	Burnouts: resist adult authority, achieve goals by escape from adult control, relyon local resources 
&#8226;	For a number of sound changes in the NCS burnouts are in lead: eg. Extremebacking of wedge (bus -&gt; boss): 
Jocks Burnouts
.43 .59
&#8226;	but social class gives way to gender: 13.7 
9. Labov sees gender as most important social determinant in sound change 
Finding 1 : For stable variables women show a lower rate of stigmatized variants and a
higher rate of prestige variants 
&#8226; -ing &#8776; -in; former used by women more in New England, NYC, Norwich,Australia, Ottawa, &#8230; 
&#8226;	stop and affricate forms of English interdentals used less by women: NYC, NorthCarolina, Belfast 
&#8226;	Quebecois Fr, Chilean Sp., Taiwanese studies report similar findings 
Finding 2 : in changes from above women adopt the prestige form more than men 
&#8226;	rhotic NYC, QF retraction of /a/ in &#8211;ation 
Finding 3 : For changes from below (the proto-typical, unconscious sound change)
woman are typically in the lead 
&#8226;	Gauchet (1905) Charmey (Sw Fr) women one generation ahead of men in
diphthongization of a: and e:
&#8226;	NYC raising of ah and oh 
&#8226;	NCS early changes of &#230;h, o, and oh (Wolfram, Eckert) 
Speculation: 
&#8226;	young women and female adolescents more fashion/style-conscious than males 
&#8226;	extending a linguistic variable is comparable to other fashion statements 
&#8226;	they spend more time with young children, who set their variables accordingly
 ------- -
4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>8 9008508007507006506005505004504002600 2400 2200 2000 1800 1600 1400 1200 1000 800F2
F1iyC
awhNi
oeyF
oahr
ayVoo^oiyF
eyCuwFuwC
owFowC
ay0uohr
P &lt; .10 P &lt; .05
P &lt; .01 P &lt; .001ohoyo
e
Figure 3.6  Movement of Philadelphia vowels in apparent time. O = mean values for 116 speakers
in the neighborhood study. Vectors connect values for groups 25 years older and younger than the
mean. ___F = free vowel; ___C = checked vowels; ___0 = before voiceless finals
600 800 1000 1200 1400 1600 1800 2000 2200 2400
F1F2
300
400
500
600
700
800
900
1000iy
i
eyuw
ow
oy
oh
ahblk
chk
b
bl kk
kl-
n-
tnkl-dngg
g
e
ndchldndnd
ns s
st
sklffstlfl
fl
l
l
to hhN h Other O
Figure 4.9a V owel system of James Adamo, 55, DetroitImage by MIT OpenCourseWare.
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	But Queen&#8217;s Annual Christmas Message: 1950&#8217;s to present (Harrington (2006):
some effect of changes in RP (raising of lax I in kit, happy)
6. Classification of sound changes:
a. shift: p -&gt; h in Japanese; V -&gt; V: / ____ [+voiced]
b. mergers: a and o merge (father  and hot); t &amp; d merge to flap, etc.
Herzog&#8217;s Principle: at a dialect boundary mergers expand: whale  vs. wail 
Garde: mergers are irreversible by normal sound change (from below)A sound change from above may lead to hypercorrection: generalization of
 change to to novel nonetymological lexical items
intrusive [r] of Eastern Mass is commonly interpreted as reflex of
 hypercorrection: the spa[r] is  (spa or spar) 
border Southern 
Hock (1986:428)	 soda sody 
opera opry
Missoura Missouri 
c. split: umlaut in German  (original phonetic context lost)
d. chain shifts: one shift elicits another related one 
drag chain: one sound moves into the space formerly occupied by another:
English Great Vowel Shift where [i:] diphthongizes and centralizes to [aj], [e:] shifts to former position of [i:] 
push chain: one sound encroaches on another, which shifts to remain distinct
(more difficult to document) 
7. Sound (more generally linguistic) change 
&#8226;	some variation is stable (e.g. t/d deletion of wes(t) documented since 16th century) 
&#8226;	 while other kinds are dynamic with the gradual replacement of one category byanother over time as in nonrhotic &gt; rhotic. 
&#8226;	mystery: how does the child discern which variation is stable and which is to be carried
forward (assuming that children are the primary vehicles of change from below)? 
8. Two kinds of sound change: 
&#8226;	changes from above: introduced by dominant social class, often with full public
awareness, show up in careful speech: NYC rhoticization
&#8226;	changes from below: initially below level of consciousness, typically lower or
middle classes initiate: Northern Cities Shift
&#8226;	NCS: [&#230;] raises and tenses, [a] of cot fronts, [_] lowers and unrounds; [_] backs
encroaching on [_] which backs and rounds
&#8226;	more detailed studies like Eckert's show group identification rather than social
class per se is better predictor (cf. solidarity of values, identification (Sturtevant
1947)
8. Belten High (Eckert) 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>7 468
35
Fig. 2.4 Stratification of (r) by occupational groups in Macy's.
Shaded area = % all (r-1); unshaded area = % some (r-1); % no
(r-1) not shown. N = total number of cases.SalesFloorwalkers
N = 13 105 7Stockboys
1418
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.
160017001800190020002100220023002400
8-14 15-19 20-29 30-39 40-49 50-59 60-69 70-79Ageaw
Figure 3.7 Distribution of F2 (aw) in apparent time by group means, simple regression and
multiple regressionF2Group means
Regression on age
Multiple regression
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	founder and chief exponent of quantitative sociolinguistics 
&#8226;	student of Uriel Weinreich (Columbia, U Penn since 1970) 
&#8226;	large scale quantitative analysis of the vernacular speech: NYC, Philadelphia,
other American dialects 
&#8226;	editor Language Variation and Change 
&#8226;	director of Dialect Survey of North America (2005) 
&#8226;	author of Principles of Linguistic Change  I, II, III 
3. Sociolinguistic interview; stylistic variants 
&#8226;	Minimal pair 
&#8226;	Word list 
&#8226;	Reading style 
&#8226;	Careful speech 
&#8226;	Casual (non-monitored) speech 
Figure 4.2 
&#8226;	NYC nonrhotic 
&#8226;	Rhotic pronunciation restored as prestige norm after WWII (change from above) 
&#8226;	81 adults of Lower East Side (1962) 
&#8226;	systematic correlation with attention to speech and social class 
&#8226;	lower middle class increases in more formal setting: linguistic insecurity 
4. Labov&#8217;s Department Store Study (1966) fig. 4.3, 4.4 
&#8226;	264 individuals encountered in two afternoons in 1964; anonymous 
&#8226;	Saks, Macy&#8217;s, S. Klein 
&#8226;	Floorwalker, sales clerk, sweeper 
&#8226;	Item from 4th Fl. WL: Where&#8217;s X(e.g. shoes)? [fourth floor]  Excuse me. [Fourth 
Floor] 
Results 
&#8226;	Stratification by store (social class): 4.3 
&#8226;	Stratification by phonological context (preconsonantal vs. word-final) 
&#8226;	Stratification by style (emphatic speech more rhotic) 
&#8226;	Stratification by occupation (2.4 in p. 56) 
&#8226;	Stratification by age 
5. Study replicated by Fowler (1986) 
&#8226;	Same results but overall more rhotic (sound change in progress) 
&#8226;	The next generation increments the change 
&#8226;	Alternative explanation of age grading is not plausible 
&#8226;	Age grading: speakers become more conservative as they get older 
&#8226;	Philadelphia [aw] fronting and raising also shows this [3.7, 3.6] 
&#8226;	Observations of different generations in same family: 4.9 a,b: raising of &#230; vowel 
&#8226;	Recordings of one speaker at two separated points: Jenny Rosetti (Philadelphia) at
ages 68 (1973) and 85 (1990): vowel system largely stable 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Sociolinguistics and Sound Change 
0. Gender differences in spoken language 
Japanese 
&#8226;	Lexical items: boku  (masc. first person) vs. watakushi (neutral) 
&#8226;	Grammatical particles: da yo (masc. blunt) wa yo (fem. Soft) 
&#8226; Voice quality: breathy voice (fem.) 
Sapir (Male and female speech forms in Yana 1928) 
&#8226;	Most words have two forms: male and female 
&#8226;	Female derived by reduction (devoicing) of final syllable 
&#8226; Male used when male addresses another male, female otherwise 
Vaupe_s region of Amazon (Jackson 1983) 
&#8226;	Eastern Tukanoan 
&#8226;	Linguistic exogamy: man must take wife who speaks a different language 
&#8226;	Individual&#8217;s identity marked by language of father 
&#8226;	When woman moves to husband&#8217;s community she continues to use her father&#8217;s language
while husband (and children) use father&#8217;s language
&#8226;	Extensive multilingualism: Barasana, Desano, Tatuyo, &#8230;. 
1. Quantitative sociolinguistics (Labov) 
&#8226;	major finding: ordered heterogeneity: a particular grammatical variable (e.g. rhotic vs.
nonrhotic) increases/decreases monotonically along some social dimension 
&#8226;	variation by style (formal---casual conversation) 
&#8226;	variation by age (may reflect sound change in progress) 
&#8226;	variation by social class and gender 
&#8226;	variation: stable vs. changing 
&#8226;	implication: Structural-Generative abstraction of ideal speaker in homogeneous speechcommunity overlooks an important aspect of linguistic competence: people alter theirgrammatical output in response to different social contexts and to signal their identity or
affiliation to particular social groups 
2. William Labov (b. 1927, BA Harvard '48, Ph.D. Columbia '64) 
1
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
% constricted [r]
Figure 4.2 Social stratification of (r) in New York CityCasual
speechCareful
speechReadingstyleWordlistsMinimalpairs01020304050607080901006-8: Lower middleSocial Class
9: Upper middle (20-29 yrs)
9: Upper middle
3-5: Working class
0-2: Lower class
0
Saks 1962 Macy's 1962
Store
Figure 4.3a Overall stratification of (r), 1962S. Klein 19620 &lt; [r] &lt; 100%1962% using constricted [r]20406080
0
Saks 1986 Macy's 1986
Store
Figure 4.3b Overall stratification of (r), 1986May's 19861986% using constricted [r]20406080
[r] 100%
80
60
40
20
0
fourth floor FOURTH FLOOR
80
60
40
20
0
fourth floor FOURTH FLOOR1962
1986% using all [r] % using all [r]Saks
Macys
S. Klein
FIGURE 4.4: Differentiation of (r) by style in 1962 and 1986Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Syllables II: sonority</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>4. differential location of epent hetic vowel in modern colloquial Arabic dialects (Ito 1986) 
Cairene:	 ?ul-t &#8216;I said&#8217; 
?ul-ti-lu/?ul-t-lu/ &#8216;I said to him&#8217; 
&#216; -&gt; i / CC __ C vs. left-to-right mapping to CVC template 
Iraqi:	 gil-t &#8216;I said&#8217; 
gil-it-la &#8216;I said to him&#8217; 
&#216; -&gt; i / C __ CC vs. right-to-left mapping to CVC template 
&#8226;	directional mapping accounts for four-consonant clusters
Cairene: ?ultil-ha 'I said to her' /?ult-l-ha/
Iraqi:	 giltil-ha'I said to her' /gilt-l-ha/ 
&#8226;	a colleague related an anecdot e concerning a lecture he attended by an Iraqi engineer 
who pronounced sixty as [sikisti] causing some confusion. 
&#8226;	Broselow (1982) observes that Egyptian learners of English tend to prounounc e Fred as 
[fired] while Iraqi's say [?ifre d]. 
5. Imdlawn Tashlhiyt Berber (SW Morocco) 
&#8226;	Fran&#597;ois Dell &amp; Moham med Elmedlaoui (1985, 1989, &#8230;) 
&#8226;	Influential in  developemnt of Optimality Theory (Prince &amp; Smolensky 1993, 2004) 
&#8226;	syllab ic nuclei span entire sonority h ierarch y 
&#8226;	CVC template with extra-templatic coronals at word edges 
&#8226;	vowel-initial sy llable only possible word-initially 
&#8226;	glides [w,y] and high vow els [i,u] are same phonemes and differ in syllable role: nucleus 
vs. margin (onset or coda) 
&#8226;	while any phoneme can be a nucleus, there is no ambiguity of syllabic parse 
yattuy 'it is high' ratk&#809;ti &#8216;she will remember&#8217; 
ikr&#809; 'he ploughed for you' bddl &#8216;exchange!&#8217; zawn &#809;
tr&#809;&#809; 'you locked' tzmt
 glt &#809; &#8216;it is stiflin g&#8217; 
tx&#809;&#809;t 'you stored' ildi zn &#8216;he pulled&#8217; 
tm&#809; &#809; 'you transformed' sxt ratlult &#8216;you will be born&#8217; 
tf&#809;tk&#809;t 'you sprained' 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	rewrite rules offer a general format to expres s phonol ogical general izations but any 
restrictions to limit the space of possib le gram mars must be imposed from the out side 
&#8226;	proposed alternative: replace rules by UG well-formedness constrain ts that directly state 
optimal (harmonic) structures 
&#8226;	constraints conflict and individual gram mars arise from priorit izing constraints (aka 
typology by ranking) 
&#8226;	two modes of input-output mapping entertained 
&#8226;	harmonic serialism: start with input and make a range of minimal changes (add/del ete a 
segment; change a feature valu e; impose a syllab ic parse; etc.) to generate a set of 
candidate out puts; select most optimal given the con straint ranking; resubmit output to 
make more changes; the successive rounds of modify-evaluate-modify-evaluate.. will 
event ually conver ge on a single structure to which no more changes can be made; it is 
defined as the output 
&#8226;	parallel alternative: one process of modification of input to gener ate a larger candidate 
set and just one round of evaluation that asse sses all candidates in parallel 
&#8226;	predicts &#8220;top-down, look-ahead&#8221; effect s where property const ructed later in derivat ion 
from a rule based perspective could influence the choice of an earlier stag e 
&#8226;	OT model explored for c. 20 years; received model of grammar but not without its c ritics 
and skeptics 
&#8226;	Parallel approach explored first; but fails to deal satisfactorally with opacity where 
corre ct surface out put form crucial ly depends on som e prior (intermediate) change 
8. brief exem plification with ITB (see Prince &amp; Sm olensky 2004: 11-19) 
&#8226;	Constraints 
&#61656; Onset: a syllable has a nonvocalic onset 
&#61656; H(armonic) Nucleus: a more sonorous nucleus is better than a less sonorous one 
&#8226;	Ranking: Onset &#187; Hnuc 
Tableau for input /haul-tn/ 
&#8226; a syllable whose nucleus is less sonorous than its onset is se lected because the competing 
parse that better satisfies Hnuc has been eliminated by the higher ranking constraint 
4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	this is a n example of a &#8220;top-down&#8221; effect from the perspective of the syllabification rules 
since the applicatio n of the nucleus projection must &#8220;lo ok ahead&#8221; to see if an  onset has 
been constructed to avoid a hiatus 
&#8226;	Dell and Elmedlaoui&#8217;s algorithm sidesteps this problem by combining the nucleus 
projection and onset creation rules into a single rule; while this &#8220;works&#8221;, Prince and 
Smolensky criticize it as being formally arbitrary; from a cross linguistic perspective, 
constraints on nuclei and onsets are d ifferent and one would want to separate them out 
as distinct statements in a gram mar 
&#8226;	If Hnuc  &#187; Onset the grammar will select ha.ul.tn parse with hiatus (non-optimal syllable 
sequence) but a m ore optimal nucleus; this would be the parse in languages like 
Japanese that freely tolerate hiatus 
9 serial syllabification for /txznt/ 
&#8226; tx(zN)t becomes input to second step 
10. parallel syllabification of /txznt/ 
5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Syllable-2 
1. sonority preference hierarchy for syllabic nuclei 
&#8226;	in most lan guages syllable nuclei are restricte d to vowels 
&#8226;	may be extended to consonants 
&#8226;	but follows sonority hierarchy: vowel &gt; glide &gt; liquid &gt; nasal &gt; obstruent 
V L N Ob nuclei 
Spani sh + - - -
Czech + + - -
German + + + -
Berber + + + +
Spani sh: abr-ir 'to open', aber.tura 'opening' &lt; /abr-tura/
Czech: pr&#809; za, but ohn-o, ohen 'fire' &lt; /ohn/; pad-l&#809;
 st 'finger', sl&#809; , pad-l-a 
German: Nebel [nebl&#809;  'fog'; handl-ung, handel -n [dl&#809; &#809; ], nebl-ig n]; haben [bm] 
Berber: tr&#809;&#809; '; txznt ' you stored' glt 'you locked &#809;&#809;
&#8226;	while a consonant (liquid) may be syllabic this option is g enerally taken only if a vowel 
is not available: cf. German [nebl&#809; &#809; ] but [nebli&#597;] not [nebli&#597;] 
2. analysis with the syllable-building rules 
/abr-tura/
 (ab)r(tu)(ra) initial p arse
 (ab)er(tu)(ra) epent hesis
 (a)(ber)(tu)(ra) reparsing
3. problems 
&#8226;	little evidence for earlier stage of (ab)er(tu)(ra) 
&#8226;	alternat ive of mapping to syllable template: combines epenthesis with syllabification on 
initial p arse with empty nuclear slo t fille d by a late r separate  rule 
&#8226;	directional mapping to [C C V C]: right to left correctly positions epent hetic vowel in Sp 
eslavo (c f. yugo -slavo) 
&#8226;	mapping is segment-driven matching phonem e to appropriate correspondi ng template slot 
&#8226;	restrictions on cod a and onset may be stated in t emplate: e.g. Tiberian H ebrew bars 
pharyngeal s from coda: /ya-&#643;mo:r/ -&gt; yi&#643;mo:r &#8216;he will guard&#8217; but /ya-&#661;bo:d/ -&gt; ya&#661;abo:d 
&#8216;he will work&#8217; with epenthesis and vowel copy as repair 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	odd-even position not sufficient 
disyllabic: ratlult /ra-t-lUl-t/ 'you will be born' 
trisyllabic: ratr&#809;t /ra-t-rgl-t/ 'you will lock' gl&#809;
6. Dell &amp; Elmedlaoui syllabification algorithm 
&#8226;	associat e a core (onset -nucleus) syllable with any sequence (Y)Z, where Z is a low vow el, 
high vocoid, a liquid, a nasal, a fricative, a stop 
&#8226;	looking for a sonority peak 
/t-IzrUal-In/ 'those from Tazrwalt'
t-Izr(w a)l-In low vowel
(ti)zr(w a)(li)n high vocoid
(ti)(zr)(w a)(li)n liquid
/I-haUl-tn/ 'he made them plentiful'
 I(ha)Ultn low vowel 
(i)(ha)(ul)tn high vocoid block by hiatus: two successive nuclei 
(i)(ha)(wl&#809; liquid )tn
(i)(ha)(wl&#809; &#809; nasal
 )(tn) 
&#8226;	left-to-right parse w hen equal sonority rank 
/baIn-n/ /t-ftk-t/ 
(ba)Inn ------- low vowel 
--------- ------- high vowel (ba)(i)n n blocked by hiatus 
--------- ------- liquid 
(ba)(yn )n ------- nasal left to right (cf. *(ba)y(nn&#809;) 
-------- (tf&#809;)tkt fricative
-------- (tf&#809; )t stop  left to right  (cf. *(tf&#809; &#809;
 )(tk&#809; )t(kt) 
(tf&#809; &#809; coda )(tkt) 
7. Optimality Theor y (Prince &amp; Sm olensky 1993, 2004) 
&#8226;	critique of rule-based system of phonol ogical grammar 
3 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Stress II: rhythm</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec21/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>&#8226; Weri: right-to-left iambic parse; degenerate foot option taken 
&#8226; Araucanian: left-to-right iambic parse; degenerate foot option not taken 
&#8226; Pintupi: left-to-right parse; degenerate foot option not taken 
&#8226; Passamaquoddy: right-to-left iambic parse; degenerate foot option not taken 
Evidence for grouping 
3. stress shifts resulting from deletion of stressed syllable 
Central Yupik: stress syllables with a long vowel and initial syllables closed by a 
consonant; otherwise assign alternating left-to-right pattern to remaining syllables. 
qay&#225;ni 'his own kayak', sag&#250;y&#225;ani 'in his (another's) drum', qay&#225;pigk&#225;ni 'his own future 
authentic kayak', q&#225;nr&#250;tkaqa 'I speak about them' &lt; /q&#225;nrut&#233;kaqa/ by deletion of stressed 
vowel and retraction of stress to the left--not to the right where it might otherwise be 
expected. (Jacobson '85: 30-34)
 x  x x
  x x x       ( x x) x   x x x x x (xx)(xx) x
qayani -&gt; qayapigkani -&gt; 
x x  x  x
qanrutekaqa x x x x x (x )(x x)x x
 &#216; 
4. quantity changes to yield a bimoraic foot 
&#8226; Latin &#8211;io verbs (Mester 1994) 
aud-i:-mus &#8216;hear&#8217; root+theme+desinence i: &#8776; i
sent-i:-mus &#8216;feel&#8217;
aper-i:-mus &#8216;open&#8217;
sepel-i:-mis &#8216;bury&#8217;
c&#225;p-i-mus &#8216;catch&#8217;
f&#225;c-i-mus &#8216;make&#8217;
&#8226; allomorphs distributed to promote exhausative parsing 
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text> 5. Alternating stress typology and binary foot parsing  
&#8226; Parsing: left -to-right/right -to-left 
&#8226; Foot type: trochaic/iambic  
&#8226; Degenerate foot option: (*)  
&#8226; Seven of eight languages attested (Kager 2005)* 
 
 
6. Optimality Theoretic alternative  (McCarthy &amp; Prince 1993)  
&#8226; Constraints:  
 Parse Syll: penalize any syllable that is not parsed into a foot  
 Foot-Binarity: penalize and foot that is not composed of two syllables  
 All-Feet L/R: assign violations marks for the number of syllables that intervene between  
 the foot and the left/right edge of the word  
 Iambic/Trochaic: foot is right/left headed  
 
&#8226; Exemplification of trochaic systems: Trochiac &#187; Iambic 
                                                  
* Buckley (2010) finds that Kashaya fills this cell.   
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>dar&#225;bt ?a9m &#225;al 
must&#225;&#8747;faa, mu9&#225;llim, muq&#225;atil, &#8747;aab&#225;atun 
kaat&#225;ba, qatt&#225;lat, makt&#225;bah, w&#225;lad, r&#225;?aa, h&#237;ya, k&#225;taba, ?ink&#225;sara, bulahn&#237;yat un, 
murtabiT&#225;tun 
&#8226; Mitchell &amp; Langendoen Generalizations 
i. stress a fin al supra-heavy syllable 
ii. otherwsise, stress a p enultimate heavy 
iii. otherwise, stress the penult or the antepenult depending on which is 
separate d from the begeniing of the word or a previous heavy syllab le by an 
even number of light syllables 
&#8226; Metrical analysis 
left-to-right moraic trochee parse w ith (main) stress on fin al foot
final mora is &#8220;e xtram etrical&#8221;
head foot is interpreted phonet ically with duration
no secondar y stress
project line 0 * * * * * * * * * * * 
parse-LR line 0 (* *) (* *) * (* *) (* *) (* *) 
head-L line 1 ( *       * )  (*  *       * ) 
unbounded -R line 2  * * 
&#8747;ajar&#225;tuhu &#8747;ajaratuh&#250;m aa 
Project line-0 * * * * * * * * * * * 
Parse-LR Q S line-0 (*) (* *)( * *) (*) (* *)(* *) * 
Head-L line 1 (* *      * )                   ( * *     *) 
Unbounded-R line 2 * * </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Biangai: right-to-left binary parse with clash 
Parse-Syll &#187; Ft-Bin &#187; All-Ft-R &#187; All-Ft-L 
/12345/ Parse-Syll Ft-Bin Align-L Align-R 
&gt;(1)(23)(45) * *,*** ****, ** 
1(23)(45) *! *,*** ** 
(12)(3)(45) * **,***! ***,** 
123(45) *!** *** 
7. in many languages syllables divided into heavy vs. light as relevant for stress 
&#8226; heavy: CV: 
&#8226; light: CV 
&#8226; variable: CVC 
8. quant ity-sensitive  parses (Hayes 1995) 
&#8226; rhythmic templates 
&#8226; iambic: [L L], [L H], [H] 
&#8226; trochee: [L L] [H]  Latin 
9. quant itative trochee: Classical Cairene Arabic (Mitchell 1962) 
&#8226;	syllab les 
light CV 
heavy: CVV, CVC 
super-heavy: CVVC, CVCC (limited to final syllab le) 
&#8226; classical pronunciation (A l-Azrah University) 
&#8747;&#225;jara	 ?adw iyat&#250;hu 
&#8747;ajar&#225;tun ?adw iyat&#250;humaa 
&#8747;ajar&#225;tuhu 
&#8747;ajaratuh&#250;m aa </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Stress-2 
24 Nov 2010 
Metrical Models 
1. "grid-only" (Prince '83, Selkirk '84, Goldsmith '93, Gordon '02): stress as rhythmic alternation 
of peaks and troughs in prominence grid with no internal grouping.
   Hayes '81 typology of alternating stress: 
Maranungku "s s 's s "s s 's s 's &#8220;s = main stress 
Warao 's s "s s s 's s "s s &#8216;s = secondary stress 
Weri s 's s "s 'ss'ss"s s = syllable 
Araucanian s "s s 's s "s s 's s 
x x x 
&#8226; primitive rhythmic alternation of peaks and troughs: ....x x x x x x x ..... 
&#8226; parameters of initial association to {peak/trough} and {left/right} edge of word; 
&#8226; one-to-one mapping of remaining syllables 
Maranungku: peak-first, left-to-right
Warao: trough-first, right-to-left
Weri: peak-first, right-to-left
Araucanian: trough-first, left-to-right
"Grid-only" model abandone d in face of empirical arguments for grouping on the basis of stress 
shifts under deletion and insertion of vowels and conceptual arguments for particular types of 
rhythm. 
2. Alternative foot theory: stress reflects a parsing of syllables into asymmetric units called feet. 
There are two basic types of feet: a trochee in which the first element is strong and the second 
weak and an iamb in which the first is weak and the second strong. Feet are optimally 
disyllabic but a monosyllabic foot can be created as a marked option.
 x  x  x 
(x x) trochee (x x) iamb (x) degenerate 
&#8226; Maranunku: left-to-right trochaic parse; degenerate foot option exercised 
&#8226; Warao: right-to-left trochaic parse; degenerate foot option not taken 
1
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>?adw iyat&#250;hu ?adw iyat&#250;humaa 
10. OT analog 
&#8226;	constraints 
Weight-to-Stress: a heavy syllable occupi es the head of a foot 
Ft-Bin: feet are bimoraic 
Final Mora of heavy and supraheavy syllable ignored 
&#8226;	ranking
Trochaic &#187; Iambic
Ft-Bin &#187; Parse-Syll &#187; All-Ft left &#187; All-Ft right
&#8226;	tableaux 
/ &#8747;ajar&#225;tuhu / Ft-Bin Parse-syll All-Ft-left
&gt;(12)(34)5 * **
 (12)(34)(5) *! **,****
  1(23)(45) * *,**!*
 (12)345 **!*
/ ?adw iyat&#250;hu / Ft-Bin Parse-syll All-Ft-left
&gt;(1)(23)(45) *,***
(12)(34)5 * **
(1)(23)45 **! *
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Pintupi: left to right binary parse: 
Ft-Bin &#187; Parse-Syll &#187; All-Ft left &#187; All-Ft right 
/12345/ Ft-Bin Parse syll All-Ft-L All-Ft-R 
&gt; (12)(34)5 * ** ***,* 
(12)3(45) * ***! *** 
1(23)(45) * *,***! ** 
(12)345 **!* *** 
(12)(34)(5) *! ***,* 
Maranungku: left-to-right parse w ith no lapse 
Prase-Syll &#187; Ft-Bin &#187; All-Ft-L &#187; All-Ft-R 
/122345/ Parse-Syll Ft-Bin All-Ft-L All-Ft-R 
(12)(34)5 *! 
(12)3(45) * 
1(23)(45) * 
(12)345 **!* 
&gt;(12)(34)(5) * 
(12)(3)(4)(5) * 
Warao: right-to-left binary parse 
Ft-Bin &#187; Parse-Syll &#187; All-Ft-R &#187; All-Ft-L 
/12345/ Ft-Bin Parse-Syll All-Ft-R ** ***,* 
***! *** 
*,***! ** 
*** 
**,**** ***,* 
**,***,***!* ***,* 
All-Ft-L 
&gt;1(23)(45) * ** *,*** 
(12)(34)5 * ***!,* ** 
(12)3(45) * ***! *** 
(1)(23)(45) *! ***!*,** *,*** </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Tone I: African languages</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text> in a language with tonal melodies, the number of tonal contrasts does not increase
with the length of the lexical item; rather the melody is extended to encompass
additional syllables 
&#8226; tonal polarity: affix takes the opposite tone from the root: [tense-root-subject] 
&#224; s&#225; g&#249; 'you go astray'
&#225; w&#236; g&#250; 'you run'
&#225; v&#61611;&#61478;l  g&#249; 'you fly'
5. adding features of [&#177;rise], [&#177;fall] does not express the equivalence with LH and HL 
6. Goldsmith (1976) Autosegmental Phonology 
&#8226;	tonal features are represented on a separate level ( tier) from segmental features 
&#8226;	the temporal  relation between the tonal tier and the segmental tier is represented 
by association lines 
&#8226;	rules of tonal phonology define and modify the associations as well as changing
the feature coefficients 
7. Margi analyzed autosegmentally 
devocalization 
u ? u - a r i u ? w - a r i -&gt; u ? w - a r i segmental tier 
| | | | |  | |  |  / | |
H L    H L H L    H L  H       LH  L tonal tier 
&#8226;	tonal stability: while vowel deletes or devocalized to a glide and hence loses itsability to hold a tone, the tone does not disappear but is reassociated with anadjacent syllable 
8. Goldsmith's (1976) Well-Formedness Condition on autosegmental representations
(rules apply to maximally satisfy it; early example of rules driven to satisfy a constraint) 
&#8226;	every tone is associated with a tone-bearing unit (TBU = syllable, mora) 
&#8226;	every tone-bearing unit is associated with a tone 
&#8226;	association lines do not cross (for locality) 
9. 	Margi tonal melodies 
&#8226;	verb roots belong to one of three tonal "conjugations": H, L, LH 
&#8226;	tones are associated with tone-bearing units (syllable) one-to- one, left-to-right 
&#8226;	tones spread to satisfy the first condition of the WFC 
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	tones associate to satisfy the second 
&#8226;	implication that asymmetric location of plateux and contours should correlate 
10. tonal polarity: 
particle has opposite tone of root 
11. some other useful properties of autosegmental notation 
&#8226;	common tone sandhi rules expressed as addition of association lines (tone spread) 
L -&gt; F / H __	 Yoruba  b&#225; 'meet' &#243; b&#225; 'he meets'
 b&#224; 'perch' &#243; ba&#61534; 'he perches' 
H -&gt; R / L ___ Buli z&#250;k 'head' w&#224; zuk&#61478; 'his head' 
&#8226; addition of association plus deletion of original association line (tone shift) 
&#8226;	across-the-board tonal change Meeussen's Rule in Shona (Odden 1981) 
H -&gt; L / H ___ Shona:  mbw&#225; 'dog' n&#233;#mbwa 'with a dog' 
badz&#225; 'hoe' n&#233;#badz&#225; 'with a hoe' 
h&#243;v&#233; 'fish' n&#233;#hove 'with a fish' 
mb&#250;nd&#250;dz&#237; 'worms' s&#233;#mbundudzi 'like worms' 
&#61656;	multiple linking of tone required 
&#61656;	imposed by Obligatory Contour Principle (OCP): adjacent identical trones
are banned: successive H tones as in h&#243;v&#233; 'fish' and mb&#250;nd&#250;dz&#237; 'worms' analyzed with one multiply-linked H 
&#8226;	tonal particle: a grammatical morpheme whose only exponent is tonal effect onneighboring word 
3
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text> 12. automatic dow nstep 
&#8226;	high tone is realized at a lower F0 value that a previous H when preceded by a L 
&#8226;	found in many diverse languages: Japanese, English list notation 
Yoruba: Laniran &amp; Clements (2003) 
&#8226;	phonetic value of H could be lower than value of preceding L 
&#8226;	grammaticalization of natural lowering of subglottal pressure across breath group
as speech is articulated from "left-to-right" 
13. Moore (Gur, Burkina Faso) 
&#8226;	H &#225; vs. L a; has automatic downstep 
&#8226;	has non-automatic downstep: second of two high's realized at a lower level: &#225;! &#225; 
&#8226;	recall English vocative 
ko s&#225;:ga 'give a broom' kor b&#233;da 'big sacks' 
ko korg&#243; 'give a sack' kor ke:g&#225; 'green sacks' 
z&#225; s&#225;:ga 'bring a broom' s&#225; b&#233;da 'big brooms' 
z&#225; k&#243;r!g&#243; 'bring a sack' s&#225; k&#233;:!g&#225; 'green brooms' 
14. data from Lama problem (PGG 7.10) 
4
110
100
90
80
70
60
L H H L H L110
100
90
80
70
60
L H H L H L H L
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Tone-1: African Languages 
1. General Point 
&#8226;	the study of tone in African lgs. raised serious conceptual problems for the
representation of the phoneme as a bundle of distinctive features. 
&#8226;	the solution to the problem (autosegmental representations) became a model forall other features 
&#8226;	tone exhibits the widest range of phonological behavior 
2. Phonetic correlates of tone 
&#8226;	F0; stiffen and slacken vocal folds 
&#8226;	realized on modal voicing 
&#8226;	domain: often larger than single segment (syllable, word) 
&#8226;	can be affected by laryngeal features of consonants (tonogenesis) 
3. notation 
&#8226;	Two-way contrast: &#225; vs. &#224; (or a) 
&#8226;	Three-way contrast: a&#61504; vs. a&#61475; (or a) vs. &#224; 
&#8226;	Contours: a&#61478; (rise) a&#61534; (fall) 
&#8226;	Features for H, M, L 
&#8226;	Goldsmith: [+highpitch, -lowpitch], [-highpitch, -lowpitch], [-highpitch,
+lowpitch] (3-way height contrast)
&#8226;	Yip: [+upper, -high], [-upper, +high], [-upper, -high] ([+upper, +high] for raised
H) (4-way height contrast) 
4. descriptive problems motivating novel conception of feature organization 
&#8226;	decomposition of contour tones Rise into LH and Fall into HL 
&#8226;	tonal melodies and tonal polarity 
5. Margi (Chadic, Nigeria): H, L, R (Williams 1973, Hoffmann 1963) 
&#8226;	rising tone behaves phonologically as combination of Low plus High 
&#8226;	derivational source 
s&#225;l s&#225;l-&#225;r&#236; 'man'
k&#249;m k&#249;m-&#225;r&#236; 'meat'
t&#225;g&#250; t&#225;gw-&#225;r&#236; 'horse'
&#250;?&#249; &#250;?w-a r&#236;&#61478; 'fire' 
&#8226;	tonal melody verbs 
s&#225; nd&#225;by&#225; H HH
gh&#224; dz&#224;?&#249; L LL
hu&#61478; &#61518;g&#249;s&#250; R LH
1
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Review</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec25/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>25</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>11. Prosodic Morphology: morphological processes of affixation, truncation, infixation, 
reduplication, and shape change that depend on t he prosod ic structure of the base. 
&#8226;	Formalized in terms of CV templates 
&#8226;	Ilocano reduplicatio n prefixes a CCVC (maximal syllable) template and phonemes are 
mapped to matching slots in the template 
&#8226;	Prosodic Morphology Hypothesis states that templates are "natural" u nits of prosody 
such as m inimal, maximal syllab le, iambic or trochaic fo ot 
&#8226;	Japanese H, LL template for hypocorist ics: ti -&gt; tii-chan, kinsuke -&gt; kin-tyan: 
&#8226;	Arabic broken plurals: jundub -&gt; janaadib 
/jundub/ /jaziir/ 
{jun}dub {jazi}ir parse trochee at left edge 
{junuu}dub {jazaa}ir reparse as LH iam b 
junuudub  jazaa?ir restore re sidue 
janaadib ---------- change vow el melody 
&#8226;	In Optimality Model constrain ts on templates are hypothesized to follow from a ran king 
of constraints on prosodic shape that is ideally independent ly motivated in the gram mar 
12. Loanw ord Phonol ogy 
&#8226;	Modeled as resolution between conflict to remain faithful to the source word while also 
satisfyin g the constrain ts on sound inventory an d phonotactics in  the receiving language 
&#8226;	Different repairs emerge for the same violation: CVC Cantonese adapts pump with 
deletion as [p&#592;m] but tips as [tipsi] with epenthesis 
&#8226;	Some notion of percept ual salience seems to play a role: [s] has cues internal to the 
fricatio n while /p/ of pump may lack them 
&#8226;	Do Cantonese speakers fail to here the final p of pump or do they judge that [p&#592;m] with 
zero corre spondent is more similar to pump than [p&#592;mpi] would be while for tips [tipsi] 
is judged more similar th an tip? 
&#8226;	Goal is to develop general theory of phonological similarity from which these 
calculations could be derived
&#8226;	While in some cases adaptation apparently occurs at abstract phonological levels (e.g. 
English flap of caddy  is loaned as /kadi/ in Mexican Spanish) in other cases the 
adaptation takes account of noncont rast (but salient) inform ation as in canto &gt; 
Mandarin [k&#593;ngt uo] to preserve the redundant but salient vowel quality at the cose of 
the distinctive but less salient nasal coda place feature 
6
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	Rhythmic parses in Quantity-Insensitive languages: param eterized rules 
&#61656; Parsing direction: left-to-right, right-to-left 
&#61656; Foot type: trochee, iamb 
&#61656; Degenerate foot option: (*) 
&#61656; 8 possible languages : right-to-left iam bic with initial lap se is said  to be missing 
(but Kashaya) 
&#8226;	Rhythmic parses in Quantity-Insensitive languages: OT constrain ts
&#61656; Parse-Syllable
&#61656; Foot Binarity
&#61656; All-Ft left/Right
&#61656; Iambic/Trochaic (le ft/right head)
&#8226;	Quantity-Sensitive parses:
&#61656; Quantitative trochee: (Ss) = (LL) or (S) = (H)
&#61656; Cairene: Left-to-Right trochaic: &#643;ajara&#769; hu
 tuhu vs. ?adwiyatu&#769;
&#61656; Iambic parse: Creek: Left-to-Right iambic: amifoci&#769; ta , imahici&#769;
&#61656; OT constraint: Weight-to-Stress: Heavy syllable is stressed 
9. Constraints 
&#8226;	Static well-formedness constraints like Lym an's Law in Jap anese (on e voice d obstruent 
per morphem e) are not easily expressed as rewrite rules 
&#8226;	But cannot be confined to lexicon since they block rendaku (compound voicing): sono 
'garden', hana-zono 'flower garden' but aka-sabi 'red rust' 
&#8226;	Other constraints like rising and falling sonority for syllable onsets and codas seem to 
trigger rules of epenthesis or deletion to impose exhaustive syllabification 
&#8226;	Optimality Theory replaces rewrite rules with constraints 
&#8226;	For a given input a set of can didate outputs is cre ated 
&#8226;	A hierarchy (ranking) of constraints sifts candidate set to find output 
&#8226;	Constraints are conflicting: faithfulness constraints want output to resemble input while 
markedness constraints drive input to less marked (more optimal) output; markedness 
constraints may conflict as well 
&#8226;	Languages differ by ranki ng of fixed set of const raints 
Continental French: Max-C, Dep-V &#187; SonSeq the.atr 
English: Max-C, SonSeq &#187; Dep-V thea.t&#601;r 
Canadian French: Dep-V, SonSeq &#187; Max-C theat&lt;r&gt; 
&#8226;	Standard OT model assumes a one step mapping between the input and output and so is 
challenged by many examples of derivational opacity like writer vs. rider 
4
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>3. Passam aquoddy (LeSour d 1993) : 
w&#225;s-is 'child' dimin. w&#225;s-&#237;s-ek 'children'
p&#233;m-sk&#243;t- e-k 'field' p&#233;m-skot- &#233;-k-il 'fields'
t&#243;pkwan 'soil' t&#243;pkw&#225;n-amkw 'soi l' particulate
l-&#233;w&#233;sto 'he speaks' w&#237;k-ew&#233;sto 'he likes to talk' 
s&#233;ht&#225;y-ew&#233;sto 'he speaks while walking backwards'
w&#237;cohk&#233;-m-a-l 'he helps the other' 
w&#237;c&#243;hke-k&#233;mo 'he helps out' 
w&#237;cohk&#233;-tah&#225;-m-a-l 'he thinks of helping the other'
t&#233;hs&#225;hkw-ap&#225;s-olt&#237;-ne 'let's (pl.) walk around on top' 
7
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	One-many and many-one relations with contour tones and tone-spreading: Mende mbu&#770;, 
ngi&#769;&#768; &#769;&#768;&#768; la, and felamaall belong to the same HL tonal melody 
&#8226;	African  lgs: Floating tones; sandhi-rules of tone spread an d deletion; downstep in M oore 
and Lama
Lama: /wa&#769;/ -&gt; wa&#769;
 l ra&#768; l ra&#770;
/na&#770; ra&#768; &#769; ra&#768;
 / -&gt; na
/wa&#769;l se&#768;wa&#769; &#769;&#769;&#769; / -&gt; wal se!wa
/ya&#780; &#768;/ -&gt; yal ra&#770; l ra &#768;
&#8226;	Asian languages have larger number of levels and shapes; divide pitch sp ace into upper 
and lower regist ers 
&#8226;	Tonog enesis: tonal contrasts frequently evolve from the phonol ogization of the small F0 
differences that accompany voicing contrasts in the preceding vowel with voiceless 
obstruent s leading to high tones and voiced obstruents to low tones; modally voiced 
sonorants may pattern with either 
&#8226;	In Zhenhai and Cham tonal contrast attracte d to stressed (prominent) syllable 
4. Autosegmental-Metrical model of intonation 
&#8226;	Metrical grid formalizes the strongest syllab le in a word or phrase 
&#8226;	F0 Intonation contour analyzed as tonal melody composed of pitch accents (to nes 
aligned to most prominent syllable) and boundary tones 
Declarative H* L% interrogative L* H% vocat ive H* 'H% 
&#8226;	English wh-questions with fronted wh have declarative contour while wh-in situ have 
nuclear (main stress): You gave wh at to Mary. 
&#8226;	English/Ger manic languages deaccent old information: I gave her a bottle of whisky but 
it turns out she doesn't like whisky. 
5. prosodic hierarchy: phoneme &gt; (mora) &gt; syllable &gt; foot &gt; prosod ic word 
6. syllable 
&#8226;	Phonot actic constraints on word edges : #tr, *#rt; rt#, *tr# 
&#8226;	Syllabic contexts for rules (delete r from s yllable coda, aspirate voiceless stops in onset) 
&#8226;	Rules of vowel epent hesis (Spanish estop) and consonant truncation (damn, mnemonic)) 
ensure exhaus tive syllabification 
&#8226;	Sonori ty Sequenci ng general ization: syllables rise is sonori ty from l eft edge and fall in 
sonority to wards right edge: clark 
&#8226;	Sonori ty hierarchy: vowel &gt; glide &gt; liquid &gt; nasal &gt; fricat ive &gt; stop 
&#8226;	English allows coronal appendi ces: stop, act, wild, sixths 
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	Recent proposals of harmonic serialism allow an incremental input-output mapping 
where derivation gradually converges on output by multiple passes through the 
constraint evaluation st age w hile maintaining a fixed con straint ranking 
10. Syllable Weight 
&#8226;	Languages in which stress seeks out the heaviest syllable may have more than one 
degree of weight and pose look-ahead problems for traditional rewrite-system where 
metrical structure is built up gradually 
&#8226;	Kelkhar's Hindi: stress rightmost heavist syllable; in case of tie stress rightmost nonfinal 
heaviest
&#61656; Hierarchy: CVVC (S) &gt; CVV, CVC (H) &gt; CV (L)
&#61656; Heaviest: re&#769; 'SHH] so&#769; 'SLHH] inqila&#769; 'S]
 :zga:ri: [ :xjaba:ni: [ :b [HL
&#61656; Ties: sami&#769;ti [L'LL] ka:ri&#769; 'HLH] :gari: [H
&#61656; Analysis: Peak Prominence &#187; Nonfinality &#187; Rightmost &#187; Leftmost 
&#61656; Peak Prominence: *&#712;&#61846;L&#187; *&#712;&#61846;H&#187; *&#712;&#61846;S 
&#61656; Tableaux 
/ka:ri:gari:/ *&#712;&#61846;L &#187; *&#712;&#61846;H&#187; *&#712;&#61846;S Nonfin Rightmost Leftmost 
&#712;&#61846;s s s s * s s s ! 
&gt; s &#712;&#61846;sss * s s
 s s &#712;&#61846;s s *!
 s s s &#712;&#61846;s * *!
&#8226;	Kobon (New Guinea
&#61656; Vowels i i u
e &#601; o
a 
&#61656; Stress falls in disyllabic window at right edge of word 
&#61656; Stress seeks out stronger vowel on sonori ty scale: peripheral &gt; central, low &gt; 
mid &gt; high:
a &gt; e haga&#769;
pe
a &gt; i ki.a&#769;
o &gt; i si.o&#769;g
u &gt; &#601; lu&#769;.&#601;l
&#601; &gt; i gis&#601;&#769;
&#61656;	Ties: penul t (trochaic &#187; iambic) 
ji&#769;nup kijigi&#769;l 
&#61656; Ranking: *stressed central &#187; *stressed peripheral &#187; *stressed high &#187; 
*stressed mid &#187; *stressed low &#187; trochaic &#187; iambic 
5
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Review of Part-2 
1. Quantitative Sociolinguistics (Labov) 
&#8226;	Ordered variation: some grammatical variable such as rhotic vs. nonrhotic speech 
increases/decreases along some social d imension (age, social class,  gender) as w ell as 
context of speech: formal vs. informal 
&#8226;	Minimal pair, word list, reading style, careful speech, casual (non-monitored) speech 
&#8226;	Depa rtment Store Study: fourth floor 
&#8226;	Some variation is stable (t/d deletion of Wes(t) while others is dynam ic leading to 
graduat e replacement fo one category by another 
&#8226;	Two kinds of sound change: change from a bove (nonrhotic - rhotic) full public
awareness and tends to show up in careful speech
&#8226;	From bel ow (e.g. NCS) : initially unconscious; initiated by lower middle class 
&#8226;	Young females tend to be leaders of sound change: they are most style conscious and 
spend time with children who follow their lead 
2. NA English dialects (Labov) 
&#8226;	Telephone survey of over 800 speakers 
&#8226;	No significant ethnicity effect; but African American and Latino speech form s eparat e 
dialects that do not participate in regional sound changes 
&#8226;	mergers expand at the expense of distinctions (Herzog) 
&#8226;	/hw/ and /w/: whale &amp; wail preserved in south 
&#8226;	hoarse /oh/ vs. horse / &#596;/  NE &amp; South 
&#8226;	Mary-merry-marry: lost in most areas except NYC and scattered areas of South 
&#8226;	Low-back merger of /o/ cot, Don and /oh/ caught , Dawn in West 
&#8226;	Northern Cities Shift: Buffalo &#8211; Chicago: post WW2
&#61656; Raise [&#230;]
&#61656; Fronting of merged [o, ah] of lockes to sound like lax
&#61656; Lowering and fronting of /oh/ 
&#61656; Drag chain: vowels shift to vacated position
&#8226;	The dialect bounda ry delimited by the NCS correlates with Yankee vs. Upland 
Southerner settlement history and cultural/political values and attitudes seen in voting 
patterns and other expressions of identity 
3. Tone &amp; Aut osegmental Phonology 
&#8226;	Tone represented on a separate tier from phonem es 
&#8226;	Association lines indicate synchronization 
1
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	In most lan guages nucleus restricte d to vowel (e.g. Spanish) while some others allo w 
syllab ic consonants: liquids (Czech), liquids and nasals (G erman), all co nsonants 
(Berber) 
&#8226;	Syllabification algorithms must take account of local and more global context 
&#8226;	Directional parse: left-to-right Cairene /?ultlu/ &gt; ?ultilu) vs. right-to-left Iraqi /giltla/ 
&gt; gilitha 
&#8226;	Sonori ty cascade in Berber: assign core onset-nucleus structure to any sequence YZ 
where Z is low vowel, high vocoid, liquid, nasal, fricative, stop 
/ra-t-lUl-t/ rat.lult /ra-t-rgl-t/ ra.tr&#809;t.gl&#809;
&#8226;	In Berber the alignment of the syllable nucleus with a sonority peak is sh ort circu ited by 
the avoidance of hiatus; this effect has been modeled in Optimality Theor y by competing 
constraints on well-formedness: Onset &#187; H-Nuc 
8. stress 
&#8226;	Metrical grid formalizes prominence; stress is not a feature; prominence interpreted by 
gram mar as durat ion, pitch, intensity in language -particular fashion: 
&#716;Ala&#712;&#61846;bama &#712;&#61846;Aber&#716;nathy 
&#8226;	Initial (C zech), Final (Farsi),  penult (Polish) are common while peninitial (L akota) an d 
antepenult (Macedonian) are rare 
&#8226;	Alternating stress patterns 
Maranungku SsSs SsSsS S = stressed syllable s = unstressed syllable 
Warao SsSs sSsSs 
Weri sSsS SsSsS 
Araucanian sSsS sSsSs 
Pintupi SsSs SsSss 
Passamaquody SsSs SSsSs 
&#61656;	Grid-only model maps R/L edge to peak/t rough and then one-to-one; allows for 
stressing edgemost syllab le on grid for primary vs.  secondary stre ss 
&#61656; Provisio for special tre atment of edge syllable as alw ays stre ssed/unstressed 
&#61656; Foot theory parses into trochee (Ss) or iamb (sS) with (S) as marked option 
&#61656; Grouping supported by shift of stress under deletion (Yupik) and rules of 
allomorphy that promote exhaustive parsing: recall Latin aud-i:-mus, aper-i:-mus 
but fac-i-mus 
3
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Loanword phonology</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec24/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901 Language and Its Structure I: Phonology
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Tone II: Asian languages</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>3. Middle Chinese (Norman 1988) 
&#8226;	ternary contrast of voiceless aspirate [ph], plain voiceless [p], and voiced [b] 
&#8226;	tone: four pitch shapes divided into two registers as function of laryngeal category
of onset consonant 
ping shang qu ru 
yin 
yang 
ping level, high yang voiced obstruent 
shang rise yin voiceless obstruent 
qu departing, fall 
ru entering, short fall, stop in coda 
&#8226;	tonal correspondences in Mandarin 
ping shang qu ru 
Yin 1 3 4 1,2,3,4
Yang 2 3,4 4 2 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>C. 'place' 'yesterday' 
ti fa sa &#61688;i&#61503; 
213-441 213-23
11-334 11-4
D. 'tongue' 'special' 
&#61694;&#61509; t&#61615;y ta p&#61509;&#61503; 
23-21 23-5
1-242 1-25
12. generalizations 
&#8226;	tone of initial syllable retained, second is suppressed 
&#8226;	initial syllable reflects underlying register of first tone 
&#8226;	second syllable reflects the contour of the first syllable tone 
&#8226;	second syllable register is H 
&#8226;	first syllable contour is level (l) 
13. analysis 
&#8226;	delete noninitial tone 
&#8226;	reassociate c node of surviving tone to stressed syllable 
&#8226;	assign H register to stressed syll (a natural correlation in Zhenhai and cross-
linguistically) 
&#8226;	assign l to contour node of unstressed syll 
5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901  Tone-2 Asian Languages 
1. general 
&#8226;	larger number of levels and shapes 
&#8226;	transciption: Chao numbering
Mandarin 1. ma&#61475; 55 'mother'
2. ma&#61504; 35 'hemp' 
3. ma&#61478; 214 'horse' 
4. ma&#61476; 51 'scold' 
2. register 
&#8226;	In many Asian lgs. the pitch space is divided into an upper and lower region 
&#8226;	parallel tones in each region 
&#8226;	register often correlated with laryngeal specification of onset consonant 
&#8226;	Cantonese (Bauer 1997) 
live syllables: CV:C, CVN
high level ji 'clothes' 55
high fall ji 'to cure' 51
high rise ji 'chair' 25
mid ji 'idea' 33
low level ji 'two' 22
low fall ji 'suspicious' 21
low rise ji 'ear' 23
dead syllables CVT, CV:T
high stopped jek 'benefit' 5
mid stopped ja:k 'to eat' 33
mid-low stopped jek 'also' 2
pi:n jam 'changed tones'
high level a:-ji: 'auntie' 55
high rising a:ji: 'no. 2' 25
earlier suffix/particle loses its segmental structure but retains high tone 
Bao (1990, 1999) 
&#8226;	formal distinction between register (h,l) and "contour" (H,L) 
&#8226;	contour node may be sequenced; permits four levels and parallel contours inupper and lower register 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>        4. Sandhi-1: Mandarin (Duanmu 2000) 
&#8226;	Mandarin third tone sandhi: 214 -&gt; 35 / __ 214 
&#8226;	cyclic vs. not 
[[3 3] 3] -&gt; 2 2 3 [3 [3 3]] -&gt; 3 2 3 &#8776; 2 2 3 
[mai hao] jiu 'finished buying wine' mai [hao jiu] 'buy good wine' 
&#8226;	Mandarin minor tone sandhi (in casual, fast speech) 
35 -&gt; 55 / {35, 55} ____ X 
cong you bing shei neng fei
55 35 214 -&gt; 55 55 214 35 35 55 -&gt; 35 55 55
'onion oil cake' 'who can fly?'
&#8226;	elimination of contour 
&#8226;	55-2-55 preserved: too big a difference perceptually? 
&#8226;	Cantonese: Yip (2002:176) "Even for those speakers who have both 53 and 55
underlying tones, the high falling tone 53 becomes level 55 before another tonethat begins with high, i.e. 53, 55, or 5." 
&#8226;	rule does not apply to 35: 53 -&gt; 55 / ___ 5 
5. Sandhi-2: Shanghai (Wu) Duanmu 1993 
se52 + pe52 -&gt; 55 21 'three cups'
se52 + b&#248;23 -&gt; 55 21 'three plates'
sz34 + pe52 -&gt; 33 44 'four cups'
sz34 + b&#248;o23 -&gt; 33 44 'four plates'
&#8226;	Contour tone separates into two components 
&#8226;	First syllable stressed 
&#8226;	loss of information from unstressed syllables 
&#8226;	spread in longer domains 
&#8226;	Shanghai has no coda consonants 
6. Sandhi-3: Tianjin (Chen 1985, 2000) 
&#8226;	Inventory H, L, HL, LH 
&#8226;	sandhi-dissimilation for shape or elimination of turning point 
xi LH lian LH -&gt; HH LH 'wash face' 
song HL xian HL -&gt; LL HL 'send letter' 
kan HL shu LL -&gt; HH LL 'read book' 
chou LL yan LL -&gt; LH LL 'smoke cigarette' 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>7. Sandhi-4: Zhenhai (N. Wu, Rose 1990, Li 2003) 
&#8226;	as in Shanghai, initial tone preserved in two syllable sandhi and second one
deleted 
&#8226;	but initial tone may be shifted to second syllable when the latter is stressed 
&#8226;	tone shift provides strong evidence for the Bao notation distinguishing tone
contour and register 
8. Citation tones: 
9. Ba o (1999) re presentation 
10. Details 
&#8226;	contrast of metrical structure: SW and WS (weak, strong) 
&#8226;	registers 
&#8226;	syllable length 
11. Sandhi pattern 
WS 
A. 'spring'	 'western calendar' 
tshy&#61518; th&#61513; &#61694;&#61513; l&#61513;&#61503; 
441-441 441-23 citation tone 
33-441 33-4 sandhi tone 
B. 'coal mine' 'hair' 
mei khwa t&#61615;y fa&#61503; 
231-231 231-5
11-441 11-4
4 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Stress I: prominence</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec20/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>/hana-sono/ Lyman's Law Rendaku
 hana-sono *!
           &gt;hana-zono
/aka-sabi/ Lyman's Law Rendaku
&gt;aka-sabi *
 aka-zabi *!
5. 	*'V.CV, *Coda-h &gt;&gt; Max-h  (triggering) 
/v&#233;hicl/ *'V.CV  *Coda-h Max-h
 v&#233;.hi.cl *!
 v&#233;h.i.cl *!
&gt;v&#233;.i.cl	 * 
6. The OT model assumes a one-step mapping between the input and output (parallelism) 
&#8226;	challenged by pervasive opacity where a sound change is defined over a context 
that is not present in the surface output (e.g. writer-rider) 
&#8226;	remains an unsolved problem; Harmonic Serialism (McCarthy, UMass) and OTLP (Kiparsky, Stanford) are alternative approaches that try to confront opacity </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Phonological Constraints and Optimality Theory 
1. Optimality Theory (Prince &amp; Smolensky 1993, 2003) 
&#8226;	partially successful solution to the constraint problem 
&#8226;	received model of phonolgical theory in generative grammar today 
&#8226;	two constraint types
markedness: structural well-formedness of output: *&#252;, Onset, *Lapse
faithfulness: correspondence relation between input and output assumed
Max: every segment of input has correspondent in output Dep: every segment of output has correspondent in input 
Ident -[feature]: two corresponding segments have same value for feature F 
&#8226;	constraints are violable  (not always true of surface output) and conflicting 
&#8226;	conflict resolved by ranking 
&#8226;	typology by ranking: all systematic differences between grammars arise from 
different ranking of a fixed set of UG constraints
&#61656; every language must fall in the class of possible rankings
&#61656; every ranking describes a possible language
&#8226;	what is carried over from traditional generative model: 
&#61656; input-output mapping 
&#61656; autosegmental, prosodic representations (OT is not a theory of representations 
though proposed constraints may have representational commitments) 
&#8226;	what is not carried over:
&#61656; no rules
&#61656; no constraints on inputs (morpheme-structure constraints)
2. 	architecture  of model 
Gen(erate) -&gt; 	 cand 1 -&gt; Con -&gt; cand x &gt; cand y &gt; cand z &gt; &#8230; 
cand 2 
cand 3
 : 
&#8226;	for each input GENerate constructs a (possibly) infinite set of output candidates 
&#8226;	the constraints (in a fixed ranking) evaluate  the candidates by assessing violation 
marks 
&#8226;	the output  for a given input is defined as the candidate that best satisfies the
constraint hierarchy
&#8226;	winner-take-all: a candidate's value is not improved relative to another by
performing better on lower ranked constraints
&#8226;	tableau is a device analogous to a truth table to prove that one candidate is more optimal (harmonic) than another </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>  24.901 Stress-1 
[0] Stress 
&#8226;	Focus of generative study since SPE 
&#8226;	Basic parameters known: 510 lgs. by Rob Goedemans 
 
&#8226;	pervasive effects on phonology: allophony (a[r]om vs. a[th]omic, consti[t]ute vs.
consti[t_]uent),Truncation (Elizabeth -&gt; Liz, *Zab), Intonation contour 
&#8226;	Gordon (2002) lgs with one stress per word in a fixed position 
initial: Czech, Irish, Latvian, Icelandic
final: Farsi, Hatian Creole, Kazakh, Kabardian
penultimate: Swahili, Polish, Albanian, Chamorro
antepenultimate: Macedonian,
peninitial: Lakota 
[1] SPE model: [&#177;stress] 
&#8226;	unique properties (cf. [&#177;nasal] 
&#8226;	no invariant phonetic correlates: intensity, duration, pitch 
&#8226;	greater than binary distinctions: Arkansas vs. Tennessee; preliminary vs. assimilation 
&#8226;	never assimilated 
&#8226;	striking nonlocality: Creek: if&#225;, hic&#237;ta , amifoc&#237; , imahic&#237;ta , isimahicit&#225; , itiwanayip&#237;ta 
&#8226;	rhythmic: repetition of a motif:  'Apal'achic"ola, cf. Finnish, Australian 
&#8226;	heavy syllables attract stress: CVV (heavy), CV (light), CVC (variable) 
&#8226;	culminativity: one syllable per word/phrase singled out as strongest 
[2] Liberman 1975: 
&#8226;	stress is not a feature 
&#8226;	reflects abstract prominence modeled in metrical grid 
&#8226;	two dimensional array of positions and prominence 
&#8226;	phonetic rules interpret the grid by assigning length, F0, intensity 
line-2 * * * 
line-1 * * * * * 
line-0 * * * *               * * * * * * 
America hurricane Tennessee 
1
http://www.unileiden.net/stresstyp/</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>3. 	simple exemplifications: word-final consonant clusters of rising sonority 
English: thea[t&#61611;r] (cf. theatr-ic)
Canadian Fr: th&#233;at[ ]
Cont Fr:  th&#233;a[tr]
Son-Seq: *final clusters of rising sonority
Max-C: violation: a cons in input without correspondent in output
Dep-V: violation: a vowel in output without correspondent in input
/theatr/ Son-Seq Max-C Dep-V
thea[t&#61611;r] *&#61482;
th&#233;a[t] *
th&#233;a[tr] *
&#8226;	English: Son-Seq, Max-C &gt;&gt; Dep-V 
/theatr/ Son-Seq Max-C Dep-V
       -&gt; thea[t&#61611;r] *&#61482;
th&#233;a[t] *!
th&#233;a[tr] *!
&#8226;	Can Fr: Son-Seq, Dep-V &gt;&gt; Max-C 
/theatr/ Son-Seq Dep-V Max-C
thea[t&#61611;r] *!&#61482;
-&gt; th &#233;a[t] *
th&#233;a[tr] *!
&#8226;	Cont Fr: Max-C, Dep-V &gt;&gt; Son-Seq 
/theatr/ Max-C Dep-V Son-Seq
thea[t&#61611;r] *!&#61482;
th&#233;a[t] *!&#61482;
 -&gt;	th&#233;a[tr] * 
Observations 
&#8226;	Continental Fr has the faithful mapping: input same as output; hence F &gt;&gt; M 
&#8226;	To compel a change some M constraint must dominate some F constraint 
&#8226;	Minimal violation: /th&#233;atr/ -&gt; th&#233;a[  ] also satisfies Son Seq but with an 
unneccessary violation of faithfulness (cf. economy, least effort) 
4. 	Lyman's Law &gt;&gt; Rendaku  (blocking) </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Metrical Models 
1. "grid-only" (Prince '83, Selkirk '84, Goldsmith '93, Gordon '02): stress as rhythmic
alternation of peaks and troughs in prominence grid with no internal grouping.
 Hayes '81 typology of alternating stress: 
Maranungku "s s 's s "s s 's s 's &#8220;s = main stress 
Warao 's s "s s s 's s "s s &#8216;s = secondary stress
Weri s 's s "s 's s 's s "s s = syllable 
Araucanian s "s s 's s "s s 's s 
x x x 
&#8226; primitive rhythmic alternation of peaks and troughs: ....x x x x x x x ..... 
&#8226; parameters of initial association to {peak/trough} and {left/right} edge of word; 
&#8226; one-to-one mapping of remaining syllables 
Maranungku: peak-first, left-to-right
Warao: trough-first, right-to-left
Weri: peak-first, right-to-left
Araucanian: trough-first, left-to-right
"Grid-only" model abandoned in face of empirical arguments for grouping on the basis of stress
shifts under deletion and insertion of vowels and conceptual arguments for particular types of
rhythm. 
2. Alternative foot theory: stress reflects a parsing of syllables into asymmetric units called feet. 
There are two basic types of feet: a trochee in which the first element is strong and the second 
weak and an iamb in which the first is weak and the second strong. Feet are optimally
disyllabic but a monosyllabic foot can be created as a marked option.
 x x  x 
(x x) trochee (x x)    iamb (x) degenerate 
&#8226; Maranunku: left-to-right trochaic parse; degenerate foot option exercised 
&#8226; Warao: right-to-left trochaic parse; degenerate foot option not taken 
&#8226; Weri: right-to-left iambic parse; degenerate foot option taken 
&#8226; Araucanian: left-to-right iambic parse; degenerate foot option not taken 
&#8226; Pintupi: left-to-right parse; degenerate foot option not taken 
&#8226; Passamaquoddy: right-to-left iambic parse; degenerate foot option not taken 
Evidence for grouping 
3. stress shifts resulting from deletion of stressed syllable 
Central Yupik: stress syllables with a long vowel and initial syllables closed by a 
consonant; otherwise assign alternating left-to-right pattern to remaining syllables. 
qay&#225;ni  'his own kayak', sag&#250;y&#225;ani 'in his (another's) drum', qay&#225;pigk&#225;ni  'his own future 
authentic kayak', q&#225;nr&#250;tkaqa  'I speak about them' &lt; /q&#225;nrut&#233;kaqa / by deletion of stressed
vowel and retraction  of stress to the left--not to the right where it might otherwise be
expected. (Jacobson '85: 30-34) 
x x x
x x x       (x x) x  x x x x x (x x)(x x) x
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>qayani -&gt; 	 qayapigkani -&gt; 
x x x x 
qanrutekaqa x x x x x       ( x ) (x x) x x 
_0 
4. quantity changes to yield a bimoraic foot 
&#8226; Latin &#8211;io verbs (Mester 1994) 
aud- i:-mus &#8216;hear&#8217; root+theme+desinence i: ! i
sent-i:-mus &#8216;feel&#8217;
aper-i:-mus &#8216;open&#8217;
sepel-i:-mis &#8216;bury&#8217;
c&#225;p-i-mus &#8216;catch&#8217;
f&#225;c-i-mus &#8216;make&#8217;
&#61656;allomorphs distributed to promote exhausative parsing 
5. Rhythmic Units (WS iambic and SW trochaic and their relationship to quantity) Hayes '85,
'94, McCarthy &amp; Prince '86. 
rhythmic perception: Woodrow 1909,&#8230; 
&#8226; alternating pulses enhanced by intensity group SW 
&#8226; alternating pulses enhanced by duration group WS 
rhythmic templates 
syllabic trochee: ('ss) and possibly ('s) as a marked option 
iamb: (L's) and ('H): [i.e. (L'L), (L'H), and ('H)]
quantitative trochee:('LL) and ('H)--not ('HL) or ('L)--strictly bimoraic 
7. Cairene Arabic:   	 light CV 
heavy: CVV, CVC 
super-heavy: CVVC, CVCC (limited to final syllable) 
&#8226; classical pronunciation (Al-Azrah University) 
sh&#225;jara ?adwiyat&#250;hu
shajar&#225;tun ?adwiyat&#250;humaa
shajar&#225;tuhu
shajaratuh&#250;maa
dar&#225;bt ?a9m&#225;al 
must&#225;shfaa, mu9&#225;llim , muq&#225;atil , shaab&#225;atun 
kaat&#225;ba , qatt&#225;lat , makt&#225;bah , w&#225;lad, r&#225;?aa, h&#237;ya, k&#225;taba , ?ink&#225;sara , bulahn&#237;yatun , murtabiT&#225;tun 
&#8226; left-to-right moraic trochee parse with main stress on final foot 
&#8226; final mora is extrametrical 
3
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Consonants: articulatory description and transcription; distinctive features</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec02/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2-3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 
Sept. 13, 2010 Distinctive Features-1 (vowels) 
[1] lexical item 
&#8226;	string of speech sounds (phonemes); two items distinct if they differ in length or position 
&#8226;	each phoneme is composed of a matrix of feature specifications 
&#8226;	features are typically binary: [&#177;Feature] 
&#8226;	features have articulatory and acoustic correlates representing the grammatically controlled aspects of 
the sound implemented in the phonetic component 
&#8226;	features also have a classificatory function: they define the alphabet of sounds that encodes the 
vocabulary of the language in the lexicon; they characterize the natural classes for the rules and 
constraints that describe the distribution and change of sounds 
&#8226;	feature theory developed at MIT in 1950-52 by Roman Jakobson, Gunnar Fant, Morris Halle
(Preliminaries to Speech Analysis) based on earlier insights of Nikolai Trubetzkoy in the 1930&#8217;s.
[2] some features for Vowels 
i ! e " &#230; a # o u $ 
high + + &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; + + 
low &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; + + &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; 
back &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; + + + + + 
ATR + &#8211; + &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; + + &#8211; 
(key words: [i] beat, [!] bit, [e] bait, ["] bet, [&#230;] bat, [#] bought, [o] boat, [u] boot, [$] foot 
&#8226;	articulatory neutral point for vowels: ["] 
&#8226;	[+high] vowel raise tongue body from neutral point; [&#8211;high] do not; [+low] vowels lower tongue 
body below neutral point; [&#8211;high] do not; [+back] vowels retract tongue body from neutral point; [&#8211; 
back] do not 
&#8226;	tense-lax distinction described here as [&#177;Advanced Tongue Root]; no consensus on this point 
&#8226;	IPA symbols are abbreviations for feature matrixes 
&#8226;	each sound is represented as plus, minus, or zero for each feature 
&#8226;	every phoneme must be representable as some plus/minus vector for features 
&#8226;	feature system is component of Universal Grammar that allows a child to distinguish speech from noise and 
begin learning vocabulary of the language of environment 
&#8226;	some believe that different part of brain activated for sounds of language as opposed to noise in general 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Consonants 
&#8226; produced with constriction or obstruction in supralaryngeal vocal tract 
&#8226; traditionally described by place and manner of articulation 
&#8226; up to eleven places distinguished 
[1] places of articulation according to the IPA 
Place stop fricative
bilabial p, b -, .
labiodental f, v
dental t// 0, 1
 ,d
alveolar t, d s, z
postalveolar 2, 3
retroflex 4, 5 6, 7
palatal c, 8 &#231;, 9
velar k, g x, :
uvular q, G ;, &lt;
pharyngeal =, &gt;
laryngeal &amp; h, ?
5 A sagittal section of the vocal tract, showing the places of articulation that occur in English.
The coronal region is shown in more detail at the right.RetroflexPalato-AlveolarCoronal
DentalAlveolarCoronalVelarPalatal
BilabialLabiodental
Image by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>: &lt;
velar vs. uvular: [+high] [&#8211;high]
stop k q
g G
fricative x ;
pharyngeal: [&#177;constricted pharynx] tongue root is articulator 
fricative = &gt;
stops not found; difficult to make a closure
laryngeal: [&#177;constricted glottis] vocal folds are the active articulators 
[constricted gl] [spread gl] 
stop &amp; + &#8211; 
fricative h &#8211; + 
examples: 
Arabic gutturals: [dorsal] [constr ph] [high] [back] [voice] [spread gl] [constr gl] 
xaali 'myuncle' + &#8211; + + &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; 
:aali 'expensive' + &#8211; + + + &#8211; &#8211; 
qaal 'hesaid' + &#8211; &#8211; + &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; 
=aali 'mycondition'&#8211; + &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; 
&gt;aali 'high' &#8211; + &#8211; &#8211; + &#8211; &#8211; 
haal 'mirage' &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; + &#8211; 
&amp;aal 'family,kin' &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; + 
[4] Sudanese Arabic (PGG ex. 1.12) 
kitaab 'book' bit 'daughter' samak 'fish' 
kitaa[f] Fathi bi[t] Fathi sama[k] Fathi
kitaa[p] Samiir bi[s] Samiir sama[k] Samiir
kitaa[p] ,ariif bi[,] ,ariif sama[k] ,ariif
kitaa[p] Xaalid bi[t] Xaalid sama[x] Xaalid
kitaa[p] Hasan bi[t] Hasan sama[k] Hasan
8 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>[3] Chamarro (Guam) fronting of back vowels 
&#8226;	vowel system in stressed syllables 
front back
high i u
mid e o
low &#230; a
gum% house i gim% the house
tom$ knee i tem$ the knee
lah! male i l&#230;h! the male
gwih%n fish i gwih%n the fish
pec$ chest i pec$ the chest
&#8226;	informal statement of changes:
u &gt; i after definite article
o&gt;e
a&gt;&#230;
&#8226;	but same change occurs in other contexts:
tun$&amp; to know en tin$&amp; you know
hul$&amp; up s&#230;n hil$? upward
otd$t ant mi etd$t lots of ants
oks$? hill gi eks$? at the hill
lag$ north s&#230;n l&#230;g$ toward north
[4] statement of rules with IPA symbols 
u &gt; i after i, e, &#230; 
o &gt; e after i, e, &#230;
a &gt; &#230; after i, e, &#230;
&#8226;	this description fails to express the fact that the changes are related:
all occur in the same context
changing sounds [u,o,a] share something in common (back vowels)
same change in each pair: back vowel changes to corresponding front one
[5] But if sounds represented with features then only certain classes of sounds can be expressed simply: 
[i,e,&#230;] and [u,o,a] are natural classes while [i,e,a] or [u,&#230;,a] are not 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>[2] manner of articulation 
&#8226; degree and type of stricture 
&#8226; stop (plosive): complete closure and blockage of airflow; sudden release (acoustic spike) [d] 
&#8226; nasal: oral closure with lowered velum so air flows into nasal cavity [n] 
&#8226; fricative: narrow constriction creating turbulence [z] 
&#8226; affricate: stop with delayed release creating turbulence [dz] 
&#8226; approximant: one articulator approaches the other but no turbulence produced 
glide (semi-vowel): w, @, j French: Louis [wi], lui [@i], lieA [je]
lateral: l, B , C Italian: fili [l] vs. figli [C]
rhotic: D, (r = trilled, E tap/flap) English: red [D], Spanish: perro [r] vs. pero [E]
[3] features for consonants: place and manner of articulation 
active oral articulators: [&#177;labial], [&#177;coronal], [&#177;dorsal]
other active articulators: velum ([&#177;nasal]), tongue root ([&#177;constricted pharynx]), glottis
([&#177;spread glottis], [&#177;constricted glottis])
nasal: [&#177;nasal]; [+nasal] sounds are produced with the velum lowered while [&#8211;nasal] (oral) sounds have the 
velum raised; most languages contrast oral and nasal plosives (i.e. [n] vs. [t]) and some contrast oral and 
nasal vowels such as French beau [bo] vs. bon [b#F]; 
nasals are found at the same places as stops: m, G, n, H, I, J,N 
stricture: [&#177;continuant]
[&#8211;continuant]: stops and affricates
[+continuant]: all others
[&#177;delayed release]
[+delayed release]: affricates
[&#8211;delayed release]: all others
[&#177;strident] (bound to coronal articulator)
[+strident]: sibilants (s, ts, ,,t,, ): high turbulence
[&#8211;strident]: interdentals 0
[&#177;lateral] (bound to coronal articulator)
[+lateral]: side of tongue is lowered
[&#8211;lateral]: all others
6 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>[5] major class features 
[&#177;syllabic]
[+syllabic] denotes vowel, carries nucleus of syllable
[&#8211;syllabic] sounds at margin of syllable or nonsyllabic
[&#177;consonantal]
[+cons] oral constriction greater than a glide/semi-vowel
[&#8211;cons] oral constriction less than a glide/semi-vowel
[&#177;sonorant] 
[+sonorant] oral constriction not sufficient to cause air pressure to build up 
to prevent voicing of vocal folds 
[&#8211;sonorant] oral constriction impedes spontaneous voicing and requires 
some adjustment to maintain voicing 
syllabic consonantal sonorant 
vowel + &#8211; + 
glide &#8211; &#8211; + 
liquid &#8211; + + 
nasal &#8211; + + 
fricative &#8211; + &#8211; 
stop &#8211; + &#8211; 
affricate &#8211; + &#8211; 
Examples 
French high vowel devocalization 
il loue [lu] 
&#8216;he rents&#8217; lou-er [lwe] 
&#8216;to rent&#8217; il lie [li] 
&#8216;he binds&#8217; li-er 
&#8216;to bind&#8217; [lje] 
Palestinian Arabic glide vocalization 
dalw-ak 
&#8216;your pail&#8217; dalu 
&#8216;pail&#8217; d3alj-ak 
&#8216;your dish&#8217; d3ali 
&#8216;dish&#8217; cf. ?abu 
?abu:k &#8216;father&#8217; 
&#8216;your father&#8217; 
Popular English lateral vocalization 
feeling [l] feel [fiw] 
Argentinian Spanish glide &#8220;hardening&#8221; 
9 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Japanese verb inflection 
negative kak-anai tob-anai mat-anai das-anai
conditional kak-eba tob-eba mat-eba das-eba
tentative kak-oo tob-oo mat-oo das-oo
continuative kak-imasu tob-imasu mat2-imasu da2-imasu
basic kak-u tob-u mats-u das-u
Russian voicing contrasts and assimilation 
Ivan mam-a Ljud-a pap-a Dim-a vod-a 
ot Ivan-a ot-mam-+ ot-Ljud-+ ot-pap-+ od-Dim-+ vot-k-a 
bjez Ivan-a bjez-mam-+ bjez-Ljud-+ bjes-pap-+ bjez-Dim-+ 
Spanish indefinite + noun 
un aro 'an earring' um beso 'a kiss' un dado 'a die' uJ kwerpo 'a body' 
Greenlandic Eskimo (high and mid vowels in complementary distribution) 
ugsik &#8216;cow&#8217; nanoq &#8216;bear&#8217;
iga &#8216;pot&#8217; se&lt;meq &#8216;glacier&#8217;
nuna &#8216;land&#8217; ne&lt;dloq &#8216;goose&#8217;
imaq &#8216;sea&#8217; ipe&lt;aq &#8216;harpoon strap&#8217;
ikusik &#8216;elbow&#8217; o&lt;pik &#8216;tree&#8217;
Kikuyu infinitive prefix 
:o-t"J"ra to run :o-kuua &#8216;to carry&#8217; 
:o-koora &#8216;to root out&#8217; ko-ruya &#8216;to cook&#8217;
ko-oria &#8216;to ask&#8217; ko-m"Ia &#8216;to know&#8217;
ko-h#ta &#8216;to be able&#8217; ko-ina &#8216;to dance&#8217;
ko-niina &#8216;to finish&#8217; :o-kaya &#8216;to cut&#8217;
:o-t2uuka &#8216;to slander&#8217; ko-:aya &#8216;to divide&#8217;
12 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>French: [i] ligne [y] lune [u] loup 
[e] bl&#233; [&#248;] peu [o] eau
["] p&#232;re [&#339;] peur [#] mort
Russian: [i] bitj [+]b+tj [u] budj
'to beat' 'to be' 'be' imper.
Korean:	[e] enuri [*] *di [o] onil
'discount' 'where' 'today'
[8] Turkish vowel harmony 
front back
high iy + u
mid/low " &#339; a #
noun pl. his N.
dal dal-lar dal-+ 'branch'
k#l k#l-lar k#l-u 'arm'
k+z k+z-lar k+z-+ 'daughter'
kul kul-lar kul-u 'slave'
y"l y"l-l"r y"l-i 'wind'
g&#339;l g&#339;l-l"r g&#339;l-y 'sea'
di, di,-l"r di,-i 'tooth'
gyl gyl-l"r gyl-y 'rose'
&#8226; roots contrast for eight possible vowels 
&#8226; most suffixes contrast for just [&#177;high]; values for [back] and [round] determined by harmony 
[&#8211; cons] -&gt; [&#945; back] / [&#945; back] Co ___ (palatal harmony) 
&#8211; cons -&gt; [&#945; round] / [&#945; round] Co ___ (labial harmony)
+high
&#8226; what does grammar predict for &#8216;his slaves&#8217;? 
[9] Tamil (Christdas 1988) 
i u *ji, *je, ja, jo, ju wi, we, wa, *wo, *wu
eo
a (asterisked sequences are ungrammatical)
jw
4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>sounds that undergo rule: [+back] vowels
sounds that trigger rule: [&#8211; back] vowels
sound change: [+back] -&gt; [&#8211;back]
[6] rules can now be defined to express sound changes: to change a sound is to alter its feature specification 
&#8211; cons &#8211;&gt; [&#8211; back] / &#8211; cons Co ____ (Co = zero or more consonants)
+back &#8211; back
&#171;a back vowel changes to the corresponding front vowel when vowel of preceding syllable is a front 
vowel&#187; a rule of assimilation 
rule terminology
focus: matrix to be changed by rule
/ = &#8220;in the context of&#8221;
____environmental dash locates focus relative to context: before or after
structural change: matrix to right of arrow
[7] neutralization of height/ATR contrasts before [r] 
Irish English General American
i weary ! cf. wean
! spirit ! wicked
e fairy " Mary crazy
" ferry " merry sexy
&#230; marry " marry taxi
&#8211; cons -&gt; &#8211; ATR / ____ r 
&#8211; back &#8211; low 
[8] [&#177;round] 
[+round] sounds produced with a compression/pursing of the lips; [&#8211;round] with lips spread 
i y e &#248; " &#339; &#230; a/' ( # ) o * u + 
high + + &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; + + 
low &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; + + + &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; 
back &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; + + + + + + + + 
ATR + + + + &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; + + + + 
round &#8211; + &#8211; + &#8211; + &#8211; &#8211; + + &#8211; + &#8211; + &#8211; 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>----------------labialization: [+round] sa vs. swa cf. whale [hw] vs. wail [w] vs. hail [h] 
palatalization: [+high, &#8211;back] sa vs. sja Russian papa vs. pjatj 'five' 
velarization: [+high, +back] sa vs. sPa leaf vs. feel [l] vs. [Q] 
pharyngealization: [+back,+low] sa vs. s&gt;a Arabic saif 'sword' vs. s&gt;aif 'summer' 
[7] prosodic features 
&#8226;	quantity/length: [&#177;long] duration of articulation
short vs. long vowels: ta vs. ta: (ta vs. taa; taR S
 vs. ta) Czech, Latin 
short vs. long (geminate) consonants: tata vs. tatta (tata vs. tat:a) Italian 
both consonants and vowels: Japanese, Finnish, Hungarian 
Japanese length contrasts
kite &#8216;coming&#8217; ki:te &#8216;listening&#8217;
site &#8216;doing&#8217; sitte &#8216;knowing&#8217;
&#8226; tone: F0 rate of vibration of vocal folds 
level: [&#177;hi], [&#177;lo] 
high vs. nonhigh/low: Moore taA vs. taO Kinande taA vs. ta 
high vs. mid vs. low: Yoruba taA vs. ta vs. taO 
contour:
rise vs. fall: taT vs. taU (Thai)
&#8226; stress: phonetic correlates vary among duration, pitch change, energy 
stressed vs. unstressed: Russian Vpapa 
primary vs. secondary: English WAlaVbama 
further examples 
Korean compounds 
ap 'front' nat 'sickle' kuk 'nation'
ni 'tooth' nal 'edge' min 'person'
am-ni 'front tooth' nan-nal 'edge of sickle' ku&#331;-min 'people'
Spanish article + noun 
kasa goma donFa tat2a boka peka
la-kasa la-&#611;oma la-&#240;onFa la-tat2a la-&#946;oka la-peka
'house' 'gum' 'lady' 'blemish' 'mouth' 'freckle'
11 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>le[j] le[3]es
&#8216;law&#8217; &#8216;laws&#8217;
sonorant consonants allow a preceding voicing contrast while obstruents often trigger neutralization 
(assimilation) 
Russian voicing assimilation:
bjez mam+ bjes pap+ bjez brata
ot mam+ ot pap+ od brata
[6] laryngeal features 
[&#177;voice]: [+voice] sounds have vibration of the vocal folds; [&#8211;voice] sounds lack it 
[&#177;spread glottis]: [+spread gl] is feature for aspirated sounds; 
[&#177;constricted gl]: [+constricted gl] is the feature for glottalized consonants 
[voice] [spread gl] [constricted gl]
voiceless unaspirated: p,t,k &#8211; &#8211; &#8211;
voiced unaspirated: b,d,g + &#8211; &#8211;
voiceless aspirated: ph,th,kh &#8211; + &#8211;
voiced aspirated: bh,dh,gh + &#8211; &#8211;
voiceless glottalized: p,,t,,k, &#8211; &#8211; +
voiced glottalized: L,M,N + &#8211; +
&#8226;	no contrast: Finnish p, t, k (cf. voiceless unaspirated stops of English spin, stem, skin 
&#8226;	binary contrasts
Spanish: p vs. b voiceless vs. voiced paso 'step' vs. basa 'base'&#177;stiff
Mandarin: p vs. ph voiceless vs. aspirated pai 'white' vs. phai 'row'
Nootka: p vs. p, voiceless vs. glottalized pa:-'go' vs. p&amp;a 'give away' 
&#8226;	ternary contrasts
Thai: p vs. ph vs. b paaO'forest' vs. phaaO'to split' vs. baOa 'shoulder'
Korean: p vs. ph vs. p, tal &#8216;moon&#8217; vs. t&#8217;al &#8216;daughter&#8217; vs. thal &#8216;burn&#8217; 
&#8226;	quaternary 
Hindi: p vs. ph and b vs. bh pal 'take care of' vs. phal 'edge of knife' vs. bal 'hair' vs. bhal 'forehand' 
&#8226;	vocal fold vibration is influenced by a variety of factors; Halle &amp; Stevens (1971) propose adding 
features of glottal tension [&#177;stiff] and [&#177;slack] see PGG pp. 40-1 
[6]	secondary articulations: superimposition of vocalic lip and tongue-body articulations in combination with 
the primary oral constriction 
10 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>[4] major place distinctions 
labials: [&#177;labial]: lower (and upper) lip 
[&#8211;labiodental] [+labio-dental] 
[m, p, b, -, .] [G, f, v] Spanish: la [.]aca English: la[v]a 
coronals: [&#177;coronal] front portion of tongue 
dental/alveolar vs. alveopalatal: [&#177;anterior] 
[+anterior] [&#8211;anterior] 
stop t, d c,8 Hungarian: kutya 
fricative s, z ,, 3 English: press [s] p
affricate ts, dz , t,, d3 Mandarin: below 
nasal n I Spanish: cana [n] [c] Magyar [8] 
ressure [2] (cf. coif, coifure) 
canFa [I] 
Mandarin sibilants 
dental tsai 51 &#8216;again&#8217; sai 51 &#8216;compete&#8217; 
postalveolar t6aJ 51 &#8216;rise&#8217; 6aJ 51 &#8216;above&#8217; 
(retroflex) 
alveolo-palatal tKi 55 &#8216;chicken&#8217; Ki 55 &#8216;west&#8217; 
high vs. lower turbulence: [&#177;strident] 
[+strident] [&#8211;strident] 
[s, ts, ,,t,] [0, 1] English: sin vs. thin [0] 
tip vs. blade (apical vs. laminal): [&#177;distributed] 
[&#8211;distributed] [+distributed] 
retroflex [4] interdental [0] 
dental [t/] alveolar [t] Australian Aboriginal 
dorsal: [&#177;dorsal]: tongue body is articulator; 
subsidiary features [high], [back], ([low]) 
[k'] of keep vs. [k] of coop: [&#8211;back] vs. [+back] 
7 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Stress III: weight</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>/nute-t/ *P/&#61611;  Nonfin
&gt;(s's)
(ss') *!
&#8226;	final ranking 
*P/&#61611;  &#187; Nonfin &#187; *P/i,u &#187; *P/e,o &#187; Iambic &#187; Trochaic </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>[5]. Chukchi  (Kamchatka Peninsula, NE Siberia) 
&#8226;	stress in disyllabic window at right edge of base 
&#8226;	Ft-Bin, Align-Rt 
&#8226;	Iambic &#187; Trochaic 
&#8226;	Nonfinality &#187; Iambic 
sg. pl. 
qora&#61504; qo&#61504; -&#61518;&#61611; ra-t reindeer
ri&#61504;cit rici&#61504;t-ti belt
melota&#61504; milu&#61504;
 -l&#61543;&#61611;n te-t rabbit 
/ricit-ti / Iambic Trochaic
(s's)s *!
&gt;(ss')s *
/ricit/ Nonfin Iambic
&gt;(s's) *
(ss') *!
&#8226;	stress will avoid a high vowel in favor of nonhigh; since vowel
harmony prevents [a,o] from combining with [e,i,u] we cannot test all
combinations (cf. jatj&#243;l-te showing no a &gt; o) 
sg. 
we&#61504; bell ni-wen
ke&#61504;li-kel paper
nute&#61504;-nut land
pi&#61518;e&#61504;-pi&#61518; snowfall
*P/i,u &#187; Iambic 
/weni-wen/ *P/i,u Iambic
&gt;(s's) *
(ss') *!
/nute-nut/ *P/i,u Iambic
(s's) * *
&gt;(ss')
&#8226;	schwa: retract stress from final schwa unless penult is schwa, in whichcase do not retract 
pa&#61504;t&#61543;&#61611;r&#61543;-&#61611;n hole </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901  Stress-3: syllable weight in stress and accent systems 
[1]. Many languages (e.g. Latin, Arabic) calculate accent location by dividing syllables 
into heavy vs. light classes 
&#8226; heavy: CVV, CV: 
&#8226; light: CV 
&#8226;	variable: CVC counts as heavy in Latin and Arabic but as light in Mongolian 
Latin: r&#233;ficit, ref&#233;:cit, ref&#233;ctus 
&#8226; some languages distinguish more than two degrees of weight 
[2]. Kelkhar&#8217;s Hindi (Prince &amp; Smolensky ' 93): stress rightmost heaviest syllable; in case 
of tie, stress rightmost nonfinal heaviest: 
&#8226; weight hierarchy: CVVC (S) &gt; CVV, CVC (H) &gt; CV (L) 
&#8226; stress strongest syllable 
ka:r&#237;:gari: 'craftsmanship' H &gt; L 
s&#243;:xjaba:ni: 'talkative' S &gt; H,L 
r&#233;:zga:ri: 'small change' S &gt; H 
&#8226;	ties: rightmost nonfinal
sam&#237;ti 'committee'
q&#237;smat 'fortune'
ro:z&#225;:na: 'daily'
r&#243;:zga:r 'employment'
a:sm&#225;:nja:h 'highly placed'
&#8226; nonfinality blocked when final syllable is strongest 
kidh&#225;r 'which way'
rupi&#225;: 'rupee'
jan&#225;:b 'sir'
asb&#225;:b 'goods'
musalm&#225;:n 'Muslim'
inqil&#225;:b 'revolution'
&#8226; constraints analysis 
Peak Prominence: *L'  &#187;*H' &#187;*S'
Nonfinality: *&#963;' # (penalize stress on final syllable)
Rightmost: *&#963;'&#963; (penalize a stressed syllable followed by an unstressed one)
one stress per word: assumed
&#8226; ranking: Peak-Prominence &#187; Nonfinality &#187;  Rightmost 
&#8226; exemplification tableaux 
1
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>/bagandarladin/ NF *L&#8217; *C&#8217; *H&#8217; Leftmost
ba&#769; *!
 gandarladin
baga&#769; *
 ndarladin
baganda&#769; *
 rladin *!
bagandarla&#769; *!
 din
bagandarladi&#769;n *!
4. Sonority-Driven Stress (Kenstowicz 1997) 
&#8226;	in some languages stress will not be consistently at the left or right edge of the 
foot but may seek out a stronger vowel 
&#8226;	strength seems to track the inherent duration of vowels in two dimensions: 
peripheral &gt; central lower &gt; higher 
&#8226;	the phenomenon has since been documented in a number of other languages 
&#8226;	it is easily modeled in an OT grammar as alignment of Peak Prom constraints with the relevant phonetic dimensions 
[4]. Kobon (New Guinea) 
&#8226;	stress falls in two-syllable window at right edge of word 
&#8226;	it seeks out stronger (more sonorous vowel) 
&#8226;	in case of tie where penult and final of equal weight stress falls on penult 
&#8226;	analysis: align disyllabic foot at right edge of word 
&#8226;	Peak -Prominence &#187;  Trochaic &#187;  Iambic 
3
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>ta&#61504;tl&#61611;&#61518;-&#61611;k to answer
pipi&#61504;q&#61611;l&#61543; -&#61611;n mouse
m&#61611;c&#61611;&#61504;kw-&#61611;n shirt
r&#61611;k&#61543;&#61611;&#61504;t-&#61611;k to &#61543;et stuck
r&#61611;m&#61611;&#61504;t-&#61611;k to wash up
*P/&#61611; &#187; *P/i,u 
/ pipi&#61504;q&#61611;l&#61543;-&#61611;n/ *P/&#61611;  *P/i,u Iambic 
&gt;s(s's)-s * ** 
s(ss')-s *!	 * 
/ r&#61611;m&#61611;t-&#61611;k/
(s's)-s * *
&gt;(ss')-s *
&#8226;	Nonfinality: no retraction of final stress to a schwa unless the penult is
a schwa in which case we do retract 
&#61611;tla&#61504; mother
l&#61611;le&#61504;-t eyes
p&#61611;nu&#61504;n middle
&#61611;&#61504;tl&#61611;q tundra
&#61611;&#61504;tt&#61611;m bone
k&#61611;&#61504;tp&#61611;t sable
n&#250;te-t	 land 
analysis  :  *P/&#61611;  &#187; Nonfin &#187; *P/i,u 
&#8226;	a familiar metrical contraint (NF) embedded within the peakprominence constraint hierarchy that tracks alignment with phonetic
scale of inherent duration 
&#8226;	argues for grammaticalization of the calculation of stress 
/&#61611;tla / *P/&#61611;  Nonfin
 (s's) *! 
&gt;(ss') * 
/ &#61611;tl&#61611;q/ *P/&#61611;  Nonfin 
&gt;(s's) * 
(ss') * *! </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Ties: Rightmost &#187;  Leftmost 
/LLL/ *L' Non-Fin Rightmost Leftmost
L'LL * **!
-&gt;LL' L * * *
LLL' * *! **
Peak -Prom &#187;  Non-Finality 
/LHS/ *L' *H' *S' Non-Fin
L'HS *!
LH'S *!
LHS' * *
observations 
&#8226;	this language presents a "look-ahead" problem for a rule-based system that builds 
up a structure incrementally by rules that examine a local context 
&#8226;	we don' t know whether to assign extrametricality (ignore the final syllable) unless 
we know that that syllable is the strongest in the word 
&#8226;	but this effectively computes the stress 
&#8226;	since OT constraints evaluate fully formed candidate outputs such "global
comparisons" are expected
3. Kashmiri (PPG, 618) 
&#8226;	Weight hierarchy: CV: (H) &gt; CVC (C) &gt; CV (L) 
masr &#225;:wun H &gt; C
zit&#243;:vuh H &gt; L
yuniv&#225;rsiti C &gt; L
&#8226;	ties: mah&#225;:ra:zi Non-Fin: n&#243;yid
bag&#225;ndarladin s&#225;la:m
b&#225;khcanha:r 
ardon&#243;:ri:sor s&#237;rinagar 
&#8226;	analysis: Nonfinality &#187;  Peak Prom &#187;  Leftmost &#187;  Rightmost 
&#8226;	sample tableaux 
2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Tone III: intonation and phrasing</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text> to achieve the same effect in Italian, a word is dislo cated to right (emarginazione) 
where low accent is the norm: adesso faccio scorrere il tuo, di bagnetto &#8220;now I&#8217;ll run 
your b ath&#8221; 
&#8226;	English deaccents non-negat ive indefinite pronouns and "light" nouns 
English Italian 
I saw Mary. Ho sentito Maria. 
I saw something. Ho sentito qualcuno . 
I saw nobody. Non ho sentito nessu no. 
He killed a man. &#8230;perche ha ucciso un uomo. 
He killed a policeman. &#8230;perche ha ucciso un poliziotto. 
&#8226;	In subject+intransitive verb som etimes depart s from final stress in English 
Unaccusatives (subject has no control) Unergatives 
My umbrella broke. My brothers are wrestling. 
The sun came out. Jesus we pt. 
His mother died. The professor swore. 
Abstractions, generics: Wood floats. Hope faded. 
&#8226;	Modifications of lexical stress for contrast 
This whisky wasn&#8217;t expor ted it was depor ted.
Divers found the wreck of the Britannic, sister ship of the Titannic. 
[13] General co nclusion 
&#8226;	Intonation is part of the phonological stru cture of a lan guage and hence exhibits so me cross-
linguistic variation but within a limited space of options 
5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
24.901  Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>24.901 Tone -3: Intonation Nov. 10, 2010 
[1]. Overview 
&#8226;	Traditional analysis of intonation especially in Britain in terms of gross F0 contours such as 
rise for interrogat ive or fall for declarative orie nted with respect to the edge of a phrase or the 
strongest stress (the nuclear accent): assi &#768; &#769; &#769; &#768; milation vs. preliminary 
&#8226;	Strong (invari ant?) correl ation between intonation contour and information content: fall 
associat ed with with com plete inform ation, rise with incom plete inform ation (Bollinger) 
&#8226;	Early gener ativists Liberman (1975) and Goldsmith (1976) propose that au tosegmental-
metrical (AM) model of tone and stress can be applied to analysis of intonation contours: 
fallin g declarative  F0 contour on cabin is phonetically and phonologically comparable to the 
HL tonal analysis of Mende ngi&#769; &#768; and fallin g contour of baloon is comparable to mbu &#770; la
&#8226;	Cf. English loans into Yoruba (Kenstowicz 2006) : 'dollar &gt; do&#769; &#768;, de'cree &gt; diki&#769; &#769;i &#768; la ri
&#8226;	AM m odel applied to analysis of sentential F0 contours in English, Japanese, Romance, 
Hungarian, Korean, Bengali, and many other languages 
&#8226;	Traditional contours analyzed as sequence of turning points (H,L) defined with respect to 
stressed syllab les and edges of phrases and larger units 
&#8226;	Universalist view of Bollinger is revealed to be just a statistical (markedness) tendency 
&#8226;	More recent attempts to model F0 contours more precisely with notions of slope and decay 
[2]. Pierrehumbert (1980) develops general m odel of AM intonation with applicatio n to English and 
later Japanese (Beckman &amp; Pierrehumbert 1988) 
&#8226;	Two tone levels (H and L) suffice for English 
&#8226;	Three tonal categories: pitch accents (e.g. H*, H*+L, ...), boundary tones (H%, %L), and 
phrase tone (H-) 
&#8226;	Spars e repres entation: not every syllable specified for a tone: phonet ic interpol ation between 
tonal targets 
&#8226;	Tones subject to phonetic implementation to generate F0 contour 
&#8226;	ToBi (tone-break-index) tran scription system 
[3]. While English is tonally im poverished for lexical co ntrasts , it has many subtle F0 distinctions at 
the sentence level with grammatical and elusive pragmatic contexts 
[4] some basic co ntours 
&#8226;	declarative:  H* L% interrogative: L* H% vocat ive: H* 'H%
 *  *  *  *
  ** * * * * * * * *  ** * * * * * * 
&#8226;	preliminary assim ilation Abernathy Aloysius 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>[5] more on the vocative 
calling contour; also found in Happy Birthday song (&#8220;Happy Birthday to Jo-ohn&#8221;) 
H*!H H* !H       H *!H      H *-!H H*!H H* !H 
Johnny Jonat han Rebec cah Loui- ise Jo-ohn Abernathy 
French
  H ! H L  H!H H !H          H !H
Monique Anne -Marie Louise Napoleon
[6] High Rising Terminal (ak a &#8220;uptalk&#8221;) 
&#8226; Common in New Zea land, Australia, N. America but not Britain 
&#8226; Pragmatically used to invite acknow ledgem ent: &#8220;Do you follow m e?&#8221; 
&#8226; Transaction opener s: &#8220;I have an appointment with Doctor Macmillan&#8221; 
&#8226; Answer to wh-question: &#8220;What&#8217;s your name?&#8221; &#8220;William Jarvi s&#8221; 
[7] Sentence level 
&#8226;	default final (nuclear) stress: eat meat VP
red car NP
barely tolerable AP
&#8226; some more subtle contrasts (Lad d 1996:208) 
neutral
   H*      H *L L%    H*       H *         H *L L%
I read it to Julia I wanted to read it to Julia
nuanc e: 'and that's that; there's nothing you can do about it' 
H* !H*L L%    H* !H* !H*L L% 
I read it to Julia I wanted to read it to Julia 
nuanc e: 'as you ough t to know; you dummy' 
L*       H *L L%    L*        L *         H *L L% 
I read it to Julia I wanted to read it to Julia 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>[10] focus operators 
the scope of a focus operator like only is m arked by stress 
I showed the letter to Mary.
I only showed the letter to Mary.  (not to Bill)
I only showed the letter to Mary. (not the will)
I only showed th e letter to Mary. (I didn't give it to her)
[11] Crosslinguistic patterns of prominence (Ladd 1996) 
&#8226;	for English, yes/no questions have same default rightmost accent 
&#8226;	but in Russian while statements have default final accent, yes/no questions have default accent 
on the inflected verb 
E She bought a book . Cf. She bought  a book.
R Ona kupila knigu.
E Did she buy a book ? Did she buy a  book?
R Ona kupila knigu? Ona kupila knigu. (focus on book).
R Ona knigu kupila. Did she buy a  book?
[12] For wh questions, English has default final accent if the Wh element is moved to C
 What did you give to Mary? 
&#8226;	In languages with wh-in-situ like Turkish and Bengali, the wh word is focused and attracts 
prominence 
&#8226;	English in-situ echo-questions and multiple wh also seem to attract stre ss 
You gave what to Mary? (cf. *You gave what to Mary?) 
Who gave what to Mary? 
&#8226;	English/Ger manic languages deaccent old (given) information 
I bought her a bottle of whisky, but it tu rns out she doesn't like whisky. 
(cf. Indian English: If yo u don't give me that cigaret te, I will have to buy a cigaret te.) 
not found in Romanian or Italian: le inchieste servono a mettere a pos to cose andante 
fuori posto &#8220;the invest igations serve to put in place things that have gone out of 
place&#8221; 
4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>[8] focus and departure from normal (default) stre ss 
Broad focus (answer to What happened? reporting whole event out of blue with no prior 
context setting up an e xpectation) 
The soldiers entered the hous e. 
Narrow focus: the answer to a wh question 
Who entered the hous e?
The soldiers entered the house.
? The soldiers entered the hous e.
Contrastive focus: one item singled out in comparison to another 
The soldiers entered the house (not the police). 
The soldiers entered the house (not the barn). 
Normal (default) stress vs. focus structure 
&#8226; controversy whether sentences can have metrical stress structure not tied to discourse 
&#8226; or does every sentence have a focus structure? 
The soldiers entered the hous e. 
&#8226;	Used as out of blue broad focus 
&#8226;	Narrow focus on house (What did the soldiers enter?) 
&#8226;	Narrow focus on VP (What did the soldiers do?) 
[9] Languages differ on how focus is m arked 
&#8226;	Particle (Papiamentu, Somali) 
&#8226;	Focus location (Hungar ian: preverbal) 
&#8226;	Shift of major stress away from def ault position (English) 
&#8226;	Change of word order: major sentence stress is more rigidly final and word order changed so 
that focused word appears at right edge (Italian, Catalan) 
&#8226;	Change of phonol ogical phrasing (Korean, Japanese) 
Kyungsang (nwu&#769; nul meknu&#769; na ma&#769; nta) &#8216;sister ate garlic&#8217; 
(nwu&#769; &#769; &#769; focus on object  na) (manul meknunta) 
3 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Phonetics II: acoustics of consonants</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-901-language-and-its-structure-i-phonology-fall-2010/resources/mit24_901f10_lec09/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text> &#169; Unknown. All rights reserved.  Also available at http://phonetics.ucla.edu/course/chapter8/figure8.html
This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license.  
For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text> &#169; Unknown. All rights reserved.  Also available at http://phonetics.ucla.edu/course/chapter8/figure8.html
This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license.  
For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
24.901 Language and Its Structure I: Phonology 
Fall 2010
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text> &#169; Unknown. All rights reserved.  Also available at http://phonetics.ucla.edu/course/chapter6/6aiarstream.html
This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license.  
For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/fairuse .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <videos>
      <video>
        <video_url/>
        <video_title/>
        <transcript>
          <slice>
            <text_slice/>
            <time_slice/>
          </slice>
        </transcript>
      </video>
    </videos>
  </lectures>
</doc>
