<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/9-98-neuropharmacology-january-iap-2009/</course_url>
    <course_title>Neuropharmacology</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Health and Medicine </list>
      <list>Biology </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>PDF - 1.7 MB</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/9-98-neuropharmacology-january-iap-2009/resources/lecture_2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Vesamicol is a drug that blocks the vescicular Ach transporter, therefore decreasing 
Ach transmission: Ach can only be released through vescicles
A Choline transporter  takes back Ach into the presynaptic terminal. If this transporter
Is blocked (hemicolinium-3 (HC-3)) the produc tion of Ach declines. This suggests that 
There is recycling. HC-3 has to be administered locally.
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>Factors that modulate Ach release:
Toxin in the venom of the black widow spider
Induce a massive release of Ach, thereby causing:
tremors, pain, vomiting, salivation, sweating
Botulinum toxins: blocks Ach release
The toxins are picked up by cholinergic neur ons at the neuromuscular junction, thereby
causing muscle paralysis. 
Symptoms: blurred vision, difficulty speaking and swallowing, muscle weakness
At low dosage Botox is used also for therapeutic purposes:
Diseases causes by permanent muscle contraction: dystonias
Also used for reducing wrinkles</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Muscarinic receptors
Metabotropic receptors (M1-M5) that activate different second messenger pathways:
Activation of phosphoinositide
Decrease of cAMP
Stimulation of K+ channels opening
These receptors play an important role in cognitive functions, and those in the
striatum are involved in motor function.
M5 muscarine receptors are involved in morphine reward and dependence
Time spent in morphinepaired
chamber (% change)
0102030
Morphine (mg/kg)0 2.5 5 25M5+/+M5-/-
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Acetylcholine
Factors that regulate Ach synthesis:
Availability of reagents
Firing rates
Since so far there are no drugs that control ChAT, the control of cholinergic system 
happen at different steps of transmissionAcetylcholine is a neurotransmitter in:
Neuromuscular junctions
Periferal Nervous System
Central Nervous System</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Muscarinic receptors outside the nervous system:
Cardiac muscle
Smooth muscles associated with several organs
They modulate heart rate and contractions, salivation, sweating, lacrimation
All these possible side effects need to be take into account for the cognitive 
effects related to muscarinic receptors
Muscarinic receptor AGONISTS (muscarine, pilocarpine, arecoline):
Mime the effects of parasympathetic activa tion: lacrimation, salivation, sweating,
Constriction of the iris, contraction of the smooth muscles of the viscera, diarrhea
Muscarinic receptor ANTAGONISTS (atropine, scopolamine)
Pupillary dilatation, reduction of secretions</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>The firing of the serotoninergic neurons is associated with the behavioral status 
of the animal: the firing slows down with sleep and shut off during REM sleep
In general the firing is constant durin g repetitive movements, like chewing, 
and it suddenly stops when a new stimulus is presented
Induced lesions of the serotoninergic system in animals show that it modulates food
Intake, reproductive behavior, pain sensitivity  and learning and memory4 812162024283236404448
Time (s)REM sleep
Slow-wave sleep
Quiet waking
Active waking
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Drug
DOPA Converted to DA in the brain
Increases catecholamine levels by inhibiting MAO
Depletes catecholamines by inhibiting tyrosine
hydroxylase
Depletes catecholamines by inhibiting vesicular
uptake
Damages or destroys catecholaminergic neurons
Releases catecholamines
Inhibit catecholamine reuptake
Stimulates DA receptors generally (agonist)
Stimulates D 1 receptors (agonist)
Stimulates D 2 and D 3 receptors (agonist)
Blocks D 1 receptors (antagonist)
Blocks D 2 receptors (antagonist)Phenelzine
Reserpine
6-Hydroxydopamine (6-OHDA)
Amphetamine
Cocaine and methylphenidate
Apomorphine
SKF 38393
Quinpirole
SCH 23390
Haloperidola-Methyl-para-tyrosine (AMPT)Drugs that affect the dopaminergic system
Action
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Irreversible inhibitors of AChE:
Sarin and Soman : chemical gases developed in chemical warfare.
They causes paralysis of the diaphragm, hence death
Some analogous  but reversible- blockers of AChE are used as antidote</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>The majority of serotoninergic nuclei are localized in the brainstem 
(medulla, pons and midbrain)
These nuclei are called the raphe nuclei and they are localized on the midline 
of the brain stem
They project to all the forebrain regions
Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 6.17 in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Mesolimbic dopamine pathway:
Domapinergic cells in the Ventral Tegmental Area (VTA) in the mesencephalon
Project to structures of the limbic system: nucleus accumbens, septum, amygdala,
hippocampus
Image removed due to copyright restrictions. Figure 5.7 (Part 2) in
Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Dopaminergic pathways
Dopaminergic neurons are localized in the mesencephalon (midbrain)
Nigrostriatal tract:
cells from the substantia nigra project to  the striatum in the forebrain
This pathway is affected in Parkinson disease. It is involved in control of movementsImage removed due to copyright restrictions. Figure 5.7 (Part 1) in
Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Ach receptors
Nicotinic : ionotropic, distributed mainly in neuromuscular junctions, autonomic
Nervous system, some neurons in the brain.
When they are activated the Na+ and Ca++ ions flow through the channel, thereby
Mediating fast excitatory responses (in case of muscle, contraction)
The nicotinic receptor is made by different subunits
The composition at the neuronal and muscular 
synapses are different.
For example the effects of nicotine are different 
In the brain and in the muscles
A nicotinic receptor antagonist is D-tubocurarine,
That is the main active ingredient of curare.
Curare blocks cholinergic transmission at the
neuromuscular junction therefore causing 
respiratory paralysis.
Interestingly, treatment with neostigmine
(anti AChE) overcomes the effects of curare
AChNa+
ACh
Outside cell
Inside cell
5 nmg
a abd
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>The NE-containing neurons are localized mostly in the LOCUS COERULEUS (LC):
an area in the pons (brain stem). These ce lls provide inputs to cords, cerebellum,
and to several areas in the forebrain.
Also NE neurons are in the ganglia of  the sympathetic branch of the autonomic
nervous system, therefore playing an important role in PNS.Image removed due to copyright restrictions. Figure 5.11 in
Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Dopamine vescicular release 
Vescicles are loaded with catheco-
lamines by the enzyme
Vescicular Monoamine Transporter
(VMAT).
VMATS are blocked by the drug 
Reserpine which causes sedation 
in animals and depressive symptoms
In humans
Catecholamine release is inhibited 
by autoreceptors located on 
dopaminergic and noradrenergic 
neurons
Autoreceptors reduce the amount of calcium that enters theFigure by MIT OpenCourseWare.
terminal in response to a nerve impulse, therefore inhibiting catecholamine release</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Transgenic animals are useful for the characterization of neurotransmitters action
Mutant mice lacking the dopamine
Transporter DAT show an  increaseIn locomotor activityTime (min)Beam breaks
0100200300400
20 60 100 140 180
Wild-type (DAT+/+) Homozygous (DAT-/-)
Heterozygous (DAT+/-)
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Location
Heart Increased rate and force of contraction b
b
b
ba
a
a
aRelaxation
Relaxation
Pupil dilation
Increased fat breakdown and  releaseContraction
Contraction
Contractionba Constriction
DilationBlood vessels
b RelaxationSmooth muscle of the
trachea and bronchi
Uterine smooth muscle
Bladder
Spleen
Iris
Adipose (fat) tissueActionLocation and physiological actions of peripheral a- and b-adrenergic receptors
Receptor subtype
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Figures by MIT OpenCourseWare.
NE transmission and the autonomic nervous system</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Parkinson disease
Caused by death of dopaminergic neurons in the substantia nigraThe major symptoms include deficits in movement, but some patients also show 
Cognitive dysfunctions 
Possible cause: oxyradical-induced oxidative stress that damages/kills
DA neurons
Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Box 5.1 (Part 1) in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Source: Grey's Anatomy. Courtesy of Wikipedia.The autonomic Nervous System</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Figures by MIT OpenCourseWare.
Acetylcholine is fundamental in sympathetic and parasympathetic branches of
Autonomic nervous system</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>5-HT receptors
There are at least 15 receptor subt ypes and they are all metabotropic, 
with the exception of 5-HT3, which is an excitatory ionotropic receptor
5-HT1A is present is many brain areas, including the hippocampus and the amygdala
It acts by inhibiting adenyl cyclase and by opening a K+ channel leading to
membrane iperpolarization
Administration of 5-HT1A agonists produce hyperphagia
The most studied antagonist (WAY-
from the pharmaceutical company) 
produced decrease in body weight 
but it was accompanied by side effects
Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 6.19 (Part 1) in Meyer, and Quenzer,
Psychopharmacology , 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Mesocortical dopamine pathway:
Domapinergic cells in the Ventral Tegmental Area (VTA) in the mesencephalon
project to cerebral cortex
Mesolimbic and mesocortical pathways have been implicated in drug abuse and 
schizophrenia
Other dopaminergic neurones are present in the retina and in the hypothalamus 
these last control the secretion of prolactinImage removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 5.7 (Part 3) in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>The NE neurons in the LC play an important role in the state of VIGILANCE:
being alert to external stimuli.
In vivo electrophysiological recordings
from the LC showed that the firing 
depends on the status of the animal
and the external stimuli
Image removed due to copyright restrictions.Figure 5.12 in
Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
  
 
9.98 Neuropharmacology
January (IAP) 2009
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>5-hydroxytryptamine (5-HT): Serotonin
Starting reagent: tryptophan
Tryptophan hydroxylase is specific of 
Serotoninergic neurons 
A diet rich in carbohydrates leads to the increase of insulin which facilitate glucose
uptake, and also several other aa, but not tryptophan
Since it is the ratio between tryptophan and other aa that is important for crossing the 
BBB a carbo-rich diet would increase the uptake of tryptophan and eventually the 
production of serotoninInvolved in depression, anxiety, obesity, aggression and drug addition
The drug para-chlorophenylalanine (PCPA)
selectively inhibits triptophan hydroxylase, 
Therefore blocking 5-HT synthesisCH2NH2
+ O2CHCOOH
CH2NH2CH
CH2NH2CH2COOHTryptophan
hydroxylaseL-TryptophanN
H
N
H
N
HL-5-Hydroxytryptophan
(5-HTP)
5-Hydroxytryptamine
(5-HT; serotonin)HO
HOAromatic L-amino
acid decarboxylase
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>Serotoninergic transmission is similar to DA and NE transmission
VMAT2 transport 5-HT into vescicles (reserpine blocker)
Presence of auto receptors that modulate firing rate- release
5-HT release can be stimulated by drugs with the structure of amphetamines
Once released, 5-HT is removed from the cleft by the e-HT transporter. 
A blocker of the transporter is fluoexitine (Prozac) that potentiate 5-HT transmission
Monoamine oxidase (MAO) also catabo lites 5-HT producing the metabolite 
5-hydroxyindoleacetic acid (5-HIAA)
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Drug
Vesamicol Depletes ACh by inhibiting vesicular uptake
Stimulates ACh release
Inhibits ACh release
Depletes ACh by inhibiting choline uptake by
the nerve terminal
Increase ACh levels by inhibiting 
acetylcholinesterase reversibly
Inhibit acetylcholinesterase irreversibly
Stimulates nicotinic receptors (agonist)
Nicotinic receptor agonist that causes depolarization
block
Blocks nicotinic receptors (antagonist)
Stimulate muscarinic receptors (agonists)
Block muscarinic receptors (antagonists)Black widow spider venom
Hemicholinium-3
Physostigmine, neostigmine, and 
pyridostigmine
Sarin and Soman
Nicotine
Succinylcholine
D-Tubocurarine
Muscarine, pilocarpine, and arecoline
Atropine and scopolamineBotulinum toxinDrugs and Toxins that affect the Cholinergic System
Action
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>NE modulates :
vigilance
anxiety
pain
hunger and eating behavior
autonomic functions
It is important to consider the localization of receptor
subunits in specific areasImage removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 5.14 in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology , 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Neurotransmitter systems
Glutamate and GABA
Noradrenaline
Acetylcholine
SerotoninDopaminewww.tropea.us</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>3. Modulation of reuptake
Dopaminergic (DA) and Noradrenergic (NE) neurons have specific transporters on 
their membranes for the reuptake of neurotransmitter. These transporters are 
different from the autoreceptors described in point 2.
Drugs that block the transporters increas e the amount of neurotransmitter in the 
Synaptic cleft therefore potentiating catecholamine transmission. 
Reboexitine is a drug that specifically blocks NE uptake
Cocaine blocks the transport of DA, NE and 5-HT
4. Modulation of metabolism
Inside the terminal the transmitters are also catabolized by 2 enzymes:
Catechol-O-methyltransferase (COMT) and monoamide oxidase (MAO)
Degradation of catecholamines produces metabolites: homovanillic acid (HVA) for DA
and 3-methoxy-4hydroxy-phenylglycol (MHPG) (CNS) and vanillymandelic acid (VMA)
(PNS) for NE.
The levels of these metabolites in blood or urines gives important indications for the
catecholaminergic activity and therefore c ontributes to the diagnosis of mental 
disorders
MAO inhibitors (phenelzine or tranylcypro mine) have been used in the treatment of 
Depression. COMT inhibitors: entacapone (Comtan) and tolcapone (Tasmar) are used
As supplememts in the treatment of Parkinson disease.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Localization of cholinergic neurons in  the CNS
Note that in the striatum (the target of dopaminergic neuronsfrom substantia nigra),
there are cholinergic interneurons. The control of movement depends on the balance 
between cholinergic and dopaminergic transmission. Therefore in Parkinson disease
anticholinergic drugs are also used to improve the control of movements: orphenadrine
(Norflex), benztropine mesylate (Cogentin), trihexyphenidyl (Artane)
Neurons of the BFCS are involved in cognitive functions
Role of cholinergic system in Alzheimer diseaseImage removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 6.7 in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology , 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>The receptors of NE and EPI are called ADRENERGIC RECEPTORS and they are
Metabotropic receptors.
They are distinguished in alpha ( 1 and  2 ) and beta ( 1 and  2)
1 and 2 receptors increase the levels of cAMP. 
2 receptors inhibit adenilyl cycl ase and increase K channels opening
1 receptors act with phosphoinositide as second messenger inducing an increase 
of Ca++ in the postsynaptic cell
The effects of drugs for the NE system are measured by looking at the vigilance: 
phenylephrine is  1 receptor agonist, while isoproterenol is a receptors agonist 0300600900120015001800Time awake (s)
Pre 1 Pre 2 Post 2 Post 1
Combined Phenylephrine Isoproterenol Control
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Catecholamines:
Dopamine (DA)
Norepinephrine (NE)
Epinephrine (EPI)
The rate-limiting enzyme is TH, which is regulated by the product (feedback)
and by stress (up-regulated).Catecholamines are synthesized in a multi-step process
NH2 CH CH
COOHTyrosine hydroxylase (TH)Tyrosine
DOPA
NorepinephrineHO
HOHO
Aromatic amino
acid decarboxylase (AADC)H
NH2 CH CH
HCOOH
DopamineHO
HO
Dopamine b-hydroxylase (DBH)NH2 CH2 CH
H
HO
HONH2 CH2 CH
OH
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Release of catecholamines is dependent on neuronal cell firing
Some drugs induce the release independently from nerve cell firing. 
Psychostimulants such as amphetamine and methamphetamine in humans cause 
increased alertness, euphoria, insomnia.In animal models increase in catecholamine release produces increased locomotor
activity and stereotyped behaviorModulation of catecholamine action
1. Modulation of release
2. Modulation of autoreceptors
Stimulation of autoreceptors inhibits catecholamine release
Autoreceptor antagosists, increase catecholamine release</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Drug
Increases catecholamine levels by inhibiting MAO
Depletes catecholamines by inhibiting tyrosine
hydroxylase
Depletes catecholamines by inhibiting vesicular
uptake
Damages or destroys catecholaminergic neurons
Releases catecholamines
Inhibit catecholamine reuptake
Seletively inhibits NE reuptake
Stimulates a 2-receptors (agonist)Stimulates a 1-receptors (agonist)
Stimulates b-receptors (partially selective for b 2)
Blocks a 1-receptors (antagonist)
Blocks a 2-receptors (antagonist)Phenelzine
PhenylephrineReserpine
6-Hydroxydopamine (6-OHDA)
Amphetamine
Cocaine and methylphenidate
Desipramine
Clonidine
Albuterol
Prazosin
Yohimbine
Blocks b-receptors generally (antagonist) Propranolol
Blocks b 1-receptors (antagonist) Metoprolola-Methyl-para-tyrosine (AMPT)Drugs that affect the Noradrenergic system
Action
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Acetylcholinesterase (AChE) degrades ACh
It is localized in the presynaptic terminal, in the membrane of the postsynaptic
terminal, and at the neuromuscular junctions
Drugs that block AChE increase the effects of Ach transmission
Physostigmine (Eserine) blocks AChE therefore causing: loss of reflexes, mental
confusion, allucination, convulsions, slurred speech. It crosses the BBB.
Neostigmine (Prostigmin) and pyrodostigmine (Mestinon) are analogous of 
Physostigmine that do not cross the BBB. They are used for the treatment of 
Myasthenia gravis: an autoimmune disorder  where antibodies attack cholinergic
Receptors at the neuromuscular junction, therefore in these patients the muscles 
are less sensitive to Ach. Reversible inhibitors:
These substances are used at low dosage also in pesticides</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>5-HT1A stimulation also produced reduction is anxiety, and this is what is used in 
the medication Buspar-commercial name for busiprone.
Another effect of 5-HT1A agonist is the inhibition of alcohol consumption
5-HT2A receptors acts by activating protein kinase C,
They are present in cerebral cortex.
Agonist of this receptor cause Hallucinations, and this 
Is supposed to be related to the effects of lysergic acid 
Diethylamide (LSD) 
The best known agonist is DOI (1-(2,5-dimethoxy-4-iodophenyl)
-2-aminopropane
Known antagonists are ketanserin and ritanserin. 
In general, these antagonists can be used for the treatment of schizophrenia. 
Recently, drugs that act on both the DA and 5-HT system have shown 
the best results for the treatment of schizophrenia with lower side effects Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 6.19 (Part 2) in Meyer and Quenzer,
Psychopharmacology , 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Dopamine receptors agonists and antagonists  control dopaminergic-related functions
Apomorphine is an agonist of both D1 and D2 receptors
SFK38393 is an activator of D1 receptor s and in mice it enhances self-grooming 
behavior
Quinprole affects D2 and D3 receptors. It causes an increase in locomotion and
Sniffing behavior
Antagonists of dopaminergic receptors cause catalepsy: lack of spontaneous 
movements
Haloperidol causes catalepsy through D2 re ceptors, SCH acts through D1 receptors
After prolonged treatment with D receptor  antagonists the animals develop behavioral 
supersensitivity, meaning that their reaction to dopaminergic stimulants is increased</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Dopamine receptors are found in the afferent stuctures of dopaminergic neurons
There are 5 known receptors: D1-D5 and they are all metabotropic receptors
D1 receptors stimulate cAMP production, while activation of D2 receptors inhibits
The production of cAMP.
This happens through the stimulation of 2 different G-proteins (D1/Gs-D2/Gi)
In addition, D2 also activates potassium channelsImage removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 5.9 in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Localized application of the neurotoxin  6-hydroxydopamine (6-OHDA) is used to 
Examine the role of specific pathways in behavior.
This neurotoxin is similar to DA, and therefore is taken selectively by dopaminergic
Neurons which are damaged and die
Image removed due to copyright restrictions. 
Figure 4.1 (Part 1) in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Mice that lack D1 receptors are insensitive to locomotor stimulating effects 
induced by cocaine
Beam breaks
05000100001500020000Wild-type (D1+/+)
Day1 2 3 4 5 6 705000100001500020000Mutant (D1-/-)
Day1 2 3 4 5 6 7
Control Cocaine
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>Drug
Depletes 5-HT by inhibiting tryptophan hydroxylase
Depletes 4-HT by inhibiting vesicular uptake
Release 5-HT from nerve terminals (MDMA and 
para-chloroamphetamine also have neurotoxic effects)
Inhibits 5-HT reuptake
5-HT neurotoxin
Stimulate 5-HT 1A receptors (agonists)
Blocks 5-HT 1A receptors (antagonist)
Stimulates 5-HT 2A receptors (agonist)
Block 5-HT 2A receptors (antagonists)para-Chlorophenylalanine
para-Chloroamphetamine, 
fenfluramine, and MDMA
DOIReserpine
Fluoxetine
5,7-Dihydroxytryptamine
Buspirone, ipsapirone, 
and 8-OH-DPAT
WAY 100635
Ketanserin and ritanserinDrugs that affect the Serotonergic system
Action
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Effects
Agonists:
Antagonists:receptors stimulation leads to constriction of the blood vessels in the bronchial 
lining, this reducing congestion and edema. 
The agonist phenylephrine in the ingredien t in Neosynephrine (a nasal spray) 
receptors stimulation induce relaxation of the bronchial muscles, therefore providing
A wider airway. In fact albuterol in a ve ry popular local medication in asthma
Prazosin is a  1 receptors antagonist and causes a relaxation of the blood vessels 
Propanolol is a receptors blocker that reduces the hearts contractile force.
They are both used as treatment for high blood pressure 
Blockers are in general used to treat the symptoms of anxiety disorders: palpitation,
tachycardia</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Neuropsychiatric disorders: anxiety, mood disorders (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/9-98-neuropharmacology-january-iap-2009/resources/lecture_3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>The majority of serotoninergic nuclei are localized in the brainstem 
(medulla, pons and midbrain)
These nuclei are called the raphe nuclei and they are localized on the midline 
of the brain stem
They project to all the forebrain regions
Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 6.17 in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Barbiturates action/applications changes according their solubility
Over time, with tolerance, the balance desired effect-side effect shift toward the last one
They are used to induce anesthesia
Their interaction with alcohol is dangerousUltrashortDuration of action
Short/intermediateThiopental (Pentothal)
Amobarbital (Amytal)
Secobarbital (Seconal)
Pentobarbital (Nembutal)HighLipid
solubilityDuration of action and uses of major barbiturates
Onset Duration Use
Moderate
Low Long
Phenobarbital (Luminal)Mephobarbital (Mebaral)10-20 s 20-30 min
5-8 h 20-40 min
Over 1 h 10-12 h Prolonged sedation
and seizure controlIntravenous
anesthesia
Surgical anesthesiaand sleep inductionMethohexital (Brevital)
DoseResponseInitial drug use
ToleranceMargin of safety
Desired ef fect Respiratory depression
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>There is a direct correlation between GABA and anxiety
There are less BDZ receptors in patients with anxiety
There are endogenous diazepam binding inhibitor that induce anxietyImage removed due to copyright restrictions. Figure 17.19 in
Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>Glucocorticoid hypothesis:
prolonged increase of glucocorticoid levels in blood determines  a reduction
In the dendritic branching and neurogenesis in the hippocampus, therefore 
Causing the cognitive deficits associated to depression.
Neurotrophic hypothesis:
Low BDNF is responsible of the impairments
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.Normal Stress Antidepressants
Normal survival
and growthAtrophy and
decreased 
survival
Increased
vulnerabilityIncreased survival
and growthBDNF BDNFNE and 5-HT Glucocorticoids</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Bipolar disorders are treated with Lithium carbonate. 
It is usually administered together with another antidepressant drug
Lithium enhance brain tryptophan therefore enhancing 5-HT actions.
It has effects on second messenger systems and brain neurotrophic factors.
Side effects: Lithium is directly secreted by the kindey at a rate inversely related to 
Sodium levels. Decrease in sodium levels leads to dehydratation, diarrhea, vomiting,
Even seizures, coma and death. 
For these reasons it has to be taken in low concentration.Manic episode Depressive episodeTime between episodes (years)
12345678910
With lithium Without lithium
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>There are several evidences in humans that the serotoninergic transmission is
Decreased in depressed patients:
In post mortem brains it has been observed a reduction of  the 5-HT metabolite
In post-mortem brains there in an increase in the 5-HT receptors
Depressed patients have a low level of blood tryptophane
PET studies have shown that in depresse d patients there is an increase in metabolic
Activity in amygdala and orbitofrontal cortex.
The activity is correlated with the severity of depression and with the treatments.
Studies in animals confirmed the involvement of 5-HT in depression</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD)
occur after a traumatic event such as war, a terroristic attack, natural disasters
People with PTSD have problems with: s ubstance abuse, marital problems, 
Depression, sense of guilt
Children whose parents have PTSD have a igher probability of having PTSD
Suggesting that there is a body factor that fecilitate the onset.
Also important are history of chronic stress, trauma, abuse.
Obsessive-compulsive disorders
Characterized by recurrent and persistent thoughts (Obsessions) that cause to the 
Individual a sense od anxiety, guilt, shame. 
In the aim to releive these symptoms the individual performs repetitive rituals 
(Compulsions) related or not to the obsessions.
The individual thinks that unless the compulsive ritual is completed, disasters will 
occur.
Some people with OCD also suffer from other movement disorders such as:
Tourettes syndrome, Sydenhams chorea and Parkinsons disease</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>Summary of the hypothesis:
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Brain areas interested in OCD
Imaging analysis shows that the following 
regions are involved in anxiety:
Basal ganglia, frontal cortex, thalamus, and
Anterior cingulate cortex. Neurosurgery that 
destroys the connections in this loop 
relieves the symptoms of anxietyImages removed due to copyright restrictions. Boxes 17.1 (A),
17.1 (B), and 17.1 (C) in Meyer and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>The firing of the serotoninergic neurons is associated with the behavioral status 
of the animal: the firing slows down with sleep and shut off during REM sleep
In general the firing is constant durin g repetitive movements, like chewing, 
and it suddenly stops when a new stimulus is presented
Induced lesions of the serotoninergic system in animals show that it modulates food
Intake, reproductive behavior, pain sensitivity  and learning and memory4 812162024283236404448
Time (s)REM sleep
Slow-wave sleep
Quiet waking
Active waking
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>The sleep pattern is altered in depressed patients
Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 16.5 (Part 2) in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology , 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>There is a connection between the NE system and anxiety
In general, the NE system is activated by alerting situations
Some of the effects of anxiolytic drugs can be explained with the modulation of LC firing
LC firing is activated by the corticotropin-releasing factor and it is inhibited by GABA
and serotonin.
This explain why depression and anxiety are often related and why SSRI are 
effective in treating anxiety
Also, increased levels of corticotropin-releasing factor (CRF) are related to anxiety
There are indications that increased DA transmission produces anxiety, while
Treatments that increase 5HT transmission also reduce anxietyInteractions between anxiety and neurotransmitters</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>We all experienced feelings associated with depression and this 
is not pathologic.
When the symptoms are disproportionate or prolonged it constitute 
mental illnessDiagnosis SymptomSymptoms of manic episodes and major depression (Part 2)
Major depressive
episodeDepressed mood (or irritable mood in children and
adolescents) most of the day, nearly every day
Diminished interest or pleasure in most activities most of the
day, every day
Significant changes in body weight or appetite (gain or loss)
Insomnia or hypersomnia nearly every day
Psychomotor agitation (increased activity) or retardation
(decreased activity)
Fatigue or loss of energy
Feelings of worthlessness or excessive or inappropriate guilt
Diminished ability to think or concentrate; indecisiveness
Recurrent thoughts of death, recurrent suicidal ideation
without a specific plan, or a suicide attempt or specific
plan for committing suicide
Source: American Psychiatric Association, 1994.
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Serotoninergic transmission is similar to DA and NE transmission
VMAT2 transport 5-HT into vescicles (reserpine blocker)
Presence of auto receptors that modulate firing rate- release
5-HT release can be stimulated by drugs with the structure of amphetamines
Once released, 5-HT is removed from the cleft by the e-HT transporter. 
A blocker of the transporter is fluoexitine (Prozac) that potentiate 5-HT transmission
Monoamine oxidase (MAO) also catabo lites 5-HT producing the metabolite 
5-hydroxyindoleacetic acid (5-HIAA)
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>In response to stress the hypothalamus 
Produces the corticotropin-releasing
Factor (CRP) that acts on the pituitary gland
Inducing the release of the adrenocorticotropic
Hormone (ACTH).
ACTH goes in the blood and reaches the 
adrenal gland where it increases the secretion
Of glucocorticoids, in particular cortisol.
Cortisol activates the energy to deal with
Stress.  Cortisol feedbacks on hypothalamus
This is called the H-P-A axis
(Hypothalamus-Pituitary-Adrenal)
In animal models, stress is induced by separating young animals from their mothers 
for brief periods daily during the first weeks of life.Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 16.3 in Meyer, and Quenzer,
Psychopharmacology , 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Discovering antidepressants
Animal models
Reduction of psychomotor activity,
Cognitive changes
Eating/sleeping
The interaction between genetic and environmental factors  is important for the 
onset of depression
Genetic factors are considered:
Decrease in the monoamine levels
Increased activity of the HPA axis to stress
Experiments on rodents proved that deprived animals respond more to stress</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Selective Serotonin reuptake inhi bitors (fluoexitine, PROZAC)
are used to treat, among others:
Depression, anxiety disorders, obsessive-compulsive disorders, obesity
They act mostly on 5-HT reuptake, and ther efore they avoid all the side effects 
due to increased NE transmission
Side effects: anxiety, restlessness, movement disorders, insomnia, headache and
sexual dysfunction
They also cause physical dependence
Electroconvulsive therapy:
It has been observed that there was an improv ement of the mood in patients having
Spontaneous seizures. Therefore inducin g convulsions can be beneficial for 
Patients that are not sensible to drug treatments.
This treatment is very expensive. It probably works by acting on several 
Neurotransmitter systems. The main side effect are confusion and memory loss.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Affective disorders:
Major depression
Bipolar disorders
Depression
Loss of interest in almost anything
Inability to experience pleasure in anythingFeelings of hopelessness, sadness, worthless, guilt and desperation
Loss of appetite, insomnia, cryi ng, fatigue, thoughts of suicide
Episodes recur throughout life
The mean of onset for depression is 27 years
Bipolar Disorders
Manic individuals feel faultless, full of  fun, and energetic. They need less sleep.
They make impulsive decisions and have unlimited confidence in themselves.
Onset between 20 and 30 years of age and episodes continue throughout life.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Anxiety disorders
Anxiety is a feeling of apprehension, fear, or worry. 
Anxiety can be a good thing: It warns for danger and it increases our energy level 
pushing us to work harder and longer
When anxiety is very intense in can cause discomfort or even terror 
Anxiety is commonly associated to depression
There are five principal categories of anxiety disorders:
Generalized anxiety disorder (GAD)
Panic disorders
Phobias
Post-traumatic stress disorder
Obsessive-compulsive disorder</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Possible treatments:
All these methods act enhancing monoamine transmission.
They require chronic administration, suggesting that the clinical 
effects are due to changes that occur over timeClass
Monoamine oxidase
inhibitors
Classic tricyclics
Second-generation:
Selective serotonin
Atypical antidepressants Maprotiline (Ludiomil)
Bupropion (Wellbutrin)
Mirtazapine (Remeron)
Memory impairment, 
confusion, amnesiaVaries with individual
mechanism of actionInsomnia, gastrointestinal
disturbances, sexual
dysfunction, serotonin
syndromeInsomnia, weight gain,
hypertension, drug inter-
actions, tyramine effect
Sedation, anticholinergic
effects, cardiovascular
toxicity
Fluoxetine (Prozac)Imipramine (Tofranil)Phenelzine (Nardil)AntidepressantsMajor Classes of Antidepressants and Their Most Notable Side Effects
Side effects
Tranylcypromine (Parnate)
Isocarboxazid (Marplan)
Amitriptyline (Elavil)
Desipramine (Norpramine)
Sertraline (Zoloft)
Paroxetine (Paxil)
Electroconvulsive shock
and transcranial magnetic
stimulationreuptake inhibitors
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Stress induces transient surges of cortisol
In depressed individuals there is  an abnormal secretion of cortisol
In this case the hypersecr etion is due to an abnormal
production of CRP by the hypothalamus.
Antidepressant therapies reduce the CRF level in
depressed patients
Dexamethasone (a synthetic glucocorticoid that 
act as a negative feedback on the hypothalamus) 
Cause a decrease in th e levels of cortisolImage removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 16.5 (A) in Meyer, and Quenzer,
Psychopharmacology, 2004.Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 16.5 (B) in Meyer, and Quenzer,
Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Generalized Anxiety Disorders:
Constant worry. Muscle tension and agitation that lead to fatigue, 
poor concentration, irritab ility and sleep difficulties.
It tends to run in families
Panic disorders:
Experiencing the effects of a fear reacti on without a threatening stimulus. Symptoms:
Heart pounding, chest pain, sweating, shortness of breath
This can happen in response to an external cue, or without warning or in situations
Where attack occurred previously.
There is a clear genetic predisposition.
Phobias:
Irrational fears related to special 
objects or situationsPhobiaSome common (*) and less common phobias
Acrophobia*
Aichmophobia
Ailurophobia
Algophobia
Astraphobia*
Claustrophobia*
Hematophobia*
Monophobia*
Nyctophobia
Ochlophobia
Pyrophobia
Thanatophobia*
Xenophobia* StrangersDeathFireCrowdsDarkness, nightBeing aloneBloodTight enclosuresStorms, thunder, lightningPainCatsSharp, pointed objects; knivesHeightsFear of
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>5-hydroxytryptamine (5-HT): Serotonin
Involved in depression, anxiety, obesity, aggression and drug addition
Starting reagent: tryptophan
Tryptophan hydroxylase is specific of 
Serotoninergic neurons 
The drug para-chlorophenylalanine (PCPA)
selectively inhibits triptophan hydroxylase, 
Therefore blocking 5-HT synthesis
A diet rich in carbohydrates leads to the increase of insulin which facilitate glucose
uptake, and also several other aa, but not tryptophan
ince it is the ratio between tryptophan and ot her aa that is important for crossing the 
BB a carbo-rich diet would increase the uptake of tryptophan and eventually the S
B
production of serotoninCH2NH2
+ O2CHCOOH
CH2NH2CH
CH2NH2CH2COOHTryptophan
hydroxylaseL-TryptophanN
H
N
H
N
HL-5-Hydroxytryptophan
(5-HTP)
5-Hydroxytryptamine
(5-HT; serotonin)HO
HOAromatic L-amino
acid decarboxylase
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Tricyclic antidepressants act by binding th e presynaptic transporter proteins and
Inhibiting the reuptake.
They also block acetylcholine , histamine , -adrenergic receptors , determining:
Sedation and fatigue, dry mouth, constipation , cardiovascular problemsIncreasing selectivity for NE
Increasing selectivity for 5-HTAmitriptyline
Imipramine
Nortriptyline
Maprotiline
Clomipramine
Fluoxetine
Sertraline
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Occurrence of OCD symptoms
0 10 20 30 40 50Percent of patients reporting
Dirt, germs, or environmental toxins
Something terrible happening
Symmetry, order, or exactness
Excessive praying or religious concern
Bodily wastes or secretions
Lucky or unlucky numbers
Forbidden, aggressive, or perverse sexual thoughts
Fear might harm others or oneself
Intrusive nonsense sounds, words, or musicPrimary symptom: Preoccupation with(A) Obsessions
0 20 40 60 80 100Percent of patients reporting
Ritualized hand washing, bathing, or grooming
Repeating rituals
Checking
Rituals to remove contact with contaminants
Measures to prevent harm to self or others
Ordering or arranging
Counting
Hoarding or collecting rituals
Rituals of cleaning household or inanimate objectsPrimary symptom(B) Compulsions
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>5-HT1A stimulation also produced reduction in anxiety, and this is what is used in 
the medication Buspar-commercial name for busiprone.
Another effect of 5-HT1A agonist is the inhibition of alcohol consumption
5-HT2A receptors acts by activating protein kinase C,
They are present in cerebral cortex.
Agonist of this receptor cause hallucinations, and this 
Is supposed to be related to the effects of lysergic acid 
Diethylamide (LSD) 
The best known agonist is DOI (1-(2,5-dimethoxy-4-iodophenyl)
-2-aminopropane
Known antagonists are ketanserin and ritanserin. 
In general, these antagonists can be used for the treatment of schizophrenia. 
Recently, drugs that act on both the DA and 5-HT system have shown 
the best results for the treatment of schizophrenia with lower side effects Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 6.19 (Part 2) in Meyer , and Quenzer,
Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Risk Factors:
Heredity
Environmental stress
Altered biological rhythmsCorrelation between mood disorders and creativity
10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80
Rate (%)Expected rate in general population
Andreasen's study of writers (1987)
Jamison's study of artists
and writers (1989)
Schildkraut and Hirshfeld's
study of artists (1990)
Akiskal and Akiskal's study of artists
and writers (unpublished)
Jamison's study of British poets born
between 1705 and 1805 (1989)
Montgomery and Montgomery's
study of poets (1993)
Ludwig's study of poets (1992)
Major depressive illness Manic depressive illness
Cyclothymia SuicideCorrelation Between Mood Disorders And Creativity
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Drug
Depletes 5-HT by inhibiting tryptophan hydroxylase
Depletes 4-HT by inhibiting vesicular uptake
Release 5-HT from nerve terminals (MDMA and 
para-chloroamphetamine also have neurotoxic effects)
Inhibits 5-HT reuptake
5-HT neurotoxin
Stimulate 5-HT 1A receptors (agonists)
Blocks 5-HT 1A receptors (antagonist)
Stimulates 5-HT 2A receptors (agonist)
Block 5-HT 2A receptors (antagonists)para-Chlorophenylalanine
para-Chloroamphetamine, 
fenfluramine, and MDMA
DOIReserpine
Fluoxetine
5,7-Dihydroxytryptamine
Buspirone, ipsapirone, 
and 8-OH-DPAT
WAY 100635
Ketanserin and ritanserinDrugs that affect the Serotonergic system
Action
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>This is known as MONOAMINE HYPOTHESYS, and it is based on the 
following observations:
Manic-like activity produced by amphet amine and cocaine is correlated with an 
Increase of chatecolamines at the synapses 
Reduction of movements in depression
Mechanism of action of the MOAi
It is very likely that NE and 5-HT systems interactions are responsible of depression
Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 16.14 (Part 1) and 16.14 (Part 2) in
Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>The effects of MAO-I according to thei r time course should be on the post-synaptic
Modifications and effects of the second messenger.
Side effects: it enhances the NE transmissi on in peripheral nerves of the sympathetic 
Branch and therefore it amplify the effects of  all the medications  that increase NE: 
nasal spray, cold medications, antiasthma drugs.
Also the foods that contain tyramine enhance NE transmission in terminals and 
should be avoided.
NE transmission increases blood pressure. 
MAOi inhibits some liver enzymes that catabolize barbiturates, alcohol, aspirin, 
therefore amplifying the effects of these drugs.Food group ExamplesDietary restrictions for patients taking MAO-Is
Dairy
Meat and meat alternativesUnpasteurized milk and yogurt; aged cheese; other cheeses
including blue, Boursault, brick, Brie, Camembert, cheddar,Colby, Emmenthaler, Gouda, Gruyere, mozzarella, ParmesanProvolone, Romano, Roquefort, and Stilton
Aged game; liver; canned meats; yeast extracts; salami;
dry sausage; salted, dried, smoked, or pickled fish such asherring, cod, and caviar; peanuts
Homemade yeast breads with substantial quantities of
yeast; bread or crackers containing cheese
Italian broad beans, sauerkraut, bananas, red plums,
avocados, raspberries
Alcoholic beverages including red and white table wines,
ale, beer, champagne, sherry, and vermouth; yeast concentrates,
soup cubes, commercial gravies, or meat extracts; soups containing items that must be avoided; soy sauce; soy bean
curd (hoison)Breads, cereals, and grains
Vegetables and fruits
Miscellaneous
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Different benzodizepines are metabolized in a different way and therefore they 
have a different interval of action
They are used as hypnotics, muscle relaxant
Anticonvulsants.
They have very low effects on respiration, but
They give dependence
A new anxiolytic is Busiprone, that does  not interfere with other CNS depressants
therefore is safer, but it has a very slow action. 
It has no effects on GABA tranmission: it is a partial agonist of 5-HT1A receptor
Often antidepressant drugs are used to treat anxietyImage removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 17.11 in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Study of concordance in
Monozygotic twins and dizygotic
Twins indicate a major role for
Heredity in bipolar disorders
Identical twinsAny mood
disorderSevere
depressionDepressionBipolar
disorder80
60
40Concordance rate (%)
20
0
Fraternal twins
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
  
 
9.98 Neuropharmacology
January (IAP) 2009
or information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms. 
F</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>The discovery of anti-depressive treatments happened by chance
It was observed that reserpine, a drug that reduces high blood pressure
Induces depression as side effect
Therefore the antidepressant are tested as molecules capable of reverse the
Reserpine-induced sedation
Remember that reserpine prevents the pack aging of neurotransmitters into vescicles,
Leaving the monoamines in the cytoplasm, where the MAO degrades them
Therefore Reserpine reduces the transmission of monoamines
(dopamine, norepinephrine and serotonin). MAO-inhibitors are therefore used as 
Antidepressants.
Images removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 16.7 (Part 1), 16.7 (Part 2), and 16.7 (Part 3)
in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>5-HT receptors
There are at least 15 receptor subt ypes and they are all metabotropic, 
with the exception of 5-HT3, which is an excitatory ionotropic receptor
5-HT1A is present is many brain areas, including the hippocampus and the amygdala
It acts by inhibiting adenyl cyclase and by opening a K+ channel leading to
membrane iperpolarization
Administration of 5-HT1A agonists produce hyperphagia
The most studied antagonist (WAY-
from the pharmaceutical company) 
produced decrease in body weight 
but it was accompanied by side effects
Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 6.19 (Part 1) in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.Diagnosis SymptomSymptoms of manic episodes and major depression (Part 1)
Manic episode Inflated self-esteem or grandiosity
Decreased need for sleep (e.g., feeling rested after only 3
hours of sleep)
Greater talkativeness than usual or pressure to keep talking
Flight of ideas or feeling that thoughts are racingDistractibility (i.e., attention too easily drawn to unimportant
external stimuli)
Increase in goal-directed activity (either socially, at work, or
sexually); agitation
Excess involvement in pleasurable activities that have a high
potential for painful consequences (e.g., unrestrained buyingsprees, sexual indiscretions, or foolish investments)
Source: American Psychiatric Association, 1994.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Drugs for treating anxiety
They are called anxiolytics and belong to the CNS depressants 
They reduce neuron excitability by enhancing GABA transmission
They are alcohol, barbiturates and benzodiazepinesWith increased doses, they cause al so sedation, anesthesia and even death
Barbiturates and benzodiazepines both enhance GABA transmission. Barbiturates
increase the duration of the opening of the channel and directly open the Cl- channel
without GABA. Benzodiazepines have no e ffects with no GABA. They increase the 
frequency of channel opening.DeathComaGeneral anesthesia
Decreasing consciousnessSleepSedationRelief from anxietyAlertness
Increasing dose of drug
 Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Neuropsychiatric disorders: schizophrenia, final exam (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/9-98-neuropharmacology-january-iap-2009/resources/lecture_4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Positive symptoms:
Negative symptoms:Hallucinations
Disorganized speech
Treated with antagonist of D2 receptors, aggravated by increasing DA transmission
Reduced speech
Social withdrawal
Intellectual impairement
Loss of motivation/ emotions
Treated with the  atypical antipsychotics</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
  
 
9.98 Neuropharmacology
January (IAP) 2009
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>PPI is a measure of the gate
It is disrupted by systemic administration of  DA agonists and reinstated by 
DA receptor-blocking antipsychotic drugs
PPI is also disrupted by systemic administration of serotonin agonists and
Glutamate antagonists
Generic name
(trade name)
Typical antipsychotics
Chlorpromazine (Thorazine)
Prochlorperazine (Compazine)
Triflupromazine (Vesprin)
Thioridazine (Mellaril)
Trifluoperazine (Stelazine)Sedation
Moderate
Moderate Moderate ModerateModerate High High High
Moderate-high Moderate-high Moderate-high
ModerateModerate ModerateLow-moderate Low-moderate
Low-moderate
Low-moderateLow-moderateLow Low
Low
Fluphenazine (Prolixin) Low Low LowLow
Low Low Perphenazine (Trilafon)
Mesoridazine (Serentil) Moderate Moderate High Low
Thiothixene (Navane) Low
Very lowVery low Haloperidol (Haldol) Low High-very highHighHighHighHigh
High
Moderate-high
Loxapine (Loxitane)
Molindone (Moban)Low LowLowLow
LowHypotensionb Motor disordersPartial list of commonly used traditional and atypical antipsychotic drugs and their side effects (Part 1)
Includes blurred vision, dry mouth, reduced gastric secretion and motility, urinary retention, and constipation.
Drop in blood pressure upon standing upright (orthostatic), dizziness, faintness, or blacking out.Autonomicside effects
b
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>EEG show that in schizofrenics, the electrical activity evoked by a stimulus is not 
localized, as in normal subjects, but it is widespread in the brain
Linkage studies across affected individuals identified specific loci on chromosomes
13, 8, 22 and 6Genetic studies
Microarray analysis revealed impairments of transcripts for the presynaptic
function in the prefrontal area, but also defects in glutamatergic and GABAergic
Transmission, energy metabolism and growth factorsNeurophysiological studies
Hypofrontality
Schizofrenia is a neurodevelopmental disorder</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>The mechanisms of action are not clearGeneric name
(trade name)
Atypical antipsychotics
Clozapine (Clozaril)
Olanzapine (Zyprexa)
Risperidone (Risperdal)
Quetiapine (Seroquel)
Ziprasidone (Zeldox)Sedation
Moderate-high
ModerateModerate
ModerateModerate
Moderate
Moderate
ModerateModerate-high
ModerateLow-moderate
LowLowLow
LowVery low
Very low
Very low LowVery low-lowHypotensionb Motor disordersPartial list of commonly used traditional and atypical antipsychotic drugs and their side effects (Part 2)
Includes blurred vision, dry mouth, reduced gastric secretion and motility, urinary retention, and constipation.
Drop in blood pressure upon standing upright (orthostatic), dizziness, faintness, or blacking out.Autonomic
side effects
b
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Drugs that treat the symptoms of schizofrenia (neuroleptics)
can cause motor impairment (catalepsy)
The second generation drugs reduce the negative symptoms, 
they have reduced side effectsThere are evidences of a reduced glutamatergic function (on DA neurons)
Some studies have found no differences in DA transmission in schizofrenics</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Amphetamine-induced stereotypy used in animal models for schizofrenia
High dosage of amphetamine induce DA release
Drugs that treat the symptoms of schizofrenia (neuroleptics)
can cause motor impairment (catalepsy)
Gate hypothesis: schizofrenics fail to gate the stimulus they receive
(as measured by PPI)
The second generation drugs reduce the negative symptoms, 
they have reduced side effects0406080100120
20
0 40 80 120Pulse
0406080100120
20
0 40 80 120Pulse
Prepulse
Times (ms)Sound (dB)Normal response
Inhibited response
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Schizophrenia
Chronic disorder that occurs in 1% of the population. 
It affects both men and women but the onset is different according to the gender
020406080100120
Age at onset16-2526-3536-4546-5556-6566-7576+
Men WomenNumber of individualsSchizophrenia
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Etiology of schizofrenia
Genetic components and environmental factors
There is an enlargement of the ventricles that is NOT
caused by cell death. It is rather due do defects 
in development that preceed the onset of the symptoms
Also, there are changes in cellular structure non accompanied by gliosis.
This suggests that the abnormalities occurred in the developmental process.Anatomical studies
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Figure 18.12 in Meyer, and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Symptoms:
Illogical thinking
Inability to recognize reality
Hallucinations (voices insulting or commanding)
Absence of emotions, lack of feelings
Symptoms change over time
Functional Imaging studies revealed:
Decreased activity in the prefrontal area (hypofrontality)
Activation of cortical areas during hallucinations
Increased activity also in subcortical areas: i.e.limbic system</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>PDF - 2.5 MB</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/9-98-neuropharmacology-january-iap-2009/resources/lecture_1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Neuropharmacology:
The study of drugs specifically employed to affect the nervous system
Several drugs used for the treatm ent of extra-neural pathology may have an e ffect on the
Nervous system 
The effects of a drug can be considered at different levels:
Molecular
Cellular
Behavioral
As the complexity of the system increases it becomes more diffic ult to predict the
effects of a drug</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Drugs can be agonists or antagonists:
Co-agonists
Competitive antagonists
Non-competitive antagonistsAgonist
Receptor
Agonist-receptor
interactionAntagonist
Receptor
Antagonist-receptor
 interaction+
=
=+
Drug action/effect No drug action/effect
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Drug action:
molecular changes produced by a drug when it binds its target
How does a drug reach the brain?
Route of administrati on:  Oral, Intravenous, 
Intramuscular, Subcutaneous, Inhalation,
topical, Epidural.There are two distinct aspects of drug action: 
Potency (the affinity of the drug for its receptor)
Once in the body the drug bi nds to inactive sites that 
retain the drug and release it 
over time, this prolongs t he action of a drug. Also, 
the amount of these proteins
Varies by individuals
The affinity of different drugs for these sites can 
explain some interactions between
drugsEfficacy: the biological effects exerted on the target
.01.05.10.51.05.010.0
0 6 12 18 24Drug concentration in blood (mg/kg)
Time (h)Threshold for effectiveness
IV (Intravenous) IM (Intramuscular)
PO (Oral) SC (Subcutaneous)IM-oil (Intramuscular in Oil)
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>The response to a drug can change over time
TOLERANCE: a diminished res ponse to drug administration  after repeated exposures 
of that drug (metabolism or comp ensatory changes in the nerve cell
SENSITIZATION (reverse tolerance), when repeated rug admini stration causes an 
Enhancements of the drug effects
Up- or down-regulation of the receptors (1/2 weeks) reflect compensatory changes</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Glutamate receptors are formed by different subunits that are targeted by different 
drugs
NBQX (2,3-dihydroxy-6-nitro-7-sulfamoyl-benzo[f]quinoxaline-2,3-dione) 
is a blocker for AMPA and Kainate receptors but not for NMDA. Rodents 
treated with NBQX show sedation, poor co ordination of movements and protection 
From chemically-induced seizures. 
There are also metabotropic receptorsalpha-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxa zolepropionic acid receptor (AMPA)
N-methyl D-aspartate (NMDA) Image removed due to copyright restriction. Fig. 7.4 in Meyer
and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>NMDA receptors have binding sites for glutamate and for other binders:
Glycine and D-serine are co-agonists. They are necessary for the activation
Of the receptor, but the limiting factor is glutamate.
So for the activation of NMDA receptors two events are necessary: glutamate and 
Membrane depolarization. Inside the cha nnel there are three more bindings sites:
For phencyclidine (PCP), ketamine and MK-801. These substances block the channel 
( non competitive antagonists)There are also blockers: Mg++ blocks the re ceptor, but it leaves its site when the 
Membrane is depolarized
Images removed due to copyright restriction. Fig. 7.5 and fig. 7.6
in Meyer and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Drug effects
Therapeutic effects
Side effects
Margin of safety
Dose50100Percentage respondingAnxietySedation
ED = Effective Dose    TD = Toxic DoseRespiratory depression
TD50 TD50ED50Drug Effects: Therapeutic Effects and Side Effects
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Neurotransmitter system: glutamate
Glutamate mediates fast excitatory transmission and it is present in all t he cells of nervous system
Glutamate is generated from glutamine (via glut aminase)  and it is loaded into vescicles by 
VGLUTs, which are present only in glutamatergi c cells. Once released in the synaptic cleft 
glutamate is removed by neuronal and glial transporters: 
Excitatory Amino Acid Transporters (EAATs).EAA T1/2 are present on astrocytes and are important
For modulating the amount of ext racellular glutamate. Excess of  glutamate can be dangerous and 
Even produce cell death Image removed due to copyright restriction. Fig. 7.3 in Meyer
and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>How do we measure the effects of a drug?
with the dosage-response curve (ED), Dosage-response curves of 
which describes the amount of biologics different analgesics the first three
or behavioral effect (response) for a Have identical efficacy, even if at 
given drug concentration (dose) Different dosage. The fourth is less 
effectiveDoseResponse (%)
50100
Maximum
response
ED = Effective DoseED100Threshold ED50Dose (mg)Percentage of elevation
in pain threshold
0255075100
1 10 100Hydromorphine
Morphine
ED50ED50CodeineHow do we measure the effects of a drug?
ED50Aspirin
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>GABA (Gamma-aminobutyric acid) and glycine are two inhibitory neurotransmitters.
Blockade of GABA transmission induces seizures.
GABA is synthesized from Glutamate by th e enzyme Glutamic Acid Decarboxylase (GAD)
Which is present only in inhibitory neurons. GA BA synthesis can be blo cked by the following 
drugs:
Allyglycine, thiosemicarbazid e, 3-mercaptopropionic acid
Image removed due to copyright restriction. Fig. 7.13 in Meyer
and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Similarly to Glutamate, GABA is loaded into vescicles by VGAT, and it is removed from 
the synaptic cleft by transporters located on both neurones and glia: GAT-1, GAT-2, GAT-3.
Tiagabine (GABITRIL), blocks  specifically GAT-1, enhances GABAergic transmission and
it is used in the tr eatment of epilepsy.
Another way to increase GABAergic transmissi on is to reduce the degradation of GABA by 
Blocking the enzyme GABA aminotransferase (GABA-T). Vigabatrin (SABRIL) is an irreversible
Inhibitor of GABA-T and it is us ed in certain types of epilepsy.
Diazepam (VALIUM) is a syntetic product that increases GABAA recept or function, however
There are endogenous molecules th at show a benzodiazepine-li ke activity endozepines, 
Which may play a role in anxiety. There is also an endogenous peptide t hat inhibits diazepam
By binding diazepam binding site (D BI: diazepam binding inhibitor). 
Benzodiazepines have a specific binding site: subst ances that bind to the si te act as convulsants,
because they decrease the GABA transmission</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Excitotoxicity hypothesis: excessive exposure to glutamate and related amino acids
cause a prolonged depolarization of neurons  that lead to their damage and death
Domoic acid is an excitatory amino acid made by some algae. It concentrates in crabs, 
Shellfish and fish. When wild life eat t hese sources they get intoxicated. 
This happened in 1961 in Capitola (C A) and inspired the movie the birds.Abnormalities in EAATs lead to diseases: half of the cases of Amylotrophic
Lateral Sclerosis (ALS) are caused by EAATs and cause degeneration of motor 
neurons.
Image removed due to copyright restrictions.
Still photo from The Birds by Alfred Hitchcock.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Basic properties of the nerve cells:
Ability to conduct electric signals
Specific intercellular connections with other nervous cells or with other tissues
Drugs can affect either one of these properties
Also, glial cells in the brain are im portant for modulating neuronal function</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
  
 
9.98 Neuropharmacology
January (IAP) 2009
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Modulation of synaptic transmission
It is based on the interaction between a neurotransmitter, released by the 
presynaptic terminal, and its receptor on the postsynaptic receptor
Regulated from molecules that peptides that affect  neuroactivity, even wi thout being transmitters
Many neurotransmitter have more than one receptor
Receptors:
Ionotropic
Metabotropic</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>There are two main type of GABA receptor s: GABAA (ionotropic) and GABAB (metabotropic)
GABAA receptor consists of a channel for Cl-. Drugs that interact with GABA are:
Muscimol (agonist)
Bicuculline (antagonist)
Pentylenetetrazol (antagonist)
Benzodiazepines*
Barbiturates*
Neurosteroids (agonists)
Ethanol (agonist)
Baclofen (LIORESAL) is an agonist for GABAB rec eptors and it is used as a muscle relaxant and 
Antispastic
* They activate the receptor together with GABA. There is no effect in absence of GABAImage removed due to copyright restriction. Fig. 7.14 in Meyer
and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Ionotropic receptors comprise multiple protein subunits that form an intrinsic ion 
Channel. They mediate fast excitatory and inhibitory neurotransmission
Metabotropic receptors are constituted by one single unit and their activation 
stimulate a second messenger system that eventually leads to activation of ion 
channels and protein kinases. Their action is slower but long-lasting</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>This means that a drug stays in the blood for some time after administration
Before reaching the CNS, where it has to cross the Blood Brain Barrier
The BBB barrier prevents that all the substances reach the brain
Also the placental barrier has to be taken into account.
Once the drug reaches the brain it can go through the cell membrane or 
binds to a receptor on the cell surface
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Interaction between drugs. 1
Once in the body a drug is metaboliz ed and eliminated, plus in the blood, 
the drug binds to non reactive substances such as albumin, that buffer their action
One of the possible causes of interference is through the interaction of a drug 
with some  of these molecules/enzymes.
Two drugs may act in different  manners but having competitive effects (i.e.: on heart rate)
On have ADDITIVE EFFECTS, or showing POTENTIATION (when the combination of 
two drugs produces effects that are greate r than the sum of their individual effects.
+
0
_Drug effect
Drug effect
Drug effect
Drug A Drug B Drug A + B(A) Physiological
 antagonism(B) Additive effects (C) Potentiation
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Presynaptic modulation (the amount of transmitter released)
Change in the fi ring frequency of the presynaptic neuron
Change in the synthesi s, storage, transpor t, release, reuptake, ca tabolism of a transmitter
i.e. L-DOPA (the precursor of DA) is given to patients  with Parkinsons disease,
i.e.: drugs that block monoamine oxidase (MAO) that degrades s erotonin (5-HT) are used to treat
Depression, and so are drugs that prevent the re upta ke of the neurotransmitter
Direct effect on the release mechanism by changing th e electric properties of  the terminals or 
modulating specific molecules involved in th e release process
Postsynaptic modulation
Long term changes in the num ber of receptors (use of agonist or antagonist drugs)
Change in the a ffinity of a ligand for a receptor
Change in ionic conductance (2ndmessenger)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Interaction between drugs. 2
Repeated use of a drug may cause an al tered production of metabolic enzymes
Involved in the catabolism of several drugs. Example: some anti-seizure drugs 
Interfere with the metabolism of oral cont raceptives. A similar effect is produced
by cigarette smoke
Drug competition: when drugs share the metabolic system. Es: alcohol increases
the metabolism of Valium increasing its effects.  
Metabolic enzymes are different at different ages and different gender therefore
Producing different effects</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>The ions can go across the membrane through channels. The ion channels are 
Open depending on voltage, ligand, or bioc hemical modification (i.e. phosphorilation)
Image removed due to copyright restriction. Fig 2.7 in Meyer
and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Basic elements of biophysics
Neurons transmit electrical signals. At  the cell membrane there is a different 
Distribution of ions that causes a rest ing potential of -70mV. This situation is
Maintained through ATP-pumps that maintain Na+ and Cl- ions concentrated 
outside the cell and K+ localized inside.
Image removed due to copyright restriction. Figure 2.10 in Meyer,
and Quenzer, Psychopharmacology, 2004.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>A particular case of neurotransmitter is represented by NO: Nitric Oxide. It is a gas
Therefore it is not stored in vescicles and it can cross the membranes. It is also
Produced by the post synaptic element and it can act as a retrograde signal. 
The only way to modulate its availability is by modulating its synthesis operated
By the enzyme Nitric Oxide Synthase (NOS).
NO action results in the activation of an enzyme that produce cGMP (a second
Messenger).
Blocking NOS prevents the tolerance and the dependance induced by drug 
administration. This may have an effect on the tolerance for drugs used for the 
treatment of chronic pain.
Another effect of cGMP activation is to  relax the smooth muscle that surround the
Blood vessels therefore increasing arteries dilatation; cGMP degradation is catalyzed
By the enzyme cGMP phosphodiesterase. If this enzyme is blocked the effects of
NO are potentiated facilitating arteries dilatation. 
Is this the mechanism used by the drug sildenafil (known commercially as VIAGRA)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Local changes in ion 
concentration induce local 
potentials, and when these 
events 
sum up and a threshold is 
reached,  a great number of voltage-gated channels is 
opened allowing a massive 
depolarization known as 
action potential.
After the propagation of the signals
the channels close (refractory 
period) until the 
Ion distribution is restored.
Lidocaine, a topic anesthetic, blocks the Na+ channels therefore  blocking the transmission of pain
Phenytoin (Dilantin) is used to preve nt epilepsy. It binds to Na+ cha nnels during the refractory period 
preventing their opening, there fore preventing the spreading of electrical activity-100-70-500+40-2+2
Depolarization
Resting 
potential
Hyperpolarization
TimeStimulus current (nA) Membrane potential (mV)Threshold
Local potentials
Action potentialsInsert microelectrode
Hyperpolarization Depolarization
Figure by MIT OpenCourseWare.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
