<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/</course_url>
    <course_title>Petrology</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Earth Science </list>
      <list>Geochemistry </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>P-T-X Phase Diagrams
Gibbs Phase Rule</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/sept22notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.109  Lecture Notes 
September 22, 2005 
Thermodynamics I 
Intro to Ph ase Diagrams 
Read: Hess Ch. 2 
Handout: using phase diagram s
Phase diagram s are graphical representations that help us understand what happens in 
igneous system s as m elts cool and crystallize. 
With igneous rocks, liquids are the f ocus. 
Terrestrial p etrology  a lot of what we see at  the surface of the earth is the result of 
melting and crystallization processes, l ook especially at basalts and granites very 
diverse rocks! 
inverse problem   we got this result, what are the conditions recorded by it?
Want to understand composition al diversity in ig neous rocks
1) history of form ation 
2) physical con ditions  P, T, volatiles 
Diopside  Anorthite phase diagram</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>What if the crysta ls are removed f rom the m elt as they f orm? 
--overgrowth reaction visible from rimmed/surrounded cr ystals, ex. rapakivi granite 
--differential settling forms cum ulates, con centration of  settled /floated crysta ls 
Removing the crystals effectively resets the bulk  com position.  This composition m oves 
along the liquidus if al l crystals rem oved.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Melting: 
At 1557 C, Fo and En react to form  Fo and liquid 
EnFo + liquid 
When all En is used up, T can increase, Fo  melts, and the am ount of Fo decreases, % 
liquid increases, until liquidus T is achieved. 
Freezing 
1. 100% liquid, above liquidus 
2. Fo crystallizes out and T  drops 
3. at 1557 C, Fo + liquid  En, all liquid goes away 
if the bulk com position is at pure En , Fo and liquid react to 100% En 
THIS IS ALL THE IDEAL CASE 
It assum es we reach eq uilibrium  at every reac tion and chan ge of T, but in the real w orld, 
sometimes equilib rium  is Not achiev ed. 
Fractional c rystalliz ation</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Exam ple of a binary (tw o com pone nt) system  with a eutectic  
eutectic from  the Greek, for coex isting or occurring together 
In real rock system s there are 8-9 chem ical components, usually: 
SiO 2 MgO FeO CaO Al2O3 K2O Na2O TiO 2 Cr 2O3 
Binary system s  liquid first form ed by m elting a m ixture of 2 pure substances which are 
insoluble in solid phas e 
Eutectic T = tem p of 1st melting 
At this T, T will r emain constan t until one of the solids is en tirely m elted out of  the 
matrix 
Steps to m ake a m elt: 
1) Heat to eu tectic T 
2) Di and som e An m elt  eutec tic liqu id 
3) Di gets used up 
4) Then T can go up, liquid  com position m oves alo ng the liquid us with increasing T, 
melting of An 
Use the lev er rule to de termine the pe rcentage of the bulk in each phase. 
(see diopside-anorthite diagram ) 
b a% liqu id = % An = a + b a + b 
There is a sp ecial pheno menon if bul k com position is near th e eutectic: eutecto idal 
precipitation. This is responsible for gr aphic granite, where the quartz and feldspar 
crystals grow concurrently and becom e aligned and intertwined. 
Pure end m ember phases  dont m elt at the eu tectic, they m elt at the m ineral m elting point 
(sam e reaso n we add salt to ice in the winter, m ixing lowers m elting points). 
Forsterite  Enstatite  S iO2 phase diagram</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>4-Melting and Crystallization Processes
T-X-X Phase Diagrams (3 Components) Freezing/Melting in Crust and Mantle</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/oct13notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Alkemade line  line between coexisting phases 
When the liquid that coexists with three so lids plots outside the compositional Alkemade 
triangle, the four phase point is a reaction point, NOT a eutectic point. 
 
Reaction boundary 
1) choose a point on the boundary 
2) construct tangent line from pure phase point  and project back to line between the 
two phases 
3) if the tangent intersects outside of the line drawn between the two phases, it is a 
reaction boundary 
 
reaction boundaries are depicted with double arrows facing lower T</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>from a point A in the Fo primary phase volume: 
1) Fo is liquidus phase 
2) Olivine crystallizes out, liquid comp osition moves away from A on an ol 
subtraction line 
3) Liquid composition reaches Fo-En reaction boundary @ C 
4) Fo and liquid react to forma En, get Fo + En + l 
5) @ B, Fo + l  An + En 
6) All l used up, left with Fo, An, En</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Primary phase volume   part of diagram where a singl e phase is the liquidus phases 
Boundary curves or cotectics  where liquid is in equilibrium with 2 phases, arrows show 
direction of falling temperature 
 
Ternary eutectic   1 special liquid composition that coexists with all 3 solid phases, 
represents the lowest temperature on the diagram where liquid is stable 
 
Temperature contours 
 
For bulk composition X (where X is closest to A and closer to B than C), A is liquidus 
phase.  A crystallizes out of  liquid, liquid composition follow s a path directly away from 
A.  The liquid composition reaches the A + B boundary curve (cotectic) where A and B cocrystallize.  The composition moves to the eutectic point as these two phases 
precipitate.  At the eutectic composition, A, B, and C crystallize until all of the melt is 
used up. 
 
For every bulk composition on a diagram with a eutectic, the first melt (lowest T) has the 
composition of the eutectic. 
 
Isothermal sections  take a slice of the three dimens ional ternary diagram for a single 
value of T.  The challenge is to reconstruc t information about the solids stable at this 
temperature. 
 
Reaction boundaries   along these boundaries, one crysta lline phase and the liquid react 
to form a second crystalline phase.  
For example, ol + l = opx 
This is the ternary equivalent of  a reaction point or peritectic</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.109 Lecture Notes 
October 13, 2005  
 
Basalts 
 
We first have to talk about ternary phase diagrams.  These are an analog for the 
crystallization of basaltic melts. (see Hess ch. 7) 
 
Ternary liquidus diagrams 
 
These hide information about the subsoli dus  only show liquidus  data (liquid and 
coexisting crystals) 
Analogous to topographical map with respect to  temperature (contour lines are isotherms) 
 
Example: 3 pure solids, A, B, C, eutectic behavior 
 
Basalts can tell us about mantle melting condi tions, i.e. temperature and pressure of 
melting.  In a system of phases with a eutec tic point, the eutectic composition records 
conditions of melt generation.  It is a liquid in equilibrium with solids present in the 
residue at depth  liquid is multiply saturate d with these phases at the conditions of melt 
generation.   
 
The melting reaction doesnt just occur as a eu tectic.  For example, in the olivine-opx-qtz 
system, melting involves a reac tion relation (peritectic). 
 
In ternary phase diagrams, all crys talline phases are pure end members.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Serpentine Stability - Recycling of Mantle
Origin of Mantle Rocks - Igneous vs. Metamorphic Processes</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/oct6notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Serpentine formation at subduction zones: 
 
At depth, serpentine breaks down, releases H 2O.  H 2O goes up into HOTTER mantle and 
triggers melting (inverted thermal gradient in mantle wedge)  
 
1) dehydration of subducted lithospher e leads to the release of H 2O 
-rises into overlying mantle wedge, encounters hotter mantle 
-leads to melting 
2) recycling of H 2O into the deep earth, phase A hydrous silicate 
 
Serpentine is 10% H 2O, so thats a lot of H 2O!  And serpentine is stable up to high P.  
Phase A (not a mineral yet, still no samples found) is 2% H 2O.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Abyssal peridotite formation: 
 
Lots of faulting allows H 2O to get down into the mantle.  This results in the production of 
serpentine at depths up to 20 km!</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Kimberlites erupt at 20-200 km/hr velocity  
According to Tom Jordan, 1970s Scientific Amer ican article, the K aapvaal craton is &gt;3 
billion years old. 
 
How do you keep cratons stable?  Buoyancy  
The less dense cratonic material floats on the mantle. 
Two types of buoyancy: 1. compositional (Mg lig hter than Fe), 2. thermal (hot lighter 
than cold) 
How do you make cratons and keep things cold?  Tim says you use a subduction zone.  
Water subducted with oceanic crust, lowers melting point of the rocks.  Wet melting in the mantle wedge can be cooler than would be expected with dry melting.  [picture of mantle wedge and volcanoes] 
 
In handout, studies of transition between garnet  and spinel peridotite, also studies of 
pyroxenes. 
 
Pyroxene quadrilateral with isotherms</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>See information on QUILF, DH Lindsey 
 
 
What happens to peridotite when you metamorphose it in the presence of H 2O?  
SERPENTINIZATION 
 
Pieces of mantle emplaced tectonically into continental crust are alpine peridotites.  
Steinmann (Swiss) found association between serpentine peridotite, pillow basalts, and 
chert in the 1800s, became Steinmanns trin ity.  Location: Davos, Switzerland.  The 
first explanation for these formations was a hot  wet ultramafic magma.  Eventually, they 
realized the serpentine peridotite was hydr ated metamorphic rock from the mantle! 
 
These rocks tell us what happens when you c onvect mantle that has been near the surface 
down into the deep earth.  The hydrous mine rals break down as a function of P + T at 
ocean spreading centers, and expose perido tite.  These are a byssal peridotites.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.109 Lecture Notes 
October 6, 2005 
 
Petrology 
Pyroxene thermobarometry  
 
Peridotites contain two pyroxenes: one is opx, orthopyroxene, and the other is a high Ca 
cpx, clinopyroxene.  These two minerals can be used to estimate T + P of the last 
residence of the nodule.  Th is is thermobarometry! 
 
How do you estimate T + P? 
Lindsley &amp; Dixon (graph in handout, En-Di series) 
2 coexisting phasesNOT a solvus 
Mg-Ca in coexisting pyroxene phases to set T, not very P sensitive. 
 
Also use garnets  pyrope Mg 3Al2Si3O12
Pyx not pure Ca-Mg phases 
As P increases, increase solubi lity of CaTs (CaAl(Si,Al)O 6) component 
In opx, Mg-Tschermakite 
Two components in opx add to pyrope: 
MgAl 2SiO 6 + MgSi 2O6 = Mg 3Al2Si3O12
) )( (
6 2 2 6 2SiO MgAl) (
O Si Mgpyrope garnet
eqa aak=  
RTV P
RS T
RTH
RTGkeq++ = =) 1 (ln  
This has been experimentally calibrated and is both P + T sensitive. 
 
So, we have two equilibria we can use as th ermobarometers in peri dotites, Ca-Mg in pyx 
and garnet-opx Al solubility. 
 
 
Adiabat  SPT
 change in P, T for a substance that  cannot exchange S (entropy) with the 
surroundings (an adia batic system).</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>5-Basalts, Komatiites Rock Series Mantle Melting Processes</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/oct25notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>How do you melt the mantle to produce basa lts?  Well use mid-ocean ridge basalts 
(MORBs) as an example because this is a part  of the earth where processes of melting are 
well-understood.  MORBs are usually olivine tholeiites. 
 
Melting processes at MORs occur to a shallow mantle depth, approximately 10 km.  In 
1864, Lord Kelvin wrote about adiabatic decompression melting, where superheating 
from decompression provides the thermal energy for melting.  At MORs, melting records variation in mantle potential temperatures.   
 
EXAMPLE:  Suppose we cool the mantle 50C.  The specific heat is about .25 
cal/gram/degree and the heat of fusion is about 100 cal/gram.  50C * .25 cal/gram/degree 
= 12.5 cal/gram to put into melting the mantle  12.5% of the rock melts. 
 
A higher mantle potential temperat ure means melting starts earlier and at greater depths.    
This is revealed by the basalt composition, pa rticularly by looking at  the percentages of 
Na and Fe in the basalt.  Na is one of the fi rst components to melt, so a basalt with a high 
Na/Fe ratio came from a rock melted to a lo wer degree, lower per centage melted out, and 
so had a lower T p, than one with a low Na/Fe ratio.  
 
Graph of global Na 8.0 vs. Fe 8.0 trend  Klein and Langmuir, 1987 
 
Water depth can be proxy for mantle poten tial temperature.  Low FeO and high MgO 
signifies great water depth and mantle poten tial.  High FeO and low MgO usually means 
that the water depth is shallow.  There is also a trend with ocean crust thickness: the 
density of basalt magma is 2700 kg/m3, and that of peridotite is 3300 kg/m3.  When the 
melt is removed, the density of the peridotit e goes down.  A less buoyant mantle will lead 
to a thinner ocean crust.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.109 Lecture Notes 
October 25, 2005 
 
Handout: basalts 
 
Basaltsclosest thing to melts of the mantle, have the potential to record interior 
processes: P,T distribution + heterogeneitie s in a planetary interior, information on 
volatiles like CO 2, H2O, S, F, Cl 
 
Basalt tetrahedroncomposition space with nor mative minerals in basalt composition, 
for classification (see handout) 
 Developed by Yoder and Tilley (1963) 
A basalt, by definition, is mos tly plagioclase and pyroxene 
 
Basalt seriesa group of rocks found together in space and time  re present process of 
fractional crystallization 
Start out with some initial magma, a product of mantle melting.  It rises from its source 
and encounters cooler overlying crust or lithosphere, crystallizes, and the melt 
composition changes as crystals precipitate.  The basalt se ries samples the compositional 
variation through this process.  The first basa lt in the series is the parent or source 
magma, and others are derivatives. 
 
Primary magmaproduced by partial melting, se parated from a mantle source at depth, 
delivered to the surface without modification 
Primitive magmacomparative term, of two rocks, the one with highest MgO or 
compatible element content (Ni or Cr) 
 
See handout 
 
Two competing ideas  about mantle melts (primary magmas) 
1) homogenous source, melted under di fferent conditions (depths) 
2) heterogeneous source explains variation in composition, mantle composition variable 
BOTH HAPPEN! 
 
With increasing pressure, melt produced by mantle melting becomes higher in MgO and FeO (more olivine rich) and lower in SiO
2  eventually nepheline normative 
 
Evidence came from investigatio ns of natural basalts, looking at first phases to crystallize 
from liquid over a range of pressures  
Found multiple sa turation points 
 
If a full mantle melt, liquid should be in equilibrium with oliv + opx + cpx + 
spinel/garnet/plag 
 
Deeper  alkali-olivine basalt  Shallower  tholeiite</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Metamorphic Petrology 6 - Metamorphism of calc-silicates</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/dec1notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Prehnite  22 3 1 0 2 () Ca Al Si O OH
Pumpellyite  3
22 3 1 0 2 () Ca Fe Si O OH+
Breaks down to epidote + ch lorite + albite + qtz  lower greenschist facies 
 
Amphibolite facies  marked by the appearance of amphibole and plagioclase (albite-
anorthite solid solution).  Plagio clase is not appearing for the first time in this facies, but 
as T goes up, the variety changes from  pure albite to about 20% anorthite 
Zoisite (like epidote, but Al rather than Fe3+) + qtz  actinolite + H 2O 
Zoisite + chlorite + qtz  actinolite + anorthite + H 2O 
@ higher T, make hornblende 
 
Granulite facies  appearance of orthopyroxene 
Hornblende + qtz  cpx + opx + plag + H 2O 
 
Blueschist  albite + chlorite   glaucophane + H23 2 8 2 2 () Na Mg Al Si O OH2 2O 
2 jadeite + 1 talc 
Classic blueschist assemblage: glaucophane + lawsonite (10% H 2O!) + chlorite 
 
Eclogite  garnet, cpx (Ca and Na, apple green colored), NO PLAGIOCLASE 
Omphacite 
Diopside + jadeite</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Fluid composition changes during metamorphi sm, depends on bulk composition of rock.  
Fluid can also sometimes buffer reactions  this is controlled by the fluid to rock ratio. 
 
 
Metamorphism of Mafic Rocks
Ex. basalts 
 
See Spear, Ch. 11 
 
Chemically complexsystem not easy to look at graphically 
SiO 2  Al 2O3  FeO  MgO  CaO  K 2O  Na 2O  H 2O 
8 components  10 phases! 
 
ACF triangle diagram  Al 2O3, FeO + MgO, CaO 
Facies for metamorphic rocks  mineral asse mblage characteristic of a set of P-T 
conditions for a particular bulk composition 
At low T, metamorphic minerals only appear in small amounts 
 
 
 
Zeolite facies  rich diversity of minera ls, often form in holes in igneous rocks 
 Analcine  26 2 () NaAlSi O H O 
  Analcine + qtz Ualbite + H 2O 
 Lamontite  24 1 2 2 4( ) CaAl Si O H O 
  Lamontite + qtz Ulawsonite 22 7 2 2 () CaAl Si O OH H O   
 Warikite lawsonite + qtz 24 1 2 2 2( ) CaAl Si O H O  U</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.109 Lecture Notes 
December 1, 2005 
 
How does fluid composition vary during metamorphism?  
 
  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 Hit reaction curve 
2
2dol qtz H O
calc tr CO++
++U 
Fluid composition becomes 
more CO 2 rich 
 
Will reach invariant point, and then travel along 22 calc tr dol di H O CO+ ++ +U curve 
(univariant).  When reaction is complete, the composition leaves the curve.  The fluid composition remains constant as T increases.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>RFM III: Pyroxenes</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/sept15notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.109  Lecture Notes 
September 15, 2005 
Rock Forming Minera ls III 
Structure a nd composition of: PY ROXENES 
Pyroxenes = chain silicates, with te trahedral and octahedral chains 
Pyroxene structure com bines tetrah edral chains + octahedral strip  I-beam s 
Diopside CaMgSi2O6 
Monoclinic, due to symm etry of octahedra 
Octahedral ducks 
The symmetry of a pyroxene can depend on the facing direction of th e octahedra.  To 
remember this, we pic ture the oc tahedron as a du ck, and sign ify as positiv e ducks f acing 
forwards and as negative ducks facing backwards. 
How to m ake an orthorhom bic pyroxene 
Pyroxene structure is a polytype 
Polytypism   one basic building unit  put together in different ways 
Orthopyroxene (OPX) 
Stack I-b eams in rows alte rnating directionality of octahedrons</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Other types of pyroxenes 
NaAlSi 2O6 jadeite 
NaFeSi 2O6 aegirine 
LiAlSi 2O6 spodum ene 
CaAl(Al, Si)O6 CaTs Calcium  Tscherm aks 
     F assaite = &gt;50% CaTs 
MgAl(Al, Si)O6 MgTs Magnesium  Tscherm aks 
Augites can have substantial amounts of Ti in M1 site  Ti-CaTs (R2+TiAl 2O6, where R 
can be any of a num ber of 2+ elem ents) 
Or with Cr, Cr-CaTs, di stinctive green pyroxenes (R2+CrAlSiO 6) 
Protoenstatite alm ost pure Mg pyroxene, like enstatite 
found in m eteorites, enstatite chondrites 
boninites  discovered 1989, contain protoenstatite 
produced in subduction zones 
compositional variation in pyroxenes due to tem perature 
when you look at pyroxenes in thin section, commonly you see evidence for exsolution  
unmixing of com ponents, chem ical separation 
important in  petro logy b ecause p rovides a record of tem perature history 
In thin section, see blebs of  unm ixed m ineral, esp. in pl utonic rocks (slowly cooled 
igneous intrusives) or in high T igneous rock s where m inerals grow directly from  melt 
Can tell abo ut rate of cooling 
@ low T, pigeonite phase disappears,  reac ts to f orm OPX and augite 
In plutonic rocks, get inverted pigeon ite, OPX with augite lamelli 
Pigeonite  augite + OPX m akes m artensite, sim ilar to phase transi tion in carbon-iron 
system</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Pyroxene polytypes 
+ monoclinic c2/c 
+ CPX 
+ clinopyroxene, diopside 
+ 
+ 
+ 
- orthorhom bic Pbcn 
+ protoenstatite 
-
+ 
+ orthorhom bic Pbcn 
+ OPX 
- orthopyroxene 
-
+ 
+ 
Pyroxene quadrilateral</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>6-Phase Equilibria: Silicate + H2O
Magma Generation in Subduction Zones</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/oct25notes2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>October 25, 2005 
Melting of silicates with water (SUBDUCTION ZONES) 
 
Handout: Melting of silicate so lids in the presence of H 2O 
 
In subduction zones, the thermal gradient is inverted due to the introduction of the cold 
slab.  This makes possible flux melting: in the lower part of the mantle wedge, vapor 
saturated melting occurs.  The melt asce nds, encounters hotter mantle, and melting 
continues.  Mantle crystals dissolve into the melt, lowering the water content and freeing 
the water for more vapor saturated melting. 
 
30,000 km of ocean ridges 80% of the volcanic activity on earth, generating 25 cubic 
km of basalt magma per year 
40,000 cubic km of subduction around earth, 3-8 cubic km volcanism in arcs. 
 
Bowen (1928)  studied the rock series f ound at subduction zone settings, the calc-
alkaline trend, work focused on the amount of CaO 
Fenner (1921)  studied the tholeiitic trend, typical of oceanic basalts (though at this 
point, the technology to dive to the ocean floor and knowledge of the mid-ocean ridge 
volcanism did not exist) 
 
The calc-alkaline trend shows depleti on in FeO with increase of SiO 2.  The tholeiitic 
trend shows constant SiO 2 and sharply rising FeO.  The difference is H 2O!  The tholeiitic 
system does not involve melting with H 2O, but the calc-alkaline system requires it.  
Important effects of H 2O: 
1) suppress early crystallization of plag ioclase, so olivine and pyroxene 
crystallize and drive down the FeO content 
2) spinel (Fe 3O4) becomes a liquidus phase 
 
H2O increases the anorthite content of plagioclase by destabilizing albite.  As a result, 
anorthite concentration is a good indicator of the amount H 2O present in melting (see 
handout) 
 
Early thermal models of subduction zones were very uncertain about predicting temperature in the cold subducted slab and th e hot mantle wedge.  Calc-alkaline igneous 
rocks have heavy element si gnatures matching subducted slab .  But based on the major 
elements present in the melt that forms calc- alkaline igneous rocks, at least 90% of the 
melt is from the mantle.  Either some material s are melting out of the slab or fluids carry 
the heavy elements from the slab into the melt.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Metamorphic Petrology 5 - Metamorphism of Mafic Rocks, Metamorphism</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/nov29notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>November 29, 2005 
 
Metamorphic Thermometry and Barometry  
 
See Spear Ch. 15 
 
 
 
Pelitic rocks commonly have garnet-biotite-p lagioclase assemblages.  Those minerals, 
along with an aluminosilicate and quartz can be used to calculate T + P. 
 
Reactions:  
garnet-biotite Fe-Mg exchange, T sensitive 
garnet + plag + aluminosili cate + quartz, P sensitive 
 
1) exchange reaction: GARB 
 
3 2 31 2 3 31 0 2 3 2 31 2 3 31 0 2 () () Fe Al Si O KMg AlSi O OH Mg Al Si O KFe AlSi O OH ++ U  
Almandine Phlogopite      Pyrope      Annite 
 
() () (1 ) 1ln() ()gt bt
pyr ann rxn rxn rxn rxn
eq gt bt
alm phlaa GH P VKS
RTa a R T R += = = + 
 
If you can calculate lines of constant K, plot on the aluminosilicate graph:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Triangle diagrams for siliceous dolomites:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Low slope  more sensitive to P than to T 
Ky, qtz assumed to be pure phases 
a  1 
 
Check compositions of garnet, biotite, and plag to find both P + T! 
 
Mixed Volatile Metamorphism
 
See Spear Ch. 12 
 
Rocks with both CO 2 and H 2O important components 
 
- calc-silicates (including siliceous dolomites) 
- ultramafic rocks, when CO 2 present in fluid 
- also basic rocks, when CO 2 present in fluid 
 
Visualization: diagrams 
2CO TX
Examine effects of T and variable fluid composition</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>S
H
large 
V small 
 
 K more sensitive to T than P 
 
 
2) GASP 
 
32 3 1 2 2 5 2 2 2 8 23 Ca Al Si O Al SiO SiO CaAl Si O ++ U  
Grossular Alumino  Qtz          Plagioclase (Anorthite) 
 
lnGKRT=  
dPVdT  both terms large</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>1) A=B, volatile absent 
 
2) Decarbonation 
2() CA x C O=+  
 
3) Dehydration 
2() HB x C O=+  
 
4) Both components removed 
22() () CH Ax C O y C O+=+ +
 
5) 22() () H x CO C y CO+=+  
 
1) rxn
PGST=  change in G such that high entropy assemblage is stabilized.  Gas 
has high S, mineral has low S. 
 
2) le Chateliers principle 
 Take a  reaction 2 CA C O=+
 If we add H 2O, dilute CO 2, drives reaction to the right 
 
4) the sum of 2 and 3  volatiles always released 
 Pure CO 2 phase cant be in e quilibrium with pure CO 2 fluid 
 
CaO  MgO  SiO 2  CO 2  H 2O siliceous dolomite 
5 components: F = 7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>RFM I: Olivine and Spinel</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/sept8notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.109  Lecture Notes 
September 8, 2005 
Rock Forming Minera ls I 
Structure a nd composition o f: OLIVINE, SPI NEL, GARNET 
OLIVINE 
Major constituent m ineral of the earths  upper m antle, found in peridotite (rock 
composed of &gt;50% olivine m ineral) 
(Mg,Fe) 2SiO 4
That is, so lid solution  of forsterite M g2SiO 4 and fayalite Fe 2SiO 4
Solid solution  continuous variation in chem ical com position &amp; physical properties 
Polym orphism  sa me chem ical com position, different crystal structure 
Polym orphs of olivine at high pressure are wa dsleyite and ringwoodite .  The transition to 
wadsleyite occurs at ~310 km  depth, and to ringwoodite at ~410 km  depth.  Ringwoodite 
has the sp inel structu re.
Coordination num ber  the num ber of anions surrounding the cation 
See work by Linus Pauling, 1932 
Paulings rules for crystal st ructures, assum es ionic bonding 
Ionic structure understood using electrost atic rules of attr action and repulsion 
Cations and anions surro und each oth er to neutralize charg e  can  rationalize crystal 
structure with coordination num ber 
Structu re of olivin e
Two types of coordination in olivine  octahedral (6 anions around 1 cation) 
tetrahedral (4 anions around 1 cation) 
coordination polyhedron  shape that you get when you connect the centers of the anions 
that su rroun d the ca tion 
Pauling radius ratio rule  rcation correlated with coordination # ranion 
coordination Average ratio 
(4) tetrahedral .225 
(6) octahedral .414 
(8) cubic .732 
(12) dodecahedral 1 (spherical packing) 
Ex. forsterite Mg 2SiO 4 
Si4+ in te trahedral s ite, M g2+ in octahedral site, O atom s anions 
Form s octahedral chains/strips 
Strips im part directionality  PHYS ICAL PR OPERTIES c onsisten t with sym metry 
Strips bound together by isol ated tetrahedral strips</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Pyralspite group 
Ugrandite group 
Yttrogarnet  YAG lasers 
At high pressures, pyroxene becom es majorite, a garnet structure</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>SPINEL 
MgAl 2O4 
Cubic close packed oxygen structure 
|A rotate up per lay er by 120, place on lower lay er 
|B 
|C 
Mg tetrahed ral, Al oc tahedral 
High symmetry  3 crystallograph ically d istinc t sites: tetrah edral s ite, oc tahedr al site, 
anion site 
Notated MgIVAl2VIO4 (does not follow radius ratio rule) 
Structu re solved by W .L. Bragg</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Inverse spin els in clude m agnetite a nd ulvospin el 
Ulvospinel FeIV(Ti, Fe) 2VIO4 
GARNET (cubic/isom etric symm etry) 
Common m ineral in peridotite a nd crustal m etamorphic rocs 
Shows a lot of  solid solu tion chem ical var iation</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>RFM IV: Pyriboles</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/sept20notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.109  Lecture Notes 
September 20, 2005 
Rock Forming Minera ls IV 
Structure a nd composition of: PY RIBOLES 
Pyriboles include pyroxenes, bi otite (sheet silicate), and am phiboles (chain silicates) 
VM Goldschm idt  coined term  pyr ibole, invented geochem istry, 1880s 
Sheet silicates (m icas)  
Hexagonal rings of tetrahedra 
Octahedral sheet layer 
Trioctahedra l  all sites f illed like MgO 
Dioctahed ral  2/3 sites f illed like Al 2O3 
Brucite, gibbsite, have no tetr ahedral layers (not silicates) 
Mg 3(OH) 6 and Al 2(OH) 6 
charge balancing 
 make a s heet silicate, add Si tetrahedrons , remove H+, satisfy charge with Si-O bond 
Amphiboles 
Literally a com bination of 2 pyx and 1 m ica 
Chain silicates (double chain) 
Basic am phibole unit, with tetrahedra l layers sandwiching octahedra: 
Arrangem ent of units:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Jim Thompson  m ixed chain width biopyriboles 
Discovered in 1970s in Chester, VT 
Chester ite, jim thompsonite, clinojim thom psonite</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>60-120 cleavage 
Amphibole polytypes: (+/- si gnifies facing direction of silicon octahedra) 
+ 
+ monoclinic 
+ clinoam phibole 
+ C2/m 
+ 
+ orthorhom bic 
- orthoam phibole 
- Pnma 
+ 
+ 
+ 
- orthorhom bic 
+ protoam phibole 
- Pnmn 
2 pyx + 1 mica = am phibole 
2 [CaMgSiO 6] + Mg 3Si4O10(OH) 2 = Ca 2Mg 5Si8O22(OH) 2 
Diopside  Talc   Trem olite 
2 [Mg 2Si2O6] + Mg 3Si4O10(OH) 2 = M g7Si8O22(OH) 2 
Enstatite Talc Anthophyllite 
You can build ANY a mphibole this way! 
Amphibole quadrilateral  graphi c representation of differe nt types of amphiboles, by 
composition</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Metamorphic Petrology 4 - Pelites - The AKFM System Continuous and Discontinuous Reactions</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/nov22notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Complication:  
MnO is an additional component in many pelites 
Spessartine garnet Mn 3Al2Si3O12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>5.  Chloritoid disappears, bi otite full solid solution  
6.  Tie line switch (gt + chl = str + bt) 
 
 
7.  Tie line switch (str + chl = ky + bt) brings out kyanite</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>1.  Chloritoid appears 
 
 
2.  Chlorite stability decreases</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3.  Staurolite appears 
 
 
4.  Garnet appears (ctd + bio + H 2O = gt + chl)  see how compositions change mineral 
assemblage!</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>November 22, 2005 
 
AFM Diagram  represents metamorphic reactions in pelites, JBT 
Assumes muscovite always present.  Projects from aluminosilicate (Al 2O5) through FeO 
and MgO 
 
Isograds in pelites depend on th e bulk composition of the rock! 
 
Scotland  Barrovian metamorphism  ch lorite, biotite, garnet, staurolite 
 
 
 
X marks typical pelite composition 
 
2 important minerals, chloritoid  and staurolite, only coexist in very aluminous bulk rock 
compositions</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>RFM II: Feldspars</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/sept13notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.109  Lecture Notes 
September 13, 2005 
Rock Forming Minera ls II 
Structure and composition of: FE LDSP ARS 
Feldspars 
The m eat and potatoes of  crustal igneous rocks 
(most abundant igneous m ineral in the crust) 
Feldspar from the German felds pat, crystals found in the field 
Alkali f eldspars are any m ixture of Albite, NaAlSi 3O8, and Kspar, KAlSi 3O8 
Kspar has three polym orphs: 
Sanidine  high T 
Orthoclase 
 Microc line  low T monoclinic 
monoclinic 
 triclin ic C2/m
C2/m
C 1 
Structure 
Based on 4 m ember ring/square consisting of SiO 4 and AlO 4 tetrahedra 
Link the squ ares in a do uble crank s haft 
Symm etry of these ring structures m akes the perfect cleavages, 88 and 92</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Sanidine &amp; Orthoclase monoc linic, Microcline triclinic  
variation in atom ic arrangem ent of feldspars du e to changes in  temperature we can 
measure this ordering using optics or xrays  give you T of equilib rium 
Al/Si dis tribution 
Kspar KAlSi 3O8 in cry stal structu re are 2 crystallograp hically distin ct tetrahedr al sites, T 1 
and T 2 
At higher T, Al and Si are random ly distributed over T 1 and T 2 
So average site occupancy is .25 Al, .75 Si 
As T goes down, T 1 prefers Al 
Si  O bond 1.61  
Al  O bond 1.73  
So unit cell length along c axis ch anges with m otion of Al atom s 
Anorthite has 2x the am ount of Al , different Al/Si arrangem ent  anorthite always 
triclin ic, unit cell of  symm etry 2x length of alkali feldspars 
Plagioclase series AlbiteAnorthite 
Polysynthetic twinning can be used to determ ine An content to ~2-4 m ole% 
From  extinction angle, see handout</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Tectosilicate (fram ework silicate)  s ilicate wh ere all Si tetrahedra are link ed together at 
apices 
Ring often notated T 4O8, tetrahedral anion, alkali catio ns in holes balance charge 
Calcium  feldspar = Ano rthite 
Plagioclase
Plagioclase twinning 
Polysynthetic (rep eated ) 
Simple (two crystals related by a twin operation) 
Review of m ineralogy: 
Twin operation  symmetry operation not  part of symmetry group of crystal 
Symm etry operations elem ents 
Reflection   m irror plane
Rotation  axis 
Twin happens when a symm etry elem ent not pa rt of the crystal structure operates on two 
halves</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>3-Earth&#8217;s Outer Mantle - Phase Relations and Variation with Tectonic Setting</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/oct4notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.109 Lecture Notes 
October 4, 2005 
 
Oxygen Barometers  (see handout from last week) 
 
(discussion of hand samples in class, xenolit hs from the mantle in basalt.  Xenolith = 
foreign rock) 
 
Important variables in earth and planets: 
T 
P 
Volatile-gases-fluids 
O2  Fe  FeO  Fe 2O3 (also S) 
H2O 
CO 2 
 
Oxygen buffers 
FMQ (or QFM)  feldspar, magnetite, quartz 
3Fe 2SiO 4 + O 2 = 2Fe 3O4 +3SiO 2
Controlled by  fO2, oxygen fugacity (tendency to escape) 
fO2 = , correction for non-ideal behavior 
 
Oxygen buffers are nice because the minera ls for the reaction can be found as pure 
phases.  If a phase is pure, a = 1. 
 
2 2 4 22 4 3 1
) ( ) () ( ) (
33 2
O Ooliv
SiO Feqtz
SiOmag
O Fe
eqf f aa ak = =  
 
RTGfrxn
O=
2ln</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Two coexisting minerals that ar e the most common oxybarometers:  
Ulvospinel-magnetite 
Hematite-ilmenite 
With these you can solve for both T + P! 
 
 
Samples of the deep earth  
The accessible ones are not very deepmost are from &lt;100 km.  In some rare cases, the 
pieces of the cratonic mantle from up to 250 km depth are preserved. 
Mineral inclusions in diamonds are mostly r egular ultramafic minerals, but sometimes 
we find CaSiO 3, MgSiO 3  perovskite? 
We have determined by laboratory experi ments that with T and P found @ 670 km, 
ringwoodite (a spinel, found in meteorites ) transitions to Mg-perovskite and MgO 
periclase.  We have no samples from the lower mantle, however. 
 
Mantle rocks are usually perido tite (see rock naming handout).  
Harzburgites have been chemically de pleted by melting and melt extraction. 
 
Al-bearing minerals present in rocks tell about depth of equilibration. 
Shallow plag peridotite 
|  spinel peridotite 
Deeper  garnet peridotite (mostly pyrope) 
 
Cratons  pieces of thick mantle lithos phere found under ancient crustal rocks.  
Interestingly, they are old (&gt;3 billion years) .  There is extremely low heat flow in a 
craton.  The lithospheric root  of the craton is 250-300 km deep, compared to 100 km deep 
under average lithosphere. 
 
How do cratons form?  This is one of the outstanding problems in geology.  One 
possibility is that cratons formed above subduction zones in the Archean, 3.5 billion 
years ago.  Supporting evidence is the existence of komatiites in cratons.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Continental Crustal Igneous Rocks</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/nov8notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>November 8, 2005 
Granites Continued, Rapakivi Texture 
 
Bowens argument: granites are produced sole ly by fractional crystallization because they 
all plot near the ternary minimum of  qtz, plag, and kspar in composition 
Problem: this system becomes eutectic-like if pressure P H2O increases or if Ca added to 
mixture in anorthite, CaAl 2Si2O8  therefore, you can ALSO  make granite by partial 
melting, since the 1st melt will be at the eutectic  composition no matter what the 
composition is 
 
In a system with a te rnary minimum, the first melt is variable.  In a system with a 
eutectic, the first melt is at the eutectic.  The last material produced by fractional 
crystallization has a compos ition near the minimum or th e eutectic, depending on the 
system. 
 
Bowen was right that fractional crystallizati on can create granite from a mafic parent 
magma (basalt).  He was wrong that this was the only possible mechanism.  The proof is 
rapakivi texture. 
 
 
Rapakivi texture has kspar crys tals ringed with plagioclase.   Anti-rapakivi  texture has 
plagioclase crystals ringed with  kspar.  Overgrowth textures such as these are evidence of 
fractional crystallization and a record the or der by which the mineral components reached 
the solidus.  In the system Ab-Kspar-An-Qtz-H 2O (Ab and An are both types of white 
plagioclase), we can clearly show that anti-rapakivi texture can be achieved by fractional 
crystallization.  It is, however, impossible to crystallize kspar followed by plagioclase, 
rapakivi texture, by fractional crystallization.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>To make rapakivi: 
Take liquid A in equilibrium with plagioclas e and kspar solid phases.  Decompress.  Now 
A is in the plag primary phase volume, so plag crystallizes to return the liquid to 
equilibrium.  This forms plag rims on all the crystals, including kspar. 
 
Q. How would we decomp ress our magma suddenly? 
A. Huge silicic eruptic events  ash flow welded tuffs, as in the San Juans mountains (a 6000 cubic km eruption) and at Yellowstone (3 eruptions in 2.4 million years, 2 of them 
&gt; 1000 cubic km eruptions).  The magma burst s open the cap of the volcano, which then 
sinks to make a caldera.  An eruption such  as this catastrophically decompresses the 
magma.  Rapakivi textures may record la rge volume catastrophi c decompressions of 
silicic magma! 
 
 
Layered intrusions  mafic  source of pla tinum for mining  appear preserved in crust 
The big ones are from the Proterozoic and th e Archean, such as the 2.05 billion year old 
Bushfeld.  &gt;90% of the Pt in the world comes from one layer of the Bushfeld that extends 
for hundreds of km in South Africa.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Major Types of Sedimentary Rocks
Distribution of Sediments on the Earth&#8217;s Surface</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/nov10notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Shock metamorphism  meteorite imp acts impose very high P-T conditions 
Example minerals are stishovite (VI fold coordination), wadsley ite (sorosilicate), 
ringwoodite (spinel) 
 
 Regional metamorphism 
o Burial metamorphism  P + T imposed by burial 
o Anorogenic metamorphism  burial in sed. Basins 
o Orogenic  deformation @ plate margin s, subduction zones and continent-
continent collision 
 
 Pyrometamorphism  by fire, where coal seams burn underground 
Also possible to metamorphos e rocks at lightning strikes 
 
Metamorphic variables
 
T most important var, requires a heat  source  in contact metamorphism, its 
intrusion, while in burial, its radioactiv e decay of elements like K, U, and Th 
 
P usually lithostatic pressure, gh 
 Granite  = 2700 kg/m3
 Basalt  3000 
 Peridotite 3300 
 
Fluid 
 
Bulk composition of protolith  SiO 2, Al 2O3, K2O, FeO, MgO, H 2O 
 Pelites  quartzofeldspathic 
 
High P, low T  subduction zones 
High T, low P  ocean floor spreading centers</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>November 10, 2005 
Handout: Sedimentary Rocks 
Beginning of metamorphic petrol ogy: sedimentary protoliths 
 
Sedimentary protoliths  
 
Siliclastics  by size, categorized as conglom erates, sandstones, or shales; by chemistry, 
categorized as graywackes, lithic sandstones, arkoses (red beds), or quartzites 
Carbonates + Evaporites 
 
Shales are the dominant type of sedimentar y rock on earth (70% of sedimentary rock 
mass), full of aluminous clays 
 
Diagenesis  chemical alteration of sediment at low T 
 
See handout for background on sedimentary rocks. 
 
Metamorphic rocks
 
Oldest crustal rocks: 
Acasta granitic gneisses 4.0 B.y. old 
Isua greenstone belt (granite gne isses, metaboninites) 3.8 B.y. old 
 
Focus on solid state  changes in rocks 
Metaigneous, metasedimentary 
Interactions with H 2O or CO 2 rich fluids 
Concept of isochemical reactions (not correct) 
Metasomatism  adding or removing elements by action of metasomatizing agent  fluid 
 
Concept of metamorphic grade  
Low T  diagenesis 
7 in between, metamorphism 
High T  melting (anatexis)  melting T depends on protolith 
 
  melting 
shales  600-700 C 
basalts  600-900 C 
marble  1000-1300 C 
 
Types of metamorphic environments  
 
 Contact metamorphism  near igneous plut ons, result of heat of intrusive magma 
Sometimes intrusions are fluid-rich  set up hydrothermal circulation systems that also 
influence the surrounding rocks 
Skarns  calcite and qtz protoliths, calc-silicate minerals 
Fluids carry metals, make ore deposits</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Metamorphic Petrology 2 - Metamorphic Facies
Heat Flow and Heat Production in Crust</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/nov17notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Reactions in simpler, lower variance systems  
 
Kyanite U sillimanite 
c = 1 
 
 
Barrows metamorphic grades  
 
Pelites  J B Thompson (1957) developed an appr oach for understand ing reactions in 
pelites.  The system is: SiO 2  Al 2O3  K 2O  MgO  FeO  H 2O.  He took advantage of 
some simplifying features in these rocks: 
1) quartz assumed always present 
2) H2O assumed present as fluid phase 
 
 + H 2O + SiO 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>November 17, 2005 
 
Metamorphic isograds  Barrow 
See Spear ch. 10, Spear ch. 4 for more on metamorphic minerals 
 
Graphical representations  
1) useful for visualizing chemical reactions 
2) reinforce the idea that bulk com position of your rock is important 
 
Plot bulk composition to  find stable phases:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Reactions when you have solid solution minerals: 
Continuous, 3 phase triangles move across the diagram 
 
Isograds  mineral appearances  depend on P, T, and the bulk composition</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Grossular + kyanite  anorthite + corundum U
Tie line switch  non-terminal reaction 
 
 
 
Anorthite U grossular + kyanite + quartz 
Terminal reaction  end of P-T stability of a phase</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Can further simplify if muscovite is always present to the two-dimensional FMA diagram 
(F = FeO, M = MgO, A = Al 2O3) 
 
Minerals  
 
Muscovite KAl 2AlSi 3O10(OH) 2  
Sillimanite-Andalusite-Kyanite Al2SiO 5  
Quartz SiO 2  
K-Feldspar KAlSi 3O8 Stable at low T + P 
and again at high T + P 
Pyrope Mg 3Al2Si3O12 Garnet 
Almandine Fe3Al2Si3O12 
Phlogopite KMg 3AlSi 3O10(OH) 2 Biotite  
Annite KFe 3AlSi 3O10(OH) 2 
Staurolite Fe2Al9Si4O22(OH) 2  
Chloritoid (Fe,Mg) 2Al(OH) 4Al3O2(SiO 4)2 
Chlorite (Fe,Mg,Al) 6(Si,Al) 4O10(OH) 8 
Cordierite Mg 2Al4Si5O18 Low P indicator mineral 
 
To plot minerals in projection:  
 
1) start with chemical anal ysis in wt % of oxides 
2) divide each wt % by gm mol wt, renormalize  calculate mol % or mol fraction 
 
 
 
Project through muscovite onto FMA face, for example:</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>7-Granitic Rocks and Crustal Magmatic Processes</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/nov3notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Granites  
Igneous processes, phase equili brium evidence (1958) see handout. 
The old granite problem has been solved. 
 
New problem  granite batholith s (with granidiorites and di orites)  how could a large 
scale batholith form by fractional crystalliz ation from a basalt parent?  There is no 
evidence for other crystals underneath the batholiths.  Where are the accumulated 
products of fractional crystallization? 
 
Tuttle and Bowen showed that granites are be st visualized as products of fractional 
crystallization.  They plotte d the compositions of natural granites to show that ONLY 
fractional crystallization after H 2O saturated melting could explain granitesthe 
compositions are all nearly the same.  He e xplained this with the phase diagram of the 
granite system, which has a ternary minimum. 
If there is a ternary minimum 
 --the first melt composition depends on bulk composition 
--you cannot make liquids of similar co mposition by melting solids with different 
compositions 
--you can make solids with compositi on at the ternary minimum by taking 
compositionally variable materials and allo wing fractional crystallization to occur 
 
However, Bowen didnt know that at higher pr essures, the phase diagram for granite has 
a eutectic, not a minimum.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Nov 3, 2005 
Magmatic processes, granitic rocks, rapakivi 
 
Handout: Magmatic Processes 
 
Phase equilibrium controls include fractiona l crystallization and partial melting.  In 
addition, the following magmatic processes are important: 
 
Magma mixing  natural consequence of periodi city or episodicity of volcanic/plutonic 
eruptions, usually mixing between magmas in different stages of evolution by fractional 
crystallization 
 
Assimilation of wall rock  heat up and melt rock in close proximity to magma.   This 
requires a LOT of heat, so the period ic recharge of magma is important 
 
Ex.  Imagine a crustal intrus ion of basalt, geotherm 30 C/km.  At 6 km depth, 200C 
granite wall rock (melts at 900C).  Intrude basalt at 1200C.  To heat the country rock 
and melt it cools the basalt.  The specific heat  of the granite is about .3 cal/gram/C, and 
the latent heat of fu sion is about 100 cal/gram requires 310 cal/gram to melt from 
200C.  Basalt cools and crystall izes at solidus 1000C.  With  similar specific heat and 
latent heat of fusion, the basalt will lose only 160  cal/gram of heat before  it solidifies.  If 
the basalt is solidified before the granite is melted, the melts cant mix. 
BUT if magmas continue to intrude, there will be enough heat to mix melts. 
 
Soret diffusion  temperature gradient eff ect (non-equilibrium process), elements 
rearrange to minimize entropy production.  Rate s of diffusion are sl ow relative to heat 
transfer rate, by about an order of 5. 
 
Metasomatize  to change composition in the so lid state, usually by fluid exchange with 
rock</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>1-Energy Functions-E-S-V and G-T-P-X</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/phase_diagrams/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Fractional Crystallization 
 
Types of fractional crystallization  
 
Perfect fractionation  Crystals are removed fr om contact with melt as soon as they are 
formed. 
 
Overgrowth zoning fractionation  Crystal grows from melt and overgrown rims on 
crystals remove the interior of the crystal from reaction with the melt.  The extent to 
which this process can occur will be governed  by diffusion rates in the crystal, because 
these rates are generally much sl ower than diffusion in the liquid. 
 
 
In contrast , during equilibrium crystallization, cr ystals and liquid continually react. 
 
Some examples  In ex. 1, composition A ( under equilibrium conditions) crystallizes 
completely to Fo and En at the reaction point.  All liquid is used up in reacting Fo + liq  En.  Under conditions of fractionation, liquid can each the En + Trid eutectic. 
 
In ex. 2 (under equilibrium conditions), compos ition A crystallizes initial feldspar B.  The 
plagioclase and the liquid change composition continually as temperature drops until the 
liquid reaches C and the feldspar reaches A.  Here all liquid is used up and we are left 
with a homogenous solid with composition A. 
 
For fractionation, feldspar is removed from c ontact with liquid and z oning develops.  The 
liquid can evolve to pure albite residue.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Methods of Melting  
 
Batch melting  an equilibrium process  a bulk composition is raised to a specific 
temperature above its solidus, the system come s to equilibrium, and the melt is removed. 
 
Fractional fusion  the opposite of fractional crystallization  melt is removed from 
contact with solid residu e as it is produced. 
 
Continuous melting with incomplete melt withdr awal  in this case, melt is generated by 
partial melting, then some of th e melt is removed, but some is  left in contact with the 
solid residue. 
 
In both the fractional fusion and continuous melting with incomplete melt withdrawal 
cases, the composition of th e residue changes continuous ly as melt is withdrawn.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Several mineral solutions exhibit this behavior  
 Alkali feldspars KAlSi 3O8  NaAlSi 3O8
Orthoclase - Albite 
 Pyroxenes  MgSiO 3 - FeSiO 3 - CaSiO 3  
Feldspathoids  KAlSiO 4  NaAlSiO 4  
   Kalsilite  Nepheline</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.104 
Using Phase Diagrams 
 
Some useful terminology: 
 
Liquidus   region above which liquid is the onl y stable phase for the entire system 
 
Solidus   region below which solids are the only stable phases in the system 
 
The lever rule   For a given bulk composition you us e the lever rule to calculate the 
amount of the phase that will be present in  a two-phase assemblage.  For the example 
below, b/(a+b) = % liquid and a/(a+b) = % anorthite. 
 
Binary system with a eutectic  
 
 
 
This is an example of congruent melting.  Th e idea is that the two things melt to some 
intermediate composition, but you need to know the phase diagram or the thermodynamic 
properties to determine the composition of  the melt.  Eutect ic means occurring 
together.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>System showing incongruent melting  
 
In this system, enstatite melts incongruently to  forsterite and liquid.  This type of melting 
reaction is called a perit ectic reatction.  Peritectic means built around. 
 
A peritectic is not a point terminal to the co existence of liquid and crystals.  Instead, one 
of the solids disappears.  This type of reac tion is also referred to as a discontinuous 
reaction, because one of the solid phases reacts out.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>System showing continuous solid solution  
 
A continuous change in compositions of cr ystal and coexisting liquid occurs with 
decreasing temperature. 
 
More on 2 component Systems  
 
Solution exhibiting critic al behavior  solvus 
Miscibility gaps</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Metamorphic Petrology 1 - Metamorphic Processes, Contact, Regional, T and P Variations</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-109-petrology-fall-2005/resources/nov15notes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Plate Tectonics + Metamorphism 
 
Miyashiro  worked in Japan in 1950s, most  famous Ryoke belt  discovered new types 
of metamorphic rocks 
Metamorphic belts were recognized that  recorded contrasting P-T conditions 
 
Al2SiO 5 triple point @ 3.5 kbars, 500C 
1 kbar  3 km in mantle, 4 km in crust 
105 Pa = 1 atm 
 
 
 
Types 
I. Zeolite  prehnite-pumpellyite  blueschist  eclogite 
II. Barrovian 
III. Low P, high T sequence  andalusite  sillimanite  greenschist   
amphibolite 
 
In the 60s when plate tectonics were r ecognized, it became clea r that these zones 
represented different parts of  the subduction environment 
I  characteristic of subducted oceanic lithosphere 
III  characteristic of the active volcanic arc</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Metamorphic facies + isograds  
 
1.  Isograds 
 
Barrow  mapped metamorphic rocks in Sc otland, recognized zones of progressive 
metamorphism  based on pressure of index minerals 
Boundaries between zones marked by the appearance of each index mineral 
 
Pelite sequence: chlorite  biotite  garnet  staurolite  kyanite  sillimanite 
See in field: Chlorite zone | Biotite zone, etc. 
 
Boundaries marking the appearance or disappe arance of minerals between zones were 
called isograds. 
Isograd  equal grade  intersection of  a surface of equal P&amp;T with the ground 
topography 
 
Appearance depends on P, T, fluids, and the bulk composition of a rock 
 
Barrovian metamorphism  classic exampl e of middle P-T conditions (usually in 
orogenic or tectonic setting) 
 
2. Facies 
 
Eskola (1910-20, later than Barro w)  recognized a distinct set of mineral assemblages 
that were characteristic of a set of P-T conditions  metamorphic facies 
 
This got complicated because of the large number of named facies.  Fortunately, people 
stopped naming new facies.  In common use now: 
 
Barrows zones Mafic rock facies Calc-silicate rock facies 
Biotite Greenschist Talc-phlogopite 
Garnet 
Staurolite Epidote-amphibolite Tremolite-actinolite-
epidote-zoisite 
Staurolite-kyanite Amphibolite Diopside-grossular-
scapolite Sillimanite 
 
K-feldspar Pyroxene granulite Forsterite</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Interpretation 
 
 
 
 
3. how do isograds and mineral assemblages record changes in P and T? 
 
system  CaO  Al 2O3  SiO 2, 3 components, phase rule F = c + 2   
F = # degrees of freedom 
c = # components 
2 = T and P 
 = # phases 
so F = 5   
 
if F = 0 (no degrees of freedom, invariant point), 5 phases coexist 
at aluminosilicate triple point, 3 of those phases are the three isomers of Al SiO2 5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>November 15, 2005 
 
Bulk composition variations (continued) 
 
Metamorphosed mudstones or shales  pelites  
SiO 2  Al 2O3  K 2O  MgO  FeO system, abundant in tectonically active areas 
CaO and Na 2O are not as abundant as these five because they are carried away in solution 
during surface weathering. 
In weathering, plagioclase is the first phase to dissolve from a pelite, through seracitic 
alteration 
 
Calc-silicates  
Less abundant, but more attractiv e are calcareous pelites (CaCO 3 + SiO 2) or muddy 
limestones.  When metamorphosed, these be come calcareous schists (in Europe, called 
marl). 
 
Siliceous Dolomites  (siliceous carbonates) 
 
Kaapval craton  3.1 Billion y ears ago platform carbonates  stromatolites grow there, 
might be older stuff but lost since pT. 
 
Only one way to make subduction zones: make pluton-sized granites/rhyoliutes or hydro-
alter ocean floor basalts a nd remelt oceans for a long time 
We cant see back that far in the rock record 
 
Meta-basic rocks  metamorphosed mafic volcanics 
Ultramafic  serpentinites 
Peridotite protoliths 
MgO-SiO 2-H2O 
 
Iron formations  sedimentary rocks, SiO 2-FeO-Fe 2O3-H2O 
BIFs</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
