<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/es-255-physics-of-rock-climbing-spring-2006/</course_url>
    <course_title>Physics of Rock Climbing</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Physics </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Open Questions in Rock Climbing</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/es-255-physics-of-rock-climbing-spring-2006/resources/mites_255s06_oqs_pres/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 12Use and Habits
 Official line vs. actual use (e.g. grigri)
 Belay methods
 Bouldering pads
 Lead climbing decision making</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 SP.255 Open Questions Talk 10System Example: Via Ferrata</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
ES.255 Physics of Rock Climbing
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 6Modeling</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 3Safety
 Component approach
 System approach 
 Social/Organization approach
 Personal approach SP.255 approach</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 4Question Beggars
 Accidents:
 Innovation: The equipment gets better
 Demographics: Age, latitude Behavior: How people climb  Related sports &amp; occupations: Marketing: Litigation: Standards &amp; Standardization:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 13Use &amp; Habits Examples
D A V  w o r k  o n
 Gym belaying
 Avalanche awareness Falling over</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 8System Components
 Ice axesmultiple uses perhaps deserve multiple standards
 EASstandards &amp; education Ropeswaterproofing, middle ma rker, sharp edge resistance, &amp; 
abrasion resistance
 Aid Hooksstrength standard Belay/rappel devicesstandards, usage, &amp; performance measures
 Camsnew axel configuration analysis Ice screwsbuild a better ice screw &amp; testing/standardization Boltswarm, wet, &amp; salty + sustainability Padsuse &amp; standards Cramponssnow ball effectNuts
Slings &amp; draws
Harnesses</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Physics of Rock Climbing
Open Questions
Dave Custer
ES.255
Feb 21, 2006</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 2Overview</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 7Classification of Qs
 System components
 Systems &amp; interactions
 Use &amp; habits</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 14The Shape of Answers
 Curriculum
 Standards
 Better equipment
 Better habits and equipment use Information</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 11VF Outcomes</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 9Systems and Interactions
 Crampon + boot
 Rappel/belay device + rope (+user)
 Carabiner + rope (frequency, radius of 
curvature, standards, education)
 Rappel/belay device + heat Via ferrata
 Artificial climbing walls</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Feb 21, 2006 ES.255 Open Questions Talk 5The Answer Mill
 Modeling
 Experiment
 Simmering</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction
Discussion: Might the natural frequencies of karabiner gates and ropes match under certain circumstances that would cause the karabiner gate to be open during fall arrest?</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/es-255-physics-of-rock-climbing-spring-2006/resources/mites_255s06_rpe_osillmdel/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
ES.255 Physics of Rock Climbing
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Development of a Simple Model for Tran sverse Vibration in a Tensioned Rope  
Dave Custers post class thoughts for Feb 13, 2006 
 Figure 1a shows an oscillation in a top rope. I suspect the pho to was taken right as slack 
was pulled in; as the camera-
man, my inten tion was to photograph the climber, not the 
oscillation.  The basic premise for calculating the frequency of oscillation is the one that I set up in class is used here. I look at the tiny little pi
ece of the rope in the middle (Figure 1b) and 
presume that the oscillation is the fundament al or first harmonic (Figure 1c). I invoke 
Newtons 2nd law, F=ma . The distance the middle of the rope  is from the vertical line is 
proportional to the acceleration &amp; the signs are opposite. The math is developed in 
Table 2. Differences between the result developed in class and the result presented here 
are due to the assumption in cl ass that the shape of  the plucked rope is triangular. 
Here, the shape of the oscillating rope is assumed to be sinusoidal. 
 
 
Fig 1a Rope oscillation recorded in situ Fig 1b  Forces on the tiny middle 
of the rope Fig 1c  Assum
 ed 
shape of o
scillation 
 Some observations on this text: The genre is not clear, but it might be an exam
 ple of what 
you might produce in this seminar, something ak in to a problem set solution. And the text 
might serve as a draft of a proposal; it in cludes some motivation support and lots of 
background model work. Further, the development says something about how I think, which is half way between the te xtbooks that are full on handwaves, without 
calculus/differential equations , and the textbooks that develo p the full wave equation (no 
handwaving), for which my solution is a special case.  
For ES.255, Physics of Rock Climbing 1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Table 1  Table of Variables for Transverse  Rope Oscillations Development 
F The net force on the tiny middle rope section   The linear density of the rope (mass/length) 
a 
or 
x&amp; &amp; The acceleration of the tiny middle rope section  The a
 ngle off of vertical at which the tiny 
middle r
ope section is pulled by the rest of 
the rope 
T The tension in the rope x The horizontal distance from the ro pe middle 
to the vertical line 
l The rope length (presumed not to change 
much desp
ite the exaggerated difference 
between the apparent lengths of the arcs in 
Figure 1c) y Half the length of the tiny middle rope 
section 
 
Table 2 Development of Equations for Transver se Oscillation of a Tensioned Rope 
ma F=  By habit, I know to invoke Newtons 2nd law. 
 ya T  =2 sin 2                (1) As a first pass, in the left/right direction, the two 
forces on the tope are the left/right components of the 
tension in the rope; the mass is the length times the 
linear density. Further trickery (trigonometry and calculus) will be needed to show the relationship 
between sin  and a . 
 


=lyx xsinmax  Trickery: 
The equation that defines the arc of the plucked rope 
at an instant of time . (I
ve inverted the usual 
relationship of the x and y axes for sine waves) 
 


= =lyxl dydx cos sin  The slope of the arc is the derivative and, for the 
points at the end of the tiny rope section, also equal to sin 
 
 


+ =
 + lyxl dydx
y at 
2cos  And I want to know the slope at the top and the 
bottom of the tiny middle rope section, where y=l/2+y and y=l/2-y. The magnitudes of the 
slopes/angles are the same for the + and  case, so I include only one. 
 
lyxl lyxl 

 =  sin sin   (2) Trig substitution [cos(90+ )=-sin ] and small angle 
approximation [sin = ] produce a useful substitution 
into Eq. 1. 
 
ya yx
lT  =  2 222
 And I pulled the minus sign out of a hat. And 
substituted Eq. 2 in Eq. 1. 
x xlT&amp; &amp;= 22
 Newtons 2nd law applied to the middle of the rope, 
expressed in terms of position (x ) and its 2nd time 
derivative ( ) x&amp; &amp;
 
T
l=  The fundamental (angular) frequency  (in 
radians/second; to get cycles/second, divide by 2 ). 
For higher harmonics multiply by the integer of your 
choice (e.g. 2, 3, or 4). 
 
For ES.255, Physics of Rock Climbing 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Discussion of karabiner-rope Coupling</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/es-255-physics-of-rock-climbing-spring-2006/resources/mites_255s06_class_3review/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Figure 2 Video frame with carabiner gate open 
 
ES.255 Class 3 Summary  4 of 4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>A Summary of ES.255 Class 3, Feb 27, 2006 
 
We did was some brainstorming on all th ree aspects, modeling, gate oscillation 
measurement, and rope o
scillation measuremen t. The blackboard as it was at the end of 
class is shown in Fig. 1. I apologi ze if I did not give specific cr edit where it is due; if such 
occurs it is because I am reconstr ucting the conversat ion from memory. 
 Philippe observes that if this  work shows the possibility that the oscillating rope can 
couple energy into the carabiner gate then he will quit climbing. Dave C says there may 
be other alternatives, for instance increasi ng the open gate strength of carabiners or 
educating clim
bers about the situ ations that lead to coupling. 
 Existing Data from the Literature:  There is some data from drop tests available in  the literature. It would be handy to eyeball 
the data and compare it to the modeling results.  
Modeling: 
 
So far, Dave C had only been thinking about  the f
requency at which resonance occurs; 
Dany suggests that the carabiner gate damp ing m
ight produce a lower Q value and thus 
extend the range of frequencies over which coupling is significant. A model ought to 
include info on resonant fr equency, Q, and the number of cycles during which a 
significant amount of energy can be transmitted from the rope to the carabiner gate. Including the damping suggests that carabiners that get dirt y or corroded (&amp; thus better 
damped) might be more pr one to chattering open. 
 One expects that if this coupling is to cause problems, then  it must occur at about the 
point where the carabiner gate locks up under load. 
 There are two parts of th
e carabiner gate cha tter cycle. In one part, the oscillation is 
governed by the spring and the gate inertia; in  the other, the gate impacts the carabiner 
body and rebounds. How these two spring parts com
bine into one frequency is not 
clear.  Dave C says he expects carabiner  frequencies on the order of a 10
th of a second to a 60th 
of a second, based on having observed high sp eed video &amp; done some spread sheet 
estimates.  
Rope Oscillation Measurement: 
 
Rod suggests use of piezos to measure oscillation, but is not sure how to incorporate them 
into a rope. They are easy to salvage from headphone spea kers or perhaps keyboards. 
Requires pream
p and amplifier to boost 10 mV signals. 
 High speed video? How high does the speed need to be? 
ES.255 Class 3 Summary  1 of 4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>It will be important to be able to control the conditions, perhaps hard for drop situation. 
 Tension measurement : If doing drop tests, it would be nice to measure tension vs. time
 . 
 The tension in the rope can be measured with  a load cell. The cha nge in tension due to 
the rope vibration is so small comp
ared to th e tension in the rope that the vibration is 
probably not measurable from the tension data.  For a static test (like a gu itar string, not like a drop), the tension can be controlled by 
tying known weights to the bottom of a suspended rope.  
Carabiner Gate Oscillation Measurement: 
 
Piezzos m
ight work well here. 
 Perhaps wiring up an ohmic contact (switch or variable resist
 ance) between the carabiner 
body and the gate to detect chatter. 
 Perhaps glue accelerometer to the carabiner dur ing a drop to measure oscillations of the 
carabiner. H
igh speed video might be grand too. 
 Perhaps drive a carabiner with a spea ker coil. Allows frequency sweeping. 
Perhaps drive the carabiner with a stepper motor or other mo
 tor. 
 Another idea would be to use faradays la w &amp; eddy currents to determine whether the 
gate is open or not. Capaciti ve sensing might work too. Do ing so m 
ight make it possible 
to not mount the measurement device on the carabiner.  Quick Low Speed Video of Carabiner Gate Opening : 
 We took 60 frame/sec video footage of carabin ers being thwacked against the table. In 
most of the footage, we could identify a singl e frame in which the carabiner gate is open 
(Fig. 2). W
e conclude that the frequency of ga te oscillation is a li ttle higher than 60 Hz. 
One implication is that well need a higher frame rate to actually measure opening times 
and to see when/whether gates are open.     
ES.255 Class 3 Summary  2 of 4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
ES.255 Physics of Rock Climbing
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Figure 1 The blackboard at the end of class, Feb 27, 2006 
ES.255 Class 3 Summary  3 of 4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Measured the frequency of rope oscillation.
Measured the spring constant of a karabiner and came up with an estimate for the oscillation frequency of the gate (~25 Hz).
Marked nylon and tried to see if any changes were observable under a light microscope ~100x magnification. No changes were readily apparent.</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/es-255-physics-of-rock-climbing-spring-2006/resources/mites_255s06_rope_oscil/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
ES.255 Physics of Rock Climbing
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Appendix 1: spread sheet results  
analysis of rope oscillation data taken on Monday, March 20, 2006 by Dany, Rod, &amp; Elizabeth 
rope linear density = 0.07 kg/m (7.25 lbs/155.5 ft) 
Length (in) Weight 
(lbs) Time (s) Cycles Observed  Observed/ 
Model   
284 25 37 100 16.98 0.978 
284 25 30 90 18.85 1.085 
284 25 30 87 18.22 1.049 
284 25 30 84 17.59 1.013 
284 25 30 85 17.80 1.025 
288 25 30 79 16.55 0.966 
288 25 30 82 17.17 1.003 
288 25 30 78 16.34 0.954 
287 50 30 109 22.83 0.939 
287 50 30 105 21.99 0.905 
287 50 30 110 23.04 0.948 
287 50 30 101 21.15 0.870 
287 50 30 110 23.04 0.948 
287 50 30 103 21.57 0.887 
287 50 30 105 21.99 0.905 
448 25 30 53 11.10 1.008 
448 25 30 49 10.26 0.932 
448 25 30 55 11.52 1.046 
448 25 30 56 11.73 1.065 
448 25 30 57 11.94 1.084 
448 25 30 55 11.52 1.046 
448 25 30 55 11.52 1.046 
448 25 30 55 11.52 1.046 
446 50 30 73 15.29 0.977 
446 50 30 72 15.08 0.964 
446 50 30 71 14.87 0.951 
446 50 30 70 14.66 0.937 
446 50 30 77 16.13 1.031 
446 50 30 72 15.08 0.964 
446 50 30 72 15.08 0.964 
446 50 30 73 15.29 0.977 
446 50 30 70 14.66 0.937 
 
  
Rope Oscillation, Experimental Results  page 2 of 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Experimental Verification of a Simple Model for Transverse Vibration in a 
Tensioned Rope  
 
Dave Custers write-up of ES255 experimental work  
conducted by Dany, Rod, and Elizabeth
 
Summary  To verify the model of rope oscillation developed in ES255 class on Feb 13, a rope
was tensioned and plucked like a guitar string . The rope length and weigh t, the length of the 
tensioned rope segment, the tension,  and the number of cycles were recorded. The measured 
frequency was then compared to th e frequency predicted by the model. Even though these 
tests were conducted at tensions  well below those expected du ring climber fall arrest, 60 % 
(1 ) of the experimental results ar e were within 6% of  the prediction and no results differed 
by more than 13%. The close match between th e model and the experimental data suggests 
that the model provides an a ccurate enough prediction of th e frequency of oscillation to 
make recommendations on fall geometries that might be prone to co upling energy from an 
oscillating rope into  a carabiner gate. 
 
Introduction   
In order to determine whether oscillating ropes can couple energy into carabiner gates to 
precipitate open gate carabiner fa ilure, it would be handy to be able to predict the oscillation 
frequency of a length of rope un der the conditions expected during climber fall arrest. A 
simple model has been de veloped to predict rope oscillation frequency 
(available with the first session in the lecture notes section ); this research 
determines how close the model is  to experimental results. 
 
Methods  
 
Basically, lengths of rope were tensioned with wei ghts and plucked like a guitar strings. The 
rope length, tensioning weight, time, and number  of oscillations were recorded. The ropes 
linear density was determined by measuring the ropes weight and length and then dividing. 
With only slight modifications, 4 different combinations of weight an d length were tested: 
25 lbs/284 in, 50 lbs/288 in, 25 lbs/448 in, and 25 lbs/446 in. (Would be nice to have a figure here.)  
Results 
 
The linear density, record ed lengths, tensions, times, &amp; cyc les are listed in Appendix 1 along 
with the resulting measured frequency of oscilla tion, which is compared with the model. In 
general the measured results are close to the predicted results. The standard deviation of the 
ratio of measured to predicted frequency is 6%; thus, one would expect 99% of measured 
frequencies to be within 18% of  the predicted frequency. 
 
Conclusion  
The model for rope oscillation frequency is pretty good. We can use it to predict fall 
geometries that are pro ne to coupling rope oscillations into carab iner gate oscillation.
Rope Oscillation, Experimental Results  page 1 of 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rope Behavior</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/es-255-physics-of-rock-climbing-spring-2006/resources/mites_255s06_rope_behav/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation8Friction Over the Top Carabiner
The dependency of the friction coefficient on mass, 
velocity, diameter, rope coating, and temperature has not been investigated</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 SP.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation14Statistical Analysis of Test Facility 
Data: Expected Error</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation9Pavier Model &amp; Damping
Spring in series with spring/dashpot 
parallel combo
Provides general idea of damping coefficientProduces close match between model 
and experiment
Matches with the observation that climbing 
ropes are not far from critical damping/morethan half the energy is lost in each cycle
No model for why this works
35 kN
20 kN 3 kNs</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation10Silly Math Tricks with Rope 
Hangtag Info
The ratio of heat to spring energy:()
()() ()uiaa uiaa uiaauiaa uiaa
hs
sh
FF
UU


   +  
= =
m  8 . 221m  8 . 2 m  6 . 4 m/s  8 . 9 kg  80m  8 . 221
2The hang tag provides the force and 
% rope extension. The length of rope
and the fall height are defined by the
test standard.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Rope Behavior
Dave Custer
(S.255
Spring 2006</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 (S.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation3where the energy goes</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation17Effects of Humidity
See: A. B. Spierings, O. Henkel, and M. Schmid. 
Water absorption and the effects of moisture on the 
dynamic properties of synthetic mountaineering ropes. International Journal of Impact Engineering 2005.
Effects on:
Drops Held: See Fig. 2
Force: See Fig. 3Elongation: See Fig. 4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation13Attaway
Admonition(s)
Gear Placement
Anchor Placements</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation18Bibliography/References
M Pavier Experimental and theoretical simulations 
of climbing falls 
O. Henkel, M. Schmid, A.B. Spierings Water 
absorption and the effects of moisture on the 
dynamic properties of synthetic mountaineering 
ropes 
A Wexler, The theory of belaying
UIAA, Standard 101, dynamic ropes
S Attaway, Rope System Analysis
C Zanantoni et al., UIAA SafeCom minutes</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 (S.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation2Overview
 Simple models
 Very simple
W e x l e r
 More complications
 Damping Carabiner friction Belayer behavior
 What you can do with the simple models
 Estimate forces and times Figure out how often to place gear
 Evaluate ropes
 Test testing laboratories
 Experimental results
 Mgdefrau data
 Belay and sharp edge tests
 Humidity</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation11GROMF Conditions
Table #: Generic, run of the mi ll fall (GROMF) characteristics
quantity symbol value Units
Mass of climber mc 80 Kg
Acceleration of gravity g 10* m/s2
Rope modulus M 24000 N
Rope length L 30 M
Free fall height H 2M
Fall factor ff 1/15
Spring constant of rope k=M/l 800 N/m</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
ES.255 Physics of Rock Climbing
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation4The Simple Model
Based on Wexler, 1950</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation16Experimental 
Verification:MgdefrauData
Maegdefrau Data
sqrt fall factor vs. 
anchor load
02468
0.00 0.50 1.00
sqrt fall factoranchor load (kN)Single Rope
Rope PairMaegdefrau Data
Load Rate vs. sqrt F/l
0.000.050.100.150.200.250.30
0.00 10.00 20.00 30.00 40.00
load rate (kN/s)sqrt(F/l) (m-1/2)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation7Kinematics
Graphs
(simple
spring)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation5The Wexler Equation
The maximum tension in the rope (the Wexler equation):



+ + =


+ + = ffg mMmgLh
g mMmg T
c c2 1 1 2 1 1max2
21ky mgy mgh= +
kkmgh g m mg
kkmgh g m mg
y2
212214 2 22 2
+ +=+ +
=Conservation of energy dictates that the climbers gravitational potential 
energy before the fall is equal to the spring energy stored in the rope after the fall:
Solve for y and ignore the imaginary root:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation6Contributions to terms in the 
Wexler equation
()mgMFmg Tky mgy mgh
2 1 12
21
+ + == +
Friction over the top
carabiner increases therope modulus.
Belayer behavior and 
damping reduce the
quantity under the 
radical sign.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>March 6, 2006 ES.255 Rope Behavior 
Presentation12GROMF Estimates
Approximate GROMF results based on mo deling the rope as a simple spring
quantity symbol value units
Time of free fall tf0.6 s
Time from rope engagement to dead-point t0.1 s
Time of rope stretch (total) tr1.2 s
Time, top to bottom of fall (tf+tr/2) 1.2 s
Rope stretch ymax3.2 m
Total fall height (free fall height + rope stretch) h+ ymax5.2 m
Velocity at the end of free fall v06.3 m/s
Velocity at dead-point vmax7.1 m/s
Maximum deceleration amax30 m/s2
Frequency (angular)  3.2 s-1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
