<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-204-planning-communications-and-digital-media-fall-2004/</course_url>
    <course_title>Planning, Communications, and Digital Media</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Communication </list>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Computer Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Planning a Web Site</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-204-planning-communications-and-digital-media-fall-2004/resources/lec2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 2: P lanning a W eb Site  
 
I. Elem ents of a Site 
A. Audience/Messag e - MIT 
B. Organization/Navigation  - EyeArc hitec t
C. Identity  - Amsterdam ; Beijing ; San Francisco
D. Delight  - Hom epage Variations Gallery
E. Justice  - MIT W eb Accessib ility Guideline s 
F. Adaptability  - Lorlenes site 2002; 2004;  MIT'  s site in 1996
G. Inspira tion - Professor Dirk Donath
 
II. Student Portals 
 
III. Resou rces 
A. W eb Publishing at MIT  
 
B. Web Style Guide, 2nd Edition</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Top Down GIS</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-204-planning-communications-and-digital-media-fall-2004/resources/lec5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Brian Robinson 
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Anne Herbst 
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Sarah Kelly 
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>High-speed PCs and user-friendly software a llow ordinary people to manipulate spatial 
data and create maps. Today, everyone is a cartographer.  
III. Neighborhood Information Systems 
In practical terms , neighborhood information systems... 
1.	Are publicly accessible, web-based tools fo r analyzing a specific place (city or 
smaller)  
2.	Help users visualize and an alyze spatial information  
3.	Seek to democratize information to improve public participation  
4.	Serve community groups, foundations, pub lic agencies, and researchers  
5.	Aid strategic neighborhood planning a nd redevelopment, community building, 
decision-making, and policy formulation  
	Philadelphia  (Census and city-wide administrative data)  
	Lawrence (Small city; Project-based; Engage ment in neighborhood planning)  
	Los Angeles (Multiple levels of access; Inco rporates local knowledge - other 
ways of knowing/including new and silenced voices; State-level)  
	NNIP  National Neighborhood I ndicators Partnership  
In theoretical terms , neighborhood information systems transform data to action. 
Thinking Visually  by Robert McKim (Lifetime Learning Publications, Belmont, 1980) 
1.	Abstraction ladder 
2.	Graphic abstraction ladder 
	What should planners keep in mind while collecting data? (Is it an accurate 
representation of reality?) 
	Analyzing data? (Does data manipulation, su ch as aggregation, a lter the results?)  
	Presenting data? (How does the tool impact the message? ) 
What Are the Shortcomings of NIS? 
Data Collection:  Wealth is a function of media n values, household income, 
and earnings 
What about social capital? Other measures of wealth? P opulation measures 
(residential, slice in time, those that respond) 
Data Analysis:  What is a neighborhood? Is the block/block group the most useful 
unit?
Data Presentation:  Classification Matters; visual literacy 
US Census Bureau </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 5: Mapping, GIS and Planning, and NIS 
I. Housekeeping 
Feedback/Feed yourself session on Monday, Oc tober 25th at 6pm 
Portfolio critique Session - Looking for volunteers! 
Web-portfolio due on Monday, November 8th 
Where we are today 
II. Overview 
Mapping is an inextricable facet of our disposition. 
Mapping is fundamentally political. 
GIS is central to planning. 
Web-based NIS are be coming more popular.  
There are advantages and di sadvantages to using NIS. 
Mapping is an inextricable facet of our disposition. 
From prehistoric drawings of the night sky painted in cave dwellings to our more recent efforts to create a comprehensive genetic r ecord of the human genome, we  as humans  
have relied on maps to communicate what we  are trying to unders tand about our world 
and about ourselves. 
Map-making is both the result and the act of ex ploration and an inextricable facet of our 
disposition. 
Use maps to find places we dont know, descri be the places we know, and plan for the 
future. 
Maps are fundamentally political. 
It is a method of broadcasti ng our interests to others and uncovering interests for 
ourselves. 
Monmoniers How to Lie with Maps 1991 Woods The Power of Maps 1992 
Cramptons Political Mappi ng of Cyberspace 2004 
Peters projection 
Planners use GIS to advance their work. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>National census of population mandated by the Constitution of the United States 
1. Conducted every ten years (mail survey)  
2. Representatives (and taxes) are a pportioned based on census counts  
3. Impacts distribution of Federal dollars  
4. View some Census data at U.S. Census 2000 Home Page 
5. What data are collected? Sample Long Form from 2000 Census 
Other Population Surveys 
1. What kind of systems do other c ountries have? -- Na tional Census  
i. UK (Census 2001) 
ii. France  (Le recensement de la population) 
iii. India 
iv. China 
v. Brazil (Censo 2000) 
vi. Tanzania 
2. Population estimate  
i. US Census Bureau 
Future leaders of the world, remember...data ar e not objective, there are ethical and value 
choices inherent in the pro cess of capturing and manipulating data. These choices will 
impact decision-making processes. Strive to be a responsible information steward 
IV. Student examples (Lab 4) 
Brian Robinson 
Sean Sacks 
Anne Herbst 
Sarah Kelly </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Sean Sacks 
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Planner&#8217;s Toolbox</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-204-planning-communications-and-digital-media-fall-2004/resources/lec1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>G. Evaluation 
1. Your Grade  
2. Mid-semester Feedback Session  
3. Final Evaluations  
 
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 
 
IV. What is a web-based portfolio? 
 
A. A collection of work, derived from a tradition of showcasing accomplishments 
B. A portable, durable container for your planning-related endeavors 
C. A product for potential employers 
D. Previous Student Work 
 
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 
 
V. Important resources (if time allows) 
 
A. Web Publishing at MIT 
B. Computer Resource Network 
C. Rotch Librarys GIS Laboratory 
D. ESRI Virtual Campus 
E. Element K (register here) 
F. IAP 2005 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 1: The Planner's Toolbox 
 
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 
 
I. Subject Pedagogy 
 
A. Planning 
1. Requires an understanding of present conditions; it is context driven  
2. It is a systematic and creative way to  influence the future of a place  
3. Planning activities focus on issues of  equity, efficiency, and democratic 
involvement  
B. Communication 
1. The expression of ideas takes many forms: written, oral, graphic, etc.  
2. Communication is persuasive, it is rarely value free  
3. It is linked to analysis and ranges from the formal/sophisticated to the 
informal/messy  
C. Digital Media 
1. The planner's toolbox consists of instru ments to analyze problems and promote 
ideas  
2. There are choices: Memos Vs. E-mail; Sketches Vs. Photographs/Video  
3. We will examine such tools as Dreamweaver, Photoshop, Excel, Access and ArcView  
D. How can we examine these three concepts simultaneously?  
1. By exploring advanced and real-world a pplications and projects (lectures)  
2. By observing demonstrations of various planning-related software packages (recitations)  
3. Through a "hands-on" approach to working with digital methods of visualization, 
analysis, and communication (labs/projects)  
 
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 
 
II. Subject Logistics 
 
A. The Team 
B. Student Groups 
 
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 
 
III. Subject Content 
 
A. Lecture Notes 
B. Recitations 
C. Lab Exercises and Projects 
D. Syllabus 
E. Calendar 
F. Required Readings </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Photographic Essay</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-204-planning-communications-and-digital-media-fall-2004/resources/lec3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>B. After September 11: Images fr om Ground Zero by Joel Meyerowitz 
III. Design Elements 
A. Light 
B. Repetition 
C. Perspective 
IV. Photographic Essays 
A. Fifty Crows 
B. Knowing Where to Stand by Anne Spirn 
V. Student Examples  
1. The Role of Stickers, Flyers, and Graffiti  by Claudia Canepa 
2. The Nature of the City  by Amelia Ravin 
3. Pigeon Square by Diana Bernal  
4. Central Square as a Funciton of Time  by Jen Peyser </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Ho Pigeon Square
Central Square, Cambridge, MA Fall 2003 
Pictures Taken by: Diana Bernal 
Unplanned Occupants of Urban Space 
The ancestors of the pigeons we  see in our cities and on our farms were  brought here by 
Europeans and escaped from captivity, soon finding a favorable environment living with 
humans. These pigeons are offspring of domesti cated animals raised for sport racing, show 
and for food (squab). Feral pi geons have established themselv es every place humans built 
cities. Human cities provide artificial cliffs (buildings) and caves (a ttics, abandoned buildings, 
open warehouses). 
William H. Kern, Jr., Ph. D., former urban wildlife specialist, Department of Wildlife Ecology and Conservation, Pinellas Count y, Largo, FL, Cooperative 
Extension Service, Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences, University of Florida, Gainesville, 32611. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text> by Claudia Canepa 
(c) September 2002</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lab 1: Visual Representation and Analysis of Place
THE ROLE OF STICKERS, FLYERS AND GRAFFITI IN CREATING A SENSE OF 
PLACE AND COMMUNITY 
Stickers, flyers, graffiti and other type s of visual announcements or forms of 
communication not only enhance community but also help define it. An outsider can enter 
a new neighborhood and learn a lot about the community from just looking at the 
announcements that are posted throughout th e neighborhood. What types of people live 
there? What do they like to do? What types of social networks have they established for 
themselves? What issues are important for the community? Answers to these questions 
can often be found by examining the information that is posted (or spray painted) on light poles, street signs, walls and community bulletin boards or kiosks. 
CENTRAL SQUARE... 
A place where people of all ages, cultur es and ethnic backgrounds converge. A 
neighborhood that is politically charged. A neighborhood characterized by socio-economic 
tensions and racial divides. A neighborhood that celebrates its diversity. A place that 
promotes change. A place that resists change.
Back to top 
by Claudia Canepa </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>7 a.m.: Rehearsal 1:00 p.m.: Backdrop 5:30 p.m.: Doors Open 10:30 p.m.: Showtime
 by Jen Peyser </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>central square: the nature of the city 
BACK to 11.204 Class page
what is the ecological city? 
a little nature in the city... or is it a little city in nature? 
 by Amelia Ravin </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>(Enter)
 by Jen Peyser </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 3: The Photographic Essay  
I. Photographs: A Call to Action 
A. How the Other Half Lives  by Jacob Riis 
(Harvard University Press: Ca mbridge, 1970 [first published in 1890]) 
1.	The Bend. Photographs: #1, #2, #3, #4, #5 Chart #1 
2.	The Street Arab. Photographs: #1, #2, #3, #4 
B. The Unpredictable Past: Explora tions in American Cultural History  by Lawrence 
Levine 
(Oxford University Press: New York, 1993) Pages 259-261. 
1.	Migrant Mother #1, #2, #3, #4 
2.	Midweek pictorial, 17 October 1936, from the FSA Scrapbook (p. 284) 
II. Photographs: The Transformation of Place  
A. The New American Ghetto  by Camilo Jose Vergara 
(Rutgers University Press: New Brunswick, 1995) 
1.	Scudder Homes, Central Ward, Newark  
2.	Park Avenue, South Bronx 
3.	178th Street and Vyse Ave, South Bronx 
4.	The oldest bank in Michigan transformed into a Domino's Pizza, East Side, 
Detroit, 1991 
5.	Herd of stampeding elephants painted on the wall facing an empty lot, Finesse 
Arts, West Side, Detroit, 1991.  
6.	Fern Street, North Camden 1979 | 1994  
7.	The Doors of the Ghetto 
i.	 Woman addict entering an abandone d building on Vyse Ave., South 
Bronx, 1989 
ii.	 Entrance to abandoned building, Brownsville, Brooklyn, 1990  
iii.	 Turnstiles are used to limit access to th e courtyard of this Newark building, 
1993 
iv.	 Cinderella entrance, ready to shed its rust, open its door wide, and display its former glory, Detroit, 1994  
v.	 Bolted iron door contrasts with the orig inal palatial look of this building, 
Harlem, New York, 1992  
vi.	 Door welded shut seals a Newark  housing project awaiting demolition, 
Scudder Homes, Newark, May 1987  </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Change Over Time</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-204-planning-communications-and-digital-media-fall-2004/resources/lec4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Moshahida Sultana
Rent Decontrol and September 11 
                   How Ha s Central Square's Housing Market Changed? 
Because Central Square is 
a 
Between Harvard and MIT 
s 
Located Close to Downtown Boston 
Has Convenient Access to Shoppin gA Center of the Bi ggest Residential 
A Center of the Largest Commerci
Well Connected by Subway and Bu
 Rent Decontrol in 1995 
             Ho using Sales Price Increased Investment Increased
 After September 11 - Influx of Immigrants and Corporate Relocation Decreased
 Rent Decreased The Com position of New Renters Chan ged
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Hiba Akar 
A 
WHO IS MOVING OUT? 
Click on images for larger views 
Mapping the percentage of the rented housing units in  the city of Cambri dge gives us the impression that most 
residential units in Central Square are rent ed rather than owned. 
However, 1990 &amp; 2000 data cl early shows that Central 
Square is losing its low and  middle income population. 
Closer look at Cent ral Square and its 
vicinity. 
Meanwhile rents are increas ing all over Cambridge; 
Rent Occupied Units Owner Occupied Units Total Occupied Units % of rent occupied units to owner occpied units % Vacant units 
the ratio of rent occupied to owne r occupied units is decreasing. 
% of owner occupied units has more than 
doubled from 1990 to 2000  in Central 
Square. 
Students might be part of  the populati on leaving Central Square. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>II. Sophisticated Examples 
A. The Visual Display of Quantitative Information by Edward Tufte 
(Graphics Press, Cheshire, CT, 2001) 
i. Dr. John Snow's map of deaths from cholera  
ii. OPEC Oil Prices (from NY Times) 
iii.	New York State Total Budget Expenditures and Aid to Localities 
(from NY Times)  
iv.	The Shrinking Family Doctor in California (from LA Times)  
III. Student Examples 
A. Who is Moving Out by Hiba Bou Akar 
B. Rent Decontrol and September 11 by Moshahida Sultana 
C. Gentrification in Central Square by Will Carry 
D. School Concentration, Wealth Cluste ring, Ethnic Diversity and Central 
Square by David Ritchay 
E. Diversity in Central Square by Susana Williams  </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>About the Research 
My Argument: After September 11, rent decontrol has actually  caused rents in Central Square to decrease. 
September 11 has also changed the composition of new renters moving to Central Square. 
My Position: I am a planner at the Manhattan Institute of Policy Research. The Manhattan Institute is a think 
tank whose mission is to develop and disseminate new id eas that foster greater economic choice and individual 
responsibility. I have come to the MIT Center for Real Estate (CRE) to present my preliminary findings about 
Central Square to some real estate economists at CRE. 
What is the question and why is it important? 
Henry O. Pollakowski has been a housing economist at the MIT Center for Real Estate since 1996. He studied 
the effect of rent decontrol in Cambridge after 1995. Cambridge maintained a very strict form of rent regulation 
till 1995 and rents were held considerably below ma rket rents. After 1996 investment increased by 
approximately 20% over what would have been the case if rent control had been main tained. Manhattan Institute 
of Policy Research hired me to find out if New York C ity could achieve the same result from deregulation. To 
do so I have selected Central Square as a sample to unders tand what kinds of changes are taking place in Central 
Square after September 11 attack of 2001.  Specifically, I want to see if rent is increasing and how the 
composition of renters is changing. My research findi ng will be helpful in unders tanding how housing market 
has changed after September 11 attack and how effective deregulation is after 2001. 
One assumption inherent in my position: Increase in housing price also increases rent but decrease in rent 
does not necessarily decrease the price of housing. 
My methodology: For this project I had to rely heavily on data but I paid equal attention to the qualitative data 
too. For example, I have consulted my observations w ith one of the real estate agencies located in Central 
Square and requested them to share with me their ow n opinion about the new trend after September 11. This 
gave me a very useful insight and helped me to go bey ond the available statistics of U.S. Census Bureau. It was 
fascinating to discover something with own eyes rather  than depending on the information available in books 
and Internet. 
Research Findings: My research finding is completely different fro m what I expected it to be. I focused more 
on rent decontrol than on any other shock like September 11 attack.  
The Most Significant Constraint: Gathering additional data was the most significant constraint in such a short 
period of time. I spent a good amount of time to find an argument that excites me and after that getting data to support my argument was the most difficult part. 
One action that I would take to overcome this constraint: I will clearly define my goal and play with the 
already existing data to find a significant relationshi p between variables. I will narrow the topic from the 
beginning in order to avoid last minute rush. 
Did I enjoy? 
I enjoyed the part of taking photos and creating website in this process. I woul d prefer to have the topic given so 
that I could spend more time in learning the technical issues and finding out creative ways to do the same thing differently. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Ethnic and Racial Composition Trends* 
70% 12% 0% 9% 3% 
6% 
Whi
i i
Asi0% 6% 3% 
i i
i
Asi
Rac ial Composition of Central Square in 2000 
te 
Afrcan Amercan 
A merican Indian 
an 
Other 
Tw o or mo re races 
Source: US Census 2000 Rac ial Composition of Central Square in 1990 
72% 19% White 
Af r can Amer can 
Amer can Indian 
an 
Other 
Source: US Census 1990 
Income: How Does Central Square Compare to Cambridge? 
Hispanic Population Trends 
*Census data asks respondents if they are Hispanic in separate question. 
In 2000, 7.2% of Central Square residents identified themselves as Hispanic, compared to 7.7% in 1990. The figures for Cambridge were 7.3 (2000) and 
6.4 (1990), (Source: US Census 1990 &amp; 2000). 
A Neighborhood Change Fact Sheet by William Carry  Dec. 2, 2003 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Decrease in low and middle income, renter groups, and students -manifest ed in the decrese in the percentage o f 
20-34 population age- suggest that they groups are moving out of Central Square. Additional data might assert i f 
students are gradually renti ng towards East Cambridge. 
link to: Purpose, Process, and Reflections 
link to: Who is moving 
out?.doc 
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>-------------------------------------------------------------------------------- Lecture 4: Change Over Time 
I. Charts and Maps 
A. Graphing Statistics and Da ta by Wallgreen et al. 
(Sage, Thousand Oaks, 1996: pp. 13-16) 
i.	Bar charts, Horizontal bar charts , Grouped bar charts, Staked bar 
charts 
ii. Histograms  
iii. Population pyramids  
iv. Pie charts 
v.	Scatterplots  
vi. Line charts, Area charts, Flow charts 
vii. Boxplots 
viii. Density maps  
ix. Choropleth maps (thematic maps)  
B. America by the Numbers by Frey et al. 
(New Press, New York, 2001) 
i.	Median income by sex and race, 1998  
ii. White attitudes toward school integration 
iii. Self-identified race of selected U.S. hispanics, 1990  
iv. Population structures, 2000 
v.	Urbanization in the United States 
vi. The face of today's urban growth  
vii. High-school dropout rate by race, 1998  
C. Understanding by Richard Saul Wurman 
(Ted Conferences, Newport, 1999) 
i.	Immigration 
ii. Juvenile crime  
D. Original charts: different presentation of the same data: U.S. Population by 
Race from 1790 to 1990 
i.	Stacked bar chart 
ii. Ratio chart  
iii. Line chart 
iv. Line chart by index </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>ETHNIC DIVERSITY BY CENSUS TRACT PERCENTAGE 1 
0.9 
0.8 
0.7 
0.6 
0.5 
0.4 
0.3 
0.2 
0.1 
0 illi25017352100 
25017352200 
25017352300 
25017352400 
25017352500 
25017352600 
25017352700 
25017352800 
25017352900 
25017353000 
25017353100 
25017353200 
25017353300 
25017353400 
25017353500 
25017353600 
25017353700 
25017353800 
25017353900 
25017354000 
25017354100 
25017354200 
25017354300 
25017354400 
25017354500 
25017354600 
25017354700 
25017354800 
25017354900 
25017355000 OTHER 
PACIFIC 
ASIAN 
NATIVE AMERICAN 
BLACK 
WHITE 
Author: 
Susana M. W ams 
Data Source: 
US Census 2000 
12/02/2002 CENTRAL SQUARE TRACT 
CAMBRIDGE CENSUS TRACTS 
This chart provides a more detailed understanding of the different groups comprising 
the Central Square area. It is very easy to see how Central Square is not one of the 
most diverse areas in Cambridge anymore. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>What has been the impact of gentrification on Central Square? 
On rents? On the racial and income  mix? On the neighborhood fabric? 
Rent and Real Estate Value Trends 
Central Square Cambridge 
1990 2000 % Chg 1990 2000 % Chg 
Median Gross Rent* $493 $971 97.0% $538 $962 78.8% 
Median Value Owner-
Occupied Unit* $219K $224K 2.4% $256K $331K 29.1% 
*Values are not adjusted for inflation. Source: US Census 2000 and 1990 
Population Trends Poverty Trends 
0 0 
l
iPerc ent Change in Poverty Rates 1990-2000: 
Central Square in the Regional Context 
-0.3 -0.2 -0.1 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 
C ent ral Sq uare C ambrdige B ost on M et ro A rea % Chg in Poverty 1990-2000 
Source: US Census 1990 &amp; 2000 -0.2 -0.1 5 -0.1 -0.05 0.05 0.1 
1 970-1 980 1 980-1 990 1 990-2000 
Decade Population Change Cent ra  Square 
Cambr dge Population Trends in Central Square and Cambridge: 
Perc ent Change 1970-2000 by Dec ade 
Source: US Census 1 970, 1 980, 1 990, 2000 
A Neighborhood Change Fact Sheet by William Carry  Dec. 2, 2003 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS: 
1. What is your position and who is your intended audience?
I am a private consultant for the Central Square Economic Development Association which is comprised of all 
the businesses in the area. Their marketing strategy relies heavily on the  diversity in Central Square mani
fested through its murals and ethnic stores.  The association wants to ensure that they should continue investing 
on this image or if they should refocus their goals since there is also a trend for gentrification. 
2. What is the question and why is it important? 
The question is: Is diversity a true character of Central Square or is it just a nostalgic image and a current 
business tool? It is important for the businesses of the area since there are conflicting views about gentrification 
and economic development among businesses themselves. Central Square has always portrayed itself as a community of immigrants and celebrates that fact.  Some stores (and also residents) capitalize on this issue and 
set restrictions for other types of development. However, different business interests feel the need to refocus 
some of their strategies and be able to learn for sure what they can count on. 
3. After some analysis, you will likely refine your question.  Describe one assumption inherent in your position. 
The assumption made was that Central Square was viewed as the most diverse area in Cambridge and that this 
diversity was only based on race and ethnicity since there was not more specific information broken down into 
neighborhoods to estimate diversity in income levels (professional, students and blue collar), different age groups etc. 
4. Briefly describe your methodology. Do you rely heavily on quantitative data? Qualitative data? A combination 
of the two? 
For the framing of the questions, qualitative data was important to me since it was matter of the image of Central 
Square. However, I relied heavily upon quantitative data to find ethnicity rations within each tract, population densities and percentages that would give me a better insight on this project. 
5. What is the principal finding? Did your analysis support or deny your original hypothesis? Did you discover a 
finding that was only remotely related to your original question, and change your question? 
My findings corroborated one of my assumptions that questioned whether diversity was being used to preserve a 
nostalgic image and a current business tool to promote an identity for the area. 
6. Identify at least three constraints you experienced during the research process. 
a.	Restrictions on the amount of data provided for the project.  Diversity for me is not only based on race or 
ethnicity, but also on different educational and income levels that may bring professionals or blue-collar 
workers to live close together. An aspect of diversity is also manifested on different age levels (i.e. 
young professionals, children and seniors in the same neighborhood). It would have been interesting to get more of this information in a smaller level than the census tract to see the actual composition of 
Central Square. 
b.	Schedule of TAs was incompatible with most of my classes.  Many of the scheduled hours were set when 
most of us were having the core courses. This was more of an inconvenience than a constraint because 
I have to chase them later otherwise. 
c.	Some of the programs are more user-friendly than other ones and I found myself repeating one of the 
labs thoroughly to re-understand the main concepts. 
7. Describe one action you would take to overcome one of these constraints. Be specific. Imagine that you were 
given the entire semester to complete the project. What action(s) would you take to improve the end result? With a full semester, I think we would have been able to utilize much more of the data existing in the network and 
have the opportunity to look for missing data on our own. 
8. Did you enjoy the process? Why or why not? How might you change your approach or question so that it had
more meaning or held your interest? 
I certainly enjoyed the process.  I felt I had the opportunity to actually utilize the tools we learned in a more 
comprehensive way.  My current approach and questions were influenced by availability of data for the course.  I may have approached Central Square in a different way if I knew I had no restrictions on what it could have been 
used (i.e. community organizations and citizen participation, minority levels of involvement in the neighborhood, 
role of religious groups in community building and immigrant access to some of these services). </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Susana Williams
DIVERSITY IN CENTRAL SQUARE 
Analysis prepared for: 
THE CENTRAL SQUARE ECONOMIC DEVELOPEMENT ASSOCIATION 
By: Williams and Associates. 
Central Square businesses have invested in its diversity as one of its great
est strengths and have marketed itself that way.  But how diverse is Central 
Square? 
Central Square portrays an image of diversity along Massachusetts Avenue. 
ion wi ii$ 2 0 2 $ 
$ $ 
$ 
$ 
$ $ 
$ 
$$ $$$ $ $$$ 
$$ 
$ $$$ $ $$ $$ $ $$ $ $ $ $$$ $ $ $ $ $ $ $$$ $ $ $ 
i i i il$ $ 
$ $ 
$ 
$ 
$ $ 
$ 
$ $ $$$ $ $$$ 
$$ 
$ $$$ $$ $ $$ $$ $ $$ $ $ $ $$$ $ $ $ $ $ $ $$$ $ $ $ i i i i l i  i i
iN N 
White Populat th n each Census Tract 
37% - 57% 
57% - 68% 
68% - 76% 
76% - 81% 
81% - 93% Cambr dge Border Central Square Boundary MBTA Subway 
BLUE 
GREEN 
ORANGE 
RED MBTA Stops 4 Miles WHITE AND NON-WHITE POPULATION BY CENSUS TRACT 
$ $ 
Non-Wh te Populaton w thn each Census Tract 
7% - 18% 
18% - 23% 
23% - 32% 
32% - 41% 
41% - 63% Cambridge Border Centra  Square Boundary MBTA Subway 
BLUE 
GR EEN 
OR AN GE 
RED MBTA Stops Explor ng the wh te-non-wh te rat o of popu at on on each tract n Cambr dge 
Author: 
Susana W lliams Data Source: 
U.S. Bureau of the Census, 2000 
MBTA 
Date: 
November 30, 2002 
Analyzing the percentages of white and non-white population in the Central 
Square Tract, one can see that the percentage of white people is much 
higher than that of non-white. </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Optional Session - Spatial Data Acquisition via MassGIS: Lisa Sweeney, Guest Lecturer&#160;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-204-planning-communications-and-digital-media-fall-2004/resources/lec8_lisaswee_ho/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>US Locations covered by detailed GIS datasets found in the MIT Libraries: 
King County, WA
Location  Rotch Library - GIS Collection | CDROM G4283.K3 2003.K49 
ARIS, Atlanta region information system
Location  Rotch Library - GIS Collection | CDROM G3924.A8 2002.A7
MassGIS data
Location  Rotch Library - GIS Collection | CDROM G3760 2002.M47 
World Data
Title  Global planner  [electronic resource]: international datasets / Tobin International, Ltd.
Location    Rotch Library - GIS Collection | DVDROM G3200 2004.T63
Set of DVDs with 3 separate datasets on each DVD.  1)Russian maps (1:500:000 scale); 2) digital chart of the world (dcw) (vector files at 1:1,000,000 scale) 3) usgs geologic data 
Title  Landsat mosaics  [electronic resource] : worldwide bundle. 
Location    Rotch Library - Circulation Desk | CDROM G3201.A43 2004.L3 
Title    NIMA GEOnet names  [electronic resource] : shapefile format for GIS. 
Location    Rotch Library - GIS Collection | CDROM G105.N55 2003 
Helpful for searching for names, especially when overlaid on Russian maps (from Global Planner) or landsat images 
Title    World  [electronic resource]. 
Location    Rotch Library - Circulation Desk | CDROM G3200 2000.W67   
Great datasets that are in process in the library so you must ask Lisa  about 
them at this point: 
 Boston Metro area aerial photo 1 foot resolutions taken February 2004 
 City of Boston 2004 assessors data 
 City of Cambridge GIS   foot resolution aerial photo taken April 2003 
 	City of Cambridge 2004 data:  
Annotation
Labels for City features 
Conservation 
Delineated wetlands
Grids
Grids used for Cambridge mapping  
Historical
 Conservation Districts
 Historical Districts 
 Historical Landmarks 
 Historical Markers 
Planimetric (2003 unless noted) </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Buildings  building polygons. Footprints split with common walls 
Building High Point  geodatabase, high point and roofline elevations 
Hydro  water bodies 
Paved Surfaces roads, sidewalks, parking lots, &amp; driveways 
Political Boundaries 
City Boundary 
Neighborhoods  Cambridge CDD neighborhoods Wards &amp; Precincts  cuurent
 Zip Codes 
Recreational
Open Space  Current
Schools
Public school locations  new as of fall 2003 
Tax
Assessors tax parcels. Current to FY2004 
Topo
Contours  2-foot interval
 Spot Elevations
DTM  from 4/17/03 flyover
Transportation
Rail Lines from 4/17/03 flyover 
Road Centerlines from 1995  
Zoning 
Cambridge Zoning  Current
 	New York City  similar to listing for the City of Cambridge above 
 	Geocoding allows one to map a list of addresses by associating it with a street file in a GIS system. ESRI Street Map USA data files are a great data source for geocoding in 
the US.  Currently the files must be requested from the GIS lab .  
Another source for geocoding are the US Tiger files, which can be freely downloaded 
from multiple sources, one of which is: 
http://www.esri.com/data/download/census2000_tigerline/   The TIGER files are not as 
well maintained as ESRIs Street Map USA so they can be more challenging to work 
with.   
 	ESRI Data And Maps </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Spatial Data Acquisitions 
MIT Library Highlights 
The GIS website: 
MIT Library Online Catalog:
When looking for gis data in Barton it is recommended to use the Advanced search options.
Many of our cds will come up if you do a subject = gis search. If you are looking for digital
data you can limit the physical format in your search to CD-ROMs or DVDROMs only.
MIT Library online map guides:
Geodata repository  bring gis data directly into ArcMap over the network 
US Data:
US Demographic data 
In addition to the several drawers of cds from the US Census Bureau in the GIS lab the MIT 
Libraries has a host of packaged  census data from Geolytics.  Geolytics goal is to make 
mapping census data easier.  Data can be exported from Geolytics cds as shapefiles and 
brought into ArcGIS where one would find many additional analysis and display tools and 
options.  To find Geolytics cds do an advanced search in Barton on Publisher = Geolytics. 
 	CensusCD 1970  
 	CensusCD 1980 
 	CensusCD+maps 
 	CensusCD. 1990 long form in 2000 boundaries 
 	CensusCD 1990. Blocks 
 	CensusCD 2000  
 	CensusCD 2000 long form SF3    
 	CensusCD neighborhood change database (NCDB): 1970-2000 tract data: selected variables for US Census tracts for 1970, 1980, 1990 and 2000 and mapping too! 
 	CensusCD estimates, projections, consumer expenditures and profiles, 2003/2008  
 	Crime reportsCD electronic resource]. 
ICPSR  Numeric Social Science data available through the Harvard-MIT Data Center </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>US Public Domain Data Online: 
The US has a lot of public domain data created by the federal government at consistent scales
for the entire US. The following data types are available through national and state websites:
USGS Seamless data server - http://seamless.usgs.gov/
The National Map - http://nationalmap.usgs.gov/
Links to many state websites through the MIT Library GIS page -
DOQQs  Digital Orthophoto Quarter Quadrangles - Public domain aerial photos covering
the United States, generally about 1 meter resolution
NED  National Elevation Dataset - 30 meter resolution elevation data for the US gathered
by the USGS over many years.
SRTM  Shuttle Radar Topography Mission  30 meter resolution elevation data for the US;
90 meter for the world gathered by NASA during an 11 day shuttle mission.
NLCD  National Land Cover Dataset 30 meter resolution land cover for the US
NHD  National Hydrography Dataset 1:100,000 scale hydrography for the entire US, more
detailed scales available in areas where local governments have participated with the USGS
http://nhd.usgs.gov/
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Data Online: 
MassGIS: 
http://www.mass.gov/mgis/database.htm 
 Image Data 
 Political/Regional Boundaries 
 Indexes 
 Infrastructure 
 Demographics (Population) 
 Topography 
 Physical Resources 
 Hydrographic (water-related) Features  
 Conservation/Recreation 
 Regulated Areas 
 Environmental Monitoring 
 Coastal and Marine Features  
 Miscellaneous 
Color Orthophoto 1:5,000 Index Grid: 
http://www.mass.gov/mgis/oqindx.htm 
You will want to download the shapefile version of this index and open it in your GIS project 
to figure out the file name for your area of interest. 
The Grid ID is composed of the first 3 digits of each coordinate in this xy pair. For example, a 
grid cell with xy coordinates of 253000m 942000m at the lower right corner would have an ID 
of 253942. All datalayers registered to these index covers will have the grid number ID as part 
of their name. </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Bottom Up GIS</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-204-planning-communications-and-digital-media-fall-2004/resources/lec6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>A. Context and Problem 
1.	Homeownership rates in the City of Lawrence  
2.	Homeownership rates in the North Common  neighborhood 
B. Housing Demand 
1.	MIT students work with potential homebuyers to identify  neighborhood assets 
and problems  
2.	Maps  created to depict resident perceptions </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>A GIS project </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Figure 4
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Figure 5
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 6: Local Knowledge and PPGIS 
I. Housekeeping 
A. Update on Exercises and Projects 
1.	Lab 5 due on Wednesday; Lab 4 will be returned to you shortly  
2.	Project 1 - Web Portfolio; Due Lecture 8 
3.	Project 2 - Will be assigned Recitation 8; Town and topic selection by Lecture 8.  
B. Other Things 
1.	Portfolio critique in one w eek! We have 2 volunteers...  
2.	Feedback/Feed yourself session tonight at 6PM....quick show of 
hands 
II. Local Knowledge and PPGIS 
A. Last Week: Mapping, GIS, and Planning 
1.	Mapping is an inextricable facet of our di sposition and is fundamentally political  
2.	GIS is central to planning; NIS is growing in popularity 
3.	Data are subjective; Values are embedded in  Census and administ rative data sets  
B. Today 
1.	Brief introduction to the concept of local knowledge 
2.	Brief introduction to PPGIS  
3.	Three Case Studies 
4.	Critique 
C. Local Knowledge and PPGIS 
1.	Local knowledge is the mixture of knowledge built up through practical 
experience and the frames of reference that  people use to filter  and give meaning 
to that experience. (Talen, 2000) 
2.	PPGIS (or BUGIS) - Public Participati on GIS (or bottom-up GIS): It is both a 
process and a product 
III. Lawrence, Massachusetts </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>An inventory of housing stock by zone. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Figure 3
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>C. Impact: Visualizing Housing Supply  
1.	Handheld computers to collect neighborhood-level data  
2.	A inventory of housing stock by zone  (no. of units, occupancy, condition, 
materials, photograph)  
3.	MIT students work with youth in the  field 
4.	A GIS project  for collective housing development decisions 
Subject Web Site 
Final Report 
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>V. Venice, Italy 
A. Context and Problem 
1. City departments collect and maintain a variety of data for various purposes  
2. Most data is collected in ad -hoc manner and as needed  
3. Data is archived in a variety of media and formats  
B. Solution: City Knowledge 
1. City workers would benefit from a more systematic organization of information  
2. Maintenance 
3. Management  
4. Examples  
i. Measurement of canal width, depth, tidal currents, etc. 
ii. What causes canal wall damage? 
iii. A word about boat traffic 
iv. Boat wakes (Figures 1 and 2) or clogged sewers (Figures 3 and 4)? 
B. Impact 
1. Informing maintenance and management decisions  
Content for the Venice case was borrowed fr om Fabio Carrera's doctoral dissertation. 
VI. PPGIS 
A. Case Study Critique 
1. Compare and contrast these projects with one another  
2. Compare and contrast one of these projects with Philadelphias NIS  
3. What are the strengths of PPGIS? Weaknesses? 
4. What type of problems are partic ularly well-suited for PPGIS?  
5. Under what circumstances would PPGIS be particularly problematic? </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Figure 2
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>IV. New Delhi, India 
A. Context and Problem 
1. Rapid urban growth/increased demand for basic services  
2. Approximately 1,200 settlements; squatte r population estimates about 3 million  
3. Local agencies lack the information they n eed to better plan a nd deliver services  
4. Delhi Jal Board (DJB) is obliged to provi de water to all low-income settlements  
B. Intervention - National Institute for Urban Affairs 
1. Working to build community capacity and increase government responsiveness  
2. New Sanjay Amar Colony is an informal settlement in eastern New Delhi  
3. Planning, Learning, and Action (PLA) techniques  
4. Community mapping exercises :  
Chalk is used to draw a map of the community directly on the ground - 
Figure 1 
Residents are asked to use leaves, pebbles, and sticks to communicate 
important demographic information - Figures 2 
Community volunteers and NIUA facilitato rs then transfer the information 
that is collected on the ground to paper - Figure 3 
These maps are simply hyperlinked rath er than spatially integrated with 
the existing data layers for New Delhi - Figures 4, 5 
C. Impact Using Information to Le verage Improved Public Services 
i.	 Insufficient number of water taps  
ii.	 A preponderance of broken water taps 
iii. Insufficient water delivery and drainage systems  
iv.	 Unequal access to water taps 
2. Actions 
i.	 Residents showed DJB engineers the lo cation of existing taps, broken taps, 
low water pressure points, and etcetera 
ii.	 A construction crew broke ground to la y new pipelines, repair and install 
new stand posts 
NIUA </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Web Portfolio Critique</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-204-planning-communications-and-digital-media-fall-2004/resources/lec7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 7: Web-Portfo lio Critique 
Nove mber 1, 2004 
 
I. Housekeeping 
A. Update on Exercises and Projects 
1. Lab 6 due Recitation 8 ; Lab 5 will b e returned to  you shortly  
2. Project 1 - Web Portfolio; Due Lecture 8 (extension due date is Lecture 9)  
3. Web Portfolio Q&amp;A Session after Recitation 8  
4. Projec t 2 - W ill be assigned Recita tion 8;  Town and topic se lection by L ectur e 8 
5. Calendar - Quick glance (A wo rd about the next m onth)  
II. Web Portfolio Evalu ation Criteria 
A. Function = 40pts 
1. Portal page is publ icly accessi ble on the WWW -  5pts  
2. Portal page display has m aximum width of 1,024 pixels - 5pts  
3. All links and buttons from portal to  subsequent pages work - 8pts  
4. Portal page indicates your full nam e - 2pts  
5. Portal page has an operating link to  the MIT web portal page - 2pts  
6. All im ages appear and load quickly -5pts  
7. All docum ents in the portfolio open pr operly (P DF, PPT, Word, etc.) - 5pts  
8. All links and buttons on subseque nt pages function properly - 8pts  
B. Organization/Navigation = 20pts 
1. Portal p age effectively o rients viewer (o rganization/navigation system  is clear) - 
5pts  
2. Your web site has at least 3 other pages (not including the po rtal page) - 5pts  
3. Each page h as an approp riate title (ap pears in the title ba r of web browser) - 5pts  
4. Subsequent pages allow viewer  to return to portal - 5pts 
C. Design and Content = 20pts 
1. Quality of text (e.g., grammar and spelling) is acceptab le - 4pts  
2. Image quality is acceptable (e.g., re solution, composition ) - 4pts  
3. Color, fonts, and other design elem ents are used consistently - 4pts  
4. At least one 11.204 Lab exercise  is available - 2pts  
5. A link to work from /the syllabus for at le ast one other MIT subject is available - 
1pts  </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>1. INTERNIC Whois search (Who has already taken your name, or not yet?)  
2. World Intellectual Property Organization (WIPO) FAQ: Internet Domain Names   
3. Nissan-dot-com dispute   
B. Search Engines and Page Rankings 
1. Google  (robot technology )  
2. Yahoo!  (listing, with a bit of preference for commer cial advertisements )  
3. Looksmart  (for-fee advertisers only; affiliated with search sites such as Lycos)  
C. Maintaining your portfolio 
1. Your tenure at MIT  
2. Resume and employment opportunities  
3. Scholarships and ot her opportunities  
 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>6. A link to prior project/portal page for an organization where you worked or were 
affiliated is available - 1pts  
D. Audience/Message = 10pts 
1. Portal page is an interesting and prof essional representation of self - 6pts  
2. Text (e.g., word selection and meaning) is  appropriate for review by a potential 
employer - 2pts  
3. Image selection is appropriate for revi ew by a potential employer (e.g., meaning) 
- 2pts  
E. Identity = 10pts 
1. Students concerns and interests in public  issues are obvious to  the viewer - 4pts  
2. Students CV or resume with contact information is available (PDF, Word, or 
HTML) - 4pts 
Note: The quality of the CV or resume will not affect your grade.  
3. Site contains at least one link to an extern al site which reveals students interest - 
2pts  
F. RESOURCES 
1. The web portfolio Q &amp; A session  
2. Contact and meet with your TA  
3. Work with each other  
4. Element K  
5. Syllabus, Lecture 2: Link to  Web Publishing at MIT  
6. Syllabus, Lecture 2: Link to Web Style Guide, 2nd Edition (also on reserve in 
Rotch Library) 
III. Portfolio Critique 
A. Student Portfolios 
1. Ian Reddy, Anna Brown, Sara Nafici  
2. Anne Herbst, Susana Williams, Tracy Sayegh  
3. Carlos Montanez, Todd Lieberma n, Danny Cherian, Claudia Canepa 
B. MIT and Other Faculty Portfolios 
1. Professor Keith Hampton  
2. Filippo Caprioglio, Professor Dirk Donath  
IV. Next Steps 
A. Reasons for Purchasing a Domain Name </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <videos>
      <video>
        <video_url/>
        <video_title/>
        <transcript>
          <slice>
            <text_slice/>
            <time_slice/>
          </slice>
        </transcript>
      </video>
    </videos>
  </lectures>
</doc>
