<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-946-planning-in-transition-economies-for-growth-and-equity-spring-2004/</course_url>
    <course_title>Planning in Transition Economies for Growth and Equity</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>Economics </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Shape of Transition: Cities under Transition (PDF) (Courtesy of Alain Bertaud and Bertrand Renaud (Principal of Renaud Advisors). Used with permission.)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-946-planning-in-transition-economies-for-growth-and-equity-spring-2004/resources/april_26/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>CITIES WITHOUT LAND MARKETS: 
LOCATION AND LAND USE IN THE SOCIALIST CITY  
 
 
 
I. INTRODUCTION  
 
 
  The rejection of private ownership of capital and of the m eans of production has been a 
central tenet of Marxist ideology .  To what extent does the socialist city  differ from  the m arket city ? 
How does its land use differ from  the outcom es of our fam iliar models of residential and business 
location based on com petitive land m arkets developed in the tradition of Alonso, Wingo, Muth, Mills 
and now extended beyond the m onocentric city ?  Also, what happens when public ownership and 
public allocation of land is the road chosen to so lve the long-standing concern with the capture of 
public generated land rents by  private owners?   What is the sy stemic impact of the administrative-
command sy stem as a substitute to the m arket?   The purpose of this paper is to describe the long-term  
effects of administrative-com mand systems which do away  with land m arkets on location and land use 
in cities.  
 
  The evidence presented  com es from  Russian cities which are the urban centers with the 
longest history  of developm ent in the absence of  land m arkets.  Except for the old historical centers, 
almost all of Russian urban growth has taken place during the Soviet era 1917-1991. The fact that urban 
developm ent took place in a period when land was nationalized and administratively  allocated, rather 
than sold on an open m arket for a price, has had a very  profound im pact and negative im pact on the 
internal organization of Russian cities. The com bination of Marxist ideology , national institutions, 
domestic econom ic sy stem and level of urbanization has produced somewhat different results in each 
socialist econom y. However, it is quite relevant to speak of a "socialist city " wherever urban 
developm ent is expected to proceed without land m arkets and land use decisions are made 
administratively .1/  The socialist city  experim ents bring out m ultiple issues of property  rights, 
institutional organization and governance, agency  problem s, as well as urban planning regulations. This 
paper focuses only on the striking spatial anom alies and pervasive urban inefficiencies caused by  the 
inability  of an adm inistrative-com mand sy stem to evaluate even very  approxim ately the value of a land 
site and its opportunity  cost in alternative uses and to rem edy the grossest land use m isallocations.   
 
 
                     
1/ Our initial interest in the structure of socialist cities started with field work in China in 1988, see Renaud and 
Bertaud, 1989.  A sem inal influence were the papers in Fr ench and Ham ilton, 1979. Qualita tive results com parable to 
those presented here for Mo scow and St. Petersb urg have also been obtained in the case o f other socialist cities su ch as 
Warsaw i n Poland and B eijing, Shanghai  and Ti anjin in China, see B ertaud, 1994. 
 1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>FIGURE 3  
  EMERG ING M ARKET S' LAND PRI CE GRADIENTS
 in Moscow ,  Krakow, an d Paris
0102030405060708090100
0 5 10 15 20 25 30
Distance from City Center (km)Relative price fro m centerMoscow, 1992
first quarter
Moscow, 1992
fourth quarter
Krakow, Poland
1992
Source: Moscow, Krakow: Joseph K. Eckert,  Paris: Ministere de l'equipement, des transports et du Lo gement (DAFU) R_prgrad.xlsParis,1995
 
 
 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>IV. THE TRANSITION TO MARKETS: IS THE SOVIET CITY SUSTAINABLE?  
 
 
  Urban land markets are expected to raise the efficiency  of the socialist city , but what 
happens during the transition, especially  in Russia?  For seven decades, Soviet planners have m ade 
urban investm ent decisions under four greatly  distor ted prices: land had not site value, interest on 
capital was not recognized, energy  prices were only  a sm all fraction of world prices, and cash wages 
bore no relation to the m arginal productivity  of labor.  The em ergence of m arkets will lead to sharp 
shifts in relative prices.  In cities, the process is likely  to be seriously  disruptive.  We can only  point 
here at som e of the m anagem ent issues during this transition to m arkets.9 What will  be the outcom e of 
the interactions between the negatively  sloped land price gradient with the positively  sloped population 
density  gradient?   What will happen to: (1) the land occupied by  existing enterprises, and (2) to the 
pricing of dwelling units, both rents and sale prices?  
 
A. Market  Prices and Affordability of Land Currently Occupied by Enterprises  
 
  Land reform  adm inistrators are presented with a difficult dilem ma: if enterprises are 
asked to pay  the m arket price (as defined above) for the land they  occupy  -- in the form  of rent or land 
use tax -- m ost of them  would not be able to afford it, and som e would have to be declared bankrupt.  
Alternatively , if the financially  weaker enterprises are given a reprieve or a waiver on the cost of land 
they occupy , this will perpetuate the status quo.  The urban com munity  will lose the opportunity  cost of 
the land.  New infrastructure would have to be developed elsewhere, while the costly  existing 
infrastructure would rem ain underused.   If the objective is to im prove land use efficiency  as rapidly  as 
possible, one approach for responding to the above dilem ma is to grant to existing enterprises explicit 
property  rights in the land they  now occupy . Then the enterprise will have the incentive to use this land 
as equity  in planning to relocate to m ore affordable, appropriate land.   
 
  The value of the land resources involved in industrial land recycling -- even under the 
emerging low and still flat price gradient estim ated for 1992 in FIGURE 3-- is very large.  If we assum e 
that the percentage of industrial land of Moscow could be reduced from  the present 32% to 10% -- still 
a high ratio by  international standards -- then about 100 square kilom eters of already  developed land 
could be recovered.  Current Russian discussions of the affordability  problem  of non-residential land 
are a false problem  which ignores the necessity  of  land use transition.  By definition, the market price 
of land is affordable to new users.  The industrial land m ay not be affordable, however, to existing  users 
who are asked to pay  for it retroactively , but these existing users are precisely  those who are using land 
in an inefficient m anner.  The affordability  dilem ma can be solved by recognizing the land equity  
interest of present land users and then allowing these users to trade freely  the land they  occupy .   
 
B. Impact of the Transition to Markets on Housing and Services Areas  
 
  The  basic price of a housing unit depends on three m ain param eters:  (1) location, (2) 
floor area, and (3) land area.  Households, when shopping for housing, have to m ake trade-offs  between 
those three param eters.  For a given shelter price, suppliers are theoretically  able to provide a dwelling 
unit in any  location.  This is possible by  allocating different com binations of values to the three basic 
param eters:  location, floor and land.  Thus, the floor-to-land-area ratio of different housing unit types 
may varies widely  within the sam e city.  The net land area required to build one square meter of floor 
                     
9  For det ails,  see B ertaud and R enaud  (1994). 
 
 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>units are now rising dram atically .1/   A prelim inary  empirical analy sis of 2,000 transactions carried in 
the first trim ester of 1992 and of another group of trans actions in the fourth trim ester of the sam e year 
provides an important first look at em erging real estate and land prices.   The study  analy zed the 
residuals from  an apartm ent sales m odel that uses only  building-specific variables based on resales of 
privatized apartm ents.  It is possible to construct a land price gradient by  plotting the residual as a 
function of distance from  the center of the city  as show in FIGURE 3. These prelim inary  results provide 
some critical inform ation.  First, the em erging price gradient is downward sloping from  the center.  
Clearly , housing kombinats are not providing the housing that household value the m ost.  As FIGURE 
3.a shows, the land price index decreases from  100% in the center to 70% at 25 km . -- a negative price 
gradient -- with the greatest decreases com ing in the first 8 km.  This m odel suggests that, at present, 
imputed land prices are only  about 1.5 tim es higher at the center than at 25 km .  This is still a very weak 
price differential to trigger the urban restructuring th at Russian cities need.  Various factors can explain 
this flat price gradient including the collapsing econom y, ambiguities about land values, and the 
disequilibrium  state of an em erging m arket.  
  
  What is rather striking and unanticipated is that the land price gradient seem s to be 
rotating very  rapidly  during the transition to m arket.7 The analy sis for the second period in Moscow 
shows that the slope of the price gradient has steepened from  100 percent in the center to 58 percent at 
only 15 kilom eters from  the center.  This a real adjustm ent of 20 percent in less than a y ear.  It can be 
expected that, with new legal clarifications of land ownership rights in Decem ber 1992, privatization, as 
well as continuing  relative price changes regarding energy  the gradient will continue to rotate rapidly .  
This expectation is also fed by  a sim ilar analy sis of land prices in Krakow, Poland which shows that in 
that city the land price differential has already  reached a m arket city  differential of  about 10 to 1.   
Polish urban reform s, in particular the restoration of private land ownership rights has been more 
thorough that what has been done so far in Russia.  At this early  stage in the developm ent of the land 
market, location values are not y et being fully  capitalized into property  values.  A m ore norm al price 
differential will only  emerge when investors have m ore certainty  about land tenure, when real estate 
inform ation institutions becom e more proficient, and when econom ic and political conditions stabilize.   
 
                     
6/  For reference, i t is estimated that about  125,000 housi ng uni ts were exchanged or sol d in 1992. Since 
there are about 3.1 m illion apartm ents in Moscow, this represents a rate of about  4 percent of the housing stock. In a 
market city, the annual  ratio of housi ng trades i s often of t he order of 15 percent  of the stock. A  m ajor soci al change i s 
taking place with the rapid privatizati on housing units by their o ccupants.  Between late 1992 and the end of 1993, 
35.5% of t he state stock was pri vatized i n Moscow and 26% i n Russia. By the end of 1994, the share of privately 
owned Moscow units was expected to reach   55%, in dram atic contrast to a ratio of less than one percent in 1990. This 
Muscovite rate o f privatizatio n remains much higher than other cities.   
7  Privatization of housi ng uni ts has been part icularly rapid in Moscow and St . Pet ersburg. B y the end of 
1994.  The share of privately owned units in Moscow has ri sen dram atically from  less than one percent  in 1990 t o 
more than 55 percent  by the end of 1994. 
 
8/  This rapid rotation is confi rmed in  the anal ysis of di fferent  Moscow housi ng pri ce dat a by G.S. 
Madalla, Y. Toda, and  N.N.  Nozdri na  in "The Pri ce of  Apart ments Auct ioned  i n Moscow:  A Heedi ng Approach"  
(unpubl ished draft  paper, M ay 1993). 
 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>space m ay vary  from  0.10 square m eter for high rise apartm ents to 15 square meters for detached 
houses.  Urban regulations and the m any-dimensional features of housing dem and im pose a lim it to the 
theoretically  infinite num ber of perm utations between location, floor area and land area. 
 
  With housing privatization which has been taking place very  rapidly  in Moscow and St. 
Petersburg, a housing m arket is em erging in Russia. H ouseholds are gaining ownership interest in the 
units they currently  occupy , but different units of the housing stock at different locations within each 
city have very  different values.  The larger part of the housing stock built in the periphery  of Moscow 
and St. Petersburg and the 150 largest cities of Russia (nationally  about 55%) consists of prefabricated, 
reinforced-concrete, large-panel, high-rise apartm ents of 5, 9, 12, 15 and 22 floors. The actual econom ic 
value of such units and not their resource cost will be revealed by  household preferences for the first 
time. High rise apartm ents at the periphery  have four problem s. (1) Operating and maintenance costs -- 
defined to include the cost of m aintenance and operations of elevators and lift pum ps, cost of central 
heating caused by  the bad insulation of panel buildings , costs of frequent structural repairs required by  
the building technology  used, and the cost of m aintenance of large com mon open space.  At present, 
rents no longer cover m uch if any thing bey ond the sharply  increased energy  costs.  (2) The space 
standards m easured according to room  dimensions and height of ceiling which did not vary between 
central and suburban locations.  (3) The quality  of am enities including distance to shops and a variety  of 
services m ay be lower than in central locations. (4 Transport costs form erly expressed only in time to 
work, are rising rapidly  in financial terms as energy  costs and other costs rise and transport subsidies 
decrease. 
 
  The m arket price which will em erge as land and real estate m arkets develop m ay turn 
out to be m uch below the replacem ent cost of such a unit.  Most importantly , the market price of such 
units expressed in term s of m arket rent, m ight not even cover maintenance costs.  Viewed through the 
prism  of emerging market prices, much of the housing stock in periphery  apartm ent buildings m ay have 
a discounted present m arket value of less than zero -- a sobering issue for privatization policy  and for 
future housing investm ent program s.  In the case of Moscow, as can be seen in FIGURE 2.a , the units 
at risk would be those located in residential areas with densities above the density  line for Paris between 
kilom eter 9 and kilom eter 22. Given the current housing shortage, transition policies of preferential 
treatm ent in term s of transportation subsidies, higher quality  maintenance m ay ease the burdens on 
residents.  But it will remain a fact that these parts of the housing stock have very  low and m ostly 
negative transitory  econom ic value.  The high accessibility  of som e parts of the suburban areas (around 
metro stations for instance) should provide  the opportunity  for the  em ergence of secondary  
employment centers.   Such centers  would contribute to restoring the econom ic value  of som e of the 
residential areas.   For this to happen,  land use  regulations and  local adm inistrative practices should 
show enough flexibility  and speedy  responsiveness  to allow land conversion wherever  firms of all 
sizes choose to use this location opportunity .  Allowing  this ty pe of land use transform ation to proceed 
 should be a high urban policy  priority . 
 
  It should be clear from  the quantitative analy sis presented that the suburban housing 
crisis which is loom ing in the cities of Russia cannot be attributed to the transition to m arkets, but to the 
legacy  of the past.  This crisis is the result of the adm inistrative-com mand which disregarded the 
practical needs and preferences of the final users and lacked m eans of self-correction.  The econom ic 
value of the housing that was produced did not m atch the true econom ic cost of the resources used.  
This cost was m asked by  distorted accounting prices which provided no meaningful guidance to 
decision m akers who resorted to inadequate or perverse phy sical and adm inistrative criteria. The 
scissors effect between low rents and low wage s on one hand, and rising operation and m aintenance 
costs on the other is not sustainable.  Restoration of an econom ic balance could result from  
 13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>III. EMERGING PROPERTY MARKETS AND REAL ESTATE PRICES  
 
 
 For seventy  years, Soviet Russia has used its great natural resources to built an urban system of 
doubtful efficiency  and sustainability .  More generally , the socialist city  has inordinately  high 
capital/output ratios and requires m ore resources for less urban output that m arket cities.  Urban land 
markets are therefore a very important part of overall econom ic reform s.  The allocation of land should 
be driven by  its current opportunity  cost. However, the value of a specific land parcel in its highest and 
best use can prove difficult to estim ate even in a stable fully  developed urban land m arket. The next best 
prices are actual market transactions which are the result of private valuation of investors looking at the 
future and risking their own-resources .  Since 1990, urban laws and constitutional reform s prom oting 
individual ownership and decisions have been enacted in Russia (Butler and O Leary , 1994), as well as 
other socialist countries, including China (Kerzner 1993). Consistent with Kornai s insight (1990), such 
reform s were initially  attem pted for narrow bureaucratic reasons. 
 
A. Synthetic Land Price Gradients and Normative Prices    
 
  During the late 1980' s, under Gorbachev s perestroika , local governm ents resources 
had becom e severely  constrained. Local m echanism s to finance the production of serviced land had to 
be found to com plement the inadequate resource transfers from  the central governm ent.  It was 
therefore decided to create a land use tax to finance local infrastructure.  In the peculiar logic of an 
administrative-com mand sy stem, officially  land has no value in construction projects.  Yet every one 
agreed that different locations have very  different econom ic values.  The solution chosen was to 
estim ate norm ative land prices on which taxes could be based.  For the first tim e, various research 
institutes began building models to calculate sy nthetic land price m aps according to which taxes would 
be raised, and from  which land price gradients could be derived.  These institutes have attem pted to 
map norm ative values of land calculated on the basis of weighted coefficients representing amenities 
such as transport, infrastructure, environm ental quality , etc.  Ty pically , dem and factors were not 
included, and price estim ates were based on the arbitrary  and highly  distorted accounting prices of the 
late 1980s.  Regardless of these fundam ental flaws, land value m aps were produced from  which one can 
infer a city 's norm ative, land price gradient.   
  The resulting norm ative land price gradients of Moscow and St. Petersburg were 
negatively  sloped.   Moscow' s gradient was som ewhat flatter than St. Petersburg.  The norm ative price 
variation between the center and the periphery in Moscow was only 2.5 to 1 (from  Rb 4,000 at km 0 to 
Rb 1,600 at 22 km  in the now irrelevant 1990 prices).  Both curves are much too flat. In market cities, 
in the absence of major topographical and legal constraints, the ratio between the land price in the 
central business district and at the fringe of the built-up periphery  is usually  on the order of 10 to 1.  In 
spite of their correct slope, the profile of these norm ative curves was highly  arbitrary  as nobody  knew 
either the highest nor the lowest values.  Such norm ative prices could greatly  improve the traditional 
urban master plans made in Russia, but they would be of no value for the choice of a specific location 
for a given investm ent. 
 
B. Housing Privatization and Rapidly Emerging Implicit Land Price Gradients  
 
  With the beginning of housing reform s, actual apartm ent sales transactions between 
private parties have been taking place in Moscow since 1991.  Privatization and opportunities to trade 
 9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>abandonm ent of the least attractive part of the stoc k com bined with increasing crowding of rem aining 
units and m uch higher rent to incom e ratios. 
 
CONCLUSIONS  
 
   The absence of land m arkets has profoundly  impaired  the ability  to allocate and recy cle 
urban land and has had a very  negative im pact on the internal efficiency , productivity , environm ental 
quality , and livability  of  the socialist city.  The extent of land use m isallocation  and the degree of 
rigidity  encountered in the Russian econom y which is by  now fully  urbanized is startling.   The  
consequence is that the socialist city  tends to have very  high capital/output ratios and consum es more 
resources per unit of output.  
 
  A second im portant lesson of the failed socialist experim ent is that the well-m eaning 
attem pt to socialize the collection of the land rent through public ownership and adm inistrative 
allocation of land has not achieved the intended results. There is nothing presented in this paper that 
would call  into question  the social  goals of any  com munity .  Rather, it is the allocation of land by  
administrative m eans in the nam e of equity  and efficiency  which has dem onstrably  failed on an 
inordinate scale.  A broad variety  of social goa ls can be accom modated under m arket conditions. Soviet 
cities rem ind us that what is  m ost  valuable  in urban land market institutions is their ability  to signal 
through prices how the current and future use of land is valued by  individuals and society -- and to 
reveal  how site valuation  shifts up or down over  tim e. 
 
  Finally , the evidence suggests that the social and econom ic transition costs of m oving to 
markets will be the highest in econom ies such as Russia that are m ost highly  urbanized and where cities 
are moving to market during a period of sharp econom ic contraction. Urban reform s are particularly  
urgent and m ost feasible in the socialist econom ies of Asia where econom ies are growing and the 
greatest wave of urbanization still lies ahead.  In order to move to markets, the main components of the 
needed urban reform  are: clear and tradable property  rights; efficient and m arket-oriented inform ation 
systems; a taxation sy stem consistent with efficient land use; and, last but not least, the tim ely publicity  
and contestability  of urban planning decisions (see Bertaud, Renaud, 1994).    
 14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>FIGURE 2 
 
 THE SOCIALIST CITY COMPARED TO THE  MARKET CITY  
 Moscow  Compared to Paris  
 
Figure 2.a  
 
 Com parative den sity profile in  the built-up areas of M oscow an d Paris
050100150200250300350
12 345 6789 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22
Distance from city center (km)popula tion de nsity (p/ha )Moscow
Paris
file:L_Budens.xls
COMPA RATIVE P OPULATION D ISTRIBUTION M oscow, St.P etersbu rg &amp; Paris
-1,000,0002,000,0003,000,0004,000,0005,000,0006,000,0007,000,0008,000,0009,000,000
0
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21
22
23
24
25
Distance  from City  center (km)Cumulative P opulation w ithin km xMoscow
St.Peters burg
Paris
file:R_mblup. xlsFigure 2.b
Unrecy cled land in
Indus trial belt
 8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>This socialist land use process creates sizable  enclaves of "fallow" or "dead land" areas 
which com bine low levels of econom ic activity  with negative environm ental qualities. The Soviet 
administrative command econom y has generated an urban developm ent process with two characteristic 
features of large land use inefficiencies:  (1) Areas  with obsolete land use occupy  large am ounts of the 
total city area; and, (2) Households tend to be con centrated in the periphery  with increasing densities 
further from  the center and "historically " low densities in central areas.  This pattern tends to increase 
transport costs and pollution by  requiring higher energy  expenditures without providing better amenities 
such as larger plot size or a better environm ent that would be the norm al trade-off for increasing 
commuting distance in a m arket econom y. 
 
B.   Why Rusting Factories in Prime Urban Locations?  
 
  The failure to recy cle land occupied by  old activities of little value yields several spatial 
outcom es:  centrally  located industrial belts, large to tal am ount of urban industrial area, low job density  
in the industrial belts, and central land areas fragm ented by  dense railway  networks. There are four 
major consequences. 
 
  First, of these pathologies, the m ost startling are the old industrial belts  that ring 
Moscow and St. Petersburg.  Developed during the 1930' s and 1950' s, these belts are still spread 
between 4 and 8 kilom eters from  the city  centers.  These industrial land use bottlenecks have never been 
recycled, even though the land values would have been prohibitively  expensive for these enterprises 
had m arket land prices been used.  The absence of m arket signals resulted in a land use freeze that 
pushed residential areas further toward the city  periphery  than in m arket cities. Meanwhile, obsolete and 
low density  activities have rem ained as enclaves on accessible and well serviced land.4 
 
  The absence of land prices and the dom inance of industrial planning in governm ent 
thinking and policies explains the second phenom enon.  Not only are Moscow and St. Petersburg 
characterized by  centrally -located industrial belts, but also the total industrial land area within these 
cities is extraordinarily large .  For exam ple, in Moscow, 31.5% of the total built-up area is used by  
industries, compared with 5% in Paris, 6% in Seoul, and 5% for Hong Kong.  In the industrial belt from  
7 to 8 kilom eters from  the center of Moscow, 67% of land is used by  industries.  (See FIGURE 1.a).  
The extensive use of prim e, centrally -located urban land for industries is particularly  inefficient in 
Russia because of socialist industrial organization which requires m ost industries to hold large 
inventories of m aterials in order to survive in the socialist system.  These industries therefore use large 
areas of land for warehousing and heavy transport infrastructure  -- a peculiar constraint on industrial 
land use that results in a low ratio of jobs per unit of land.  In a m arket econom y, such a low job-to-land 
ratio would be incom patible with the central location of these industries. 
 
  Third, the distribution of jobs by  distance to the city  center shows that both Moscow 
and Saint Petersburg, are still m onocentric cities with a high concentration of jobs in the city  center, a 
feature common with most market econom y cities.  (See FIGURE 1.b).  As the transition to m arkets 
progresses, m any industrial jobs will disappear and m ore service jobs will be created.  The majority  of 
these jobs will be located in the city  center further reinforcing the m onocentric characters of these cities. 
 The histogram s of the geographical distribution of jobs for Moscow ( FIGURE .1.b) and Saint 
Petersburg (not shown) confirm  that the industrial zones do not significantly increase the number of 
                     
4 The alm ost Dickensian character of centrally located factorie s in the Soviet Union and China also reflects a 
very low rat e of technol ogical change, especi ally compared to those of t oday s em erging m arkets in Asia.  See t he 
discussion of high growth rates with  little or zero pr oductivity gains under central pl anning in Renaud, 1990.   
 
 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>C. The Socialist City Compared With the Market City:  Moscow   versus Paris  
 
  The comparison of density profiles  between Moscow and Paris is revealing (see 
FIGURE 2.a).  Both m etropolitan regions have a population of about 9 m illion.  They  are strongly  
radio-concentric, and have sim ilar peak densities.  However, the way  densities are distributed 
geographically  is strikingly  different.  Paris shows the ty pical density  profile of a m arket econom y city, 
with a negatively  sloped gradient.  In sharp contrast, Moscow has a positively  sloped density  gradient.   
The net density  of Moscow at 15 kilom eters from  the c ity center is twice as high than in the center.  The 
density  of Moscow suburbs at 15 kilom eters from  the center is the sam e as in the center of Paris.  One 
should note the drop of density  at 6 kilom eters from  the center in Moscow. This drop of density  is due 
to the unrecy cled industrial land use producing the enclaves of "dead land" in the city  fabric. 
 
  T he degree of population dispersion  can be m easured in a rough m anner by  com paring 
the m edian distance to the center per person.  FIGURE 2.b shows the cum ulative population distribution 
curve of Moscow, St. Petersburg and Paris.  The cum ulative curves of Moscow and Paris intersect each 
other at Kilom eter 14, corresponding to a population of about 6 m illion people.  This m eans that within 
a circle of a 14 kilom eters radius, Moscow and Paris serve the sam e population, and as a consequence 
have the same average density .  However, because of the difference in the density  profile between the 
two cities, the m edian distance per person to the center is 7 km  for Paris and 10 km for Moscow, a 42%  
greater dispersion in the case of Moscow .  Is the land use and the density  profiles of socialist cities like 
Moscow or St.-Petersburg a m ere curiosity  for land use specialists?   Em phatically  not.  It matters a 
great deal to the Russian urban econom y where three-fourth of the population lives,  for the following 
reasons: 
 
1. Average densities being equal, the population of a city  with a positively  sloped density  profile is 
more dispersed than one located in a city  with a negatively  sloped profile.  This implies higher 
transport costs, higher prim ary infrastructure costs, higher urban operating costs, and a greater share 
of labor time wasted in travel.  these distortions are paid for in the form  of lower levels of econom ic 
developm ent. 
 
2. A large am ount of floor space has been developed where there is little dem and for it, that is, in the 
suburbs with less accessibility .  When transport subsidies are progressively  removed and full wages 
restored, demand -- and consequently  land prices -- for this ty pe of high density  housing far from  
the city  center will drop even further.  Prices could well drop below replacem ent costs and trigger 
abandonm ent. 
 
3. The fully -serviced,  underused land close to the city  center has a high opportunity  cost.  
                                                                               
liberalizatio n are n ow triggering massive shifts in  relativ e prices that are deeply disruptive, as discussed further in Part 
IV. 
 
 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>15
 BIBLIOGRAPHY  
 
 
1. BERTAUD, A. (1994), Land Markets, Urban Form, and the Environment  paper presented at the Annual 
World Bank Conference on Environmentally Sustainable Development, Washington DC, September. 
 
2. _____________ and  B. RENAUD (1994),  Cities Without Land Markets, Lessons of the Failed Socialist 
Experiment , World Bank Discussion Papers Series No. 227, March. 
 
3. BUTLER, S. B. and S. OLEARY (1994), Laws Relating to Housing and Urban Development in the Russian 
Federation, Washington DC: The Urban Institute, March. 
 
4. ECKERT, J. K. (1993)  The Use of Automated Real Estate Databases to Stimulate the Development of Property Markets and Facilitate Privatization in  V. RENARD and R. ACOSTA eds.  Land Tenure and Property 
Development in Eastern Europe, Paris: Pirvil-CNRS and ADEF . 
 
5. FRENCH R.A. and F.E.I. HAMILTON eds., The Socialist City, Spatial Structure and Urban Policy, 
Chichester, U.K.: John Wiley, 1979. 
 
6. KERZNER, D.S. (1993) The Commercial Real Estate Laws of the Peoples Republic of China and Shenzhen: An Overview  Vanderbilt Journal of Transnational Law , Vol. 26, 581-631. 
 
7. KORNAI, J. (1990) The Affinity Between Ownership Forms and Coordination Mechanisms Journal of 
Economic Perspectives,  Vol. 4, No.3. 
 
8. MEYER, J. R. and J. GOMEZ-IBAEZ (1981)  Autos, Transit and Cities, Cambridge: Harvard U. Press. 
 
9. RENAUD, B. (1990). "China's 1988 Urban Housing Reform s: Origins, Scope, and  Major Obstacles" in G.C. 
Lim and W. Chang (eds), Dynamic Transformation: Korea, NICs, and Beyond , Seoul, Korea:  Myung Bo Publishing 
Co. 
 
10. __________, (1991b). Housing Reform in Socialist Economies , World Bank Discussion Papers Series No. 
125, June. 
 
11. __________, (1992). "The Housing System of the Former Soviet Union: Why Do the Soviets Need Housing Markets", Washington DC: Fannie Mae, Housing Policy Debate , Vol.3, Issue 3, November. 
 
12. __________, (1995)  The Real Estate Economy and the Design of Russian Housing Reforms ,  Urban 
Studies,  Vol. 32, Nos 8 and 12 , Oct ober and December (forthcoming). 
 
13. __________ and A. BERTAUD, (1989), Urban Housing Reforms: The City experiments and the 1988 
Reform  Plan, paper presented at the Joint China-World Seminar on the Urban Housing Reforms System Reforms, 
Beijing, PRC. 
  
14. WORLD BANK,(1994),  Russia: Housing Reform and Privatiz ation: Strategy and Transition Issues , Vol.1: 
Main Report, xlviii and 198 pages; Vo l.2: Annexes, 175 pages. March.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>jobs to justify their prime location  so close to the city  center.  No data were available to conduct a more 
detailed analy sis of present land use and floor space.  But the very high spot prices reached by new 
office space in Moscow and Saint Petersburg are indicative of an acute supply  constraint for land and 
floor space dedicated to services in the city center, a ty pical shortage in socialist econom ies in 
transition. 
 
  Fourth, obsolete form s of intercity  transport further solidify  this frozen land use pattern. 
The land of the industrial belt of Moscow is serviced by  a dense network of railways  which have the 
effect of further fragmenting the land and making land on the exterior side of the industrial belt 
expensive to service .  Only  a sm all part of the volum e of traffic on the rail network within Moscow 
Municipal boundary  is used for passenger and commuter traffic; most of it is used for freight .  This 
fragm entation further reduces the usability  of land ad jacent to centrally -located industrial areas and 
increases significantly  the cost of the prim ary infrastructure network which has to be developed to 
service it.   This fragm entation of urbanized land by   railroads  is linked to the Soviet Union' s 
extraordinarily  high dependence on rail transport com pared to any  other country  which is nine times 
higher than in Western Europe, and to the industrial bias of Soviet econom ic and urban planning. This 
problem  is encountered in m ost Soviet  cities and other socialist econom ies. 
 
C. Dynamics of Housing and Residential Development in the Socialist City  
 
  The prevalence of unrecy cled large-scale industrial belts in Moscow and St. Petersburg 
is a subset of a larger set of spatial distortions found in Russian cities.  The process of developm ent of 
housing projects under the adm inistrative com mand-sy stem and the activities of real estate developers 
in market cities follow different m otivations and y ields totally  different outcom es from  those predicted 
by market m odels of location and land use.  The key  to understanding these larger distortions also 
provides a tool to design policies for reducing ine fficiencies.  In a m arket, housing developers are value  
maximizers while in a supply -driven com mand econom y bureaucratic housing builders are cost 
minimizers with little interest in final users satisfaction since these are not the direct clients which are 
other adm inistrations.   
 4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>FIGURE 1 
 
 INDUSTRIAL LAND USE AND JOB DENSITY PATTERNS  
 
 MOSCOW  - LAND USE 
Job density in Built-up Areas
050100150200250
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21
22
Distance  from City Cen ter (km )Job Densit y (job/hect are)
file:R_mblup.xlsFigure  1.bMOSCOW - LAND USE
Percentage of Industrial Land within t he Buil t-up A rea
0%10%20%30%40%50%60%70%
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21
22
Distance from  City center (km)% of Industrial Land within built-up Area
file:R_mblup.xlsFigure 1.a
 5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>II. LAND ALLOCATION IN CITIES WITHOUT MARKETS   
 
 
  In Soviet Russia, and other socialist cities as well, adm inistrative decisions based on 
"needs" and norm s govern the use and quantity  of land consum ed.  By  contrast, in a m arket econom y, 
land price differentials constitute the m ost im portant factors determ ining quantity  and location of land 
consum ed.  These divergent principles governing land allocation and land use could be expected to 
produce different spatial and efficiency  outcom es.  A quantitative land use analy sis of Moscow and St. 
Petersburg reveals that there are indeed m ajor differences between Russian cities and market econom y 
cities in the distribution and consum ption of land.2  Inspection of land use m aps or satellite photos of 
other Russian cities confirm s that these are sy stemic features of the socialist city .3 
 
A.  Absence of Incentives to Recycle Land in Soviet and Other Socialist Cities  
 
  As their econom y and their population grow, cities expand through the progressive 
addition of concentric rings, similar to the process for trees in successive growing seasons.  New rings 
are added to the periphery  as the city  grows.  Within each ring, land use reflects the com bined effects of 
demography , technology , and the econom y at the time when the ring was developed.  While this 
organic increm ental growth is com mon to all cities, in a market city changing land prices exert their 
pressure sim ultaneously  in all areas of the city , not just at the periphery .  Land prices exert a powerful 
influence to recy cle already  developed land in the inner rings when the ty pe and intensity  of the existing 
use is too different from  the land's optim um econom ic use.  Thus, changing land values bring a built-in 
urban dynamism as continuous variations in land prices trigger land use changes  by  putting a constant 
pressure on the existing uses of land. 
 
  By contrast, under Russia' s com mand econom y, the absence of land prices rem oved all 
incentives to redevelop built-up areas.  Once land was allocated, it was almost never recycled. Without 
price signals, it was adm inistratively  simpler to respond to current land dem and pressure by  developing 
at the periphery  than to redevelop well-located areas with obsolete land uses.  While the city expanded 
outward, land use in already  developed areas rem ained unchanged.  One striking illustration of this 
phenom enon is the persistence and uniform ity of housing ty pes in successive rings around Moscow.  
Each ty pe is usually  designated by  the period in which it was built.  Thus, driving from  the center of 
Moscow, one passes through rings of Stalin, Khrushchev, and then Brezhnev flats. 
 
                     
2  The m ethodology used is based on the m easurem ent of  population density in the built-up area, i.e. the 
population within two concentric rings at 1 km  interval divided by the built-up area within this  inte rval.  This built-up 
area does not  include l arge parks, phy sical obst acles to land use such as ri vers and l akes, and any  undevel oped area. 
These densities are derived from  digitized land use m aps, sa tellite photographs and detailed databases related to land 
uses by  type of users.  These dat a bases are rout inely maintained by  local urban pl anning offi ces. The geocoded data 
was analyzed with a graphics-based GIS software.  
 
3  In Chinese cities, however, the socialist land use system  has a m uch shorter and m ore recent history than 
Russia.  Al so, R ussia has com pleted its urbani zation but  China is just entering its phase of most massive urban growt h.  
As a resul t, the historical Chinese urban core whi ch wa s devel oped under a m arket econom y has kept  a much larger 
relativ e importance th an in Russia.  Mo reover, in China, the absence of large urban infrastru cture and public transport 
investm ent  plus severe under investm ent in housing between 1949 and 1979 has led to m ore com pact cities and 
reinforced the population density at the center.  But now, under the rapid urba n investm ent of the last decade, 
administrative processes operati ng without land m arkets are agai n generating outcom es similar to those of Soviet cities: 
new resid ential floor area ratios follow the Russian  pattern and are h igher in the periphery than in the cen ter. (Fo r more 
comparative data, see B ertaud, 1994). 
 
 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>In a market econom y, private developers com pete for the sam e location.  The winning 
bid will go to the activity  estim ated to be m ost profita ble at that site. Land prices exert their pressure on 
the whole supply  of land, including the already  built land.  This is the key  to econom ically  efficient 
cities and lies at the core of our urban models.  As the city  expands, land prices tend to rise throughout 
the city .  Land prices stay  the highest in the m ost accessible areas around the city  center and along 
transport corridors.  This was already  Von Thnen s fundam ental insight. Such pricing triggers density  
increases in those areas.   The rise in density  triggered by  relative price changes is due to the 
compounded effects of two phenom ena:  (1) Floor-to-land area ratios (FAR) increase in central 
locations because of land recy cling through dem olition and reconstruction, and (2) The consum ption of 
land space per job or per resident decreases because the m ore efficient land users out-bid less efficient 
land users who then m ove to m ore peripheral locations where land is cheaper. 
 
  Over time, the interaction of these effects produces a population density  profile that is 
negatively  sloped from  the high-population center to the sparsely -populated periphery .  The driving 
force behind this density  gradient is not m aster planning by  city planners, but the individual decisions of 
real estate developers who want to maximize the difference between production costs and the m arket 
value of the final product.  As a city  grows larger and richer, recycling land in already  built-up areas 
offers the opportunity  to m aximize this difference.  This is an increm ental and decentralized process but 
it is not slow.  In advanced industrial econom ies, about 2% to 5%  of all urban jobs within an urban area 
relocate every  year, depending on econom ic growth conditions.  In a m arket econom y like the US, 
families relocate about every  five y ears, but 80% of m oves are within the sam e urban area.  
 
  By contrast, under the adm inistrative-com mand econom y, housing construction 
organizations are ty pically  integrated into housing kombinats  and they  respond to very  different 
incentives.  A kom binat' s perform ance is m easured by  its ability  to reduce input costs  while m eeting 
quantitative production targets.  The costs have to be m inimized while the value  of the final product is 
irrelevant.  Land m ay be free, but it m ust be allocated from  what is available.  Due to the lack of 
incentive for land recycling, the supply  of land is lim ited to the new areas developed that y ear in the 
outer fringe.  As a consequence, kom binats have to m eet their production targets using land that is 
almost exclusively  at the periphery .  The density  of the newly  built area (defined as the unit of floor 
space divided by  unit of land) will then reflect the ratio between the developed land available and the 
amount of floor space to be built to m eet the production quota.   
 
  As the socialist city  expands, the land at the periphery  becom es less and less desirable 
and m ore expensive to develop because prim ary infrastructure -- and m etro lines in the case of Moscow 
and St. Petersburg -- have to be expanded.  But in a com mand econom y, housing is entirely  supply -
driven and, if the supply  of serviced land is lagging behind the floor space production target, the 
building density  in the outer rings will tend to rise.  Over tim e, Soviet housing kom binats have been 
stacking up more floor space on the m ore distant land.  The failure to price land is com pounded here by  
artificially  low energy  prices.  The dy namics of such a sy stem do not tend to produce the resource-
preserving, m ore efficient negative density  gradient of m arket cities. 5  
                     
5  Note that the art ificially low soci alist cash wage (see R enaud, 1991) com pounds resi dential land use 
distortions.  In market cities, b ehavioral stu dies sh ow that urban resid ents tend to value their time traveling to work as a 
significant proport ion bet ween one-t hird and one have of the hourl y-wage equi valent of their salary (see C hapter 8 in 
Meyer and Gom ez-Ibaez, 1981).  In socialist cities, the di storting effects on land use allo cation of the lack of land 
prices are further masked by the artificially lo w value that urban resi dents are pl acing on t heir time.  Pri ce and wage 
 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>The World Bank  
Policy Research Working Paper No 1477 
 
 
 
CITIES WITHOUT LAND MARKETS:  
LOCATION AND LAND USE IN THE SOCIALIST CITY 
 
 
by 
 
 
Alain  BERTAUD* and  Bertrand  RENAUD** 
 
* Principal Urban Planner 
Infrastructure and Urban Development Department 
** Housing Finance Advisor 
Financial Sector Development Department 
The World Bank  
H Street N. W. 
Washington DC 20433 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
March 1995   
 
 
 
 
 
The empirical findings presented in this paper result from a program of technical cooperation carried 
out between the Russian Federation and the World Bank.  We are especially grateful to Joseph K. Eckert, Natalya V. Kalinina, Mikhail P. Berezin, Olga Kaganova and Oleg Matiukhin for their assistance during this period; particularly to J. Eckert for the use of the price gradient data.  The analyses and conclusions are solely those of the authors whose views should not be attributed to the 
World Bank nor to any of its affiliated organizations.  
 
ISBN 0-8213-2740-2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>CITIES WITHOUT LAND MARKETS:  
LOCATION AND LAND USE IN THE SOCIALIST CITY  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
ABSTRACT 
 
 How does the spatial dy namics of the socialist city  com pare with that of the m arket city ? What 
happens to a city  when all investm ent decisions are m ade without land m arkets?   What are the outcom es 
when the forces described by  familiar urban m odels aren t allowed to work?  This paper describes the 
structure of Russian cities after seventy  years of Soviet developm ent.  This is the longest socialist 
experience on record and its results are of param ount interest to urban econom ists. In the absence of 
price signals and of econom ic incentives to recy cle land over time, the administrative-com mand process 
has led to a startling pattern of land use.  Its central feature is a perverse  population density  gradient 
which rises as one moves away  from  the center of the city . The Soviet city  is also characterized by  
rusting factories in prim e locations and distant residen tial areas in the suburbs.  Such a structure tends to 
maximize the econom ic and social inefficiency  of the socialist city  and environm ental ill-effects.  Real 
estate prices are now em erging with m arket-oriented urban reform s. Their negative gradient signals 
again the massive scale and fundam ental nature of past land m isallocation in the Soviet city . The 
experience of socialist cities is also a powerful warning about the ill effects of public ownership and 
allocation of land to achieve the  socialization of land rents. 
 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Emergence of the Private Firm (PDF) (Courtesy of John McMillan, Christopher Woodruff, and the American Economic Association. Used with permission.)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-946-planning-in-transition-economies-for-growth-and-equity-spring-2004/resources/march_29/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>168 Journal of Economic Perspectives 
reasonably stable and predictable if the shadow of the future is to give  rms reason 
to be able to trust each other. If you keep your word only because of the prospect 
of future gains, you are more likely to renege when the business environment is very 
noisy. Corrupt bureaucrats and politicians, by extorting bribes, discourage entrepreneurs from investing ( Johnson, McMillan and Woodruff, 2002b). High and 
volatile in ation could undermine  rms attempts at selfhelp contracting. Mass 
privatization, by adding to the uncertainty about which lines of business are going 
to be pro table, might disrupt the nascent inter rm relationships. 
The same ambivalence between the force of informal mechanisms and their 
limits, by the way, is seen in many developing countries. In Africa and Latin 
America,  rms lacking access to the courts engage in a remarkable range of 
productive activity (de Soto, 1989; Fafchamps, 2001; Woodruff, 1998). The lack of 
marketsupporting institutions, however, makes it hard or impossible for these 
 rms to grow into sophisticated corporations. 
The economic transition has been far more painful in some excommunist 
countries than in others. Relative success came in those countries where new market activities were quickly established. Ironically, and contrary to the leaveit
tothemarket view, markets arose faster where the government did not completely 
withdraw, but rather set a stable platform. New  rms entered and grew more slowly 
in Russia, where the government abruptly ceased controlling prices and rapidly 
privatized the state  rms, than in China, where the government mostly continued doing what it had been doing before. 
9 
Conclusion 
The importance of entrepreneurs in the transition economies is a reminder 
that the task of economic transition is not just a matter of government of cials 
enacting certain policies or setting certain rules of operation for the new 
economy. Entrepreneurs acted as reformers, too. Indeed, much of the task of 
devising the new ways of doing business in transition economies has been taken 
on by entrepreneurs. 
By pursuing his own interest, Adam Smith (1776 [1976], volume 1, pp. 
47778) famously wrote of the merchant, he frequently promotes that of society more effectually than when he really intends to promote it. The entrepreneurs in 
the transition countries exemplify Smiths dictum. By creating jobs, supplying 
consumer goods, constraining the market power of the state  rms and building 
reform momentum, they have produced real welfare gains. 
y We thank David Ahn, Simon Board, Simeon Djankov, Brad De Long, John Earle, Alan 
Krueger, Barry Naughton, Timothy Taylor and Michael Waldman for helpful comments. McMillan thanks the Stanford Graduate School of Business for research support. 
9 On the parallel roles of bottomup and topdown forces in developing market rules and procedures, 
see McMillan (2002).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>164 Journal of Economic Perspectives 
directions of causation. But given the importance of informal trading arrangements 
early in the transition, theory suggests that, by making relationships harder to 
establish, macroeconomic instability created a barrier to entry. 
While contracting is mainly supported by informal relationships among  rms, 
the courts also foster it. The courts in the transition economies are still inadequate; it takes a long time to build a wellfunctioning legal system. The evidence shows, 
however, that even these highly imperfect courts facilitate doing business. Managers of startup  rms were asked in a 1997 survey whether they could appeal to the 
courts to enforce a contract with a trading partner. In Poland, 73 percent said they 
could, and in Russia, 56 percent said they could. Belief in the courts affects behavior. Those who say the courts are effective offer more trade credit and are 
more willing to take on new trading partners ( Johnson, McMillan and Woodruff, 
2002a; see also Frye and Shleifer, 1997; Hendley, Murrell and Ryterman, 1999). By 
making it easier for new  rms to enter, workable courts improve on relational 
contracting and boost overall productivity. Even weak courts can be useful. 
The absence of wellfunctioning credit markets matters less early in transition 
than later. In place of external funds,  rms reinvest from their own pro ts. The high pro ts mean that entrepreneurs have the resources they need for expansion, 
without needing to borrow. Retained earnings has been the biggest single source of investible funds for startup  rms in transition economies. In addition, where 
inter rm relationships are working well,  rms receive trade credit from their 
suppliers. Trade credit was almost nonexistent among Russian  rms as of 1997, but in Poland it was as large a source of  rms capital as bank loans ( Johnson, McMillan 
and Woodruff, 2002b). As entry occurs and pro t rates are driven downward, 
however, credit markets become more important. In Vietnam, there is some evidence that credit markets were beginning to reach new private  rms: 24 percent 
of  rms in a 1997 survey reported having bank credit, up from 8 percent in 1991 
(Hemlin, Ramamurthy and Ronns, 1998). 
An alternative source of capital is equity markets. State support is needed for 
an equity market to develop. In Poland, a regulatory agency that intervened to 
protect minority shareholders from expropriation by insiders allowed the stock 
market to develop rapidly (Glaeser, Johnson and Shleifer, 2001). New issues were 
offered regularly. In the Czech Republic, by contrast, the absence of regulatory 
oversight meant people were, rightly, reluctant to invest in  rms because they 
feared the managers would misuse their money, and so the stock market stayed 
inactive. Why is regulation needed for equity markets? Informal creation of share 
ownership is dif cult. Fixed costs of issuing shares to a large group of investors 
prevent a slow buildup of the relationship, with investors testing entrepreneurs as trading partners in Vietnam reported doing. Because outside shareholders lack 
information on the  rms internal affairs, managers can easily expropriate the 
returns owed to the shareholders ( Johnson and Shleifer, 2001). Prospective shareholders need legal and regulatory protection before they are willing to hand their 
money over to  rms. 
Entrepreneurs running de novo startups in Poland reported that an average of 
25 percent of their equity capital was owned by private  rms or people other than</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Journal of Economic PerspectivesVolume 16, Number 3Summer 2002Pages 153170 
The Central Role of Entrepreneurs in 
Transition Economies 
John McMillan and Christopher Woodruff 
All sorts of small enterprises boomed in the countryside, as if a strange army 
appeared suddenly from nowhere, remarked Deng Xiaoping, re ecting 
in 1987 on the  rst eight years of Chinas economic reforms (Zhao, 1996, 
p. 106). These startup  rms drove Chinas reform momentum; they were arguably 
the single main source of Chinas growth. But their rapid emergence, Deng said, 
was not something I had thought about. Nor had the other comrades. This 
surprised us. The reformers had not foreseen the key to their own reforms. The 
other excommunist economies had similar experiences. As in China, new  rms were drivers of reform. They strengthened the budding market economy by creat
ing jobs, supplying consumer goods, mobilizing savings and ending the state  rms 
monopoly. As in China, also, the reformers usually did not anticipate the force of 
entry. 
Of the two routes to a private sectorprivatizing the existing  rms and 
creating new onesthe policy debates focused almost exclusively on the former. 
Little attention was given to what reform policies would foster entry. Dusan Triska, 
for example, the architect of Czechoslovakias privatization program, said privatization is not just one of the many items on the economic program. It is the 
transformation itself  (Nellis, 2001, p. 32). It is not surprising that those who had 
spent their lives under central planning did not foresee the impact of entrepreneurship, but few analysts from the West predicted it either. 
The reason for underestimating entrepreneurship, perhaps, was a sense that 
setting up a business, risky anywhere, is especially risky in an economy undergoing 
y John McMillan is Professor of Economics, Graduate School of Business, Stanford Univer
sity, Stanford, California. Christopher Woodruff is Assistant Professor of Economics, Grad
uate School of International Relations and Pacic Studies, University of California at San 
Diego, La Jolla, California.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>The Central Role of Entrepreneurs in Transition Economies 169 
References 
Baker, George, Robert Gibbons and Kevin J. 
Murphy. 1994. Subjective Performance Mea
sures in Optimal Incentive Contracts. Quarterly 
Journal of Economics . 109:4, pp. 1125156. 
Belka, Marek et al. 1995. Enterprise Adjust
ment in Poland: Evidence from a Survey of 200 
Private, Privatized, and StateOwned Firms. 
Centre for Economic Performance Discussion Paper No. 233, April. 
Berkowitz, Daniel and David DeJong. 2001. 
Entrepreneurship and PostSocialist Growth. 
William Davidson Institute Working Paper No. 
406. 
Berkowitz, Daniel and Jonathan Holland. 
2001. Does Privatizatio n Enhance or Deter Small Enterprise Formation? 
Economics Letters . 
74:1, pp. 53 60. 
Bilsen, Valentijn and Jozef Konings. 1998. 
Job Creation, Job Destruction and Growth of 
Newly Established, Privatized and StateOwned 
Enterprises in Transition Economies: Survey Evidence from Bulgaria, Hungary and Roma
nia. 
Journal of Comparative Economics. 26:3, pp. 
429  45. 
Brown, David and John Earle. 2001. Privatiza
tion, Competition, and Reform Strategies: Theory and Evidence from Russian Enterprise Panel 
Data. SITE Working Paper No. 159, Stockholm 
School of Economics. 
Carlin, Wendy et al. 2001. Competition and 
Enterprise Performance in Transition Econo
mies: Evidence from a CrossCountry Survey. 
CEPR Discussion Paper No. 2840. 
Che, Jiahua and Yingyi Qian. 1998. Institu
tional Environment, Community Government, 
and Corporate Governance: Understanding 
Chinas Township Village Enterprises. Journal 
of Law, Economics, and Organization. 14:1, pp.1 
23. 
de Soto, Hernando. 1989. The Other Path . New 
York: Harper and Row. 
Djankov, Simeon and Peter Murrell. 2002. 
Enterprise Restructuring in Transition: A 
Quantitative Survey. Journal of Economic Litera
ture. 40:3, pp. 73992. 
Djankov, Simeon and Tatiana Nenova. 2001. 
Constraints to Entrepreneurship in Kazakhstan.  World Bank, March. 
Djankov, Simeon et al. 2002. The Regulation 
of Entry. Quarterly Journal of Economics. 117:1, 
pp. 137. 
Earle, John and Zuzana Sakova. 1999. Entre
preneurship from Scratch: Lessons on the Entry 
Decision into SelfEmployment from Transition 
Economies. IZA Discussion Paper No. 79. 
Earle, John and Zuzana Sakova. 2000. Business Startups or Disguised Unemployment? Evidence on the Character of SelfEmployment 
from Transition Countries. 
Labour Economics. 
7:5, pp. 575 601. 
Fafchamps, Marcel. 2001. Networks, Com
munities and Markets in SubSaharan Africa: Implications for Firm Growth and Investment. 
Journal of African Economies . 10:0, pp. 109  42. 
Federal Reserve Board of Governors. 1994. 
National Survey of Small Business Finance . Wash
ington, D.C.: Board of Governor of the Federal Reserve and U.S. Small Business Administratio n. 
Frye, Timothy and Andrei Shleifer. 1997. The 
Invisible Hand and the Grabbing Hand. Ameri
can Economic Review. Papers and Proceedings, 
87:2, pp. 35458. 
Glaeser, Edward, Simon Johnson and Andrei 
Shleifer. 2001. Coase versus the Coaseans. 
Quarterly Journal of Economics. 114:3, pp. 853900. 
Haltiwanger, John and Milan Vodopivec. 
2000. Gross Worker and Job Flows in a Transi
tion Economy: An Analysis of Estonia. Mimeo, 
University of Maryland, November. 
Hemlin, Maud, Bhargavi Ramamur thy and 
Per Ronns. 1998. The Anatomy and Dynamics 
of Small Scale Private Manufactur ing in Vietnam. Mimeo, Stockholm School of Economics. 
Hendley, Kathryn, Peter Murrell and Randi 
Ryterman. 1999. Law, Relationships, and Pri
vate Enforcement: Transactional Strategies of Russian Enterprises. Mimeo, University of Wisconsin, January. 
Johnson, Simon and Andrei Shleifer. 2001. 
Privatization and Corporate Governance. 
Mimeo, MIT. 
Johnson, Simon, John McMillan and Christo
pher Woodruff. 2000. Entrepreneurs and the 
Ordering of Institutio nal Reform: Poland, Slova
kia, Romania, Russia and Ukraine Compared. 
Economics of Transition. 8:1, pp. 136. 
Johnson, Simon, John McMillan and Christo
pher Woodruff. 2002a. Courts and Relational 
Contracts. Journal of Law, Economics, and Orga
nization. 18:1, pp. 22177. 
Johnson, Simon, John McMillan and Christo
pher Woodruff. 2002b. Property Rights and Fi
nance. American Economic Review . Forthcoming. 
Koford, Kenneth and Jeffrey B. Miller. 1998. 
Contractual Enforcement in an Economy in 
Transition. Mimeo, Department of Economics, 
University of Delaware. 
Konings, Jozef, Hartmut Lehmann and Mark 
E. Schaffer. 1996. Job Creation and Job De
struction in a Transition Economy: Ownership, Firm Size and Gross Job Flows in Polish Manufacturing. Labour Economics . 3:2, pp. 299317.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>158 Journal of Economic Perspectives 
being spun off from stateowned  rms). The level of selfemployment in Poland 
increased from 6 percent of the labor force in 1988 to 12 percent in 1993 
(according to Earle and Sakova, 1999, using labor market surveys).4 Although most 
of the  rmlevel studies in transition countries focus on manufacturing, entry may have been even more important in the service sector, given the underdevelopment 
of the service sector in the centrally planned economies. In Poland, the service 
sector grew from 40 percent of nonagricultural GDP in 1989 to 66 percent of GDP 
in 1997. 
Russia, by contrast, saw less rapid entry. A 1995 study found that just 6 percent 
of manufacturing employment was in de novo  rms (Richter and Shaffer, 1996). Selfemployment in Russia in the early years of the transition increased only from 
2 percent of the labor force in 1988 to 3 percent in 1993 (Earle and Sakova, 1999). 
Con rmation of the slowness of entry comes from data collected by Djankov and 
Nenova (2001) on employment in manufacturing  rms with fewer than 50 employ
ees in 1997. Since small  rms were uncommon in the planned economy, small size is a rough proxy for de novo startups. They  nd that small  rms represented 
24 percent of manufacturing employment in Poland, but only 10 percent in Russia, 
and that the employment share of small  rms in the Russian service sector more 
than doubled from 13 percent in 1989 to 30 percent in 1997.
5 All data on 
increasing shares in Russia need to be interpreted in the context of a shrinking 
economy. For example, Russia also saw services increase from 40 percent of the 
nonagricultural economy in 1989 to 62 percent in 1997. The share of services increased in spite of the fact that output of services actually declined by 1 percent 
per year during the 1990s; manufacturing declined much more rapidly. 
The speed of entry in China, Poland and Russia was consistent with the time 
path of pro ts shown in Figure 1. Robust entry in China and Poland brought plummeting pro ts. In Russia, entry was slower, and pro ts remained high. 
In Vietnam, also, the available data indicate that entry of private  rms was 
robust (though we are unaware of any pro t data there). Vietnam is an intriguing example, for it is an extreme case in its lack of formal marketsupporting institu
tions. Yet Vietnams private sector boomed. The number of registered private  rms 
grew by 40 percent per year between 1993 and 1997. Private sector employment 
grew from 3.8 million to 10.2 million between 1988 and 1992, while employment in 
state  rms fell from 4.1 million to 3.0 million and in cooperatives fell from 
20.7 million to 18.6 million. In the following three years, from 1992 to 1995, private 
4 The labor survey data indicate that the majority of the selfemployed work for their own account. These 
workers may represent not robust entry, but desperation in the face of unemployment (Earle and 
Sakova, 2000). Nevertheless, in 1993, over 4 percent of Polands workforce were selfemployed people 
who also hired others, a level much higher than in the other transition countries examined by Earle and 
Sakova. 
5Djankov and Nenova (2001) data also show that employment in small  rms grew rapidly in Poland 
during the 1990s, from an average of 8 percent in 1990 1992 to 23 percent in 1996 1998. (Comparable data for Russia are not available.) For Russia, small manufacturing  rms are de ned as those with fewer than 100 employees, rather than 50, as in Poland, hence the difference between Poland and Russia is 
understated. The service sector data for Russia and Poland are from the World Development Indicators 
database.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>The Central Role of Entrepreneurs in Transition Economies 161 
organized. Trade associations helped  rms to work productively with each other, by 
spreading information about who had breached contracts and coordinating the 
sanctioning of them. This meant that reneging brought more severe consequences 
than merely losing the business of the offended party and thus increased the 
likelihood of cooperation (McMillan and Woodruff, 2000; Recanatini and Ryter
man, 2000). 
The selfhelp mechanisms evolved over time to support more complex trans
actions. Early in the transition,  rms sold mostly to customers located in the same 
city or limited sales to customers about whom they had prior information from 
family members, friends or other  rms with whom they did business. They were likely to inspect a customers factory or store before selling to it. These are ways to 
reduce the risk of dealing with new trading partners, though they involve costs of 
exclusion or of time spent investigating trading partners. Relationships with  rms 
located in distant cities are harder to manage than local sales, but limiting the circle 
of trading partners means passing up some opportunities for growth. Sales to 
customers located in other cities, and to customers about whom the manufacturer 
had no prior information, became more common as the transition progressed. 
Table 1 illustrates these changes using data from surveys in three transition 
countries, Vietnam, Poland and Russia. The surveys asked  rms about the charac
teristics of their oldest and newest customer relationships. The table splits relation
ships into those that began earlier and later in the transition. Relationships labeled 
old are those begun in the  rst six years of reform, before 1993 in Vietnam and 
before 1995 in Poland and Russia, while those labeled new were formed between 
1994 and 1997 in Vietnam and between mid1995 and 1997 in Poland and Russia. 
All of the variables shown on Table 1 are measured at the start of the relationship 
and, as such, are indicators of the formation of new relationships rather than the 
development of the speci c bilateral relationships. 
These data show statistically signi cant increases in transactions with custom
ers from other cities, with customers about whom nothing was known at the start of 
the relationship, and in relationships that were initiated without the seller having 
visited the buyers factory or store. In Poland, for example, 35 percent of the 
customer relationships started by surveyed  rms between 1989 and mid1995 
involved customers from a different city, compared with 45 percent of relationships 
started in 1995 or after. About 39 percent of the newer customers in Poland were anonymous when the trading relationship began, compared with 27 percent of the 
older customers. Trading started in 38 percent of the new Polish relationships 
without the seller visiting the buyers facility, compared with 29 percent of the older relationships. 
The patterns in the other countries are similar, both for Vietnam and Russia, 
as shown in the table, and for Slovakia, Romania and Ukraine, which are not shown. 
Further evidence on the increase over time in the sophistication of dealings comes 
from Bulgaria, where quality incentives developed. Suppliers became increasingly 
willing to guarantee quality and to replace substandard goods based on their 
trading relationships (Koford and Miller, 1998). 
These data suggest that the problems of governing more complex relationships</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>156 Journal of Economic Perspectives 
Pro ts and Entry 
Four transition countries, Poland, Russia, China and Vietnam, span the range 
of entrepreneurship patterns. Poland was among the most successful in fostering 
new private  rms. Russia was among the least successful, though entry occurred 
even there. China took a distinctive path with entry of competitive enterprises run by local governments. Vietnam offers an example of robust growth of private  rms 
even with an almost total absence of formal institutions to facilitate business. 
A telling measure of the success of a transition economys reforms is the time 
path of entrants pro ts. Figure 1 shows the path of pro ts in the  ve years following the start of transition in China (19791984) and in Poland and Russia 
(19901995). In China, at the start of the reform era in 1979, the average pro ts of nonstate  rms were 28 percent of invested capital. This is very high in compar
ison to earnings in a mature market economy: small businesses in the United States 
typically earn returns between 9 percent and 15 percent of assets.
2 As Chinas 
transition proceeded, the new  rms pro ts declined steadily through the  rst 
decade of reform, falling to 15 percent of invested capital in 1984 and leveling out 
at 6 percent in 1991 (Naughton, 1995, p. 150). 
In Poland, pro t rates of manufacturing  rms in their  rst year of operation 
fell from an average of 25 percent of invested capital for  rms formed in 1990 to 
6 percent for  rms formed in 1995. In Russia, also, pro ts earned by entrants were 
high at the start of the reforms:  rms established in 1990 earned an average pro t 
of 17 percent on invested capital in their  rst year of operation. By contrast with 
China and Poland, however, pro ts did not decline over time:  rstyear pro ts for 
 rms established in 1995, at 16 percent, were almost as high as those for the  rms established in 1990 ( Johnson, McMillan and Woodruff, 2002b).
3 
The high pro ts earned in all three countries early in the transition are easily 
explained. The starting point was a heavily distorted economy with un lled market 
niches. Firms that were able to overcome the impediments to doing business and 
produce and sell goods and services were very pro table. In Poland and China, as 
marketsupporting institutions developed, the impediments declined and so rents 
2 The U.S. data are from the National Survey of Small Business Finances (Federal Reserve Board of 
Governors, 1994). The NSSBF sampled 273 manufacturing  rms with between 10 and 250 employees. 
The return on invested capital averages 15 percent. However, in the surveys of  rms in the  ve eastern 
European countries, pro ts as a percentage of assets were obtained in categories, with the lowest 
category being negative and the highest category being 41 percent or greater. When these categories 
are used with the U.S. data, the average return on invested capital is 9 percent rather than 15 percent. 
It is likely, then, that the data from Poland and Russia discussed in this section understate somewhat the 
return to capital. 
3A word of caution about comparing the pro t data from China on the one hand and Russia and Poland 
on the other: The Polish and Russian data are from surveys of about 300 manufactur ers in each country 
in 1997 ( Johnson, McMillan and Woodruff, 2002b). Firms were asked about pro ts in their  rst year of operation. Figure 1 shows the average pro t rate of  rms beginning operation in each year. As such, they 
are subject to possible recall and selection bias. The China data were gathered contemporaneously from 
 rms operating at the time.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>John McMillan and Christopher Woodruff 163 
geographically nearby  rms. Anonymous trades need a greater extent of formal 
contractual assurance. 
Third, as products become more complex, there is an increased need to order 
them, and to commit to buy them, in advance of production. Without the courts, 
suppliers may be unwilling to switch to producing complex goods and services. 
Fourth, although  rms can for a while grow incrementally by investing their 
retained earnings, they reach a point where, to take advantage of economies of scale, they must make big discrete jumps in their investments. Having a long
delayed return, such investments are unlikely to be made on the basis of ongoing relationships. Sunk costs tempt someone to renege: a purchaser after the costs are 
sunk may renegotiate the buying price, or the government after the costs are sunk 
may impose a speci c tax. Largescale investments require legal protection. 
Finally, as pro ts decline through the process of economic transition, while 
investments often become larger and longer term,  rms can rely less on retained 
earnings to grow and increasingly need access to external  nance. 
A role for the government, even early in the transition, is to set a stable 
platform for entrepreneurs selfhelp. Macroeconomic instability, common at the beginning of a reform program, can undermine informal cooperation. Consider a 
trading relationship in which the seller allows the buyer to pay with a 30day delay. 
In stable times, the ability to delay payment has a predictable value to the buyer and 
cost to the seller. The value of continuing the relationship is also predictable. The 
level of credit offered can be set in such a way that repayment is in the sellers interest. But now suppose that, after the goods are delivered by the seller, there is 
some unforeseen shock that increases the value to the buyer of not making the 
required payment and affects only the trading partners current payoffs, not the 
stream of future gains from the relationship (such as a sharp decrease in bank 
credit or a rapid decline in the buyers demand). If the shock makes the gains from 
reneging large enough, the buyer will not pay.
8 
Risks were inherent in any trading relationship in all of the transition coun
tries, but the policies of some governments magni ed them. Unstable macroeco
nomic conditions made it harder to predict the behavior of trading partners. High 
and variable rates of in ation and economic growth led to  uctuations in a trading partners gain from breaking the cooperative relationship. Macroeconomic stability 
was conducive to the development of informal trading relationships. On this score, 
countries like Slovakia, where in ation peaked in 1991 at 35 percent, and Poland, where in ation peaked in 1990 at 75 percent, fared well. Russia and Ukraine, where 
price stability was longer in coming, fared worse. Of course, the lack of entry in 
Russia and Ukraine may have contributed to macroeconomic instability as well as the other way around. We know of no data that would allow us to separate the 
8 The situation we have in mind is similar to the Rotemberg and Saloners (1986) model of price wars 
during economic booms. In their model, collusion is most likely to break down in a boom when the 
demand for the product is high, because that is when an individual sellers gain from undercutting the 
groupmaximizing price is highest. Hence, collusion is harder to sustain in industries with more variable 
demand.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>John McMillan and Christopher Woodruff 167 
destruction of existing jobs by shrinking  rms. For stateowned  rms, in the  rst 
half of the 1990s, job creation was small and job destruction among these enter
prises was large. In the private sector, there was a lot of job creation. Yet, surpris
ingly, the private sector also had higher rates of job destruction than the state enterprise sector. These data indicate more  ux in the private sector, with some 
 rms expanding rapidly and others contracting. The simultaneous high rates of job 
creation and job destruction were especially pronounced among the smallest  rms, 
those with fewer than 20 workers. This could be attributable to learning by the small 
 rms, which is especially important in the transition setting, where costs and 
demands are subject to far wider uncertainty than in a stable economy. 
New rms also provide competitive discipline for the preexisting  rms. State
owned and privatized rms in eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union are 
signicantly more likely to have undergone restructuring if they faced competition 
(Carlin et al., 2001; Djankov and Murrell, 2002). In China through the 1980s, while the township and village enterprises burgeoned, the state rms markup of price over 
marginal cost fell by 15 percent; the increased competitiveness of the output market 
was associated with an increased total factor productivity for the state  rms (Li, 1997). 
There is some evidence, also, that a transition economys overall performance 
is correlated with entry. Comparing economic growth rates of the different regions 
of Russia, Berkowitz and DeJong (2001)  nd that the fastergrowing regions have 
more entry of new  rms. 
Implications for Policy 
In the early 1990s, a common view among those advising the reforming 
countries was that the overriding objective was to get the government out of the 
economy. Once the prohibitions on market activity were abolished, the argument 
went, the private sector would quickly take over. Later, in light of the grim 
performance of Russia and the rest of the former Soviet Union, this simple view was 
supplanted by a recognition that reforming an economy is exceedingly hard. 
Success requires a complex package of microeconomic reform, macroeconomic stability and institution building. 
Our analysis speaks to both views. On the one hand, it says there is something 
in the leaveittothemarket view. Pro tdriven entrepreneurs can do a remarkable 
amount, even to the extent of creating temporary replacements for the key social 
institutions of property rights and contract. 
On the other hand, our analysis says getting the government out achieves its 
aim only in a narrow set of circumstances. The selfhelp substitutes for market
supporting institutions work well only for  rms that are small. Larger  rms, dealing 
with many suppliers and customers and trading at a distance, cannot rely solely on 
personalized relationships to undergird their transactions. Formal institutions are 
needed, therefore, both by privatized  rms and, after a while, by startup  rms if 
they are to grow to an ef cient scale. Moreover, government policy does matter even at the level of the small startups, for the business environment must be</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>154 Journal of Economic Perspectives 
deep reform. With prices volatile as a result of the reforms, it is unclear which lines 
of business are going to be the most pro table. State  rms, fearing competition, 
harass the new  rms, and corrupt bureaucrats extort bribes. Without the normal 
marketsupporting institutions, the new  rms usually cannot rely on the courts to enforce their contracts; bank loans are unobtainable for most; and there is little 
legal or regulatory provision for shareholding. 
These handicaps notwithstanding, large parts of the new market economy 
arose spontaneously, through the initiatives of entrepreneurs. They succeeded by selfhelp: they built for themselves substitutes for the missing institutions. Reputa
tional incentives substituted for court enforcement of contracts. Trade credit (loans from  rm to  rm along the supply chain) substituted for bank credit. Reinvestment 
of pro ts substituted for outside equity. 
In this paper, we summarize entrepreneurial patterns in the transition econ
omies, particularly Russia, China, Poland and Vietnam.1 Markets developed spon
taneously in every transition country, but they were built at varying speeds. Some governments impeded the entrepreneurs selfhelp by creating conditions that 
made it hard for informal contracting to work; others created an environment that was conducive to selfhelp. The spontaneous emergence of markets, furthermore, 
has its limits. As  rms activities became more complex, they came to need formal 
institutions. Some governments fostered entrepreneurship by building marketsupporting infrastructure; others did not (Frye and Shleifer, 1997). We will argue 
that the success or failure of a transition economy can be traced in large part to the 
performance of its entrepreneurs. 
The Environment for Entrepreneurship 
All the transition economies, from the former Soviet Union and central and 
eastern Europe to China and Vietnam, were similar in one important respect: their 
planned economies had been dominated by large  rms, producing few consumer 
goods. Small and mediumsized  rms were almost nonexistent, although they are a 
large part of every market economy. Trade and services were also a much smaller 
part of the transition economies than is typical for a market economy. As reform led 
to greater  exibility in prices, wages and production decisions, the imbalances inherited from the planned economy created enormous pro t opportunities for 
entrepreneurs. Entrepreneurs responded by starting enterprises at a rapid 
though varyingrate in each of the transition countries. 
Some governments actively made it hard for entrepreneurs to operate. Expro
priation of pro ts through of cial corruption was the most conspicuous of such 
actions. Managers of startup manufacturing  rms were asked in a survey whether 
extralegal payments were needed in order to receive government services or a 
1 Our focus will be on the states role in encouraging startup  rms, not on efforts to create a market 
sector by revamping the old state  rms; on that issue, see Djankov and Murrell (2002), Megginson and 
Netter (2001) and Nellis (2001).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>John McMillan and Christopher Woodruff 155 
business license ( Johnson, McMillan and Woodruff, 2002b). More than 90 percent 
of Russian managers said they were, compared with about 20 percent of Polish 
managers. Corruption deters investment. Those  rms in the sample that were the 
most concerned about corruption invested nearly 40 percent less than those least 
concerned. The ma a is a further deterrent to entrepreneurship. Asked whether 
payments to private agencies were necessary for protection of their activities, 
more than 90 percent of Russian managers and 8 percent of Polish managers said 
they were. 
Managers were asked in the same survey whether they would invest $100 today 
if they expected to receive $200 in two years (an implied annual rate of return of 40 percent). The responses to this question give an indication of both the oppor
tunity cost of money and the security of property. A striking 99 percent of the 
Russian managers said they would not, compared with 22 percent of the Polish 
managers. 
Illegitimate takings aside, of cial policies often make it expensive to set up 
 rms. Entrepreneurs must apply for business licenses to establish that their com
panys name is unique and provide proof of their startup capital; then they must  le 
with the tax and labor authorities. In Russia, setting up a new business takes an entrepreneur over two months and costs 38 percent of per capita GDP in of cial 
fees (Djankov et al., 2002). In Poland, it takes nearly a month and costs 28 percent 
of per capita GDP. In Vietnam, it takes nearly six months and costs a striking 
150 percent of per capita GDP. 
The governments decisions on privatizing state  rms may also have affected 
the environment for new  rms. Mass privatization could add to the general uncer
tainty, thus deterring entry. Across Russias regions, more new  rms have been 
formed where there was less privatization of small state enterprises, though more 
entry has occurred where there was more privatization of largescale state enter
prises (Berkowitz and Holland, 2001). The continued presence of state enterprises 
also raised barriers to entry. They absorbed scarce capital and received regulatory 
favors (as did the privatized  rms). Anecdotes abound of state  rms sti ing new 
entrants to prevent them from becoming competitors. 
Not only did governments impede entrepreneurship, formal institutions to 
underpin entrepreneurial activity developed only slowly. In Vietnam in the mid
1990s, for example, after a decade of reform, the market institutions were still 
inadequate. Banks almost exclusively served stateowned  rms. There were no 
creditreporting bureaus. Courts able to enforce contracts between private  rms 
were just being created. Among manufacturers we surveyed between 1995 and 
1997, less than 10 percent said that courts or the government could enforce a 
contract with a buyer or seller, and just 10 percent said that they had received credit 
from banks when they started their business (McMillan and Woodruff, 1999b). In 
another survey carried out in 1997, 74 percent of private  rms reported having no 
debts to banks, and such debts represented only 20 percent of the capital among 
the 24 percent of the  rms that did have them (Ronns, 1998).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>The Central Role of Entrepreneurs in Transition Economies 157 
Figure 1 
Time Path of Pro ts 
Notes: The horizontal axis shows the number of years into reform. For China, year 1 means 1979 and 
year 6 means 1984. For Poland and Russia, year 1 means 1990 and year 6 means 1995. 
Sources: China: Naughton (1996, p. 150). Poland and Russia: Johnson, McMillan and Woodruff 
(2002b). 
fell. Russias stalled transition shows up in the absence of any decline in pro t 
levels. 
Data on the rate of entry of new  rms are consistent with the pro t paths 
shown in Figure 1. Entry occurred rapidly in China. Most of the new entrants there 
were not private  rms, but rural enterprises run by local governments, called 
township and village enterprises. The share of Chinas industrial output accounted for by rural enterprises increased from 9 percent in 1978 to 30 percent in 1991 
(Naughton, 1995, p. 164). Since none of the increase in output of rural  rms in 
China came from privatized state  rms, all of it is attributable to newly formed 
 rms. The entry of these new enterprises was driven by the extraordinarily high 
rates of pro t available early in the reforms. The competition engendered by rapid 
entry was the primary cause of the fall in pro ts. 
Entry in Poland was also rapid. Industrial employment in Polands private 
sector  rms increased from 15 percent in 1991 to 37 percent in 1994, according to 
Konings, Lehmann and Schaffer (1996), using data collected by the Polish Central 
Statistical Of ce. The 21percentagepoint increase was apparently largely the result 
of new entrants, since privatized  rms represented only 6 percent of industrial 
employment in 1994. At least onesixth of industrial employment in Poland in 1994, 
then, was in de novo  rms (de novo meaning started from scratch rather than</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>160 Journal of Economic Perspectives 
well. When it is hard to locate alternative trading partners, because  rms are scarce 
or market information is inadequate or transport costs are high,  rms make efforts 
to maintain their existing relationships. They recognize that they are to some 
extent locked in with their trading partners, which provides an incentive to behave 
cooperatively (Kranton, 1996; Ramey and Watson, 2001). The evidence we present 
in this section suggests that selfenforcing contracts are all that is needed to support 
a lot of entrepreneurship, especially at the start of the reforms. 
Evidence from Vietnam is especially pertinent here, since formal institutions 
were almost nonexistent for some years after its transition began. Consider access 
to capital. Even in developed market economies, a major source of capital for small
and mediumsized  rms is trade credit from suppliers. The lack of formal  nancial markets meant that credit from suppliers was even more important to private sector 
 rms in transition countries. In 53 percent of the relationships between the 
manufactures we surveyed and their customers, some portion of the bill was paid on credit. That suppliers were willing to offer credit in the absence of formal enforce
ment of contracts is noteworthy. What gave the suppliers con dence that they 
would be paid? The willingness to sell goods on credit depended upon repeated 
interactions, according to the managers we surveyed (McMillan and Woodruff, 
1999a). Trading relationships most often began with cash transactions, as the 
partners tested each other. Firms got contractual assurance by dealing with  rms 
they knew through having dealt with them before. 
Informally enforced trade rests on the shadow of the future. A  rm lives up to 
its agreements because it wants to go on doing business with this trading partner. 
For the future to weigh heavily enough to induce cooperative behavior, the 
discounted value of the future pro t stream must outweigh whatever immediate pro ts could be squeezed from the deal. Some of the conditions in the transition 
economies actually worked against cooperation. The scarcity of credit meant the 
opportunity cost of capital was high. With high discount rates,  rms have an 
incentive to take current pro ts rather than wait for future pro ts. Moreover, as we 
saw, pro ts tended to decline over time. To the extent that this was predictable, the 
gains from forwardlooking behavior were lowered. That  rms were nevertheless 
able to operate mutually bene cial relationships is striking. 
Other circumstances of the transition aided informal contracting. Cooperation 
is easier to sustain when severing the relationship results in higher costs. Early in 
the transition, trading partners were most often located in the same city or even the 
same neighborhood. There were usually few  rms nearby producing any given 
product. When a supplier severed a relationship with a customer, the customer had 
to incur a high cost of searching for another trading partner. As a result, trading 
partners tended to be locked in with each other, inducing them to try to sustain 
their existing relationships (Kranton, 1996; Ramey and Watson, 2001). 
Cooperation is more easily sustained, also, if punishment for malfeasance 
comes not only from the trading partner who has been cheated but also from other 
 rms in the community. We found that gossip was important in Vietnams manu
facturing community. Firms gathered information about potential or existing trading partners from other  rms. Sometimes this information gathering was</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Old 
28.8% 31.8% 
57.6% n.a. n.a. 
36.6% 30.8% 
226 344 66 Table 1 
Development of Relationships with Trading Partners 
Vietnam 
Relationships Poland 
Relationships Russia 
Relationships 
New Old New Old New 
Located in a different city 38.9% 35.0% 45.0% 14.5% 
(2.27) (2.40) (3.44) 
Previously unknown 65.5% 27.0% 38.9% 
(1.74) (2.94) 
Did not visit before  rst 50.5% 28.8% 37.5% 35.3% 
transaction (3.00) (2.16) (0.70) 
Number of  rms 191 281 342 162 Journal of Economic Perspectives 
Notes: Old relationships are those initiated prior to 1993 in Vietnam and prior to 1995 in Poland and 
Russia. In parentheses: tvalues for differences between old and new relationships. The data on 
previously unknown for Vietnam and Poland are not directly comparable because of differences in the 
survey instrument. Entries marked n.a. are not available in the survey used in the given country. 
Sources: Johnson, McMillan and Woodruff (2000); McMillan and Woodruff (1999b). 
can be overcome not only where courts work relatively well, as in Poland, but even 
where courts do not function at all, as in Vietnam. Receiving no help from the state, 
entrepreneurs made do for themselves, by relying on the incentives that arise in 
ongoing relationships. Repeated games substituted for the courts; trade credit and 
pro t reinvestment substituted for  nancial markets. The mechanism of selfhelp 
supported increasingly sophisticated transactionsat least in the early years of 
transition. 
State Support for Entrepreneurship 
Selfhelp in creating market institutions is not a permanent solution for 
entrepreneurs. It faces a number of natural limits. 
First, the development of the market as the transition proceeds lowers the costs 
of searching out new trading partners, which weakens a  rms threat to cut off 
dealings if a trading partner reneges on a deal. The cost of breaking a relationship 
falls. Firms then become less willing to cooperate with each other, and the need for 
workable laws of contract and courts able to enforce them becomes more pressing. 
Second, repeated games entail personalized inter rm relationships. When 
 rms are small, they need only deal with customers and suppliers with whom they 
have a particular connection: those located nearby, or managed by a friend or 
relative, or coming via personal recommendations. Firms were able to some extent to overcome these limitations, as noted above: even in Vietnam, they were able to 
trade at a distance. Such informal mechanisms are limited, however. To grow 
beyond a certain size,  rms need to manage armslength anonymous dealings: for example, to begin trading with  rms in distant cities rather than just with</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>166 Journal of Economic Perspectives 
Welfare Effects of Entrepreneurship 
The creation of jobs has been arguably the most important welfare bene t of 
the new entrants. Given the distortions and inef ciencies in the communist 
planned economy, the old  rms had to shed jobs during the transition, and new 
entrants were needed to take up the slack. New  rms have usually been the 
fastestgrowing segment in transition economies. In Poland and in Russia, de novo 
manufacturing  rms grew faster, invested at a higher rate and generated faster 
employment growth than did privatized  rms (Belka et al., 1995; Richter and Schaffer, 1996; Johnson, McMillan and Woodruff, 2000). In Vietnam, the private 
sector created (in net terms) some 10 million jobs in the seven years from the start 
of reforms, while the stateowned and collective  rms shed workers. 
This pattern is repeated in most of the transition economies for which data 
exist. In Estonia, small privately owned  rmsmostly startups created almost all 
of the new jobs between 1989 and 1994 (Haltiwanger and Vodopivec, 2000). In 
Romania, 86 percent of de novo manufacturing  rms created jobs between 1994 and 1996, while only 13 percent of privatized  rms did so. In Slovakia, 79 percent 
of de novo  rms grew, against 52 percent of privatized  rms ( Johnson, McMillan 
and Woodruff, 2000). De novo  rms in Bulgaria, Hungary and Romania between 1990 and 1996 grew more quickly than did privatized or stateowned  rms (Bilsen 
and Konings, 1998). Though de novo  rms represented less than 3 percent of 
employment in the samples in Bulgaria and Romania, they created more than half of the new jobs. In a sample of  rms from 25 transition countries, Carlin et al. 
(2001)  nd that sales and employment grow faster in de novo  rms than in 
privatized or state  rms; they also  nd that productivity gains are smaller, probably re ecting that new  rms start at a higher level of ef ciency than the state  rms and thus have less room for productivity growth. 
The key difference does not seem to be between stateowned and private  rms, 
but rather that de novo  rms outgrew all other  rms. Many studies  nd little 
difference between the performance of stateowned  rms and privatized  rms. The 
 nding that de novo  rms perform better than privatized and stateowned  rms is not quite universal, however. The Johnson, McMillan and Woodruff (2000) data 
show essentially no difference in the growth rates of startups and privatized  rms in 
Russia and Ukraine. Lizal and Svejnar (2001)  nd that the rates of investment of private  rms in the Czech Republic were somewhat lower on average than those of 
stateowned  rms in the 19921998 time period and that small  rms in the Czech 
Republic were credit constrained while large  rms were not (which may explain in part their  rst  nding). Taken as a whole, then, the evidence indicates that de novo 
 rms were more dynamic than privatized state  rms, except perhaps where the 
latter had favored access to capital. 
Entrepreneurial  rms provide other bene ts. Small new  rms are dynamic. 
They learn and change rapidly, and thus they provide a large number of indepen
dent experiments on how to do business. One measure of this dynamism is their job 
churning. In a study of Estonia, Haltiwanger and Vodopivec (2000) separate the net change in employment into the creation of new jobs by expanding  rms and the</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>170 Journal of Economic Perspectives 
Kranton, Rachel E. 1996. Reciprocal Ex
change: A SelfSustaining System. American Eco
nomic Review. 86:4, pp. 83051. 
Le, Wei. 1997. The Impact of Economic Re
form on the Performance of Chinese State En
terprises, 19801989. Journal of Political Econ
omy. 105:5, pp. 1080106. 
Li, Hongbin and Scott Rozelle. 2000. Saving 
or Stripping Rural Industry: An Analysis of Pri
vatizatio n and Ef ciency in China. Agricultural 
Economics. 23:3, pp. 24152. 
Lizal, Lubomir and Jan Svejnar. 2001. Invest
ment, Credit Rationing, and the Soft Budget 
Constraint: Evidence from the Czech Republic. 
Review of Economics and Statistics . 83:1, pp. 9299. 
McKenzie, John. 2000. Creating a Market in 
Management Training for Vietnams Private 
Firms. International Labour Organization 
Working Paper. 
McMillan, John. 2002. Reinventing the Bazaar: A 
Natural History of Markets . New York: Norton. 
McMillan, John and Christopher Woodruff. 
1999a. Dispute Prevention Without Courts in 
Vietnam. Journal of Law, Economics, and Organi
zation. 15:3, pp. 63758. 
McMillan, John and Christopher Woodruff. 
1999b. Inter rm Relationships and Informal 
Credit in Vietnam. Quarterly Journal of Economics . 
114:4, pp. 1285320. 
McMillan, John and Christopher Woodruff. 
2000. Private Order under Dysfunctional Public 
Order. Michigan Law Review. 98:8, pp. 2421 
458. 
Megginson, William L. and Jeffry M. Netter. 
2001. From State to Market: A Survey of Empir
ical Studies on Privatization. Journal of Economic 
Literature. 39:2, pp. 321 89. 
Naughton, Barry. 1995. Growing Out of the Plan . 
New York: Cambridge University Press. 
Nellis, John. 2001. The World Bank, Priva
tization, and Enterprise Reform in Transition Economies: A Retrospective Analysis. Mimeo, 
Operations Evaluation Department, World 
Bank. 
Ramey, Garey and Joel Watson. 2001. Bilat
eral Trade and Opportunism in a Matching Market. Contributions to Theoretical Economics. 1:1, 
http//www.bepress.com/bejte/contributions/ 
vol1/iss1/art3/ 
 . 
Recanatini, Francesca and Randi Ryterman. 
2000. Disorganization or SelfOrganization? 
Mimeo, World Bank. 
Richter, Andrea and Mark Schaffer. 1996. The 
Performance of De Novo Private Firms in Russian 
Manufacturing, in Enterprise Restructuring and Eco
nomic Policy in Russia . Commander, Fan and Schaf
fer, eds. Washington, D.C.: World Bank, pp. 253 
74. 
Ronns, Per. 1998. The Transformation of 
the Private Manufacturing Sector in Vietnam in the 1990s. Stockholm School of Economics Working Paper No. 241. 
Rotemberg, Julio and Garth Saloner. 1986. A 
SupergameTheoretic Model of Price Wars dur
ing Booms. American Economic Review . 76:3, pp. 
390 407. 
Smith, Adam. 1976 [1776]. An Enquiry into the 
Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations . Chi
cago: University of Chicago Press. 
Whiting, Susan H. 1996. Contract Incentives 
and Market Discipline in Chinas Rural Indus
trial Sector, in Reforming Asian Socialism . J. Mc
Millan and B. Naughton, eds. Ann Arbor: Uni
versity of Michigan Press, pp. 63110. 
Wolff, Peter. 1999. Vietnam: The Incomplete 
Transformation . London: Frank Cass Press. 
Woodruff, Christopher. 1998. Contract En
forcement and Trade Liberalization in Mexicos Footwear Industry. 
World Development. 26:6, pp. 
97991. 
Zhou, Kate Xiao. 1996. How the Farmers 
Changed China . Boulder: Westview Press.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>The Central Role of Entrepreneurs in Transition Economies 165 
the top managers family. This is a somewhat higher level of outside ownership than 
other countries for which such data are available: Vietnam, at 19 percent, Slovakia, 
19 percent, and Romania, 14 percent ( Johnson, McMillan and Woodruff, 2000; 
McMillan and Woodruff, 1999b). The lesson, once again, is that informal mecha
nisms work only up to a point. Investors are willing to entrust their money to 
managers they have some reason to believe in, perhaps because of ties of family or 
ethnicity or because the manager comes recommended by a trusted third party. 
Large  rms with diversi ed shareholding cannot develop by such informal mech
anisms, but some degree of outside ownership can. 
Evidence that selfhelp mechanisms in  nancial markets have limits comes 
from Earle and Sakovas (2000) study of entrepreneurship in Poland, Russia and 
four other eastern European countries. Employers, as compared to wage workers, 
are more likely to have received property during posttransition restitution and to have had higher earnings in 1988. Also, the parents of those who became employers 
were more likely to have owned a business prior to communism and more likely to 
have had a university degree than are the parents of wage workers. These  ndings 
suggest that access to capital was a binding constraint on entry, one not entirely 
overcome by informal credit. 
China did things differently with its new  rms. Entry occurred in the non
standard form of the township and village enterprises (Che and Qian, 1998; 
Whiting, 1996). These  rms were publicly owned, by communities of a few thou
sand people. They were managed by village government, and the pro ts were 
shared between villagers and local government by explicit rules. Around 60 percent 
of pro ts were reinvested, and the remainder was paid as bonuses to workers or 
used for local public goods such as education, roads and irrigation. Managerial 
discipline in the township and village enterprises came from the fact that these 
enterprises had no access to government subsidies to cover any losses and faced 
intensely competitive product markets. 
The township and village enterprises received some bene ts from having the 
village government as a partner. Access to state banks and to rationed inputs was 
eased. Public ownership helped remedy the lack of laws protecting against arbitrary 
expropriation by the state, as well as helping with contract enforcement. Moreover, 
Chinas local governments, arguably, did not sabotage their township and village 
enterprises by overtaxing them because they could see that if they did, the  rms 
would fail and their own revenue source would be lost. 
The township and village enterprise organizational form was a transitional 
device. After a decade and a half of growth, they began to be privatized. By the late 
1990s, more than half of them were partially or fully privately owned (Li and 
Rozelle, 2000). By the turn of the century, the township and village enterprises were 
well on their way to becoming conventional  rms. 
Entrepreneurs require more from the state, in the medium and long run, than 
the absence of interference. If  rms are to be able to grow to yield economies of 
scale, they need laws of contract so they can take on anonymous dealings and 
 nancial regulation so they can get bank loans and outside shareholding.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>John McMillan and Christopher Woodruff 159 
sector employment grew by more than 2.4 million, during which time state sector 
employment remained constant.6 Substantially all of this private sector growth 
came from new entry or expansion of household enterprises, mostly retail and 
repair shops or small manufacturing enterprises. Vietnam has had no formal 
program of privatization. Though there were some ad hoc spinoffs from stateowned  rms, these represent a minority of the private  rms. For example, only 
6 percent of  rms we surveyed in 1995 said that more than half of their equipment 
came from stateowned  rms (McMillan and Woodruff, 1999b). 
Entry was robust, then, in Poland, Vietnam and, in its own way, in China, while 
it was comparatively weak in Russia. Other transition countries saw entry to varying 
degrees. Ukraine and the rest of the former Soviet Union were like Russia, for 
example, whereas Slovakia was more like Poland. Pro ts were high early in the 
transition because the inef ciencies of the planned economy left unsatis ed de
mands and un lled market niches. Where reform was successful, it brought com
petitive markets, eroding pro ts. Where it was less successful, the entrants pro ts remained high. 
Entrepreneurs Strategies 
In the early years of economic transition, the absence of credit markets, courts 
and other market institutions created substantial impediments to entry. Potential 
entrants had to  nd money with which to purchase equipment and inputs. They 
had to identify reliable suppliers and customers when most  rms were new and 
little information was available. The unusually high pro t rates early in the transi
tion provided a strong incentive for entrepreneurs. But what substituted for the 
missing formal institutions? 
How did the entrepreneurs succeed in overcoming the lack of market
supporting institutions? Ongoing relationships among  rms substituted for the 
missing institutions. Firms relied on the logic of the incentives to cooperate that 
arise in playing a repeated game. Where courts and laws are unreliable for settling 
disputes,  rms trust their customers to pay their bills and their suppliers to deliver 
quality goods out of the prospect of future business. Interviews with Vietnamese 
managers, for example, indicate that they think quite consciously in terms of building relationships with speci c customers and suppliers (McMillan and 
Woodruff, 1999a).
7 
Early in the process of transition, repeated game incentives work especially 
6 Registration data are from McKenzie (2000); employment data from Wolff (1999, p. 63). Joint ventures 
between state  rms and foreign investors are included in the state sector. Beginning in 1993, statistics 
for collectives and private  rms were combined. The increase of 2.4 million jobs is for private  rms and 
collectives combined; however, it is reasonable to presume that collectives continued to decline (their 
output shrank from 2.7 percent of GDP in 1992 to 0.8 percent in 1998), meaning the employment 
increase is attributable to private  rms. 
7 On the interaction between formal and informal contracting mechanisms, see Baker, Gibbons and 
Murphy (1994).</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Importance of Institutions (PDF) (Courtesy of Meijun Qian, Jun Qian, and Franklin Allen. Used with permission.)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-946-planning-in-transition-economies-for-growth-and-equity-spring-2004/resources/feb_17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Law, Finance, and Econ omic Growth in China*
Franklin Allen Jun Qian Meijun Qian 
Finance Department Finance Depa rtment      Finance Department 
The Wharton School Carroll School of Management      Carroll School of Management 
University of Pennsylvania Boston College      Boston College 
Philadelphia, PA 19104 Chestnut Hill, MA 02467      Chestnut Hill, MA 02467 
Last Revised: February 3, 2004 
Abstract 
China is an important counterexample to the fi ndings in the law, institutions, finance, and 
growth literature: neither its legal nor financial system is well developed by existing standards, yet 
it has one of the fastest growing economies. We co mpare growth in the State Sector (state-owned 
firms), the Listed Sector (publicly listed firms), and the Private Sector (all other firms with various 
types of private and local government ownership). With poorer applicable legal and financial 
mechanisms, the Private Sector grows much faster than the State and Listed Sectors, and provides 
most of the economys growth. This suggests that  there exist effective alternative financing 
channels and governance mechanisms, such as those based on reputation and relationships, to 
support this growth. 
JEL Classifications: O5, K0, G2. 
Keywords: Law and finance, economic growth, privat e sector, corporate governance, reputation 
and relationships. 
* We appreciate detailed comments from an anonymous referee that significantly improved the paper, and assistance 
from Qiao Yu and Wuxiang Zhu in  conducting the firm survey. We received helpful comments from Dan 
Bergstresser, Loren Brandt, Dong Chen, Gregory Chow, Julan Du, Jie Gan, Li Jin, Sung Wook Joh , Simon Johnson, 
Ross Levine, Lijun Lin, Anthony Neoh, Tom Rawski, Yihong Xia, and seminar/conference participants at the 
American Economic Association meetings, the Asia Corpor ate Governance Conference in Korea, Boston College, 
Fudan University (Shanghai, China), Harvard Business School and Law School, IMF/World Bank, New York Fed, 
MIT, the 1st Tsinghua International Finance Conference in Beij ing, China, and the Wharton Conference on The 
Future of Chinese Management.  Financial support from Boston College and The Wharton School of the University 
of Pennsylvania is acknowledged. The authors are responsible for all remaining errors. 
 Corresponding author: Finance Department, Wharton School, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA 19104.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>the annual growth rate of PPP-adjusted GDPs during 1990-2002, China has been growing much 
faster than India, which has the second highest growth rate during the same period. With the recent 
entrance into the WTO and large potential markets it can provide, China will play an increasingly 
significant role in the world economy. 
II.2 Legal System
We first examine similar measures on the lega l system of China and compare them to the 
average measures of the 49 countries studied in LLSV (1998). See Appendix A.1 for a list of the 
definitions of the measures used in the paper. Fr om Table 2-A, we can see that in terms of overall 
creditor rights, China falls in be tween the English-origin countries that have the highest measures 
of protection, and French-origin co untries that have the poorest protection. Table 2-B shows that 
Chinas shareholder protection shows a similar patte rn. Because the distribution of these measures 
may be heavily skewed toward the tails due to a few outlier countries with very high and low 
scores, we also provide the percentage of countries in the sub-samp les and the entire sample of 
LLSV countries that have equal or higher  measures than Chinas (numbers in brackets in Tables 
2-A and 2-B). Almost half of countries in the Fr ench-origin sub-sample, to which China compares 
favorably, have equal or better measures of cred itor and shareholder rights. The overall evidence 
thus suggests that the majority of LLSV sample countries have better creditor and shareholder 
protections than China. 
Insert Tables 2-A and 2-B here. 
We obviously cannot draw our conclusions re garding the comparison of legal systems 
based on Tables 2-A and 2-B alone . First, the scores on creditor and shareholder rights mainly 
measure the protection of owners of publicly traded co mpanies. As above, the stock market and 
private ownership of corporations  are recent phenomena.  More importantly, these scores measure 
the legal system on paper, not in practice.  Even though the Chinese government has adopted 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Figure 3-C compares total equity issuance, incl uding IPO and SEO. With the exception of South 
Korea, China seems to be on similar pace in term s of size of equity issuance (as fraction of GNP 
in a given year) with  Taiwan and India. 
Insert Figures 3-A, 3-B, 3-C, and 3-D here. 
From the above comparisons it is clear that the development of Chinas external markets 
relative to its overall economic growth is not dram atically different from other emerging countries 
in Asia. One of the common patterns emerged from these comparisons is that the development of 
external markets trails that of the growth of overall economy. This is not surprising given that the 
development of these markets require minimum e fficiency of a countrys  institutions including 
legal system, accounting standards, and the development of associat ed professionals. By contrast, 
during early stages of the economic growth, alte rnative institutions and mechanisms alone can 
support the growth of firms and overall economy, as  is the case for China based on our evidence. 
Perhaps similar institutions have worked well in other emerging and developed economies as well, 
and future research can determine whether the Chin ese experience also occurs in other countries.  
IV. Evidence on the Listed Sector 
In this section, we focus on publicly traded  companies and examine their financing and 
investment decisions. As stated in the introduc tion, we want to draw general conclusions on 
whether there are fundamental differences betw een the Chinese firms and firms studied in 
previous papers (LLS 1999, LLSV 1997, 2000b, 2002). Befo re doing that, let us look at the unique 
ownership structure and corporate govern ance mechanisms in the Chinese firms. 
IV.1 Types of Stock 
Table 7-A introduces the types of stock issued by listed Chin ese firms. First, there are 
tradable and nontradable shares. Th e nontradable shares are either held by the state/government or 
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>51</slideno>
          <text>34. ____, ____, and ____, 2002. Government Ownership of Banks, Journal of Finance , 57 (1), 265
302. 
35. ____, ____, ____, and Robert Vishny, 1997. Legal determinants of external finance, Journal of 
Finance , vol. 52, 1131-1150.  
36. ____, ____, ____, and ____, 1998, Law and Finance, Journal of Political Economy , vol. 106, 
1113-1155. 
37. ____, ____, ____, and ____, 1999, The Quality of Government, Journal of Law, Economics, and 
Organization , vol. 15 (1), 222-279. 
38. ____, ____, ____, and ____, 2000a, Investor protection and corporate governance, Journal of 
Financial Economics , vol. 58 (1-2). 
39. ____, ____, ____, and ____, 2000b, Agency Problems and Dividend Policy Around the World, 
Journal of Finance , 55 (1), 1-34. 
40. ____, ____, ____, and ____, 2002. Investor Protection and Corporate Valuation, Journal of 
Finance , 57 (3), 1147-1170. 
41. Lardy, Nicholas, R., 1998. Chinas Unfinished Economic Revolution , Brookings Institution Press, 
Washington, D.C. 
42. Lau, Lawrence, Yingyi Qian, and Gerard Roland, 2000. Reform without Losers: An Interpretation 
of Chinas Dual-Track Approach to Transition, Journal of Political Economy , Vol. 108 (1), 
pp.120-143. 
43. Levine, Ross, 1999. Law, finance, and economic growth, Journal of Financial Intermediation , 
vol. 8 (1-2), 36-67. 
44. ____, 2002. Bank-based or Market-based Financial Systems: Which is Better? Journal of 
Financial Intermediation , Vol. 11, 1-30. 
45. ____, and Sara Zervos, 1998. Stock Ma rket, Banks, and Economic Growth, American Economic 
Review, Vol. 88 (3), 537-558. 
46. Li, David, 1998. Changing Incentives of the Chinese Bureaucracy, American Economic Review   
AEA papers and proceedings issue, 88 (2), 393-397. 
47. McKinnon, Ronald, 1973. Money and Capital in Economic Development , The Brookings 
Institution Press. 
48. McMillan, John, 1995. Chinas N onconformist Reform, Ch.13 of Economic Transition in 
Eastern Europe and Russia: Realities of Reform , ed. Edward P. Lazear, Stanford: Hoover 
Institution Press, 1995, pp. 419-433.  
49. ____, 1997. Markets in Transition, Ch.6 of Advances in Economics and Econometrics Vol.2, ed. 
David M. Kreps, and Kenneth F. Wallis, Camb ridge: Cambridge University Press, 210-239. 
51</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>banking sector, bank loans, including loans from  the non-state banks, provide a large amount of 
funds to firms, and constitute a large fraction of fi rms total financing needs. For example, firms in 
the State Sector rely on bank loans to raise more th an 25% of their total financing needs. A similar 
pattern holds for jointly- and collectively-owned companies, both of which belong to the Private 
Sector. Our survey evidence, to be presented in  Section V, also indicates that bank loans are 
important financing sources, especially during the start-up period of Private Sector firms. 
Self-fundraising includes proceed s from capital raised from local governments (beyond 
state budget) and communities and ot her investors, internal financi ng channels such as retained 
earnings, and all other funds rais ed domestically by the firms.32  First, the size of total self-
fundraising of all firms has been growing very  fast over the period of 1994-2002, at an average 
annual rate of 14%. At the end of 2002, total self -fundraising (for the purpose of fixed assets 
investment) reached US$275.5 billion, compared  to a total of US$106.6 billion domestic bank 
loans for the same year. It is important to poi nt out that equity and bond issuance, which are 
included in self-fundraising, apply only to the Li sted Sector, and account for a small fraction of 
this category. Second, self-fundraising is the most important source of fina ncing for many types of 
firms. For example, individually owned companies (of the Private Sector), not surprisingly, rely 
mostly on self-fundraising (about 90 % of total financing). Interesti ngly, even for state- or quasi-
state-owned companies, self-fundraising is also important in that it captures somewhere between 
45% and 65% of total financing. 
Finally, state budget and foreign (direct) investments are the ot her two important financing 
sources. As was the case for all socialist countries, China used to rely on a central planning system 
to allocate the state budget to most of the co mpanies in the country. But state budget now only 
32 Our current data source, the China Sta tistical Yearbook (2000), does not provide the breakdowns of fundraising, 
thus we only have the total figures.   
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>41</slideno>
          <text>fastest growing economies in the world, China differs  from most of the co untries studied in the 
law, institutions, finance, and grow th literature, and is an importa nt counterexample to the findings 
in the existing literature. Its legal and financ ial systems as well as institutions are all under
developed, but its economy has been growing at a very fast rate.  More importantly, the growth in 
the Private Sector, where applicab le legal and financial mechanisms  are much poorer than those in 
the State and Listed Sectors, is much faster than  that of the other sectors. We believe that the 
system of alternative mechanisms and institutions  plays an important role  in supporting the growth 
in the Private Sector, and they are excellent substitutes for standard corporate governance 
mechanisms and financing channels. 
Going forward, our results pose an important  question for both re searchers and policy 
makers: should China also transform the Private S ector toward the standar d form like it has been 
doing for the State Sector?  Given the success of the Private Sector and the deficiency in the State 
and Listed Sectors, we believe that much more research is required, in order to better understand 
how alternative mechanisms work where standard mechanisms are not available or not suitable. 
Our work also has general implications for the li terature on law, institutions, finance, and growth: 
there are important factors that are not well understood. Adopting result s obtained from studying 
developed countries to the development of  emerging countries can be misleading and 
counterproductive. We find that these substitu tes have worked well in China, and similar 
substitutes based on relationship and reputation ma y have also worked well in other economies 
including developed economies. Therefore, a be tter understanding of how these non-standard 
mechanisms work to promote growth can shed light on alternative development paths that can 
benefit many other countries. 
41</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>books of all the banks in China.28  Whether the government will do exactly this remains to be 
seen, but it is clear that the ultimate source of eliminating NPLs lies in the overall economic 
growth. As long as the economy maintains its str ong growth momentum so that the governments 
taxable income also increases, the government can always assume the remainder of the NPLs 
without significantly affecting the economy. 
II.4 Growth in the State, Listed, and Private Sectors 
Table 6-A compares the growth of industrial output  produced in the State and Listed 
Sectors vs. that of the Private Sector from 1996 to 2002. It is clear that the Private Sector 
dominates the State and Listed Sectors in terms of either the size of the output,29 or in terms of the 
growth trend. From Panel A of Table 6-A, the Pr ivate Sector grew at an annual rate of 14.3% 
between 1996 and 2002, while the State and Listed Sectors combined grew at only 5.4% during 
the same period.30  In addition, the growth rates for investme nt in fixed assets of these two sectors 
are comparable (Panel B of Table 6-A), which imp ly that the Private Sector is actually more 
productive than the State and Listed Sectors. Fi nally, there has been a fundamental change among 
the State, Listed, and Private Sectors in terms of their contribution to the entire economy: the State 
Sector contributed 76% of Chin as total industrial output in 1980, but in 1996 it only contributed 
28.5%; in 1980 individually owned firms, a type of  Private Sector firms, are negligible, but in 
27 Chinas RMB has been pegged to US dollar (only) at 8.28 to 1. The foreign exchange reserves are in the form of US 
dollars (in cash), T-bills, and other dollar denominated debt securities. See for example, Financial Times (01/09/2004) 
and Asia Wall Street Journal (01/13/2004) for more details. 
28 One potential risk for using foreign reserve to boost the banking system is the pressure of significant RMB 
appreciation relative to US$ and other major foreign currencies. Necessary hedg ing strategies shoul d be planned by 
the banks, in addition to tighten the currency flow as it has been the case. 
29 Total output in 1999 is US$1200 billion for the Private Sector, while it is around US$400 billion in the State and 
Listed Sectors combined. 
30 There is an ongoing process of privatizing SOEs. Potentia lly this may bias the growth rate of the Private Sector 
higher, as there are firms shifting from the State Sector to the Private Sector. However, the overwhelming majority of 
SOEs are transformed into publicly traded firms (the List ed Sector). Thus this proce ss is unlikely to change the 
validity of the results above. 
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>45</slideno>
          <text>A.3. External Financing Variables (LLSV 1998), used in Tables 4a, 4b, and 4c 
Variable  Description Sources 
External cap 
/ GNP The ratio of the stock market capitalization held by minorities 
to GNP in 1994. The first variable is computed as the product 
of the aggregate stock market capitalization and the average 
percentage of common shares not owned by the TOP 3 shareholders in the TEN largest non-financial, privately- owned 
domestic firms in a given country. A firm is considered privately owned if the State is not a known shareholder. Moodys International, 
CIFAR, EXTEL, WorldScope, 20-Fs, 
PriceWaterhouse, and 
various country sources 
Domestic 
firms / Pop Ratio of the number of domestic firms listed in a given country to its population (in millions) in 1994. Emerging Market Factbook 
and World Development 
Report (WDR) 1996.  
IPOs/Pop Ratio of the number of initial public offerings of equity in a given country to its population (in millions) for the period 1995:7-1996:6. SDC, AsiaMoney, 
LatinFinance, GT Guide to World Equity Markets, and 
WDR 1996.  
Debt/GNP Ratio of the sum of bank debt of the private sector and 
outstanding non-financial bonds to GNP in 1994, or last 
available International Financial Statistics, World 
Bondmarket Factbook. 
GDP growth Average annual percent growth of per capita gross domestic 
product for the period 1970-1993. WDR 1995 
Market cap/ 
sales The median ratio of the stock market capitalization held by 
minorities to sales in 1994 for all nonfinancial firms in a given 
country on the WorldScope database. Firm's stock market 
capitalization held by minorities is computed as the product of the stock market capitalizati on of firm and the average 
percentage of common shares not owned by the top three shareholders in the ten larges t nonfinancial, privately owned 
domestic firms in a given country. A firm is considered privately owned if the State is not a known shareholder in it.  WorldScope 
Market cap/ 
cash-flow The median ratio of the stock market capitalization held by 
minorities to cash flow in 1994 for all nonfinancial firms in a 
given country on the WorldScope database. Firm's stock market 
capitalization held by minorities is computed as the product of the stock market capitalization of the firm and the average 
percentage of common shares not owned by the top three shareholders in the ten larges t nonfinancial, privately owned 
domestic firms in a given country. A firm is considered privately owned if the State is not a known shareholder in it.  WorldScope. 
Debt/sales Median of the total-debt-to-sales ratio in 1994 for all firms in a WorldScope. 
given country on the WorldScope database. 
Debt/cash 
flow Median of the total-debt-to-cash-flow ratio for all firms in a 
given country on the WorldScope database. WorldScope. 
Secondary source LLSV(1998), China details from Shanghai, Shen Zhen Stock exchange, Firm annual report. 
45</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>48</slideno>
          <text>Step2: Adjusted alpha (China) = Alpha (China from regression) - beta(LLSV) X(China). Then compare the adjusted 
Alpha (China) with Alpha (LLSV samples). 
Method 2: Unrestricted Model 
Step1:  Alpha (China) = mean (yigamma(LLSV)*Z(China)) 
Step2: The same as the step 2 in Restricted Model above. 
The following table presents the alpha for LLSV sample firms, Alpha for Chinese firms, and the discrepancy. 
 Dividend/Earnings Dividend/Sales Tobin'q 
Alpha in LLSV 44.9493 1.8907 1.1559 
Alphas for Chinese firms: Unrestricted Model 
Restricted Model 11.5033 2.5876 0.5151* 
Unrestricted Model 11.8270 1.1490 0.5831 
Adjusted alphas for Chinese Firms: Restricted Model 
Restricted Model 14.5388 0.8131 0.2946 
Unrestricted Model 14.8626 -0.6255 0.2582 
Discrepancy 
Restricted Model 30.4105 1.0776 0.8613 
Unrestricted Model 30.0804 2.5162 0.6898 
Note: * denote the significance at 1% level. The other two alphas in the restricted model for China are not significant. 
Method 3: Firm level Out-of-sample predictions: 
We also perform firm level out-of-sample predictions, based on the regression results from LLSV (2000, 2002). The 
results are similar to the above two methods. Method 3 can actually be proven to be mathematically identical to the 
unrestricted model in Method 2, and thus the details are omitted here. 
Summary of Results: 
1) The out-of-sample prediction for Dividend / Earning is dramatically different from empirical observed value (lower
than the low boundary).  
2) The observed Dividend /sales, and Tobins q ratios locate between predicted boundaries.
3) The discrepancy of unexplained portion of the dependent variables is big for Dividend/Earnings, but small for 
dividend/Sales, and Tobins q.
(The average ratios themselves are no t dramatically different between Chin a and other countries. 30.23 (China,
dividend/earnings) vs. 32.61, 2.35 vs. 1.99, and 1.21 vs. 1.38.)
Conclusion: We can conclude that the independent variables proposed in previous studies, do not explain the firm
behaviors exactly the same for Chinese firms as for firms in other countries. However, we can not specify which 
variables, hence what mechanism is different , and how much difference exactly is there. 
48</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>62</slideno>
          <text>0.6 
0.5 percentage0.4 
0.3 
0.2 
0.1
0
1994 1995 1996 1997 1998 1999 2000 2001 2002
Calendar Yea r 
iState Budget Bank Loan 
Foreign Investment Fundra sing 
Figure 2-B Financing Sou rces for the State Sector percentage 0.700
0.600
0.500
0.400
0.300
0.200
0.100
0.000
1994 1995 1996 1997 1998 1999 2000 2001 2002 
Calendar Yea r 
iState Budget Bank Loan 
Foreign Investment Fundra sing 
Figure 2-C Financing Sou rces for the Private Sector 
62</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>of the land from the government, who has the ulti mate control. The opera tion-rights contract is 
long-term, between 20-50 years.42  In terms of fixed assets, 16 out of the 17 firms purchased and 
own all of their fixed assets. Among them, 9 firm s purchased their fixed assets from the State 
Sector, and 7 out of the 9 firms c onsidered the price they paid to be the same as market value of 
the assets. There is one firms executive indicated that for the rental portion of fixed assets from 
SOE, there is no formal contracts between the firm and the SOE. 
Next, when asked about the prospects of goi ng public, founders and ex ecutives list access 
to large scale of funding and reputation increase as the most important benefits, and the 
disclosure of valuable information to competitors  and outsiders and large amount of fees paid 
to the government, investment banks, and consulting firms as the most critical disadvantages of 
going public. We also asked the founde rs and executives about the degree of difficulty in receiving 
funding through a certain channel. 80% of the firms regard short-term  bank loans as easy to 
have access to and are low costs, while around 55% of firms regard long-term bank loans as 
easy and low cost. Around 50% of firms also be lieve trade credits among firms and funds from 
family and friends as easy and low cost. These forms of financing channels reduce the cost of 
capital for firms because reputa tion and relationships help reso lve the potential problems of 
asymmetric information and agency costs.   
Corporate Governance 
Figure 4-C provides some information on governance mechanisms. First, over 60% (30%) 
of firms believe that if their own firm is not run efficiently, it is possible (very likely) to have 
its assets purchased (or taken ove r) by another firm or investor, while no one answered it is not 
possible for this to occur. Not reported in the figure, we also asked firms about product market 
42 With operation rights, a firm has more control over the la nd than under a land rental contract. For example, firms 
can rent the land to another party once obtaining the operation rights from the government. Land rental contracts have 
shorter terms on average (5-10 years). 
32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>65</slideno>
          <text>&lt;0
0% 0% 10% 20% 30% 40% Annual return in the past 5 years 
 0~0.1 0.1~0.2 0.2~0.3 &gt;0.3 
10% 20% 30% 40% Expected annual return in the 
next 3 years 
&lt;0  0~0.1 0.1~0.2
 0.2~0.3 &gt;0.3 
holdi
i/ 
f 
0% ild i/ 
0% 20% 30% 40% Ownership when startup 
Par tner GOV T. TVE Share-
ng 
Others Fore gn Founder
amily 
10% 20% 30% 40% Current ownership 
Part ner Fore gn TVE Share-ho ng 
Ot hers GOVT. Found er
family 
10 % 
Collective TVE 
Others 
0% 5% 10% 15% 20% 25% 30% 35% 40% Founder's previous experience 
SOE 
GOVT 
Private Firm JV 
Figure 4-A Background Information of Survey Firms 
(The following two graphs present percentage of firms, who regard the corresponding financing sources as 
very important (25-50%) or extremely important (&gt;50%) for their starting up and growth.) 
65</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>competition. Forty percent of surveyed firms founde rs/executives believe that if their firm is not 
operating efficiently, within 3-6 months, 20% of it s market share will be taken away, while 80% 
of firms founders/executives believe the entire ma rket share of the firm will be taken away in two 
years. When asked about what type of losses conc ern them the most if the firm failed (top right 
histogram in Figure 4-C), every firms founders/ex ecutives (100%) said reput ation loss is a major 
concern, while only 60% of them said economic losses are of major concern.  
The success of a firm in the Private Sect or depends crucially on whether the local 
government supports the firm or not. In the bottom histogram of Figure 4-C, we asked firms about 
their relationship with the government officials. Over 40% of survey firms state the local 
government support the growth of the firm without demanding profit sharing, while for some other firms, the government is either a partial ow ner or demand profit sharing without investing in 
the firm. The supportive attitude of the government toward firms in the Private Sector is remarkable considering the fact th at the Chinese government is wide ly regarded as corrupt and not 
respecting property rights  of private citizens. 
V.2 Further Evidence for Firm s in Two Successful Regions 
WenZhou -- Village Chambers 
Wenzhou, a city in the Zhejiang Province, is the home of some of the earliest and most  
successful firms of the Private Sector. Entrepreneurs in the region are known for their keen 
business sense and sharp management skills, and th ey often lead the Privat e Sector in terms of 
innovation.43  They usually start their family-run busi nesses in townships with a similar product 
emphasis, in order to have the easy access to  the necessary technology, management skills, and 
potential clients and partners. Thus we observe specialization by regions (e.g., Town A produces 
43 McMillan and Naughton (1992), McMillan and Woodruff ( 2002) point out entrepreneurs facilitate the transition 
from planning economy to market-based economy by, fo r example, starting up firms and entering industries 
dominated by state-owned enterprises. 
33</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>35</slideno>
          <text>special zone established by the local government.44  It acts as the liaison between the local 
government, entrepreneurs, and foreign investors, a nd the regulator as well as service provider for 
enterprises operating in the zone.  
Enterprises in the zone are required to repor t their operating and fina ncial information to, 
and are regulated by the center. But they understand that the cent er will almost never interfere 
with their internal decisions. The centers offi cials are mainly from the local government. The 
high-tech development zone grew very fast sinc e its inception. From 1997 to 2001, the size of the 
zone increased eight fold, and currently ther e are 250 firms, with a total of US$ 200 million 
foreign direct investment coming from more than  20 countries and regions,  including those from 
Taiwan. Firms are operating in a wide range of industries, from high-tech  to clothing, and export 
their products to all major markets around the world. 
During the early stage of the special zone, investors from Taiwan were willing to commit 
their capital to these start-ups and refinance them  whenever necessary.  Ac tually the reason that 
many investors are from Taiwan is no coincidenc e.  Many people in Kunshan have relatives in 
Taiwan and through them the investors obtained th e information on the inve stment opportunities.  
The Taiwanese investors also came to understand  that although there were almost no formal 
investor protections, local government official s have an incentive to  cooperate with the 
development of the special zone and creating an economic boom in the local economy. This is the 
case because a booming economy can greatly enhance th e chance of an official being promoted, in 
addition to participating in prof it sharing.  Another interesting phenomenon during the early stage 
of development was that these investors from Taiwan did not stay in the area as they often do now. 
As a result, there was virtually no monitoring of the entrepreneurs, and complete separation of 
ownership and control. 
44 For more information, refer to  this website: http://www.china-hitech.org /hitech/chinese/qiye.asp. 
35</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>50</slideno>
          <text>17. Djankov, Simeon, Rafael La Porta, Florencio Lopez-de-Silanes, and Andre Shleifer, 2002. The 
Regulation of Entry, Quarterly Journal of Economics , 117 (1), 1-37. 
18. ____, ____, ____, and ____, 2003a. Courts, Quarterly Journal of Economics , 118 (2), 453-517. 
19. ____, ____, ____, and ____, 2003b. The Regul ation of Labor, working paper, Harvard 
University. 
20. Demirguc-Kunt, Asli, and Vojislav Maksimovic,  1998. Law, finance, and firm growth, Journal 
of Finance , vol. 53 (6), 2107-37. 
21. _____, and Ross Levine, 2002. Financial Structure and Economic Growth: Cross-country Comparisons of Banks, Markets, and Development , MIT Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts. 
22. Gomes, Armando, 2000. Going public without governance: managerial reputation effects, 
Journal of Finance , vol. 55, 615-646. 
23. Graham, John, and Campbell Harvey, 2001. The Theory and Practice of Corporate Finance: 
Evidence from the Field, Journal of Financial Economics , Vol. 61, 1-35. 
24. Greif, Avner, 1989. Reputation and Coalitions  in Medieval Trade: Evidence on the Maghribi 
Traders, Journal of Economic History , Vol. 49, 857-882. 
25. ____, 1993. Contract Enforceability and Economic Institutions in Early Trade: The Maghribi 
Traders Coalition, American Economic Review , Vol. 83 (3), 525-548. 
26. ____, 1994. Cultural Beliefs and the Organizati on of Society: A Historical and Theoretical 
Reflection on Collectivist and Individualist Societies, Journal of Political Economy , Vol. 102 (5), 
912-950. 
27. Hayek, Friedrich, 1960. The Constitution of Liberty , University of Chicago Press, Chicago, IL.  
28. Jayaratne, Jith and Philip E. Strahan, 1996. 	  The Finance-Growth Nexus: Evidence from Bank 
Branch Deregulation, Quarterly Journal of Economics  111(3), 639-70. 
29. Johnson, Simon, John McMillan, and Christopher Woodruff, 2002a. Property Rights and 
Finance, American Economic Review , 92, 1335-1356. 
30. ____, ____, and ____, 2002b. Courts and Relational Contracts, Journal of Law, Economics, &amp; 
Organization , 18 (1), 221-277. 
31. King, Robert, and Ross Levine, 1993. Finance and Growth: Schumpeter Might Be Right, Quarterly Journal of Economics , Vol. 108 (3), 717-738. 
32. Kortum, Sameul, and Josh Lerner, 2000. Assessi ng the Contribution of Venture Capital to 
Innovation, RAND Journal of Economics , 31, 674-692.   
33. La Porta, Rafael, Florencio Lopez-de-Silanes, and Andrei Shleifer, 1999. Corporate Ownership 
Around the World, Journal of Finance , 54 (2), 471-517.  
50</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>In this section we first provi de evidence on Chinas entire ec onomy, and then on the status 
of its legal and financial systems. We next comp are China to the countries studied by the existing 
literature (the LLSV sample and th e Levine sample). Finally we compare growth in the State, 
Listed, and Private Sectors of China. 
II.1 Status of Chinas Economy 
Tables 1-A and 1-B illustrate Ch inas status as one of the mo st important countries in the 
world. At the end of 2002 it had a population of 1.28 billion people, the la rgest of any country.  
From the column on the left in Table 1-A, Chinas GDP ranked 6th in the world using simple 
exchange rate calculations.9  However, if we use PPP formula to recalculate the GDPs, Chinas 
economy is the second largest behind only the US, as shown in the middle column of Table 1-A. 
Moreover, with the same PPP formula and assumi ng that the US economy continues to grow at 
4.69% per year, it will take only 10 years before China overtakes the US to be the largest economy 
in the world.10 
Insert Tables 1-A and 1-B here. 
It may be more useful to compare Chinas economic growth with other major emerging 
economies rather than the most developed countri es, since Chinas rapid growth only started in 
1979 when it opened its door to the outside world.11  In Table 1-B we compare China with the 
seven largest emerging economies in the world. In  terms of PPP-adjusted GDP figures in 2002, 
China is almost twice the size of Mexico, the s econd largest emerging economy. While in terms of 
9 Except otherwise noted, we use the exchange rate of 1 US $ = 8.28 RMB in all of our cu rrency-related calculations 
throughout the paper.
10 All of Chinas GNP and GNP growth figures exclude Hong  Kong. The PPP conversion fact or we used is obtained 
from the World Bank Development Indicator. For details refer to the Handbook of the International Program, 
United Nation, New York 1992. The growth rate of the US is calculated using the period 1990-2002. 
Measured by simple exchange rates, Chinas GDP in 1980 was US$180.6 billion while in 1990 it reached US$368 
billion. Also note that the exchange rate between RMB and US$ changed from US$1 = 4.25 yuan to 8.28 yuan in 
1992, which introduced a significant downward bias for Chinas GDP figure in 1992. See http://www.safe.gov.cn/0430/js_tzyg.htm (i n Chinese) for more details. This is why using PPP adjusted figures to 
measure GDP and its growth is more appropriate. 
7
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>based standards, as compared to an alternativ e system with a much simpler set of accounting 
standards. 
To summarize, Chinas legal system is underdeveloped relative to most countries, 
including other major developing countries.  By the arguments of LLSV and Levine, Chinas poor 
legal system tends to hinder the development of corporate governance mechanisms of Chinese 
companies, their fund raising through capital market s, and their growth as well as the growth of 
the overall economy.  What we argue is that this prediction ignore s how well alternative 
mechanisms can replace formal legal system. 
II.3 Financial System 
We first examine Chinas financial system at the aggregate level, including both its 
banking system and financial markets. We then ex amine its stock exchanges in more detail and 
also briefly discuss its venture capital markets.  Finally, we examine the problems in the banking 
sector. 
Insert Table 3 here. 
In Table 3 we compare Chinas financial system to those of LLSV (1997, 1998) sample 
countries, using measures from Le vine (2002). We first compare the size of a countrys equity 
markets and banks relative to that countrys GDP. Chinas stock markets, which did not exist until 
1990 but have been growing very fast, are smaller than most of the other countries, both in terms 
of market capitalization and the total value traded as fractions of GDP.15 By contrast, Chinas 
banking system is much more important in terms of size relative to its stock markets, with its ratio 
of total bank credit to GDP (1.11) higher than ev en the German-origin countries (with a weighted 
average of 0.99). However, when we consider bank credit issued (or loan s made) to the Private 
15 Note that total value traded is a better measure th an market capitalization because the latter includes non-
tradable shares, while the form er measures the floating supply of shares  in the markets, or the fraction of total 
market cap traded in the markets. See Table 4-A of th is section and Section IV below for further discussions. 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>collectively-owned firms (or purchas ing assets from the latter), while the latter firms typically 
have good relationship with  state-owned banks.  
During the firms subsequent growth period, fi nancing from private credit agencies is the 
most important channel. These non- state lenders usually charge very  high interest rates and/or 
require large amount of collateral on loans, can force liquidation should the entrepreneurs default, 
and the associated loan contracts resemble junk bonds to a certain de gree. Interestingly, loans from 
state-owned banks are no longe r the dominant source of fundi ng during the growth period. On 
average, each surveyed firm currently has loan relationship with 4.3 banks/financial institutions, 
with the maximum (minimum) being 12 (1). Collat eral value counts an average of 82.6% of the 
loan value on average (among the 11 firms whic h answered this question), with maximum 120% 
and minimum 20%. Fixed asset is the most popular form of collate ral, and third party guarantee 
being the second most popular form. These facts impl y that financial institu tions, state or private, 
seem to understand the risk of a start-up firm an d price this risk acco rdingly in their loan 
contracts. 
During firms growth period (Figure 4-B), ther e are a few other channels that are important 
sources of financing, in partic ular, investment from ethnic Ch inese investors (from Hong Kong, 
Taiwan, and overseas Chinese). Th is financing source, as comp ared to investment from non-
Chinese foreign investment (FDI), relies on relationship between the investors and the 
entrepreneurs, as well as the reputation of the entrepreneurs. Other sources include trade credits 
among business partners, state and local budget, and foreign direct investment (FDI) from non-
Chinese investors, while investment from venture cap italists (VC) is not wi dely used during either 
the start-up stage or the growth period. 
For start-up firms, securing land and other fixed assets is important for their survival. 
While not reported in the figures, more than half of surveyed firms purchase the operation-rights 
31</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>49</slideno>
          <text>References: 
1.	Acemoglu, Daron, and Simon Johnson, 2003. U nbundling Institutions: Law vs. Politics, working 
paper, MIT. 
2.	____, ____, and James Robinson, 2001. The Colonial Origins of Comparative Development: An 
Empirical Investigation, American Economic Review , 91 (5), 1369-1401. 
3.	____, ____, and ____, 2002. Reversal of Fortune: Geography and Institutions in the Making of the 
Modern World Income Distribution, Quarterly Journal of Economics , 117, 1231-1294. 
4.	Aharony, Joseph, Chi-wen Lee, and T.J. Wong, 2000. Financial Packaging of IPO Firms in China, forthcoming, Journal of Accounting Research . 
5.	Allen, Franklin, and Douglas Gale, 2000a. Comparing Financial Systems , MIT Press, Cambridge, 
MA. 
6.	____, and ____, 2000b. Corpor ate Governance and Competition, in Corporate Governance: 
Theoretical and Empirical Perspectives, edited by X. Vives, Cambridge University Press, London, 
23-94. 
7.	Beck, Thorsten, Asli Demirguc-Kunt, and Ross Le vine, 2003a. Law, Endowments, and Finance, 
forthcoming, Journal of Financial Economics . 
8.	____, ____, and ____, 2003b. Law and Finance:  Why Does Legal Origin Matter? forthcoming, 
Journal of Comparative Economics . 
9.	____, and Ross Levine, 2002, Industry Growth a nd Capital Allocation: Does Having a Market- or 
Bank-Based System Matter? forthcoming, Journal of Financial Economics . 
10. Blanchard, Oliver, and Andrei Shleifer, 2001, Federalism with and without Political 
Centralization: China vs. Russia, IMF St aff Working Papers, Special Issue.   
11. Bris, Arturo, William Goetzmann, and Ning Zhu, 2003. Efficiency and the Bear: Short Sales and Markets around the World, working paper, Yale University. 
12. Bruton, Garry, and David Ahlstrom, 2002. An In dustrial View of Chinas Venture Capital 
Industry: Explaining the Difference between China and the West, Journal of Business Venturing , 
Vol. 17, 1-27. 
13. Burkart, Mike, Fausto Panunzi, and Andrei Sh leifer, 2003.  	 Family Firms, forthcoming, Journal 
of Finance . 
14. Chow, Gregory, 2002. Chinas Economic Transformation , Blackwell Publishing, London, UK. 
15. Claessens, Stijn, Simeon Djankov, and Larry Lang , 2000. The Separation of Ownership and 
Control in East Asian Corporations, Journal of Financial Economics,  58, 81-112. 
16. _____, _____, Joseph Fanand, and Larry Lang,  2002. Disentangling the Incentive and 
Entrenchment of Large Shareholdings, Journal of Finance , Vol. 57 (6), 2741-2771. 
49</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>63</slideno>
          <text>Stock Market Comparison 
140% 
120% 
100% 
80% 60% 
40% 
20% 
0% Market cap /GNP Tai
ia wan 
Korea 
China 
Ind
0
1973 1976 19791982 19851988199119941997000197 2
year 
Figure 3-A: Market cap/GNP ratios 
Coporate Bond Market Corporate bond /GNP 40% 
35% 30% 25% 
20% 
15% 
10% 
5% 
0% Taiwan 
Korea 
China 
7013 6
197912 5 8
191 4
19972000 7 7 8 8989 9199 9 9 9 91 1 1 1
year 
Figure 3-B: Comparison of Corporate bond market 
63</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>59</slideno>
          <text>Table 8-A Summary Statistics of Listed Firms (in US$ millions) 
Data source for Tables 8-A, 8-B, and 8-C (also empirical tests in Appendix B): Firms are listed in SHSE and SZSE (as 
of December 2000), data downloaded  from Taiwan Economic Journals Asia Emerging Market Database 
(http://www.tei.com.tw/ ). 
Key financial items and ratios 
Mean Median Min Max Std. Dev Number of obs 
Market Capitalization 448.2 354.9 0.0 8190.2 513.9 1174 
LT Debt / Common Equity 0.3 0.1 0.0 6.9 0.6 981 
Net Income 99.6 502.0 -1,215.9 21,718.6 721.0 979 
EPS 0.2 0.2 -3.2 1.6 0.4 979 
Proceeds from Stock Sales  163.6 0.0 -290.8 29,379.2 987.0 975 (272) 
Dividend 50.8 18.4 0.0 8,106.0 270.2 979 (617) 
Retained Earnings 26.4 33.2 -2,125.7 2,210.18 234.4 979 (951) 
Bonds Issue 0.8 0.0 0.0 521.0 17.3 975 (6) 
Long Term Borrowing 634.9 233.1 0.0 157,053.1 5,073.7 974 (895) 
Note: the numbers in the bracket are the statistics of nonzero observations. 
Table 8-B Comparing Ownership Structure of Listed Firms 
 Panels A and B are taken from LLSV (JF1999). The first row is the average of Asia countries included in Claessen et 
al. (2000), excluding Japan. The last row for Ch ina includes our sample of 1147 listed firms. 
Country  Widely State Family Widely Held Widely Held 
Held Financial Corporation 
Panel A: LLS (1999) Sample with Large Firms 
High anti-director average 34.17 15.83 30.42 5 5.83 
Low anti-dir. average 16 23.67 38.33 11 2 
Sample average 24 20.19 34.81 8.3 3.7 
Panel B: LLS (1999) Sample with Medium Firm Size 
High anti-dir. average 16.67 10.33 50.92 5.83 1.67 
Low anti-dir. average 6 20.87 53.8 6.67 2.67 
Sample average 10.74 16.19 52.52 6.3 2.22 
Panel C: Asian firms  
Asia (no Japan, from 3.09 9.36 59.36 9.66 18.55 
Claessens et al. 2000 ) 
China (our calculations) 0.44 60 13.56 1.83* 24.17** 
Notes: 1) Widely held firms are defined as no large shareholder holding more than 10% of shares; State 
(family) firms are those with controlling shareholder being the state (a family);  
Widely held financial (widely held corporation) are those with controlling shareholder being a widely-held
financial company (widely-held corporation). 
*: For these Chinese firms, we identify the dominant shareholder to be a financial company, but we are not sure
whether the financial company is widely held or not; 
**: For these Chinese firms, we identify the dominant shareholder to be another listed and traded corporation, but we 
are not sure whether this corporation is widely held or not.
59</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>find that the law-finance-growth  nexus established by existing literature works well for the State 
and Listed Sectors in China: with poor legal protections of minority and outside investors, 
(standard) external markets are weak , and growth of these firms is sl ow or negative.  However, the 
size, growth, and importance of these two sector s in the economy are dominated by those of the 
Private Sector. With poorer app licable legal protections and st andard financing channels, the 
Private Sector has been growing much faster an d contributing to most of the economys growth. 
Our conclusion for the imbalance among the three se ctors is that there ex ist very effective, 
alternative financing channels and corporate governance mechanisms to support the growth of the 
Private Sector. Our evidence suggest s that these alternative channels  and mechanisms are in part 
based on reputation and relationships, and they ca n substitute for and do at least as well as 
standard channels and mechanisms.   
Using measures from the existing literature, we  first find that Chinas law and institutions, 
including investor protection systems, corporat e governance, accounting standards, and quality of 
government, are significantly less developed than those in most of the countries in the LLSV 
(1997, 1998) and Levine (2002) samples. We also fi nd Chinas financial system is dominated by a 
large but under-developed banking system that is mainly controlled  by the four state-owned banks. 
Its newly established Shanghai Stock Exchange (SHSE hereafter) and ShenZhen Stock Exchange 
(SZSE hereafter) have been growing very fast since their inception in 1990, but their scale and 
importance are still not comparable to other channels of financing, in particular the banking sector, 
for the entire economy. Developing the banking system, in particular  alleviating the burden of 
non-performing loans (NPLs) of state-owned banks on the banking system and the whole 
economy, is as important as further developing the stock market.       
forged; 2) privately owned companies (excluding publicly traded companies that were privately owned): controlling 
owners of these firms can be Chinese citizens, investors (or companies) from Taiwan or Hong Kong, or foreign 
investors (or companies). See Appendix A.4 for more details. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>State Sector, and the status quo of its banking se ctor. However, the high government ownership 
has not slowed down the growth of the most impo rtant sector of the economy, the Private Sector. 
The most glaring problem for Chinas banking sector is the amount of NPLs within the 
four largest state-owned banks. A large fraction of these bad loans results from poor lending 
decisions made for SOEs, some of which were du e to political or other non-economic reasons, and 
these loans accumulated over the years without ever being resolved. The additional problem is that data availability on NPLs is limited, which can be vi ewed as a strategic disclosure decision of the 
government. But this lack of disclosure of NPLs only fuels speculations that  the problem must be 
severe. As Lardy (1995) argues, if using inte rnational standards on NPLs, the existing NPLs 
within the state-owned banks as of mid-1990s can make these banks to tal net worth to be 
negative so that they are in effect insolvent. 
Insert Tables 5-A and 5-B here. 
Tables 5-A and 5-B compare NP Ls and banking system profita bility in China and other 
major Asian economies in more recent years. Firs t, as Table 5-A indicates, NPLs, either as a 
fraction of total new loans made by all banks or as a fraction of GDP in a given year, are the 
highest in China from 2000-2002.23  This comparison includes the period during which Asian 
countries recovered from the 1997 financial cris is, and the period during which the Japanese 
banking system was disturbed by the bad loan problem. Second, as Table 5-B indicates, the 
profitability of Chinas banking sy stem, measured by the return to equity or assets, is also among 
the lowest in the group of countries. 
In recent years the Chinese government has taken active measures to  solve this problem. 
First, four state-owned asset management companies were formed with the goal of assuming these 
23 Information on NPLs first became available in 1998. However, the figures in 1998 and 1999 probably significantly 
underestimate the actual size of NPLs, and are ignored in our discussions. 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>contributes 10% of state-owned  companies total funding. On the other hand, as a financing source 
foreign investment is comparable  to state budget, both in terms of  aggregate size and in terms of 
the relative importance in firms financing. This evidence confirms  that China has evolved from a 
central planning, closed economy to ward an open market economy. 
With the knowledge on the four financing channels  at the aggregate level, we now focus on 
different types of firms financi ng decisions. The results are presen ted in Figures 2-A, 2-B, and 2
C. In all of these figures, each of the four connect ed lines represents the importance of a particular 
financing channel over the time period of 1994-2002, measured by the percentage of firms total 
financing coming from this channel. 
First, Figure 2-A (2-B) illustrates how firms in the Listed Sector (State Sector) finance 
their investment. From Figure 2-A, we can see that  just below 30% of publicly traded companies 
funding comes from bank loans, and this ratio has b een very stable, despite the fast growth of the 
stock markets. Around 45% of Listed Sectors  total funding comes from (self-) fundraising, 
including internal financing and proceeds from equity and bond issuance.33 The growth of 
publicly traded firms has been im pressive, with total market capitalization including non-tradable 
shares reaching US$330 billion at the end of 1999. On the contrary, SOEs are on a downward 
trend, as privatization of these firms is still in progress. From the information on equity and bond 
sales, we know that these sources  of (self-) fundraising that rely  on the use of external markets 
only constitute a small fraction of total funds raised, compared to internal financing and other forms of fundraising. Combined with the fact that self-fundraising (bank loans being the second 
most important source) is also the most important  source of financing for the State Sector (Figure 
33 Publicly traded firms also receive funds  from the state budget, because some of the firms in this category used to be 
state-owned, and the funding relationship has not been completely severed.  But the state budget is not as important as 
foreign direct investment, which as of 1997 accounts for 9.5% of total financing. 
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>by other legal entities, namely other firms ( listed or non-listed) or organizations. Through 
nontradable shares, in particular state-owned shares, the government  retains (partial) control of 
firms that used to belong to the State Sector. Among the tradable shares, Classes A and B shares 
are listed and traded in either the SHSE or SZSE , while Class A (B) shares are issued to Chinese 
investors (foreign investors includi ng those from Taiwan and Hong Kong). Class H shares can be 
listed and traded on the HKSE and are issued by selected Red Chip Chinese companies. 
Insert Tables 7-A, 7-B, and 7-C here. 
From Tables 7-B and 7-C, we can see that the ownership structure of a listed companys 
equity in China is different from that observed in many other countries. First, from Table 7-B, 
non-tradable shares constitute a majority of all shares, while mo st of non-tradable shares are 
held by the state. On the other hand, the majority of tradable sh ares are A shares, or the shares 
held and traded by Chinese citizens. Second, Tabl es 7-C provides some evidence on the relation 
between ownership and control of the Board of Directors. Informa tion provided here is based on a 
survey of corporate governance practices among 257 companies listed on the SHSE conducted in 
the year 2000 by Integrity Management Cons ulting and the Research Center of SHSE.34 
Consistent with Tables 7-A and 7-B and the one-share, one-vote scheme adopted by firms in the 
Listed Sector, state and legal pe rson shareholders appoint most of  the board members as shown in 
Table 7-C. While selecting 48% of all direct ors on the board, and taki ng into account that 
shareholders selected only 76% of  all directors in the 257 surveyed  companies (the other directors 
were appointed by the government), state and le gal person shareholders, owning 44% of all the 
shares, selected 70% (or 48 out of 76) of t hose directors that took office through the voting 
process. 
34 The survey is based on over 10,000 questionnaires sent to directors, supervisors, and other senior managers in listed 
companies. Also see Corporate Governance and Enterprise Reform in China: Building the institutions of Modern 
24</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>property rights and government corruption are cr ucial institutions determining financial and 
economic outcomes. Although our results are based on China, similar substitutes based on 
reputation and relationships may be behind th e success of other economies as well, including 
developed economies. Thus a thorough examination of these substitutes ha s much more general 
implications and can provide valuable guidance for many other countries. Finally, some of our 
results are consistent with existing research on economies in transition (f rom Socialist, central 
planning systems to market-based economies), including Eastern European countries, Russia, 
Vietnam, and China.8 Unlike existing research, our paper pr ovides both aggregat e and firm-level 
evidence on the finance aspects of the Chinese economy, and examines why China differs from other countries studied in the strands of literature on law, institutions, finance, and economic growth. 
The rest of the paper is organized as fo llows. Section II compares Chinas legal and 
financial systems to other countries , as well as the growth in the St ate, Listed, and Private Sectors. 
Section III presents evidence on firms financing channels in China and other countries. Section 
IV examines the Listed Sector, including corpor ate governance, firms financing channels, payout 
policy, and valuations. In Section V we first pr ovide survey and anecdotal evidence on Private 
Sector firms, and then discuss the alternativ e financing channels and governance mechanisms. 
Finally we conclude in Section VI. Appendix A cont ains explanations of all the variables that we 
use in the paper, and Appendix B provides details of our empirical tests on the Listed Sector. 
II. Evidence on Chinas Legal and Financial Systems, and Growth in the Three Sectors 
8 See McMillian (1997), McMillan and Wood ruff (2002) for reviews of this literature. We discuss the difference 
between Chinas transition toward a market-based ec onomy to that of other countries in Section V. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>61</slideno>
          <text>Singapore (E) HK (E) 
) 
US (E) 
South Africa (E)
Japan (G)
) 
Thailand (E) 
) (G) 
)) Mexico(F) 
China UK (E) 
India (E) ) 
Indonesia (F) 
-4 -2 0 2 4 6 8 
10 12 14 16 18 20 22 24 26 
Investor Protection External MarketMalaysia (E
Taiwan (G
France (FGerman
Brazil (FArgentina (FPakistan (E
South Korea (G) percentage Figure 1 Comparison of Legal and Financial Systems 
60%
50%
40%
30%
20%
10%
0%
1994 1995 1996 1997 1998 1999 2000 2001 2002 
Calendar Yea r 
iState Budget Bank Loan 
Foreign Investment Fundra sing 
Figure 2-A Financing Sources for the Listed Sector 
61</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>and Strahan 1996). The third literature provides evidence for the li nk and causality between law, 
finance, and economic growth. For example, Levine (1999) finds that the legal environment 
contributes to the growth of financial intermediation, which in  turn stimulates the overall 
economic growth of a country.3 
However, many of the above studies are at count ry level, and they treat each country in 
their sample on an equal-weight basis. For example, among the countries in the LLSV (1998) 
sample, large diverse countries such as Brazil and India receive the same weight as small 
homogeneous countries like Jordan and Ecuador . We might expect that small homogeneous 
countries could have more effective legal system s because they can be closely tailored to the 
countries needs. Moreover, most  of the studies exclude one of  the most important developing 
countries in the world, China.4  In this paper, we demonstr ate that China is a significant 
counterexample to the findings of the existing lite rature on law, institutions, finance, and growth. 
Despite its poor legal and financial systems, Chin a has one of the fastest growing economies in the 
world. 5  Using Purchasing Power Parity (PPP) formulas, it already has the second largest 
economy, and will overtake the U.S. and b ecome the largest in the world in ten years. We examine 
three sectors of the Chinese economy: 1) the State Sector  includes all companies where the 
government has ultimate control (state-o wned enterprises, or SOEs); 2) the Listed Sector includes 
all firms that are listed on an exchan ge and are publicly traded; and 3) the Private Sector  that 
includes all the other firms w ith various types of private and local government ownership.6 We 
economic conditions (e.g., Hayek 1960, Posner 1973, Beck et al. 2003b), and religion and cultural beliefs (e.g., Greif 
1994, Stulz and Williamson 2003). 
3 In addition, Beck and Levine (2002) find evidence for manufacturing industries across 42 countries, while 
Demirguc-Kunt and Maksimovic (1998) find evidence at firm level. 
4 Some of the papers (e.g., DLLS 2002, 2003a, 2003b), do examine certain aspects of the Chinese economy or its legal 
system, but none of them provides a comprehensive st udy on China, nor a study on Chinas Private Sector. 
5 In 2003, despite the impact of the SARS epidemic, the expected growth rate of Chinas GDP is over 9%, the highest 
among the largest economies in world. See Wall Street Jour nal (01/21/2004) and Asian Development Bank for details. 
6 The Private Sector includes the following types of firms: 1) quasi-state-owned companies, namely, collectively- 
and jointly-owned companies, where joint ownership between the government and local communities or institutions is 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>64</slideno>
          <text>Equity Issuance 
0% 1% 2% 3% 4% 5% 6% 7% /Ta i 
i aIPO&amp;SEO GNP w a n 
Ko r e a 
Ch in a 
In d 
97019731976179182159881991199419720098 9 9 9 01 1
year 
Figure 3-C: Comparison of Equity Issuance  
0% 5% 
1970 1973 1976
1979 19821991972000 Ta i 
Ch i 
i a Comparison Growth in GDP 
-5 % 10 % 15 % 20 % 25 % 30 % 35 % 40 % 45 % 
1985 1988 1994 19
year Annual growth rate w a n 
Ko r e a 
n a 
In d 
Figure 3-D: Comparison of GNP growth rates   
(In all of the following graphs, the vertical axis repr esents the percentage of fi rms managers/founders who 
provide the same answer for a particular question in the survey.) 
64</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>36</slideno>
          <text>V.4 Discussion 
In this section we discuss mechanisms suppor ting the growth of the Private Sector. We 
believe the most important reason for the growth  is the work of alternative financing and 
governance mechanisms. How can these be underst ood?  First, Greif (1989, 1993) argues that 
certain traders orga nizations in the 11th century were able to overc ome problems of asymmetric 
information and the lack of legal and contra ct enforcement mechanisms, because they had 
developed institutions based on reputation, implic it contractual relations, and coalitions. Certain 
aspects of the growth of these institutions resemble what works in Chinas Private Sector today, in 
terms of how firms raise funds and contract with investors and business part ners. In addition, Greif 
(1994) and Stulz and Williamson (2002) point out th e importance of cultural and religious beliefs 
on the development of institutions, legal origins, and investor protections. These factors are of 
particular relevance and importance to Chinas development of institutions. Without a dominant 
religion, one can argue that the most important force in shaping Chinas social values and 
institutions is the set of beliefs  first developed and formalized by Kong Zi (Confucius). This set of 
beliefs clearly defines family and social orders, which are very different from the western beliefs on how legal codes should be formulated.
45 Throughout the paper we have presented evidence 
that reputation and relationships make many fina ncing channels and governance mechanisms work 
in Chinas Private Sector. 
Second, there are alternative co rporate governance mechanisms that have worked well in 
both developed and developing countries. First, Allen and Gale  (2000b) argue that competition  in 
product and input markets may be more effective th an either the US and UK system based on the 
threat of takeover, or the Japanese, Frenc h, and Germany system based on monitoring, while 
McMillan (1995, 1997) argues that competition and th e entry of non-state firms can facilitate the 
36</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>on the relation between legal system  and external markets, China is  placed close to the bottom left 
corner of the graph. 
Insert Figure 1 here. 
Finally, we briefly discuss Chin as venture capital markets. It is often argued that one of 
the reasons the US has been so successful in recent years in developing new industries is the 
existence of a strong venture capital sector.22  Allen and Gale (2000a) s uggest that venture capital 
should be thought of as closer to market financ e rather than intermediated finance, because 
venture capitalists can easily cash out by sell ing firms in the IPO market, which makes them 
willing to provide seed capital initially. Since its inception in the 1980s, Chinas venture capital 
industry has enjoyed fast growth, in particular since 1992. Cons istent with our previous findings, 
Chinas venture capital industry, measured by US st andards, is under-devel oped and its role in 
supporting the growth of young firms is very limite d. For example, based on interviews conducted 
with 36 venture capitalists in 24 venture companies, Bruton and Ahlstrom (2002) find that the 
limited formal rules and regulations  are often ineffective, while al ternative mechanisms based on 
reputation and relationship are the norm in all stages and phases of the industry.   
Banking Sector 
Chinas banking sector is dominated by four large and inefficient, state-owned banks. As 
reported in LLS (2002), the government owns an average of 99.45% of the 10 largest commercial 
banks in China as of 1995 (it was 100% in 1970), and this ownership level is one of the highest in 
their sample of 92 countries. Moreover, the LLS (2002) results on the negative relationship of 
government ownership of banks and the growth of a countrys economy seems to apply to Chinas 
(external cap/GNP, domestic firms/Pop, IPOs/Pop, Debt/GNP, and Log GNP) to the mean of all countries, with a 
positive (negative) figure indicating that this countr ys overall score is higher (lower) than the mean.  
22 For example, Kortum and Lerner (2000) have documented a strong relationship in the US between the extent to 
which venture capital is used in an industry and the rate of patenting. 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>60</slideno>
          <text>Table 8-C External Funding at Firm Level 
Country English origin French origin German Origin Scandinavian LLSV sample China 
average average average origin average average 
Market cap / sales 0.69 0.51 0.63 0.37 0.58 0.06 
Market cap / cash flow 5.16 3.85 7.48 3.25 4.77 0.52 
Debt / sales 0.26 0.27 0.3 0.28 0.27 0.67 
Debt / cash flow 2.01 2.06 3.18 2.42 2.24 5.34 
Sources: LLSV countries  WorldScope, and LLSV (1997); data for China is based on a panel of 7377 firm-year 
(1174 listed firms, 1992-2000) observations, with each ratio being the mean of the pooled panel of firms during the 
same time period.  
Table 9 Summary Statistics for Survey Firms 
The sample includes 17 firms, with one from Shanghai, 3 from Jiangsu Province, and 13 from Zhejiang Province. The 
Sample covers firms in the industry of Chemical product (3), Fabric making and printing (3), Metal Product (2), 
medical and health products (2), Realty management (2), Auto repairing (1),  Food processing (1), agriculture product processing (1), and Electronic products (1), handcraft and art products (1). (Note: some firms are in multiple business 
lines). The following table presents summary statistics for sample firms with informatio n ended as of Dec. 2002.
 mean min max Std.dev 
Age of the firm 11.4 3 27 6.7 
# of employees 1634.3 90 5552 2107.8 
Size (Total Assets in mil. US$) 55.3 0.6 337.3 82.7 
D/E ratio 2.1 0.38 14.95 3.4 
Net income (in mil. US$) 2.5 0.2 9.0 2.8 
Return on Assets 0.1 0.00 0.34 0.1 
60</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>44</slideno>
          <text>Accounting 
standards or a change in government economic and social priorities." Average of the months of April and October of the monthly index between 
1982 and 1995. Scale from zero to 10, with lower scores for higher 
risks 
Index created by examining and rating companies' 1990 annual 
reports on their inclusion or omission of 90 items. These items fall 
into seven categories (general in formation, income statements, 
balance sheets, funds flow statem ent, accounting standards, stock 
data, and special items). A minimum of three companies in each country was studied. The companies represent a cross section of 
various industry groups; industrial companies represented 70%, and 
financial companies represented the remaining 30% International 
accounting and 
auditing trends, 
Center for International 
Financial Analysis 
and Research 
Secondary source: LLSV(1997) 
A.2. Financial System Variables (Levin e 2002), used in Tables 3a and 3b 
Variables Definition Original Source 
Bank Credit  Ratio of Total Credit deposited into banks from private IFS, WDI and country 
sectors /GDP specific publications 
(Total) Value Traded Ratio of domestic equity traded on domestic exchanges /GDP  IFS, WDI, EMFB, and country specific publications 
Market Capitalization Ratio of domestic equities listed on domestic exchanges/GDP Intl Financial Statistics 
(IFS), World Development 
Indicators (WDI), Emerging Markets Factbook (EMFB), 
and country specific 
publications 
Overhead cost Overhead cost divided by Total Bank system assets Levines calculations (2002) 
Structure- Size Log(Market Capita lization/Bank Credit); measure size of Levine (2002) 
markets and banks 
Structure- Log(Value Traded/Bank Cred it); measure size/trading Levine (2002) 
Activity  volume of markets and banks 
Structure- Log(Market capitalization ratio*overhead cost ratio); Levine (2002) 
efficiency measures relative efficiency of markets vs. banks 
Structure 
Regulation Sum of the four categories in regulatory restriction. National regulatory 
authorities 
Regulatory 
Restriction The degree that commercial banks are allowed to engage in security, firm operation, insurance, and real estate. 1 National regulatory authorities 
unrestricted; 2-permit to conduct through subsidiary; 3-full 
range not permitted in subsidiaries; 4-strictly prohibited  
Finance size Log (market capitalization ratio * private credit ratio) Levine (2002) 
Finance-
Activity  Log (total value traded ratio* private credit ratio) Levine (2002) 
Finance- Log (total value traded ratio/overhead cost) Levine (2002)
Efficiency 
 Secondary source: Beck, Demirguc-Kunt and Levine (1999), and Levine (2002). 
44</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>various protection measures into the law, from wh ich we calculated the scores, one can argue that 
a more important measure for the status of the le gal system would be law enforcement. Table 2-C 
provides some evidence in this rega rd. It is important to  note that all the m easures, including those 
for China, are drawn from independent internati onal rating agencies. For two key categories of law 
enforcement, the rule of law and corrupti on, Chinas measures are significantly below all average 
measures of LLSV sample countries, regardless of  their legal origins. This suggests that the 
relatively high scores of creditor - and shareholder-protec tions of China in Tables 2-A and 2-B are 
not reliable. 
Insert Tables 2-C and 2-D here. 
We also compare Chinas legal system to ot her emerging countries, similar to the growth 
comparison in Table 1-B. From Table 2-D, we can see that Chinas corruption index is the worst 
among the seven developing countries, while its measur e of anti-director right s (creditor rights) is 
only higher than that of India and Mexico (Arg entina and Mexico). Hence the development of 
Chinas legal system is not ahead of any othe r major emerging economies, and it is clearly 
dominated by those that have E nglish common-law origin (India, Pakistan, and South Africa).   
In order to have an effective law enforcem ent system, a country must have a sufficient 
supply of qualified legal professionals. 12  By one estimate, there are currently 150,000 lawyers in 
China, roughly the same number of license d attorneys as in the state of California.13 Lawyers 
represent only 10% to 25% of all clients in civil and business cases, and even in criminal 
12 Djankov et al. (2003a, DLLS hereafte r) compare the efficiency and formal ism of the justice system across 109 
countries. Consistent with other LLSV findings, they find justice systems in common law countries are more efficient 
than civil law countries and in particular, developing co untries. The results are based on how two specific types of 
disputes, the eviction of a tenant and collection of a bounced  check, are resolved in a coun trys judicial system. China 
is included in the data, and its justice system actually ranks high relative to other socialist and developing countries. 
But these rankings are misleading since both types of disputes ar e rare events in China, as the real estate including the 
rental market as well as the market for the use of personal checks are under-developed, and limited in only a few large 
cities. 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>39</slideno>
          <text>our results that alternative mechanisms based on  reputation and relationships provide the most 
important support for the growth of the Private Sector. 
Finally, there is a strand of literature studyi ng transitional economies, such as Russia, 
China, and Eastern European countries, from Social ist systems to market systems. It is important 
to point out why China differs from other transi tional economies. First, with the exception of 
Russia, Chinas economy is much larger than ot her transitional economies. With a small economy, 
a country can adjust its legal a nd financial systems to the stre ngths of its economy much easier 
than what a large country can do. The recent econo mic struggle in Russia proves this point (e.g., 
Shleifer and Treisman 2000). The success of China s Private Sector demonstrates that alternative 
mechanisms can work wonders in large economies.  
Second, it is probably easier for other countries to adopt drastic reform measures in the 
short run, as the people are more ri sk tolerant toward regime shif ts. China, under the influence of 
the Confucius views, is different, in that people hold th e belief that fundamental changes in society 
should be gradual and only after they are proven correct or sens ible. Moreover, any such change 
should not shake the foundations of the societ y based on existing beliefs. Accordingly, China 
adopted a gradual, dual track pa th in its economic reform, in th at the continued enforcement of 
the existing planning system goes alongside with th e fast-paced development of financial markets, 
as compared to the big bang approach taken by other countries. The dual track system is 
equivalent to lump-sum transfers from the market sector to the planning sect or to achieve a Pareto 
improvement of the entire society, while its non-s tandard institutions suit this transition period 
because they provide incentives for economic agen ts to innovate and to compete and provide 
enough benefits to those in power so  that they do not preclude the reform process (e.g., Lau et al. 
2000, Qian 1999). 
39</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>57</slideno>
          <text>Table 5-B A Cross-Country Comparison of Banking System Profitability 
The profitability is measure as the return on average Eq uity (ROAE), and return on average Assets (ROAA). The 
latter is presented in the brackets. 
1997 1998 1999 2000 2001 2002 
China 6.6 (0.21) 4.0 (0.2) 3.2 (0.18) 3.9 (0.21) 3.5 (0.21) 4.16(0.21) 
Hong Kong 
India 18.7 (1.8) 17.0 (0.9) 11.0 (1.0) 
9.7 (0.5) 18.2 (1.6) 
14.2 (0.7) 18.8 (1.6) 
10.9 (0.5) 15.7 (1.4) 
19.2 (0.9) 15.6(1.4) 
19.6(1) 
Indonesia -3.8 (-0.3) n/a n/a 15.9 (0.3) 9.7 (0.6) 21.1(1.4) 
Japan 
South Korea -18.6 (-0.6) 
-12.5 (-0.6) -19.2 (-0.7) 
-80.4 (-3.0) 2.7 (0.1) 
-34 (-1.5) -0.7 (0) 
-7 (-0.3) -10.4 (-0.5) 
15.8 (0.7) -14.5(-0.6) 
13.1(0.6) 
Taiwan 11.2 (0.9) 9.5 (0.8) 6.9 (0.6) 5.1 (0.4) 4.0 (0.3) -5.2(-0.4) 
Source: The Asian Banker data center 2003, http://www.thesianbanker.com.  
Table 6-A Growth Rates of the Stat e and Listed Sectors and Sundry Sector 
In this table, Panel A displays the growth rate of industr ial output for the two sectors in China. The state and Listed 
Sectors includes state-owne d and publicly traded compan ies where the government holds controlling shares.  The 
Sundry Sector consists of firms with all other types of owne rship structures. Data source for this table is the Chinese 
Statistical Yearbook 2000, 2001, 2002, and 2003. For each sector, we also calculated th e weighted average growth 
rate across the selected ownership types. Panel B displays th e average growth rate of inv estment in fixed assets for 
the two sectors. 
Growth rate  Panel A: Industrial Output Panel B: Investment in Fixed Assets 
(%)
Year State &amp; Listed Private State &amp; Listed Private 
Sectors Sector Sectors Sector* 
1996 15.9 17.4 10.2 17.3 
1997 -0.6 18.9 9.0 6.1 
1998 -6.5 10.2 17.4 9.0 
1999 5.8 6.8 3.8 7.5 
2000 14.0 24.2 3.5 11.4 
2001 4.6 9.9 6.7 12.6 
2002 6.5 12.5 7.2 16.8 
Ave. Annual rate (95- 02) 
5.4 14.3 8.2 11.5 
Notes: * - includes foreign-owned companies, companie s owned by investors from Taiwan and Hong Kong, and  
TVEs; Sources: China Statistic Yearbooks 2000 - 2003. 
Table 6-B Employment in the Formal and Sundry Sectors 
1995 1996 1997 1998 1999 2000  2001 2002 95-02 annual 
Year 
Panel A: Number of Employees (million)* growth rate 
State &amp; Listed 115 116 115 94 89 85 81 77 -5.7% 
Sectors 
Private Sector 221 233 233 235 240 233 245 246 1.5% 
State &amp; Listed Panel B: Percentage of total employees belonging to each sector (%) 
34.3 33.3 33.0 28.7 27.2 26.8 24.9 23.8 
Sectors 
Private Sector 65.7 66.7 67.0 71.3 72.8 73.2 75.1 76.2 
Note: * - indicate non-agricultural employees; source: China Statistic Yearbooks 2000 - 2003. 
57</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>54</slideno>
          <text>Table 2-A A Comparison of Creditor Rights: China and LLSV Countries 
Country  English- French- German- Scandinavian- LLSV China 
origin origin origin origin average sample 
average average average average 
No automatic stay on assets 0.72 0.26 0.67 0.25 0.49 0 
Secured creditors first paid 0.89 0.65 1 1 0.81 0 
Restrictions for going into reorganization 0.72 0.42 0.33 0.75 0.55 1 
Management does not stay in reorganization 0.78 0.26 0.33 0 0.45 1 
(Overall) Creditor rights* 3.11 
(78%)# 1.58 
(53%)# 2.33 
(83%)# 2 
(75%)# 2.3 
(68%)# 2 
Legal reserve required as a % of capital 0.01 0.21 0.41 0.16 0.15 0 
Notes: *: equals the sum of the scores of the four categories above, where 1 = Creditor Protection is in the Law, and 
0 otherwise ; #: numbers in the bracket indicate percentage of countries in the sub-sample whose measure is higher 
or equal to 2 (Chinas overall measure). 
Source: China   Bankruptcy Law of China (2000); LLSV countries  LLSV JPE paper 
Table 2-B A Comparison of Shareholder Rights 
Country  English- French- German- Scandinavian- LLSV China 
origin origin origin origin sample 
average Average Average Average average 
One share  one vote 0.17 0.29 0.33 0 0.22 1 
Proxy by mail Allowed 0.39 0.05 0 0.25 0.18 0 
Shares Not Blocked before meeting 1 0.57 0.17 1 0.71 0 
Cumulative Voting/ Proportional 0.28 0.29 0.3 0 0.27 0 
Representation 
Oppressed Minority 0.94 0.29 0.5 0 0.53 1 
Preemptive Right to New Issue 0.44 0.62 0.33 0.75 0.53 1 
Percentage of Share Capital to call an 0.09 0.15 0.05 0.1 0.11 0.1 
Extraordinary Shareholder Meeting 
Antidirector Rights* 4 
(94%)# 2.33 
(45%)# 2.33 
(33%)# 3 
(75%)# 3 
(65%)# 3 
Mandatory Dividend 0 0.11 0 0 0.05 0 
Notes: * is the sum of the scores on Rows (2), (3), (4), (5), and (7), where, score =1, when the protection is in the 
law; 0 otherwise.  #: Numbers in the bracket indicate percentage  of countries in the sub-sample whose 
measure is higher or equal to 3 (Chinas overall measure). 
Source: China  Company Law and Commercial Codes of China (2000); LLSV countries  JPE paper 
Table 2-C A Comparison of Law Enforcement 
Country  English French- German Scandinavian LLSV China 
Origin Origin origin origin sample 
average average average average average 
Efficiency of Judicial System 8.15 6.56 8.54 10 7.67 N/a 
Rule of law 6.46 6.05 8.68 10 6.85 5 
Corruption 7.06 5.84 8.03 10 6.9 2 
Risk of Expropriation 7.91 7.46 9.45 9.66 8.05 N/a 
Risk of contract Repudiation 7.41 6.84 9.47 9.44 7.58 N/a 
Accounting rating on Accounting Standards 69.62 51.17 62.67 74 60.93 N/a 
Source: China  International country risk (rating agency); LLSV countries  same as above 
54</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>The external corporate governance mechanisms  are also limited and weak. First, the 
existing ownership structure, ch aracterized by cross-holdings of  shares among listed companies 
and institutions, makes hostile take overs virtually impossible. Secondly, institutional investors do 
not have a strong influence on management or on the stock market. Open-end funds are a very 
recent addition to the set of financial institutions in  China. As for information disclosure, there is a 
lack of qualified accounting and auditing profes sionals as pointed out earlier. Moreover, 
ineffective bankruptcy implementation makes the threat and penalty for bad firm performance 
non-credible.36 
Finally, the government plays th e dual roles of regulator and blockholder of many listed 
firms. The China Securities Regulation Committee (C SRC) is the counterpart of the SEC in the 
US, and its main role is to monitor and regulate stock exchanges and listed companies. While the 
government exercises their shareholder control ri ghts in listed firms ma inly through state-owned 
asset management companies, which hold large fract ions of the state shares. However, since the 
top officials of these asset management comp anies are elected by the government, it is doubtful 
that they will pursue their fiduciary role as control shareholders di ligently. Moreover, the 
governments dual roles can lead to conflicting goals in dealing with  listed firms, which in turn 
weakens the effectiveness of both of its roles. 
IV.3 Evidence on Ownership, Financing, Dividend and Valuation 
In this section, we examine and compare vari ous characteristics of listed firms in China 
with those of other countries. Our results on Chinas Listed Sector are based a sample (panel data) 
of more than 1100 listed firms that we collect ed from SHSE and SZSE, for the period of 1992
36 Cross-country information on the efficiency in bankruptcy procedure, based on survey of lawyers and bankruptcy 
judges around the world, is available from World Bank (http://rru.worldbank.org/Doingbusiness ). Among 108 
countries, Chinas goals of insolvency index is equal to the median of the sample.    
26</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>37</slideno>
          <text>transition to market-based economies for emerging  economies. What we see from the success and 
life cycles of Private Sector firms in WenZhou a nd other surveyed firms s uggest that it is only 
those firms that have the strongest  comparative advantage in an indus try (of the area) that survived 
and thrived. Second, Gomes (2000) demonstrates that a managerial reputation effect can replace 
formal governance in an IPO firm. Evidence from  the Chinese venture capital industry (Bruton 
and Ahlstrom 2002) supports this view. Third, Bu rkart, Panunzi, and Sh leifer (2002) link the 
degree of separation of ownership and control to different lega l environments, and show that 
family-run firms  will emerge as the dominant form of ow nership structure in countries with weak 
minority shareholder protections, whereas professi onally managed firms must be the optimal form 
in countries with strong invest or protection.  Evidence in Clae ssens, Djankov and Lang (2000) and 
Claessens et al. (2002) suggests that family-owned firms with  very high concentration of 
ownership is the norm in many Asian countries outside China and these firms have performed 
well. Based on our survey evidence, as well as empi rical results on the Listed Sector, family firms 
are a norm in both the Listed and Private Sectors in  China, consistent with findings in listed firms 
in other Asian countries. Fourth, Allen and Gale (2000a) show that  if cooperation among different 
suppliers of inputs is necessary and all supplie rs benefit from the firm doing well then a good 
equilibrium with no external governance is possible,  as internal, mutual mo nitoring can ensure the 
optimal outcome.46  We have shown trade credits to be an  important form of financing source for 
firms during their growth period.  Finally, the common goal of sharing high prospective profits 
can tie local and foreign investors with entrep reneurs and managers to overcome numerous 
obstacles and achieve just that. Under this common goal in a multi-pe riod setting, implicit 
contractual agreements and reput ation can act as enforcement m echanisms to ensure that all 
45 Also see Orts (2001) and Chapters 1, 19, and 20 in Chow (2002). 
46 Allen and Gale (2000b) point out that the success and growth of the non-profit organizations in developed countries 
such as the US is a good example of how altern ative corporate governance systems can work well. 
37</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>52</slideno>
          <text>50. ____, and Christopher Woodruff, 1999a. Interfirm Re lationships and Informal Credit in Vietnam, 
Quarterly Journal of Economics , 114, 1285-1320. 
51. ____, and ____, 1999b. Dispute Prevention without Courts in Vietnam, Journal of Law, 
Economics, and Organization  15, Oct. 1999, 637-658. 
52. ____, and ____, 2002. The Ce ntral Role of Entrepreneurs in Transition Economies, Journal of 
Economic Perspectives  16, 153-70. 
53. Morck, Randall, Bernard Yeung, and Wayne Yu , 2000. The Information Content of Stock 
Markets: Why do Emerging Markets Have Synchronous Stock Price Movement, Journal of 
Financial Economics , 58 (1), 215-260.  
54. Naughton, Barry, 1995. Growing Out of the Plan : Chinese Economic Reform, 1978-1993 , 
Cambridge University Press,  
55. Orts, Eric, 2001. The Rule of Law in China, Vanderbilt Journal of Transitional Law , Vol. 34 (1), 
43-115. 
56. Posner, Richard A., 1973. Economic Analysis of the Law , Little-Brown, Boston, MA. 
57. Qian, Yingyi, 1999. The Institu tional Foundations of Chinas Market Transition, working paper, 
Stanford University. 
58. Rajan, Raghuram, and Luigi Zingales, 1998.  Financial Dependence and Growth, American 
Economic Review  88, 559-87. 
59. Schipani, Cindy, and Junhai Liu, 2002. Corporate Governance in China: Then and Now, 
Columbia Business Law Review , Vol. 2002, 1-69. 
60. Shleifer, Andrei, and Daniel Treisman, 2000. Without a Map: Political Tactics and Economic 
Reform in Russia, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.  
61. Stulz, Rene, and Rohan Williamson, 2002. Culture, openness, and finance, forthcoming, Journal 
of Financial Economics . 
62. Tadesse, Solomon, 2001. Financial Architect ure and Economic Performance: International 
Evidence, working paper, University of South Carolina 
63. Tenev, Stoyan, Chunlin Zhang, and Loup Brefort, 2002. Corporate Governance and Enterprise 
Reform in China, Building th e institutions of Modern Market , World Bank, IFC. 
64. Tian, George Lihui, 2001. State Shareholding and the Value of Chinas Firms, working paper, 
London Business School. 
65. Xiang, Bing, 1998. Institutional factors influenc ing Chinas accounting reforms and standards, 
Accounting Horizons  12 (2), 105-119. 
52</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>47</slideno>
          <text>Appendix B Empirical Tests on Listed  Firms in China and Other Countries 
Data: We have firm level accounting and security market data for all the listed firms in Ch ina (panel data set of 1174 
firms, 1992-2000 period, total of 7377 observations). We compare these Chinese firms with those studied in LLSV 
(2000, 2002; 4103 firms from 33 countries, 1989-1994 period). We do not have detailed firm level data for LLSV 
samples, but we do have: 1) the cross-sectional summary statistics by country; 2) th e regression results across 
countries. We examine dividend policy and firm valuations, and our empirical models and results are presented below. 
Method 1: Synthetic firm approach: 
Step1:  Using the summary statistics from LLSV samples, we create a synthetic firm for each of the 33 countries. 
For this synthetic firm, each firm characteristic is equal to the median  of the same variable across all the firms in that 
country. Following the same procedure, a synthetic firm is also created for China based on the information of 1100+ 
firms.  
Step2:  Three OLS regressions are run on the 33 (LLSV countr ies) synthetic observations. The dependent variables 
in these tests are: 1) dividend/earnings ratio, 2) dividend/sales ratio, and 3) Tobins q (measured by market to book 
assets ratio). The independent variables are the same ones used in LLSV (2000, 2002). Ba sed on the results from each 
of the 3 regressions, we then conduct an out-of-sample prediction for China using the estimated coefficients and 
variances.  Step3:  Compare the true (observed) firm characteristics of the Chin ese synthetic firm to those predicted values 
from Step 2, and see whether the true value falls in the boundaries of predicted values. 
The following table presents th e coefficients estimates, t ratios, prediction, and boundaries from the regression on 33 
synthetic firms, and empirical value from Chinese firms in sample. 
y: Div/Earn y: Div/Sales y: Tobin's q 
intercept 42.44 1.30 intercept -0.58 
 (3.79*) (0.64) (-0.58 ) 
Civil law dummy 3.42 
(0.33) -1.06 
(-0.56 ) Growth in sales 0.00 
(0.17) 
Low protection -9.09 1.57 Common law 0.30 
 (-0.91 ) (0.86) (0.30) 
GS 0.47 
(0.72) 0.16 
(1.36) Anti-director rights 0.65 
(1.81*) 
GS*civil law -1.12 0.00 CF rights 5.87 
 (-1.18 ) (0.00) (1.89*) 
GS*Low Protection 0.86 
 (0.89) -0.20 
(-1.13 ) CF rights*common Law -0.52 
(-0.15) 
Div tax advantage -10.54 0.25 CF rights*anti-director -2.12 
(-0.85 ) (0.11) (-1.78* ) 
R square # of observations 0.16 
33 0.09 
33 R square 
# of observations 0.39 
27 
Predicted values for China 57.14 ~161.07 - 8.82 Predicted values for China 0.57 
(lower and upper bounds)  ~10.19 (lower and upper bounds) ~ 1.86 
Observed ratio from China 30.23 2.35 Observed ratio for China 1.22 
Method 2: Alpha approach 
Utilizing the alpha notation from assets pricing models, we want to see how much of the variations in the dependent variables are NOT explained by the independent variables. There are two versions of this model: restricted and 
unrestricted, depending on wh ether we restrict the coefficients on each independent variable to be the same for 
Chinese firms and for firms in other countries.   
Method 2 - Restricted Model  
Step1: For Chinese firms, we run re gressions according to: y = alpha(China) + gamma*Z + e, where y is the actual 
value of Tobins q, or dividend payout ratio. Z is a vector of firm characteristics.  
47</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>NPLs and liquidating them.24  Second, state-owned banks have improved their loan structure by 
increasing loans made to individual lenders while being more active in risk management and 
monitoring of loans made to SOEs.25  Third, there has been a boom in the entry and growth of 
non-state financial intermediaries within the banking system. For example, in 1997, total new 
loans made by the four largest state-owned banks accounted for more than 75% of all new loans, 
while new loans made by shareholding banks accounted for less than 7%.26 In 2001 the share of 
new loans made by state-owned banks dropped to 49% while the fraction of new loans made by 
shareholding banks rose to 23.5%. This trend is expected to continue wi th more foreign banks 
entering the domestic credit markets in the near future as a result of Chinas entrance into the WTO. All the above facts taken together can expl ain why NPLs have been falling in recent years, 
as shown in Table 5-A. 
To summarize, the continuing effort of refo rming and improving the banking system is one 
of the most important tasks for China in the near future. In fact, China recently announced that its 
central bank will inject foreign currency reserves, in the amount of US$85 billion, into 2 of the big 
4 state-owned banks, to improve their balance sh eets and enhance the likelihood that these banks 
can go public by the end of 2004. Similar fund inject ion plans for the other 2 state-owned banks 
are also in the works.27  Given that Chinas total foreign exchange reserve is US$400 billion while 
the total amount of NPLs as of 2002 is 15% of GDP, or US$188 billion using the US$1 = 8.26 
RMB exchange rate, the foreign reserve itself shoul d be more than enough to rid the NPLs off the 
24 Information from auction data shows that the cash recovery on some of the loans ranges from 8% to 60%. Details 
on these Asset Management companies (including the auctions of NPLs), are available from the authors upon request. 
25 For example, the ratio of consumer lending to total loans made for the four state-owned banks increased from 1% in 
1998 to 10% in 2002. Moreover, mortgage lending by the Industrial and Commercial Bank of China, the largest bank 
in China, had grown by 32 times during the 1998-2002 period. The source for the above data is The Almanac of 
Finance and Banking in China (2001 and 2002), and The Economist, January 2003 (pp. 68). 
26 Owners for these shareholding banks include local government, foreign banks, and individuals. Most of these banks 
are not publicly listed and traded. 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>I. Introduction 
Several related strands of lit erature on law, institutions, finance, and economic growth 
have emerged in financial economics in recent year s, and their impact on other areas of research 
has been significant. First, La Porta, Lopez- de-Silanes, Shleifer, Vishny (LLSV hereafter) and 
others have produced a substantial body of empirical eviden ce that links the origin of a countrys 
legal system to the countrys institutions a nd financial and economic outcomes. One of the 
central results of this literature is that, count ries with English common-law origin (French civil 
law origin) provide the strongest (weakest) legal protections to both shareholders and creditors 
(LLSV 1998, 2000a). Countries with E nglish origin also seem to have  better institutions, including 
less corrupt governments (LLSV 1999), more effici ent courts (Djankov et al., DLLS hereafter, 
2003a), and more informative accounting standa rds (LLSV 1998). Better legal protections and 
better institutions, in turn, seem to lead to bett er outcomes for the financial system, both at the 
aggregate and firm levels.1 Related to the LLSV results, there is a recent literature attempting to 
understand why and how a countrys legal origin a ffects the countrys institutions, and how legal 
origin and institutions, both jointly and separately, affect economic and financial outcomes.2 
The second literature champions the view that the development of the financial system that 
includes a stock market and intermediation, contri butes to a countrys ov erall economic growth 
(e.g., McKinnon 1973).  Recently, researchers have  strengthened this view by presenting 
supporting empirical evidence at the country-l evel (e.g., King and Le vine 1993, Levine and 
Zervos 1998), as well as at the industry- and firm-levels (e.g., Rajan and Zingales 1998, Jayaratne 
1 For example, relative to firms in French-origin countries, firms in English-origin countries have more dispersed 
shareholder ownership (LLS 1999), rely more on external capital markets to raise funds (LLSV 1997), have higher 
values (LLSV 2002), and can enter a new market or industry more easily (DLLS 2002). 
2 Endeavors by researchers include examining the difference between contracting institutions and property rights 
institutions (e.g., Acemoglu and Johnson 2003), the endowm ent of geography and disease environment in former 
colonial countries (e.g., Acemoglu et al. 2001, 2002, Beck et al. 2003a), the legal systems ability to adapt to evolving 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>IV.2 Corporate Governance35 
Listed firms in China have a two-tier board st ructure: the Board of Directors and the Board 
of Supervisors. The Board of Supervisors is a mixture of the German-style supervisory committee 
and Chinas socialist regime in which employees ar e also owners of the enterprises. In recent 
years there is a trend of modeling listed firms board structure afte r that of US corporations. The 
supervisors of a listed firm are usually either officials chosen from government branches, or 
executives from the parent companies. Though they ar e at the top of the firms hierarchy, they are, 
most of the time, supervisors by name only. For example, they are usually pa id less than the firms 
directors, who rank below them. The Board of Di rectors is controlled by the firms parent 
companies. As shown in Table 7-B above, not a ll directors are elected by the shareholders. The 
rest of them are nominated and appointed by the firms parent companies and the nomination 
process is usually kept secret. Most of the directors are well e ducated, with 60% of them holding 
graduate or equivalent degrees. However, incentive pay is rarely explicitly specified in the 
directors compensation packages, but a large fraction of non-pecuniary payments, including perks such as company cars and subsid ized housing, can be linked to fi rm performance. Since the two-
tier board system consists of memb ers who are not voted in by the sh areholders, it is unlikely that 
this board structure can effec tively monitor firms managers, because the goals of board and 
supervisory members are not congruent with each other or with those of the shareholders. Some 
listed firms do not convene regular board meetings , and some directors do not take the meeting 
rules and their fiduciary duties seriously. In some  corporations, directors act as managers or 
executives, and the excessive overlap in these positions causes corruption. 
Market, published by the World Bank in 2002, which provides more detailed information on the ownership and 
control structure. 
35 Information presented in this section is based on Corpor ate Governance and Enterprise Reform in China: Building 
the institutions of Modern Market (World Bank, 2002), and Schipani and Liu (2002). 
25</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>2000.37  Table 8-A presents the summary statics of a snapshot of the sample firms at the end of 
2000: the average market cap is US$ 448 milli on (median is US$ 355 million), the average 
leverage ratio, measured by the ratio of long-term debt and co mmon equity, is 32% (median is 
9%). In short, these are large firm s operating in virtually all industries. 
Table 8-B compares the ownership structure of these firms to those from LLS (1999) 
sample, which includes over 1000 listed companie s from 33 countries. The main result of LLS 
(1999) is that countries that pr otect minority shareholders poorly  (strongly) tend to have more 
concentrated (dispersed) ownership, as shown in the first two panels of Table 8-B. Consistent with 
the prediction from Burkart et al . (2003), Claessens et al. (2000) show that family firm is the 
dominant form of ownership structure in Asia, wh ere the protections of mi nority shareholders are 
in general weak. In the last row of Table 8-B, th e ownership structure of listed firms in China is 
closer to that of other Asian firms documented in Claessens et al. ( 2000), than to LLS (1999) 
results. First, consistent with our previous evidence on ownership structure, the dominant owner of 
60% of our sample firms is the (central) gover nment. Second, for 13.6% of firms the dominant 
owner is founders families, while only 0.44% of a ll firms are widely held, so that no shareholder 
owns more than 10% of stocks. Third, for 24.17% ( 1.83%) of firms, the domi nant shareholder is a 
financial company (another listed firm).38 
Table 8-C provides some evidence on financing s ources at the firm level. The ratios for all 
the countries (except for China) in the table are take n from LLSV (1997). In LLSV (1997), a ratio 
(e.g., market cap/sales) for a country is obtained by first finding the median of this ratio (market 
cap/sales) across firms within various industries of  that country, and then by taking the average of 
37 These data sets are available from  Asia Emerging Market Data Bas e of the Taiwan Economic Journal 
(http://www.tei.com.tw/main.html ).
38 Since we do not have ownership data for this financial company (listed firm), we do not know whether this 
company (listed firm) is widely held or not. But given the fact that state-ownership is prevalent in listed firms and 
banks, it is reasonable to assume that they are not widely held. 
27</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>1996 they contributed 15.5% of tota l industrial output, and the above  trend of the Private Sector 
replacing the State Sector will continue in the near future.   
Insert Tables 6-A and 6-B here. 
Table 6-B presents the number  of non-agricultural employees  in the three sectors. The 
Private Sector is a much more important sour ce for employment opportunities than the other 
sectors. Over the period from 1995 to 2002, the Priv ate Sector employs an average of over 70% of 
all non-agricultural workers, while the TVEs (a ty pe of Private Sector firm) are by far the most 
important employer for workers from the rural areas.  Moreover, the number of employees 
working in the Private Sector has been growi ng at 1.5% over this seve n-year period, while the 
labor force in the State Sector has been shrinkin g. These patterns are particularly important for 
China, given its vast population and potential problem of unemployment. 
III. Firms Financing Sources: Aggregate Evidence and Cross-country Comparisons 
In this section we compare, at  the aggregate level, how firm s raise funds in China and in 
LLSV sample countries with the emphasis on emergi ng economies. It is wort hwhile then to study 
what other channels of financi ng are playing the role of substi tuting for external capital markets 
and standard, textbook financing channels. 
III.1  Chinas Most Important Financing Channels
The four most important financing sources for a ll firms in China, in terms of fixed assets 
investments, are: (domestic) bank loans, firms self-fundraising (or fundraising for short), state 
budget, and foreign direct investment.31  By far the two most important sources of financing 
channels are self-fundraising and bank loans. Consistent with previous evidence on Chinas 
31 Detailed information on all the financing channels is available from the Almanac of Chinas finance and banking 
(2000-2003), and from the authors upon request. 
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>55</slideno>
          <text>Table 2-D A Comparison of Legal Systems: China and other Major Emerging Economies 
Efficiency 
of Judicial 
System Rule 
of law Corruption Anti-director 
Rights One 
share 
one vote Creditor 
rights Accounting Standards 
China na 5 2 3 1 2 na 
India (E) 8 4.17 4.58 2 0 4 57 
Pakistan (E) 5 3.03 2.98 4 1 4 na 
S. Africa (E) 6 4.42 8.92 4 0 4 70 
Argentina (F) 6 5.35 6.02 4 0 1 45 
Brazil (F) 5.75 6.32 6.32 3 1 2 54 
Mexico (F) 6 5.35 4.77 0 0 0 60 
Source: China  International country risk (rating agency); all other countries  from LLSV sources; E (F) 
denotes the legal origin of the country is the En glish common-law system (French civil-law system). 
Table 3 A Comparison of Financial Sy stems: Bank- vs. Market-based Measures  
(Value-weighted approach) 
Measures English 
Origin* French Origin
* German Origin
* Scandinavian origin 
* Sample average China 
Bank and Market size Bank credit/GDP 0.62 0.55  0.99 0.49 0.73 1.11 
(0.24) a 
Overhead Cost/Bank 0.04 0.05 0.02 0.03 0.03 0.12 
Total Assets 
Total value 0.31 0.07 0.37 0.08 0.27 0.11 
traded/GDP 
Market 0.58 0.18 0.55 0.25 0.47 0.32 
Capitalization/GDP 
Structure Indices: Markets vs. banks
** Structure Activity -0.76 -2.03 -1.14 -1.83 -1.19 -1.07 
(0.46) a 
Structure Size -0.10 -1.05 -0.77 -0.69 -0.55 -1.24 
(0.29) a 
Structure Efficiency -4.69 -6.00 -5.17 -6.17 -5.17 -1.48 
(-3.07) 
Structure aggregate 1.21 -0.05 0.66 0.13 0.72 N/A 
Structure regulatory 7.02 8.21 10.15 7.72 8.95 16 
Finance activity Financial Development -1.18 -3.38 -0.84 -2.86 -1.58 -0.85 
(Banking and market (-2.38) 
sectors) Finance size 5.10 4.29 5.22 4.60 4.95 -1.02 
(-2.55) a 
Finance efficiency 2.18 0.44 2.85 1.04 2.01 -0.60 
(1.14) 
Finance aggregate 1.23 0.13 1.47 0.48 1.05 N/A 
Notes: All the measures for countries other than China are taken from Levine (2002); measures on China (in Tables 
3a and 3b) are calculated using definitions from Levine (2002) (see Appendix for list of definitions) 
*: the numerical results for countries of each legal orig in group is calculated based on a value- (GDP of each 
country) weighted approach; 
**: Measuring whether a countrys financial system is ma rket- or bank-dominated, the higher the measure, the more 
the system is dominated by markets; a: numbers in bracket indicate bank cr edit issued to only private sectors 
(instead of total bank credit); 
Sources: Almanac of Chinas Finance and Banking (2000); China Statistical Yearbook (2000) 
55</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>66</slideno>
          <text>i
ily VC pri
it ic 
Chi FDI 
0% ( ) 
VC FDI iPr i
l l 
iic 
Chi
0% 10% 20% 30% Start-up financing 
Banks 
Others Fr ends 
Founder 
/famvate 
cred
 agent Ethn
nese 
10% 20% 30% 40% 50% Financing in growth period years 3-8
Others Fr ends v ate 
Credit Agent 
State/ oca
Budget Trade 
Cred ts Ethn
nese 
Figure 4-B Financing Ch annels of Survey Firms 
i
 li ly 
ible ible 
0% ic l in 
vri
Legal /ion in 
i
0% 10% 20% 30% 40% 50% 60% 70% 80% 90% Possibility of assets being acqu red 
Very ke
not possposs
10% 20% 30% 40% 50% 60% 70% Concerns following the failure of firm 
Econom oss 
ous sense 
Safety 
consequence Reputat
var ous sense 100% 
0% 10% 20% 30% 40% 50% 
partially support, 
demanded sharing no 
relationship Relationship with local government 
Government 
invest/own return not demand profit 
Figure 4-C Governance Mechanisms of Survey Firms 
66</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>startup and current status, the two dominant forms are founder and family, and shareholding 
(resembles a private equity structure), while partne rship is not a widely used ownership structure. 
Third, about 35% of the founders of our sample firms worked in TVEs prior to starting up their 
own firms, while 23% (18%) of the founders wo rked in SOEs (government agencies). The 
experience from the State Sector or other Private S ector firms is valuable for these entrepreneurs, 
as they gained knowledge on how to run a private firm and/or deal with government officials. 
Financing Channels 
Figure 4-B presents evidence of financing channe ls of the firms. First, it is not surprising 
that during the startup stage, funds from founders  family and friends are important source of 
financing. Moreover, funds from friends, in the fo rm of private loans and equity, are also very 
important during the firms subsequent growth pe riod (top right histogram in Figure 4-B). Second, 
funding from financial intermediaries is probabl y the most important source for the surveyed 
firms: over 40% of firms surveyed regard banks as either a very importa nt (25-50% of funding) 
or an extremely important (more than 50% of total funding) financing source. This evidence 
again highlights the importance of the banking se ctor in China. Among financial intermediaries, 
the four largest state-owned banks  are ranked the highest in terms of providing funds, while other 
state-owned banks are ranked second . However, it is not clear that  state-owned banks provide the 
cheapest, most convenient start-up financing channe l for all Private Sector firms. The important 
caveat here is that for almost all the surveyed  firms that received star t-up financing from state-
owned banks had already establishe d close relationship with those banks before the inception of 
the firms. This is possible because these firms originated by spinning off from state-owned or 
Europe), and McMillan and Woodruff (1999a, 1999b, survey done in Vietna m on trade credits and resolution of 
disputes). 
30</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>most important benefits, and disclosure of valuab le information to competitors and outsiders and 
large amount of fees paid as the most critical disadvantages of going public.    
Secondly, despite the almost non-existence of  formal governance mechanisms, alternative 
mechanisms have been remarkably effective in the Private Sector. Perhaps the most important of 
these is the role of reputati on and relationships (Greif 1989, 1993) . Another important mechanism 
that drives good management and corporate gove rnance is competition. Given the environment of 
low survivorship during early stag es of firms development, gain ing comparative advantage in the 
region and the industry provides a strong incentive for all firms. Family-run firms also provide 
effective governance (Burkart et al. 2003), as the founders of many successful Private Sector firms usually have a very high ownership stake. Fina lly, in anticipating the possible loss of their 
investment due to the failure of the firm, poor fo rmal investor protections, political risks, and 
corrupt government officials, why are investors, in particular investors from Taiwan, Hong Kong 
and other countries, willing to fi nance and refinance these firms? An important reason is the 
common goal of sharing high prospective profits  can tie local and foreign investors with 
entrepreneurs and managers to overcome numerous  obstacles and achieve just that. Under this 
common goal in a multi-period se tting, implicit contractual agreem ents and reputation can act as 
enforcement mechanisms to ensure that all partie s fulfill their roles to make the firm successful. 
Profit sharing also makes it incentive compatible for officials at various levels to support the 
growth of the firm. 
Our results on the difference between the three sectors in China challenge the law and 
finance view that it is the legal origin that cau ses the difference in financial systems, the finance 
and growth view that it is the development of stock markets and banking system that causes the 
difference in growth of firms and economies, as well as the view supporting the law-finance-
growth nexus. Moreover, the succe ss of the Private Sector in China also challenges the view that 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>prosecutions they represent defendants in only ha lf of the cases.  Among the approximately five 
million business enterprises in China, only 4% of them currently have regular legal advisers.  
Moreover, only one-fifth of all lawyers in Chin a have law degrees, and ev en a lower fraction of 
judges have formally studied law at  a university or college.  Needless to say, it will be a long time 
before China has a strong legal labor force.  A nother reason that many of the new laws will not be 
effectively enforced in China is the intrinsic conf lict of interests between fair play in practicing 
law and the monopoly power of th e single ruling party, especial ly in cases where government 
officials or their affiliates ar e involved.  Fortunately for inve stors and entrepreneurs, some 
independent judicial authority seems to be  evolving in the area of business law. 
Finally, we comment on the current st atus of Chinas accounting system.14 The reform 
started in 1992, with the enact ment of regulations governing the enterprises with foreign 
investment, which provided the necessary accoun ting infrastructure to assist companies in 
attracting foreign direct investment.  The ASBE  (Accounting Standards for Business Enterprises) 
of China, together with the 13-industry regulat ion board, have been trying to move Chinas 
accounting practice in the Listed Sector toward the IAS (Internat ional Accounting Standards).  
However, the most glaring problem in Chinas accounting system is the lack of independent, 
professional auditors, similar to the situation of legal professiona ls. This implies that the proposed 
IAS-based standards may be count erproductive within Chinas curr ent infrastructure: with few 
auditors understanding the new stan dards and enforcing them, and the lack of an effective judicial 
system, embezzlement of companys assets and frauds may occur more frequently under IAS
13 Information presented here is from Orts (2001). In addition, from the official website of Ministry of Justice of China 
(in Chinese: http://www.legalinfo.gov.cn/gb/moj/introduce.htm ), there are about 110,000 lawyers and 9,000 law firms 
in China as of 2002. 
14 See Xiang (1998) for more information. We thank Arnold Wright and Mohamed Hussein for pointing out this 
source to us. 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>53</slideno>
          <text>Table 1-A Comparison of China and LLSV Countries: GDP and Growth* 
China vs. LLSV Sample Countries* 
GDP in 2002 GDP in 2002 using PPP** Average Annual Growth Rate of 
GDP using PPP (1990-2002) 
Rank Country GDP (US$ 
Bil.) Country GDP (Intl 
$ Billion) Country/group of 
countries Weighted 
Ave. (%) 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 US (E)a 
Japan (G) a
Germany (G) 
UK (E) 
France (F) a 10,416 
3,978 
1,978 
1,552 
1,409 US (E) 
China 
Japan (G) 
India (E) 
Germany (G) 10,138 
5,732 
3,261 
2,694 
2,171 China 
English Origin b
French Origin b
German Origin b
Scandinavian Origin b11.3 
5.0 
3.9 
3.1 
4.0 
6 China 1,237 France (F) 1,554 
7 Italy(F) 1,180 UK (E) 1,510 
8 Canada (E) 715 Italy (F) 1,481 
9 Spain (F) 649 Brazil (F) 1,311 
10 Mexico(F) 637 Russia 1,141 
Notes: *: Legal origin follows LLSV category; a: E, F, G denotes the English-, French-, and German-origin of the 
countrys legal system; b: size-weighted average for countries in LLSV sample. Direct Source for all countries GDP: 
World Bank. 
**: The GDP of each country in 2002 is converted from local currency to international Do llars, use Purchasing Power 
Parity (PPP) conversion factor. The PPP conversion factor  is obtained from The World Bank Development Indicator 
(Table 5.6, World Bank. For details on how to calculate th e indicator, see Handbook of the International Program, 
United Nation, New York 1992. 
Table 1-B Comparison of China and Other Major Emerging Economies: GDP and Growth 
GDP in 2002* GDP in 2 002 on PPP basis** Annual growth rate of GDP 
using PPP (1990 - 2002) 
Rank Country GDP (US 
$ bil.) Country GDP 
(Int'l $ bil.) Country Growth 
rate (%) 
1 China 1237 China 5732 China 11.3 
2 Mexico (F) 637 India (E) 2694 India (E) 7.1 
3 India (E) 515 Brazil (F) 1311 Pakistan (E) 5.7 
4 Brazil (F) 452 Russia  1141 Mexico (F) 4.3 
5 Russia 346 Mexico (F) 878 Argentina (F) 4.0 
6 South Africa (E) 104 South Africa (E) 441 Brazil (F) 4.0 
7 Argentina (F) 102 Argentina (F) 401 South Africa (E) 3.5 
8 Pakistan (E) 60 Pakistan (E) 291 Russia  -2.2 
Notes: *: GDP figures are World Bank; E (F) denotes th e legal origin of the country is the English common-law 
system (French civil-law system). 
 **: Similar to Table 1-A, the PPP conve rsion factor is obtained from The World Bank Deve lopment Indicator (Table 
5.6, World Bank. For details on how to calculate the indicator, see Handbook of the International Program, United Nation, New York 1992. 
53</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>profitable. As a result, stock pr ices are more likely to move away from and do not reflect firm 
specific information.19 
Insert Table 4-A and 4-B here. 
Next, we briefly examine the role of financ ial markets in helping firms raising funds 
(LLSV 1997). The evidence is presented in Table 4- B. From the comparison of the external capital 
markets, it is clear that financing via financial ma rkets in China is different from the LLSV sample 
countries, in that both the scale and relative  importance (compared with other channels of 
financing) of the external market s is not significant. For example, for the ratio of External Capital 
and GNP, the LLSV sample average is 40%, compared to Chinas 10%; for the ratio of total debt 
(including bank loans and bonds) over GNP, the LLSV sample average is 59%, compared to Chinas 22%.
20  We provide firm-level evidence on financing in Section IV below. 
In summary, the overall evidence on the compar ison of China and othe r countries external 
markets is consistent with LLSV (1997, 1998) predictions: with an under-de veloped legal system, 
the fact that China has small external markets comes as no surprise. Figure 1 compares Chinas 
legal system and external financial markets to  those of LLSV countries.  The horizontal axis 
measures overall investor protecti on in each country, while the vertical axis measures the (relative ) 
size and efficiency of that countrys external markets.21 Countries with English common-law 
systems (e.g., US, UK) lie in the t op-right region of the graph, while  those with French civil-law 
systems (e.g., France, Argentina) lie in the botto m-left region. Consistent  with LLSV predictions 
19 One example of the imperfect regulations is the restriction on short sales. Bris et al. (2003) find that limiting short 
sales contributes to the high co-movement of stock prices, but does not tend to increase the probability of a market 
crash, as commonly feared by gove rnments in emerging countries. 
20 However, if we include debt issued to all sectors includ ing State and Listed Sectors, this ratio increases to 79%, 
suggesting that the majority of debt does not go through the capital markets but rather through a centralized system, 
and consistent with evidence on bank credit. 
21 Following LLSV (1997, 1998, 2000), the score on the horizontal axis is the sum of (overall) creditor rights, 
shareholder rights (anti-director rights and one-share, one-vote), rule of law, and finally, the corruption index of the
government, while the score of the verti cal axis indicates the distance of a countrys overall exte rnal markets score 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>40</slideno>
          <text>Third, the role played  by the government during reform process is very different in China 
than in most other transition economies, in part icular, Russia (e.g., Blanch ard and Shleifer 2001).  
In a broader context, LLSV (1999) find that gove rnments in countries with French laws or 
socialist laws have lower quality (in terms of  supporting economic grow th) than those with 
common laws and richer countries. But clearly China is a counterexample to LLSVs argument on 
government: while the Chinese Communist Party larg ely remains autocratic, government officials, 
especially those in the most de veloped areas (e.g., Jiangsu and Zhejiang Provinces), played an 
active supporting role in promoti ng the growth of Private Sector . This is different from the 
grabbing hand role played by government officials in some other countries. The reason for this 
supporting role is three fold. First, as Li (1998) points out, star ting in the early 1980s, the central 
government implemented a mandatory retirement ag e for almost all bureaucrats at various levels, 
which made the officials younger and more familiar w ith capitalist ideas. In Russia, officials from 
the old regime were entrenched and able to extract rents from the new economy without any 
contribution. Secondly, during earl y stages of Chinas reform, TV Es, in which local governments 
are partial owners, provided the most important source of growth in the Private Sector. The 
enormous success of TVEs and the promotion of the associated officials provided examples and 
incentives to other officials to follow suit. Thirdl y, as discussed above, profit sharing with firms in 
a multi-period setting also makes it incentive compatib le for officials at vari ous levels to support 
the growth of the firm. 
VI. Concluding Remarks 
In this paper we examine and compare Chinas formal systems of law and finance and the 
co-existing, alternative system of institutions and mechanisms, and the relation between the 
development of these systems a nd Chinas overall economic growth. With one of the largest and 
40</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>the medians across industries to ob tain the ratio for the country. A similar procedure is taken to 
find the ratios for China using our panel data se t of listed firms. Finally, we take the average 
(median) ratios across groups of countries according to their legal origins, and compare them to 
those of China. The evidence in Table 8-C is cons istent with previous evidence at the aggregate 
level: in terms of total equity, the listed Chines e companies do not rely on the external markets as 
much as their counterparts in LLSV countries, but they rely heavily on debt, in particular bank 
debt, more so than other LLSV countries. 
Finally, we examine dividend pol icy and valuations of listed firms in China, and compare 
them to firms studied by LLSV (2000b, 2002). Ma king the most out of the available data,39 we 
performed three different sets of empirical tests and find similar re sults. Detailed descriptions of 
these tests are presented in Appendix B. First, LLSV (2000b) find that firms in countries with 
poorer protection of outside shareholders tend to have lower divide nds due to more severe agency 
problems. Using dividend/earnings ratio as a pr oxy for dividend policy, we find that on average 
Chinese firms tend to under-pay dividends to their shareholders compared to firms in countries 
studied in LLSV (2000b). Second, LLSV (2002) find th at firms in countries poorer protection of 
outside shareholders tend to have lower Tobin s Q, measured by the market-to-book assets ratios. 
When we examine Tobins Q of listed firms in China, we cannot reject the hypothesis that on 
average their Tobins Q is lower compared to countries with bette r shareholder protections (LLSV 
2002). 
Overall, because investor protections are weak (and agency  problem is severe) in the 
Listed Sector in China, both dividend ratio and Tobins Q are low compared to similar firms 
operating in countries with str onger investor protections. Th ese results confirm that LLSV 
39 The data sets that we employ include: 1) accounting an d financial information for 1100+ listed firms from China 
(1990-2000); 2) LLSV (2000b, 2002) results are based on information for over 4100 firms from 33 countries (1989
28</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>43</slideno>
          <text>petition. Automatic stay prevents secured creditors from gaining 
possession of their security. It equa ls zero if such a restriction does 
exist in the law 
Secured creditors 
first Equals 1 if secured creditors are rank ed first in the distribution of the 
proceeds that result from the disposition of the assets of a bankrupt 
firm. Equals zero if nonsecured creditors, such as the government and 
workers, are given absolute priority  Bankruptcy and reorganization laws 
Management does not stay Equals 1 when an official appointed by the court, or by the creditors, 
is responsible for the operation of the business during reorganization. Bankruptcy and reorganization laws 
Equivalently, this variable equals one if the debtor does not keep the 
administration of its property pending the resolution of the 
reorganization process. Equals zero otherwise 
Creditor rights An index aggregating different  creditor rights. The index is formed by 
adding 1 when: (1) the country imposes restrictions, such as 
creditors' consent or minimum dividends to file for reorganization; (2) Bankruptcy and 
reorganization laws 
secured creditors are able to gain possession of their security once the 
reorganization petition has been approved (no automatic stay); (3) 
secured creditors are ranked first in the distribution of the proceeds 
that result from the disposition of the assets of a bankrupt firm; and 
(4) the debtor does not retain the administration of its property 
pending the resolution of the reorganization. The index ranges from 
zero to four 
Legal reserve The minimum percentage of total share capital mandated by corporate Company law or 
requirement law to avoid the dissolution of an existing firm. It takes a value of commercial code 
zero for countries without such a restriction 
Efficiency of Assessment of the "efficiency and in tegrity of the legal environment Business 
judicial system as it affects business, particularly foreign firms" produced by the country risk rating agency Business International Corp. It "may be International Corp. 
taken to represent investors' assessments of conditions in the country 
in question." Average between 1980 and 1983. Scale from zero to 10 ; 
with lower scores, lowe r efficiency levels. 
Rule of law Assessment of the law and or der tradition in the country produced by 
the International Country risk rating agency International Country International Country 
Risk 
Risk (ICR). Average of the months of April and October of the Guide 
monthly index between 1982 and 1995. Scale from zero to 10, with 
lower scores for less tr adition for law and order (we changed the scale 
from its original range going from zero to six) 
Corruption ICR's assessment of the corruptio n in government. Lower scores 
indicate that "high government officials are likely to demand special 
payments" and "illegal payments are generally expected throughout 
lower levels of government" in the form of "bribes connected with import and export licenses, tax assessment, policy protection, etc." 
Average of the months of April and October of the monthly index 
between 1982 and 1995. Scale from 0 to 10, with lower scores for higher levels of corruption (we changed the scale from its original" 
range going from zero to six) International Country 
Risk Guide 
Risk of ICR's assessment of the risk of "o utright confiscation " or "forced International Country 
expropriation nationalization." Average of the months of April and October of the Risk Guide 
monthly index between 1982 and 1995. Scale from zero to 10, with 
lower scores for higher risks  
Repudiation of contracts by 
government ICR's assessment of the "risk of a modification in a contract taking 
the form of a repudiation, postponement, or scaling down" due to "budget cut backs, indigenization pressure, a change in government, International Country 
Risk Guide 
43</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>46</slideno>
          <text>A.4. Definitions on different types of firms in China (used in Tables 5b and Figures 1-3) 
1.	State-owned Enterprises : Non-corporation economic units where the entire assets are owned by the state 
and which have registered in accordance with the "regulation of the Pe ople's Republic of China on the 
Management of Registration of Corporate Enterprises." Excluded from this category are the sole state funded 
corporations in the limited liability corporation. 
Note : The government is the de facto owner, and they choose managers to run the firm. Even though these 
firms do enter the credit plan, but this process is constructed and enforced by state banks, which are also 
under the control of the government. 
2.	Collective-Owned Enterprises :  Economic units where the assets are owned collectively and which have 
registered in accordance with the "Regulation of th e People's Republic of China on the management of 
registration of corporate Enterprise. 
Note : Local government can be regarded as the agent of central government. Therefore, any firm owned by 
local government is also owned by central government.  Collective ownership here means the community in the city or rural area joins the ownership. 
3.	Township-village Enterprises (TVEs) : Enterprises and economic units lo cated in rural areas, collectively-
owned or with most of investment from residents in these rural areas. An enterprise in a rural area is legally registered as a TVE where rural communities or residents invest more than 50% of the firms total assets or 
act as the control owners in the operation of enterprise. 
Note : There can be firms that are both collectively-owned an d TVEs, as long as they are in the rural areas and 
have more than 50% of total assets coming from residents from the same rural area/county. The difference is 
that TVEs are all located in rural areas while collectiv ely-owned firms can be in cities; while TVEs can be 
solely owned by residents of that rural area and the local government has no ownership nor control over the 
firm. 
4.	Jointly-owned firms : Economic Units established by two or more corporate enterprises or institutions of 
the same or different ownership, through joint investme nt on the basis of equality, voluntary participation and 
mutual benefits. They include state joint ownership enterprises, collective joint ownership enterprises, joint 
state-collective enterprise, and other joint ownership. 
Note : Enterprise involved with foreign investment/ownership  is not in this category. They are in the Category 
of "Enterprise with Foreign investment, which has 3 different types. 
5.	Share-holding Corporations Ltd : Economic units registered in accordance with the "Regulation of the 
People's Republic of China on the management of Corporations", with total registered capitals divided into 
equal shares and raised through issuing stocks. Each  investor bears limited liability to the corporation 
depending on the holding of shares, and the corporation bears liability to its debt to the maximum of its total assets. Note : The above is essentially the same definition of US public companies, but these Chinese companies 
have non-tradable shares that are the by-product of the reforming process. 
46</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>56</slideno>
          <text>Table 4-A A Comparison of the Largest Stock Markets in the World 
Rank Stock Market Total Market Cap (US$ billion) Concentration Turnover Velocity 
1. NYSE 11,535 57.1% 87.7% 
2. Nasdaq 3,597 75.9% 383.9% 
3. Tokyo 2,962 70.5% 58.8% 
4. London 2,475 78.3% 69.3% 
5. Paris 1350 86.2% 268.8% 
6. Frankfurt 1186 45.3% 128.6% 
7. Toronto 756 75.5% 75.0% 
8. China (HongKong) 624 65.4% 60.9% 
9. China (domestic) 622 2.73% 500% 
10 Taiwan 237 52.9%% 259.3% 
Notes: 
1.	All figures (except the figures relating to Chinas domestic exchanges) are taken from http//:www.fibv.com , the 
web site of the international organization of stock excha nges. The figures relating to Chinas domestic exchanges 
are taken from CSRCs own database.  
2.	All figures relate to the period 1 January to 31 December 2000. 
3.	Concentration  means the total turnover of the companies making up 5% of the total market capitalization 
expressed as a percentage of the total turnover of the wh ole market for the year. If liq uid market capitalization is 
taken into account, concentration is about 5% in Chinas domestic markets. 
4.	Turnover velocity  is the total turnover for the year expressed as a percentage of the total market capitalization. 
Turnover velocity has in fact climbed down from the 1996 high of 913% in Shanghai and 1350.3% in Shenzhen. 
Table 4-B A Comparison of External Capital Markets (Mean) 
Country English-origin French-origin German-origin Scandinavian- LLSV Sample China  
Average Average Average origin Average Average (2002) 
External capital/GNP 
Domestic Firms/Pop 
IPOs/Population 
Total Debt/GNP 
GDP growth (one-year) 
Rule of Law 
Anti-director Rights 
One share = one vote 
Creditor rights 0.6 
35.45 
2.23 
0.68 
4.3 
6.46 
3.39 
0.22 
3.11 0.21 
10 
0.19 
0.45 
3.18 
6.05 
1.76 
0.24 
1.58 0.46 
16.79 
0.12 
0.97 
5.29 
8.68 
2 
0.33 
2.33 0.3 
27.26 
2.14 
0.57 
2.42 
10 
2.5 
0 
2 0.4 
21.59 
1.02 
0.59 
3.79 
6.85 
2.44 
0.22 
2.3 0.49 
(0.16) 
0.93 
0.05 
0.35 
6.77 
5 3 
1 
2 
Sources:  LLSV (1997 JF) paper; Almanac of Chinas Finance and Banking (2003). 
Table 5-A A Comparison of Non-performing Loans of Banking Systems 
1997 1998 1999 2000 2001 2002 
China n/a 2.0 (2.2) 9.5 (10.6) 18.9 (24.9) 16.9(22.7) 12.6(15.2) 
Hong Kong 
India 1.3 (3) 
n/a 4.3 (10.2) 
7.8 (1.6) 6.3 (13.9) 
7.0 (1.6) 5.2 (12.6 ) 
6.6 (1.6) 4.9 (12.9) 
4.6 (1.7) 3.7(9.6) 
2.2(0.8) 
Indonesia 0.3(0.2) 11.8 (4.6) 8.1 (2.0) 13.6 (3.2) 9.9 (2.2) 4.5(0.9) 
Japan 
South Korea 2.7 (5.4) 2.9 (5.1) 5.1 (10.8) 
4.8 (6.3) 5.3 (10.9) 
12.9 (12.9) 5.8 (11.5) 
8.0 (8.6) 9.2 (15.3) 
3.4 (3.4) 7.4(12.8) 
2.5(2.6) 
Taiwan 2.4 (3.2) 3.0 (3.9) 4.0 (5.7) 5.2 (7.6) 6.2 (9.4) 4.1(5.2) 
Notes: NPL is measured as % of total loans ma de, and as % of GDP (numbers in brackets). Both the loan and 
NPL are the aggregate of all banks in a country. 
  Source: The Asian Banker data center 2003, http://www.thesianbanker.com. 
56</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>From Table 4-A, Chinas domestic stock exchanges, SHSE and SZSE, with their combined 
size or volume, rank the 9th among the largest stock exchanges in the world. In addition, the Hong 
Kong Stock Exchange (HKSE hereafter), where se lected firms from Mainland China can now be 
listed and traded, is ranked 8th in the world by itself.18  If we rank the combined size of all stock 
exchanges in a country, China would rank the 5th, behind only the US, Japan, UK, and France. 
As fast as the growth of Chinas stock mark ets has been, they are not efficient in that 
prices and investors be havior do not reflect fundamental values  of listed firms. Again from Table 
4, Concentration measures the fra ction of total turnover of the ma rket within 2000 that is due to 
the trading and turnover of compan ies within the largest market cap  quintile. Large cap stocks in 
China are not frequently traded and the concentration ratio, 2.73%, is much lower than any other 
major stock exchange in the world (Frankfurt ha s the second lowest concentration ratio -- 45.3%). 
On the other hand, medium- and small-cap stocks ar e traded extremely frequently in China, as 
shown by the extremely high Turno ver Velocity, defined as th e total turnover for the year 
expressed as a percentage of total market cap. Ch inas velocity of 500% is even much higher than 
that of NASDAQ with the well-known trading patte rns of technology stocks in recent years. 
Consistent with our findings, Mo rck et al. (2000) find that stock prices are more synchronous in 
emerging countries, including China, than in de veloped countries. They contribute this 
phenomenon to poor minority invest or protection and imperfect re gulation of markets in emerging 
markets. In particular, they  argue that poor protection of minority investors makes rumors more 
influential on moving sectors of stock returns,  while informed risk arbitrage becomes less 
18 However, a fraction of all the (equity) shares is non-tra dable. See Section IV.1 for details. Nevertheless, total 
market capitalization using tradable sh ares reached US$170  billion in 2001. 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>parties fulfill their roles to make the firm successful. Profit sharing also makes it incentive 
compatible for officials at various leve ls to support the growth of the firm. 
There are other mechanisms supporting the grow th of Chinas Private Sector, as well as 
growth of other emerging economies. First, in  a series of papers, Djankov et al. (2002, 2003a, 
2003b; DLLS hereafter) examine vari ous aspects of institutions, including regulations of entry and 
labor, and efficiency of judici al systems across countries. Among the DLLS papers, the entry 
barrier is probably the most rele vant factor for China. DLLS (2002) find that countries with 
heavier (lighter) regulation of  entry have higher corruption (more democratic and limited 
governments) and larger unofficial economies (c ounter the regulation wh ich can reduce overall 
efficiency). Thus the regulation of entry benefits politicians/bureaucrats instead of public interests. 
China is included in the data that includes 85 countries, with much lower barriers to entry compared to countries with similar per capita GDP. The low entry barriers contribute to the 
growth of Chinas Private Sector, as they imply higher competition in the product and input 
markets, which we view as one of the most e ffective governance mechanis ms within the Private 
Sector. Moreover, in terms of entry barriers, Chin a is once again an outlie r in the DLLS sample, 
considering that China is one of  least democratic countries, whic h tend to have high barriers to 
entry. 
There exist non-standard methods to remove entr y barriers that can r econcile the seemingly 
contradictory facts, based on our survey. First, 16 out of the 17 firms applied license (required) 
before the business started, with 50% of them i ndicating that it takes 2 weeks to 1 month to go 
through the procedure and 37.5% say it takes 1-2 months. The main  problem for the application of 
license seems to be dealing with government bureaucracy. To ease this problem, most of the 
firms founders/executives ask the friends of govern ment officials to negotia te on their behalf, or 
the firms can offer profit sharing to government o fficials. But these methods are consistent with 
38</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>predictions work well for Chinas Listed Sector that includes many firms converted from the State 
Sector, and is also consistent wi th evidence presented in Figure 1. 
V. Evidence on the Private Sector 
In this section we study how firms in the Pr ivate Sector raise funds, their various growth 
paths, and the alternative mechanisms employed by owners that can substitute for formal corporate 
governance mechanisms. Due to data limitations, much  of this evidence is by necessity anecdotal 
or by survey.40  We first present evidence based on a su rvey of 17 firms in Jiangsu and Zhejiang 
provinces in Section V.1, and then we expand ou r evidence to two highly successful regions of 
Private Sector firms in Section V.2. Finally, Section V.3 provides discussions of our evidence.  
V.1 Survey Evidence41 
As Table 9 shows, among the 17 firms that we surveyed, one firm is from Shanghai, three 
are from Jiangsu Province, and the rest 13 are fro m Zhejiang Province. These firms operate in a 
wide range of industries. The average age of the firm is over 11 years, and they employ an average 
of over 1600 employees. The average size of (book) assets is US$55 million, with average return on assets being 10%. Finally, on average firms ar e highly levered, with av erage debt/ (private ) 
equity ratio reaching 2.1. Figure 4-A presents more  background information about the firms. First, 
there exist significant variations in both firms past performance, in terms of average annual 
returns to assets in the past 5 years, and their expected future annual returns in the next 3 years 
(top two histograms of Figure 4-A). Second, in term s of ownership structur e, both at the time of 
1994), while detailed firm-level data for LLSV sample are not available to us; but we do have their cross-sectional
summary statistics by country, as well as the regression results across countries. 
40 To our knowledge, with the exception of some well-known firms who voluntarily provide information to the public, 
firm-level information (financial, acco unting, or operational) is non-existen t for most Private Sector firms. 
41 The survey questions, as well as the ta bulation of answers, are available at 
http://www2.bc.edu/~qianju/research.html . In designing our survey forms, we follow Graham and Harvey (2001, 
survey of US CFOs), Johnson, McMillan, and Woodruff (2 002, survey of 5 former Communist countries in Eastern
29</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>shoes, Town B shirts, Town C umbrellas, etc.). This specialization can be a result of firms 
attempt to signal to potential customers that th ey are competitive in an industry by locating the 
firm in the region filled with other firms produc ing and selling similar products. During recent 
years certain developed areas have shifted product emphasis from labor-intensive products such as 
clothes to more high-tech products, for example,  parts of radios, TVs, and computers.   
The failure rate for start-ups in most industr ies is high. New product st rategies often start 
with mimicking successful or popular products. Some of these products are labor intensive while others require skillful labors and craftsmen. Pa tent laws are difficult to implement so often 
disputes are settled among the entrepreneurs th emselves. To overcome this problem, some 
entrepreneurs expend effort and money to ensure  that the key parts of  their new products are 
difficult to disassemble and to copy. Another produc t strategy for many entrepreneurs is that they 
often aim at "exporting" their products to other regions, including to  foreign countries, instead of 
selling them locally. KUNSHAN --- Foreign Direct Investment and the Separation of Ownership and Control 
Kunshan County, which is in Jiangsu provin ce and close to Shanghai, is famous for 
attracting foreign direct investme nt, especially from Taiwanese investors. Some of the most 
effective government policies ha ve included setting up special de velopment zones with favorable 
land and tax policies. For example, in 1997, Kuns han set up a high-tech development zone, to 
attract foreign investment for bu ilding factories within the zone. Enterprises, in the ownership 
form of joint ventures, cooperatives, and sole ly owned by foreign investors, can take full 
advantage of a tax waiver and tax reduction for the initial periods. Moreover, firms whose high-
tech products are export-oriented can enjoy even more tax advantages. There is a center in the 
34</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>We next examine separately financing channe ls, corporate governance , and the growth of 
firms in each of the three sectors. The Stat e Sector has been shrinking with the ongoing 
privatization process, which include firms going pub lic. Our empirical results on the Listed Sector 
are based on a sample of more than 1100 firms listed and traded on SHSE and SZSE. First, we 
find that the equity ownership is  concentrated among the State for firms converted from the State 
Sector, and founders families for non-state firms.7 Second, the standard corporate governance 
mechanisms are weak and ineffective in the Listed Sector. Finally, when we examine listed firms 
dividend policy and valuations and compare them to those in the LLSV (2000b, 2002) sample firms, we find both the dividend ra tio and firm value of Chinese firms are low compared to similar 
firms operating in countries with stronger investor protections, consistent w ith LLSV predictions.   
More interesting results are found for the Priv ate Sector. Our evidence is mainly based on 
surveying 17 entrepreneurs and executives in Zh ejiang and Jiangsu Provinces, two of the most 
developed regions in China. Firs t, the two most important financing channels for these firms 
during their start-up and subseque nt periods are financial interm ediaries, including state-owned 
banks and private credit agencies, and founders friends and families. Firms have outstanding 
loans from multiple financial intermediaries, with most of the loans secured by fixed assets or third party guarantees. During a firms growth  period, funds from ethnic Chinese investors 
(from Hong Kong, Taiwan, and othe r countries) as well as other foreign investors are also 
important sources. Many firms purchase the operation ri ghts of land from the government, with 
a typical contract that lasts for 20-50 years. When asked about the prospect of going public, 
founders and executives list access to large scale of funding and reputation increase as the 
7 Our result on family ownership is similar to the findings of Claessens, Djankov and Lang (2000) and Claessens et al. 
(2002) on listed firms in Asia, while different from the findings of LLS (1999) . 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>2-B), we can conclude that altern ative channels of financing are important even for the State and 
Listed Sectors. 
Insert Figures 2-A, 2-B, and 2-C here. 
Next, we consider how firms in the Private Sector raise funds (Figure 2-C). Self-
fundraising here includes all kinds of  internal finance, capital raised from family and friends of the 
founders and managers, and funds raised in the fo rm of private equity and loans. Clearly, this 
category is by far the most important source of fi nancing, with close to 60 % of total funds raised 
coming from this channel. The other fact that we want to stress here is that because firms in this 
sector operate in an environmen t with poorer legal and financial mechanisms and regulations than 
those firms in the State and Listed Sectors, all financing sources probably work differently from 
how they work in the State and Listed Sectors,  and those in developed countries. In Section V 
below we present detailed evidence on how differe nt types of self-fundraising help Private Sector 
firms at various stages. 
III.2  Comparing Financing Channels in Emerging Economies 
We briefly compare financing channels at the aggregate level in China and other major 
emerging economies in Asia. In pa rticular, we relate the aggregat e financing channels with the 
growth of the economy during different growth peri ods, in order to determine whether the Chinese 
experience in financing is special. First, Figure 3- A compares the development of stock markets at 
the aggregate level, while Figure 3-D compares th e growth rates in GDP. Both Taiwan and South 
Korea experienced high GDP growth in much of the 1970s, while the total market cap of their 
respective stock markets accounted for less than 20% of their GNPs during the same period, and 
the growth of stock markets did not take off un til mid- to late-1980s. Fi gure 3-B compares the 
growth of corporate bond markets:  South Korea having the fastest growth path, while in Taiwan 
and China the corporate bond markets seem to la g the development of stock markets. Finally, 
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Sector only, Chinas ratio dropped sharply to 0.24, suggesting that most of the bank credit is 
issued to companies in the State and Listed Se ctors. Moreover, Chinas banking system is not 
efficient: its overhead cost to tota l assets (0.12) is much  higher than the average of French-origin 
countries (0.05), the next highest group of count ries.  The second panel of Table 3 compares the 
relative importance of financial markets vs. banks (Structure indices). China has the lowest scores for both Structure Activity and Structure size categories, suggesting that Chinas banking sector is much larger than its financ ial markets, and this dominance by the banks over 
markets is stronger than the aver age of all LLSV sample countries.
16 
We also compare the development of th e entire financial system (Financial 
Development), including both banks  and markets, in the last pane l of Table 3. If we use all bank 
credit (including to the State and Listed sector s) then Chinas overall financial market size 
(Finance Activity and Finan ce Size) lies in the middle of the pack among those LLSV 
countries. However, given that all other countries measures were based on private bank credit 
only, if we re-calculate Chinas financial system the same way, we find that it is not as large as the 
LLSV sample average level, and is only higher than  the French-origin countries average. In terms 
of the efficiency of the financial system, Ch inas measure is below all sub-samples of LLSV 
countries.17  Based on the above evidence, we can conc lude that Chinas financial system is 
dominated by a large but inefficient banking sector . 
Financial Markets 
16 Structure activity and Structure size are relative size measures, with a smalle r value indicating that the 
countrys financial markets are smaller than its banking syst em. We also compare Structure  efficiency, in Table 3, 
which is the relative efficiency of markets vs. banks. Sinc e China has the highest score, it seems that Chinas stock 
markets are actually relatively more effici ent than banks, compared to other countries. Again this result is mainly 
driven by the extremely high costs of Chinas banking system.  
17 We also examine the trend of financial system development in China in the 1990s. It is clear that: 1) the overall size 
of both markets and banks is growing; 2) banks dominate the markets even though markets are becoming more 
important relative to banks; 3) efficiency (both in terms of banks and the overall system) remains low. 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>58</slideno>
          <text>Table 7-A Types of Common Stock Issued in China 
Tradable on the Definition 
Exchanges? 
No State-owned Shares that are controlled by the cent ral government during the process in 
(private shares** which firms are converted into a limited liability incorporation but before they 
Block are listed. All these shares are managed and represented by the Bureau of 
Transfer National Assets Management, which also appoints board members on firms 
Possible) boards. 
Entrepreneur's Shares reserved for firms founders du ring the same process described above; 
shares different from shares that founders can purchase and sell in the markets 
Foreign owners Shares owned by foreign industrial investors during the same process 
Legal entity Shares sold to legal identities (such as other companies, listed or non-listed ) 
holders during the same process 
Employee shares Shares sold to firms employees during the same process 
Yes A Shares Chinese companies listed in Shanghai or Shenzhen Stock Exchanges, and 
(New shares sold to Chin ese (citizen) investors 
issued B Shares Chinese Company listed in SHSZ or SZ SE, but shares are sold to foreign 
shares) 	 investors 
H Shares Chinese Company listed in Hong Kong (shares can only be traded on the HK 
Exchange but can be  held by anyone) 
 **: There are sub-categories under this definition 
Table 7-B Tradable vs. Non-tradab le Shares for Chinas Listed Companies 
Year 	 State/total Non-tradable^/total Tradable/total A/total shares A/Tradable shares* 
shares shares shares 
1992  0.41 0.69 0.31 0.16 0.52 
1993  0.49 0.72 0.28 0.16 0.57 
1994  0.43 0.67 0.33 0.21 0.64 
1995  0.39 0.64 0.36 0.21 0.60 
1996  0.35 0.65 0.35 0.22 0.62 
1997  0.32 0.65 0.35 0.23 0.66 
1998  0.34 0.66 0.34 0.24 0.71 
1999  0.36 0.65 0.35 0.26 0.75 
2000  0.39 0.64 0.36 0.28 0.80 
2001  0.39 0.64 0.36 0.29 0.80 
2002  n/a 0.65 0.35 0.26 0.74 
2003  n/a 0.64 0.35 0.27 0.76 
^: Non-tradable shares include state-owned and shares ow ned by legal entities; *: tradable shares include A, B, 
and H shares; Source: China Security Regulation Committee Reports (2000) and http://www.csrc.gov.cn 
Table 7-C Ownership and Control in Listed Firms of China 
Company Ownership and Control (%) 
Shareholder type Ownership Control (board seats) 
State  24 21 
Legal person 44 48 
Employees 2 3 
Tradable Shares 30 4 
Total  100 76 
Source: Table 4.6 p.83, Corporate Governance and Enterprise Reform in China, Building the institutions of Modern Market, 2002, World Bank publication. 
58</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>42</slideno>
          <text>Appendix  A: Brief Descriptions of  All the Variables and Their Sources 
A.1. Creditor/Shareholder Rights Variables (Tables 2a and 2b) 
Variables Description Sources 
Legal Origin Identifies the legal origin of  the company law or commercial code of Reynolds and Flores 
each country  (1989), LLSV (1997) 
One share-one vote 1) Equals 1 if ordinary shares carry one vote per share, and 0 
otherwise; 2) equals 1 when the law prohibits the existence of both Company law or 
commercial code 
multiple-voting and non-voting ordinary shares and does not allow 
firms to set a maximum number of votes per shareholder irrespective 
of the number of shares owned, and 0 otherwise  
Proxy by mail Equals 1 if shareholders can mail their proxy vote to the firm, and 0 Company law or 
allowed otherwise  commercial code 
Shares not blocked Equals 1 if firms cannot require shareholders to deposit their shares Company law or 
before meeting prior to a general shareholders meeting (to prevent selling shares), commercial code 
and 0 otherwise 
Cumulative voting Equals 1 if shareholders can cast all their votes for one candidate to Company law or 
or proportional the board of directors (cumula tive voting) or a mechanism of commercial code 
representation proportional representation in the board by which minority interests 
may name a proportional number of directors to the board is allowed, 
and 0 otherwise  
Oppressed minorities 
mechanism Equals 1 if minority shareholders have either a judicial venue to 
challenge the decisions of management or of the assembly or the right 
to step out of the company by requiring the company to purchase their shares when they object to cer tain fundamental changes (e.g., 
mergers, and asset dispositions); and equals 0 otherwise. Minority shareholders are defined as those shareholders who own 10% of Company law or 
commercial code 
shares or less 
Preemptive rights Equals 1 when grants shareholders the first opportunity to buy new Company law or 
issues of stock, and this right can be waived only by a shareholders' commercial code 
vote; equals 0 otherwise  
Percentage of share The minimum percentage of ownership of share capital that entitles a Company law or 
capital to call an share - holder to call for an extr aordinary shareholders' meeting; it commercial code 
extraordinary ranges from 1% to 33% 
shareholders' 
meeting 
Anti-director rights The index is formed by adding 1 when (1) the country allows shareholders to mail their proxy vote to the firm, (2) shareholders are 
not required to deposit their shares prior to the general shareholders' 
meeting, (3) cumulative voting or  proportional representation of 
minorities in the board of director s is allowed, (4) an oppressed 
minorities mechanism is in place, (5) the minimum percentage of 
share capital that entitles a share- holder to call for an extraordinary 
shareholders' meeting is less than or equal to 10% (the sample median), or (6) shareholders have preemptive rights that can be 
waived only by a shareholders' vote. The index ranges from 0 to 6 Company law or 
commercial code 
Mandatory dividend Equals the percentage of net income that the company law or Company law or 
commercial code requires firms to distribute as dividends among commercial code 
ordinary stockholders. It equals 0 for countries without such a restriction 
Restrictions for 
going into 
reorganization Equals 1 if the reorganization procedure imposes restrictions, such as 
creditors consent; it equals 0 otherwise  Bankruptcy and reorganization laws 
No automatic stay on secured assets Equals 1 if the reorganization procedure does not impose an automatic stay on the assets of the firm on filing the reorganization Bankruptcy and reorganization laws 
42</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
