<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-914-planning-communication-spring-2007/</course_url>
    <course_title>Planning Communication</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Communication </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Sociology </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-914-planning-communication-spring-2007/resources/sample1</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-914-planning-communication-spring-2007/resources/sample1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
 
Sample Feedback on Team Briefings 
 
Case: Anacostia Waterfront Initiative 
 
Team X 
 
Our evaluation covers your  briefing, visual aids, and handout, though the 
feedback below may offer more on one of those than the other elements. 
 
Briefing  (content and delivery) 
 
Your team excelled in several key dimensions: You made specific  criticisms of 
the light rail decisionmaking process conducted to date (rather than offering 
generalities about the need to consult more); you had a strong visual package  
to illustrate the geography and visual interest inherent in this strategy area and 
to offer us a clear storyboard from start to finish (and you supplemented the main briefing with rich back-up data and a useful case comparison to Portland); and team members responded  very directly to briefe e questions. The latter 
helped you compensate for the limited attention, up front, to the threshold question of whether light rail is likely to  be worth it. You also coordinated well as 
a team. 
 
As for individual speakers, Student-As  overview was clear, and her brief 
statement of the projects potential was helpful (in real life, youd try to find out 
in advance where the key decisionmakers are most skeptical or are likely to 
need the most help: The idea of the light rail? Specifics on implementation? The 
lead agencys role in a complex inter-agency plan? Something else?). 
 
Your up-front recommendations were clear, followed by a preview with a 
straightforward logic. Student-Bs  outline of how principles of equitable 
development was clear and well timed: Ot her groups needed this but didnt have 
it. Ditto the analysis of alternatives. Likewise, Student-C offered a specific 
critique, well supported by visuals, of  the weak stakeholder engagement carried 
out so far. Note that the Board chair s later question is still a key one: 
Government should do a better job of consulting, fine, but what exactly is our 
organizations role vis--vis that problem? This is a concern born of years of 
pushing agencies to do better at what they are entrusted to do: You have to set 
priorities and understand your role, or youll get nowhere. But the key is that 
your briefing persuaded us to think that far: Your case that public involvement 
efforts to date have been inadequate was well made. The slide with two simple lists (consulted, insufficient consultation) was superb to nail this case. 
Student-Ds  wrap-up was effective: detailed and persuasive. 
 
The more detailed recommendations were well summarized. We especially 
appreciated the attention to what the Anacostia Waterfront Corporation (AWC) 
Page 1 of 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>needs to learn and why one needs to build the capacity of resident stakeholders 
to participate in a complex, many-issue decisionmaking process over time. 
 
Responses to our questions were well informed. In a longer briefing, you would want to listen carefully to the concerns and extend  your analysis to meet them. 
You did this on the overall value of light rail as a policy strategy, citing Portland and clear links to needs East of the River (though a deeper analysis would get into job projections, ridership, traffic an d other disruption costs, etc.). On the 
participation front, you devoted considerab le energy to a planning process that 
another  agency had run and seemed surprised at Goldsmiths query about 
AWCs role. It isnt clear, at this point, that there will be an AWC in a few 
yearsa vigorous institution with influence, that is, not just a corporation on 
paperand you didnt really have the political data with which to assess the specifics of holding the transportation agency accountable. So it was fine to 
underscore how poorly run the agencys process really was and, in terms of the 
AWC role, to re-connect the transportation strategy to AWCs larger aim of engaging affected communities in revitalization decisions. 
 
Finally, your team managed time well, covering the additional information 
contained in the Portland example and the important connection to Federal 
transportation legislation. It was an ex cellent, informative briefing all around. 
 
Visual aids (slides) and handout 
You had many excellent slides. The data were well selected and clearly 
summarized. The visual storyboard was si mple, logical, and persuasive, taking 
us from your recommendations to each component, unpacking it, returning to 
the core, using maps to re-place us in context. These were some of the best 
slides we saw all semesteron consultation, links to AWCs mission (for coalition 
building strategy), physical planning al ternatives, and more. A few reminders: 
Dont ever lead with abbreviations (LRT, CB O) in early slides. Spell things out in 
almost all cases. If community means community residents, say that, or community organizations and residents if you mean both (or whatever else 
you mean). The handout  is well organized and clearly written; it conveys key 
technical insights as well as the crucial institutional aspectswhy, if AWC wants this strategy area to succeed, it must  strengthen participation and make it 
meaningful. 
 
Your score and grade 
 
In scoring each group, we weighed substantive argumentation first and 
foremost, considering delivery only to the ex tent that it related directly to your 
effectiveness as argument makers (or per suaders). Above, we comment on style 
but didnt score it. We considered visual s as an additional element, weighing 
content more heavily than use. Score: 97, Grade: A 
Page 2 of 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-914-planning-communication-spring-2007/resources/qstion_silbrberg</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-914-planning-communication-spring-2007/resources/qstion_silbrberg/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The example of Building 114: FPA never filled in MGH building and it has been empty for 6 years. 
Nothing for the public, MGH not exerting themselves to fill it. So the idea of spreading out the spaces and 
making the developer offer rentfree space is to avoid more empty spaces. Several smaller sites will make 
a network of places to visit. Can see no other way of doing this unless the BRA builds, fits out, and offers 
the site. 
Spalding rehab center is committed to coming to the site and it is a great use for the site. Lots of activity, 
staff, patients etc. 
What about the Moran AutoPort (MassPort facility across the channel from our site)? 
This is staying. Bulk cargo (like automobiles) is one of the successful areas for MassPort, so different 
uses for that site are not under consideration. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.914 Gateway: Planning Communication 
Followup with Susan Silberberg 
Amanda and Frank spoke with Susan on the phone on Sunday evening, February 11, 2007. We used the 
questions from groups as starting points. Hopefully we've covered all the main questions that were sent. 
What is the Mayor's authority? 
The Mayor can get what he wants if he wants this to be a flagship project, it will be. He has unrivalled 
power to get people together and get things done. Although the BRA and Mayor are separate, he will 
appoint the BRA director. 
All great projects have the backing of a highly placed person; this project is no different. If the Mayor 
comes out in support of it, the project will take off. He must get involved. Someone has to take 
leadership and the Mayor is the most likely. The National Parks Service is there, but has no money. 
Mass General Hospital is not interested. The City needs to take ownership and champion this. Susan 
emphasized this. 
What is the contextual framework for the different sectors of government? 
State regulations are set independently from the SPDF requirement. These regulations were drawn up by 
the city and approved by the State. 
The CNY plan will become an amendment to the Municipal Harbor Plan; the State will then approve this. 
The State could reject the plan but is unlikely to, because they are kept informed through the process via 
the Municipal Harbor Committee this makes small tweaks to get everyone happy. There is potential for 
maneuvering here for example the City could leave unpopular decisions to the State to impose. In June 
2006, the draft plan was released to the public, and a 60day comment period followed. The planners are 
waiting to do a presentation to the City. In the meantime, the people at the State agencies have changed 
(partly due to the change in administration). Tweaking of the plan is expected and, potentially, desired. 
The State Coastal Zone people have always been on board. 
Is there a real problem with the conflict of interest? (i.e. BRA as land owner, planning authority, 
and economic development body) 
The conflict of interest will always be there, in this instance it is as much of an issue as any other project. 
BRA has internally approved the plan before making it public, so they have resolved their own internal 
interdepartment issues. Remember that the BRA is not a single entity. It has director, but there are 
multiple factions (asset management, economic development, planning and zoning, etc.) 
How will the plan be carried out (the management organization, etc)? How will it be funded? 
BRA has no capacity as a programming organization. Instead the plan suggests a voluntary nonprofit 
modeled on Friends of Fort Point Channel (FFPC). This will manage facilities/programming after 
implementation. 
The organization will be more active than FFCP, since there are bigger issues to deal with on this site 
(particularly with the historic facilities). It would be formed from local nonprofits, land owners etc.
e.g. National Park Service (NPS), Mass Gen Hospital (MGH). Funding via Chapter 91 licenses, money 
from developers, private sponsorship, tenants paying dues. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>NPS would probably be the lead programming partner (like the Childrens Museum is for Fort Point). 
They have no financial resources to contribute (most of their budget goes on security for the USS 
Constitution). Unlikely to be conflict between the NPS and the management organization. 
MGH would need to be persuaded that involvement is worthwhile. Thus far, they have not been very 
involved, since they see no benefit to contributing. 
This organization needs to be set up some existing organizations are compromised by previous 
positions. (There is currently a Friends of the Navy Yard organization that was formed in opposition to 
development). It takes time, leadership, and resourcesa fresh DUSP graduate should go and sort it out! 
If the organization is set up and the Mayor is in support, it will be possible to get going. At the moment 
everything is waiting for this organization to emerge, no one else at present is capable of doing it. 
What consultation has the BRA carried out? How did the consultation process work? Community 
involvement? Outreach to Charlestown? 
A lot of consultation more than half of meetings held in Charlestown (at the Knights of Columbus Hall 
in the Uptown neighborhood) not in the CNY. Local newspaper given all info after meetings. BRA 
neighborhood planner (Carlos Montanez, a DUSP grad) led the outreach. 
Other Boston wide bodies involved Conservation Law Foundation, Save The Harbor Save The Bay, etc. 
Boston Harbor Association attended every meeting. 
Interesting to compare with South Boston there, the neighborhood had a strong emotional attachment to 
the waterfront and took an active role in development planning. Charlestown is less passionate; it comes 
down to topics like parking. 
The plan is designed for a wide constituency, including Charlestown residents. Tourism elements are 
good, but key point is universal access to the Harborwalk. In general, there is broad support for the plan 
(story loops, etc.)its just that the Charlestown residents are not emotionally invested in the area and 
feel no attachment to the Navy Yard. 
SPDF clarifications 
Buildings are required to have FPA space on the first floor, which can be used for restaurants, retail, etc. 
(but not housing or office space). Since no restaurants or shops want to move out to the CNY right now, 
there are a lot of buildings with vacant ground floor space. Parcel 4 has 20,000 sq. ft. of empty FPA. 
For a clear breakdown of the $100 per sq. ft. SPDF issue for Pier 5, see page 59 of the Waterfront 
Activation Plan. 
The planners want all the SPDF space to be builtout (i.e. ready for use). The developer must provide 
SPDF space rentfree and with free utilities for the lifetime of the license. The plan seeks to spread out 
the 34,000 sq. ft. of statemandated SPDF around the CNY (several small attractions rather than 1 big 
museum). The idea is to get a critical mass of cultural SPDF spots so that then restaurants and retail will 
be attracted to the FPA space to revitalize the CNY. 
The reserved SPDF space must be interior space (this is a problem for CNY since some attractions are 
outdoorsy, but good because attractions will be more yearround). SPDF has no formal definition but it 
needs to be a major attraction (e.g. moving the Aquarium, except that the Aquarium can't afford this). 
The proposed Maritime Interactive Park (story loops, etc.) would probably count as a SPDF. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-914-planning-communication-spring-2007/resources/sample3</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-914-planning-communication-spring-2007/resources/sample3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
 
Feedback on Team Briefings 
 
Case: Anacostia Waterfront Initiative 
 
Team Y 
 
Our evaluation covers your  briefing, visual aids, and handout, though the 
feedback below may offer more on one of those than the other elements. 
 
Briefing  (content and delivery) 
 
Your briefing had a number of key strengths: An easy-to-follow 
decomposition of the problem; clear attention to the Anacostia Waterfront Corporations (AWCs) role and competencies; and an effective outline of 
policy options (grounded in available analysis) as well as data needs. 
 
But the presentation of the Market Creek development in San Diego was 
somewhat confusing, as the main presentation touted it and yet, under questioning, you expressed doubt that it would translate well to Anacostia. Presenting the risks or drawbacks to that model, since it was your focal 
model, was important. Also, the visuals were not very visual, though text 
was clear, and you over-used the core slide (even though signposting is important). A map or two would have let you connect business development to the transportation and watershed restoration topics, since both promise to change mobility patterns dramatically over the long run, and transit-oriented 
shopping districts could be a natural East of the River. An excellent slide on 
adjusting the Market Creek lessons to suit the Anacostia/AWC contextthis is at least as important as touting community partnership as a goalgot buried in your appendix. And we needed more attention to risks in this high-risk strategy area, si nce planning can trigger markets but not control or 
predict them very well. But in general, the briefing offered a clear exposition 
of key opportunities that lie ahead in a critical strategy area, grounded in a 
solid read of the context. 
 
As for individual speakers and points, Student As  intro was clear and well 
linked to the preview slides. The agenda slide was busy and overly complex; 
this needed another revision or two. Student B  set up the implementation 
speakers effectively, and simple slides helped at this point. Student Cs  
outline on attracting outside retail was missing a reference to retail demand: 
Beyond their concerns about crime and expensive land development, retailers under-estimate the buying power of inner-city communities. This 
would be a key selling point for AWC in this strategy area. Also, we could 
have used the key points about adjusting (Market Creek versus AWI) here. Student D  made an energetic pitch for locally-owned retail, and time ran 
short as Andy and Xav posed questions about how AWC could leverage as much as possible in this relatively high-risk domain. 
Page 1 of 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Overall, you conveyed the potential of a community-responsive retail 
development strategy and highlighted financial and other roles for AWC 
effectively. It would have strengthened your briefing had you highlighted 
risks or pitfalls as well, since the record on locally planned economic 
development is so mixed, and Market Creek is, for now, just one place. 
 
Visual aids (slides) and handout 
As noted above, key slides were so dominated by text that you missed opportunities to use images (whether maps, photos, charts, or other: See Team Rs slides) to strengthen the message and give the viewer-listener relief (variety). You took the admonition to have and use a core message slide seriously, but the graphic even re-appears on the conclusion slideand 
as a logo of colored bubbles on many other slides. It was over-used. 
 
Your other slides reflected solid choices about text, though: Ideas are crisp 
and concisely rendered, and you manage to keep AWCs potential role in view. 
 
Your score and grade 
 
In scoring each group, we weighed substantive argumentation first and foremost, considering delivery only to th e extent that it related directly to 
your effectiveness as argument makers  (or persuaders). Above, we comment 
on style but didnt score it. We consider ed visuals as an additional element, 
weighing content more heavily than use. 
 
Score: 91  Grade: A-  
Page 2 of 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-914-planning-communication-spring-2007/resources/sample2</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-914-planning-communication-spring-2007/resources/sample2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>In general, Students D and E  also had important points but relied heavily 
on notes and rushed somewhat, making it harder for us to understand key 
points made by both. A reference to it is not here, for example, left us 
wondering, as we looked again at  the slide, whats the it? Student Es  
points about reactions of the tenants were critical, but they seemed directed 
at the screen.  
 
Cherie Abbanat noted that transition remarks, to get you from speaker to 
speaker, were some of the teams best, because they were off script. 
 
The closing message could have been simplified for greater impact, and you 
probably should have noted Commo nwealths uncomm on demographic 
make-up. That is, context matters. The supporting slide (Principles for future redevelopment) was too busy, offered too much text. A graphic integrating 
the physical and non-physical elements of your message here would have 
been super. 
 
Visual aids (slides) 
 
Too many of the visuals seemed weakly linked to the spoken points, also 
oddly timed, as though you needed more practice with the slides and some revision to get a clear and persuasive storyboard togethera logical, intuitive package to back up your remarks. 
 
On the other hand, individual slides we re gems, e.g. Slide 8 (Physical design 
interventions), which combines a clear he ader with specific design advice and 
quotes by residents. Plus several that follow in that section. These would be 
enormously helpful to key briefees, or secondary audiences, not in attendance. These have a stand-alone quality. 
 
Score: 90 
Grade: B+ 
 
Page 2 of 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
 
Feedback on Team Briefings 
 
Case: Public housing redevelopment 
 
Team Z 
 
Our evaluation covers your  briefing, visual aids, and handout, though the 
feedback below may offer more on one of those than the other elements. 
 
Briefing  (content and delivery) 
 
Student As  intro was crisp, clear, and engaging. But physical positioning of 
the team was a problem: She seemed hidden behind other team members 
who lurked near the briefees. You need  to minimize distractions and place 
the focus on the speaker and the visuals. 
 
The logic of the briefing was interesting: Tenant engagement is the foundation (not an after-thought), and it enables physical design tools to make a difference. The team didnt come back to the core message enough, reliant as most of you were on a script (written notes). And the two halvesphysical and non-physicalcould  have been much better integrated 
(this was true for almost every team). 
 
Student B , your early points were the clearest, but relying as you did on 
your notes, you missed an opportunity to connect with the audience. Also, watch the wonk-ish
1 jargon: facilitate accountability and reciprocity. It was 
tricky to see the connection between some of these points and the slides 
(see below), tooa problem that affect ed several presenters. One slide per 
main point might have helped us button the two together. 
 
Student Cs  most effective contributions were in response to questions, 
extemporaneous (unscripted), in exchan ge with Xav. Again, this is the 
opportunity  in a briefingto create a conversation that informs or teaches 
important pointsand not a sign of shortcomings. Student Cs  explanation 
of risks in various engagement strategies signaled preparedness, more than 
the easy answers that arent credible (in the field) any more. But on repeated 
questioning, try not to aim for the one right answer. Youre not being tested. 
Youre in an informed conversation with stakes for real decisions: Explore the options with the briefee. You dont need to know everything. 
 
                                       
1 Wonk is an idiom. Its know spelled backward. In the simple st terms. a wonk is 
technically  savvy but only that. Wonks struggle to build constituencies for their 
ideas. We use wonkish to convey a styl e of speech that is needlessly complex, 
even inaccessible. 
Page 1 of 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/11-914-planning-communication-spring-2007/resources/xavbriefing</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-914-planning-communication-spring-2007/resources/xavbriefing/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>0</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 14
Creating the visual aids
Keep them simple
Average attention span
per slide is 8 seconds
Most audiences can handle
about 1 slide per minute
of briefing
Simplify technical concepts with metaphor
The stretching of vorticity
is a difficult physical concept, but comparing it to a skater's conservation of momentum helps to clarify what we mean</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Figure by MIT OCW . Slide 16325
300275
1955 1956Before Stricter Enforcement
After Stricter EnforcementNearly all the important questions are left unanswered by this display: 
Connecticut traffic deaths, Before (1955) 
and after (1956) stricter enforcement by the police against cars exceeding speed limit.
Graphics Must not Quote Data Out of Context
The data here lack context</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 7
Middle: Choose a structure
Cause/Effect
Problem/Solution
Categories or elements of the problem
Questions/Answers
Chronological  historical background</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 19
Image quality matters
Consider size: make images legible, 
intuitive, easily grasped 
Choose colors with care: simpler is often 
better (less distracting)
Make quantitative data accessible: Use 
minimum 16-point font (general rule), use only the data you need.
Dont include inappropriate visuals and 
then apologize for them during the 
briefing .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>30</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 36
How do you look?
Where to Stand?
If you need to pick a place to stand  go left, out of the 
projection line.
Mediate between screen and audience: Direct our attention, you control the focus.
How to Speak?
Project, Project, Project  Practice
Pause after complicated ideas
Avoid a canned sound: Dont rely on a speech script, have a well-informed conversation with the listeners.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>31</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 37
The briefing doesnt live on the screen
Dont read the 
screen
Say more than you 
show
Hand-out more 
than you say
Leave paper trail: important 
audiences may not 
be able to attend</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 8
Begin and end with your message
Highlight Major 
Points
Summarize Recommendations
Synthesize in light of problem/purpose
Outline next steps
Project Progress
Change Requests
Issues
Other InformationS
Y
N
T
H
E
S
I
ZEStatus Report
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 10
Overview
The hub-and-spoke is a well-tested structure for 
briefings aimed at busy decisionmakers.
The hub is your core message(s), expressed in simple, action-oriented language. Its the heart of what you want listeners to remember.
The spokes are the components of the message, which lend supporting evidence or illustration.
Each member of the team should be able to 
move the listener from hub to spoke (or vice-
versa), as needed, at any point in the briefing.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 3
1. Know the audience and context
Make-up: 
Race/ethnicity? Gender? Generation? 
Professional culture or 
affiliation? Size? Political attitudes or loyalties? Education level? Economic status?
Context: How does your 
briefing fit into a sequence of analysis 
and action? Whose 
action?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 1
How to Prepare and Deliver
an Effective Briefing
Xavier de Souza Briggs
Department of Urban Studies + Planning
Course 11.914: Planning Communication
Spring 2007</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 24
Focus on the overall composition
What is the eye drawn to?
Where does the reader want to focus?
Less is more: use a few simple 
elements to make a point</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 30
Preparing and handling questions
Preparing : What doubts is the listener likely to 
have? Where will they want details or extra 
evidence? Where might they challenge us?
During the briefing: Listen carefully. If youre 
unsure about the question, summarize it and 
check
Listen actively (nod, make eye contact, acknowledge)
Answer the question and move on
Say you dont know if you dont know
State that you will gather and provide answers 
later, if necessary</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 5
Begin with the end in mind
Purpose of the briefing 
Recommendations
Roadmap  what structure do you use?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 9
Nonlinear: Hub-and-spoke structure</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 20
Size: Make images legible 
Image courtesy of the CIA &lt;http://www.cia.gov&gt;CUBAlie de la Tortue North Atlantic 
Windward passage ocean
Port-de-Paix
Cap-Haitien
GonaivesGolfe de le Gonave
Saint-Marc Hinchelie de la Gonave
Hispaniola
PORT-AU-PRINCEJeremie
MiragoaneLes Cayes Jacmel
Caribbean SeaDominican Republic
0 30 60 km
0 30 60 ml
Figure by MIT OCW. Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>27</slideno>
          <text>Rehearse
If on the 
sidelines: 
maintain professional composure.
If speaking , 
channel your 
energy, avoid 
distracting gestures.NON-VERBAL COMMUNIATION
SPEAKS LOUDLY
Figure by MIT OCW.
Briefing How-To                     Slide 32</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 12
3. Visual storytelling
The purpose of visual aids is to enhance 
comprehension and retention of important 
ideas. If a slide does not aid (truly add value), drop it.
Except in highly design-oriented or marketing-oriented presentations, the main purpose is not to entertain the audience per se, though 
creating visual interest helps engage us.
The visuals and spoken remarks should be well 
aligned. This is the concept of a visual storyboard (outline) to help you sync the two.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>This adds valuable comparison 
16
14
12
10
8
1951 1953 1955 1957 1959New York
Massachusetts
Connecticut
Rhode Island
Traffic Deaths per 100,000 Person in Connecticut, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, and New York, 1951-1959
Figure by MIT OCW.Briefing How-To                     Slide 18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>29</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 35
Connect with your audience
A presentation is two-way
communication
Pay attention to audience reaction
Modify your talk as needed (are they listening or 
doing something else?)
Look for nods, smiles and other cues to determine if your message is being received.
Direct your answer to a question to the person 
who posed it. Interact naturally, conversationally.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>33</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 39
Special tips to teams
Keep disagreements in perspective: different 
team members will have different instincts about some things;
Dont focus on dividing up air time (speaking 
time) evenlyfocus on whatever will best 
inform the audience, be flexible.
The team is always on: Even the members on the sidelines should reflect the teams professionalism, avoid distracting side 
conversations or body language (e.g. fidgeting). 
Decide who will handle what questions and who 
will direct traffic (coordinate) to avoid awkward pauses</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 22
Simpler may be better 
JAPAN  SEAVLADIVOSTOK
BASIN
YAMATO 
RIDGE
YAMTO 
BASINJAPAN
MURORAN
TRENCH 
RISEHOKKAIDO3000
35003500
2000200020001000500
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 26
Message content: Emotional arguments
Use them sparingly, consider the 
audiences receptiveness
Have a single message
Appeal to our values
Create emotion: Outrage? Wonder? Delight?
Move us to action
Include evidence and examples (reason + emotion = powerful persuasion)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 21
Consider colors: This is complex
JAPAN SEAJAPAN
BASIN
YAMATO 
RIDGEMURORAN35003000500
20002000
TRENCH 
RISE
20001000
HOKKAIDO
VLADIVOSTOKMetres
Metres7000
6000
5000
4000
3000
2000
1000
500
200
7000600050004000300020001000500200Sea Level
Hypsometric / Teintes Hypsometriques
Area below sea level regions
 sous niveau de la merBathymetric Tints / Teintes Bathymeriques
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>32</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 38
Finish Strong
Try to recap your primary message
If culturally appropriate: Thank the 
decisionmakers (or other audience 
members) for their time and attention.
Offer to take questions (or more 
questions).
During Q&amp;A: Use your extra slides (not shown during main briefing), if 
appropriate, to extend or clarify your 
arguments, teach the audience more.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 29
4. Deliver the briefing
Focus and center yourself
Show enthusiasm for 
your subject
Be yourselfdont imitate others styles
Dont read us a scriptmemorize your main points, keep notes at 
hand if you like.
Project your voice so we 
can hear and engage with 
the topic</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>28</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 34
Connect with the audience
Use the terms that your audience knows
Use examples to explain new ideas
Engage the audience
Establish eye contact; look at people not the screen
Use friendly hand gestures
Speak to specific individuals if you know them</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 15
Visual Arguments Need Evidence
Present evidence
Teach with evidence
Convince with 
evidence</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>Abbanat/ -- Effective Oral Presentations                   Slide 24
Make Data AccessibleContent
10.0
8.0
13.0
9.0
11.0
14.06.0
4.0
12.0
7.0
5.08.04
6.95
7.58
8.81
8.33
9.967.24
4.26
10.84
4.82
5.6810.0
8.0
13.0
9.0
11.0
14.06.0
4.0
12.0
7.0
5.09.14
8.14
8.74
8.77
9.26
8.106.13
3.10
9.13
7.26
4.7410.0
8.0
13.0
9.0
11.0
14.06.0
4.0
12.0
7.0
5.07.46
6.77
12.74
7.11
7.81
8.846.08
5.39
8.15
6.42
5.738.0
8.0
8.0
8.0
8.0
8.08.0
19.0
8.0
8.0
8.06.58
5.76
7.71
8.84
8.47
7.045.25
12.50
5.56
7.91
6.89
10 20510
5 15 10 205 15
10 20510
5 15 10 205 15X Y X Y X Y X YI II III IV
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 11
Whatever structure you choose, you will 
need to tell the audience a story, in part 
with visuals</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 4
2. Structuring: Linear is one way to go
Beginning
Middle 
EndSummarize the Issue
Supply the 
recommendations
Craft the analysis
Analyze the issue
Choose a framework
Recap/Synthesis/ Next Steps</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 17
This adds the context 
325
300
275
250
225
1951 1953 1955 1957 1959A few more data points add immensely to the account:
Connecticut Traffic Deaths, 
1951-1959
Figure by MIT OCW .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>34</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 40
Sources
Purpose, Movement, Color: 
A Strategy for Effective Presentations
Tom Mucciolo and Rich Mucciolo, MediaNet, Inc., 
1994
The Quick and Easy Way to Effective Speaking
Dale Carnegie, Dale Carn egie Associates, Inc., 1962
The Visual Display of Quantitative Information
Edward R. Tufte, Graphics Press, 1983</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 2
The tasks
Know your audience
Be clear on the purpose(s) of the briefing and 
the context (location, time, timing vis--vis 
decisions or actions that follow)
Carry out your analysis and prepare 
recommendations
Decide on your core messages
Structure the briefing effectively
Create visual aids to help tell your story
Practice, practice, practice
Deliver responsively</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 6
Middle: Presenting the analysis
Inductive Reasoning  Best Approach
Put the bottom line on top
Use with receptive audiences
D = A + B + C
Deductive Reasoning
Build the case
Mystery novel approach: what happens next?
Use with hostile audiences
A + B + C = D</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>Briefing How-To                     Slide 31
Rehearse
Practice and time the briefing at least 
three (3) times
Get feedback 
Content: Is it clear? Whats persuasive and 
whats not?
Structure : Is it working for you? Is there a better 
way?
Delivery : Is your body supporting the message or 
distracting the audience? Voice effective?
What are the main ways we can improve?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
