<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21l-430-popular-culture-and-narrative-use-and-abuse-of-the-fairy-tale-fall-2015/</course_url>
    <course_title>Popular Culture and Narrative: Use and Abuse of the Fairy Tale</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>Literature </list>
      <list>Fiction </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Angela Carter&#8212;A Brief Guide to Non&#8211;Featured Stories (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21l-430-popular-culture-and-narrative-use-and-abuse-of-the-fairy-tale-fall-2015/resources/mit21l_430f15_angelacarter/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21&#8211;22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21L.430 / CMS.920 Popular Culture and Narrative: Use and Abuse of the Fairy Tale
Fall  2015
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lizanne Henderson and Edward J. Cowan, Scottish Fairy Belief (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21l-430-popular-culture-and-narrative-use-and-abuse-of-the-fairy-tale-fall-2015/resources/mit21l_430f15_lizanne/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9&#8211;10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21L.430 / CMS.920 Popular Culture and Narrative: Use and Abuse of the Fairy Tale
Fall  2015
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Robert Graves, The White Goddess&#8212;A Historical Grammar of Poetic Myth (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21l-430-popular-culture-and-narrative-use-and-abuse-of-the-fairy-tale-fall-2015/resources/mit21l_430f15_robert/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23&#8211;25</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21L.430 / CMS.920 Popular Culture and Narrative: Use and Abuse of the Fairy Tale
Fall  2015
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Christa Kamenetsky, Children&#8217;s Literature in Hitler&#8217;s Germany - The Cultural Policy of National Socialism (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21l-430-popular-culture-and-narrative-use-and-abuse-of-the-fairy-tale-fall-2015/resources/mit21l_430f15_christa/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19&#8211;20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21L.430 / CMS.920 Popular Culture and Narrative: Use and Abuse of the Fairy Tale
Fall  2015
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Key stories from Maria Tatar&#8217;s The Classic Fairy Tales (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21l-430-popular-culture-and-narrative-use-and-abuse-of-the-fairy-tale-fall-2015/resources/mit21l_430f15_tatarclassicfairytales/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5&#8211;6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>  MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21L.430 / CMS.920 Popular Culture and Narrative: Use and Abuse of the Fairy Tale 
Fall 2015 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>  
   
    
   
  
    
    
  
    
    
   
 
  
    
   
  
  
  
  
   
  
       
 
 
 OCW Lecture notes, sessions 5-6: Key stories from Maria Tatar&#8217;s The Classic Fairy Tales 
In order to have a common body of tales from which to work, we considered versions of a 
central group of major stories in Maria Tatar&#8217;s edition, The Classic Fairy Tales 
(New York: 
Norton, 1999), including &#8220;Little Red Riding Hood&#8221;, &#8220;Beauty and the Beast&#8221;, &#8220;Snow White&#8221;, &#8220;Cinderella,&#8221; &#8220;Bluebeard&#8221; and &#8220;Hansel and Gretel&#8221;. We noted the market implications of the 
prettification that the tales underwent at the hands of Perrault, and introduced the concept of 
&#8220;mediation&#8221; to describe the transmutation of oral tales into written literary form intended for upper-class audiences. We queried why Tatar had placed a version of &#8220;Little Red Riding Hood&#8221; 
collected in 1885 ahead of the Perrault text of 1697, concluding that because it was considered to 
be a &#8220;folk tale&#8221; it was therefore presumed to be &#8220;old&#8221;, and hence to ante-date any of the written 
evidence. We gave particular attention to the points about fairy tales as a women's tradition, and 
noted their characteristic symbolic opposition of the domestic and the wild, along with the 
importance of transitions between them (usually perilous). The tales appear to be highly 
dualistic. We noted another polarity, namely the opposition of animal and human (the boundaries 
between which seemed which much more porous in our material than in the general modern 
world view, enabling relatively easy passage between animal and human states); and also 
between the natural and the supernatural, suggesting still another form of dualism, that between 
the natural order and the supernatural one. We talked about the presently accepted boundaries of 
the order of nature as they was defined by the great Victorian scientists (amid protests that they 
were drawing these too narrowly and from an overly-materialist point of view) and the fairy tale 
cosmos which seems to contain parallel realities: the natural order of everyday life strongly 
contrasting with that of the Otherworld, and how this was an asymmetrical relationship, in the 
sense that while supernatural beings were able to enter the natural order freely and at will, if 
mortals strayed into the Otherworld it was generally by invitation and was fraught with hazard 
(leading to yet another symbolic opposition&#8212;that between power and vulnerability&#8212;widely 
present in these stories). 
* </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Albert B. Lord, The Singer of Tales (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21l-430-popular-culture-and-narrative-use-and-abuse-of-the-fairy-tale-fall-2015/resources/mit21l_430f15_albert/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7&#8211;8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21L.430 / CMS.920 Popular Culture and Narrative: Use and Abuse of the Fairy Tale
Fall  2015
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 &#8220;word for word and line for line&#8221;, Lord remarks that what he meant was  
that it was "like" the version in question; obviously, since the  
speaker did not know what a word or a line was.  
"...the pi cture that emerges is not really one of conflict between  
preserver of tradition and creative artist; it is rather one of the  
preservation of tradition by the constant re -creation of it." p.29  
"Memorization is a conscious act of making one's own, and repe ating,  
something that one regards as fixed and not one's own.  The learning  
of an oral poetic language follows the same principles as the learning  
of language itself, not by the conscious schematization of elementary  
grammars but by the natural method. " p.36  
"The theme [he means the various episodes out of which these tales are  
built], even though it be verbal, is not any fixed set of words, but a  
grouping of ideas." p.69  
"A general principle is here involved that is of significance when we  
are deali ng with a tradition being invaded by printed song books:  
namely, that if the printed text is read to an already accomplished  
oral poet, its effect is the same as if the poet were listening to  
another singer.  The song books spoil the oral character of t he  
tradition only when the singer believes that they are the way in which  
the song should be presented.  The song books may spread a song to  
regions where the song has not hitherto been sung; in this respect  
they are like a migrant singer.  But they ca n spoil a tradition only  
when the singers themselves have already been spoiled by a concept of  
a fixed text." p.79  
Versions may change as a singer grows and matures; after maturity is  
reached, about 50, "From the time that maturity is reached and the  
singer has established the general outlines of a theme, evidence seems  
to indicate that he changes it little if at all." p.94.  
  "When the singer of tales, equipped with a store of formulas and  
themes and a technique of composition, takes his place befor e an  
audience and tells his story, he follows the play which he has learned  
along with the other elements of his profession.  Whereas the singer  
thinks of his song in terms of a flexible plan of themes, some of  
which are essential and some of which are  not, we think of it as a  
given text which undergoes change from one singing to another.  We are  
more aware of change than the singer is, because we have a concept of  
the fixity of a performance or of its recording on wire or tape or  
plastic or in writ ing.  We think of change in content and in wording;  
for, to us, at some moment both wording and content have been  
established.  To the singer the song, which cannot be changed (since  
to change it would, in his mind, be to tell an untrue story or to  
6
Lord, Albert B. The Singer of Tales. Harvard University Press, 1960.  &#169; Harvard
University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 Albert B. Lord, The Singer of Tales  (Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard  
U.P., 1960)  
 
These notes are included here, because although they relate to the great 
heroic ballad tradition of the Balkans, rather than to tales and tale telling, 
they vividly captur e compositional and transmission methods in an old 
predominantly oral culture, similar to the ones the Grimms found in north 
Hesse, and Propp in early twentieth century Russia   
 
The story of The Singer of Tales is a rich and interesting one.  
Suggestions had been circulating for some time in the scholarly world  
during the early years of the twentieth century, about an archaic 
performance tradition featuring long heroic songs in the Balkans, which 
took as their topic the wars of the Christians and the Turk s.  These used a 
method of composition -in-performance, a method, apparently 
improvised, that enabled the production of lengthy sung narratives of 
several thousands of lines of length,.  There was a further, sensational, 
suggestion, namely that these oral b ards were using the same methods 
that Homer had, nearly two thousand years previously.  The phenomenon 
prompted a number of intriguing questions: what were the mechanisms of 
transmission here?  When these performers sat down cross legged with 
their one -string gusles and entertained their audiences in taverns and 
coffee -houses, were they performing from memory or was some other 
mechanism in play.  Harvard scholars Milman Parry and Albert Lord 
went to the area to explore this, and made an epic sequence of fie ld-
recordings on aluminium disc, capturing several thousand hours of 
performance.   The results, enshrined in Albert Lord&#8217;s wonderful book, 
The Singer of Tales, were to transform our understanding of oral tradition 
and the processes of transmission in oral  or predominantly oral societies.   
 
Lord says "The singer of tales is at once the tradition and an individual  
creator.  His manner of composition differs from that used by a writer  
in that the oral poet makes no conscious effort to break the  
traditiona l phrases and incidents; he is forced by the rapidity of  
composition in performance to use these traditional elements." p.4  
"With oral poetry we are dealing with a particular and distinctive  
process in which oral learning, oral composition, and oral  
transmission almost merge; they seem to be different facets of the  
same process." p.5  
"Although it may be true that this kind of poetry has survived longest  
among peasant populations, it has done so not because it is  
essentially 'peasant' poetry, but rathe r because the peasant society  
1
Lord, Albert B. The Singer of Tales. Harvard University Press, 1960. &#169; Harvard
University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 has remained illiterate longer than urban society." p.6  
 
There are three ways of looking at the Homeric corpus: one, that it  
was written, and by a single author, Homer, back in the ninth century BC.  
But writing in ancient G reece could not be traced so far back.  
A second theory had Homer as the last brilliant representative of a series 
of &#8220;redactors&#8221; who had gathered oral fragments together and gradually 
cobbled hem together to form  huge written epic structures.  The third 
approach, and the one which Parry and Lord set themselves to document, 
was that Homer was an oral bard, a wandering poet -singer who moved 
around the aristocratic courts of ancient Greece with his lyre, performing 
episodes from the epics that were later gat hered together under his name.  
This raised fascinating questions about his compositional method, and the 
means by which his songs were transmitted orally for nearly three 
centuries, before being codified in written form at the orders of 
Pisistratus, tyran t of Athens in the 6th century BC.   
 
Lord says "These scholars who made the third choice were moving in  
the right direction, namely towards oral tradition, but in putting the  
poet of our Homeric texts before the period of writing, they were  
unwittingly  creating more problems than they were as yet equipped to  
handle.  Their choice was a compromise  Oral tradition was a fickle  
mistress with whom to flirt.  But scholars could call in to their help  
the 'fantastic memories' so 'well attested' of illiterat e people.  They  
felt that a text could remain from one generation to another  
unaltered, or altered only by inconsequential lapses of memory.  This  
myth has remained strong even to the present day.  The main points of  
confusion in the theory of those sc holars who made the third choice  
arose from the belief that in oral tradition there is a fixed text  
which is transmitted unchanged from one generation to another." pp.7 - 
10. 
This idea was first propounded by James Macpherson, the editor of 
Ossian in eigh teenth century Scotland, who posited various mechanisms 
in traditional societies which could ensure that oral material was 
transmitted coherently over long periods of time. 
Lord continues, "The theories of multiple authorship can  
be divided into two general classes.  The first, and the earliest, saw  
the Homeric poems as compil ations of shorter songs, stitched together 
 by their compiler.  D'Aubignac presented this in his Conjectures in  
2
Lord, Albert B. The Singer of Tales. Harvard University Press, 1960.  &#169; Harvard
University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 "It may tru thfully be said that the singer imitates the techniques of  
composition of his master or masters rather than particular songs.   
For that reason the singer is not very clear about the details of how  
he learned his art, and his explanations are frequently in very  
general terms.  He will say that he was interested in the old songs,  
had a passion for them, listened to singers, and then, &#8216;work, work,  
work&#8217; and little by little he learned to sing.  He had no definite  
program of study, of course, no sense of  learning this or that formula  
or set of formulas.  It is a process of imitation and of assimilation  
through listening and much practice on one&#8217;s own." p.24  
The beginner, "has very likely not learned much about &#8216;ornamenting&#8217; a  
song to make it full and b road in its narrative style.  That will  
depend somewhat on his model.  If the singer from whom he has learned  
it is one who uses much 'ornamentation,' he has probably picked up a  
certain amount of that ornamentation too.  Whether his first song is  
fully developed or not, it is complete in its story from beginning to  
end and will tend to follow the story as he heard it from his master.   
If, however, and this is important, he has not learned it from one  
singer in particular, and if the stories of that song differ in the  
various versions which he has heard, he may make a composite of them.   
He may, on the other hand, follow one of them for the most part,  
taking something from the others too.  Either way is consistent with  
the traditional process.  On e can thus see that although this process  
should not be described as haphazard, which it is not, it does not fit  
our own conceptions of learning a fixed text of a fixed song." p.24  
"Our proper understanding of these procedures is hindered by our lack  
of a suitable vocabulary for defining the steps of the process.  The  
singers themselves cannot help us in this regard because they do not  
think in terms of form as we think of it; their descriptions are too  
vague at least for academic preciseness.  [The l earner/performer] without 
writing thinks in terms of sound groups and not in words, and the two do 
not necessarily coincide.  When asked what a word is, he will reply that  
he does not know, or he will give a sound group which may vary in  
length from what  we call a word to an entire line of poetry or even  
an entire song.  The word for 'word' means an 'utterance.'  When the  
singer is pressed then to say what a line is, he, whose chief claim to  
fame is that he traffics in lines of poetry, will be entirely  baffled  
by the question; or he will say that since he has been dictating and  
has seen his utterances being written down, he has discovered what a  
line is, although he did not know it as such before, because he had  
never gone to school.&#8221; p.25  
Of one pa rticular singer who said he had given a particular version  
5
Lord, Albert B. The Singer of Tales. Harvard University Press, 1960.  &#169; Harvard
University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 since there is not 'original' to be varied!" pp.100 -101 
"...'oral transmission', 'oral composition,' 'oral creation,' and  
'oral performance' are all one and the same thing.  Our greatest  
error is to attempt to make 'scientifically' rigid a phenomenon that  
is fluid." p .101 
  "It seems to be highly significant that the words 'author' and  
'original' have either no meaning at all in oral tradition or a  
meaning quite different from the one usually assigned to them." p.101  
  "In the Parry Collection there are songs from si ngers who learned  
them from printed texts.  Their songs, however, are very close to the  
printed versions, and one realizes that the singer was attempting  
consciously to memorize or at least to follow closely what was  
printed.  Singers like [a true trad itional master] Avdo...make no attempt to 
memorize...even when a song is read to them, but singers imbued with the 
idea that the written text is the proper one strive to keep to it even 
verbally if possible.  With them the tradition is dead or dying.  It c ould be 
truly said, I believe that the only way in which they can compensate for  
their lack of awareness of the tradition, that awareness that we are  
beginning to see as deeply conservative, religiously maintaining the  
meaning of a song, is to memorize or attempt to memorize." p.109  
A section follows dealing with the fact that songs vary from fathers to 
sons, and why.&#8221;...one cannot write song.  One cannot lead Proteus 
captive; to bind him is to destroy him.  
  But writing, with all its mystery, came to th e singers&#8217; people, and 
eventually someone approached the singer and asked him to tell the song 
so that he could write down the words.  In a way this was just one more 
performance for the singer, one more in a long series.  Yet it was the 
strangest performa nce he had ever given.  There was no music and no 
song, nothing to keep him to the regular beat except the echo of previous 
singings and the habit they had formed in his mind.  Without these 
accompaniments it was not easy to put the words together as he us ually 
did.  The tempo of composing the song was different, too.  Ordinarily the 
singer could move forward rapidly from idea to idea, from these to theme.  
But now he had to stop very often for the scribe to write down what he 
was saying, after every line o r even after part of a line.  This was difficult, 
because his mind was far ahead.  But he accustomed himself to this new 
process at last, and finally the song was finished.  
  A written text was thus made of the words of song.  It was a record of a 
special performance, a command performance under unusual 
circumstances.  Such has been the experience of many singers in many 
lands, from the first recorded text, I believe, to present times.  And what 
has been said of other performances can be said of it; for tho ugh it is 
8
Lord, Albert B. The Singer of Tales. Harvard University Press, 1960.  &#169; Harvard
University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 singers who have memorized songs from these collections.   
In spite of authentic manner of presentation, in spite of the fact  
that the songs themselves are often oral poems, we cannot consi der  
such singers as oral poets.  They are mere performers.  Such  
experiences have deceived us and have robbed the real oral poet of  
credit as a creative composer; indeed to some extent they have taken  
from epic performance an element of vital interest. " p.14  
Lord begins, intriguingly, by looking not at the singer, but at the  
audience, because, he argues, their situation, horizons of expectation, and 
attention span have a direct shaping influence on the singer's approach to 
his material.  
"If we are full y aware that the singer is composing as he sings, the  
most striking element in the performance itself is the speed with  
which he proceeds.  It is not unusual for a Yugoslav bard to sing at  
the rate of from ten to twenty ten -syllable lines a minute.   
Since...he has not memorized his song, we must conclude either that he  
is a phenomenal virtuoso or that he has a special technique of  
composition outside our field of experience.  We must rule out the  
first of these alternatives because there are too many  singers; so  
many geniuses simply cannot appear in a single generation or continue  
to appear inexorably from one age to another.  The answer, of course,  
lies in the second alternative, namely, a special technique of  
composition." p.17  
Lord sees the exi stence of literacy and written/printed texts as deadly -- 
not to the songs t
hemselves, but to the method of composition by which 
they are realised [which in the end amounts to the same thing] --schools, 
cities, and literacy event
ually put paid to it in urban  areas. p.20 
"We must remember that the oral poet has no idea of a fixed model text  
to serve as his guide.  He has models enough but they are not fixed  
and he has no idea of memorizing them in a fixed form.  Every time he  
hears a song sung, it is differ ent." p.22  
"Sometimes there are published versions of songs in the background.   
[Named Informant] in Bihac told us that he did not learn to sing until  
he was about twenty -eight (he was forty -five in 1935), and that he had  
learned his songs from the song  books, the Matica Hrvatska collection  
in particular.  Although he could not read, somebody had read them to  
him.  He had also heard the older singers in his district.  The  
entrance of these song books into the tradition is a very interesting  
phenomeno n, and one that is open to gross misinterpretation.  Yet as  
long as the singer himself remains unlettered and does not attempt to  
reproduce the songs word for word, these books have no other effect on  
him than that of hearing the song." p.23  
4
Lord, Albert B. The Singer of Tales. Harvard University Press, 1960.  &#169; Harvard
University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 1715, but it was Lachmann and his followers in the nineteenth century  
who made serious attempts to dissect the poems according to his lieder  
theories.  The attempts were unsuccessful and unconvincing; for the  
dissectors could not agree on where to use the scalpel.  The theory  
was discredited [...] The work of the first group of dissectors led to  
several valuable compilations.   [Elias] Lonnr ot [1802 -1884] put together 
the Finnish Kalevala , the Estonians entered the competition with the 
Kalevipoeg , and the Serbs attempted a number of &#8220;national&#8221; epics on the 
Kosovo theme.  But nothing comparable to the Homeric poems was 
produced. The problem of  the way in which the Homeric poems had 
attained their length, if they were not literary productions of a single 
author, remained unsolved." pp.10 -11.  
"They knew and spoke often of folk ballad and epic, they were aware of  
variants in these genres, yet th ey could see only two ways in which  
those variants could come into being: by lapse of memory or by wilful  
change.  This seemed so obvious, so much an unquestioned basic 
assumption, that they never thought to investigate exactly how a 
traditional poetry o perated.   
They always thought in terms of a fixed text or a fixed group of texts  
to which a poet did something for a reason within his own artistic or  
intellectual self.  They could not conceive of a poet composing a line  
in a certain way because of ne cessity or because of the demands of his  
traditional art." p.11  
Comparing their recordings, Parry and Lord felt able to say: "Our singer 
of tales is a composer of tales.  Singer, performer,  
composer, and poet are one under different aspects but at the sa me  
time.  Singing, performing, composing are facets of the same act.  
  It is sometimes difficult for us to realize that the man who is  
sitting before us singing an epic song is not a mere carrier of the  
tradition but a creative artist making the traditi on." p.13  
This was a sensational finding.  But it was complicated by the fact that 
the south Slavs had had a written tradition for a thousand years when 
Parry and Lord began their work, and it was true that many of the 
traditional singers who seemed to per form in the true authentic manner 
were in fact performing memorised written material which had been 
circulating for some time.  But there was a deeper strand, a still lingering 
technique that had survived the onset of literacy and still preserved the 
compo sitional methods of an almost unimaginable antiquity.  
"The majority of such 'folk' singers are not oral poets.  The  
collector even in a country such as Yugoslavia, where published  
collections have been given much attention for over a century, some of  
which have become almost sacrosanct, must be wary; for he will find 
3
Lord, Albert B. The Singer of Tales. Harvard University Press, 1960.  &#169; Harvard
University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 in Yugoslavia only a comparatively small number of the older people are 
still unable to rea d and write.  Common fare in all school books have 
been the songs from Vuk&#8217;s collection or, to a lesser extent, from Njegos&#8217;s 
work [&#8230;]  
  The effect on the younger generation which could read was that the 
young people began to memorize songs from the books.   They still 
learned the art from their elders and could sing songs picked up from oral 
tradition, but they were moving away from that tradition by memorizing 
some of their repertory from the song books.  The memorization from a 
fixed text influenced their  other songs as well, because they now felt they 
should memorize even the oral versions.  The set, &#8216;correct&#8217; text had 
arrived, and the death knell of the oral process had been sounded.  There 
are very few younger singers, particularly among the Christian 
population, who have not been infected by this disease.  This is somewhat 
less true among the Moslems, because none of their collections has been 
given the almost sacred authority of Vuk&#8217;s or Njegos&#8217;s.&#8221; pp.136 -7. 
  &#8221;The singers who accept the idea of a fixe d text are lost to oral 
traditional processes.  This means death to oral tradition and the rise of a 
generation of &#8216;singers&#8217; who are reproducers rather than re -creators.  Such 
are the men who appear in costume at folk festivals and sing the songs 
they have memorized from Vuk&#8217;s collection.  You or I could do the same 
with a certain amount of training and with a costume.  These &#8216;singers&#8217; are 
really counterfeits masquerading as epic bards!  They borrow the songs of 
real singers complete from first word to last ; one can follow the text in 
the book.  They are a menace to the collector.  The idea of the fixed text 
has been established in them, but they are not by this token literary poets, 
even though they are now members of the community of those with 
written &#8216;me ntality&#8217;, in spite of the fact that some of them are still 
unlettered.  
  The change has been from stability of essential story, which is the goal 
of oral tradition, to stability of text, or the exact words of the story.  The 
spread of the concept of fixity among the carriers of oral traditional epic 
is only one aspect of the transition from an oral society to a written 
society.  Ironically enough, it was the collector and even more those who 
used his collection for educational, nationalistic, political, or religious 
propaganda who presented the oral society with a fixed form of its own 
materials...Today in Yugoslavia the transition under this aspect is nearly 
complete.  The oral process is now nearly dead.&#8221; p.138  
 
     * 
11
Lord, Albert B. The Singer of Tales. Harvard University Press, 1960.  &#169; Harvard
University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 written, it is oral.  The singer who dictated it was its &#8216;author,&#8217; and it 
reflected a single moment in the tradition.  It was unique.  
  Yet, unwittingly perhaps, a fixed text was established.  Proteus was 
photographed, and no matter under what ot her forms he might appear in 
the future, this would become the shape that was changed; this would be 
the &#8216;original&#8217;.  Of course, the singer was not affected at all.  He continued 
as did his confreres, to compose and sing as he always had and as they 
always  had.  The tradition went on.  Nor was his audience affected.  They 
thought in his terms, in the terms of multiformity.  But there was another 
world, of those who could read and write, of those who came to think of 
the written text not as the recording of a moment of the tradition but as 
the song.  This was to become the difference between the oral way of 
thought and the written way.&#8221; pp.124 -125. 
He speaks of the kinds of things that happen to a text when the singer is 
asked to dictate it without singing an d pausing after each verse, and there 
are two effects both with obvious potential relevance to Fairy Tales, one 
is that performers can&#8217;t do it outside their usual setting and at a totally 
different speed from what they&#8217;re used to, and the resulting text is  inferior 
to their normal standard, verse frequently being interspersed with 
explanatory prose and so on.  The other effect, and you get this with the 
most able singers, is a very superior text, of conspicuous length and 
richness of ornament, precisely bec ause the singer has more time to think, 
and his talent makes him less context bound.  This latter is what Lord 
thinks happened in the case of Homer, as he explains in the second, 
Homeric, section of his book. pp.126 -7 
  &#8220;The use of writing in setting down oral texts does not per se  have any 
effect on oral tradition.  It is a means of recording.  The texts thus 
obtained are in a sense special; they are not those of normal performance, 
yet they are purely oral, and at their best they are finer than those of 
normal performance.  They are not &#8216;transitional,&#8217; but are in a class by 
themselves.  
  It is necessary for us to face squarely the problem of &#8216;transitional&#8217; texts.  
Is there in reality such a phenomenon as a text which is transitional 
between oral and writte n literary tradition?&#8221; p.128  An important point 
this in traditional Homeric studies.  Lord thinks not: &#8220;...this process is not 
a transition from an oral to a literary technique of composition.  It is a 
transition from oral composition to simple performanc e of a fixed text, 
from composition to reproduction.  This is one of the most common ways 
in which an oral tradition may die; not when writing is introduced, but 
when published song texts are spread among singers.  But our singer does 
not necessarily bloss om forth as a literary poet.  He usually becomes ---
nothing at all.&#8221; p.130  
9
Lord, Albert B. The Singer of Tales. Harvard University Press, 1960.  &#169; Harvard
University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 falsify history), is the essence of the story itself.  His idea of stability, to 
which he is deeply devoted, does not include the wording, which to him 
has never been fixed, nor the unessential parts of the story.  He builds his 
performance, or song in our se nse, on the stable skeleton of narrative, 
which is the song in his sense." p.99  
  "We are occasionally fortunate enough to be present at a first  
singing, and we are then disappointed, because the singer has not  
perfected the song with much practice and b y the text of repeated  
performance.  Even after he has --and it may change much as he works it  
over--it must be accepted and sung by other singers in order to become  
a part of the tradition, and in their hands it will go through other  
changes, and so th e process continues from generation to generation.   
We cannot retrace these steps in any particular song.  There was an  
original, of course, but we must be content with the texts that we  
have and not endeavour to 'correct' or 'perfect' them in accordanc e  
with a purely arbitrary guess at what the original might have been.  
  Indeed, we should be fully aware that even had we this 'original,'  
let us say, of the wedding of Smailagic Meho, we would not have the  
original of the basic story, that is the song of the young man who  
goes forth into the world to win his spurs.  We would have only the  
application of this story to the hero Meho.  Each performance is the  
specific song, and at the same time it is the generic song.  The song  
we are listening to is ' the song'; for each performance is more than a  
performance; it is a re -creation.  Following this line of thinking, we  
might term a singer's first singing of a song as a creation of the  
song in his experience. Both synchronically and historically there  
would be numerous creations and re -creations of the song.  This  
concept of the relationship between 'songs' (performances of the same  
specific or generic song) is closer to the truth than the concept of  
an 'original' and 'variants'.  In a sense each per formance is 'an'  
original, if not 'the' original.  
  The truth of the matter is that our concept of 'the original,' of  
'the song,' simply makes no sense in oral tradition.  To us it seems  
so basic, so logical, since we are brought up in a society in whic h  
writing has fixed the norm of a stable first creation in art, that we  
feel there must be an 'original' for everything.  The first singing in  
oral tradition does not coincide with this concept of the 'original.'   
We might as well be prepared to face t he fact that we are in a  
different world of thought, the patterns of which do not always fit  
our cherished terms.  In oral tradition the idea of an original is  
illogical.  
  It follows, the, that we cannot correctly speak of a 'variant',  
7
Lord, Albert B. The Singer of Tales. Harvard University Press, 1960.  &#169; Harvard
University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 &#8220;One of the difficulties in comprehending the change from oral to written 
style lies in the fact that we think of the written always in terms of 
quality, and that of the highest.  We  assume without thinking that written 
style is always superior to oral style,  even from the very beginning .  
Actually this is an error in simple observation of experience, perpetrated 
alas by scholars who have shunned experience for the theoretical.  A 
superior written style is the development of generations.  When a 
tradition or an individual goes from oral to written, he, or it, goes from an 
adult, mature style of one kind to a faltering and embryonic style of 
another sort...  
  While the presence of writi ng in a society can have an effect on oral 
tradition, it does not necessarily  have an effect at all.  The fact of writing 
does not inevitably involve a tradition of written literature; even if it did, 
a tradition of written literature does not inevitably i nfluence an oral 
tradition.  The Southern Slavs had a tradition of written literature since 
the end of the ninth century; indeed they invented the alphabets used by 
the Slavs.  Yet this written tradition had no influence on the form of the 
oral tradition u ntil the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.  The two 
existed side by side, not, of course, within the same group, but certainly 
within the same district.  In mediaeval times, writing and written 
literature, first on foreign models but soon developing alon g its own lines, 
were cultivated in the monasteries, as in the rest of Europe.  The carriers 
of oral tradition were the unlettered people outside the monasteries.  
Beginning in the fifteenth century on the Adriatic coast and on some of 
the islands, particu larly in the cities of Split, Zadar, and Dubrovnik, again 
under foreign influence and with foreign models at first, a rich literary 
tradition arose not only among the clergy, but more especially among the 
wealthy merchant aristocracy.  In the villages surr ounding these cities and 
among the other classes of the population in the cities, that is, among 
those who were not of patrician families and not educated in the schools 
abroad, or later at home, oral tradition continued to flourish among the 
unlettered.  In both these instances the literary tradition was not a 
development from the oral tradition.  It was stimulated from outside, from 
Byzantium or from Italy.&#8221; pp.134 -135 
 
 What has been the effect of the collections on the tradition itself?  The 
larger, mor e expensive editions did not reach the communities in which 
the singing was cultivated, nor did they have any effect in places where 
there was no person who could read.  But during the nineteenth century 
schools began to spread slowly, and after World War 1 schools were to be 
found in most communities.  Since the establishment of the Communist 
regime a concentrated battle against illiteracy has been going on, and now 
10
Lord, Albert B. The Singer of Tales. Harvard University Press, 1960.  &#169; Harvard
University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see http://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ellis and the Grimms; German nationalism; folk tradition; oral and written culture (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21l-430-popular-culture-and-narrative-use-and-abuse-of-the-fairy-tale-fall-2015/resources/mit21l_430f15_ellisgrimms/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1&#8211;4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>  
 
  
 
 
  
 
    
 
  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 volume scholarly work, intended to be taken very seriously indeed and possessing the usual 
hallmarks of the type: scholarly apparatus, notes on the text, preface, list of abbreviations, 
acknowledgments, introduction, glossary, bibliography, footnotes, endnotes, appendices, index&#8212; 
the slimmed down tale-only versions of the Grimms&#8217; text came later.  
Then we turned to consider Ellis&#8217;s account of the Brothers Grimm in more detail, centering on 
informant Dorothea Viehmann, and the fact that she seems to have been &#8212;1) literate; 2) middle 
class; 3) French-speaking, and asked how these characteristics might af
fect her status as a source.  
We went from there to considered the specific details of Ellis&#8217;s case against the Grimms.  
The Grimms claimed that they had collected from the peasantry and subsequent scholars 
believed them; that their tales, therefore, represented in a direct and faithful way the Volksgeist, 
the cultural core, of the German people.  This belief became so entrenched that even when powerful evidence accumulated in the 20
th century that they had (a) collected from their 
bourgeois&#8212;frequently French-speaking&#8212;neighbors and friends amongst the lesser aristocracy and had (b) systematically bowdlerized and re-written between successive editions the materials 
they had got, the belief that they had captured the very soul of the German people was so deeply 
entrenched in the learned world that this evidence had never been accorded its proper weight. 
Ellis considered the extent of the Brothers&#8217; personal interventions in the text, their habitual re-
alignment of the family relationships at the heart of so many of these stories, substituting wicked 
step-mothers for actual birth-mothers and erasing the frequent traces of father/daughter incest, 
hence considerably distorting the message of the original tales. 
As a class we were particularly interested in the assumptions about the links between language 
and literature and the projection of power which underlay the whole enterprise. W
idening out a 
little, we considered the differences between &#8220;hard&#8221; and &#8220;soft&#8221; power; the concept of &#8220;cultural imperialism&#8221; --the global dominance of English, for example, enabling people all over the world 
to be exposed to the full blast of Anglo-American popular culture.  Then we noted the cultural 
prestige and power of writers (&#8220;the chief glory of every people arises from its authors&#8221; as Dr. 
Johnson remarked): the idea that Great Countries have Great Literature, (as we see at home in 
the Center for Editions of American Authors founded by the Modern Language Association at 
the height of the Cold War to establish a core of classic texts able to rival anything the rest of the 
world could produce), and it was to renew the power and prestige of German letters that the 
brothers Grimm began their work. 
So we saw something of a great scholarly controversy about the nature of oral vs. written 
tradition, during which many of the assumptions people commonly have about Fairy Tales came 
to the surface and we
re seen to be controversial, and contested; the idea of folk culture and the 
status of oral tradition; links between language and culture and identity, who and what one is; 
and complex issues about the inheritance from the past and how it should be treated.  Culture and Nationalism, is a powerful motif here, the idea (which should be well to the front of the minds of 
all students of writing) that there is a body of quasi-sacred texts called &#8220;Literature&#8221; which not 
only offer unique insight into the world and the way it works; but as also somehow constituting 
the life-blood of the nation, a kind of extended and permanent national consciousness, so that if 
one were to ask, say &#8220;who and what are the American people&#8221; one could simply point to the 
canon of American literature and say &#8220;that&#8221;. The more deeply we are read in this material, the 
more fully we realize ourselves as representatives in the deepest sense of our national cultures. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text> 
 
 
 
 
  
 
  
 
  
 
  
  
 
  
  
  
 
 
 
 Sessions 1-4: Ellis and the Grimms; German nationalism; folk tradition; oral and written 
culture. 
A good place to start is to consider what we generally mean by &#8220;Fairy Tales&#8221;. A typical 
formulation might contain some or all of the following properties: &#8220;old; magical; peopled by 
types rather than heavily individuated characters; formulaic; oral; for children&#8221;. We then 
read 
Ellis, chapters 1-3, and found that the Grimms&#8217; work took place in a context of growing German nationalism, with an intense focus on German language and culture. The collection was 
envisaged by the Grimms as a serious work of philology, an attempt to reform and re-build 
German Literature then awakening from a lengthy period of relative eclipse, to challenge French 
linguistic and cultural dominance. From there we pass ed to the concept of oral tradition, the 
doctrine of &#8220;survivals&#8221;, and of the cultural shortcomings of Modernity&#8212;the central idea here being that a separate and distinctive strand of culture, later called &#8220;folklore&#8221;, was preserved in 
oral tradition by the common people, and that although sustained by living memories, some of its 
contents were extremely ancient. One key earlier text here was James Macpherson in the 
elaborate scholarly apparatus to his sensationally-successful edition of the Poems of Ossian 
(1765) which had made the argument for the coherence of oral tradition and its ability to transmit 
cultural materials in a stable form over long periods of time, so that most contemporaries 
considered that contact with orality guaranteed, ipso facto, contact with high antiquity. We 
needed to remind ourselves about such matters, because in the university reforms of the later 
nineteenth century folklore arrived too late on the scene to establish itself as a central academic 
discipline, so that there are only a handful of departments in America today.  
Our starting point was James Macpherson and the overwhelming impact upon the European 
intelligentsia of Ossian, 
the epic poem ostensibly collected in the Highlands of Scotland during 
the middle years of the eighteenth century.  The argument was that things of great cultural richness might be found in oral tradition, in the custody of the common people. The culture of 
literacy was artificial and expensive to maintain.  It was also bland and homogeneous, since 
literate intellectuals all tend ed to read the same things and think in the same way.  So that the 
bearers of the oral tradition might actually be the true custodians of national identity&#8212;and also its creators. &#8220;Das Volk dichtet&#8221;, said the Grimms (&#8220;The People create&#8221;), and this proved a 
powerful idea subsequently. As an example, we considered briefly how American historian Frederick Jackson Turner (1861-1932) had used this model to argue that the true real America 
was found not on the Europeanized east coast but out in the Wild West, on the Frontier.  So it 
had to be amongst the common people and nowhere else that theory suggested the Grimms 
should find their evidence, as they themselves appear ed to acknowledge, but&#8212;if Ellis is right&#8212; 
this wasn&#8217;t quite how things turned out.  
A number of conceptual challenges meet us, therefore, on entering this field: forming some grasp 
of oral tradition and how it worked and the things it contained being of obvious importance.  
Also, we need to know something about the cultural politics of Europe at the time. When the 
Grimms began their work, the Napoleonic wars were in progress and their native Hesse/Kassel 
was under French military occupation. In addition, Germany was politically divided into a 
myriad of small principalities and 
France was culturally dominant, French being the preferred 
language of the upper classes in much of Europe. The Grimms&#8217; object was to rebuild German literature on the foundations of a vigorous genuinely national tradition, and to this end what they 
published was not a fairy-tale volume of the kind we are familiar with nowadays, but a big multi -
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text> 
  
 
  
   
  
   
  
 
 
   
 
       
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
  
       We also touched upon the intriguing question of the ownership of tradition: whether we should 
consider popular literature as produced for the people, or as produced by them. Some 
approaches consider the common people as the mere passive custodians of a once-aristocratic 
tradition which had long ago fallen into their possession as fashions altered further up the social 
scale. This is the so-called &#8220;trickle down&#8221; theory, and we consider it in more detail when we 
turn to the writings of the great Russian folklorist Vladimir Propp. It arises again with the 
creation of a mass &#8220;pop culture&#8221; during the twentieth century. 
The overall strategy was to develop an approach which did not treat the text as a stable and self-
sufficient object to be pinned upon a dissecting table and taken apart using various formalistic 
critical approaches; not just to consider the wider  perspective offered by the comparative study 
of genres and their rise and fall, but of how the very substance of what we call &#8220;literature&#8221; is 
affected by things far indeed from the surface of textuality, scarcely even belonging to the study 
of &#8220;literature&#8221; as normally conceived, but involving 
wide international forces, social, economic, 
and political, which our texts hold briefly in equilibrium, presenting a unique point of cultural vantage.  
* 
From a more practical point of view, in class, we considered how to look ahead to pace work 
demands over the approaching weeks, since the load cannot be distributed completely equally, one should pace oneself and fit it in to one&#8217;s other schedules wherever one can. In any course 
one should at an early stage, as a matter of routine, look at previous test papers if there is an 
examination, because this indicates what the course designers thought important, and permits 
information gathering to proceed in the most efficient and intelligent way. Since we have 
continuous assessment here we look at essay no 1, and try to suss out what it might require, chief 
amongst which would seem to be the ability to give a clear outline version of what the Grimms 
were about and why, and what Ellis thought about them. The face-to-face version of the class 
also laid much stress the dangers of plagiarism and the value of the square bracket in 
distinguishing one&#8217;s own work from other peoples&#8217; while note taking; the value of pencil 
annotation and marginalia in the set texts, and the usefulness of compiling summative notes in 
the process of internalization. Above all, ensuring that material downloaded or cut and pasted 
from the net was identified as such&#8212;by quote marks, colored type, or other typographical 
device, and always including sources and page numbers so that what is your work and what is 
other people&#8217;s remains clearly distinguished.  
The taught version of the Class stressed the value of online research, and how to use a number of 
subscription-only scholarly sites, such as the Oxford English Dictionary, The Oxford Dictionary 
of National Biography, 
and JSTOR. For example, looking up the word &#8220;tradition&#8221; in the OED, 
reveals many historical uses of the term and gives a good idea of what people have meant by it down the centuries.  Using JSTOR, we were able to track down a number of reviews of Ellis&#8217;s 
One Fairy Story Too Many: The Brothers Grimm and their Tales in a number of scholarly 
journals. Books of reputation are likely to be noticed in this way, so a survey of scholarly 
reviews is a speedy way of gaining an informed overview of any particularly &#8220;hot&#8221; book or topic.  
We found that Ellis&#8217;s characteristically plain-spoken manner had raised eyebrows in the 
scholarly community, but his conclusions had not been significantly challenged. 
* 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text> 
  
   
  
 
     
  
 
  
   
  
    
  
   
     
 
 
 
  
 
 
  
 
 
  
  
 
   
 
 
  
  
 
 
    
 Likewise a number of questions were touched upon which were to loom larger as the class 
progressed; the growth, for example, of children&#8217;s literature, i.e. writing specifically for a 
youthful audience.  We think of classic titles, such as Winnie-the-Pooh;  The Wind in the 
Willows; Peter Pan; Treasure Island; Harry Potter (a brilliant attempt to have a text mature in 
step with its first audience), but these are essentially literary.  There are innumerable illustrated 
stories which loom large in modern childhoods&#8212;from The Very Hungry Caterpillar; Where&#8217;s 
Spot? The Elephant and the Bad Baby; Janet and Alan Ahlberg&#8217;s books (their most popular 
work The Jolly Postman sold six million, think of it, six million copies. There&#8217;s an interesting 
Youtube video (you get it by keying in &#8220;The Jolly Postman&#8221; with a cute kid reading her way 
through it, and doing so well, taking out all the letters the Postman delivers, including 
Goldilocks&#8217; note of apology to the Three Bears, and an advertising circular addressed to the 
Wicked Witch); down to that characteristic modern production, The Little Vampire which 
unsettlingly conflates the genres of gothic and juvenile fiction. We were presented at several 
points in the class with a chance to look at the creation of emergent literary forms.  The development of the Fairy Tale as a distinct literary type overlaps with a good deal of this, and so 
offers an excellent vantage point from which to observe a wide spectrum of  cultural change. 
There are wide-ranging gender questions as well: the idea is that the Fai ry Tale is 
 essentially a 
women&#8217;s tradition.  This seem distinctly plausible on the face of things, when one bears in mind  
the largely female informants in the Wild and Hassenpflug families from which the Grimms got 
so many of their tales, and, of course, their star informant, Dorothea Viehmann.  There is the 
considerable input of French courtly women writers at the end of the 17th and beginning of the 
18th century. As we go on we find this motif return again and again, climaxing in the work of 
Angela Carter and Liz Lochhead in the later years of the twentieth century.  This was a theme 
especially close to the hearts of the pioneers of the feminist revival of the 1970s, and the 
attendant implication that the great fairy tale tradition was essentially highjacked by male 
collectors and editors with their greater social power and access to the press at periods when it 
was scarcely considered respectable for a woman of birth to be a published author.  So we add to 
the complex web of appropriation and counter-appropriation the Grimms making off with 
essentially French stories; then a group of men--Basile, Straparola, Perrault, the Grimms, Hans 
Christian Andersen, Walt Disney, making off with women&#8217;s stories, so that true tradition is 
continually being overlaid by something else, becoming a kind of palimpsest.  
There is the recurring question of commercialization and the exploitation for profit of cultural 
commons, and the resulting overlap between &#8220;folk&#8221; and popular culture which we examine in 
detail when we come to Disney 
This includes the growth of the concept of the &#8220;folk&#8221; itself, and 
what were thought to be its properties. This is linked with fascinating questions of distribution.  The Grimms attempted to assert the cultural distinctiveness of one particular national strand of 
tradition, although, as Ellis suggests, their standing as leading philological scholars should have 
made them well aware of the international distribution of much of the material with which they 
worked. Fairy Tales really seem to be a global phenomenon, and as the class went on we 
considered various theories about whether they are produced by all societies at a particular stage 
of development, or whether they sprang into being in a small number of culturally favored spots, 
such as the Nile delta, or northern India, and were diffused from there along the trade routes into 
the West.  You do not have to dig very deeply into commentary on early Italian collectors such 
as Straparola and Basile before you find the Middle East and even China being cited as the 
ultimate source of tales transmitted to the West through the great portal of Renaissance Venice.  
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>  MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
21L.430 / CMS.920 Popular Culture and Narrative: Use and Abuse of the Fairy Tale 
Fall 2015 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Calvin S. Hall and Vernon J. Nordby, A Primer of Jungian Psychology (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21l-430-popular-culture-and-narrative-use-and-abuse-of-the-fairy-tale-fall-2015/resources/mit21l_430f15_calvins/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14&#8211;15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21L.430 / CMS.920 Popular Culture and Narrative: Use and Abuse of the Fairy Tale
Fall  2015
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <videos>
      <video>
        <video_url/>
        <video_title/>
        <transcript>
          <slice>
            <text_slice/>
            <time_slice/>
          </slice>
        </transcript>
      </video>
    </videos>
  </lectures>
</doc>
