<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/</course_url>
    <course_title>Pricing</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Economics </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Business </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec07</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec07/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 OUT-PRICING 
ooding the US mark et with below-cost bromine, at an even lower 
price than Dows. But Dow simply instructed their agents to buy up 
US Bromine at the very low price, then sell it back in German y at 
a prot but still lower than Bromk onventions price. In the end, the 
cartel could not keep up selling below cost, and had to give in. 
(2) Low Qual ity Trap 
	Customers assume qualit y is low 
(3) Fragile Mark et Share Trap 
	The consumers you attract are not loyal. Sprin t has found that its 
recen t 25% discoun t plan has led to higher churn. The problem is that 
the defecting customers are only 2.6% of their total number of year
end subscrib ers. The risk is that the other 97.4% of the custome rs are 
going to want discoun ts too.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 OUT-PRICING 
	Bad Comm unication example: In 1997 Compaq Computer Corp CEO 
Eckhard Pfeier claimed that his compan ys new busin ess model and 
aggressiv e price cuts will not lead to the price war among major 
PC makers that some were anticipating. The compan y says...the an
nounced prices make the DeskPros 6-8% cheap er than the comparable 
Dell oerings. Pfeier [says]... all-out war will be averted because 
cuts by other manufacturers will come from their margins, obviously 
something Pfeier feels wont carry too far given current mark et pres
sure. 
 Explain yourself if you are changing your prices to avoid retaliation 
	Heart monitor manufacturer had to sell o multiple units that didnt 
comply with proposed FTC regulation , so they reduced price. This 
set o a price war as their comp etitors did not understand what they 
were doing. 
3.	Responding to Competitive Price Erosion Using the Other 3Ps 
Sabotage Customer Perceptions of Price Cut by exploiting Product, Promotion 
and Placemen t 
3.1. Product. 
	Develop a Fighting Brand. Read Should You Launc h A Fighter Brand? 
by Mark Ritson in Harv ard Business Review, Octob er 2009 before you do. 
	Intel used its Celeron chip to ght price wars with rather than its 
premium Pentium chips reasonably successfully . 
	Deltas Song airlin e did not stave o JetBlue. 
	Impro ved Product 
	Norton Anti-Virus. After McAfee came in oering Net-to-Zero re
bate, Syman tec examined customer researc h showing that customers 
wanted more manageabilit y across products (AV + Utilities). Instead, 
they responded by shifting to a value bundle. Norton SystemW orks, 
which was a well integrated suite of great point products with a sin
gle, easy-to-use user interface. Syman tec built a lead in protabilit y 
from retail segm ents, while McAfee retreated and continued to invest 
in corporate solutions. 
3.2. Promotion. One danger of price wars is that a promotional message can get 
lost. However, promotion can actually be an eectiv e tool to counter price erosion. 
	South west Airlines, for example, responded to Americans value-pricing 
move not with a price move of its own but rather with an advertisin g</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 OUT-PRICING 
discuss anything that was illegal. And we knew the law and I knew it well, 
he said. Whatever we do, we mustn t discuss prices, Mason said. Tennan t 
said that was the rst thing that Taubman mentioned to him. 
	Airlines colluded between 2004 and 2006 to levy heavy fuel surcharges on 
transatlan tic ights. Virgin Atlantic escap ed nan cial punishmen t because 
it came forward to expose the collusion. BA was ned $200 million by the 
Oce of Fair Trading, Britains comp etition watchdog, and $300 million 
by the DoJ. Virgin Atlantic escaped nancial punishmen t because it came 
forward to expose the collusion. Keith Packer, cargo manager, got eight 
months in US prison and a $20k ne for his part in rigging the cost of price 
services to and from America. 
	Peter Baci, Senior VP of Yield Managemen t for Sea Star Line, LLC, got 4 
years in prison for xing the prices of cargo shipped between the US and 
Puerto Rico. Baci claimed in court that he was acting on orders, but this 
didnt help him at sentencing. 
1.2. Predatory pricing. Pricing low with an intent to drive your comp etitor out 
of business can be prosecuted under the anti-monop olization regulation s of the 
Sherman Act. However, the Supreme Court ruled in 1986 that fare wars that do 
not drive out comp etitors are a boon to consumers, and the governmen t must 
be very careful not to chill the very conduct the antitrust laws are designed to 
protect. 
2. Preempting Competitive Price Erosion 
One thing to note is that in some sense comp etitiv e price erosion is becoming less 
of a concern empirically . According to RSR Researc h (January 2010), the exten t 
to which pricing aggressiv eness from comp etitors was considered a challenge fell 
from 48% to 38%. Instead, price erosion became more driven by internal pressure 
to impro ve sales. 
2.1. Assessing risk of price erosion. 
2.1.1. At risk. 
(1) Falling Demand 
(2) Spare Capacit y 
(3) Few dierences in dieren tiation value 
Beer is classic example of a product where there is a potential for price wars. It is 
an undieren tiated product with high xed costs. Falling demand due to increased 
demand for wine and other alternativ es.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>OUT-PRICING 
Anheuser-Busc h executiv es last month said they were lowering prices 
to win back drinkers who are choosing wine and spirits over beer. 
Miller, the No. 2 U.S. brew er, will matc h Anheuser-Busc hs cuts to 
avoid losing mark et share heading into the summer season. 
Contents 
1. Legal Regulation of Pricing 1
1.1. Price xing and bid rigging 2
1.2. Predatory pricing 3
2. Preempting Competitive Price Erosion 3
2.1. Assessing risk of price erosion 3
2.2. Assessing competitors pricing sophistication 4
2.3. Pricing threat 5
2.4. Talking to the press about pricing 5
3. Responding to Competitive Price Erosion Using the Other 3Ps 6
3.1. Product 6
3.2. Promotion 6
3.3. Placement 7
3.4. Why not lower price? 7
In this lecture series we have intentionally ignored competitors. We did this to avoid 
a natural tendency to let competitors dictate prices. Instead, we have focused on 
pricing techniques intended to erect and protect price fences that allow us to defend 
our value proposition from competitors. 
1. Legal Regulation of Pricing 
People of the same trade seldom meet together, even for merriment 
and diversion, but the conversation ends in a conspiracy against 
the public, or in some contrivance to raise prices. 
Adam Smith 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 OUT-PRICING 
campaign proclaiming, Wed like to matc h their new fares, but wed have 
to raise ours. 
	Dont get too complicated. A Medical device manufacturer told its client 
hospitals that if he was forced out of the mark et, they would be at the 
mercy of the larger compan y. With a monop oly position, the CEO warned, 
the customers would nd their short-term price cuts transform into long-
term price increases. This was not every eectiv e as the hospitals were not 
sure how credible this was. 
3.3. Placemen t. 
	Form strategic partnerships with distributors and suppliers or complemen
tary good sellers. Do not tell your distributors not to distribute a low-cost 
good. That leads to jail time. 
	2003, 3M was found guilty under Section 2 of the Sherman Act for a 
de facto exclusiv e dealing arrangemen ts whereb y 3M oered customers 
large cash paymen ts to purchase their transparen t tape exclusiv ely 
from 3M. Damages totaled $68 million. 
	In 2001 Bed, Bath and Beyond planned to introduce Waterford/Crystal 
and Chin a. However, Federated and May Co. secured the exclusiv e 
deal for the purp ose of preventing Bed Bath &amp; Beyond from selling 
the Lenox/Waterford products. Successful prosecution in NY state 
and million-dollar nes. 
	Criteria for legal action is any two of 
	Product boycott is horizon tal (e.g., encompassing two or more 
comp etitors) as opposed to vertical (e.g., covering entities at 
dieren t levels of the distribution chain) 
	Designed to suppress price comp etition 
	Involves rms with mark et power or control over a critical source 
of supply . 
	Instead work with key buying inuencers. For example, when Microsoft 
threatened to enter the small business nancial software mark et, Intuit 
started a special program to reach out to the 200,000+ accoun tants who 
provide support for QuickBooks. 
3.4. Why not lower price? 
(1) Shallo w-Pockets Trap 
	You may have deep pocketed comp etitors. Wal-mart vs K-mart in 
1990s. 
	Bromine manufacturer Dow defeated predatory pricing by a governmen t-
supp orted German cartel, B romk onvention. Bromk onvention had been</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 OUT-PRICING 
2.3. Pricing threat. Selectiv ely revealing information about capabilities and fu
ture plans can be useful in avoiding harmful negativ e-sum game. The goal of such 
information is to dissuade comp etitors from reducing prices and ever challenging 
the rms resolv e. 
	Some strategists say that expanding capacit y makes you so fearsome that 
no comp etitor dares cut prices for fear of your response. 
	However, the airline industry only regained protabilit y after they cut 
capacit y after 9/11. In 2003, the industry load factor had recovered 
from 9/11 and was the highest ever: 73.4% of available seats were 
lled. 
	Talking about a cost advantage can sometimes backre: 
	An early car computer software rm stated that comp etitors would 
not be able to under-cut its prices since it had a cost advantage due 
to out-sourcing of call centers. Its comp etitors also moved their ser
vice departmen ts overseas, which led to price increases from the call-
centers. 
	Most eective strategy is to commit in public to ght back with pricing. 
	In the case of Winn -Dixie and Big Star vs. Food Lion, price matc hing 
commitmen t lead to doubling of prices on 79 commonly purchased 
brand items after two years as Food Lion raised its prices. 
	However, the recen t secret memo that was revealed about Best-Buys 
attempts to circum vent its own price-matc hing policies shows problems 
of these policies . 
2.4. Talking to the press about pricing. Firms should take steps when comm u
nicating with the press to make sure that their pricing strategy is advantageously 
perceiv ed by comp etitors, in the same manner as they manage perceptions of stock
holders and securities analysts 
 Pre-announce pricing intentions and justify increases and decre ases 
	Good Comm unication example: Serguei Belousso v...., the CEO said 
hes now taking a cue from Apple, p ositioning Parallels [desktop virtual 
machine software] as a premium product with impro ved qualit y and 
service. What he says he wont do, is get in a price war with close 
comp etitor VMW are Fusion. Belousso v is convince d that the best 
path to more mark et share is impro ving the product and supp ort while 
adding more features than the comp etition. Mac users, he says are not 
as price-conscious as their Windo ws counterparts, and are willing to 
pay more for a product that works well.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 OUT-PRICING 
1.1. Price xing and bid rigging. In the United States, price xing can be 
prosecuted as a criminal felony oense under Section 1 of the Sherman Antitrust 
Act. Price xing is an agreem ent among comp etitors to raise, x, or otherwise 
main tain the price at which their goods or services are sold. It is not necess ary that 
the comp etitors agree to charge exactly the same price, or that every comp etitor 
in a given industry join the conspiracy. Price xing can take many forms, and any 
agreemen t that restricts price comp etition violates the law. 
Any comm unication directly with comp etitors about prices or other elements 
of comp etition is strictly forbidden under US and EC antitrust laws. Even indi
rect comm unication about prices may be treated as evidence of possible collusion 
which, combined with other evidence of collusiv e intent, could result in an antitrust 
indictmen t. 
1.1.1. Patterns that the FTC looks for when detecting price xing. 
 Identical prices may indicate a price-xing conspiracy, especially when: 
	Prices stay identical for long periods of time 
	Prices previously were dierent 
	Price increases do not appear to be supported by increased costs. 
	Discounts are eliminated, especially in a market where discounts historically 
were given. 
	Vendors are charging higher prices to local customers than to distant cus
tomers. This may indicate local prices are xed. 
1.1.2. Red Flags to FTC in employee behavior. Each of the following situations has 
triggered a successful criminal antitrust prosecution: 
	Any reference to industry-wide or association price schedules. 
	Any statement indicating advance (non-public) knowledge of competitors 
pricing. 
	Statements to the eect that a particular customer or contract belongs to 
a certain vendor. 
	Statements that a bid was a courtesy, complementary, token, or cover 
bid. 
	Any statement indicating that vendors have discussed prices among them
selves or have reached an understanding about prices. 
1.1.3. Examples of successful price xing prosecutions. 
	Alfred Taubman, the former chairman of Sothebys auction house, served 
9 months of a one-year jail sentence for rigging fees charged to clients. He 
was also ned $7.5m. Taubman acknowledged a dozen meetings with his 
Christies rival but insists they never colluded. We were careful never to</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
15.818 Pricing 
Spring 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 OUT-PRICING 
2.1.2. Not at risk. 
(1) Tight Capacity 
(2) Steadily Increasing Demand 
(3) Plenty of dieren tiation value. Razor-Blade or Two-Sided Markets are 
ideal. 
In April, 2009, in the UK, Amazon oered 100 popular MP3s at just 29p (0.50c) 
per download. Apples iTunes store responded by raising prices on the most pop
ular MP3s to 99p, or $1.50. Apple could do this because of switc hing costs and 
superiorit y of iTunes experience. 
2.1.3. Cross-pric e elasticities. A cross-price elastic ity measures the percen tage change 
in unit sales for a rms product to the percen tage change of a comp etitors price. 
% change in demand of product A EA,B = % change in price of product B 
It is also possible to calculate a cross-price elasticit y for your product using the 
log-log transformation and the slope formula in Excel. The ys are the log of sales of 
your good, the xs are the log of price of your comp etitors goods. Ideally it would 
be zero. Anything over 0.5 is worrying. 
2.2.	Assessing comp etitor s pricing sophistication. 
	What are their price/cost structures? 
	Are they strategically sophisticated? You can only play a pricing game at 
the level of your least strategic comp etitor. 
	Pricing Game: 
(1) You need to pick an selling price between $0 and $50 for this object 
which will maximize your chances of winning this comp etition. 
(2) This is a tricky mark et where the ideal price-discount is 20%.	 Any 
higher, then people do not switc h their brand allegiance. Any lower, 
then people begin to doubt the qualit y of the product. 
(3) The person who picks a selling price at stage 1 which manages to 
undercut the average price by 20% (i.e. charges 80% of the average 
price) will win this object. 
Group Average Iteration 
Computer Scien tists 3.8 
Portfolio Managers 2.8 
High School Studen ts 1.6 
CEOS 1.0 
Strategic pricing relies not only on an understanding of game theory but an 
understanding of how well your comp etitors understand game theory .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec01</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec01/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>0</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
15.818 Pricing 
Spring 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 PRICING BEYOND THE 3 CS 
	Activit y-based pricing is where the customer agrees to pay the price 
when the cost is determined with an agreed mark-up based on the con
tribution to xed costs. Activity-based pricing is better than regular 
cost-based pricing in such situations. 
	For example, Owens Minor, a medical supply equipmen t distrib
utor, impro ved pricing performance by adjusting its mark-up to 
be higher on adult diapers compared to replacemen t ultrasound 
lm. 
(4) Ignoring the value you create leads to underpricing
Pet Rock
  
Rather than asking what prices rms need to charge in order to cover their costs 
and achieve their prot objectiv es, rms should ask how their pricing strategy will 
aect their cost structure. 
2.2. Customer-Based Pricing. There are many versions of customer-based pric
ing. 
(1) B2B: Salesforce allows purchasing agents to dictate their prices. 
	An aquarium cleaning product rm sold below their cost because they 
were scared of losing the custom of a big-b ox retailer. 
(2) B2C: Giving away a valuable product or add-on for free because the com
pany fears a customer revolt. 
	Flickr hosts 4 billion images (as of Oct 2009). However, the user base 
is so passionate that managers are reluctan t to charge more.
The problems with customer-based pricing are that:
(1) Customers do not reveal how much they value the product 
	Radiohead launched a pay what you want scheme for their album In 
Rainbows. 62 percen t paid nothing. Average price of $2.26 an album. 
(2) Customers need to be educated about the value of the product 
	For example, it was hard for customers to understand what TiVo of
fered over a traditional VHS recorder. 
(3) When custome rs are used to being in control of a rms pricing, they revolt 
at price changes 
	Turbotax starting charging users $9.95 for each additional return they 
led. Users revolted and gave them a 1.5 star rating on Amazon. 
The compan y retreated, reverted to charging nothing and refunded 
the money . 
	Residen t Evil 5, a computer game, tried a dieren t approac h: This 
is the part where I get to say BS, the vice presiden t of Strategic 
Planning &amp; Business Developmen t wrote on the Capcom forums. RE5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 PRICING BEYON D THE 3 CS 
is well worth every penny of $60. A huge game, with tons of repla y 
value, loads of unlockables, new weapons, co-op, mercenaries mode, 
etc. If any game warran ts its price point, its RE5 
Instead of asking themselv es what their customers would pay, rms should ask 
themselv es what are the prices at which they can convince their customers are 
supp orted by their products value. How can they segmen t to reect dierences in 
customer valuation? 
2.3. Comp etition-Based Pricing. Comp etition-based pricing describ es the sit
uation where a rm does not have a pricing policy that relates to its product, but 
instead a pricing policy that reects its comp etitors pricing decisions. 
Sometimes this simply takes the form of a rm copying their comp etitors pricing 
and not conductin g their own pricing researc h. 
Sometimes such pricing can take the form of a rm setting a mark et share ob
jectiv e and discoun ting their price relative to their competitor until they attain 
it. 
The problems with comp etition-based pricing are that: 
(1) It encourages rms to ignore their unique value proposition 
	A radiology software rm with a unique 3D capabilit y lost millions 
because they priced at the same price as the mark eting leader. 
(2) It can lead to price wars 
	If a rm sets a mark et share objectiv e when the mark et size is xed or 
declining, then this imme diately signals that this gain in mark et share 
will come at the loss of a competitor. This leads to price wars. 
	For example, the 2005 price war between Anheuser-Busc h and Miller 
was provoked by at sales. 
(3) Focusing on mark et share does not necessarily lead to maxim um prots 
	Even in industries with large economies of scale, some segmen ts of the 
population are more protable to serve. In the UK, cable companies 
have often ignored this and focused on extending their mark et share 
to rural villages . 
Instead of setting mark et share objectiv es, rms should focus on identifying the 
most protab le segmen ts to serve, and nding ways of protably serving them while 
protecting themselv es from price wars. 
3. To Summarize 
The 3 Cs are often though t of as pricing dos, but they can just as well describ e 
pricing donts.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>PRICING BEYOND THE 3 CS 
Contents 
1. Why Study Pricing?	 1 
2. Three Cs and Pricing	 1 
2.1. Cost-Based Pricing	 2 
2.2. Customer-Based Pricing	 3 
2.3. Comp etition-Based Pricing	 4 
3. To Summarize	 4 
1. Why Stud y Pricing? 
(1) Even slight impro vemen ts in pricing can yield signican t results. For ex
ample, for a compan y with 8% prot margins, a 1% impro vement in price 
realization, assuming a steady unit sales volume, would boost the compa
nys prots by 12.5%. By contrast, decreasing xed costs by 1% would only 
lead to an increase in prots of 4%. (Dolan 1992) 
	Continen tal Airlines had 44 million passengers in 2001, at an average 
ticket price of $193. Charging $2, or 1.04%, more per ticket would 
have transformed a loss into a prot. 
(2) 80% of managers know how much it costs to produce their product. 23% 
say they know their customers willingness to pay for the product. 
(3) 41% of rms have identied their inabilit y to recruit emplo yees with the 
right pricing tool sets as their major barrier to implemen ting pricing prac
tice overhauls. 
2. Three Cs and Pricin g 
Typically an introductory mark eting class teaches that any pricing strategy 
should reect the 3 Cs of pricing: 
Costs 
Customer 
 Comp etition 
Advanced pricing analysis, however, views the 3 Cs as describing a set of con
straints that pricing strategies must overcome to succeed. The 3 Cs also describ e 
three bad pricing strategies. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 PRICING BEYON D THE 3 CS 
	Cost-Based Pricing. Or, pricing on the basis of what it costs you to make 
the product. 
	Customer-Based Pricin g. Or, allowing your customers to dictate your pric
ing policy. 
	Comp etition-Based Pricing. Or, choosing your pricing strategy exclusiv ely 
on the basis of what your comp etitors do. 
2.1. Cost-Based Pricing. Cost-Based Pricing involves setting a price such that 
P rice = (1+ percentmar kup)(UnitV ariableCost + AverageF ixedC ost) 
Practical implemen tation problems: 
(1) You have to know costs. 
	A baby sleepsuit compan y made a loss despite engaging in cost-plus 
pricing, because they did not realize how much their packaging cost. 
	For example, Diamond Deliv eries in Philadelphia. The bicycle divi
sion, which managemen t though t of as Diamonds core business, gen
erated just 10% of total revenues and barely covered its own direct-
labor and insurance costs. Diamond was charging custom ers $4.69 per 
job, but with fully allocated costs of $9.24 per job, the compan y was 
losing $4.55 every time a cyclist picked up a package.1 
	You need to be able to estimate the costs of everything. 
(2) Costs are a function of sales which are in turn a function of prices. This 
makes such calculations circular . Imagine a rm whose average costs de
crease with sales. 
	If they sell less, their costs go up. But is a time of declining sales really 
the right environmen t to increase prices? 
	For example, Wang Computer 
	If they sell more, their costs go down. But pricing at average cost 
for small-scale capacit y means that the rm may never disco ver this. 
This is an issue for rms that face large economies of scale or unkno wn 
experience curves. 
	For exampl e, an aeroplane manufacturer found that every time 
they managed to double their sales, they reduced labor time per 
aeroplane produced by 10 percen t. 
(3) Cost-based pricing is misplaced in industries where there are high xed 
costs and near-zero marginal costs. Distributing xed costs is hard. 
	Complicated when products aect xed costs in dieren t ways. 
1Are We Making Money Yet?, Inc Magazine July 1 1995.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>PRICING BEYOND THE 3 CS 5 
Generally, the problem is that each of the 3 Cs encourages a powerless approach 
when it come to pricing. In all cases, the rm is reacting to a constraint, rather 
than shaping that constraint. The rest of this course will focus on how we can 
shape customer and competitive reactions to our pricing strategy, in a way which 
means that rms do not have to worry about hitting the cost oor. 
A more attractive reworking of the 3 Cs would be: 
 Create Value 
 Calibrate Value 
 Communicate Value 
 Capture Value
The course is based around these new 4 Cs.
Figure 1. Aim of 15.818: Tools to allow students to transform 
industries into pricing leaders Source: Based on Deloitte Analysis</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec03</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec03/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 PRICING UNDER CONSUMER UNCER TAINTY 
2.3. Signaling by the customer. One potential source of dieren tiation value is 
for Veblen or snob goods, where part of the products appeal is its high price. 
 High prices allow customers to signal their worth to other individuals 
	When a fountain pen manufacturer raised its prices, it sold more. 
	It also allows customers to signal their worth to themselv es 
	It also allows gift-buy ers to signal the value of their presen t. 
	Scottish whiskies had dicult y in Japan when they tried to enter with 
lower prices. 
	LOreal has had huge success with the Because youre worth it cam
paign</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 PRICING UNDER CONSUMER UNCER TAINTY 
2.1.1. Practic al timing consider ations. 
 Decouple the pain of paying from consumption for experience goods 
	For example, people are willing to pre-pa y and pay a premium for 
things they enjoy (such as vacations) 
	Decouple the pain of paying from the pain of learning how to use a tech
nology good. 
	Customers are more likely to switc h if they do not have to pay full 
price for a technology service in the same month they are learning 
how to use it. 
 Decouple pain of paying from possibility of bad experience of products. 
	Cellphone companies gain more customers if they preannounce an au
tomatic rebate when there is service interruptions. 
2.2. Asymmetric information about product qualit y. High prices may imply 
high qualit y if qualit y is uncertain. 
 Do you want the cheap est surgeon to perform laser eye surgery on you? 
However, the question remainsL: Wh y does this w ork? It isnt credible that these 
prices reect costs (for example having better-qualit y lasers ). The bad surgeon 
could have bad lasers and still charge a high price. 
Generally , high prices as a signal of qualit y work well with: 
 Customers of middling sophistication who are uncertain about qualit y 
	Some survey evidence of limited abilit y to think iterativ ely through 
the credibilit y of price as a signal of qualit y 
	Scenarios when people who are not knowledgable anticipate that there will 
be repeat or more knowledgable purchasers in the mark et too. 
	I migh t buy more expensiv e cigars as I assume they are priced right 
for cigar fans 
	Capacit y constrain ts 
 Show promoters in Vegas sell more seats at higher prices 
2.2.1. Other occasions that price inuenc es quality. 
	High prices may signal qual ity of fellow shopp ers 
	If you subscrib e to a cheap dating service, you may just meet cheap 
people. 
	High price being equated with high qualit y is so ingrain ed in customer 
behavior that it has a neurologica l comp onent. 
	For example, customer perceptions of the qualit y of wine are aected 
by price. This has been conrmed by neural imaging.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 PRICING UNDER CONSUMER UNCERTAINTY 
Figure 1. When to emphasize EVC and when to emphasize con
sumer price framing considerations 
To summarize: There is a clear use for EVC but there is also a clear use for price 
framing. The art of pricing is realizing which to emphasize and when.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
15.818 Pricing 
Spring 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 PRICING UNDER CONSUMER UNCER TAINTY 
they constan tly look for clues as to whether this price they are seeing is going to 
be a good deal relativ e to an unkno wn reference price. 
1.1. Product Line Strategies. The compromise eect is a crucial behavioral 
impulse when designing prices. Customers often choose the mid-priced option to 
protect themselv es from making a bad choice. The implication here is that one can 
increase prots by adding a low-price or high-price option in addition to an existing 
product. 
1.1.1. Consider ations for Compr omise Eect. 
	Not just for B2C mark ets. 
	Works success fully in B2B mark ets. Purchasing agents are never crit
icized for purchasing the mid-price option.
Needs to be same brand.
  
	Lab evidence shows that if you add a premium brand as a decoy prod
uct it doesnt have the shift consumers from low-price option to mid-
price option. 
	Everyone at the rm needs to know what the intention of introducing de
coys is. 
	Architectural software rm lost money after sales force manager mis
understo od its decoy premium product and started discoun ting it to 
matc h the mid-price product. 
1.2. Discoun ting Strategies. One way that rms can signal that their price will 
be cheaper than the unkno wn reference price is to advertise a disco unt, so that the 
reference price is anchored upwards. 
1.2.1. Proportional Discounts. 
	People tend to think of prices in terms of proportion or percen tage changes 
rather than absolute changes. Take for example the following decision. 
There is no absolute dierence in money saved, but consumers respond 
dieren tly. 
Good PC Xerox 
Stick with order of machine for $1,000 $20,000 
Cancel and re-order one for $600 $19,600 
 When discoun ting, discoun t cheapest part of the product bundle 
	More eectiv e to discoun t o dessert than total meal. 
	More eectiv e to discoun t car nancing than entire car price.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>PRICING UNDER CONSUME R UNCER TAINTY 
Contents 
1. When customers do not know reference prices 1 
1.1. Product Line Strategies 2 
1.2. Discoun ting Strategies 2 
1.3. Price Cues 3 
2. When pricing aects a customers valuation 3 
2.1. Timing Strategies 3 
2.2. Asymmetric information about product qualit y 4 
2.3. Signaling by the customer 5 
In the last lecture, we focused our atten tion on how rms can use EVC as a 
conceptual framew ork to guide their thinking about pricing. We emphasiz ed the 
importance of value comm unication, given that what matters is perceiv ed dieren
tiation value rather than the rms notion of dieren tiation value. In this lecture, 
we cover how rm strategy has to change when customers stop making decisions 
based on price and start using price to make decisions. 
A reworking of the EVC framew ork to emphasize consumer behavior would be. 
P ricea  (P erceivedRefP riceb|P riceab)+(PerceivedDiffV alueab|P riceab)) 
We discuss in turn: 
(1) How to make consumers feel comfortable about a price when they are not 
clear about the reference price 
(2) How price can inuence the perceiv ed dieren tiation value of the product 
1. When customers do not know reference prices 
Many customers do not know prices. A recen t MIT study interview ed people 
in line at the store. They found that while 80% of custome rs though t they knew 
the price of the objects in their basket, only 50% did know the price. Given their 
relativ e lack of price knowledge, customers often seek price cues to inform them 
as to whether it is a good deal or not. This lack of price knowledge means that 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 PRICING UNDER CONSUMER UNCER TAINTY 
	The percen tage change from 0 is innit y, which perhaps explains why cus
tomers like free products so much. An MIT experimen t just showed that 
going from free to 1 cent for a chocolate can reduce demand by 17 percen t, 
even if comp etitiv e products also increase by 1 cent. 
1.2.2. Credible Discounting. 
(1) MIT researc h suggests that eectiv eness of sales signs decreases at around 
30 percen t saturation. 
(2) Pricing software needs to reect the need for credibilit y 
	JCPenney recen tly started discoun ting earlier but less (10 percen t dis
counts) rather than 20 percen t discoun ts, on basis of projections from 
pricing software 
(3) Firm needs to give credible reasons 
	GMs employee disco unt program was so successful because it signaled 
a large discoun t. 
	Similarly , liquidation sales are success ful because again there is a cred
ible reason for the rm to be discoun ting. 
1.3. Price Cues. 
1.3.1. Key Item Pricing. Most popular strategy used in retail. Takes advantage 
of the fact that consumers know the price of a few items and retailers price these 
aggressiv ely. Works well in the lab. Less real-world evidence it works well because 
repeat purchase items often have huge uctuations in prices rendering customers 
price knowledge imperfect. 
1.3.2. Price Endings. $9 endings are eectiv e at signalling value relativ e to an un
known reference price. 
	Previously , $9 endings have been taken as reecting left-to right process
ing by customers (for example, a customer believes that a sweater that is 
mark ed $9.99 is closer to $9 than $10). 
	However, more recent research suggests a more nuanced relationship with 
the compan ys brand message. (e.g. Discoun t Stores vs. Art Galleries) 
2. When pricing affects a customer s valuation 
The price of a product itself can send importan t signals about the product. 
2.1. Timing Strategies. Getting the timing of pricing right can actually aid how 
much consumers enjoy your good. Basically , consumers prefer to avoid a paymen t 
that is timed when either they are enjoying the good, or when they expect in 
particular to not enjoy the good.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec02</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec02/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
15.818 Pricing 
Spring 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 PRICING ECONOMIC VALUE TO THE CUSTOMER 
(2) Initial Customer Lock-In 
(3) Pre-empt comp etitiv e response 
We discuss these in detail in weeks 3-6 of the course . 
There are three ways that EVC analysis gets used (as a formula, as a guideline 
and as a diagnostic), which we now discuss in turn. 
Using EVC as a Pricing Formula 
It is best to use EVC as a pricing formula 
	When comp etitors prices are well-kno wn and concrete 
	When a products dieren tiation value is easy to calibrate 
	When a products dieren tiation value is easy and believable to comm uni
cate 
The Atlantic Computi ng exampl e is an almost ideal setting for the use of EVC as 
a formula. 
The ideal setting for the use of EVC as a formula is one where the seller knows 
precisely how the customer will use the product, and intimate details of their likely 
cost savings or net benets of using the technology . This generally implies a man
ufacturing or engineering setting. This is no surprise, since consultan ts developed 
EVC analysis for these kind of industries. EVC can be particularly useful as a tool 
to help the sales force sell and prevent price erosion by allowing them to answ er 
questions like: 
	How can you justify charging that much for your product? 
	Why should I buy your product when your comp etitors product is $3,000 
cheap er? 
	What is most worthwhile for our rm to keep in mind about your oering? 
However, the system should not be so complex that sales people bypass it. 
Using EVC as a Pricing Guideline for new products 
EVC can be useful for a rm that is choosing the initial price of its product. 
The classic example of this is Zantac. As a second entrant to the stom ach ulcer 
mark et, it may have been natural for them to price at or just under the incum bents 
(Tagamets) price. However, EVC analysis demonstrated large dierentiation value 
because of the twice-daily dosage format and fewer side eects, and as a consequence 
they priced at 50 percen t above the incum bents price. In two years they were the 
mark et leader.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 PRICING ECONOMIC VALUE TO THE CUSTOMER 
	Business hotels have been able to capture the customers dieren tiation 
value for pillow-top mattresses and expensiv e bedding because usually 
the rm is paying for the hotel stay. 
(3) Advantageous mental accoun t: Customers have dierent mental accoun ts 
which they evaluate separately when they make purchase decisions. Price 
closer to EVC if your product falls into an advantageous mental accoun t 
such as Vacation Money or Tax Refun d Money. 
	For example, success of travel agency selling Las Vegas packages that 
oered a $300 tax rebate special to coincide with the 2008 Bush tax 
rebate checks. 
May have to price well below EVC if. 
(1) Uncertain ty Eect: Uncertain ty over realization of attributes 
	For example, a new anti-dandru shamp oo was unable to command a 
price premium because its claims could not be veried by experts and 
consumers knew that its eectiveness would vary. 
(2) Newness Eect: Attributes are new and therefore hard to understand 
	For example, Boxee is a freew are cross-platform media center software 
with social networking features that is a fork of the open source XBMC 
media center software with some custom and proprietary additions. 
Since customers are unlik ely to understand the value that implies , 
they may have to price below EVC when they release their hardw are 
(allegedly) in 2010. 
	Make clear this is temp orary . 1969 study: Five brand s in two stores. 
One had discoun t from initial price, other had no sign of discoun t. In 
all ve cases, the store that had mark ed the discoun t as being from 
the list price did better in the long run. 
(3) Expenditure eect: When it is a larger proportion of expenditure. 
	For example, an industrial carpet cleaner could charge higher prices 
to oce managers than dedicated oce cleaning compani es. 
(4) When it is ethically right or legally appropriate to do so 
	Bottled water priced at $35 for a 12 pack during Hurricane Rita 
	North Carolina Price Gouging Law. North Carolina denes price 
gouging as intentionally charging an unreasonably excessiv e price un
der the circumstances for goods or services that are used by North 
Carolinians during an emergency to preserv e, protect or sustain life, 
health, safety or economic well-being. 
May wish to price below EVC for strategic reasons if. 
(1) Winner-tak es-all mark et</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 PRICING ECONOMIC VALUE TO THE CUSTOMER 
EVC example 
Atlantic Computer has developed software that allows their servers to host twice 
as much webspace as its rivals. How should they price this new software-serv er 
combination? 
	Relativ e to buying two servers from Atlantics comp etitor, by buying one 
doubly ecien t server from Atlantic, a rm would save $4,000 in labor costs, 
$500 in electricit y and $1,500 in software licenses. This suggests that the 
dieren tiation value relativ e to the closest comp etitiv e oering is $6,000. 
	The price of two servers from the comp etitor is $6,800. 
	This suggests that the EVC of a server with the software is $6,000 + $6,800 
= $12,800. 
Practical Implement ation of EVC analysis in a firm 
	Identify what benet your product provides 
	Make sure you dene a benet, not a feature. Skill here reaps large 
rewards. 
	Xerox became very protable because it priced per photo copy. 
	Identify closest comp etitiv e oering and calculate its price 
	Be honest about who your closest comp etitor is 
	For example, even though a B2B online video-calling service 
may want to compar e itself to dedicated-line video-conferencing 
systems, its real closest competitor is Skyp e, which is free. 
	Be honest with yourself about the price that comp etitors sell their 
product for. 
	For example, a web back-up compan y calculated an EVC price 
that was 100 percen t greater than what they were charging. 
However, they omitted to include the fact that all their rivals 
discoun ted at 80 percen t from list. 
	Get the units and time-horizon right. This is far easier to do when 
you have dened the products benet properly. 
	For example, an cleaning product manufacturer left money on 
the table by not reecting the fact that its cleaner cleaned twice 
as much as its comp etitor. 
	Identify potential sources of diere ntiation value 
	Be specic, not vague. It is importan t that your rms value proposi
tion does not sound like it was churned out by generic software. 
Measure how much value these create  
	Have an indep enden t lab do measurable testing.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 PRICING ECONOMIC VALUE TO THE CUSTOMER 
Using EVC as a Pricing Diagnostic for existing products 
EVC is a useful tool for establishing whether an existing product that is per
forming poorly is overpriced or mis-promoted 
(1) Overpriced 
	Segw ay recognized that compared to its EVC, segways were felt by 
the majority of customers to be overpriced at a price point of $3,000. 
Therefore the Segw ay compan y focused on nding ways of reducing 
the average price, such as the use of Segw ay on one-day city tours. 
(2) Value message is not focused on crucial dieren tiation value 
	Michelin initially emphasized all its points of dieren tiation value such 
as longevit y, speed and safety, in its advertising. Customer tests re
vealed that their most salien t and easy to comm unicate dierentiation 
value was safety, and Michelin switched its advertising to emphasize 
that, with great success. 
(3) Value message is not being comm unicated eectiv ely 
	Duracell found out that its value message that it lasted for longer 
was not believed by custome rs. Therefore they switc hed from a quan
titativ e message to one that emphasized that consumers should use 
Duracell batteries when reliabilit y was crucial. 
It is essen tial to conduct a form of EVC analysis before instituting a price cut, to 
protect managemen t from making the wrong decision.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>PRICING ECONOMIC VALUE TO THE CUSTOME R 
Contents 
Denition 1 
EVC example 2 
Practical Implementation of EVC analysis in a rm 2 
How far should a rm discount from EVC? 3 
Using EVC as a Pricing Formula 5 
Using EVC as a Pricing Guideline for new products 5 
Using EVC as a Pricing Diagnostic for existing products 6 
Definition 
Economic Value to the Customer (EVC) is based on the insigh t that a customer 
will buy a product only if its value to them outweighs the value of the closest 
alternativ e, or when Utilitya  Utilityb. The utilit y of a product depends on its 
value to the customer minus its price. 
V aluea  P ricea  V alueb  P riceb 
Rearranging gives: 
P ricea  [V aluea  V alueb]+ P ricebP ricea  DifferentiationV alueab + P riceb 
Rewriting [V aluea  V alueb] as the dieren tiation value between product a and 
b allows us to summarize product as price ceiling as 
P ricea  DifferentiationV alueab + P riceb 
Therefore, to sell a product, a rm needs to price at or below its comp etitors 
price plus the value advantage its product has to the customer over the rival prod
uct. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>PRICING ECONOMIC VALUE TO THE CUSTOMER 3 
	For example, an air-lter compan y got a lab to measure the 
number of dust particles in the air and estimate the eect this 
would have on asthma suerers. 
	Often curren t customers are willing to take part in benchmarking stud
ies, as they view it as free consulting. 
	For example, W.W. Grainger oered consulting and measure
ment incen tives to 15 clients who agreed to participate. 
 Add the reference price and dieren tiation values together to get EVC. 
The next challenge is to determine how far below EVC the rms ideal price 
point will be. 
How far should a firm discount from EVC? 
It is a common misperception that EVC analysis implies that a rm should price 
at the EVC. This is not the case. The EVC describ es only the maximum price a 
rm migh t theoretically charge. Generally , a rm will decide to forego some of their 
dieren tiation value.1 There is some neurological basis for this fairness eect.2 
Youre standing on the sidew alk with a friend, minding your own 
business, when a man approaches with a proposition. He oers you 
$20 in one-dollar bills and says you can keep the money , under one 
condition: You have to share some of it with another person. You 
can oer this other person as much or as little as you like, but if 
they reject your oer, neither of you get to keep any of the money . 
What do you do? 
This suggests a 50 percen t discoun t rule. 
	For example, Atlantic Computer ultimately priced not at the suggested 
EVC, but instead discoun ted its dieren tiation value by 50 percen t ($3,000), 
so that it priced the product at $9,800. 
Set price closer to EVC if. 
(1) End-Benet eect:	 When your product is an essen tial part of a known 
end-use. 
	Since Bridal Bouquets are a small but essen tial part of a large and 
expensiv e end product, orists are able to charge a great deal more for 
them than for other bouquets. 
(2) Shared-Cost eect: When the cost is shared. 
1Sloan Managemen t Review Why the Highest Price Isnt the Best Price, Winter 2010. 
2The Neural Basis of Economic Decision-Making in the Ultimatum Game, Science 13, June 2003.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec04</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec04/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 MEASURING CUSTOMER REACTIONS TO PRICES 
	For example, a chemical distributor was told by its customers that 
they would pay 75 percen t less than the mark et price for waste disposal 
services. 
	Customers may say a price that reects how they want the person 
conducting the survey to view them, but does not reect their actual 
willingness to pay. For example, Phillips conducted a survey where the 
teenage participan ts said they wanted yellow boom boxes. However, 
when they came to leave the room, they all chose black boom boxes. 
	Customers may simply be unsure about their willingness to pay. For 
example, an American bridal survey found that brides overstated will
ingness to pay ve-fold. 
1.3. Implemen tation. 
(1) In person 
	The key is to nd the right setting. Rushed settings produce worse 
data. The best data comes from times when people take time and 
survey-taking becomes a comm unal activit y. 
(2) Online 
	The problem here is reliabilit y of data. We found that when we asked 
survey participan ts what browser they used, 40 percen t lied. This 
gure actually increased when we raised their compensation. 
(3) Focus Groups 
	A crucial problem here is that the incentives of the focus group fa
cilitator can often lead to misleading results and analysis. However, 
without a facilitator no pricing questions get answ ered. 
2. Improving Price Surveys by Using Conjoint Anal ysis 
Choice-based conjoin t is a laboratory survey of how customers would value dif
feren t attribute bundles. It is usually (and best) used for product design. 
2.1. Conducting conjoin t analysis. 
(1) You choose a limited selection of product features to permutate in questions. 
Price should be one of these features. 
(2) Software then gives survey responden ts a selection of choices between dier
ent product bundles. It is importan t that you make sure that responden ts 
always have the option not to buy. 
(3) Software then conducts logit analysis and gives regression output. 
(4) The estimates of how much a customer values each product feature can 
be converted into rough dollar amoun ts by multiplying by the ratio of the 
coecien t on price. This allows us to establish EVC amoun ts.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>In this lecture we learn both how to price new products by using survey tools, 
and how to improve pricing of existing products by measuring price elasticities. 
Table 1. Price Measurement Matrix 
Variable Measured Uncontrolled Experimental Im
provement 
Pricing for the rst time Surveys Conjoint 
Improving existing pric- Historical Sales Data Field-Tests 
ing (Scanner/Store) 
1 MEASURING CUSTOMER REA CTIONS TO PRICES 
Contents 
1. Uncon trolled Price Surveys 2
1.1. Unstructured Questions 2
1.2. General issues with price survey techniques 3
1.3. Implemen tation 4
2. Impro ving Price Surveys by Using Conjoin t Analysis 4
2.1. Conducting conjoin t analysis 4
2.2. Conjoin t advantages 5
2.3. Conjoin t disadv antages 5
3. Using Historical Data to Impro ve Existing Pricing 5
3.1. Price Elasticities 5
3.2. Estimating a constan t price elasticity 5
3.3. Spreadsheet analysis 6
3.4. Why is a price elasticity ever useful? 6
3.5. Drawbac ks of historical pricing analy sis 7
3.6. Ways of impro ving historical pricing analysis 8
4. Impro ving Pricing Analysis by Using Field Experimen ts 8
4.1. Challenges with eld experimen ts 8
Math Appendix 9
Mid-p oint elasticit y formula 9
Using calculus to move from logs to price elasticit y formula 9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 MEASURING CUSTOMER REACTIONS TO PRICES 
2.2. Conjoin t advantages. 
	Conjoin t analysis reduced the rather articial focus on price in surveys by 
including information about features. 
	Conjoin t output allows researc hers to give utilit y-values to various com
ponents which can help accurat ely determine the EVC. 
	Quick and relativ ely cheap 
2.3. Conjoin t disadv antages. Do not use conjoin t if 
	Customers are likely to take price as a signal of the qualit y of the attribute. 
This problem is often severe and means that you need to severely limit the 
number of attributes. More than 3 is often too many. 
	Product features are not well understood by customers. 
	Part of a more complex system of related products. 
3. Using Historical Data to Improve Existing Pricing 
3.1. Price Elastic ities. The price elasticit y of a product measures the responsiv e
ness of sales to a change in price. Price elasticit y is dened as the percent change 
in quan tity sold given a 1% change in price. 
This helps analysts gure out whether revenues will be the same, higher or 
lower after a change in price. If elasticit y=1, revenues will be the same from a 
price change. If elasticit y is &gt;1, revenues will be higher with a price decrease. If 
elasticit y&lt;1, revenues will be higher with a price increase. 
On average, price elasticities are around 2, but on average is not very useful. 
The standard formula is 
% change in quan tity demanded Qd/QdEd =	 = % change in price Pd/Pd 
3.2. Estimating a constan t price elasticit y. One problem with the formula 
Qd/Qd for the price elasticit y is that it can take two dieren t values for whether Pd/Pd 
P or Q are the original or nal values. This shouldnt matter if you are compari ng 
price elasticities across segmen ts and are always consistent about what values you 
use (for example the value that is used in the denominator, should be the one used 
to calculate the numerator). 
This occurs because we are assuming a linear relationship between price and 
quan tity. One (smart) way of getting around this is by assuming that the demand 
curve instead has a constan t elasticit y. 
The functional form for a constan t-elasticit y demand curve is 
Sales = aP b 
x</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 MEASURING CUSTOMER REACTIONS TO PRICES 
	A drapes manufacturer could not calculate an elasticit y because it had 
kept the same price for the last 10 years. 
(3) If the data goes back too far it may describ e an old scenario.	 Dont use 
pricing data more than 5 years old. 
	A book catalog compan y calculated an articially low price elasticit y 
by including pre-in ternet-era data. 
(4) Misleading because of changes in other confounding factors 
	For example, ice-creams are priced higher and sell better in hot weather. 
However, if one performs multivariate analysis rather than univariate 
analysis when calculating price elasticities, it is possible to control for 
these observ able sources of bias. 
3.6.	Ways of impro ving historical pricing analysis. 
(1) CRUCIAL. Calculate dieren t price elasticities for each type of customer, 
each region, each product. 
(2) Use more data than just aggregate sales and prices 
	DHL emplo yed software that included the reactions of customers who 
called and got a quote but didnt ship -that is, a failed sale. By in
cluding data from this group of custome rs, they improved their quote 
to book ratio from 17 percen t to 25 percen t. 
(3) Use panel data econometrics where you include controls for places and times 
in your regression analysis. The problem is that this can get very expensive 
both in terms of personnel and costs of acquiring data. 
4. Improving Pricing Anal ysis by Using Field Experiments 
A lot of the problems with historical data analysis happ en because the price 
changed for reasons that were also associated with changes in sales (for example 
the weather and ice-cream sales). This can be controlled for by using controlled 
price experimen ts. Can be very successful. Ambassadors travel group disco vered 
they had a price elasticit y of 0.3 and were able to increase prots by 15 percen t. 
Usually we tend to think of eld tests as being experime nts, but new tools such 
as Google Analytics are actually puttin g them easily in the reach of rms with 
smaller budgets. 
4.1.	Challenges with eld experimen ts. 
(1) Ensure will have enough price-v ariation. 
	One experimen t I encoun tered had lowered all prices by 15%, which is 
only useful if your aim is to drop all prices by 15%. 
(2) If too visible, can anger customers</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
15.818 Pricing 
Spring 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MEASURING CUSTOMER REACTIONS TO PRICES 9 
	Amazon had to refund $7,000 to angry customers after its DVD pricing 
experimen ts were spotted 
(3) Stock-outs or problems with an experimen tal cell (such as mailing problems) 
can be detrime ntal to establishing concrete conclusions. 
(4) Multiple pricing experimen ts make interpretation of one cell dicult 
	Fingerh ut runs 30,000 pricing experimen ts a year, making interpreta
tion of results that involve complemen ts and substitutes dicult. 
Math Appendix 
Mid-p oint elasticit y formula. If you are concerned about the appro ximations 
involved with the simple elasticit y formula but are not doing the kind of detailed 
historical analysis which is amenable to the log transformation, you can use the 
midp oint elasticit y formula. 
(Q2Q1) 
Ed = (Q1+ Q2)/2 
P 2P 1 
(P 1+P 2)/2 
(Q2  Q1)(P 2  P 1) (P 1+ P 2)Ed =  (Q1+ Q2) 
Using calcul us to move from logs to price elasticit y formula. Our constan t 
elasticit y demand function is 
Q = aPxb 
Let u = ln Q, v = (ln p) 
d ln Q du dudqdpEd =  d ln P == dv = dq dpdv 
d ln Q dy dev 1 dy v dy x Ed	 = e = =  dQ dx dv Qdx dxy</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 MEASURING CUSTOMER REACTIONS TO PRICES 
1. Uncontrolled Price Surveys 
Very early in the development of survey techniques for mark eting, 
researc hers learned that it was futile to ask consumers outrigh t 
what they would be willing to pay for a product. 
The Strategy and Tactics of Pricing, Nagle and Hogan 
1.1. Unstructured Questions. The most obvious way of nding out customers 
feelings about price is to ask them a question like How much should this can of Coke 
cost?. Such a question has problems from the outset, because the question does 
not demand that the customer actually buy the can of Coke. Instead it conates 
price awareness with willingness to pay. 
1.1.1. Van Westendorps Price Sensitivity Meter. Marginally better is: How much 
would you be willing to pay for a can of Coke? This type of price questioning 
is used in a species of pricing researc h named Van Westendorps Price Sensitivit y 
Meter. Here, customers are asked: 
	At what price would you consider the product too expensive? 
	At what price would you consider the product to be so cheap you would 
not consider it? 
	At what price would you consider the product to start to get expensive? 
 At what price would you consider the product to be a good value? 
This was originally proposed in 1976 as a way of gauging how important the kind 
of price-qualit y signal that we discussed in the previous lecture is for a product. 
However, it has been distorted from its original intention and is commonly used as 
a way of getting a price range for a product. The lower bound is the intersection of 
too cheap and expensiv e. The upper bound is the intersection of too expensiv e 
and cheap . 
This metho dology has been discredited. I suspect its persisten t popularit y it lies 
in the facts a) that it produces a gure with intersecting lines that is reminiscen t of 
some kind of demand and supply curve and b) Van Westendorp had an impressiv e 
sounding last name. 
Problems in general with open-ended questioning approac h: 
	The problem with this is that a custom er will almost always say: it depends. 
After all, my willingness to pay for a can of Coke would probably vary from 
$.20 in a supermarket if I was in a hurry and I had plenty of Coke cans 
back home, to $5 if I was in a hotel room and the only place I could get a 
drink was from a hotel minibar. 
	People are not very good at this kind of open-ended question since we are 
not called upon to make this kind of judgement often. Suppose you were</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 MEASURING CUSTOMER REACTIONS TO PRICES 
Taking logs 
log Sales = log a + b log P 
We can then use spreadsheet analysis to nd the value of the constan t b which 
summarizes the price elasticit y. 
3.3. Spreadsheet analysis. It is quite straigh tforw ard to use a spreadsheet tool 
like excel to calculate a price elasticit y from historical data. The steps are 
(1) Create new columns for log(sales ) and log(prices). Use the excel function 
= LOG() to convert the raw sales data into log form. 
(2) In a new cell, insert the function =SLOPE(kno wn ys, known xs) 
(3) Choose for the known ys the log of sales, and for the known xs the log of 
prices. 
(4) You should get a negativ e number that represen ts the price elasticit y 
One drawbac k to this procedure is that is not clear how reliable your estimate 
is. As an alternativ e you can also use the Data Analysis Add-In for Excel and 
the Regression option to get measures called standard errors (whic h tell you how 
precise your estimate is), and R-squared which is a statistic that helps you know 
how much of the variation in sales is explained by price1 
3.4. Why is a price elasticit y ever useful? 
	Relativ e margins (More on this in our next lecture): 
An electronics retailer priced batteries the same all over....[Price 
Elasticit y Analysis] showed the battery that had the highest price 
sensitivit y in Dallas had the lowest price sensitivit y in Boston. In 
other words, while Texans would buy this particular battery only 
within a narro w price range, Bostonians were far less picky about 
it. The store altered its prices accordingly, sold more batteries 
and made more money at it. 
Associated Press, 2007 
	Rule of thumb pricing tool, especially in retail sector with a large number 
of SKUs. This caries a weighty health warning since you are eectiv ely 
assuming away your comp etitors, that you are already optimizing and that 
you have increasing marginal costs. 
% change in quan tity demanded Qd/QdEd =	 = % change in price Pd/Pd 
1You can also use the array function LINEST() should you not be able to install the Analysis 
Add-In.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 MEASURING CUSTOMER REACTIONS TO PRICES 
given a suitcase and asked to guess how much it weighed. People have 
a tough time with questions like this. However, when on the other hand 
people are given two suitcases and asked to say which one is heavier, they 
get it right 100 percen t of the time. 
	Lyon (2002) suggests that 20% of responden ts say that the price that would 
be right is lower than the price at which they say they would nd the 
product too cheap at. 
	Such huge price ranges are they give clients an excuse to go with their gut. 
1.1.2. Monadic Pricing Studies. Monadic pricing studies are a fancy name given to 
single cell pricing researc h where responden ts are asked a single question about a 
product. 
	If a Coke can is priced at $0.99, how likely are you to buy it? 
	If a Coke can is priced at $0.99, how likely are you to buy it at the snack-
shop at work? 
	If a Coke can is priced at $0.99, would you buy it at the snack-shop at 
work? 
	If a Coke can is priced at $0.99 and Pepsi is $1.09 at the snack-shop at 
work, would you buy Pepsi, Coke or neither supp osing, you had no soda so 
far that day? 
This kind of phrasing is less likely to confuse survey-tak ers as they just have 
to make a choice rather than naming a price. This would at least get you more 
accurate answ ers for your particular setting. One advantage if you test a broad 
enough range of prices, you can recreate a demand curve. 
Potential Problems: 
	By focusing the customers atten tion on a reasonable price, you may be 
censoring extreme responses such as $5 which may be the basis for protable 
segmen tation. 
	Need a lot of responden ts to get an answ er. Do not be tempted to use 
a price ladder, however. Asking follow-up questions such as how about 
$0.89?, How about $0.79?. just lead the customer to behave as though 
they are negotiating. 
	Need to ensure that the question is not overly focused on the price. 
1.2. General issues with price survey techniques. There are three main aws 
to this approac h 
(1) Customers may delib erately understate their willingness to pay</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 MEASURING CUSTOMER REACTIONS TO PRICES 
Revenue for a rm: 
Revenue = P  Q 
If they maximize revenue with respect to the quan tity they sell: 
Marginal Revenue = P Q + QP 
Q Q 
P Marginal Revenue = P + Q  Q 
P QMarginal Revenue = P [1 + Q  P ] 
We can simplify since the price elasticit y Ed 
P QEd = 1/Q  P 
1Marginal Revenue = P [1  ]Ed 
If you are a prot maximizing rm, then you of course set price such 
that MR=MC. 
1Marginal Cost = P [1  ]Ed 
Dividing by P and rearranging yields: 
1 P = Marginal Cost  1  1 
|Ed|
Let us supp ose you estimate a price elasticit y of Ed = 2, then you can calculate 
a rough mark-up such that your price should be twice cost. If Ed = 3 then price 
should be 3/2 marginal cost (or a 50 percen t mark-up). If demand is only somewhat 
elastic Ed = 1.5, then price should be three times cost. 
Hint: Use the absolute value of the price elasticit y. The formula is already 
adjusted for it being negativ e. 
Hint: Dont use the formula for price elasticities less than one. In my opinion it 
does not work well for price elasticities less than 1.5. 
3.5. Drawbac ks of historical pricing analysis. 
(1) Need accurate pricing data 
	For example, the mark eting division of a Web server space compan y 
faced problems when the sales force didnt keep record of discounts. 
(2) Need variation in price</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec08</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec08/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 SUMMARIZING PRICING 
2. Pricing Menu 
New product to price
Limited field tests 
framed as 
introductory pricingB2B
EVC Analysis with 
Benchmarking
Strategic Analysis 
of EVC discountB2C
Open ended 
price questioning
Monadic/Conjoint 
tests
Figure 2. Pricing a new product 
Improving pricing for 
existing product
Use EVC as initial 
diagnostic 
Obtain broad historical 
data
Calculate price 
elasticities for different 
products/customers
Develop price 
segmentation fences
Figure 3. Pricing an existing product</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 SUMMARIZING PRICING 
3. 10 Challenges to Pricing Intuition 
(1) If we use cost-plus pricing, we will make a prot 
 Only if you are incredibly accurate with your sales projections 
(2) Our customers always prefer low prices 
	Customers will always say they like lower prices. However, in many 
mark ets price serves as a guide to qualit y, and pricing too low can send 
out a negativ e signal. 
(3) Our customers do not know prices, so our pricing strategy is unimp ortant. 
	Lack of customer price knowledge makes how you present the price 
even more importan t. This is where strategies such as good-better
best and price ending cues are key. 
(4) Simpler pricing structures are better. 
	You always want three prices. Simplifying pricing structures means 
giving away money . Due to the taxi-meter eect, customers may not 
always appreciate it when rms do price simply . 
(5) If we are protable, we do not need to price-discriminate. 
	On the contrary: Price segmen tation is actually going to be most 
eectiv e for already-pro table rms, because eectiv e segmen tation 
requires the mark et power implied by protabilit y. 
(6) Razor Blade pricing works because our customers are stupid 
	Razor blade pricing works because it is actually subtle price segm en
tation. High-v alue, high-usage customers pay more. Low-value, low-
usage customers pay less. 
(7) Our product has network eects, so we need to set a low price 
	Your product may well not have network eects at all. 
	Even when a product has network eects, price segmen tation is key. 
The crucial questions for network goods are: Whom do I set a low 
price to and whom do I set a high price to? 
(8) Firms need to adjust prices until I ll capacit y. 
 It can be more protable to have unused inventory or capacit y. 
(9) Industries need to work together to ensure that they avoid harmful price 
wars 
	Statemen ts like this lead to jail time. It is the responsibilit y of the 
rm, and the rm alone, to avoid a price war. 
(10) Our comp etitors understand our pricing strategy 
	Firms have to activ ely manage perceptions of their pricing by com
petitors, regulators and other stakeholders.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
15.818 Pricing 
Spring 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>SUMMARIZING PRICING 
Contents 
1. Pricing Aim 1
2. Pricing Menu 2
3. 10 Challenges to Pricing Intuition 3
1. Pricing Aim 
Use of 
Pricing 
Data
Pricing 
SophisticationPrimitive 
Pricing
-Gut Feel
-Cost PlusReactive 
Pricing
-Competition 
based
-Some ExcelAdaptive 
Pricing
-Fact based pricing 
approach
-Reactive to 
customersPre-emptive 
Pricing
-Complex Price 
Segmentation
-Novel Pricing Metrics
-Experimentally driven 
pricing approach
Figure 1. A taxonom y of pricing strategies 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_supp01</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_supp01/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>B2B NEGOTIATIONS 
Contents 
1. Price Waterfall Analysis	 1 
1.1. Action plan	 1 
2. Negotiation	 1 
2.1. Say: Our price is X	 2 
2.2. A Final Story	 2 
B2B is prett y unique to the exten t that pricing negotiations are key to most 
pricing outcomes. Consumer products (with the exception of cars) very rarely have 
negotiated prices. 
1. Price Waterfall Anal ysis 
Firms must understand how sensible the prices are that your curren t negotiation 
process is leading to. 
1.1. Action plan. 
	Plot the price paid against the number of units bough t by the customer. 
Often it becomes eviden t that your best (high-v olume) customers are paying 
more per unit than your less protable customers. This is not a recip e for 
happ y and long-term relationships. 
	One often-recommended solution is to construct a price waterfall chart. 
This allows you to work out the true net price for each customer. 
	Start with Transaction price 
	Net Rebate 
	Net Allowance 
	Net Discoun t 
	Calculate nal Pocket Price 
2. Negotia tion 
Price often looms larger in sales reps minds than in repeat buyers minds. You 
do not know if the price is too high until you lose the sale 
	Establish economic value before discussing price 
	Be the rst person to bring up price: If you dont talk price, your customer 
will. 
 94% of sales reps do not talk price until their customer does 
 1/3 will not say price ever, will only write it down or point 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
15.818 Pricing 
Spring 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 B2B NEGOTIATIONS 
2.0.1. Implement Pricing Policy via a Price Menu. 
	Establish consisten t, transparen t criteria for discoun ting -Fixed prices, 
Flexible oers 
	Never give ad-ho c discoun ts to repeat customers 
 Reward loyalty and trial, not sheer volume
Study of 64 rms who dropp ed vendors
	Price was reason vendor was dropp ed 8.1% of the time 
	70.2% delivery problem 
	9.4% qualit y problem 
	6.2% service problem 
2.1. Say: Our price is X. Be rm. Do not be descriptiv e. Ban Phrases like: 
	Regular, normal, list, book, lowest, best, reduced, basic, usual price 
The best I can do  
	We can work a little on this price 
	Our price is lower than anyone else 
	Our price is less than a bag of chips per widget 
	How does $100 sound to you? Am I in the ballpark? 
	Tell me where I need to be. What do I have to do to get your business? 
2.2. A Final Story. Two village idiots wanted to invest $100 they won in the 
lottery . They went to a pumpkin farmer they knew and bought 100 pumpkins at 
$1.00 each. After nding a good place to park and sell the pumpkins from their 
trucks atbed, they started selling them at $1.00 each. When they sold that load 
they went back to the farmer for more. After selling several truck loads they counted 
their money and realized they still had only $100. After counting it several more 
times to be sure, Charley said to Bobby, This is getting us nowhere! We sold all 
our pumpkins, but we still only have $100. Somethings wrong but I surely cant 
gure it out. Bobb y said to Charley , You idiot, I was gonna let you gure it out, 
but youre just too dumb since you didnt even nish the third grade. Its as plain 
as the nose on your ugly face that the only way we can make money is to get a 
bigger truck!</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec05</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec05/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>goods to not always come out in a perfectly consistent manner. 
(2) Capacity 
	Charging $199 for the 8GB IPhone, and $299 for the 16GB IPhone. 
Here the low-valuation types have to signal that they will not be using 
a full range of the multimedia capacity of the IPhone. 
(3) Pleasantness 
	Sales rep in charge of economy line at printing company that delivered 
materials to non-prots was deliberately chosen to be unpleasant.4 
(4) Convenience of Purchase 
	The classic example here is coupons. There were 253 billion coupons 
issued in 2005. Low-valuation types have to signal their low valuations 
by going to the bother of clipping and remembering the coupon. 
(5) Quantity 
	Low-valuation types signal their type by forgoing bulk discounts. 
(6) Channel 
	Bestbuy.com has better prices than Best Buy stores, but a low-touch 
environment. Those with low valuations have to signal this by being 
prepared to not see the product before they purchase it. 
(7) Geography 
	Supermarkets charge dierent prices depending on location. Often, 
however, such price dierences are more a reection of local competi
tion than strategic price-segmentation.5 
(8) Add-on Pricing 
	The classic example of add-on pricing is where a hotel separates out its 
low-valuation types (vacationers) from its high-valuation types (busi
ness people) by charging for incidentals such as internet access. Low-
valuation types have to signal their low values by being willing to go 
without internet.6 
	This kind of price-segmentation is very like feature-based price seg
mentation except that the feature is explicitly optional. 
	The problem is that it can begin to feel like extra fees, which are 
separately painful each time a customer incurs them. 5 PRICING TO  SEGMENT CUSTOMERS 
skill to identify a product feature or aspect of your product, where you can distort 
quality downwards and ultimately not annoy your customers. An obvious place to 
start is to reframe the product choice as the idea that you are distorting product 
quality upwards from the low-value product, rather than vice versa. 
4.2. Dierent  types of product attribute segmentation. 
(1) Reliability  
Commercial oven thermometers cost 10 times more than oven ther  
mometers aimed  at the domestic market, because they promise within 
2 degree accuracy rather than within 10 degree accuracy. Here the 
low-valuation type have to signal that they are willing for their baked 
4Another example is The Mystery of the Rude Waiter: Why my favorite restaurant employs 
such a churlish lout, Tim Harford, Jan. 21, 2006 5See Wal-Mart Price Discrepancies Investigated, September 22 2008, WKMG 
6See How Much Should Hotel Web Access Cost? Sometimes its free. Sometimes its $20 a 
day. Why? By Steven E. Landsburg, Slate.com Wednesday, Feb. 1, 2006 News.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
15.818 Pricing 
Spring 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>PRICING TO SEGM ENT CUSTOMERS 
Contents 
1. Why the demand curve can be misleading as a concept for pricing 1 
2.	Strategic assessmen t of whether a rm should move from a single price 
strategy 1 
3. Customer-based price segmen tation	 2 
3.1. Implemen tation challenges	 2 
3.2. Price discrimination with anti-comp etitiv e intent	 2 
3.3. Ethical issues with customer-based price discrimination	 3 
4. Product-based price segme ntation	 4 
4.1. Necessary criteria for success	 4 
4.2. Dieren t types of product attribute segm entation	 5 
4.3. Challenges with product-line price segmen ting 6 
Appendix A. An example using radiology information software 7 
1. Why the demand curve can be misleading as a concept for pricing 
In the last lecture, we though t hard about how to measure the demand curve. 
But it is importan t to also think about why it slopes downwards. The answ er is 
variation in how much our customers value our product. 
The most crucial insigh t of this class is that we shouldnt think about where we 
should price along our demand curve. Instead we should think, how many dieren t 
prices to dieren t customers can I charge along my demand curve? 
P riceH  DiffV alueH 
ab + P ricebH 
a 
P riceL  DiffV alueL + P ricebL 
a ab 
In this familiar setting, by pricing at or below the Low price a rm is leaving 
money on the table. The crucial question is always how your rm can charge a lower 
price to low-valuation types and get them to enter the mark et, but still persuade 
the high-v aluation types to pay the high price. During this class we will talk about 
high and low types. This is just a short-hand for the multiple types along the 
demand curve, and the aim is always to construct price strategies to price to all of 
them. 
2.	Strategic assessment of whether a firm should move from a single 
price strategy 
(1) Does my product oering have dieren tiation value? 
(2) Can I identify 2+ customer value proles who theoretically have dieren t 
valuations for my product? 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 PRICING TO SEGMENT CUSTOMERS 
the dieren t costs of dealing with dieren t buyers or are the result of a sellers 
attempts to meet a comp etitors oering. 
3.2.1. Specic Legal Tests. 
(1) The Act applies to commo dities, but not to services, and to purchases, but 
not to leases. 
(2) The goods must be of like grade and qualit y. 
(3) There must be likely injury to comp etition (that is, a private plain ti must 
also show actual harm to his or her business). 
(4) Normally , the sales must be in interstate commerce (that is, the sale must 
be across a state line). 
3.2.2. Anti-trust authorities look for. 
	Below-cost sales by a rm that charges higher prices in dieren t localities 
	Price dierences in the sale of identical goods that cannot be justied on 
the basis of cost savings or meeting a comp etitors prices; or 
	Promotional allowances or services that are not practically available to all 
customers on proportionately equal terms. 
3.2.3. Outc omes from Robinson-Patman. 
	Merc k would sell the drugs to hospitals at a 92% discoun t from the cat
alog price, but only if the hospitals reached certain mark et shares for the 
drugs. Prosecuted for swindling Medicare/Medicaid by not oering these 
discoun ts. 
	Robinson-P atman explains why in Costco you enter a bizarre alternate 
universe of products for sale. Cereal comes in twin packs. Coke is available 
in cases containing 32 cans, not 24. Printer cartridges are sold in three-
packs, not as singles or in pairs as at other stores. 
	Since the Brooke Group Ltd. v. Brown &amp; Williamson and Volvo Trucks 
North America, Inc. v. Reeder-Simco GMC rulings there have been fewer 
successful prose cutions. Plain tis have to show harm rather than intent. 
3.3. Ethical issues with customer-based price discrimination. 
(1) Price discrimination must be legal 
	In addition to Robin son Patman Act (1936): B2B regulation, EU de
velopmen ts 
	Wheeler Lea Amendmen t: Bans unfair or deceptiv e acts in commerce 
	Racketeer Inuenced and Corrupt Organizations Act (RICO). Victo
rias Secrets diering catalog prices were prosecuted as mail fraud 
under this act. 
	Some state laws forbidding gender based price-segmen tation.1 
(2) Price discrimination must be culturally acceptable. It may be perceived as 
unfair or illegal even if it is not. 
	2/3 of adult internet users believe that it is illegal for online retailers 
to charge dieren t people dierent prices.2 
1See Is Ladies Night Legal?, Gelf Magazine, Septem ber 2007 
2Online shopp ers seem naive about prices: Consumers unaware of price customization, study 
nds, Associated Press, June 1 2005</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 PRICING TO SEGMENT CUSTOMERS 
	A similar story is true for rebates, which started o with the same 
premise as coupons, but retailers got addicted to slippage and people 
forgetting to send their rebate forms in. 
(7) Need pricing power 
	The problem here is generally non-strategic comp etitors. You are only 
able to main tain price fences while your comp etitors co-op erate. 
	Some surprising industries are able to sustain the kind of pricing 
power that you need for price segmen tation. For example, dry 
cleaners persist in charging more for womens blouses than mens 
shirts. 8 
	However, in ad-metrics industry a protable add-on used to be 
trademark infringemen t monitoring services, since these were 
of interest predominan tly to lawyers and other high-v aluation 
types. However, protabilit y of this segmen t has been chal
lenged by one-price-ts-all start-ups. 
Appendix A. An example using radiology informa tion softw are 
A radiology imaging services rm makes software that stores radiology images. 
The marginal cost of this software is zero. There are two potential groups of 
customers for this product: Hospitals and Veterinarians. 
The dieren tiation value of this software is that it allows a healthcare provider 
to compare and contrast more than one image at a time. In fact it actually allows 
them to compare up to 10 images at once. Both Veterinarians and Hospitals prefer 
to be able to look at more images at once, than not. However, hospitals value the 
abilit y to compare up to 10 images more than Veterinarians do, because the human 
anatom y is far more complex than the average dog or cat anatom y. 
The ideal strategy. There are QH Hospitals and QL Veterinarians who comp ose 
the mark et for this software. The EVC equations are simpli ed by assuming that 
because this software is so unique the appropriate reference product is no purchase, 
which has a price of zero. 
PH  DV A + DV B 
H H 
PL  DV A + DV B 
L L 
At the momen t the rm is following a penetration pricing strategy where they 
price at DV LA + DV LB = PL to everyone in order to maximize sales. There fore 
prots are 
current = PL(QH + QL) 
In a dream world, the rm would divine whether the custome r is a High or Low 
type and charge them accordingly . The prots of doing so would be equal to 
dream = PH QH + PLQL 
This would increase prots over the rms curren t pricing strategy by (PH 
PL)QH . In the real world, however, the software rm would be worried that if they 
8Taken to the Cleaners? Nobody can explain why laundries charge less for mens shirts than 
for womens, even E. Landsburg , Slate.com. July 3, 1998</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>an appropriate pricing schedule and to maintain appropriate price fences between 
the dierent products. 
4.1.	Necessary criteria for success. 
(1) Can identify an unambiguous component of dierentiation value correlated 
with overall EVC (e.g. convenience). Structure product accordingly. 
(2) Distortion:	 This component of dierentiation value must be correlated 
strongly enough with overall EVC that high-valuation types will pay a 
premium rather than not have it. Or in other words, you are going to force 
your low-valuation types to signal that they have low-valuations because 
you are going to distort your product quality downwards. 
	Comfort, Speed, Reliability, Ease of use are good places to start. 
(3) Compensation: This component of dierentiation value must be not so 
essential that low-valuation types will never buy the product without it. 
Price to compensate them. This is why we see discounts for economy class 
discomfort. 
I illustrate analytically the concepts of Distortion and Compensation in a 
detailed mathematical illustration in the appendix to this handout. Though this 
is a highly analytical concept based on economic ideas of signaling, this is actually 
the place where pricing becomes more of an art than a science. You will need the 4 PRICING TO SEGMENT CUSTOMERS 
	Bloomberg waged a war on a Chinese restaurant that charged $1 more 
on its English menu, though it was dicult to nd a law to prosecute 
under. 
	Controversy of supermarket chain that had unique 10 percent mark
up for stores targeted at Hispanic shoppers3 
	Sometimes, just sometimes, this can be resolved by better framing. 
	Disney customer-based discrimination would be a lot less palat
able if they said they are going to charge more for adults, than 
if they said, as they do now, they are going to oer discounts to 
kids. 
(3) Privacy Issues 
	Customer-based price discrimination that makes use of past customer 
data is often felt to encroach on a customers privacy. This is becoming 
more important in Europe, and latterly so in the US. 
(4) We worry about the ethical nature of price discrimination. I would argue, 
however, that when a company does not price-segment because it cant nd 
appropriate metrics, then this can lead to just as bad consequences. For 
example, in the early 2000s 90% of those who suer from AIDS could not 
aord the prices charged for AIDS drugs. 
The feeling that such a practice is not fair can be ascrib ed partly to a feeling 
of customer powerlessness. This has led rms to redesign their price segmen tation 
strategies to emphasize that customers have a choice into which bucket they fall. 
4. Product-based price segment ation 
In product-based price segmen tation, the customer decides what price they will 
pay based on the products observ able characteristics . The rms job is to create 
3See 9 questions with Nash Finch Co. and Some grocery stores add 10 percen t fee, Dan 
Boniface, 9news.com, Octob er 10, 2008 .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 PRICING TO SEGMENT CUSTOMERS 
charged a Veterinarian one price and a Hospital another price for this software, as 
the Veterinarian would just resell it to the Hospital. 
Product-b ased price segmentation. Product-Based Price segmen tation is where the 
design of the product is such that it encourages customers to signal whether they 
are a high-v aluation or a low-valuation type through their choice of product. High-
valuation types value the software more in two dimensions: the number of images 
it can composite (A) and high-qualit y documen tation that facilitates the use of the 
software (B). 
The high-v aluation types value the number of comp osite images more. 
DVA
H&gt; DVA
L 
The high-v aluation types also value the documen tation more. 
DVB&gt;DVL B
H 
The challenge is how to use these dierences in valuations to segmen t the mark et. 
Let the rm designs two products. 
 Complete product 
 Discoun t product (whic h has no documentation). 
The aim is to ensure that high-v aluation types choose the complete product and 
the low-valuation types choose the discoun t product. In particular, high-v aluation 
types must be deterred from pretending to be low-valuation types and buying the 
discoun t product. Therefore the price of the complete good needs to be less than 
the net benets of the discoun t good given its lower price and lower dieren tiation 
value. But this is simply the binding EVC equation. 
P C = P D + DV
. B
H 
For high-v aluation types, the reference product is now endogenously determined 
by the choice of price for the discoun t product. For low-valuation types, the outside 
option is still no software with a price of zero. To ensure that they buy the product, 
the rm needs to price at: 
P D = DV
. A
L 
Therefore, recognizing that by oering this discoun t product the reference price 
has now changed for high-v aluation types, means that the rm prices the complete 
product at: 
P C = DVA
L+ DVB
H 
. 
How do these prices do compared to the perfect segmen tation ideal? Ideally , the 
rm would charge low-valuation types: 
PL  DVA
L+ DVB
L 
But under product-based segmen tation, the rm instead charges low-valuation 
types:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 PRICING TO SEGMENT CUSTOMERS 
(9) Timing of Deliv ery 
	High-v aluation types are willing to pay more for early delivery of goods. 
This can be as simple as charging a premium for express shipping. Or 
it can be as complex as skimming your initial mark et and pricing high 
for early adopters, and then lowering prices for late adopters. Low-
valuation types therefore have to signal their low valuations by waiting 
for the product to go mass-mark et. These kind of skimming strategies, 
however, can lead to customer unhappi ness, as we saw in the case of 
Apple with their IPhone pricing. 
4.3. Challenges with product-line price segmen ting. 
(1) Finding attributes that correlate with EVC 
	For example, a skateboard manufacturer sold a premium line of skate
boards with better wheels and colors, and also a discoun t stripp ed-
down line where there were few patterns and the wheels were obviously 
plastic. The stripped down basic skateboards sold out, and actually 
resold for higher prices on eBay than the non-stripp ed premium ver
sion. 
(2) Ensuring the integrit y of the dieren t products within the product line is 
main tained. 
	Customers can re-engineer low-segmen t products. For example, GPS 
for boating was re-engineered to work for airplanes. 
(3) Perceiv ed fairness for low-segmen t users 
	A catalog compan y found a negativ e eect on all sales for including 
dieren tial pricing for plus-sizes 
	Dell faced a backlash from all customers for its new XPS pricing 
scheme, where high-v alue custome rs got access to faster technical 
supp ort. 
(4) Price segmen tation can unwittingly reveal your costs. 
	Fast-setting bandage material manufacturer revealed just how cheap 
its product was to make when it started selling its product as a novelty 
craft item. 
(5) Can create bad publicit y if price fences are found out 
	Best Buy got caugh t out with a secret website that customer service 
reps showed in-store customers, that supp orted its policy of chargin g 
less on the internet than in stores.7 
(6) Cost-Eectiv eness of Separation 
	Main taining dieren t product features can be expensiv e. This can 
mean that it may in limited circumstances be necessary to discon
tinue product-based price segmen tation. For example, a baby carrier 
compan y had to discon tinue organic line as it was too expensiv e to 
manage. 
	Sometimes product segmen tation goals can be lost to short-term prot 
goals. For example, Alamo and National decided to co-lo cate their car 
rental services. 
7Press Release: Attorney General, DCP Commissioner Sue Best Buy For Deceiving, Over
charging Customers, May 2007 .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 PRICING TO SEGMENT CUSTOMERS 
(3) Is there empirical evidence that these dierent customers actually have the 
EVC dierences you expect them to have? 
	Very dierent price elasticities indicate that they do have dierent 
EVC. 
(4) Is there empirical evidence that customers in this value prole have similar 
enough EVC? 
	You can nd out whether you have segmen ted enough, by trying to 
segmen t again. If the new price-elasticities that you calculate are no
ticeably dieren t from each other then you have not segme nted enough. 
When mark eters talk about customer segme nts, they are often thinking of a 
certain type such as Denim Dads, Yoga Mommies, or Gen Y-ers. However, 
when pricing analysts use the term segmen tation, they are thinking of some
thing far more specic. The aim of empirical analysis at all times is to identify 
and charge dieren t prices to High and Low types. There are two main means 
of implemen ting segmen tation: Customer-based and Product-attribute based. In 
customer-based price segmen tation, the rm selects which prices the customer will 
pay based on their observ able characteristics. In product-based price segm entation, 
the customer decides what price they will pay based on the products observ able 
characteristics. The rms job is to create an appropriate pricing schedule and price 
fences between the dieren t products. 
3. Customer-based price segment ation 
3.1. Implementation challenges. In customer-based price segmentation, the rm 
selects which prices the customer will pay based on their observable characteristics. 
(1) Unambiguous indicator of group membership 
	For example, veterinarians have veterinarian school certicates that 
the rm could demand be produced for a discount. 
(2) Characteristic must be correlated with EVC 
	This is not always clear cut. We saw this in the empirical example that 
we discussed in class, where the doctors had widely dierent valuations. 
This is problem too in the real world. 
	For example, Quickbooks had been charging existing customers 
less because it reckoned that they would value an upgrade less 
since they already had it. However, there was actually a split 
between those who valued it less and those who valued it more. 
(3) Product must not be tradeable across groups 
	An enterprising veterinarian could purchase the software and resell at 
a prot to a hospital. 
	This explains why customer-based segmentation is found mostly for 
services or experiences. 
3.2. Price discrimination with anti-competitive intent. A seller charging 
competing buyers dierent prices for the same commodity or discriminating in 
the provision of allowances - compensation for advertising and other services 
may violate the Robinson-Patman Act. This kind of price discrimination may give 
favored customers an edge in the market that has nothing to do with their superior 
eciency. Price discrimination is generally lawful, particularly if they prices reect</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>9 PRICING TO SEGMENT CUSTOMERS 
P D = DV LA 
Therefore the rm distorts prices downwards by DV LB , to compensate low-
valuation types for the fact that they have to choose not to get the documen tation 
to signal that they are the low-valuation type. Ideally the rm wants to charge 
high-v aluation types a price of: 
PH  DV A + DV B 
H H 
But under product-based segmen tation, the rm instead charges high-v aluation 
types: 
P C = DV LA + DV HB 
Therefore the rm distorts price downwards by (DV A  DV A) to bribe the H L 
high-v aluation type to buy the non discoun t product. 
A.0.1. Protability. For product-based price segmen tation to be protable requires 
it to be more protable than current pricing practices. 
pbseg mentation  current = 
P C QH + P DQL  PL(QH + QL) 
(DV A + DV B )QH +(DV A)QL  (DV A + DV B )(QH + QL)L H L L L 
Therefore the protabi lity condition for customer-based price segmen tation is: 
(DV B  DV B )QH  QLDV B 
H L L</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec06</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_lec06/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>PRICING AND IT 
Contents 
1. Pricing and IT Systems 1
1.1. Great uses for price optimization software 1
1.2. Some problems these systems have faced 2
2. Case Study: Google Adwords Pricing 3
2.1. Adwords Pricing Process 3
2.2. Lessons to learn from Google 4
3. Pricing for Software Platforms 5
3.1. Two-Sided Platforms 5
3.2. Pricing strategies in two-sided platforms 5
3.3. Implementation of two-sided platform pricing strategies 6
3.4. Challenges with two-sided platform pricing 7
In todays lecture we discuss two separate issues. The rst is how software 
platforms can transform pricing. The second is pricing for software platforms. 
1. Pricing and IT Systems 
Theoretically, IT advances have the potential to revolutionize pricing. However, 
there has been mixed success. Generally, they perform two functions: 
(1) Automating the calculation of price elasticities. This is very useful if you 
have multiple dierence SKUs or dierent sources of data. (See earlier 
lectures battery example). 
(2) Suggesting a price based on these price elasticities given some kind of con
straint (such as limited or perishable capacity). This involves price opti
mization. 
1.1. Great uses for price optimization software. 
1.1.1. Avoiding overcrowding. One optimal use for IT pricing software systems is 
when there is an externality problem. A good example is road congestion pricing, 
where a city prices roads higher during peak hours to deter drivers from driving 
then. This is also the case for water parks, theme parks and so on. These are 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 PRICING AND IT 
	Quote from USA Today (2007) 
A few years ago, 7-Elev en Inc. noticed that when 
it fought to beat down certain costs, so its con
venience stores could reduce some of the prices they 
charged consumers, the eort wasnt always worth
while, says Kay Trapp, manager for merc handise pric
ing. It turned out that several items with newly low
ered prices saw no change in sales. The chain bought 
price-optimization software to get such insigh ts in ad
vance. We decided it made us smarter, Trapp says. 
(3) Limitations to the use of optimization software created for selling airplane 
seats in industries that have no capacit y constrain ts.. 
	Example of software that created articial constrain ts in order to be 
able to say that it was optimizing. 
2. Case Study: Google Adwords Pricing 
A lot of these problems are caused because IT systems model peoples pricing 
behavior in the future as being like it was in the past. They also assume that people 
will not try and outsm art the pricing software. However, it makes a lot more sense 
if IT systems instead were focused on giving incen tives so that people were actually 
willing to tell the rm what they were willing to pay. This is what Google has 
been able to do with its automated auctions for advertising searc h terms Adw ords 
system. By doing this, Google has transformed itself into the mark et leader in the 
provision of advertising. 
2.1. Adwords Pricing Process. First, a quick description of the Google searc h 
term auction mechanism: 
Firms enroll in Adwords  
	They pick the particular searc h terms that they want their ads to displa y 
next to 
	They then place a bid for each of these terms. 
	(Roughly) the rm that bids the highest amoun t has their ad displa yed 
rst, and pays the price bid by the second highest bidder. 
	I say roughly because Google also adjusts the price bidders pay based 
on their Qualit y Score, that is, how many customers click through on 
the ad. 
	The second highest bidders ad displa ys second, and they pay the price bid 
by the third highest bidder, and so on.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 PRICING AND IT 
examples of goods that have a very high xed capacit y and highly variable demand, 
leading to congestion at certain times that they need to manage. 
1.1.2.	 Avoiding spare capacity . 
The most expensiv e thing in a restauran t is an empt y table 
Gus Bassele, restaur ant marketer 
Most rms want to operate at somethin g close to full capacit y whenev er they 
can. By booking a hotel room, I am directly preventing another custom er from 
taking that hotel room. 
This trade-o between pricing a room low and selling it now against waiting and 
potentially selling a room at the last minute for a higher price, has given rise to the 
practice of revenue managemen t. 
The good news is that Sloan is including more revenue managemen t examples 
in the operation s managem ent class that is taugh t by Professors Vivek Farias and 
Jeremie Gallien. Those of you who are thinking of working in the airline industry , 
the travel industry , or any industry that has a xed number of goods to sell should 
take this class. Also, those of you with a operations managemen t bent will learn 
useful optimization techniques. 
In a general sense, while optimization techniques for revenue managemen t are 
importan t, equally importan t is constructing the right price fences to optimize 
around. Revenue can be impro ved by: 
	Identifying new pricing fences 
	Preventing arbitrage across existing pricing fences 
	Improving customer perceptions of pricing fairness 
1.1.3. Sometimes there are success stories outside of traditional revenue manage
ment domains. Generally most success stories outside of industries with xed ca
pacities rest on a better understanding of price elasticities. Theoretically , optimiza
tion systems could optimize over cost schedules, but I have come across no software 
systems that do this very well primarily because managers simply do not know cost 
schedules. 
1.2. Some problems these systems have faced. 
(1) Used a price management rather than optimization tool. 
	Large department store invested in expensive pricing optimization soft
ware. Merchandizing set key commands on override and used it pre
dominantly to manage the prices that they set using their super gut. 
(2) Sometimes management uses it for uses it was not intended for...</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>5 PRICING AND IT 
3. Pricing for Softw are Platforms 
3.1.	Two-Sided Platform s. 
3.1.1. What is a two-side d platform? The majority of new business models on the 
internet are actually two-sided platforms. This is especially true for companies that 
MIT Sloan graduates set up. These are sometimes referred to as two-sided networks 
or two-sided mark ets. A two-sided platform is one where two groups interact over 
a comm on platform or mark et. 
In the Keurig Case, we though t hard about how to price strate gically with lock-in. 
Generally , there are large ties between mark ets which have lock-in or razor-blades 
pricing and mark ets that are two-sided platforms. For example, Keurig would have 
been a two-sided platform if it just acted as an intermediary for the roasters and the 
customers and did not attempt to sell coee itself. The key dierence in mark ets 
where there is just lock-in is that the customers decision to purchase a product 
gives the rm purchasin g power over him. By contrast, in a two-sided platform, the 
customers decision to purchase a product also gives the network operator power 
over the purchasing decisions over those on the other side of the network. 
There are three major dieren t kinds of two-sided platforms (Evans and Schmalensee 
2007)1 
(1) Exchanges.	 These are typically networks that bring together disparate 
groups of buyers and sellers. 
	Examples include craigslist.org, a Mall, eBay.com. 
(2) Software systems .	Generally the platform is the operating system, and the 
two groups are compu ter users and program developers. 
	Linux, Windo ws 
	XBox, Playstation 
(3) Content-Bas ed Markets. Thes e are mark ets, such as newspap ers, where on 
one side there are advertisers and on the other side users who want access 
to the content. 
	The content can be user generated like on Facebook. 
	Or it can be generated by the website as in the case of yellowpages.com, 
Salon.com or (perhaps) Google 
These mark ets tend to be characte rized by high xed costs and strong network 
eects. 
3.2. Pricing strategies in two-sided platforms. Pricing strategy for two-sided 
platforms is more complicated, because there are potentially two sets of access fees 
and usage fees to set. 
1There are also paymen ts system s, but these are too specic to discuss in this class</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 PRICING AND IT 
ough its website. To acquire restaurants, Re customers thr wards Net
works oered restauran ts advances of $10k to $25k. The restauran t 
rewards network receiv ed dining credits of 150% to 200% of the amoun t 
of the advance. So for example, if a restauran t was advanced $10k, 
the Rewards Network would be entitled to sell its members $20k of 
credit at the restauran t. They signed up 3 million customers and 
10,000 restauran ts. However, they were then hit by an unfavorable 
class-action suit for usurious interest rates. 
(4) Comp etitiv e Concerns 
	Why is the Kindle priced so high? Some observ ers have speculated it is 
to appease Amazons standard publishing mark et. However, Amazon 
is also having trouble pricing e-books high where high is above $9.995 
	However, the iPad is priced even higher ($499 iPad costs around $290 
to make) 
5Kindle Readers Ignite Protest Over E-Bo ok Prices, Wired Apr 6, 2009, Priya Ganapati</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>7 PRICING AND IT 
However, the real challenge was actually persuading suppliers to pay 
the 5% listing fee. They simply could not see the value proposition. 
(2) Software systems 
	Adob es revolutionary price model was to give away the reader for free 
and make people pay for Adob e Distiller. 
	Opentable charged restauran ts to join its reserv ation service. After 
a $1000 to $1300 syste m setup fee, restauran ts paid $100 to $200 a 
month plus $1 for each honored reserv ation. This restricts the number 
of restauran ts that it can sell for. Customers receiv e reward points. For 
each reserv ation a customer made, they earned $1. By 2009, Opentable 
has served 75 million diners at 8,400 restaurants. 
(3) Content Mark ets 
	Platforms have to decide whether to charge people or use an advertising-
based model.2 This is not always obvious. 
	Facebooks big challenge is to think of a way of monetizing the interac
tion between users and advertisers. The key issue they face is privacy 
concerns. 
3.4. Challenges with two-sided platform pricing. 
(1) Make sure that you are subsidizing an attractiv e group of customers 
	FreePC learned this lesson in 1999 when it provided computers and 
Internet access at no cost to consumers who agreed to view Internet-
delivered ads that could not be minimized or hidden. Unfortunately , 
few mark eters were eager to target consumers who were so cost-c onscious. 
FreePC abandoned its oer after losing $80 million.3 
	Youtub e.com may just have the wrong kind of content to successfully 
monetarize. Too much is highly personal.4 
(2) Product supply issues 
	One interesting side note is to think why it is that in a two-sided tech
nology mark et such as a Playstation or an Xbox, rms persisten tly un
dersupply the mark et initially . The real winners in such situations are 
the game console proteers who hawk the systems on eBay. Playsta
tion 3s sold roughly for $1,500 on eBay just after the launc h. The 
retail price was $599. 
(3) Lack of broad understanding of these issues can lead to legal problems. 
	Sometimes usage fees are very large. Rew ards Network is a two-
sided platform that allows restauran ts to oer coup ons to potential 
2See Why You Didnt Pay To Read This , Slate.com, Oct 27, 2007 . 
3Free-PC.com sets o sales frenzy , 11 Feb 1999, ZDNET.co.uk 
4YouTube Is Doomed, April 9 2009, Benjamin Wayne</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
15.818 Pricing 
Spring 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 PRICING AND IT 
2.2. Lessons to learn from Google. 
(1) Auctions can help price your good 
	Auctions are incredibly successful at encouraging buyers to state their 
true valuations. Think of the typical auction, where the winning bidder 
pays the price bid by the second-highest bidder. Can you think of any 
circumstances under which the highest bidder would choose to bid less 
than they did? 
	It is no surprise then that rms that sell goods much prefer to use 
auctions when possible. About 80 percen t of private equity rms in 
a recen t poll said they prefer to use auctions when acting as sellers. 
Mean while, about 90 percen t of the same rms said they preferred to 
avoid auctions when acting as buyers. (Auction Process Roundtable, 
Mergers and Acquisitions, Decem ber 2006, pp. 31-32.) 
	Auctions therefore represen t an attractiv e alternativ e to implemen ting 
revenue managemen t techniques. Rather than using historical data 
and assumptions, the rm simply gives customers the right incen tives 
to state their true willingness to pay. 
	Items that were dicult to price through other means (for example, 
Art and Houses ). These goods were characterized by high enough 
prices to make it worthwhile to run an auction. 
	Items that needed to be sold quickly and in bulk (for example trade-in 
cars, various nancial instrumen ts and Dutch owers). It was worth
while running an auction in order to be sure of quick sales. 
(2) Identifying the right type of network interaction to price can be crucial 
	Pay-per-clic k big success compared to pay-per-impression 
	Pay-per-action is less clearly a success 
(3) Pricing on the most micro scale possible is essen tial for protabilit y 
	(Goldfarb and Tucker 2009) show that crucially the most protable 
searc h terms are the ones at the most micro level with the fewest 
searc hes. 
	We provide evidence that Google is able to charge even more when the 
mark et is thin -that is, when the mark et is part of the long tail. 
	The crucial take-away is that to emulate Googles success in using 
electronic auctions, the key thing to do is to use auctions to price the 
most micro and specic version of your product that you can. 
Question: Why are advertisers willing to pay a higher average price per click for 
appearing rst?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 PRICING AND IT 
	An access fee is the price paid to use the network technology , which is 
indep enden t of usage 
	A usage fee is the price paid to interact with someone else over the network 
(1) Identify the group that has larger spillo vers for the other group 
	For example, a nightclub having more women customers is more likely 
to attract a large number of men than a nightclub having a large 
number of men is to attract a large number of women. Browsers bring 
greater benets to advertisers than vice versa. 
	We can use our Excel technique again to gauge the dierences in elas
ticity between groups. We need to subsidize the group that has the 
lower absolute elasticit y. In our example, men have a higher elasticit y 
for the presence of women than vice-v ersa. 
(2) We also need to identify the group that is more price-sensitiv e. 
	For example, lawyers clients are more price-sensitiv e than lawyers 
themselv es. 
(3) If price-sensitivit y and spillo vers go in the same direction, that is great. If 
not, then it makes strategic sense to reduce access fees on the price-sensitiv e 
side and raise the usage price for the less network-sensitiv e side. 
Another strategy is to target subsidies so as to encourage a particular user of 
the platform to agree to use your platfor m. For example, when Universal Studios 
agreed to make only HD-D VDs. 
3.3. Implemen tation of two-sided platform pricing strategies. 
(1) Exchanges 
	EBay is the classic example of a successful two-sided exchange network. 
They charge both listing fees and transactional fees to their sellers. 
	Chemdex provided an online marketplace for sales of chemicals, en
zymes, lab equipmen t, biotech products like peptides, and many types 
of chemical reagen ts. Chemdex signed up nearly 150,000 users who 
ordered products from more than 2,000 suppliers. The Chemdex data
base listed around a million products from beakers to specialt y bio
chemicals. At the point of its IPO Chemdex recorded quarterly sales of 
$165,000, mostly to Genen tech, and had lost $6.8 million in the same 
quarter. Yet it raised $112.5 million at IPO, and its stock rose 60% on 
the rst day, valuing the whole compan y (including those shares still 
privately held) at over $750 million. Its value eventually shrunk to 1% 
of its previous value. It made its money by charging a 1 percen t fee 
on transactions. The problem with this compan y was that all their 
mark eting eorts (Get a Free T-shirt!) were aimed at consumers.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_supp02</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-818-pricing-spring-2010/resources/mit15_818s10_supp02/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>NON-LINEAR PRICING 
Contents 
1. Quan tity Discoun ts	 1 
2. Metered Pricing	 1 
3. Value-Based Pricing Metrics	 1 
Sometimes we need to sell more than one unit of our good to each customer. 
1. Quantity Discounts 
The basic theory about oering quan tity discoun ts is that it allows you to serve 
high-v aluation and low-valuation customers. High-v aluation customers signal the 
fact they are high-v aluation customers to you by purchasing in bulk. Low-valuation 
customers signal that they value your product less by buying fewer units but at a 
high unit price. 
There are some practical problems: 
	There are often practical problems when it comes to managing returns, 
as customers may buy more units to get the discount but expect to be 
refunded at the average per-unit price for the units they return. 
	The ideal product is something like a banana, where resellers cannot store 
or hoard the product and it is dicult and expensive to resell. 
	There must be no realistic chance of hoarding of the product by consumers. 
	The Robinson-Patman Act was explicitly designed to try and prevent rms 
using these kind of non-linear taris to benet chain stores at the expense 
of Mom and Pop stores 
2. Metered Pricing 
Often some form of metered pricing arrangement is preferable where the buyer 
purchases goods simply on the basis of usage. Variations along this theme are 
razor-blade models where the customer buys a low price durable (the razor) and 
then subsequen tly purchases high price consumables (the blades). 
3. Value-Based Pricing Metrics 
With any form of pricing, the key to pricing multiple units of a good to each 
customer is to get the pricing metric right. 
	For example, for most information services it makes sense to price per 
download rather than per minute. 
	It very rarely makes sense to charge per hour. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu 
15.818 Pricing 
Spring 2010 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
