<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/</course_url>
    <course_title>Problems of Philosophy</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>Ethics </list>
      <list>Philosophy </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 20: Appiah and Spencer on Race
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout20/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
are required for us to allow that a certain pattern of usage concerning the word Y 
results in Y referring to a thing X: 
(1) Existence  X must exist 
(2) Adequacy  Some of what was said to be true of Y must be approximately true of 
X. 
(3) Uniqueness  X must be the best candidate for the job of being Ys referent  no 
other thing that satisfies the existence condition satisfies the adequacy condition. 
4. Why there are no races 
On the ideational view  Appiah says that idea of race has been used in a way to required significant correlations between the biological and the moral, literary or psychological characters of human beings; and these be explained by the intrinsic nature of the members of the race. Nothing meets these criteria so there are no races. 
-But is it still used that way today? 
On the referential view  
There are many ways of classifying people , but to satisfy Uniqueness we need there to be 
one way that is the best. 
Appiah, Anthony. The Uncompleted Argument: DuBois and the Illusion of Race. Critical Inquiry 12, no. 1 (1985): 2137.  University of Chicago Press. All 
rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu / 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 
Handout 20 
Appiah and Spencer on Race 
1. A Rough View of the Landscape 
Biological Realism  Races exist and are biological categories 
Was the widely accepted view back in the day and was used to justify racism. The 
view has been mostly rejected on the basis of the idea that races dont actually carve out any natural categories, but it is making a bit of a comeback. 
Social Constructivis m  Races exist and are social categories 
A widely accepted view according to which races are defined primarily by the social role they play. (Analogy: dimes) 
Race Eliminiativiesm  Races dont exist 
The main idea (I think) is that there is no interesting natural or significant category carved out by race terminology. 
2. Spencer: In Defense of Biological Races 
1. Human continental populations are real biological entities. 
2. Human continental populations are folk races. 
3. Folk races are real biological entities 
Definitions: 
A race is a group of people called a race in some language. 
A folk race  a race that is talked about in ordinary language 
Essence  That which makes something what it is 
Biological Entity  a thing whose essence consists of biological qualities in whole or in part 
(Spencer will count a biological entity as real if careful biology has determined that the 
entity actually exists). 
Defense of P1 
Structure program : A program that divides individuals into a specified number of clusters 
based on genetic similarity. (The program may declare that no single best clustering is 
found. 
Rosenberg et al reported that humans can be divided into five continent-level biological 
populations that are called human-continental population : Africans, East Asians, 
Eurasians, Native Americans and Oceanians. 
Note: there is still some controversy about the upshot of these results. One thing worth noting is that the number 5 was input by the research group. Other choice 
points include number of loci, sample size, geographic dispersion of the samples, etc (In one version for K=6, the Kalesh people of Northern Pakistan count as a 
Spencer, Quayshawn. Are Folk Races like Dingoes, Dimes or Dodos? In The Norton Introduction to Philosophy. 2nd ed. Edited by Gideon Rosen, Alex 
Byrne, Joshua Cohen, et al. W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 2018.  W.W. Norton &amp; Company. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
distinct cluster). However, Spencer points out that the largest study on human 
population subdivision has since confirmed Rosenbergs result, using a population of heavily mixed people. Furthermore, Spencer says, ~70% of samples studied 
since 2002 confirmed the result despite using very different genomic data, ethnic 
group samples, and structure-like programs. 
(Rosenberg et al confirm that only ~5% of genetic variation can be explained by 
variation in continental clusters). 
Defense of P2 
US governments OMB racial scheme: American Indians, Asians, Blacks, Pacific 
Islanders and Whites correspond closely to the continental clusters. 
3. Appiah In Defense of Eliminativism 
In Appiahs article on DuBois, he claims that races dont exist. He considers and rules 
out various ways of understanding races: 
 Biological  Appiah claims this conception has been debunked 
 Cultural  There is huge cultural variation amongst so called races 
 Historical  Appiah thinks this is circular. Whether two races count as having a shared history will depend on what makes two groups of peoples history count as shared. 
 Social/Oppression  Many so called distinct races have experienced similar patterns of oppression. 
In other work Appiah (Race, Culture Identity goes into greater detail: 
Ideational view  to understand what race means requires understanding what people take 
to be the central truths about races; On this view: The critical beliefs define the concept. 
(Example: you are the same race as your parents, people with very different skin colors 
are of different races). 
Strict critical theory: To know what race means you should believe all of the 
critical beliefs. (Something is a race only if all the critical beliefs are true of it). 
Vague critical theory: To know what race means you should believe most of the critical beliefs. (Something is a race only if most of the c ritical beliefs are true of it). 
To argue that races dont exist: argue that there is nothing in the world that matches most 
of the central beliefs people have about race. 
Referential view  to understand what race means is to be able to identify t he things to 
which it refers. To figure this out, we look at what things in the world give the best causal 
explanation of the way the word has been used . Appiah thinks that three things (at least) 
Appiah, Anthony. The Uncompleted Argument: DuBois and the Illusion of Race. Critical Inquiry 12, no. 1 (1985): 2137.  University of Chicago Press. All rights reserved. 
This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
Spencer, Quayshawn. Are Folk Races like Dingoes, Dimes or Dodos? In The Norton Introduction to Philosophy. 2nd ed. Edited by Gideon Rosen, Alex Byrne, Joshua Cohen, 
et al. W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 2018.  W.W. Norton &amp; Company. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 1: Basics of Analytic Philosophy
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>0</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 1 
Basics of Analytic Philosophy 
1. What Do We Do? 
Philosophy addresses questions which are usually big, important, and are the intellectual leftovers 
 questions that we dont yet have complete methods for answering in any other academic 
discipline. Examples: 
1. Does God exist? (A specific version: does an all-powerful, all-knowing, perfectly-
benevolent agent who created the universe exist?) 
2. Is it rational to have faith? 
3. Are there objective facts about whats right and wrong? 
4. Is the mind a physical entity? 
5. Is there free will? 
6. Is gender socially constructed? 
2. How Do We Do It? 
Through argument. Heres what the process looks like for an individual philosopher, which during Fall 2019, will be you! 
Discover - Discover an intellectual reaction (for example, by contemplating a question or reading a 
philosophy paper) 
Explore - Explore the reaction (for example, by free- writing) 
Formalize - Turn the reaction into an argument. (This is the part that requires skills youll be 
learning in this class). See if you still endorse the reaction upon seeing it in argument form. If 
not, modify the argument, or explore your reaction further. Play around until youre happy. 
Convey - Convey the argument to others 
Receive Feedback - If youre lucky enough to get feedback from another human, listen extremely 
carefully to their intellectual reaction. Take it in. Ask questions about it until you fully 
understand it. (Note  the aim is not to refute it, its to understand it!) 
Start over: Discover - Observe a reaction to their reaction in yourself</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 16: Williams on Personal Identity
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 16 
Williams on Personal Identity 
1. The Case 
Suppose A and B are going to be put to sleep. Wires will be set up between their brains such that 
all the information encoded in As brain will be transferred to Bs and vice versa. 
When they wake up well be confronted with two people: 
One person with what -was-As body and what- was-Bs mind. Well call him The A -bodied person 
The second with what- was-Bs body and what- was-As mind. Well call him The B -bodied person 
Before being put to sleep its announced that the one of the two people after the experiment will 
be given $100,000 and the other will be tortured. Each of A and B before the experiment are asked which treatment they want each post-procedure person to get from a purely selfish perspect ive. 
2. In Support of Psychological Criteria 
Consideration 1: Suppose A chooses that the B -body person gets the pleasant treatment and the 
A-body person gets the unpleasant person. And B chooses the reverse (that the A-body person get the pleasant treat ment). 
The experimenter cant act in accordance with both preferences. 
Suppose she gives the pleasant experience to the A-body person and the unpleasant experience to 
the B-body person, in accord with Bs pre-procedure preferences. Then the A-body person will be 
very pleased upon waking up, and claim I made the right choice! Im so glad the experimenter 
decided to go with what I wanted. Whereas the B-body person will be upset and claim: My choice wasnt honored! 
This is some evidence that the A-body person really is B, and the B-body person really is A. And that 
in fact each person made the right choice. 
Why is this evidence ? Perhaps the thought is: 
If Xs belief about his past are beliefs about what A did, that is some evidence that X is A. 
Consideration 2: Suppose A has anxiety and hopes that as a result of the procedure his anxiety 
will diminish. After the procedure the A-body person is asked: Do you feel relief from your anxiety? The A -body person will respond: What are you talking about? Ive never had any 
anxiety. If the B -body person is asked the same question hell say sadly, this procedure did 
nothing to relieve my anxiety. 
Why is this evidence for the psychological criterion? Perhaps the thought is: 
If Xs claims about his past mental life are claims about what As mental life was like that is some evidence that X is A. 
Williams, Bernard. The Self and the Future. Philosophical Review 79, no. 2 (1970): 16180.  Duke University Press. All rights reserved. This content is 
excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>More generally, perhaps the thought is: we should defer to present people who their past selves were . 
3. In Support of the Bodily Criterion 
Suppose Im told Ill be tortured. Ill be unhappy about this. Suppose they say: while youre being tortured you wont remember being informed of the fact 
that youll be tortured 
This wont mitigate my concern (Note: according to Parfit this should mitigate my con cern a bit) 
Suppose they then add that during the torture I wont remember several things. 
This wont mitigate my concern. Ill think torture + amnesia! Thats awful! 
Suppose they also add that the torture will result in my brain getting messed up in su ch a way 
that I have apparent memories that are not my own. 
This wont mitigate my concern. Ill think in addition to being tortured Ill have gone mad. 
But, Williams says, this is the same as the case described earlier, just presented differently! Acco rding to the psychological criteria my comfort should be increasing as the description 
continues and at the end I should think this person being tortured will not be me! 
Other intuition- pumps in the vicinity: 
 Fears about general anesthesia 
 If you were told youd be in a car accident, and wake up with amnesia and with a 
different personality, would you want to invest in this persons well being, pain relief, medical care etc? Would you expect your friends and family to care for this person? 
4. Possible Source s of the Conflicting Intuitions 
Possible Source #1: The language, its described as Ill be tortured, Ill cease to remember my 
past, etc. Response: if we found the idea incoherent we wouldnt/shouldnt go along with it. Williams suggests that, whats underlying the intuition is the thought my undergoing physical pain in the 
future is not excluded by any psychological state I may be in at the time (169) (with certain obvious exceptions). 
Possible Source #2: The other person, the person would be me in a body-swap case, is not even 
mentioned! So I latch on to the only person in the story who could be me. 
5. Breaking it Down 
(From p.172): 
(i) A is subjected to an operation which produces total amnesia; 
(ii) Amnesia is produced in A and other interference leads to certain changes in his 
character 
Williams, Bernard. The Self and the Future. Philosophical Review 79, no. 2 (1970): 16180.  Duke University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded 
from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>(iii) Changes in his character are produced, and at the same time illusory memory beliefs 
are induced in him; these are of quite a fictitious kind and do not fit the life of any actual person; 
(iv) The same as (iii) except that both the character traits and the memory impressions are designed to be appropriate to another actual person B. 
(v) The same as (iv) except that the result is produced by putting the information into A 
from the brain of B by a method which leaves B the same as he was before; 
(vi) The same happens to A as in (v) but B is not left the same, since a similar operation is 
conducted in the reverse direction. 
When would you start feeling comforted? 
Williams thinks that A should clearly be afraid of situation (i), (ii) and (iii). 
Doesnt seem like the fact that the memory impressions are those of an actual human being 
should make a difference. (iv) And if we think that why should it matter to me whether they just happened to be the same or whether they were obtained through B (v). 
So the crucial turning point must happen in (vi), where As psychology gets transplanted into B. 
But once weve gotten to (v), says Williams, why would A care what happens to this other person? 
The move from (v) to (vi), says Williams, seems like one of the least plausible ones to block because the change is a change that happens to somebody else! 
Objection 1: Youre begging the question Williams when you say its happening to somebody 
else. On my view its happening to A! 
Response: If you think what happens to the B-bodied person in (vi) is happening to A, and so in 
(vi), A isnt being tortured, then you should also think that A isnt being tortured in (v). 
After all in both (v) and (vi) the person being torture d  the A-bodied person is exactly the same 
in all respects  character, history, apparent memory. So if you think its not A being tortured in 
(vi), you should think its not A being tortured in (v). 
Objection 2: Its unreasonable to insist that a sharp line be drawn somewhere. It might be indeterminate or ambiguous at which point the A-bodied person is no longer A. 
Response: This may be intellectually comforting but what is A who is anticipating all this 
supposed to make of the fact that in some versions of the case it will be indeterminate whether or not it is A being tortured? ! 
That it is conceptually undedicable whether it will be me or not, is something which, it seems, I can do nothing witih ;because, in particular, it seems to have no comprehensible representation 
in my expectations and the emotions that go with them (175). 
Analogy: Perhaps its like a case in which its indeterminate whether an object youre 
sentimentally attached to is destroyed? 
Response: Its not. To regard the prospect ive pain -sufferer just like the transmogrified object of 
sentiment, and to conceive of my ambivalent distress about his future pain as just like ambivalent 
distress about some future damage to such an object, is of course to leave him and me clearly distin ct from one another, and thus to displace the conceptual shadow from its proper place. I 
Williams, Bernard. The Self and the Future. Philosophical Review 79, no. 2 (1970): 16180.  Duke University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded 
from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>have to get nearer to him than that. But is there any nearer that I can get to him without 
expecting his pain? If there is, the analogy has not shown us it. We can certainly not get nearer by expecting as it were ambivalent pain; there is no place at all for that. There seems to be an 
obstinate bafflement to mirroring in my expectations a situation in which is conceptually undecidable whether I occur (177-178). 
Williams ends up saying he has no idea what option to choose if he were presented with the 
original case and that he finds this rather disturbing. 
One last consideration: If Parfit is right and we care about psychological connectedness or 
continuity, then even in cases in which we clearly dont survive, we should still prefer there to be 
beings who are more psychologically connected to us. 
But do we? Imagine a case in which youre killed, but prior to your death some of your 
memories get transplanted into another person. Does that make you feel even a bit better about 
dying? 
Williams, Bernard. The Self and the Future. Philosophical Review 79, no. 2 (1970): 16180.  Duke University Press. All rights reserved. This content is 
excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 5: The Euthyphro
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 5 
The Euthyphro 
1. Metaethics 
Metaethicists are interested in some variety of the following question: 
What does it mean to say that something is good or right? 
Theyre not looking for a moral theory (whats good is that which maximizes happiness)  unless 
you think all it means to be good, is, say, to maximize happiness. 
(In this case: the question why be good? would be a question that makes sense). 
Socrates is asking Euthyphro a metaethical question  he wants to know what goodness consists 
in, what it means for something to be good  not just some criteria for what is good. 
Euthyphros Answer: Divine Command Theory 
Whats good is that which is loved by God (/the gods). 
2. Socrates Argument 
(1) Suppose for reductio that good means: loved by God. 
(2) It is not because it is a loved thing that it is loved by those who love it  (Assumption) 
(3) God loves the good because its good. (Assumption) 
(4) God loves the good because its loved by God. (1,3) 
(5) Its not the case that God loves the good because its loved by God. (2) 
(6) God loves the good because its loved by God, and its not the case that God loves the 
good because its loved by God. (4,5) 
(7) Good does not mean loved by God (1- 6, reduction ad absurdum ). 
3. The Euthyphro Dilemma 
Sometimes this argument is put in the form of the dilemma. Suppose goodness is just being loved by God. We can now ask: 
Is whats good loved by God because its good or is it good because its loved by God? 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Horn (a) 
Whats good is loved by God because its good Problem: Bringing in God doesnt give us an understanding of what goodness is. Divine 
command theory doesnt answer the metaethical question. 
Horn (b) 
Whats good is good because its loved by God (Gods love makes it good) 
Problem: Then it seems we have no particular reason to care about the good and/or theres no 
substance to the claim that God is good. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 4: Is It Rational to Have Faith?
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Buchak proposes 
REU(A) = u(O2) + r(p(S))[u(O1)-u(O2)] 
r is a risk function. Example r(p) = p2 
If a risk function has a high value for a particular probability the possibility of improving over the 
minimum by that probability will count for a lot in the agents estimation, and if it has a low 
value then it will not count for much. An agent with a convex risk function is risk avoidant - in general risk avoidant agents aim to 
decrease the spread of possible value. 
3. The Value of Informatio n 
Its a theorem that the expected utility of performing an experiment with no cost is either positive 
or zero. In other words, it never hurts to gain more information before making a decision, and in many cases it helps. This isnt true if youre risk ave rse! 
Why? Gaining more information is, in a sense, a risky action. It could lead to a worse outcome 
than youd get otherwise if you get misleading information. For risk averse agents, the prospect 
of gaining non-misleading information may not outweigh the risk of getting misleading 
information. 
Say Anna doesnt wait for the verdict: 
Bates is innocent Bates is guilty 
Anna says yes 10 0 
Anna says no 1 1 
Suppose her risk function is r(p) =p2 
REU( Yes) = 0 + r(p(Innocent))(10-0) 
REU( No) = 1 
Suppose shes currently confident enough in Bates innocence that, despite being risk averse, it 
makes sense for her to marry him. (This will hold as long as shes more than ~34% confident) 
And suppose Anna thinks that theres a 90% chance there will be an innocent verdict and 10% 
chance there will be a guilty verdict. 
Supposing an innocent verdict, theres a 99% chance Bates is innocent, and a 1% chance he isnt. 
Supposing a guilty verdict, theres an 88% chance Bates is guilty and a 12% chance hes 
innocent. 
Given her risk aversion, a guilty verdict is enough to sway her not to marry Bates: 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>REU guilty verdict (Yes) = (.12)2(10) = .144 
REU guilty verdict (No) = 1 
(But she would still marry him if she were an EUT maximizer!) 
So does it make sense to wait? No! 
Bates is innocent, 
investigation finds 
him innocent 
p = .891 Bates is innocent, 
investigation finds 
him guilty 
p = .012 Bates is guilty, 
investigation 
finds him guilty 
p = .088 Bates is guilty and 
the investigation 
finds him innocent 
p = .009 
Say yes to 
Bates now 10 10 0 0 
Say no to 
Bates now 1 1 1 1 
Wait for the 
verdict and 
then decide 10 1 1 0 
REU (Decide now)= 0+0+.903(10)+ 0 = 9.03 
REU(Wait for the verdict) = 0+.9912(1)+ 0 + .892(9) = 8.11 
So should you have faith/avoid information/ignore information? If youre a risk-avoidant, 
pretty confident in the claim in question, and the risk of misleading evidence is sufficiently high, 
then yes. 
If you are risk avoidant, then you require a higher degree of belief t o take a risk; therefore, you 
are more easily talked out of taking a risk.  Consequently, if the negative evidence wouldnt be 
conclusive s o that backing out on bad information and backing out on good information are both 
possible, you are in particular danger of the former . (11) 
Faith keeps us from being blown about by the changing winds of evidence (14). 
Buchak, Laura. When is Faith Rational? In The Norton Introduction to Philosophy. 2nd ed. Edited by Gideon Rosen, Alex 
Byrne, Joshua Cohen, et al.  W. W. Norton &amp; Company. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 4 
Is it Rational to Have Faith? 
1. Buchaks Theory of Faith 
A proposition X is a candidate for faith for a person S if S care that X holds and is uncertain that X 
holds on the basis of evidence alone. 
S has faith that X if and only if 
(1) X is a candidate for faith for S 
(2) S is willing to take a risk on X without looking for additional evidence; and 
(3) S is willing to follow through on such risky actions even when he receives evidence against 
X. 
Examples: Faith that your friend will keep your secret, Moses faith that God would lead his people out of Egypt, Annas faith that Bates is innocent. 
When is it rational to have faith? 
Buchaks answer: when youre antecedently quite confident in the proposition in question, and 
when the evidence you might encounter against the proposition is sparse or unreliable. 
The intuitive idea: if youre risk averse, even weak evidence will sway you . In such circumstances 
the risk of misleading evidence may outweigh the benefit of non-misleading evidence. 2. Buchaks Theory of Risk Aversion 
Heads Tails 
Deal 1 (A) 0 utility points (utiles) 10 utility points 
Deal 2 (~A) 5 utility points 5 utility points 
EU(A) = (.5)(0) + .5(10) = 5 
EU(~A) = 5 
How do we rationalize a preference for Deal 2? Consider a case in which A yields O1, if S obtains, O2 if ~S obtains and where u(O2) &lt; u(O1) 
S ~S 
A O1 O2 
EU(A) = p(S)u (O1)+p(~S)u (O2) 
= u(O2) + p(S)[u(O1)-u(O2)] 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 11: Incompatibilism
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
Respon se: Causation is consistent with determinism. 
Objection 3: Conditionalists say that 
S could have done X 
means 
If S had chosen to do X, S would have done X. 
Response : What premise of the argument is the conditionalist going to deny? The crucial premise 
is premise (6). Suppose we substituted 
(6) J could not have rendered L false. 
with 
(6a) It is not the case that if J had chosen to render L false, J would have rendered L false. 
Van Inwagen says  (6a) still seems true, but lets suppose for the sake of the argument that (6a) is 
false: that if J had chosen to render L false, J would have rendered L false. 
This would show that (6) does not mean the same thing as (6a) since (6), van Inwagen argued, is 
true. 
So either the conditionalists analysis is true, but so is (6a) (since (6) is) and the argument goes 
through, or the conditionalists analysis is false.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
2.2 Defense of (5) 
If J could have rendered the conjunction of P 0 and L false, then J could have rendered L false. 
Why? Because P0 expresses some state of the world before Js birth, and so , van Inwagen thinks, 
J cant render P 0 false. This means that if he can render the conjunction false, that must be 
because he can render L false. 
2.3. Defense of (6) 
Van Inwagen argues that if somebody could render a proposition false, then that proposition is 
not a law of physics. Which means that if J could have rendered L false, then L is not a law of 
physics. But by stipulation L is a law of physics. 
Why think that if somebody could render a proposition false then that proposition is not a law of 
physics? 
Suppose the following are both true: 
(A) Nothing ever travels faster than light 
(B) Jones a physicist can construct a particle accelerator that would cause protons to travel at 
twice the speed of light. 
(It follows from (A) that Jones will never exercise such a power). van Inwagens two claims: (A) and (B) are consistent, but (B) entails that (A) is not a law of physics. 
surely it is a feature of any proposition that is a physical law that no one can conduct an 
experiment that would show it to be false. (193) 
*Humeanism vs non-Humeanism about laws 
3. Obje ctions 
Objection 1: In day to day life we have criteria for determining whether an agent could have acted 
otherwise. These criteria determine what it means to say that an agent could have acted 
otherwise. These criteria make no mention of determinism so if you think free will and determinism are incompatible youre confused. 
Response : Predestinarianism says (1) if an act is foreseen its not free (ii) all acts are foreseen by 
God. Clearly this view is incompatible with free will, but are ordinary criteria make no appeal to 
it. So the inference from ordinary criteria for free will make no appeal to X to X is 
compatible with free will is false. 
Objection 2: Quite the contrary - free will entails determinism! To say that someone acted freely 
require s that he acted. But to say that someone acted requires that the person caused the relevant 
phenomenon (e.g. hand rising to occur). If determinism is false then the hand -raising would be 
uncaused, in which case its not even an act to begin with. 
Van Inwagen, Peter. The Incompatibility of Free Will and Determinism. Philosophical Studies: An International Journal for Philosophy in the Analytic Tradition 27, no. 3 (1975): 
18599.  Springer. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 
Handout 11 
Incompatibilism 
1. Van Inwagens Argument 
Determinism (v.I, p.186): (a) For every instant of time there is a proposition that expresses the state 
of the world at that instant. (b) If A and B are any propositions that express the state of the world 
at some instants, then the conjunction of A with the laws of physics entails B. 
Law of physics  a law of nature that is not about the voluntary behavior of rational agents 
Free will  the power or ability of agents to act otherwise than they in fact do. 
Case: A judge J had the opportunity to raise his hand at time T to pardon somebody but he did 
not. 
L = the laws of physics P = a proposition that expresses the state of the world at T P
0 = a proposition that expresses the state of the world at a time before the judges birth, T 0 
From p.191: 
1. If determinism is true, then the conjunction of P 0 and L entails P. 
2. If J had raised his hand at T, then P would be false. 
3. If (2) is true then if J could have raised his hand at T, J could have rendered P false. 
4. If J could have rendered P false, and if the conjunction of P 0 and L entails P, then J could 
have rendered the conjunction of P 0 and L is false. 
5. If J could have rendered the conjunction of P 0 and L false, then J could have rendered L 
false. 
6. J could not have rendered L false. 
7. If determinism is true, J could not have raised his hand at T. 
2. Defending the Premises 
2.1. Defense of (4) 
Let  represent logical entailment. 
Suppose (P
0 and L) P 
It follows (by logic) that: 
(~P) ~(P 0 and L) 
So if you can make it the case that (~P)  that is, you can render P false  then arguably you can 
also make it the case that conjunction of P 0 and L false. 
Van Inwagen, Peter. The Incompatibility of Free Will and Determinism. Philosophical Studies: An International Journal for Philosophy in the Analytic Tradition  27, no. 3 
(1975):18599.  Springer. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 10: Panpsychism and Dual Aspect Monism
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 10 
Panpsychism/Dual Aspect Monism 
1. Two Hard Problems 
The Hard Problem of Consciousness  The hard problem of consciousness is another way of bringing 
out the challenge consciousness poses to physicalism. Its not unrelated to the knowledge 
argument, but it focuses on explanation . The thought is, no amount of science will be able to 
explain why particles moving around in such and such way will give rise, to say, red experience. 
The Hard Problem of Matter  What is physical matter in and of itself, beyond the structure 
described by physics? Like the hard problem of consciousness, the hard problem of matter seems like a problem science 
cant solve. 
2. The Hard Problem of Matter 
Traditional scientific methods tell us what matter does, not what matter is. It describes the 
software, rather than the hardware of the universe. Examples: 
 What is charge? A matter of repelling other matter with the same charge and 
attracting other matte r with different charge. 
 What is mass? A matter of responding to applied forces, gravitationally attracting other particles with mass, curving spacetime, interacting with the Higgs field 
But we might want to know what is it thats doing the attracting, curving the spacetime, interacting with the 
Higgs field? 
One proposal: structuralism  all there is is structure and relations. Theres no thing which is the 
thing that realizes it. But, the argument goes, there are lots of abstract mathematical structures. 
Presumably the particular structure describing our universe differs from the other abstract 
structures because its realized by some stuff. 
3. Can we Solve Both Problems at Once? 
The hard problem of matter calls for non- structural (qualitative) properties and consciousness is 
the one phenomenon we know that might provide us with some. We know what conscious properties  qualia  are like in and of themselves , not just how they relate 
to other stuff: when Mary sees red for the first time she isnt learning anything about how the 
property of looking red relates to other things  shes learning what its like. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>So heres the proposed solution: perhaps consciousness of some primitive or rudimentary form is 
the hardware that the software physics describes runs on. Maybe fundamental particles are 
mental beings  streams of experience in physical relation to other streams of experience. 
This is a proposed answer to the hard problem of matter. How does it purport to solve the hard 
problem of consciousness? If matter just is consciousness there is no question about how consciousness arises from matter. 
4. Dual aspect monism 
Monism  all of reality is made of the same kind of stuff. 
Dualism  reality is made of two types of stuff 
Dual aspect monism accepts that the brain is a purely material system, but says that it has an 
intrinsic nature which we can detect from the inside that cant be captured by any physical 
theory. It then proposes that we think of everything like this. All matter has an intrinsic mental 
nature. 
5. Objections 
Panpsychism  implausible that fundamental particles are conscious. 
Response  look at the alternatives! Combination problem  how does more complex consciousness arise out of simpler forms of 
consciousness? Looks similar to the original hard problem. 
Response  theyre working on it. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 8: The Knowledge Argument against Physicalism
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 8 
The Knowledge Argument against Physicalism 
1. Some Terminology 
Physicalism  all information is physical information 
(Another possible formulation: all facts are physical facts) 
Physical information -The information given by science (note: Jackson doesnt regard this as a 
definition, since its somewhat vague) 
A Qualia Freak  Someone who thinks that there are features of bodily sensations and perceptual 
experiences that no amount of physical information includes. 
These features are called  qualia : the hurtfulness of pain, the itchiniess of itches, how it feels to 
be jealous, taste a lemon, etc. 
2. The Knowledge Argument for Qualia 
Fred  Fred can make all the color discriminations we make plus more. Show him a batch of ripe 
tomatoes and hell sort them into two piles which he says are as different to him in terms of color 
appearance as yellow is from blue. He calls these calls red 1 and red 2. 
1. We can gain all the physical information about Fred that we like and we still wont know certain information about Fred: what kind of experience Fred has when he says red
1 and 
red 2. 
2. Not all information is physical information 
(This can be dramatized by imagining that Fred donates his body to science and they are able to transplant his optical system into somebody else. After the operation this person will know more 
about Fred than was known before). 
Mary  Mary is a brilliant scientist who has spent her whole life in a black and white room. She is 
an exper t on color vision and neurophysiology and knows all the physical information one could 
possibly know about color vision. But shes never seen color. One day she leaves the room and 
sees a ripe tomato. 
1. Prior to leaving the room Mary knows all the physical information there is to know about seeing red. 
2. Prior to leaving the room Mary doesnt know what its like to see red. 
3. Not all information is physical information. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>3. The Zombie Argument 
1. There is a possible world in which there are beings who are physical duplicates of us but 
they dont have any conscious experiences (they are zombies). 
2. Facts about our conscious experience are not physical facts about us. 
3. Not all facts are physical facts. 
Jackson thinks this argument is not as good as his because one might reject premise (1). 
4. Epiphenomenalism 
A problem for non-physicalism: plausibly, our conscious experiences cause various physical 
events (the pain causes me to say ouch, the thirst causes me to reach for the water). But we have 
good reason to think that the physical world is causally closed  all physical events that are caused at all are caused by and explained by other physical events. As a result many dualists (non-physicalists) are epiphenomenalists  they think th at conscious 
experiences dont have causal powers. Some people think this is absurd. Why? 
(1) Its just obvious that, say, pain causes pain behavior 
Response: All thats obvious is that pain is frequently followed by pain behavior. But thats 
consistent with both being effects of some underlying process. (Movie analogy). 
(2) The unpleasantness of pain is an evolutionary adaptation to bring about avoidance behavior. 
If the experience of pain is causally inefficacious then natural selection couldnt act upon it. 
Response: Jackson denies that the qualia associated with pain were naturally selected for. Polar bears were selected who had warm coats. Warm coats happened to be heavy. But the heaviness 
of the coat wasnt selected for. 
(3) The problem of other minds  we use peoples behavior to infer facts about their mental life. 
If their experiences werent causing their behavior this inference would be illegitimate. 
Response: A can be evidence for B even if B doesnt cause A. Readi ng in the newspaper that the 
Spurs won is evidence that the Spurs won, but the newspapers report didnt cause the Spurs to win. Rather both were brought about by a common cause. 
5. Jackson s Reflection s on Physicalism 
Jacks on think s physicalis m is an over ly optimisti c view of our cognitiv e powers . Insofa r as our 
mind s hav e evolve d to solv e ver y specifi c problems , why thin k we d end up wit h the abilit y to 
comprehen d everythin g ther e is to comprehen d abou t the universe? 
Sea slug analogy 
Conside r the anteceden t probabilit y tha t everythin g in the Univers e be of a kin d tha t is relevant 
in som e way or othe r the surviva l of hom o sapiens . It is very low surely . Bu t then one must admit 
that it is very like ly tha t there is a par t of the whol e schem e of things , mayb e a bi g part, whic h no 
amount of evolution will ever bring us near to knowledge about or understanding (135). 
Jackson, Frank. Epiphenomenal Qualia. Philosophical Quarterly 32, no. 127 (1982): 12736.  Oxford Academic. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our 
Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu / 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 3: The Problem of Evil
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 3 
The Problem of Evil 
The Problem of Evil as an Argument Against the Existence of God 
(1) There is evil. 
(2) If an omnipotent (=all powerful) benevolent (=all good) being existed there would be no 
evil. 
(3) An omnipotent benevolent being does not exist. 
Mackies Assumptions : 
Good is opposed to evil  a good thing always eliminates evil as far as it can, the more good a thing is the less evil it is and vice versa 
Proposed Solutions: 
Objection to Premise (1): There is no evil in the world 
Objections to Pr emise ( 2): If good and evil are in some intertwined , theres some sense in which 
you cant have one without the other . We shouldnt assume that an omnipotent benevolent being 
would prevent the existence of evil. 
(a) Evil is needed to bring about good, just as water is needed to bring about plant growth. 
Mackie: Then God is not omnipotent. 
(b) The idea of a world without evil is incoherent (Schlesinger) 
An omnipotent being isnt assumed to be able to do whats logically impossible. (c) Having some evil in the universe makes it better 
If goodness is opposed to evil (as in Mackies assumption), then how could something evil make 
the world more good? 
Mackie proposes understanding the proposal as follows: On the first level are: 
Evil1 = pain/misery 
Good1 = pleasure/happiness. 
Distinct from Good1 is Good2 which requires a combination of Evil1 and Good1: 
Version 1 
Good2 = sympathy with suffering, heroism in facing danger, gradual decrease of Evil1 and 
increase of Good 1 
Problem: Evil2 = Malevolence, cruelty, callousness, cowardice, states in which Good1 is 
decreasing Evil1 is increasing. 
Version 2 
Good2 = Free will 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Problem: We can have free will without Evil1. Presumably we can imagine a single individual 
who has the freedom to bring about evil but never does. So we can imagine that all people are such that they have the freedom to bring about evil but never do. 
Objection  if God set things up such it was impossible to act wrongly we wouldnt actually 
be free. 
Mackies Response 1: This requires thinking that free will requires some form of 
indeterminacy, or randomness. But whats good about that? Mackies Response 2: Free will of this sort is incompatible with omnipotence. 
Also: What about animal suffering or suffering that has nothing to do with free will? (d)Good without evil is a logical impossibility.
Analogy 1: There couldnt be something big in the universe without something small. 
Bigness is a relative term that only makes sense in comparison to smallness. 
Mackies Response: Relative greatness can be promoted only by a simultaneous 
promotion of relative smallness. I feel sure that no theists would be content to 
regard Gods goodness as analogous to this  as if what he supports were not the good but the better and as if he had the paradoxical aim that all things should be 
better than other things. [I dont understand this]. 
Analogy 2: There could be no redness in the world unless some things werent red . 
Something can only exist if its opposite exists. 
Mackies Response: False. Maybe if everything were red, we wouldnt notice 
redness, but it would still be true that everything is red. 
2
Mackie, J.L. Evil and Omnipotence. Mind 64, no. 254 (1955): 200212.  Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our 
Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 21: Haslanger on Race and Gender
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout21/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 21 
Haslanger on Race and Gender 
1. Haslangers Approach 
Three ways to figure out the meaning of X: 
Conceptual - What is our concept of X 
Method: reflective equilibrium (compare to the ideational strategy ) 
Descriptive - What natural kind if any does our usage of X track 
Method: Look at the world and see what actual phenomena or concept might be pointing 
to. (Physical, biological, social) (compare to referentialism) 
Analytical - What is the point of having a concept of X, what concept if any would do the work 
best? What cognitive or practical tasks does having the concept enable us to accomplish and 
what would best fulfill this role? 
Haslanger favors the analytical approach. The world by itself cant tell us what gender is, or 
what race is; it is up to us to decide what in the world, if anything, they are (34). 
The idea is not to describe what we actually we mean, but how might usefully revise what we mean for certain theoretical and practical purposes. 
So What Do We Want the Concept To Do? 
Haslanger will focus on: 
(i) The need to identify and explain persistent inequalities between males and females, 
and between people of different colors 
(ii) The need for a framework that will be sensitive to both the similarities and differences among males and females, and the differences among individuals in groups demarcated by color  including concern to account for intersectionality of race, class, gender 
3. Gender 
Slogan in some literature gender is the social meaning of sex .  Two problems with standard 
accounts 
The commonality problem  is there anything social that females all have in common? There is 
tremendous variation in the social role of females in different times, places and cultures. The normativity problem  Any definition of what it takes to be a woman will be value laden and will 
marginalize certain females, privilege others, and reinforce gender norms. 
Haslangers account (p.42): 
Haslanger, Sally. Gender and Race: (What) Are They? (What) Do We Want Them to Be? Nos 34, no. 1 (2000): 3155.  Wiley-Blackwell. All rights reserved. 
This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>S is a woman if and only if: 
i) S is regularly and for the most part observed or imagined to have certain bodily 
features presumed to be evidence of a females biological role in reproduction; 
ii) That S has these features marks S within the dominant ideology of Ss society as someone who ought to occupy certain kinds of social position that are in fact subordinate (and so motivates and justifies Ss occupying such a position); and 
iii) The fact that S satisfies (i) and (ii) plays a role in Ss systematic subordination, i.e. along 
some dimension Ss social position is oppressive, and Ss satisfying (i) and (ii) plays a role 
in that dimension of subordination. 
S is a man if and only if 
i) S is regularly and for the most part observed or imagined to have certain bodily features presumed to be evidence of a males biological role in reproduction; 
ii) That S has these fea tures marks S within the dominant ideology of Ss society as 
someone who ought to occupy certain kinds of social position that are in fact privileged (and so motivates and justifies Ss occupying such a position); and 
iii) The fact that S satisfies (i) and (ii) plays a role in Ss systematic privilege, i.e. along some 
dimension , Ss social position is privileged and Ss satisfying (i) and (ii) plays a role in 
that dimension of privilege. 
Clarifications regarding Subordination and Oppression 
Subordination and privilege are part of the structure of oppression. Oppression is understood as 
a structural phenomenon that positions certain groups as advantaged or disadvantaged relative to 
others. Some representative quotes (Haslanger 39-40): 
Frye: an enclosing structure of forces and barriers which tends to the immobilization and 
reduction of a group or category of people. Young: Oppression refers to the vast and deep injustices some groups suffer as a consequence of 
often unconscious assumptions and reactions of well-meaning people in ordinary interactions, media and cultural stereotypes, and structural features of bureaucratic hierarchies and market 
mechanisms 
Example: Taxi company 
The importance of along some dimension  Black male example. In the US there are contexts 
in which being a perceived male is not something that that a Black man has going for him 
(systematic targeting by police), but there are also contexts in which Black males benefit from being male. 
4. Race 
* No racial genes responsible for the morphological and cultural patterns we associate with 
different races 
Haslanger, Sally. Gender and Race: (What) Are They? (What) Do We Want Them to Be? Nos 34, no. 1 (2000): 3155.  Wiley-Blackwell. All rights reserved. 
This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Gender 
In theory Haslangers account opens the door to the possibility of constructing non-hierarchical 
genders on the basis of non-hierarchical differences in social positioning between people marked as male and people marked as female. 
Haslanger doubts that sex will ever completely cease to have social meaning because the 
differences in what human bodies contribute to reproduction, which bodies bear the main 
physical burden of reproduction, etc are socially significant facts. 
Race 
Its less clear whether there is reason for color to have social meaning after the revolution. 
Though Haslanger proposes that perhaps we can use e thnicity  to talk about something like 
race but that doesnt presuppose systematic subordination or privilege. 
Another Objection : Trans -identities 
Katheri ne Jenkins: Gender as class versus gender as identity. But how to use the word 
woman? Jenkins proposes that at least at this point in time, woman should be used to refer 
to a gender identity since refusing to do is a way of reinforcing transphobic ideology. 
Haslanger, Sally. Gender and Race: (What) Are They? (What) Do We Want Them to Be? Nos 34, no. 1 (2000): 3155.  Wiley-Blackwell. All rights reserved. 
This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>* In different contexts racial distinctions are drawn on the basis of different characteristics 
(Brazilian and US classification schemes for who counts as Black differ , at different times 
Italians, Germans, Irish and Jews have been racialized in the US) 
These considerations support the idea that race could be understood as a position within a social 
network. 
Definition (p.44): A group is racialized if and only if its members are socially positioned as 
subordinate or privileged along some dimension (economic, political, legal, social, etc.), and the 
group is marked as a target for this treatment by observed or imagined bodily features presumed to be evidence of ancestral links to a certain geographical region. 
5. Back to the Normativity and Commonality Objections 
Commonality  is there social that all e.g. women can be said to have in common? Haslanger says: 
nothing like individual beliefs, values, psychological traits, etc. But what women have in 
common is a particular type of social position. 
Objection: some women are not oppressed as women. Response: There could be females who arent women in Haslangers sense. But thats okay. The 
analysis is meant to capture an important political category for critical feminist efforts and non-
oppressed females do not fall within that category. 
(it is part of the project of feminism to bring about a day where are no more women) 
(46). 
Normativity  defining genders or races will inevitably privilege certain e.g women and marginalize 
others. Haslanger says: it is inevitable and important to choose factors for understanding races and genders which are significant for the purposes for which the definition is meant to be used. 
Certain people may not count as real women but Haslangers thought is that this is not incompatible with the feminist and anti-racist values her account is meant to be in suppor t of. 
6. Negotiating Terms 
Haslanger acknowledges that she is appropriating everday terminology for specific theoretical and political purposes and that this could potentially be problematic. 
These analyses might not fit peoples self-understandings of whats involved in being a certain 
race or gender. In particular, Haslanger is suggesting that we reject what have seemed to us to 
be positive social identities. 
Im asking us to understand ourselves and those around us as deeply molded by injustice and to 
draw the appropriate prescriptive inference. This, I hope, will contribute to empowering critical 
social agents (48). 
This raises the question: Can there be non -hierarchical genders and races? Will there be genders 
and races after the revolution? 
Haslanger, Sally. Gender and Race: (What) Are They? (What) Do We Want Them to Be? Nos 34, no. 1 (2000): 3155.  Wiley-Blackwell. All rights reserved. 
This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 13:  Moral Responsibility
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 13 
Mor
al Responsibility 
1.Versions of the Argument
(a)The Basic Argument (Strawson, p.5)
1.Nothing can be the cause of itself (causa sui)
2.In order to be truly morally responsible for ones actions one would have to be the cause
of oneself  at least in certain crucial mental respects
3.Nothing can be truly morally responsible
(b)Elaborated (adapted a bit, from p.6):
1.When one act s for a reason what does is a function of how one is, mentally speaking.
2.So if one is to be truly responsible for how one acts, one must be truly responsible for how
one is, mentally speaking  at least in certain respects.
3.To be truly responsible for how one is, mentally speaking, in certain respects, one must
have brought it about that one is the way one is, mentally s peaking, in certain respects.
4.But one cannot really be said to choose the way one is mentally speaking, in any respectat all, unless one is already equipped with some principles of choice, P1  preferences,
values, pro-attitudes, ideals  in the light of which one chooses how to be.
5.But then to be truly responsible on account of having chosen to be the way one is, onemust be truly responsible for having P1 in the light of which one chose how to be.
6.But for this to be so one must have chosen P1.
7.But for this to be so one must have had some principles of choice P2 in the light of which
one chose P1.
8.True self-determination is impossible because it requires the actual completion of an
infinite series of choices of principles of choice.
9.True moral responsibility requires true self-determination.
(c)A More Natural Version (adapted a bit from p.7)
1.One is the way one is, initially, as a result of heredity and early experience, and these arethings for which one cannot be held to be responsible.
2.One cannot at any later stage of life hope accede to true moral responsibility for the wayone is by trying to change the way one already is as a result of heredity and previousexperience.
Why? Because the particular way in which one is moved to try to change oneself and the degree of ones success in ones attempt at change will be determined by 
how one already is as a result of heredity and previous experience, and any further 
changes that one can bring about only after one has brought about certain initial changes wi ll be determined, via the initial changes, by heredity and previous 
experience. Maybe some changes are traceable to indeterministic or random factors, but one definitely is not responsible for this! 
3.At no stage can there be true moral responsibility for the way one is.
Strawson, Galen. The Impossibility of Moral Responsibility. Philosophical Studies: An International Journal for Philosophy in the Analytic Tradition  75, no. 1/2 (1994): 
524.  Springer. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3. Objections and Responses 
Objection 1  Compatibilism 
Compatibilists think you can be a morally responsible agent just in virtue of your actions being 
caused in a certain way  for example by your desires, when they coincide with your higher order 
desires. They reject (2) in the last argument. 
Response: The kind of responsibility compatibilists give us is not true moral responsibility. 
Compatibilists have given various accou nts of when punishment is fitting but they cant, says 
Strawson, reasonably think its truly and ultimately just to punish, if the causes of action are not 
things we are responsible for. 
Objection 2  Libertarianism 
Libertarians are incompatibilists who believe determinism is false, and so we do have free will and are morally responsible. 
Response: Denying determinism doesnt help. Youre no more responsible for truly random 
events going on in your brain than for determined events going on in your br ain. 
p.19: In the end, whatever we do, we do it either as a result of random influences for which we 
are not responsible, or as a result of non-random influences for which we are not responsible, or as a result of influences for which we are proximally responsible, but not ultimately responsible. 
Objection 3  There is a self beyond the motivation system 
The idea is that you self is independent of your personality or motivational structure  your CPM. Your self, S, considers the deliverances of CPM and makes a decision in light of them, but independent of them. 
Response: S decides on the basis of the CPM, but whatever S decides it decides because of the 
way S is. 
Strawson, Galen. The Impossibility of Moral Responsibility. Philosophical Studies: An International Journal for Philosophy in the Analytic Tradition 75, no. 1/2 (1994): 524.  Springer. 
All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>4. At no stage can one be truly morally responsible for their actions. 
(d) Yet another version! (adapted a bit from p.13) 
1. You do what you do because of the way you are. 
2. To be truly morally responsible for what you do you must be truly responsible for the way 
you are  at least in certain crucial mental respects. 
3. You cannot be truly responsible for the way you are. 
4. You cannot be truly responsible for what you do. 
Defense of (3): 
To be truly responsible for the way you are, you must have intentionally brought it about that 
you are the way you are in a way that makes you responsible for how you are. But this is 
impossible. 
Why? 
(a) For you to have intentionally brought about the way you are, you must already have had 
a certain nature N in the light of which you intentionally brought it about that you are as 
you are now. 
(b) For it to be true that you are truly responsible for how you are, you must be truly 
responsible having had the nature N in the light of which you intentionally brought it 
about that you are the way you. 
(c) To have intentionally brought it about that you had that nature N in a way which makes you responsible for it, you must have existed already with a prior nature N, in the light of 
which you intentionally brought it about that you had the Nature N in the light of you 
intentionally brought it about that you are the way you now are 
Regress! 
2. Why Does It Matter? 
Belief in absolute moral responsibility has been central to Western religious moral and cultural 
tradition. 
It implies that there is a fundamental sense in which no punishment or reward is ever ultimately 
just. Its no more just to punish somebody for their actions than for their hair color. 
Its relevant to our self- understanding  we have a feeling we have that we are fully morally 
responsible for what we do (cake versus Oxfam tin) and how we are that Strawson thinks come 
about just because we have self-conscious awareness of ourselves as agents who deliberate about 
what to do. 
Strawson, Galen. The Impossibility of Moral Responsibility. Philosophical Studies: An International Journal for Philosophy in the Analytic Tradition 75, no. 1/2 (1994): 5 
24.  Springer. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 6: Mackie's Moral Skepticism
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 6 
Mackies Moral Skepticism 
1. What Kind of Claim is Moral Skepticism? 
Contrast the following two questions: 
(1) What are we expressing when we make moral claims? 
(2) Are there objective moral values? 
Some subjectivist-y answers to (1) 
 Relativism - Saying murder is wrong is the equivalent of saying something like I 
believe murder is wrong, or Murder is incompatible with such and such moral standards. 
o Analogy: Saying A is to the left of B is the equivalent of saying something like 
relative to my perspective A is to the left of B 
 Expressivism - Saying murder is wrong is a way of expressing certain feelings we have 
about murder. Its the equivalent of saying something like Boo murdering! 
Mackie denies these views. 
Problems with relativism : moral disagreement 
Problems with expressivism : 
Mackies worry about expressivism: It is a very natural reaction to any non-cognitive analysis of ethical terms to protest that there is more to ethics than this, something more external to the 
maker of moral judgments, more authoritative over both him and those of or to whom he speaks Also: Frege -geach problem/The embedding problem  How do we explain whats mean when 
moral sentences are embedded in more complex sentences? 
Examples: I wonder whether lying is wrong, I think lying is wrong but I might be mistaken, James will lie about such matters, unless doing so would be wrong in which case he wont, lying is not wrong, etc 
This turns out to be quite difficult. 
Instead, Mackie answers (1) as following: When we express moral claims we are asserting that there are certain objective facts about rightness and wrongness, goodness and badness, that hold. His answer to (2) is that all such claims are false. This is a ra dical view and Mackie acknowledges that a good argument is therefore required. He 
endeavors to provide some. 
2. The Argument from Disagreement 
1. There is a great deal of moral disagreement. 
2. The best explanation for the existence of moral disagreement is that there are no 
objective moral facts. 
3. We have good reason to believe that there are no objective moral facts. (1,2). 
Mackie, J.L. The Subjectivity of Values. In Ethics: Inventing Right and Wrong. Penguin Books, 1991.  Penguin Books. All rights reserved. This 
content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Defense of (2) 
Of course there is a great deal of disagreement on a host of matters that we think there are facts about: scientific matters, cosmological matters, historical matters 
But such scientific disagreement results from speculative inferences or explanatory hypotheses based on inadequate evidence, and it is hardly plausible to interpret moral disagreement in the same way. Disagreement about moral codes seems to reflect peoples 
adherence to and participation in different ways of life. The causal connection seems to be mainly that way round: it is that people approve of monogamy because they 
participate in a monogamous way of life rather than that they participate in a 
monogamous way of life because they approve of monogamy. (74) 
the actual variations in the moral codes are more readily explained by the hypothesis 
that they reflect ways of life than by the hypothesis that they express perceptions, most of 
them seriously inadequate and badly distorted of objective values (75). 
Is the argument for (2) relying on something like this? If disagreement is explained by variation in ways of 
life, then the best explanation for the disagreement is that there are no facts of the matter? Why think this? 
3. The Argument from Queerness 
1. If there were objective values then they would entities or qualities or relations of a very 
strange sort, utterly different from anything in the universe (76). 
2. In general, we should avoid positing entities or qualities or relations of a very strange sort, utterly different from anything in the universe. 
3. We should avoid positing objective values. (1,2) 
Defense of (1): 
 Metaphyiscal Weirdness : If things were objectively good or right theyd somehow have to 
have to -be-pursuedness built into them. Thats odd. (Also - Hume argues that no fact 
alone can be intrinsically motivating, the person has to have some desire in order for motivation to take hold) 
 Epistemological Weirdness : How could we possibly come to know about these 
entities/qualities or relations? 
 Supervenience : What is the connection between the fact that doing X would cause, say, 
inordinate pain, and the fact that X is wrong. It doesnt follow logically, or from the meaning of any words, but its also not a coincidence. Its wrong because it causes pain  
but what kind of because is this? More generally: plausibly, the moral facts supervene on the naturalistic facts, but how and why? 
o Definition: A facts supervene on B facts if there can be no change in the A facts without a change in the B facts. (Facts about molecules supervene on facts about atoms: no change in molecule facts without a change in atom facts). 
Potential objection to (2): companions in guilt  essence, number, identity, solidity, inertia, 
substance, necessity and possibility, causation, power, infinite extension of time and space 
Mackie, J.L. The Subjectivity of Values. In Ethics: Inventing Right and Wrong . Penguin Books, 1991. Penguin Books. All rights reserved. This content is 
excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/ . 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu / 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 2: The Argument from Design
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 2 
The Argument from Design 
Cosmologists tell us that our universe is fine-tuned for life   for life to even have a shot of evolving 
certain extremely stringent conditions have to be met. Had the values of the physical constants 
been even slightly different our universe would not have life in it. 
The Fine Tuning Argument (as explicated by Roger White) 
1. If a fact E that we observe stands in need of explanation, hypothesis H provides a satisfactory explanation of E and one that is better than any alternative explanation 
available, then E provides significant evidential support for H. 
2. That our universe is hospitable to life stands in need of explanation. 
3. That God adjusted the constants in order to allow for life to develop provides a satisfacto ry explanation for why our universe is life- permitting. 
4. There is no comparably satisfying explanation of this fact available. 
5. Therefore that our universe is life-permitting provides significant evidential support for theism. (from (1)-(4)) 
Premise (1): Inference to the Best Explanation is a general principle defended by epistemologists 
and philosophers of science. Both in day to day life, and in science, it seems like we come to believe things because they provide the best explanation of the evidence 
Premise (2): Not every improbable event stands in need of explanation. Contrast: a string of 
scrabble letters that spell gibberish versus a string of scrabble letters that spell a line from Hamlet. 
-As a matter of fact cosmic fine tuning strikes many scientists and philosophers as 
calling out for explanation. 
-Perhaps its the fact that life seems valuable, or interesting that makes a universe hospitable for life call out for explanation. 
Objection to Premise (2) : Its not surprising that the universe is fin e-tuned for life because if it 
werent, we wouldnt observe that it werent. 
Whites Response: It was not inevitable that we would observe the constants to be fine-tuned. What was inevitable was just that if we were to observe the constants at all , we would 
find them to be fine-tuned for life. 
Premise (3) : We frequently appeal to the actions of rational agents in explanation. Objections? 
Premise (4): White considers the following objection 
Objection to Premise (4) : The multiverse provides a comparably satisfying explanation of fine- tuning. 
Whites Response: The multiverse theory explains why some universe is fine -tuned for life, 
but not why ours is. It would be odd, therefore, to conclude that the multiverse exists on the basis of fine tunin g evidence. 
However, if there is independent evidence for the existence of the multiverse, then White thinks this could undermine Premise (2). Asking why our universe is fine -tuned for life 
might be asking why Smith won the lottery. 
White, Roger. The Argument from Cosmological Fine-Tuning.  Roger White. All rights reserved. This content 
is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Conclusion : The conclusion follows from (1)-(4). 
Premise (2) says that the fact E (our universe is fine-tuned for life) stands in need of explanation. 
Premise (3) says hypothesis H (God adjusted the constants to allow for the development of life) 
provides a satisfactory explanation of E. 
Premise (4) says that there is no better explanation available. Premise (1) says that when a fact E stands in need of explanation, hypothesis H explains E, and 
there is no better explanation available, then E provides significant evidential support for H. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu / 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 7: Nagel on Ethics
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 7 
Nagel on Ethics 
Nagel is first and foremost proposing a methodology for deciding the metaethical question. We 
need to do first order moral theorizing and see how it goes. 
Here are what he takes to be some relevant considerations: 
(1) Our practice of engaging in practical reason requires that we able to ask, in an objective 
sense, what should I do? So giving up on objectivity is a gigantic cost of a theory. 
We cannot evade our freedom. Once we have developed the capacity to 
recognize our own desires and motives, we are faced with the choice of whether to act as they incline us to act, and in facing that choice we are inevitably faced with an evaluative question (118). 
The opposition here is between a theory about how things are and a practice 
that would be impossible if this was how things were (116-117). 
(2) Thinking about abstract metaphysics is not the way to decide the matter: The claim to 
objectivity does not depend on the existence of a universe of moral facts that impinge on 
us causally. (Compare to mathematics). We take there to be objective facts about some 
subject matter when we have uncontroversial and well-developed methods for answering questions about the subject matter that have a good claim to be reliable. So the wa y 
forward is to do some first order moral theorizing and see how it goes: 
Only the effort to reason about morality can show us whether it is possible  whether in thinking about what to do and how to live, we can find methods, reasons and principles whose validity does not have to be subjectively or relativistically qualified (102). 
(3) Ultimately, claims about lack of objectivity are going to have to compete with first order moral claims  claims like the oppression of women is wrong. 
The claim that, at the most objective level, the question of what we should do 
becomes meaningless has to compete head- to-head with specific claims what what 
in fact we should do and their ground. (115). 
Nagel, Thomas. Ethics. In The Last Word. Oxford University Press, 2001. Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our 
Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu / 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 19: Scheffler's The Afterlife
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>(b) Projects whose value derives largely from the benefits it will provide to large numbers of 
people over a long period of time. 
Examples: trying to find a cure for cancer (ultimate success may be a long way off + it seems less important if everybody will be dead in the not too distant future anyway), social and political activism, environmental activism, scientific researc h, 
What about: creative and scholarly work, having children, certain aspects of raising and caring 
for children? 
In sum: there are many projects and activities whose importance to us is not diminished by the 
prospect of our own death, but is diminished by the prospect of the earths destruction shortly 
thereafter. 
3. Reaction to DS Reveals An Impulse to Personalize  our Relation to the Future 
The premature death of people we love and care about strikes us a bad thing. 
But Scheffler thinks theres more to our dismay about the scenario than this. He notes that most 
people regard it as a bad thing if everyone they care about dies before they do. But why? 
Not just concerns about loneliness 
Scheffler thinks there is something that seems positive to us about the fact that our own death 
with involve certain relational disruptions  it personalizes ones relation to the future. The 
world after ones death becomes more like a party you had to leave early than a gathering of 
strangers. 
One reason the doomsday scenario seems bad, says Scheffler  is that we are not part of the future 
after our death. 
Our concern for conservation and our concern for peronsalizing our relation to the future, 
Scheffler thinks, can also be supported by the value we place in participating in traditions : This 
is a way of preserving what is valued beyond an individual life span or generation, and also allows us to think of ourselves as custodians of these values for the future. 
4. The Infertility Scenario and Some Upshots 
P.D. Jamess The Children of Men infertility scenario  people become disinterested in things, 
even things meant to deliver immediate gratification (food, sex, art, enjoyment of nature) the world 
becomes full of lassitude, depression, ill-defined malaise, readiness to give way to minor infections, a perpetual disabling headache (James, p.9, quoted in Scheffler, p.41). 
The Afterlife conjecture  In doomsday scenario worlds people would cease to value, engage in, 
and be emotionally attached to many activities and pursuits. 
Consequence: Were not as egoistic as we think  we value our lives and activit ies in a way that 
relies on thinking of them as embedded in something larger than ourselves. 
Scheffler, Samuel. Lecture I: The Afterlife (Part I). In Death and the Afterlife. Oxford University Press, 2016.  Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. This 
content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 19 
Schefflers The Afterlife 
The afterlife  the goings on of living beings (and particularly humans after we die 
Doomsday Scenario  imagine that the earth will be completely destroyed thirty days after your 
death in a collision with an asteroid. 
Schefflers project is to reflect on what humans in fact value by considering our reactions to the 
scenario 
Note 1: For Scheffler valuing is more than having a belief in something being valuable. 
It is a complex attitude with doxastic, motivational, emotional and deliberative components. 
Note 2: In describing our attitudes Scheffler means to be describing his attitudes a nd 
those of whoever else shares them. 
1. Reaction to DS Highlight s Certain General Features of Human Valuing 
Point 1: We wont react with so what? It wont happen until after I die . Why should I care? 
This suggests: a nonexperientialist interpretation of our values -things other than our own 
experiences matter to us. Point 2: We would react with profound dismay even prior to determin ing whether the event on 
balance is a good or bad thing. 
This suggests: there is a nonconsequentialist dimension to what matters to us. If our values were 
purely consequential, then whether we regard the Doomsday scenario positively or negatively 
would require a detailed calculation of the consequences of the scenario. But we react negatively 
without doing the sums. So our reaction reflects a nonconsequetialist feature of our values. 
Point 3: The fact that our reaction is one of profound dismay, Scheffler thinks, is best explained 
by the idea that the phenomenon of human value is conservative in the se nse that we want the 
things we value to be sustained and preserved over time. 
2. Reaction to DS Shows that Much of We Value Depend s on the Afterlife 
How would the doomsday scenario affect our motivations to engage in various projects? 
 Our reasons to engage in certain projects might seem less strong 
 Our emotional investment might weaken 
 Our belief that they are worthwhile activities might weaken 
Vulnerable projects: 
(a) Projects whose ultimate success is something that may not be achieved until some time in 
the distant future 
Scheffler, Samuel. Lecture I: The Afterlife (Part I). In Death and the Afterlife. Oxford University Press, 2016.  Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. This 
content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 22: Charles Mills-White Ignorance
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 22 
Charles Mills - White Ignorance 
Mills argues that there is a particular form of active ignorance he terms white ignorance. White 
ignorance is a kind of ignorance connected to the subordination of people of color, and in which 
(the social construct of) race plays a causal role. There is shared ignorance among white people 
about people of color and about the reality of race and racial relations (in the U.S. and elsewhere). 
I 
Individual and Social Epistemology: The tradition of Anglo-American epistemology is individualistic and abstracts away from the ways 
in which a knower might be embedded in the social world - in race, class, gender, etc. Influential 
20th century epistemologists (Quine, Kornblith, and Goldman) challenged individualistic epistemology by proposing a naturalized and therefore socialized epistemology which 1. Focuses on 
the social paths to knowledge, and 2. Isn
t restricted to believers taken singly.  
A veritistic  epistemology is one which asks which practices have a comparatively favorable impact 
on knowledge as contrasted with error and ignorance?An individual veritistic epistemology asks 
this question for nonsocial practices; a social veritistic epistemology asks this question for social practices (16). Feminist and critical race theorists have incorporated gender and race into socialized 
epistemology. 
Ignorance: 
False belief and the absence of true belief. Social epistemologists who want to understand 
ignorance look at how social groups get knowledge wrong - at the social mechanisms behind the 
spread of misinformation
 and the distribution of (possibly massive) error within the larger social 
cluster, and at the sometimes pernicious social practices that encourage such widespread error.  Mills claims that there is a certain form of pervasive ignorance about race spread throughout the 
larger social cluster of white people. Mills intends the term white ignorance to imply that there is 
a possibility of a contrasting knowledge, and asks what are the social mechanisms which produce 
and encourage white ignorance. 
II 
There is (or was) minimal philosophical literature on racial epistemology. But - Mills claims that white ignorance has been a theme of many of the classic fictional and nonfictional works on the 
African American experience and the experiences of many other people of color: 
 Ralph Ellisons Invisible Man: an epistemological novel, asking questions about how we 
demarcate false insight from real insight, apparent truth from real truth: For what it recounts is 
the protagonists quest to determine what norms of belief are the right ones in a crazy looking-
glass world where he is an invisible man simply because white people refuse to see methey 
see only my surroundings, themselves, or figments of their imagination - indeed, anything and 
everything except me due to the construction of their inner eyes (18). 
 Herman Melville
s Benito Cereno: Amasa Delanos interpretation of the scene aboard the ship -
that the whites were in control of the black slaves, as was proper - persisted despite what we 
Mills, Charles W. White Ignorance. Chapter 1 in Race and Epistemologies of Ignorance. Edited by by Shannon Sullivan and Nancy Tuana. 1 
State University of New York Press, 2007.  State University of New York Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>might regard as overwhelming evidence to the contrary. This is a self regulation by racist 
assumptions and blind innocence (19). 
 James Baldwin - I have spent most of my life, after all, watching white people and outwitting 
them so that I might survive (18). 
 Du Bois on the veil (that which stands between POC and white people, such that while people 
cant properly see POC) and 
double consciousness (the black self-conscious recognition of white 
ignorance, a sense of always looking at oneself through the eyes of others) (19). 
These examples describe an asymmetry between typical white views of blacks and typical black views of whites; colored people of this country know and understand the white people better than 
the white people know and understand them. Mills aim in the rest of the chapter is to gesture 
toward some useful directions for mapping
 this kind of white ignorance, and for developing 
epistemic criteria for minimizing it (20).  
III 
What I want to pin down, then, is the idea of an ignorance, a non-knowing that is not contingent 
but in which race - white racism and/or white racial domination and their ramifications - plays a crucial causal role (20): 
1. White ignorance is an historicized concept: Mills accepts social construction about race 
(denies that race is biological). Thus, white ignorance is a phenomena existing in certain time 
periods and cultures. 
2. White ignorance is to be 
distinguished from general patterns of ignorance prevalent among 
people who are white but in whose doxastic states race has played no determining role (e.g., 
widespread ignorance among white people (and everyone else) about the exact temperature of 
the earth
s crust or precise income distribution in the U.S.). 
3. Sometimes it will be difficult to adjudicate whether certain ignorance should be understood as 
white ignorance (i.e., whether race has played a causal role in such ignorance). 
4. White ignorance can be caused by racist motivation and/or by impersonal social structures which operate regardless of a cognizer being racist - e.g., while a cognizer might express 
white ignorance in their explicitly racist beliefs (e.g., that blacks are inferior), a non-racist 
cognizer might also express white ignorance about a subject matter (e.g., black peoples access 
to opportunities after abolition) because there has been social suppr
ession of the relevant 
knowledge. 
5. White ignorance isnt necessarily confined to white people - black people can also manifest 
white ignorance - i.e., have false beliefs about black people and the reality of race - due to the fact that white ideology is pervasive and (almost) hegemonic. 
6. White racial ignorance can produce a doxastic environment in which particular varieties of 
black racial ignorance can flourish, but we might hesitate to call this white ignorance (e.g., 
beliefs that white people are blue eyed devils). 
7. White ignorance
 includes ignorance about factual matters and, Mills argues, about moral 
matters - white ignorance can involve incorrect judgements about the rights and wrongs of 
situations. Mills claims that improvements in our cognitive practice should have a practical 
Mills, Charles W. White Ignorance. Chapter 1 in Race and Epistemologies of Ignorance. Edited by by Shannon Sullivan and Nancy Tuana. State 2 
University of New York Press, 2007.  State University of New York Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative 
Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>written, what is memorialized in museums, statues, national holidays, songs, what is covered by the 
press, etc. 
 How slavery is written about in textbooks and popular media (the magnolia myth) 
 Erasure of Jim Crow 
 Persons and communities massacred in colonization (Native Americans and the Indian-white 
wars, Indigenous Australians) 
 The Great For
getting of the Belgian Congo. 
Mills claims that how collective memory is managed is a part of collective identity and self-
representation: there will be an intimate relationship between white identity, white memory
, and 
white amnesia, especially about nonwhite victims (e.g., colorblindness, the myth of the meritocratic U.S.). 
Testimony 
Its now widely accepted in philosophy that much of what we know relies on taking the testimony 
of others seriously. But, when one entire group is cast as epistemically suspect - untrustworthy or unintelligent - then their input won
t be solicited or will be treated with suspicion. This can result in 
a closed circuit of epistemic authority that reproduces white delusions (34). 
 Marginalization of African American scholars and journals 
 Fear in speaking out about lynchings or race riots 
 Contemporary examples? Testimony about police violence, racism on college campuses, etc. 
Social Group Interest Phenomena like self-deception and the connection between individual interest and individual 
cognition are widely recognized in philosophy. Mills extends this to a social context informed by the realities of race
 and of domination and exploitation. As a group, whites have interest in the 
racial status quo, and this encourages cognitive distortions of various kinds. 
 Race is the primary social division in the U.S., and sociological data indicates that whites generally see black interests as opposed to their own. This will af
fect white social cognition - the 
concepts favored and used, the refusal to see racial discrimination, amnesia about the past, and hostility to black testimony. 
So - racialized perception, conception, memory, testimony, and social group interests are all 
interlocked and determine one another, jointly contributing to the blindness of the white eye
 and 
producing collective modes of denial (35). 
White ignorance has been able to flourish all of these years because a white epistemology of 
ignorance has safeguarded it against the dangers of an illuminating blackness or r
edness, 
protecting those who for racial reasons have needed not to know. Only by starting to break these rules and meta-rules can we begin the long process that will lead to the eventual overcoming of this white darkness and the achievement of an enlightenment that is genuinely multiracial (35). 
Mills, Charles W. White Ignorance. Chapter 1 in Race and Epistemologies of Ignorance. Edited by by Shannon Sullivan and Nancy Tuana. State 
University of New York Press, 2007.  State University of New York Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>payoff in heightened sensitivity to social oppression and the attempt to reduce and ultimately 
eliminate that oppression (22). 
8. White ignorance is not the only kind of privileged group-based ignorance - e.g., male ignorance 
(accepting that gender is a social construct). 
9. Speaking generally about white ignorance doesnt commit one to the claim that it is uniform 
across the white population. People have individual histories and are socially situated in a 
variety of ways - this can help destabilize white ignorance, and some white people work to 
overcome and undo the white ignorance they have socially inherited. 
10. White ignorance isnt just a sociological concept - it is a normative one. Mills takes it that we should be trying to reduce white ignorance - there are typical ways of going wrong that need to 
be adverted to in light of the social structure and specific group characteristics, and one has a 
better chance of getting things right through a self-conscious recognition of their existence and 
correspondingly self-distancing from them (23). 
IV 
What are the individual and social mechanisms though which white ignorance operates? How does race affect individual and social processes of cognition? Mills looks at 5, complexly interrelated, processes of cognition and how race can affect them.  
Perception and Conception 
Perception is never raw but is always mediated by concepts, including social concepts. Many of 
these concepts are not neutral but are oriented toward a certain understanding, embedded in sub-
theories and larger theories about how things work
 (27). White perception can be mediated by 
racist concepts or concepts/ideologies of white superiority/ white normativity. When these concepts/ ideologies are socially entrenched, it is very difficult for any individual cognizer to not perceive 
through 
 them. 
 White normativity: Historically whiteness has been coextensive with full humanity, people of color viewed as less than fully human or as savages. This is why it didn
t seem contradictory to 
claim that lands teeming with people were uninhabited, or for the declaration of independence to enshrine equality between all men while declaring Native Americans as savages. The concept 
of white normativity drove perception with whites being aprioristically intent on denying what 
was before them (27). In these cases, certain concepts blocked accurate vision and caused/ 
produced white ignorance. 
 Color-blindness: The transition away from old-fashioned racism has not put an end to white normativity but has subtly transformed its characterif previously whites were color demarcated 
as biologically and/or culturally superior, now through a strategic color
-blindness they are 
assimilated as putative equals to the status and situation of nonwhites on terms that negate the 
need for measures to repair the inequalities of the pastwhites refuse to recognize the long 
history of structural discrimination that has left whites with the differential resources they have 
today, and all of its consequent advantages in negotiating opportunity structures (28). 
Memory 
There is collective memory and collective amnesia. The way such memory is managed affects what 
individual cognizers are able to know and widespread patterns of ignorance - how textbooks are 
3 
Mills, Charles W. White Ignorance. Chapter 1 in Race and Epistemologies of Ignorance. Edited by by Shannon Sullivan and Nancy Tuana. State 
University of New York Press, 2007.  State University of New York Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 15: Parfit on Personal Identity
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Parfit thinks its less absurd to regard fusion as death (=not surviving) than to regard fission as 
death, since some aspects of your psychology will indeed cease to exist. But he still thinks that 
enough can be maintained that it seems implausible to regard it as death  especially if a suitable 
fusion partner is selected for you. 
5. Refining the Psychological Continuity Account 
Recall that we defined memory continuous as the ancestral of memory connected. 
Similarly, well define psychologically continuous as the ancestral of psychologically 
connected ( A is psychologically connected to B if and only if A and B share sufficiently similar 
psychologies, and Bs psychology depends on As in the right sort of way). 
Note that connectedness is intransitive, but continuity is transitive. 
Parfit thinks that connectedness is more important for survival than continuity. 
Either way though: both connectedness and continuity come in degrees which means that survival, 
the thing that matters according to Parfit, comes in degrees as well. 
How much connectedness or continuity is required to count some being as a past self of ours 
might vary in different contexts  its up to us what criteria we set, but it will be somewhat arbitrary. 
6. The Upshots 
(a) Self Interest 
A principle some have found plausible: Act in your own self- interest  (the interest of your future 
self) A way to motivate the principle: Act in accordance with what you want + most people want 
whats in their own self- interest. Parfit doesnt object (here) to that. But the self- inter est principle 
is stronger that whats motivated by this thought. It says you should act in your own self interest 
whether you want to or not. 
So now imagine somebody that doesnt care particularly about the interest of his future self. 
Once we accept th e idea that what counts as a persons future self is essentially arbitrary  its 
hard to motivate the claim that this person has special reason to care about his own interest more 
than others. (b) Fear of Aging and Death 
Whether in -the-distant future you actually is you is again, for Parfit, not a deep question. Its 
just a matter of how we decide to use personal identity language. So theres no real reason to 
fear your own distant death any more than you would somebod y elses. 
Parfit and Humes hope: more of what is bad depends on false belief. 
Parfit, Derek. Personal Identity. Philosophical Review 80, no. 1 (1971): 327.  Duke University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our 
Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Parfit considers the rejection of P1. Why cant we imagine a single person with 2 bodies? 
Certain surgical procedures result in split- brain  in which there are two separate spheres of 
consciousness each of which controls half of the patients body. But it seems much less plausible to think of there being one person with two bodies if the mind is divided permanently and each half develops in its own ways, creates its own memories, etc. 
What to do? 
Parfit s favorite approach : There is no answer . Second to favorite: Answer (3) 
But the crucial point for Parfit is that the identity question doesnt matter. Whether you are the 
same person as one or both fission products or not, whats important for survival is the relation that 
exists between you and the fission products, not any questions about identity. 
Terminological note : Survival does not entail identity 
Survival is being essentially used as code for what matters when we talk about survival. 
(Another option in a similar spirit: Claim that you dont survive in fission cases, but thats fine 
because survival is not what matters.) 
3. What Matters for Survival ? 
If identity is not what matters, what does matter? 
Roughly psychological continuity. Parfit thinks that when we take judgments of personal identity to be of great importance, thats 
really because in the cases were considering, identity implies psychological continuity. 
Parfit proposes that we think of identity as non-branching psychological continuity. 
X and Y are the same person if they are psychologically continuous and there is no person who 
is contemporary with either and psychologically continuous with the other. 
What does psychological continuity consist in? Continuity with respect to things like quasi -
memory, beliefs, desires, personality traits and so forth. 
[Parfit defines q -remembering an experience as: 
(1) I have a belief about a past experience which seems in itself like a memory belief (2) someone 
did have such an experience and (3) my belief is dependent up on this exper ience in the same 
way (whatever that is ) in which a memory of an experience is dependent upon it. (15).] 
4. Fusion 
In fusion cases two people come together. While they are unconscious their bodies grow into 
one. One person wakes up. 
q-memories can be maintained but some things will be lost. They cant be both optimists and 
pessimists, they cant both intend to go shopping and intend to not go shopping etc 
Parfit, Derek. Personal Identity. Philosophical Review 80, no. 1 (1971): 327.  Duke University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our 
Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 15 
Parfit on Personal Identity 
1. Parfits Goals 
Parfit wants to argue against two claims: 
(a) Questions of personal identity of the form Is X the same person as Y must always have 
an answer. 
(b) Unless we can answer personal identity questions in some particular case, we cannot 
answer several other important questions (survival, responsibility etc.) 
Parfit is then going to argue that his picture has some important upshots: it makes less sense to 
have a self-interested theory of morality, and it also makes less sense to be depressed about aging and death. 
2. Fission 
Some cases: 
Brain Transplant 1 : Your brain is transplanted into a new body. The new body has the same 
character and apparent memories. 
Brain Transplant 2 : Half of your brain is damaged, as well as your body. The healthy half gets 
transplanted into a new body that has the same character and apparent memories. 
Fission : Your brain is divided and each half is transplanted into a new body  both resulting 
people have the same character and apparent memories. (Or: teletransportation) 
Three options for how to think about fission cases: 
(1) I survive as one of the two people 
(2) I do not survive 
(3) I survive as both people. 
Argument against (1): No grounds for supposing it to be one rather than the other 
Argument against (2): 
P1: In Brain Transplant 1, you survive. 
P2: In Brain Transplant 2, you survive 
Why? P1+ people have in fact survived with half their brains destroyed. So its plausible 
that you survive in Brain Transplant 2 as well. 
P3: The only difference between Brain Transplant 2 and Fission is that in Fission there is more you-
ish stuff around. 
P4: More you-ish stuff around cant take you from survival to non-survival. C: In Fission you survive. (P2-P4) 
Argument against (3): P1: The two fission products, A and B are two distinct people. 
P2: Identity is a transitive relation. C: A and B are not both identical to C, the original person (P1, P2) 
Parfit, Derek. Personal Identity. Philosophical Review 80, no. 1 (1971): 327.  Duke University Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our 
Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 9: Responding to the Knowledge Argument
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout9/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 9 
Responding to the Knowledge Argument 
1. Churchlands Reconstruction of the Knowledge Argument (p.331) 
(1) Mary knows everything there is to know about brain states and their properties. 
(2) It is not the case that Mary knows everything there is to know about sensations and their 
properties. 
(3) Sensations and their properties are not brain states and their properties 
2. First Response: The Intentional Fallacy 
The first worry that Churchland raises is that the argument might be committing whats called the intentional fallacy and so invalid. Consider: 
(4) Lois Lane knows that Superman can fly 
(5) Lois Lane doesnt know that Clark Kent can fly. 
(6) Clark Kent isnt Superman. (4,5) 
This fallacious argument is appealing to whats sometimes called like Leibnizs L aw 
a is identical to b if and only if a and b have every property in common. 
But its commonly thought that, because of examples like this, Leibnizs Law doesnt hold when 
the properties in question are properties like is known to be or is believed to be 
But we can construct an example more analogous to the knowledge argument? 
(7) Jones knows everything there is to know about Hitler. 
(8) Its not the case that Jones knows everything there is to know about Adolf Shicklgruber. 
(9) Hitler is not Adolf Shicklgruber. (7,8) 
You might think though that in any spelled out version of the case (5) will be false. If Jones really 
does know everything about Hitler, then hell know, for example, that Hitlers name was Adolf 
Shicklgruber. So its not completely clear that theres an analogue to the knowledge argument 
in which the intentional fallacy is committed. 
Its also worth thinking about whether the argument, as Jackson described it, really does rely on 
Leibnizs Law . 
2. A Second Response: Modes of Knowing 
The second worry is also based on the idea that the argument is invalid, this time because of an 
equivocation (the same word being used in two different ways) on knows. 
Sense 1: Knowledge that involves manipulation of concepts 
Sense 2: A prelinguistic apprehension that involves innate dispositions to make certain 
discriminations. 
Churchland, Patricia Smith. Are Mental States Irreducible to Neurobiological States? Chapter 8 in Neurophilosophy: Toward a Unified Science of the Mind-Brain. MIT Press, 
1986.  MIT Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>So the thought is that (1) is true because Mary knows in sense 1 everything there is to know about 
brain states and their properties. She doesnt know in sense 2 everything there is to know about 
brain states and their properties. 
(2) is true because Mary doesnt know in sense 2 everything there is to know about sensations and 
their properties, but she does know in sense 1 everything these to know about sensations and their 
properties. The idea is that there is no single sense of know which makes both premises true. 
[A related thought: Some people think that Mary has all the knowledge that about brain states 
and sensations while in the black- and-white -room. What she lacks is knowledge how  for 
example, the knowledge of how to sort ripe and unripe tomatoes using vision alone.] 
3. A Third Response: Reject Premise (2) 
Heres a way to test whether Mary would know what its like to see red. 
The Test: Present her with a f irst red object when she leaves the black- and-white room and ask 
her to tell you what color it is on the basis of vision alone. 
Churchland claims that shell be able to answer correctly upon learning the complete 
neuroscience is an empirical question whic h we wont be able to answer for sure until we know what 
the complete neuroscience says. utopian neuroscience will probably look as much like existing neuroscience as modern physics 
looks like Arisotelian physics (332). 
Churchland says that Mary might be able to produce red in her imagination if she knows the 
complete science. She tries to give us a feel for how this could be. 
perhaps she could, by introspective use of her utopian neuroscience, tell that she has, say, a 
gamma state in her O patterns, which knows from her utopian neuroscience is identical to having a red sensation. Thus she might recognize redness on this basis (333) 
What is introspective use of neuroscience? 
All one need imagine is that Mary internalizes the theory in the way an engineer has 
internalized Newtonian physics, and she routinely makes introspective judgments about her own 
states using its concepts and principles. Like the engineer who does not have to make an effort but sees the world in a Newtonian matter, we may consider that Mary sees her internal world via the utopian neuroscience (333). 
Some questions to think about: 
i. Do you think Jackson would accept The Test as a way to determine whether she 
knows what red looks like? 
ii. In general, is whether you can know A on the basis of learning B an empirical 
question? 
Churchland, Patricia Smith. Are Mental States Irreducible to Neurobiological States? Chapter 8 in Neurophilosophy: Toward a Unified Science of the Mind-Brain. MIT Press, 
1986.  MIT Press. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu / 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 14: Locke on Personal Identity
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>or 
there is a chain of persons C1, C2, C3Cn that exist at times t&lt; t 1t n-1&lt;tn&lt;t, 
such that 
 A is memory connected to C1, and 
 For all i, C i is memory connected to C i+1, and 
 Cn is memory connected to B. 
A is B iff at t1 A is memory continuous with B at t 2. 
5. Should The Criterion Only Focus on Memory ? 
Locke argued that personal identity is a concept we use it to guide our practice of blaming and 
punishing : only blame and punish a person for crimes he/she committed . 
And, says Locke, we should only blame and punish people for crimes they remember 
perpetrating. 
But is Locke right about this? And isnt Locke is overlooking other important maxims? 
Absent some exchange, attribute property to a person only if he/she is the previous 
owner. Anticipate pleasure and suffering only if it will be yours. Fear death only if you will not be around in the future. 
The Amended Broader Version of the Psychological Criterion of Persistence for People Say that As mental state at t
1 is psychologically connected to Bs mental state at t 2 iff Bs mental state 
at t 2 has many desires, beliefs, memories in common with As mental state at t 1, and As mental 
state at t 1 causes Bs mental state at t 2 to be as it is. 
Let psychological continuity be the ancestral of the psychological connectedness relation. 
A is B iff As mental state at t 1 is psychologically continuous with Bs mental state at 
t2. 
6. Some other Theories of Personal Identity Over Time 
The Soul Criterion 
A is B iff thesoul A has at t 1is the soul B has at t 2 
The Bodily Criterion 
A is B iff the body A has at t 1is the body B has at t 2 
The Brain Criterion 
A is B iff the brain A has at t 1 is the brain B has at t 2 
Lockes objections to the bodily criterion: the prince and the cobbler, Socrates and the mayor of 
Queensborough. Similar objections might apply to the soul and brain criterion. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 14 
Locke on Personal Identity1 
1. Three Uses of Terms Like Identity 
1. To refer to a self-conception . E.g: My fascination with philosophy threatens my identity as an 
experimental scientist. 
2. To refer to the relation that holds between things that share many intrinsic properties. E.g: 
These two paper clips are identical. We may call this qualitative identity . 
3. To refer to the relation that holds between each thing and itself, and nothing else. We may call 
this strict identity . 
Questions about strict identity typically come up when you know that there is one thing with 
features F, and that there is one thing with features F*, and you ask: Is the thing with features F the thing with features F*? 
Examples: Is the youngest person in this room the tallest person in this room? 
Is the third perfect number the 28? 
2. Strict Identity Over Time 
Were going to be interested in strict identity but across time . 
Questions about strict identity across time come up when you know that there is one thing with 
features F at time t
1, and that there is one thing with features F* at a later time t 2, and you ask: 
Is the thing with features F at t 1 the thing with features F* at t 2? 
Examples: Is the shirt youre wearing the one I gave you for your birthday? 
Is the person I saw at the coffee shop this morning the same as the person I sat next to on 
the airplane yesterday? 
We care a great deal about questions of the identity of persons over time: 
Is the person I am pointing at now a person who will be given a million dollars tomorrow? 
Is the person I am pointing at now going to be suffering from a horrible illness next year? 
Is the person I am pointing at now one of the people who will be alive tomorrow? Is the person on trial today the person who committed the murder three months ago? 
3. Lockes Criterion of Persistence Over Time 
For Masses 
Whenever A is mass that exists at one time, t
1, and B is a mass that exists at a later time, t 2 
A is B iff every part of A at t 1 is a part of B at t 2, and vice -versa 
1 Parts of this handout are taken from a handout made by Professor Caspar Hare . 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lockes Criterion of Persistence Over Time for Organisms (Vegetables, Animals, Man) 
Whenever A is an organism that exists at on e time, t1, and B is an organism that exists at a later 
time, t2 
A is B iff A and B partake in the same life, though that life be communicated to new particles of matter vitally united to the living [organism] 
In other words: there is a kind of organizational continuity that exists between an organism at 
different times which is what makes it a single organism. 
(Compare: a club, 24.00) 
Lockes Criterion of Persistence Over Time for People 
Whenever A is person who exists at one time, t
1, and B is a person who exists at a later time, t 2 
A is B iff at t2, B remembers As actions and experiences at t1. 
(Note: in what follows theories of personal identity over time will assume that A is a person who 
exists at t 1 and B is a thing that exi sts at a later time, t 2). 
4. Objections to Lock e from Reid and some Modifications 
Objection 1: He Mistakes Testimony for the thing Testified 
According to Locke, my remembering doing something makes it the case that I did it. But isnt 
that objectionably circular? Isnt it part of the concept of remembering that I only remember the 
things I did? 
Modification to Avoid Reids First Objection 
Say that I quasi-remember doing something when I am in a mental state that is intrinsically just like 
the one I would be in if I remembered doing it. 
A is B iff at t2, B quasi -remembers As actions and experiences at t 1. 
Objection 2: Locke is Saying that Strict Identity is Intransitive 
Say that a relation is transitive when, for all things x,y,z, if x bears the relation to y, and y bears the 
relation to z, then x bears the relation to z. 
Strict identity is a transitive relation. But, when lives are long and memory is short (e.g. the boy, 
young officer, general), remembering is intransitive. The general remembers being the young officer, the young officer remembers being the boy, but the general does not remember being the boy. So Locke cannot be giving a criterion of strict identity. 
Modification to Avoid Reids Second Objection 
Say that As mental stat e at t
1 is memory connected to Bs mental state at t 2 iff at t 2, B quasi -
remembers being A at t1 
Say that A at t is memory continuous with B at t  (the ancestral of the forward memory connected 
relation) iff either 
A at t is memory connected to B at t , 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 18: Wolf on Meaning of Life
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The Answer : A subject whose life lacks meaning has a life that is not in accord with or responsive 
to certain important facts. 
Wolf thinks recognition of our place in the universe, our insignificance, involves recognition of 
the mereness of our subjective point of view. In the face of such a recognition a life devoted to the subjects own fulfillment or survival seems soplisistic or silly.To live such a life expresses a kind 
of commitment that ones happiness is all that matters, but that seems very implausible. 
Compare: Nagel argues that if you fail to see the pain of others as a reason, you are acting 
as if others pain is not real . Such a person is making an error. 
Similarly, devoting oneself wholly to ones own satisfaction is to act in a way that is not in accordance with the truth that ones own satisfaction doesnt matter all that much. 
Objection : Our s peckness warrants the conclusion that there is no meaning to life, and that each 
individual life is necessarily absurd. So seeking meaning in life is not the appropriate response to our cosmic insignificance. 
Response : Living in a way that is significan tly focused on, engaged with, and concerned to 
promote or realize value whose source comes from outside of oneself, does seem to harmonize 
with [the fact of our insignificance and the of the mereness of our subjectivity], whereas living purely egocentrically does not. Living lives that attain or realize some nonsubjective value may not make us meaningful, much less important, to anyone other than ourselves, but will give us 
something to say, to think, in response to the recognition of perspectives that we ourselves 
imaginatively adopt that are indifferent to our existence and to our well-being (14) 
Wolfs Moral : There can be meaningful lives even if there is no overall meaning to life. 
To Think About: Does our own satisfaction matter at least a bit ? If so, isnt the question a matter of 
how much our own satisfaction compares to other, arguably, specky-projects? Why doesnt 
devotion to non-self-oriented specky-projects express a commitment to these other specky- things 
being all that matters? 
Wolf, Susan. The Meaning of Lives.  Susan Wolf. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see 
https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 18 
Wolf on the Meaning of Life 
1. What is the What is the Meaning of Life? Question? 
* What does a life represent or symbolize? 
Lives are not parts of languages or symbolic systems 
* What is the purpose of human existence why are we here? with the hope that the answer 
will inform what we should do with our lives 
The standard secular response is: there is no purpose. If we werent designed by a God 
with some intention, the idea that were here for some reason is implausible. Were j ust 
the output of some physical processes. 
* How can one find meaning in a life? 
Wolf thinks meaningfulness is an intelligible feature to be sought after in a life. 
2. What Makes for Meaning if Life? 
A Hypothesis Wolf Rejects : Experiences that we fin d subjectively rewarding, emotionally 
satisfying, experience s that feels meaningful/ha ve importance/meaning/significance to the 
subject. 
Wolf rejects this view. She thinks we can judge other peoples lives as meaningful or not 
and that our judgments are not determined by whether we think those people had 
emotionally satisfying experiences. 
The strategy: Consider candidates for meaningless lives , and see what these lives are missing: 
The Blob - person spends day after day in front of a TV, watching sitcoms and drinking beer. Life 
lived in hazy passivity 
Useless 
-the idle rich hopping from one amusement to another 
-The corporate executive working all the time, experiencing great stress for the sole 
purpose of accumulation of wealth 
-The pig farmer who buys more land to grow more corn to feed more pigs to buy more 
land to grow more corn to feed more pigs 
Bankrupt 
-Devoting ones life to create and build up a company to hand over to ones children but the item the company manufactures is rendered obsolete by new technology shortly before retirement 
-Scientist whose life work is rendered useless by the announcement of a breakthrough weeks before her research would have yielded the same result 
-Devotion to a relationship that turns out to be a fraud 
Wolf, Susan. The Meaning of Lives.  Susan Wolf. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see 
https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The c ontrast: 
Active engagement (unlike Blob) in a project that has positive value (unlike Useless) and which is 
to some extent successful (unlike Bankrupt). 
A meaningful life is one that is actively and at least somewhat successfully engaged in a project (or projects) of 
positive value (5). 
3. Clarifications 
Projects  the word is used in a broad sense to encompass not only goal-directed tasks but other 
sorts of ongoing activities and involvements as well. Active  activity is not enough for active engagement. The alienated housewifes life may be full of 
activity but her heart isnt it. Shes just going through the motions. 
Positive value  Wolf leaves this intentionally unspecific so that the account is ecumenical to a 
broad range of views of positive value. But she wants to rule out a view on which it suffices for 
positive value that the project seem to have positive value from the subjects perspective. This 
would blur what she takes to be the important distinction between living a meaningful li fe and 
living a life that seems meaningful. 
One role for this distinction: explaining the sorts of epiphanies one experiences when one suddenly recognizes that ones life to date has not been meaningful. The yearning for meaningfulness will not be satisfied by putting the scales back on 
Lastly : positive value  moral value (consider athletes and artists) 
4. Should We Care About Having a Meaningful Life? 
Fact: a lot of people want meaning in their lives. But we dont just think its fine for people to like meaning, in the way its for people to like 
country music. We think people ought to pursue lives that are meaningful. 
But this is a bit mysterious. 
Question: What is so good about living a meaningful life and who exactly is it good for? 
 Not necessarily morally better  so not better for the world 
 Not necessarily happier  Blobs hazy passivity may feel better than the experience of a 
tortured artist. So its not obviously better for the subject. 
So what kind of ought is used in the claim that one ought to care about meaning in ones life, or live a meaningful life, or want a meaningful life? 
Wolf thinks the ought involved is closest to the prudential ought  it is bad for the subject to have a 
life thats not meaningful  even if s he has no desires that meaningfulness would satisfy. If 
meaninglessness wont make her unhappy, what about a lack of meaning is bad for subject? 
Wolf, Susan. The Meaning of Lives.  Susan Wolf. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see 
https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 17: Dennett-Where Am I?
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 17 
Dennett  Where am I ? 
The case: Dennets brain is put in a vat so he can go explore some radioactive substance 
underground in Tulsa Oklahoma. When he awakes from the surgery h e names the brain 
Yorick and the body Hamlet and himself Dennett. Where is Dennett? 
Different views: 
(1) Where Hamlet goes there goes Dennett. Problem  Body swapping 
(2) Where Yorick goes there goes Dennett. Problem  Dennett is thinking Obviously Im 
not inside a vat right now. 
Further support: He imagines robbing a bank in California (the vat is kept in Texas). Several questions arise 
 Whose jurisdiction would he be under? CA or TX? 
 Would CA put Hamlet in prison and leave Yorick happily in his vat in Texas? Or would TX put Yorick in some dark dungeon? Den nett 
notices hes prefer the latter. 
 Could the Houston people provide an alibi by claiming he was in Texas during the bank robbery? 
(3) Dennett is wherever he thinks he is  At any given time a person has a point of view and the location of the point of view is the location of the person. Problem  sometimes we are ignorant about where are. Imagine we are lost in the woods, or believe we are in some other country, etc. Response: in such cases we are still sure that we are in our own 
body. 
 Butnot obviously in Dennetts current situation. Does this view 
entail that Dennett is in some indeterminate location? 
 Someone in a Cinerama who is under the illusion that hes on a roller coaster and forgets momentarily that hes seated in a theatre. 
 Workers who operate mechanical arms undergo a shift in point of view 
(4) Dennett exists in two places  just like you can stand with one foot in Rhode Island and one foot in Connecticut. Problem: Hamlet goes to Tulsa Oklahoma for his underground expedition. Then gradually he gets disconnected. First he cant hear, then he cant speak, then he cant see, then he becomes paralyzed untilDennett experiences himself 
as disembodied and fully believes himself to be in Houston. 
 Did he move faster than the speed of light (when the last radio signal 
died)? Does this show that hes not a material object? 
o Compare to: a treaty being signed changing the location of a country. Does this show that countries arent physical objects? In a sense yes, in a sense no. But do we think of ourselves as in some sense abstract objects, like we might think of a country? 
The story continues: 
Dennett, Daniel C. Where Am I? Chapter 6 in Science Fiction and Philosophy: From Time Travel to Superintelligence . 2nd ed. Edited by Susan Schneider. Wiley-Blackwell, 2016. 
 Wiley-Blackwell. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Dennett is put to sleep for about a year while they work on getting him a new body. When 
Dennett wakes up with his new body (Fortinbras) he goes to visit Yorick in the vat and just for 
fun turns the switch to off but nothing happens! 
It seems that before they had even operated on the first occasion they had constructed a computer duplicate of my brain, reproducing both the complete information-processing structure and the computational speed of my brain in a giant computer program. After the operation, but before they had dared to send me off on my mission to Oklahoma they 
had run this computer system and Yorick side by side. The incoming signals from 
Hamlet were sent simultaneously to Yoricks transceivers and to the computers array of inputs. And the outputs from Yorick were not only beamed back to Hamlet, my body; they were recorded and checked against the simultaneous output of the computer program which was called Hubert for reasons obscure to me. Over days and even 
weeks, the outputs were identical and synchronousHuberts input, and hence activity, 
had been kept parallel with Yoricks during my disembodied days. (6) 
Before waking Dennett up they hooked Hubert (rather than Yorick) to Fortinbras. 
Dennett now has the option of switching the control of his body back to Yorick from Hubert. He tries it out and nothing happens. He flicks the switch back and forth and noti ces no difference 
whatsoever. He realizes it doesnt matter which one hes hooked up to. He settles on Yorick. 
He gets set up with a device that controls connections to both brains, and he is the only person 
that has access to these connections. (Dennett requests this in part to make sure that the other 
brain doesnt get hooked up to a separate body and create a bunch of havoc in his financial and social affairs, in addition to puzzlement about which one he is). Theres a switch on the device which a llows him to switch between brains from time to time just for kicks, but the switch is 
unmarked so he never knows which he is. 
At a certain point Dennett is giving a lecture and flips the switch as a demonstration. Heres 
what emerges: 
THANK GOD! I THOUGHT YOUD NEVER FLIP THAT SWITCH! You cant imagine how horrible its been these last two weeks  but now you know; its your turn in 
purgatory. How Ive longed for this moment! You see, about two weeks ago  excuse 
me, ladies and gentlemen, but Ive got to explaini to myum, brother, I guess you could 
say, but hes just told you the facs, so youll understand  about two weeks ago our two brains drifted just a bit out of synchand of course once the process started, it snowballed, for I was in a silightly deifferent receptive state for the input we both 
received, a difference that was soon magnified. In no time at all the illusion that I was in 
control of my body  our body  was completely dissipated. There was nothing I could do  no way to call you. YOU DIDNT EVEN KNOW I EXISTED! Its been like being carried around in a cage, or better, like being possessed  hearing my own voice say things I didnt mean to say, watching in frustration as m yown hands performed deeds I 
hadnt intended. Youd scratch our itches, but not the way I would have, and you kept 
me awake, with your tossing and turning. Ive been totally exhausted, on the verge of a nervous breakdown, carried around helpleslly by your frantic round of activities (8). 
Dennett, Daniel C. Where Am I? Chapter 6 in Science Fiction and Philosophy: From Time Travel to Superintelligence . 2nd ed. Edited by Susan Schneider. Wiley-Blackwell, 
2016.  Wiley-Blackwell. All rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>          24.00F19 Lecture Handout 12: Compatibilism
        </lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/24-00-problems-of-philosophy-fall-2019/resources/mit24_00f19_lecturehandout12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Handout 12 
Compatibilism 
1. First and Second Order Desires and the Will 
A wants to X doesnt have much content apart from context because it is consistent with (p.7): 
(a) The prospect of doing X elicits no sensation or emotional response in A 
(b) A believes he does not want to do X 
(c) A believes that he does not want to X 
(d) A wants to refrain from X- ing 
(e) A wants to do Y and believes it is impossible to do both X and Y 
(f) A does not really want to do X 
(g) A would rather die than X 
So you cant predict much about what a person will do just from knowing they want X. 
Frankfurt thinks we should distinguish between: 
First order desire to X  X refers to an action 
Second order desire to X  X refers to a first order desire 
The will  the desire or desires which motivate the agent in some action, or those by which the 
agent will or would be motivated (The will is identical with one or more first order desires  it is an effective desire ). 
2. Second Order Desires 
Two kinds of situation in which A has a second order desire: 
(1) A has the desire to desire to X, but also the desire to refrain from X- ing  the desire they 
want to have is a desire they want to be unsatisfied. Example: a doctor wants to understand what its like to strongly desire an addictive substance. He forms th e desire to 
have that desire (perhaps temporarily) but he doesnt want such a desire to be satisfied. 
He doesnt want the desire to take the drug to be his will 
(2) A has the desire to desire to X, and he wants the desire to X to be effective. This entails 
that A already has the desire to X. Example: I want to want to concentrate on my work. 
This kind of 2
nd order desire is called a second order volition 
Frankfurt thinks that 2nd order volitions are essential to personhood. Wantons have 2nd order 
desires but no 2nd order volitions. Wantons do not care about their will. Their desires move 
them to do things but they neither want to be moved by those desires nor prefer to be moved by 
others. A wanton is not concerned with the desirability of his desires . 
Example: unwilling addict  has 2 conflicting first order desires  the desire to take the drug and the desire not to take it, but it is the desire not to take the drug that she desires to be her will. 
Wanton addict  also has conflicting first order desires, but no preference between them. 
Frankfurt, Harry G. Freedom of the Will and the Concept of a Person. Journal of Philosophy 68, no. 1 (1971): 520.  The Journal of Philosophy, Inc. All rights 
reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>3. Free Will 
Frankfurt thinks that 2nd order volitions are the key to free will. 
On one view: an agent acts freely if she does what she wants to do. But Frankfurt thinks, even if 
theres something right about this as an account of what it is to act freely, it doesnt capture the 
idea that the will is free. The freedom to act as one wants to act isnt sufficient for free will. 
If freedom of action is roughly the freedom to do what one wants , then free dom of will is roughly the 
freedom to will what one wants . This means that with respect to any first order desires, the person is 
free to make that desire her will, or to make some other desire her will instead. 
Free will is exercised when an agent bring s her will into conformity with her second order 
volitions. 
Consequence: The unwilling addicts will is not free. Whichever way the unwilling addict 
acts, she acts according to her desires . But her will is not what she wants it to be. 
 There can be conflicts among 2nd order desires. If the someone fails to identify himself 
with any of his conflicting first order desires then he is not a person. 
 There can be 3rd order desires, etc. Still, when a person identifies herself decisively with 
one of the first order desires that identification resounds through all the levels that there are. 
 Someone who is free to do what he wants to do and to will what he wants to will has all the freedom it is possible to desire or conceive. All the freedom we could want is 
compatible with determinism. 
4. Frankfurt on Moral Responsibility 
Frankfurt denies any straightforward connection between free will and moral responsibility. 
Being morally responsible, Frankfurt thinks, doesnt entail that you could have had whatever will 
you wanted to have. 
o Example: the willing addict  the willing addict wants to be an addict. In this case, we can imagine, his will is not free because the desire for the drug would be 
effective even if he didnt want that desire to constitute his will. But when he takes 
the drug, he takes it freely . Furthermore, even though his will is outside of his 
control by his second order desire that his desire for the drug should be effective 
he has made his will his own. (20). 
Question: what about the unwilling addict? Frankfurts view opens the 
possibility for an account of moral responsibility according to which an 
agent is morally responsible when she acts freely and her first order desires 
conforms to her higher order desires  in other words she has made her 
will her own. 
Frankfurt (in other work) also denies the claim that a 
person is morally responsible for what she 
does do only if she can do otherwise. 
Frankfurt, Harry G. Freedom of the Will and the Concept of a Person. Journal of Philosophy 68, no. 1 (1971): 520.  The Journal of Philosophy, Inc. All 
rights reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu/ 
24.00 Problems of Philosophy 
Fall 2019 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>From the Stanford Encylopedia of Philosophy: 
Here is a close approximation to the example Frankfurt presented in his original paper: 
Jones has resolved to shoot Smith. Black has learned of Jones's plan and wants Jones to shoot 
Smith. But Black would prefer that Jones shoot Smith on his own. However, concerned that 
Jones might waver in his resolve to shoot Smith, Black secretly arranges things so that, if 
Jones should show any sign at all that he will not shoot Smith (something Black has the 
resources to detect), Black will be able to manipulate Jones in such a way that Jones will shoot 
Smith. As things transpire, Jones follows through with his plans and shoots Smith for his own reasons. No one else in any way threatened or coerced Jones, offered Jones a bribe, or even 
suggested that he shoot Smith. Jones shot Smith under his own steam. Black never 
intervened. 
In this example, Jones shot Smith on his own, and did so unencumbered  did so freely. 
But, given Black's presence in the scenario, Jones could not have done otherwise than shoot 
Smith. 
So in response to van Inwagen, its possible to agree that: If determinism is true, the agent could 
not have acted otherwise while still claiming that: 
(a) The agent acted freely ( in the sense that she did what she wanted to do) 
(b) The agent acted of her own will ( in the sense that the will by which the agent was moved 
was the will she wanted to have , first and second order desires coincide). 
(c) The agent is morally responsible (perhaps because of (a) and (b)). 
McKenna, Michael, and D. Justin Coates. Compatibilism. In Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy. 2019.  Michael McKenna and D. Justin Coates. All rights 
reserved. This content is excluded from our Creative Commons license. For more information, see https://ocw.mit.edu/help/faq-fair-use/. 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
