<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-472-public-economics-ii-spring-2004/</course_url>
    <course_title>Public Economics II</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Economics </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Public Administration </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Unemployment Insurance - Theory</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-472-public-economics-ii-spring-2004/resources/policyapplicatio-1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Policy Application: The Cash Cow  of Imperfect Experience Rating  
The U.S. is actually relatively unique among industrialized nations in having any 
experience rating of its UI system, however imperfect.  Most nations finance their UI 
systems through a flat payroll tax that is unrelated to the firm s actual layoff experience. 
 Such a system can turn the UI system into a cash cow  that subsidizes the existence 
of highly inefficient firms. 
Consider the case of Canada s UI system, where workers had to work only 10 
weeks to qualify for 42 weeks of UI with a repl acement rate of 60%, at no extra cost to 
their firm.  In this system you and four fr iends are considering buying a fishing boat.  
You know that this fishing boat can only produce $40,000 worth of fish catch during the 
entire year.  That is only $8000 for each of you, and this is not enough to support each 
of you for an entire year.  So, in the absence of UI, you would not purchase this fishing boat. 
Given that structure of the Canadian UI  system, however, this purchase will be 
more attractive.  In this system, you and your  friends could each just work 10 weeks, for 
a total of 50 work weeks.  Each of you would report earning $800 per week for those 10 weeks, and then report being laid off.  Then you would each receive $19,200 of UI during the rest of the year (60% of t he $800 per week reported earnings, for forty 
weeks).  So the total UI benefits income acro ss all five recipients is $19,200*5 = 96,000. 
 Adding the $40,000 of fish produced, that is a total income to the firm of $136,000, or 
$27,200 per worker per year  for only 10 weeks of work!  This makes the purchase of 
the fishing boat much more attractive. 
This example illustrates the fundamental  problem with imperfect experience</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>rating: it subsidizes the existence of ineffici ent firms.  This firm is not an economically 
viable employer of five employees; it could only pay each employee $8000 per year if 
there was no UI system.  But by exploiting imperfect experience rating, it can remain 
viable.  Thus, UI is not simply a system of insurance against true unemployment risk in Canada, but also a large government transfer to firms and their laid off workers.]</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Background
Individual Motivation
Annuities</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-472-public-economics-ii-spring-2004/resources/annuities-1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>14.472  February 16, 2004 
Annu ities  Page 3 of 3 
Timing of a nnuitization  
Fully annuitize a t start 
 
 [] []11
1
1Max 
                  s. t.  L
hh s
s s
s
L
ss
sVW uc
pcW
=
==
=
 (8) 
 
 
 
FOC: 
 []1'hs
s suc ps =
1 (9) 
 
 
 
Wait one period and then annuiti ze, recognizing that there m ay be learning about survival 
probabilities and pricing m ay vary  with risk classification.  Assum e the discount rate does 
not change with the news. 
 
 
 [] [] []() []31
11
22
1
2
1
2Max ' 1 "
                  s. t .  ''
                          ""LL
hh hs hs
s ss
ss
L
ss
s
L
ss
sVW uc uc uc
cp c W
cp c W  
==
=
==+ +
+=
+=

s
 (10) 
 
 
 
FOC: 
 []
[]
[]11
1
1'' "
'' ''      for  2,3,...
'" ""      for 2,3,...h
hs
ss s
hs
ss suc
uc p s L
uc p s L 
 
 
=+
= =
== (11) 
 
Purchase of ann uities 08/19/04 Page 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>14.472  February 16, 2004 
Annu ities  Page 2 of 3 
 
 
If no adm inistrative cost s (actu arially fair). 
 [] []21
1
1
1Max 
                  s. t .  L
hh s
ss
s
L
hs
ss
sVW uc
RcW

=

==
=
 (5) 
 
 
 
FOC: 
 []1'1 s s
suc R   =  (6) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Value of annuitization: 
 [][]0h hiVW V W=  (7) 
 
 
 
Purchase of ann uities 08/19/04 Page 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>14.472  February 16, 2004 
Annu ities  Page 1 of 3 
Assum ptions: 
Expected utility of  additive pref erenc es with  no a ge variation in per iod utilities and no  
other risks 
No utility f rom bequests . 
 
Lifetime utility no annu ities, cons tant inte rest rate  
 [] []01
1
1
1Max 
                  s. t .  L
hh s
s s
s
L
s
s
sVW uc
RcW
=

==
=
 (1) 
 
 
 
FOC: 
 []1'hs s
ssuc R  1  =  (2) 
 
 
 
 
 
Lifetim e period-annuities arbitrary prices 
 [] []11
1
1Max 
                  s. t.  L
hh s
s s
s
L
ss
sVW uc
pcW
=
==
=
 (3) 
 
 
 
FOC: 
 []1'hs
s suc ps = (4) 
 
 
Purchase of ann uities 08/19/04 Page 1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Efficient Public Goods Provision</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-472-public-economics-ii-spring-2004/resources/optipubgoodssupp-1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>14.472   Spring    page  1 of 4 
Optimal Publ ic Goods Suppl y   
 
ASamuelson FOC 
 
Notation 
x  consumpt ion 
y  labor supply 
z  earni ngs 
w  wage 
g  public good 
[] ,,ux yg u tility 
if  fract ion of popul ation type  i
p  price of public good 
 
 
 
Social welfare maximizat ion: 
 
 
 
 
(),, Maximize ,,
subject to: 0i
xyg i i i
ii iifu xyg
Ep g fxwy
++ 
 (1 ) 
 
 
 
FOC:  
 
 
 [] ,,i
ix i i i fux yg f=  (2 ) 
 [] ,,i
iy i i ii fux yg fw=  (3 ) 
 
 ,,i
ig i i fux yg p =  (4 ) 
 
 
 
 
 
Implying: 
 ,,
,,i
gi i
ii
xi iux ygf pux yg
=  (5 ) 
 ,,
,,ii
gi i
i i
yi iwux ygf pux yg
=  (6 )</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>14.472   Spring          page  4 of 4 
Optimal Publ ic Goods Suppl y   
 
Using the other FOC: 
 
 
 
21
21
2112 1 2
1 1 22 22 22 1
12 2 2 12 1 2
1 1 22 22 22///,, ,, , , ,,,,,, ,, , , ,,gg g g
x
xx x xwwwwwwux yg ux yg ux y g ux ygf fu xy gux yg uxyg ux y g uxygp                      + =
 ( 16) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
This re duces to the Samu elson condit ion if 
 
 21
2112
22 2 2
1 2
22 22/
/,, ,,
,, ,,g g
xxww
wwux y g ux yg
ux y g uxyg   
   =
 ( 17) 
 
 
 
For example, this holds with everyone having the same utility function that is additive:  
 
ax by cg   ++  
 
or everyone  has a u tility function se parabl e in labor and wit h the same subaddit ive form:  
 
,,iuh xgy   . 
 
Otherwise , the deviation from t he Samu elson condit ion de pends on t he MRS for t he imitated 
type compared wit h that for an imit ator, that is, it depends on how t he MRS v aries wit h labor 
supply.  
 
And t he condit ions for t he Samu elson ru le to hold are diffe rent for diffe rent numeraire s.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>14.472  Spring    page  3 of 4 
Optimal Publ ic Goods Suppl y   
Rearranging t erms and adding and subt racting 212
22 1
22 2
22/,,,,,,g
x
xwwux ygux y gux yg    to the 
last equati on: 
 
 
 ()21
21 211
22 12
11 1 2 2 2 2
22
2
22 11
22 22 2
22/
//,,,, ,,,,
,,,, ,,,,x
gg
x
g
gx
xww
ww wwux y gfu xyg f uxygux yg
ux yguxyg uxygux yg
p          
         ++ 
 = ( 14) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Rearranging t erms again:
 
() () 21
21
21
21/
/
/
/12,, ,,11 22 12 1,, ,, , ,1 11 2 22 22 12,, ,,11 22
12,, ,,22 22 1,,22 12,, ,,22 22ww
ww
ww
wwux yg ux ygggfu xyg fu xyg uxy gxx xux yg uxygxx
ux y g ux ygggux y gxux y g uxygxx
 
    
     
 
  
  
   
  ++ 
 p


=



 ( 15)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>14.472  Spring        page  2 of 4 
Optimal Publ ic Goods Suppl y   
BSecond-Best FOC 
R. Boadway and M.  Keen,  Publ ic Goods,  Self-Selection and Optimal Income Taxation, 
International Eco nomic Review  v34, n3 (August  1993) , 463- 78. 
 
 
 
  (7 ) (),,
/,Maximize ,,
subject to:          0
                         ,, ,   for al l  and jii
xyg i i i
ii ii
ii
ii j jww gfu xyg
Ep g fxwy
ux yg ux y i j
  ++ 


 
 
 
Assume t wo types.  Assume t he only binding mo ral hazard const raint is type 1 considering 
imitating t ype 2. 
 
 
 ()
2112
,, 11 1 2 2 2
11
11 2 2/Maximize ,, ,,
subject to:          0
                         ,, , ,xyg
ii ii
wwfux yg fuxyg
Ep g fxwy
ux yg ux y g   
  +
++ 

 (8 ) 
 
 
 
FOC:  
 
 1 1
11 1 1 1 1 ,, ,, 0x x fu xyg f uxyg      + = (9 ) 
 
 1 1
11 1 11 1 1 ,, ,, 0y y fu xyg fw uxyg      + = ( 10) 
 
 212 1
22 2 2 2 2/ ,, , , 0x x ww fu xyg f uxy g         = ( 11) 
 
 212 1
22 2 22 2 2/ ,, , , 0y y ww fu xyg fw uxy g         = ( 12) 
  
 ( ) 2112 1 1
11 1 2 2 2 1 1 2 2/ ,, ,, ,, , ,gg g g ww fuxyg fuxy g uxyg uxy g p           ++  =  ( 13)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Social Security in OLG Growth Models</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-472-public-economics-ii-spring-2004/resources/socisecurolgsett-1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Within Cohort Theoretical Models</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-472-public-economics-ii-spring-2004/resources/socseculengofcar-1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Estate Taxes</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-472-public-economics-ii-spring-2004/resources/atkins_glitz_mod/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>14.472  Spring 2 004  page  2 of 3 
Atkinson-St iglitz  August 19, 2004 
 
Then we have the FOC for the consum ption lev els (assum ing inte rior solutions) 
 
 
()()1111 1 1 1 1 1
11 2 1 11
2 ,, ,,
                        xxfu xxy f ux xy    =    (2) 
 
()()2211 1 1 1 1 1
11 2 1 11
2 ,, ,,
                        xxfu xxy pf ux xy    =     (3) 
 
()()1 122 2 2 1 2 2
21 2 2 1 2 12
2 ,, / ,,
                        x x fux xy f ww ux xy    =   (4) 
 
()()2 222 2 2 1 2 2
21 2 2 1 2 12
2 ,, / ,,
                        x x fux xy pf ww ux xy    =   (5) 
 
Taking ratios, we have 
 
 
1
211 1 1
12
11 1 1
12,,
,,
                        x
xux xy
p
ux xy=  (6) 
 
11
2222 2 2 1 2 2
21 2 1 2 1
22 2 2 1 2 2
21 2 1 2 12
2
2
2,, /
,, /,,
,,
                        xx
xxfu xxy ww
p
fu xxy wwux xy
ux xy
   =
     (7) 
 
 
The first condition is the usual lack  of m arginal taxation at the t op of the earnings distribution.  
The second condition involves no taxation if 
 
 
 
 
1 1
2 212 2 22 2 2
12 12
22 2 2 12 2
12 1 22
2
2
2/ ,,
,, /,,
,,
                        x x
x xww ux xy
ux xy wwux xy
ux xy  =
  1
1
  (8)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>14.472  Spring 2 004  page  1 of 3 
Atkinson-St iglitz  August 19, 2004 
 
 
Notation  
ix  consum ption in period i 
y  labor supply 
z  net of tax earnings 
w  wage 
[,ux y] utility 
if  number of workers of type  i
p  producer price of good 2 
q  consum er price of good 2 
 
 
There are tw o theorem s to look at, bo th invol ving a lack of tax ation of commodities in the 
presence of optim al incom e taxation.  One has general nonlinear taxation, while the other has 
linear commodity taxation.  Both ar e shown in the two-types model. 
 
A. Full nonlin ear taxation 
 
 
Social welfare m aximization assum ing full nonlinear taxation: 
 
 
 
  (1) ()12
12
12 1 2, ,
,, /Maximize ,
subject to:          0
                         , ,   for all  and ii i
ii i
ii i j j j
jii
xy i
ii
iiwwfu xxy
Ef x pxwy
ux xy ux xy i j
+
    + 


 
 
 
 
 
Assum e that the only binding constrai nt is type 1 im itating type 2.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Social Insurance Theory</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-472-public-economics-ii-spring-2004/resources/ssfacts/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>under the NRA and $31,080 for the NRA year; no te st after that).  After that, lose $1 
in benefit for every $2 ($3) in earnings if age between 62 -NRA (NRA year).  There is 
a complex formula for increasing your benef it later if you lose be nefits due to the 
earnings test. 
- Benefits are subject to income tax only if  have more than $ 32,000 ($25,000) in non-SS 
income for a couple (single person); most  people dont pay tax on them.  $12.7 billion in 
revenues to the trust fund came from  taxation of benefits in 2001.  
- Revenue from the taxation of the first 50 % of benefits goes to the SS Trust Fund.  
Additional revenue from taxation of up to 85% of benefits goes to the Medicare Hospital 
Insurance Trust Fund. 
- There are disability benefits too.  Can qualify with less than  40 quarters if young; benefits 
are based on &lt;35 years of earnings.  To qua lify, must pass medical screening process and 
not have worked for last 6 months. 
 
3. Family benefits: 
- Law is gender-neutral (but most dependent s are women, so Ill use that language) 
- A dependent spouse is eligible for a benefit of  50% of the workers PIA.  The dependent 
can start this benefit as soon as she is 62 a nd her spouse has started receiving his benefit.  
The spouses benefit is reduced if she starts it before she reaches the NRA (slope is a 
little steeper than above)  
- A dependent spouse may also be entitled to he r own retired worker benefit.  If so, she 
receives the larger of the two benefits (t echnically, she first gets her retired worker 
benefit, then it is topped up to the amount  of the spouse benefit if applicable). 
- A surviving spouse gets 100% of the workers PI A.  This benefit is first available at age 
60 and it is reduced if  the worker started benefits befo re his NRA or if the survivor 
started the benefit before her NRA.  Als o, a younger surviving spouse with dependent 
children can get benefits. 
- There is also a benefit for children under 18 of  deceased, retired, or disabled workers of 
75% of the workers PIA; however, the family  as a whole can get no more than 175% of 
the workers PIA.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>14.472 Public Economics II 
February 18, 2004  
Key Social Security Facts
 
1. Revenue: 
- Financed by payroll tax (F ICA) of 12.4% on wages up to taxable max ($87,900 in 2004).  
The taxable maximum is wage-indexed.   
- Tax is paid by both employer and employee (6.2% each).  
- System covers all workers, except some state and local government employees. 
- This is a pay-as-you-go system (current tax revenues used to fund current benefits), not 
fully funded. 
- Trust fund: currently, taxes collected each year  are greater than benefits paid out ($627.1 
billion vs. $461.7 billion in CY  2002), and the excess is put in  the SS trust fund, which is 
invested in government bonds.  Trust fund is  expected to grow until about 2018, then 
benefits will exceed taxes and we will draw down the trust fund, until it runs out around 
2042.  
- The SS trust fund generates a substantial amount of intere st income  $84.9 billion in 
2003.  This represents a 6.0% e ffective annual interest rate. 
 
2. Worker benefits: 
- Anyone who works 40 quarters is entit led to retired worker benefits. 
- Benefits are a real annuity (rece ive until you die and indexed to CPI) 
- Benefits are computed  in several steps: 
1. Take nominal annual covered earnings (up to taxable max) for all years of work 
(including post 62). 
2. Use average wage index to convert to r eal (earnings after age 60 left nominal). 
3. Take highest 35 years (including zeroes, if  necessary) and divi de by 35*12 to get 
AIME (Average Indexed Monthly Earnings). 
4. Apply progressive formula to AIME to  get PIA (Primary Insurance Amount); 
replacement rate is .9 on first $612, then .32 up to $3,689, then .15 for amounts above $3,689.  The benefit is based on PIA.  Break points in the formula are wage-indexed. 
5. It is up to the worker to decide when to  start receiving benefits .  Most people start 
them right after they retire, but some pe ople wait.  If you start them before you are 
retired, you have to worry about  the earnings test (see #9). 
6. If start benefits at NRA (Normal Retirement Age), benefit is PIA.  NRA is 65 for 
those born before 1938.  The NRA rises nonlinea rly with birth year until it hits 67 for 
those born after 1960. 
7. If start benefits before NRA,  benefit is reduced by 6.67% per year.  If start at age 62 
(the Early Entitlement Age), benefit is 80%  of PIA.  Once NRA rises to 67, if start 
benefit at 62 get only 70% of PIA (reductio n is 6.67% per year for first three years 
then 5% per year after). 
8. If start benefits after NRA, get a delayed retirement credit (DRC).  The DRC depends 
on the year of birth.  If born in 1939, each year  one delays benefits is a 7% increase in 
the PIA.  For those born in 1942 or later, th e DRC is 8% for each year after the NRA . 
9. If you are still working when you start benefits, you are allowed to keep all the 
benefits if your wage is below the ear nings test ceiling (i n 2004, $11,640 for those</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Voluntary Private Provision of Public Goods and Private Charity</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-472-public-economics-ii-spring-2004/resources/pubgoodprivateeq-1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>14.472 - Spring   page  1 of 4 
Public Goods  priv ate equilibrium 
 
CNash equilibrium with private provision  
Noncooperat ive, not cooperat ive equi librium 
 
T. Bergst rom,  L. Blume,  and H.  Varian, "On t he Priv ate Prov ision of Public Goods, " Journal o f Public 
Economi cs 29 (1986) , 25-49. 
 
Notation 
ix  consumpt ion of household i 
ib  income of househol d i 
ig  publ ic good cont ribut ion of househol d i 
G  public good cont ribut ion of gov ernment  
g  public good lev el: i gG g=+  
[],i
iux g utility of hou sehold i - concav e 
if  fract ion of popul ation of t ype i 
p  price of public good,  set equal t o 1 
it  income t ax of househol d i 
 
 
Assume t wo types, with equal numbers.  
Private cont ribut ion equilibrium ( no gov ernment  activity) 
 
Individual choice , assu ming []0,i
xug= 
 
 
 
, Maximize ,
subject to:        i
xgi i
ii iux gg
xg bj  +
+    ( 1) 
 
 
 
FOC:  
 
 
 
, ,i i
x ii j g ii j uxgg uxgg   + +    ( 2) 
 
 
 
with equality if . 0ig&gt;
 
Equil ibrium is simul taneous sol ution of t wo FOC for t wo agent s.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>14.472 - Spring    page  4 of 4 
Public Goods  priv ate equilibrium 
Equilibrium is now: 
 
 
 
 
11 1 1 1 1 2 vb tg wgg      +
     ( 12) 
22 1 2 2 1 2 vb tg wgg      ++      ( 13) 
 
 
 
 
Assume taxes are small enough not to change the type of equilibrium.  Then, in case , there i s 
no ef fect on t he real allocat ion. C
 
This impl ies that there is full offse t to gov ernme nt prov ision finance d by cont ributors, assu ming we  
stay with equilibrium of type . C
 
There would  be an ef fect once we cross t he bord er into type B.  In type B, the critical question 
is whet her redist ribut ion is  from or t o cont ribut ors. 
 
 
 
FMultiple public goods  
 
With mult iple public goods and many people,  we would expect  most  people t o cont ribut e to 
only one good .  If there are mult iple cont ributions f or agent  1, for example,  we hav e the first 
orde r condit ion ( with  being t he utility of age nt i with respect to public good ). ikw k
 
 
 
 
[] 11 11 21 1 1 11 12 12 12 22 gg vb g g w w g g +=       = +    ( 14) 
 
 
 
 
If the budget of the agent is small relative to publ ic good spending on any good,  then we coul d 
start with marginal  utilities assu ming no cont ribution: ik jk
jiwG g
 + 
  .  With possible 
contributions small, the marginal utilities do not change noticeably, and all of the contribution is 
made to the charity with the highest marginal ut ility at zero cont ribut ion.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>14.472 - Spring    page  2 of 4 
Public Goods  priv ate equilibrium 
 
Four possible equilibria:  
 
12 no contributions:  0
contr ibutions onl y by i:  0; 0
contr ibutions by  both:   0; 0ii
ijAg g
Bg
Cg==
&gt;=
&gt;&gt;jg
g
 
 
To ke ep it simpl e, assu me addit ive utility functions: 
 
 
 
,i
ii i i ux g vx wg     =+      ( 3) 
 
 
This makes preferences for bot h goods normal.  
Then t he equi librium is: 
 
 
 
11 1 1 1 2 vb g wgg      +
     ( 4) 
22 2 2 1 2 vb g wgg     +      ( 5) 
 
 
 
 
DComparative statics of government provision with financing 
 
Assume t hat the gov ernment  prov ides G, financed by ( nonnegat ive) taxes on 1 and 2 and 
possibly an out sider.  
 
 
 
 
1 Gt t+2       ( 6) 
 
 
 
 
With equilibrium of type, neit her t axes nor gov ernment  prov ision encourages priv ate 
cont ribut ion: A
 
 
 
 
gG=         ( 7)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>14.472 - Spring    page  3 of 4 
Public Goods  priv ate equilibrium 
With equilibrium of typeiB, there are two possibilities.  Government contributions/taxes might be 
so large as t o hav e equilibrium of t ype , or we sti ll hav e an equi librium of type AiB: 
 
 
 
 
ii i i i i vb tg wgG      =+     ( 8) 
 
 
 
 
Assume that taxes are proportional to government spending, with constant . is
 
 
 
 
i i tsG=        ( 9) 
 
 
 
 
Then diffe rentiating the equilibrium condit ion, we hav e: 
 
 
 
 
 
ii i i ii
ii i idg svw svw
dG vw vwi   += =  +    ( 10) 
 
 
 
 
If , then there is full offse t.  The  same  holds if utility is qu asilinear - 1is= 0iv=.  We put off anal ysis 
of case  until after we consider income redist ribut ion. C
 
 
 
 
EComparative statics of income redistribution  
 
We assume no gov ernment  prov ision and lump-sum income redist ribut ion: 
 
 
 
 
12 0 tt+=       ( 11)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Income Tax Deduction of Charitable Donations</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/14-472-public-economics-ii-spring-2004/resources/warmglowpreferen-1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>L=X
Nn(u[cn]ann+bnv[G])
E+pG+X
Nn(cnn)
(2)
+XX
nm(u[cn]ann+bnv[G](u[cm]amn+bnv[G]))
The FOC for public good provision is
X
Nnbnv0[G]=p (3)
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>2.3 Warm Glow Preferences that do enter Social Wel-
fare:=1
The FOC (16) - (20) become
L
c1=N1(u0[c1])u0[c1]1g[c1,G]
c=0 (30)
L
c2=N2(u0[c2])+u0[c2]2g[c2,G]
c=0. (31)
L
G=X
Nnbv0[G]ng[cn,G]
G
p+b(v0[G]v0[Gg2+g1])+=0
(32)
L
g1=N1w0[g1](bv0[Gg2+g1]+w0[g1])N1+1=0 (33)
L
g2=N2w0[g2]+(bv0[Gg2+g1]+w0[g2])N2+2=0 (34)
Donations of the low type may be subsidized. The dominance of donations
of the high type over public provision remains true.
If donations of both types are subsidized ( 1,2=0), the private con-
sumption FOC have the same form as with fully public provision.
L
c1=N1(u0[c1])u0[c1]=0 (35)
L
c2=N2(u0[c2])+u0[c2]=0 (36)
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>3N o t a t i o n
n skill index (equal to productivity)
Nn number of workers of skill n
xn compensation at job of skill n
cn consumption of worker holding job of skill n
u[cn]utility of private good consumption
amn disutility of labor for a worker of skill nholding a job of skill m
G public good supply
bnv[G]utility of public good consumption
gn donation of worker holding a job of skill n
w[gn]warm glow utility
Gn public good provision net of donation of a worker holding a job of skill n
p cost per unit of the public good
E other public expenditures
sn donation subsidy rate for worker in job of skill n
 Lagrangian on the resource constraint
n Lagrangians on the incentive compatibility constraints
 Lagrangian on the adding up constraint for public good provision
n Lagrangians on the minimum donation constraints
 index to distinguish SWF with and without warm glow utility
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>2 Warm Glow Preferences
With preferences u[cn]ann+bnv[G]+w[gn], the FOC for individual do-
nations for workers who make positive contributions satis es
(1sn)pu0[cn]=( 1 sn)pu0[xn(1sn)pgn] (12)
=bnv0[Gn+gn]+w0[gn]=bnv0[G]+w0[gn]
The donation level with a zero subsidy (the minimum donation level),
g[cn,G],s a t i s es the individual FOC
pu0[cn]=pu0[xnpgn]=bnv0[Gn+gn]+w0[gn]=bnv0[G]+w0[gn](13)
Dierentiating the implicit equation,
g
c=pu00
w00&gt;0,g
G=bv00
w00&lt;0. (14)
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>2.2 Warm Glow Preferences that do not enter Social
Welfare: =0
Increasing the donation of the high type while lowering the donation of the
low type weakens the incentive compatibility constraint while having no other
eects, until the lower limit on g1is hit. Similarly, donations by the high
type dominate public provision. Thus we know that g1=g[c1,G]. Assuming
that public good supply is less than optimal without any subsidization, we
also have no binding minimum donation constraint for the high type, 2=0.
Thus we can write the FOC (16) and (17) for the case =0as
L
c1=N1(u0[c1])u0[c1]1g[c1,G]
c=0 (21)
L
c2=N2(u0[c2])+u0[c2]=0 (22)
T u r n i n gt ot h eo t h e rF O C ,w i t h g1at its minimum, (18) and (20) become
L
G=bv0[G]X
Nn1g[c1,G]
Gp+b(v0[G]v0[Gg2+g1])+=0
(23)
L
g2=(bv0[Gg2+g1]+w0[g2])N2=0 (24)
It is plausible for all but very large donors that v00is small enough that
v0[G]v0[Gg2+g1]is very small. Then the FOC for public good supply
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Assuming that the incentive compatibility constraint is binding ( &gt; 0), we
have
u0[c1]
u0[c2]=1+/N 2
1/N 1&gt;1 (37)
If donations of both t ypes are subsidized ( 1,2=0):
L
g1=N1w0[g1](bv0[Gg2+g1]+w0[g1])N1=0 (38)
L
g2=N2w0[g2]+(bv0[Gg2+g1]+w0[g2])N2=0 (39)
Solving for w0[gn]we have

1
N1
w0[g1]=+
N1bv0[Gg2+g1] (40)

1+
N2
w0[g2]=
N2bv0[Gg2+g1] (41)
The total utility gain from a donation by the lower type is
bv0[G]+w0[g1]=bv0[G]+
+
N1(bv0[Gg2+g1])
/
1
N1
(42)
=
bv0[G]++
N1(bv0[Gg2+g1]bv0[G])
/
1
N1
We can evaluate the subsidy level.
(1s1)=bv0[G]+w0[g1]
pu0[c1]=bv0[G]++
N1(bv0[Gg2+g1]bv0[G])
p
(43)
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Note that the subsidy rate for type 1 can exceed the subsidy rate for type
2 and still support the optimum. Using the maximal subsidy for type 1 that
still leaves a zero contribution, we have:
(1s1)pu0[c1]=b1v0[G] (8)
(1s2)pu0[c2]=b2v0[G] (9)
Withb1=b2,we have s1s2sincec1c2with strict inequality if the
incentive compatibility constraint is binding.
If the incentive compatibility constraint binds, the constraint becomes
u[c2]a22+b2v[G]=u[c1]a12+b2v[GG/N 2] (10)
The FOC for the public good satis es:
X
Nnbnv0[G]=pb2(v0[G]v0[G(11/N2)] (11/N2)) (11)
This may or may not satisfy the Samuelson rule and can deviate in either
direction depending on the shape of the public good utility function, that is
the sign of (v0[G]v0[G(11/N2)] (11/N2)).I fvis small, this is close
to the Samuelson rule.
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>14.472 Handout on Optimal Tax Treatment
of Private Contributions for Public Goods
with and without Warm Glow Preferences
February 2004
1 Standard Preferences
1.1 Optimal Public Provision
Maximize c,GPNn(u[cn]ann+bnv[G])
subject to: E+pG+PNn(cnn)0
u[cn]ann+bnv[G]u[cm]amn+bnv[G]form&lt;n for alln
(1)
Forming a Lagrangian, we have
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>is approximately
L
Gbv0[G]X
Nn1g[c1,G]
Gp+=0 (25)
We can express the deviation from the Samuelson condition as
bv0[G]X
Nnp1g[c1,G]
G=1g[c1,G]
G
N2(bv0[Gg2+g1]+w0[g2])
(26)
Using again the assumption of a small v00, and so approximate constancy of
v0, and the FOC for individual donations, we can write this as
bv0[G]X
Nnp=1g[c1,G]
G
N2(1s2)pu0[c2] (27)
From the FOC for consumption, this can be written as
bv0[G]X
Nnp1g[c1,G]
G+( 1s2)p(u0[c2]) (28)
or
bv0[G]X
Nn1g[c1,G]
G+s2p+( 1s2)pu0[c2] (29)
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>the government of the marginal contribution by the high type. Similarly, in
terms of the marginal utilities of type 1.
bv0[G]X
Nns1p+( 1s1)pu0[c1]w0[g1] (48)
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Similarly, for the high type
(1s2)=bv0[G]+w0[g2]
pu0[c2]=bv0[G]+
N2(bv0[Gg2+g1]bv0[G])
p
(44)
Taking the ratio
1s1
1s2=bv0[G]++
N1(bv0[Gg2+g1]bv0[G])
bv0[G]+
N2(bv0[Gg2+g1]bv0[G])&gt;1 (45)
Thus the high type receives a higher subsidy. If, as is plausible, v00is small
relative to individual donations, then (1s1)/(1s2)1.
If donations of both types are subsidized ( 1,2=0)a n dv00is small, the
FOC for public good level becomes approximately:
bv0[G]X
Nnp+0 (46)
bv0[G]X
Nnp=pw0[g2]
N2(bv0[G]+w0[g2])(47)
=pw0[g2]
N2(1s2)pu0[c2]
=pw0[g2]+( 1s2)p(u0[c2])
=s2p+( 1s2)pu0[c2]w0[g2]
Ifw0is much larger than v0,then the last two terms approximately cancel
and the FOC is as if the only cost of public goods were the marginal cost to
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>1.2 Subsidized Private Provision
cn=xn(1sn)pgn (4)
Utility can be written:
u[xn(1sn)pgn]ann+bnv[Gn+gn] (5)
The contributions for workers who make positive contributions satisfy
(1sn)pu0[cn]=( 1sn)pu0[xn(1sn)pgn]=bnv0[Gn+gn]=bnv0[G]
(6)
Social welfare maximization
Maximize c,G,gPNn(u[cn]ann+bnv[G])
subject to: E+pG+PNn(cnn)0
u[c2]a22+b2v[G]u[c1]a12+b2v[Gg2+g1]
GPNngn;gn0for alln
(7)
T h eo p t i m u mw i l lh a v eo n eo ft w of o r m s-e i t h e rb o t hh a v et h es a m ec o n s u m p -
tion and (generically) the incentive compatibility constraint is not binding,
or the optimum will have the incentive compatibility constraint binding.
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>2.1 Social Welfare Optimization
Considering the two-types model with one public good, we can write a for-
mulation allowing warm glow to enter ( =1)a n dn o te n t e r( =0)s o c i a l
welfare.
Maximize c,GPNn(u[cn]ann+bv[G]+w[gn])
subject to: E+pG+PNn(cnn)0
u[c2]a22+bv[G]+w[g2]u[c1]a12+bv[Gg2+g1]+w[g1]
GPNngn;gng[cn,G]for alln
(15)
Die r e n t i a t i n gw eh a v el o t so fF O C :
L
c1=N1(u0[c1])u0[c1]1g[c1,G]
c=0 (16)
L
c2=N2(u0[c2])+u0[c2]2g[c2,G]
c=0 (17)
L
G=X
Nnbv0[G]ng[cn,G]
G
p+b(v0[G]v0[Gg2+g1])+=0
(18)
L
g1=N1w0[g1](bv0[Gg2+g1]+w0[g1])N1+1=0 (19)
L
g2=N2w0[g2]+(bv0[Gg2+g1]+w0[g2])N2+2=0 (20)
We consider the FOC separately for the values of of 0 and 1.
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
