<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/</course_url>
    <course_title>Quantum Physics III</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Physics </list>
      <list>Theoretical Physics </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch3</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare  
https://ocw.mit.edu 
8.06 Quantum Physics III 
Spring 2018  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch8</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare  
https://ocw.mit.edu 
8.06 Quantum Physics III 
Spring 2018  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch1</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>0</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>1.2. DEGENERATE PERTURBATION THEORY 17
Our notation distinguishes the states in VNfrom those in Vbecause the former have two
labels and the latter have only one.
We now consider the evolution of the degenerate eigenstates as we turn on the pertur-
bation. Again we assume that the states vary continuously in and thus write:
|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht  |n;k/an}backeti}ht=|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht+|n(1);k/an}backeti}ht+2|n(2);k/an}backeti}ht+O(3),
E(0)
nEn,k() =E(0)
n+E(1)
n,k+2E(2)
n,k+O(3).(1.2.17)
These equations hold for k= 1,...,N. Note that for each value of kthe energy corrections
might be dierent and thats why the energy corrections carry the labelk. Our goal is to
nd the state corrections |n(p);k/an}backeti}htand the energy corrections E(p)
n,kforp1 and for each k.
As before we demand that |n(p);k/an}backeti}htforp1 has no component along |n(0);k/an}backeti}ht, i.e.
/an}backetle{tn(0);k|n(p);k/an}backeti}ht= 0 for p1 (1.2.18)
Note, however, that |n(p);k/an}backeti}htmay have components along |n(0);/an}backeti}htwith/ne}ationslash=k. So|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht
may and in fact will have a component in VN.
The perturbed eigenstates must satisfy
H()|n;k/an}backeti}ht=En,k()|n;k/an}backeti}ht, (1.2.19)
and substituting the perturbative expansions above we obta in equations completely analo-
gous to the ones in Eq.(1.1.13)
0: (H0E(0)
n)|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht= 0, (1.2.20)
1: (H0E(0)
n)|n(1);k/an}backeti}ht= (E(1)
n,kH)|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht, (1.2.21)
2: (H0E(0)
n)|n(2);k/an}backeti}ht= (E(1)
n,kH)|n(1);k/an}backeti}ht+E(2)
n,k|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht,(1.2.22)
.........
In the following we will discuss a solution to rst order for t he case in which the de-
generacy in VNis completely broken to rst order in perturbation theory; t hat is, the rst
order corrections to the energies split the Nstates completely. Our solution will proceed
in three steps:
1. Hit the O() equation with /an}backetle{tn(0);|to learn that Hmust be diagonal in the chosen
basis for VNand to determine the rst-order energy shifts.
2. Use the O() equation to calculate the components of |n(1);k/an}backeti}htinV.
3. Hit the O(2) equation with /an}backetle{tn(0);|to determine the second order energy correction
E(2)
n,kand the component of |n(1);k/an}backeti}htinVN.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare  
https://ocw.mit.edu 
8.06 Quantum Physics III 
Spring 2018  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>16 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
perturbation theory. Happily, this is not really true. The e igenvectors of H(0)are in fact
ambiguous , precisely due to the degeneracy. The eigenvectors of H(0)are actually the span
of the two vectors listed in (1.2.4). The perturbation selec ted a particular combination
of these eigenvectors. This particular combination is the o ne that we should use even for
= 0. The lesson is that to get states that vary continuously as is turned on we must
choose the basis in the degenerate subspace of H(0)carefully. We will call that carefully
selected basis the good basis.
1.2.2 Systematic Analysis
Again, we are looking at the perturbed Hamiltonian
H() =H(0)+H, (1.2.9)
whereH(0)has known eigenvectors and eigenvalues. We will focus this t ime on a degenerate
subspace of eigenvectors of dimension N &gt;1, that is, a space with Nlinearly independent
eigenstates of the same energy. In the basis of eigenstates, H(0)is a diagonal matrix that
contains a string of N &gt;1 identical entries:
H(0)= diag{E(0)
1,E(0)
2,..., E(0)
n,... ,E(0)
n/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
N, ...}. (1.2.10)
In the degenerate subspace we choose a collection of Northonormal eigenstates
|n(0);1/an}backeti}ht,|n(0);2/an}backeti}ht, ...,|n(0);N/an}backeti}ht. (1.2.11)
Accordingly, we have
/an}backetle{tn(0);p|n(0);l/an}backeti}ht=p,l, (1.2.12)
H(0)|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht=E(0)
n|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht. (1.2.13)
This set of vectors span a degenerate subspace of dimension Nthat we will call VN
VNspan{|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht,k= 1, ...N}. (1.2.14)
The total state space of the theory, denoted by His written as a direct sum:
H=VNV , (1.2.15)
whereVis spanned by those eigenstates of H(0)that are not in VN. We denote by |p(0)/an}backeti}ht
withpZa basis for V. That basis may include both degenerate and non degenerate
states. Together with the states in VNwe have an orthonormal basis for the whole state
space:
/an}backetle{tp(0)|q(0)/an}backeti}ht=pq,/an}backetle{tp(0)|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht= 0. (1.2.16)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
for example, of an atom in an external magnetic eld that can b e varied continuously. In
that case we can view as the parameter that allows us to turn on the perturbation by
letting/ne}ationslash= 0. The parameter is also useful in organizing the perturbation analysis, as w e
will see below.
We spoke of a Hamiltonian that diers slightly from H(0). In order to use perturbation
theory we need Hto be a small perturbation of the Hamiltonian H(0). We will have to
deal with themeaning of small. At rstsight we may imagine th at small means that, viewed
as matrices, the largest entries in Hare smaller than the largest entries in H(0). While
this is necessary, more is needed, as we will see in our analys is. An additional advantage of
usingis that by taking it to be suciently small we can surely make Hsmall.
We assume that the Hamiltonian H(0)is understood, namely, we know the eigenstates
andeigenvalues of H(0). Wewant toknowtheeigenstates andeigenvalues of H(). Onemay
beable to calculate those exactly, but this is seldom a reali stic possibility. Diagonalizing H
is seldom useful, since HandHdonot generally commuteandtherefore Heigenstates are
not eigenstates of H(). In perturbation theory the key assumption is that the eige nvalues
and eigenvectors of H() can be found as series expansions in powers of . We hope, of
course, that there are some values of for which the series converges, or at least gives useful
information.
Figure 1.1: The energy eigenvalues of H() asvaries from zero to one. On the = 0 vertical
axis theH(0)eigenstates are represented by heavy dots. By the time = 1 the dots have shifted.
In Figure 1.1 we illustrate some of the phenomena that we may s ee in the spectrum
of a system with Hamiltonian H(). We show how the energies of the various states may
change as the parameter is increased from zero. The two lowest energy eigenstates ar e
non-degenerate and their energies can go up and down as varies. Next up in energy we
have two degenerate states of H(0)(the Hamiltonian as = 0). The perturbation splits the</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>1.2. DEGENERATE PERTURBATION THEORY 21
1.2.3 Degeneracy lifted at second order
We now investigate the case when the degeneracy is completel y unbroken to rst order.
The situation and the setup is similar to the one we just consi dered: we have a degenerate
subspace VNof dimension Nand the rest of the space is called V. This time, however, we
will assume that the degeneracy of H(0)is not broken to rst order in the perturbation H.
Concretely, this means that on the VNbasis|n(0);k/an}backeti}htwithk= 1,...,N, we have
/an}backetle{tn(0);|H|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht=E(1)
n,k. (1.2.42)
The rst order energy correction is the same, and equal to E(1)
n, for all basis states in VN.
You should compare with (1.2.24), where the energy had an ext ra subscript to distinguish
its various possible values.
Because the degeneracy is not broken to rst order we do not kn ow at this point what
is the good basis in VN. We will consider here the case when the degeneracy is comple tely
lifted to second order. We express our ignorance about good b asis vectors by stating that
we are searching for the right linear combinations:
|(0)/an}backeti}ht=N/summationdisplay
k=1|n(0);k/an}backeti}hta(0)
k. (1.2.43)
For some values of the constants a(0)
kwithk= 1,...,Nthe state |(0)/an}backeti}htwill be good. We
can think of a(0)as the column vector representation of |(0)/an}backeti}htinVN. We have written
just one state, |(0)/an}backeti}ht, even though we are expecting to nd Ngood states to span the
degenerate subspace. We therefore adjust the notation to re ect this. We introduce a new
indexI= 1,...,Nand write
|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht=N/summationdisplay
k=1|n(0);k/an}backeti}hta(0)
Ik, I= 1,...,N. (1.2.44)
The indexInow labels the dierent good states and their dierent vector r epresentations
a(0)
I. Our most immediate goal is to nd those vectors a(0)
Iand thus the good basis. To
do so we will have to consider second order energy correction s. The states |(0)
I/an}backeti}htform an
orthonormal basis in VNif the coecients a(0)
Isatisfy
/an}backetle{t(0)
J|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht=IJ/summationdisplay
k(a(0)
Jk)a(0)
Ik=IJ. (1.2.45)
We set up the perturbation theory as usual
|I/an}backeti}ht=|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht+|(1)
I/an}backeti}ht+2|(2)
I/an}backeti}ht+... ,
EnI() =E(0)
n+E(1)
n+2E(2)
nI+3E(3)
nI+... .(1.2.46)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>20 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
The piece in Vvector drops out for our case of interest:
/an}backetle{tn(0);|H|n(1);k/an}backeti}ht/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
VN=E(1)
n,/an}backetle{tn(0);|n(1);k/an}backeti}ht/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
VN. (1.2.35)
Back into equation (1.2.33) we now get
/summationdisplay
pHn,pHp,nk
E(0)
pE(0)
n+/parenleftBig
E(1)
n,kE(1)
n,/parenrightBig
/an}backetle{tn(0);|n(1);k/an}backeti}ht/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
VN+E(2)
n,kk,= 0.(1.2.36)
Setting=kwe can determine the second correction to the energies:
E(2)
n,k=/summationdisplay
p|Hp,nk|2
E(0)
pE(0)
n. (1.2.37)
Fork/ne}ationslash=we get
/summationdisplay
pHn,pHp,nk
E(0)
pE(0)
n+/parenleftBig
E(1)
n,kE(1)
n,/parenrightBig
/an}backetle{tn(0);|n(1);k/an}backeti}ht/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
VN= 0. (1.2.38)
Had we not included the piece of |n(1);k/an}backeti}htalong the degenerate subspace we would have
had an inconsistency, since there is no reason why the rst te rm on the left-hand side must
be zero. Now the above equation just xes the components of |n(1);k/an}backeti}htin the degenerate
subspace as long asE(1)
n,k/ne}ationslash=E(1)
n,:
/an}backetle{tn(0);|n(1);k/an}backeti}ht/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
VN=1
E(1)
n,kE(1)
n,/summationdisplay
pHn,pHp,nk
E(0)
pE(0)
n, k/ne}ationslash=. (1.2.39)
We thus have
|n(1);k/an}backeti}ht/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
VN=/summationdisplay
/negationslash=k|n(0);/an}backeti}ht1
E(1)
n,kE(1)
n,/summationdisplay
pHn,pHp,nk
E(0)
pE(0)
n. (1.2.40)
It may seem that this extra piece, found by using the O(2) equation, is higher order than
it should in the perturbation: its numerator contains two po wers ofH. But this expression
also has a curious energy denominator, E(1)
n,kE(1)
n,, in which each term has a power of H.
All in all, the correction to the state is properly rst order inH.
Summarizing our result we have
Degenerate perturbation theory with degeneracies lifted a tO():
|n;k/an}backeti}ht=|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht/parenleftBig/summationdisplay
pHp,nk
E(0)
pE(0)
n|p(0)/an}backeti}ht+/summationdisplay
/negationslash=k|n(0);/an}backeti}ht
E(1)
n,kE(1)
n,/summationdisplay
pHn,pHp,nk
E(0)
pE(0)
n/parenrightBig
+O(2)
En,k() =E(0)
n+Hnk,nk2/summationdisplay
pHnk,pHp,nk
E(0)
pE(0)
n+O(3), E(1)
n,k=Hnk,nk.
(1.2.41)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>1.1. NONDEGENERATE PERTURBATION THEORY 5
Multiplying out we get a series in with coecients -independent vectors in the state
space of the theory. If this is to vanish for all values of those coecients must be zero.
Collecting the coecients for each power of we
0: (H(0)E(0)
n)|n(0)/an}backeti}ht= 0,
1: (H(0)E(0)
n)|n(1)/an}backeti}ht= (E(1)
nH)|n(0)/an}backeti}ht,
2: (H(0)E(0)
n)|n(2)/an}backeti}ht= (E(1)
nH)|n(1)/an}backeti}ht+E(2)
n|n(0)/an}backeti}ht,
3: (H(0)E(0)
n)|n(3)/an}backeti}ht= (E(1)
nH)|n(2)/an}backeti}ht+E(2)
n|n(1)/an}backeti}ht+E(3)
n|n(0)/an}backeti}ht,
.........
k: (H(0)E(0)
n)|n(k)/an}backeti}ht= (E(1)
nH)|n(k1)/an}backeti}ht+E(2)
n|n(k2)/an}backeti}ht+...+E(k)
n|n(0)/an}backeti}ht.
(1.1.13)
Each equation is the condition that the coecient multiplyi ng the power of indicated to
the left vanishes. That power is reected as the sum of supers cripts on each term, counting
Hashavingsuperscriptone. Thisgives asimpleconsistency c heck onourequations. These
are equations for the kets |n(1)/an}backeti}ht,|n(2)/an}backeti}ht,...as well as the energy corrections E(1)
n,E(2)
n,....
Noteagain that doesnotenter intotheequations, andthusthekets andenerg ycorrections
areindependent.
The rst equation, corresponding to 0, is satised by construction. The second equa-
tion, corresponding to 1, should allow us to solve for the rst correction |n(1)/an}backeti}htto the state
and the rst correction E(1)
nto the energy. Once these are known, the equation corre-
sponding to 2involves only the unknowns |n(2)/an}backeti}htandE(2)
n, and should determine them. At
each stage each equation has only two unknowns: a state corre ction|n(k)/an}backeti}htand an energy
correctionE(k)
n.
A useful choice. We now claim that without loss of generality we can assume tha t all the
state corrections |nk/an}backeti}ht, withk1 contain no vector along |n(0)/an}backeti}ht. Explicitly:
0 =/an}backetle{tn(0)|n(1)/an}backeti}ht=/an}backetle{tn(0)|n(2)/an}backeti}ht=/an}backetle{tn(0)|n(3)/an}backeti}ht=... . (1.1.14)
To show this we explain how we can manipulate a solution that d oes not have this
property into one that does. Suppose you have solution in whi ch the state corrections |n(k)/an}backeti}ht
have components along |n(0)/an}backeti}ht:
|n(k)/an}backeti}ht=|n(k)/an}backeti}htak|n(0)/an}backeti}ht, k1, (1.1.15)
with some constants akand with |n(k)/an}backeti}htorthogonal to |n(0)/an}backeti}ht. Then the solution for the full</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
where
|n/an}backeti}ht=0=|n(0)/an}backeti}ht,andEn(= 0) =E(0)
n. (1.1.5)
As we said, the solution is assumed to take the form of a regula r power series expansion
in. To make this clear consider a function f() such that its derivatives to all orders exist
for= 0. In that case we have a Taylor expansion
f() =/summationdisplay
n=01
n!f(n)(0)n=f(0)+f(0)+1
2f(0)2+1
3!f(0)3+(1.1.6)
Theexpansionis apowerseries in , withcoecients f(0),f(0),etc, that are independent
and reect the value of the function and its derivatives at = 0.
For our problem we note the values of |n/an}backeti}htandEn() for= 0 (1.1.5) and write:
|n/an}backeti}ht=|n(0)/an}backeti}ht+|n(1)/an}backeti}ht+2|n(2)/an}backeti}ht+3|n(3)/an}backeti}ht+... ,
En() =E(0)
n+E(1)
n+2E(2)
n+3E(3)
n+...(1.1.7)
The superscripts on the states and energies denote the power ofthat accompanies them
in the above expressions. The above equations are a natural a ssumption; they state that
the perturbed states and energies, being functions of , admit a Taylor expansion around
= 0. Our aim is to calculate the states
|n(1)/an}backeti}ht,|n(2)/an}backeti}ht,|n(3)/an}backeti}ht,... (1.1.8)
and the energies
E(1)
n, E(2)
n, E(3)
n, ... (1.1.9)
Note that all these states and energies are, by denition, independent. Here |n(1)/an}backeti}htis the
leading correction to the state |n(0)/an}backeti}htas we turn on , andE(1)
nis the leading correction to
the energy as we turn on . We will notimpose the requirement that |n/an}backeti}htis normalized. It
suces that |n/an}backeti}htis normalizable, which it will be for suciently small pertu rbations. For
= 1 we would nd the solution for H(1) =H(0)+Hin the form
|n/an}backeti}ht  |n/an}backeti}ht1=|n(0)/an}backeti}ht+|n(1)/an}backeti}ht+|n(2)/an}backeti}ht+|n(3)/an}backeti}ht+... ,
EnEn(1) =E(0)
n+E(1)
n+E(2)
n+E(3)
n+...(1.1.10)
Substituting the ansatz (1.1.7) into the Schr odinger equa tion (1.1.4) we will nd the
conditions for such solution to exist:
/parenleftbig
H(0)+HEn()/parenrightbig
|n/an}backeti}ht= 0, (1.1.11)
which more explicitly takes the form
/parenleftBig
(H(0)E(0)
n)(E(1)
nH)2E(2)
n3E(3)
n...kE(k)
n+.../parenrightBig
/parenleftBig
|n(0)/an}backeti}ht+|n(1)/an}backeti}ht+2|n(2)/an}backeti}ht+3|n(3)/an}backeti}ht+...+k|n(k)/an}backeti}ht+.../parenrightBig
= 0.(1.1.12)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>12 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
z 0.9 1.2 1.5
f(z) 1.34536 1.56205 1.80278
f8(z) 1.33939 1.47946 1.20297
f14(z) 1.33939 1.67280 4.82288
f20(z) 1.34490 1.36568 -18.4895
f30(z) 1.34545 2.23047 641.772
Table 1.1:f(z)
1+z2=/summationtext
iciziandfn(z) =/summationtextn
i=0cizi.
1.1.2 Example: Anharmonic oscillator
Consider the simple harmonic oscillator
H(0)=p2
2m+1
2m2x2. (1.1.48)
We want to explore the eect of a perturbation proportional to x4. This has the eect
of changing the original quadratic potential for a more comp licated potential that includes
a quartic term. To do analysis in a clear way, we must consider units. Using the constants
/planckover2pi1,m,of the harmonic oscillator a length scale dcan be uniquely build:
d2=/planckover2pi1
m. (1.1.49)
The unit-free coordinate  x/dthen has a simple expression in terms of creation and annihi-
lation operators:
x=/radicalbigg
/planckover2pi1
2m(a+a) =d1
2(a+a)x
d=1
2(a+a). (1.1.50)
It follows that an  x4perturbation with units of energy takes the form
H=/planckover2pi1x4
d4=m23
/planckover2pi1x4=1
4/planckover2pi1(a+a)4. (1.1.51)
Using the unit-free parameter , the perturbed Hamiltonian will therefore be
H() =H(0)+m23
/planckover2pi1x4=H(0)+1
4/planckover2pi1(a+a)4. (1.1.52)
We will identify the states |k(0)/an}backeti}htofH(0)with the number eigenstates |k/an}backeti}ht,k= 0,1,...,of
the harmonic oscillator. Recall that
E(0)
k=/planckover2pi1(k+1
2),|k/an}backeti}ht=(a)k

k!|0/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.53)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>1.1. NONDEGENERATE PERTURBATION THEORY 13
The Hamiltonian H() denes an anharmonic oscillator. In a classical anharmoni c oscil-
lator the frequency of oscillation depends on the amplitude of oscillation. In the quantum
harmonic oscillator all levels are equally spaced. The freq uencies associated with transi-
tions between various levels are therefore integer multipl es (i.e.harmonics) of the basic
frequency associated to a transition between the rst excit ed state and the ground state.
In the quantum anharmonic oscillator the spacing between th e energy levels is not uniform.
First the simplest question: What is the rst-order correct ionE(1)
0to the energy of the
ground state? For this, following (1.1.21) we simply calcul ate the expectation value of the
perturbation on the ground state:
E(1)
0=/an}backetle{t0|1
4/planckover2pi1(a+a)4|0/an}backeti}ht=1
4/planckover2pi1/an}backetle{t0|(a+a)4|0/an}backeti}ht=3
4/planckover2pi1, (1.1.54)
where we used
/an}backetle{t0|(a+a)4|0/an}backeti}ht= 3, (1.1.55)
as you should verify. It follows that the corrected energy is
E0() =E(0)
0+E(1)
0+O(2) =1
2/planckover2pi1+3
4/planckover2pi1+O(2) =1
2/planckover2pi1/parenleftbig
1+3
2+O(2)/parenrightbig
(1.1.56)
We note that the energy of the ground state increases with &gt;0. This is reasonable as the
quartic term in the modied potential squeezes the ground st ate. How about second order
correction to the ground state energy? For this we use (1.1.3 6) takingn= 0:
E(2)
0=/summationdisplay
k/negationslash=0|Hk0|2
E(0)
kE(0)
0. (1.1.57)
The sum is over all k1 such that Hk0is non-vanishing. Here
Hk0=1
4/planckover2pi1/an}backetle{tk|(a+a)4|0/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.58)
We consider ( a+a)4|0/an}backeti}htwhich corresponds, up to constants to acting on the ground st ate
wavefunction 0withx4. This should give an even wavefunction. So ( a+ a)4|0/an}backeti}htmust
be a superposition of |0/an}backeti}ht,|2/an}backeti}ht, and|4/an}backeti}ht. We cannot get states with higher number because
there are at most four creation operators acting on the vacuu m. A short calculation (do
it!) conrms that
(a+a)4|0/an}backeti}ht= 3|0/an}backeti}ht+6
2|2/an}backeti}ht+
4!|4/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.59)
This immediately gives
H00=3
4/planckover2pi1, H 20=3
2
2/planckover2pi1, H 40=
6
2/planckover2pi1, (1.1.60)
the rst of which we had already determined and is not needed f or the second order com-
putation. Back in (1.1.57) we have
E(2)
0=|H20|2
2/planckover2pi1|H40|2
4/planckover2pi1=(/planckover2pi1)2
2/planckover2pi19
2(/planckover2pi1)2
4/planckover2pi13
2=/parenleftbig9
4+3
8/parenrightbig
/planckover2pi1=21
8/planckover2pi1.(1.1.61)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 1
Perturbation theory
c/ciclecoytB. Zwiebach
It is often the case that the Hamiltonian of a system diers sli ghtly from a Hamiltonian
that is well studied and completely understood. This is a sit uation where perturbation the-
ory can be useful. Perturbation theory allows us to make stat ements about the Hamiltonian
of the system using what we know about the well studied Hamilt onian.
The well studied Hamiltonian could be the that of the simple h armonic oscillator in one,
two, or three dimensions. In a diatomic molecule, for exampl e, the potential that controls
the vibrations is not exactly quadratic; it has extra terms t hat make the vibrations slightly
anharmonic. Inthatsituation theextratermsinthepotenti al represent perturbationsof the
Hamiltonian. The hydrogen atom Hamiltonian is also a well un derstood system. If we place
the atom inside a weak external magnetic eld or electric el d, the situation is described by
adding some small terms to the hydrogen Hamiltonian. Simila rly, the interaction between
the magnetic moments of the proton and the electron can be inc orporated by modifying the
original hydrogen atom Hamiltonian. The interaction betwe en two neutral hydrogen atoms
at a distance, leading to the van der Waals force can be studie d in perturbation theory by
thinking of the two atoms as electric dipoles.
The Hamiltonian of interest is written as the understood, or iginal Hamiltonian H(0),
plus a perturbation H:
H(0)+H. (1.0.1)
SinceH(0)is Hermitian and the sum must be a Hermitian Hamiltonian, the perturbation
operatorHmust also be Hermitian. It is convenient to introduce a unit- free constant
[0,1] and to consider, instead, a -dependent Hamiltonian H() that takes the form
H() =H(0)+H. (1.0.2)
When= 1 we have the Hamiltonian of interest, but allows us to consider a family of
Hamiltonians that interpolate from H(0), whenis equal to zero, to the Hamiltonian of
interest for equal to one. In many cases perturbations can be turned on and o; think,
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>1.2. DEGENERATE PERTURBATION THEORY 15
1.2.1 Degenerate toy model
Consider an example with two-by-two matrices. The unpertur bed matrix H(0)will be set
equal to the identity matrix:
H(0)=/parenleftbigg1 0
0 1/parenrightbigg
. (1.2.1)
We have a degeneracy here as the two eigenvalues are identica l (and equal to one). The
perturbation matrix His chosen to be o diagonal:
H=/parenleftbigg0 1
1 0/parenrightbigg
. (1.2.2)
We then have
H() =H(0)+H=/parenleftbigg1
1/parenrightbigg
. (1.2.3)
Using labels n= 1,2 the unperturbed eigenstates can be taken to be
|1(0)/an}backeti}ht=/parenleftbigg1
0/parenrightbigg
,|2(0)/an}backeti}ht=/parenleftbigg0
1/parenrightbigg
, E(0)
1=E(0)
2= 1, (1.2.4)
with the corresponding eigenvalues indicated as well. To r st order in , the eigenvalues
predicted from non-degenerate perturbation theory (1.1.3 7) areEn() =E(0)
n+Hnn.
This gives
E1() =E(0)
1+H11= 1+0 = 1 ?
E1() =E(0)
2+H22= 1+0 = 1 ?(1.2.5)
The eigenvalues are unperturbed to rst order in since the matrix His o-diagonal.
These answers, however, are wrong. We can compute the exact e igenvalues of H() and
they are 1 . There is also a problem with the state corrections. Equatio n (1.1.37) states
that
|n/an}backeti}ht=|n(0)/an}backeti}ht/summationdisplay
k/negationslash=nHkn
E(0)
kE(0)
n|k(0)/an}backeti}ht. (1.2.6)
but this time, with E(0)
1=E(0)
2the denominator is zero, and the Hmatrix element is also
zero, giving us an ambiguous result.
So what can we do? A direct calculation shows that
H() has eigenvectors1
2/parenleftbigg1
1/parenrightbigg
with eigenvalue = 1+ , (1.2.7)
and1
2/parenleftbigg1
1/parenrightbigg
with eigenvalue = 1 . (1.2.8)
You may think the eigenvectors jump from those of H(0)indicated in (1.2.4) to those of
H() as soon as becomes nonzero. Such discontinuity is totally against the spirit of</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>1.1. NONDEGENERATE PERTURBATION THEORY 11
In this simple example there is no need to use perturbation th eory since the eigenvalues,
E+andE, can be calculated exactly as functions of 
E() =1
2(E(0)
1+E(0)
2)1
2(E(0)
1E(0)
2)/radicaltp/radicalvertex/radicalvertex/radicalbt1+/bracketleftBigg
|V|
1
2(E(0)
1E(0)
2)/bracketrightBigg2
.(1.1.45)
The perturbative expansion of the energies is obtained by Ta ylor expansion of the square
Figure 1.3: The Taylor expansion of the function f(z) =
1+z2aboutz= 0 has a radius of
convergence equal to one.
root in powers of . To perform this expansion we need the result
f(z)/radicalbig
1+z2= 1+z2
2z4
8+z6
6+5
128z8+O(z10). (1.1.46)
The function f(z) exhibits branch cuts at z=i(see Figure 1.3), thus the expansion
off(z) aroundz= 0 has radius of convergence equal to one: the series converg es for|z|&lt;1
and diverges for |z|&gt;1. Table 1 shows f(z) evaluated for z= 0.9,1.2,and 1.5. The various
approximations to the full series are shown.
For our expansion of (1.1.45), convergence for |z|&lt;1 implies convergence when
|||V|
1
2|E(0)
1E(0)
2|&lt;1 = |V|&lt;1
2|E(0)
1E(0)
2|. (1.1.47)
For|V|&gt;1
2|E(0)
1E(0)
2|the perturbation series does not converge. We learn that for
convergence the perturbation must be small compared with energy dierences inH(0). It
is not sucient that the magnitude of the matrix elements of Hbe small compared to
those inH(0), energy dierences matter. This result leads us to expect com plications when
energy dierences go to zero and H(0)has degeneracies.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>24 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
This is an eigenvalue equation that tells us that the energy c orrectionsE(2)
nIare the eigen-
values ofM(2)and the vectors a(0)
Iare the associated normalized eigenvectors. These
determine, via (1.2.44), our orthonormal basis of good zero th order states. If His known,
the matrix M(2)is computable and Hermitian and can therefore be diagonaliz ed.
We will leave the computation of the component of |(1)
I/an}backeti}hton the degenerate subspace.
That can be done if the degeneracy is completely broken to qua dratic order (the eigenvalues
ofM(2)are all dierent). Still, it takes some eort and one must use th e order3equation.
Our results so far are
|I/an}backeti}ht=|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht+/parenleftBig/summationdisplay
p|p(0)/an}backeti}htHpI
E(0)
nE(0)
p+/summationdisplay
J/negationslash=I|(0)
J/an}backeti}hta(1)
I,J/parenrightBig
+O(2),
EIn() =E(0)
n+E(1)
n+2E(2)
In+3E(3)
In+...O(3).(1.2.63)
Here thea(1)
I,Jare still unknown coecients that determine the component o f the rst cor-
rection to the states along the degenerate subspace. If you f ollowed the discussion, all other
symbols in the above equations have been dened and are compu table given H.
The answer for the coecients a(1)
I,Jturns out to be
a(1)
I,J=1
E(2)
nIE(2)
nJ/bracketleftBigg/summationdisplay
p,qHJpHpqHqI
(E(0)
pE(0)
n)(E(0)
qE(0)
n)E(1)
n/summationdisplay
pHJpHpI/parenleftbig
E(0)
pE(0)
n/parenrightbig2/bracketrightBigg
.(1.2.64)
The third order corrections to the energy are
E(3)
In=/summationdisplay
p,qHIpHpqHqI
(E(0)
pE(0)
n)(E(0)
qE(0)
n)E(1)
n/summationdisplay
p|HpI|2
/parenleftbig
E(0)
pE(0)
n/parenrightbig2. (1.2.65)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>14 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
Therefor the corrected ground state energy to quadratic ord er is
E(0)
0+E(1)
0+2E(2)
0=1
2/planckover2pi1/parenleftbig
1+3
221
42/parenrightbig
. (1.1.62)
The computation can be carried to higher order, as rst done b y Bender and Wu (Phys.
Rev.184(1969)1231). They nd that1
E0() =1
2/planckover2pi1/parenleftbig
1+3
221
42+333
8330885
644+916731
128565518401
5126+O(7)/parenrightbig
(1.1.63)
As it turnsout thecoecients keep growingandtheseries doe snot converge forany nonzero
; the radius of convergence is actually zero! This does not me an the series is not useful.
It is an asymptotic expansion. This means that for a given sma ll value ofthe magnitude
of successive terms generally decrease until, at some point , they start growing again. A
good approximation to the desired answer is obtained by incl uding only the part of the sum
where the terms are decreasing.
Exercise 3. Calculate the rst order correction E(1)
nto the energy for the state |n/an}backeti}htof
numbern. Exhibit the anharmonicity of the oscillator by using this r esult to nd, to rst
order in, the energy separation  En() =En()En1() between levels.
Let us now nd the rst order correction to the ground-state w avefunction. Using
(1.1.34) with n= 0 we have
|0(1)/an}backeti}ht=/summationdisplay
k/negationslash=0Hk0
E(0)
kE(0)
0|k/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.64)
We then nd
|0(1)/an}backeti}ht=H20
2/planckover2pi1|2/an}backeti}htH40
4/planckover2pi1|4/an}backeti}ht=3
4
2|2/an}backeti}ht1
16
4!|4/an}backeti}ht
=3
4aa|0/an}backeti}ht1
16aaaa|0/an}backeti}ht.(1.1.65)
This means that to rst order the ground state of the perturbe d oscillator is
|0/an}backeti}ht=|0/an}backeti}ht/parenleftBig
3
4aa|0/an}backeti}ht+1
16aaaa|0/an}backeti}ht/parenrightBig
+O(2). (1.1.66)
1.2 Degenerate perturbation theory
If the spectrum of H(0)has degenerate states, as shown in Figure 1.1, tracking the e volution
of those states as becomes nonzero presents new challenges. We rst show that n aive
extrapolation of our results for a non-degenerate state do n ot work. We will also be able to
appreciate the basic diculty.
1Bender and Wus results, in eqns. (2.12) of their paper must a ll be multiplied by a factor of 2, as they
takeA0= 1/2.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>1.1. NONDEGENERATE PERTURBATION THEORY 7
Recalling our orthogonality assumption, we have /an}backetle{tn(0)|n(1)/an}backeti}ht= 0 and the term with E(1)
n
drops out. We get
E(2)
n=/an}backetle{tn(0)|H|n(1)/an}backeti}ht, (1.1.23)
which states that the second correction to the energy is dete rmined if we have the rst
correction |n(1)/an}backeti}htto the state. Note that this expression is not explicit enoug h to make it
manifest that E(2)
nis real. This and the earlier result for the rst correction t o the energy
have a simple generalization. Acting with /an}backetle{tn(0)|on the last equation of (1.1.13) we get
0 =/an}backetle{tn(0)|/parenleftBig
(E(1)
nH)|n(k1)/an}backeti}ht+E(2)
n|n(k2)/an}backeti}ht+...+E(k)
n|n(0)/an}backeti}ht/parenrightBig
.(1.1.24)
Using the orthogonality of |n(0)/an}backeti}htand all the state corrections, we have
0 =/an}backetle{tn(0)|H)|nk1/an}backeti}ht+E(k)
n, (1.1.25)
and therefore we have
E(k)
n=/an}backetle{tn(0)|H|n(k1)/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.26)
At any stage of the recursive solution, the energy at a xed or der is known if the state
correction is known to previous order. So it is time to calcul ate the corrections to the
states!
Let us solve for therstcorrection |n(1)/an}backeti}htto thestate. Thisstate must besomeparticular
superposition of the original energy eigenstates |k(0)/an}backeti}ht. For this we look at the equation
(H(0)E(0)
n)|n(1)/an}backeti}ht= (E(1)
nH)|n(0)/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.27)
This is a vector equation: the left-hand side vector set equa l to the right-hand side vector.
As in any vector equation, we can check it using a basis set of v ectors. Forming the inner
product of each and every basis vector with both the left-han d side and the right-hand side,
we must get equal numbers. We already acted on the above equat ion with /an}backetle{tn(0)|to gure
outE(1)
n. The remaining information in this equation can be obtained by acting with all
the states /an}backetle{tk(0)|withk/ne}ationslash=n:
/an}backetle{tk(0)|(H(0)E(0)
n)|n(1)/an}backeti}ht=/an}backetle{tk(0)|(E(1)
nH)|n(0)/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.28)
On the left-hand side we can let H(0)act on the bra. On the right-hand side we note that
withk/ne}ationslash=nthe term with E(1)
nvanishes
(E(0)
kE(0)
n)/an}backetle{tk(0)|n(1)/an}backeti}ht=/an}backetle{tk(0)|H|n(0)/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.29)
To simplify notation we dene the matrix elements of Hin the original basis
Hmn /an}backetle{tm(0)|H|n(0)/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.30)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>10 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
Figure 1.2: The second order corrections to the energy of the state |n(0)/an}backeti}htreceives negative contri-
butions from the higher energy states and positive contributions f rom the lower energy states. We
have, eectively, a repulsion preventing the state |n(0)/an}backeti}htfrom approaching the neighboring states.
Exercise 2. The state |n/an}backeti}htis not normalized. Use (1.1.37) to calculate to order 2the
quantityZn() dened by
1
Zn()/an}backetle{tn|n/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.42)
What is the probability that the state |n/an}backeti}htwill be observed to be along its unperturbed
version|n(0)/an}backeti}ht?
1.1.1 Validity of the perturbation expansion
We now return to a question we did not address: What do we mean w hen we say that
His small? We have said that Hmust be small compared to the original Hamiltonian
H(0), but it is not clear what this means, as both expressions are o perators. For some
insight into this matter consider an example where H(0)is a two-by-two diagonal matrix
with non-degenerate eigenvalues
H(0)=/parenleftBigg
E(0)
10
0E(0)
2/parenrightBigg
. (1.1.43)
The perturbation, called V, only has o-diagonal elements so that
H() =H(0)+V/parenleftBigg
E(0)
1V
VE(0)
2/parenrightBigg
. (1.1.44)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>1.2. DEGENERATE PERTURBATION THEORY 23
This gives the piece of |(1)
I/an}backeti}htinVin terms of the unknown zeroth order eigenstates.
We have now extracted all the information from the order equation. We look now
at the order 2equation, which contains the second order corrections to th e energy and
therefore should help us determine the zeroth order good sta tes. We hit that equation with
/an}backetle{tn(0);|and we get
0 =/an}backetle{tn(0);|(E(1)
nH)|(1)
I/an}backeti}ht/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingleV+/an}backetle{tn(0);|(E(1)
nH)|(1)
I/an}backeti}ht/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
VN+E(2)
nIa(0)
I.(1.2.55)
Happily, the second term, involving the components of |(1)
I/an}backeti}htalongVN, vanishes because
of the by now familiar property (1.2.28) adapted to this case . The piece with E(1)
non the
rst term also vanishes. We are thus left with
0 =/an}backetle{tn(0);|H|(1)
I/an}backeti}ht/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingleV+E(2)
nIa(0)
I. (1.2.56)
Introducing a resolution of the identity to the immediate ri ght ofH, only the basis states
inVcontribute and we get
0 =/summationdisplay
p/an}backetle{tn(0);|H|p(0)/an}backeti}ht/an}backetle{tp(0)|(1)
I/an}backeti}ht+E(2)
nIa(0)
I, (1.2.57)
where there is no need to copy the |Vanymore. Using the result in (1.2.54) we now get
0 =/summationdisplay
pHnl,p1
E(0)
pE(0)
nN/summationdisplay
k=1Hp,nka(0)
Ik+N/summationdisplay
k=1E(2)
nIka(0)
Ik(1.2.58)
Reordering sums and multiplying by minus one we get
N/summationdisplay
k=1/parenleftBigg
/summationdisplay
pHnl,pHp,nk
E(0)
pE(0)
nE(2)
nIk/parenrightBigg
a(0)
Ik= 0. (1.2.59)
To understand better this equation we dene the NNHermitian matrix M(2)
M(2)
,k /summationdisplay
pHn,pHp,nk
E(0)
pE(0)
n. (1.2.60)
The equation then becomes
N/summationdisplay
k=1/parenleftBig
M(2)
,kE(2)
nIk/parenrightBig
a(0)
Ik= 0. (1.2.61)
Recalling that the Kronecker delta is the matrix representa tion of the identity, we have
/parenleftBig
M(2)E(2)
nI1/parenrightBig
a(0)
I= 0. (1.2.62)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
corrected state is
|n/an}backeti}ht=|n(0)/an}backeti}ht+/parenleftbig
|n(1)/an}backeti}hta1|n(0)/an}backeti}ht/parenrightbig
+2/parenleftbig
|n(2)/an}backeti}hta2|n(0)/an}backeti}ht/parenrightbig
+...
=/parenleftbig
1a1a22.../parenrightbig
|n(0)/an}backeti}ht+|n(1)/an}backeti}ht+2|n(2)/an}backeti}ht+...(1.1.16)
Since this is an eigenstate of the Hamiltonian H(), it will still be an eigenstate if we change
its normalization by dividing it by any function of . Dividing by the coecient of |n(0)/an}backeti}ht
we have the physically identical solution |n/an}backeti}ht
given by
|n/an}backeti}ht
=|n(0)/an}backeti}ht+1/parenleftbig
1a1a22.../parenrightbig/bracketleftbig
|n(1)/an}backeti}ht+2|n(2)/an}backeti}ht+.../bracketrightbig
(1.1.17)
We can expand the denominator so that we get
|n/an}backeti}ht
=|n(0)/an}backeti}ht+|n(1)/an}backeti}ht+2/parenleftbig
|n(2)/an}backeti}ht+a1|n(1)/an}backeti}ht/parenrightbig
+... (1.1.18)
The explicit expressions do not matter, the key point, actua lly visible in (1.1.17), is that
we have a physically identical solution of the same equation in which the state corrections
are all orthogonal to |n(0)/an}backeti}ht. This shows that we can impose the conditions (1.1.14) witho ut
loss of generality.
Solving the equations. Let us nally begin solving equations (1.1.13). For this we n ote
that the Schrodinger equation for the ket |n(0)/an}backeti}htimplies that for the bra we have
/an}backetle{tn(0)|(H(0)E(0)
n) = 0. (1.1.19)
This means that acting with /an}backetle{tn(0)|on the left-hand side of any of the equations in (1.1.13)
will give zero. Consistency requires that acting with /an}backetle{tn(0)|on the right-hand side of any of
the equations in (1.1.13) also give zero, and presumably som e interesting information. For
the-equation this gives:
0 =/an}backetle{tn(0)|(E(1)
nH)|n(0)/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.20)
Since|n(0)/an}backeti}htis normalized and E(1)
nis a number, this means that
E(1)
n=/an}backetle{tn(0)|H|n(0)/an}backeti}ht. (1.1.21)
This is the most famous result in perturbation theory: the rst correction to the en ergy of
an energy eigenstate is simply the expectation value of the c orrection to the Hamiltonian
in theuncorrected state. You need not know the correction to the state to determ ine the
rst correction to the energy! Note that the hermicity of Himplies the required reality of
the energy correction.
We can actually ndsomeinteresting formulae (but not yet fu lly explicit!) forthehigher
energy corrections. For the 2equation, acting with /an}backetle{tn(0)|on the right-hand side gives
0 =/an}backetle{tn(0)|/parenleftBig
(E(1)
nH)|n(1)/an}backeti}ht+E(2)
n|n(0)/an}backeti}ht/parenrightBig
. (1.1.22)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>22 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
Note that in the energy expansion we have accounted for the de generacy to zeroth and rst
order: the index Irst appears in the second-order corrections to the energy. Using the
Schr odinger equation
H()|I/an}backeti}ht=EnI()|I/an}backeti}ht, (1.2.47)
gives the by now familiar equations, of which we list the rst four:
0: (H(0)E(0)
n)|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht= 0,
1: (H(0)E(0)
n)|(1)
I/an}backeti}ht= (E(1)
nH)|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht,
2: (H(0)E(0)
n)|(2)
I/an}backeti}ht= (E(1)
nH)|(1)
I/an}backeti}ht+E(2)
nI|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht,
3: (H(0)E(0)
n)|(3)
I/an}backeti}ht= (E(1)
nH)|(2)
I/an}backeti}ht+E(2)
nI|(1)
I/an}backeti}ht+E(3)
nI|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht.(1.2.48)
The zero-th order equation is trivially satised. For the or derequation the overlap with
/an}backetle{tn(0);|works out automatically, without giving any new informatio n. Indeed, the left-hand
side vanishes and we thus get
0 =/an}backetle{tn(0);|(E(1)
nH)|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht. (1.2.49)
Since/an}backetle{tn(0);|is aHeigenstate with eigenvalue E(1)
n, up to a vector in V(see (1.2.34)),
the above right-hand side vanishes. Acting on the order equation with /an}backetle{tp(0)|gives useful
information:
(E(0)
pE(0)
n)/an}backetle{tp(0)|(1)
I/an}backeti}ht=/an}backetle{tp(0)|(E(1)
nH)|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht=/an}backetle{tp(0)|H|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht,(1.2.50)
using the orthogonality of VandVN. Letting
HpI /an}backetle{tp(0)|H|(0)
I/an}backeti}ht, (1.2.51)
we then have
/an}backetle{tp(0)|(1)
I/an}backeti}ht=HpI
E(0)
pE(0)
n. (1.2.52)
Since the ket |(0)
I/an}backeti}htis still undetermined, it makes sense to write this informat ion about
|(1)
I/an}backeti}htin terms of the unknown a(0)
Icoecients. We have
HpIN/summationdisplay
k=1/an}backetle{tp(0)|H|n(0);k/an}backeti}hta(0)
Ik=N/summationdisplay
k=1Hp,nka(0)
Ik, (1.2.53)
Back into (1.2.52) we get
/an}backetle{tp(0)|(1)
I/an}backeti}ht=1
E(0)
pE(0)
nN/summationdisplay
k=1Hp,nka(0)
Ik. (1.2.54)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>1.1. NONDEGENERATE PERTURBATION THEORY 9
Remarks:
1. The rst order corrected energy of the (non-degenerate) g round state overstates the
true exact ground state energy. To see this consider the rst order corrected ground
state energy E(0)
0+E(1)
0. Writing this in terms of expectation values, with |0(0)/an}backeti}ht
denoting the unperturbed ground state, we have
E(0)
0+E(1)
0=/an}backetle{t0(0)|H(0)|0(0)/an}backeti}ht+/an}backetle{t0(0)|H|0(0)/an}backeti}ht
=/an}backetle{t0(0)|(H(0)+H)|0(0)/an}backeti}ht
=/an}backetle{t0(0)|H()|0(0)/an}backeti}ht.(1.1.38)
By the variational principle, the expectation value of the H amiltonian on an arbitrary
(normalized) state is larger than the ground state energy E0(), therefore
E(0)
0+E(1)
0=/an}backetle{t0(0)|H()|0(0)/an}backeti}ht E0(), (1.1.39)
which is what we wanted to prove. Given this overestimate at  rst order, the second
order correction to the ground state energy is always negati ve. Indeed,
2/summationdisplay
k/negationslash=0|Hk0|2
E(0)
kE(0)
0, (1.1.40)
and each term is negative because the unperturbedexcited st ate energies E(0)
k(k/ne}ationslash= 0)
exceed the unperturbed ground state energy E(0)
0.
2. The second order correction to the energy of the |n(0)/an}backeti}hteigenstate exhibits level repul-
sion: the levels with k &gt; npush the state down and the levels with k &lt; npush the
state up. Indeed,
2/summationdisplay
k/negationslash=n|Hkn|2
E(0)
kE(0)
n=2/summationdisplay
k&gt;n|Hkn|2
E(0)
kE(0)
n+2/summationdisplay
k&lt;n|Hkn|2
E(0)
nE(0)
k.(1.1.41)
The rst term gives the negative contribution from the highe r energy states and the
second term gives the contribution from the lower energy sta tes (see Figure 1.2).
The systematics of solving the equations is now apparent. Fo r each equation we take
inner products with all states in the state space. That gives the full content of the equation.
We rst take the inner product with /an}backetle{tn(0)|, as this makes the left-hand side equal to zero
and is thus simpler. Then we take the inner product with /an}backetle{tk(0)|with allk/ne}ationslash=nand that
gives the remainder of the information that is contained in t he equation.
Exercise 1. Calculate |n(2)/an}backeti}htandE(3)
n.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>1.1. NONDEGENERATE PERTURBATION THEORY 3
two levels, and that happens generically. In the gure, the p erturbation splits the levels to
rst order in , as shown by the dierent slopes of the two curves that meet at = 0. In
other words, viewed as power series in the energies of the two states have dierent linear
terms in. The last level shown corresponds to four degenerate states . The perturbation
to rst order in splits the states into a group of three states and a fourth. To second order
inthe three states split further. A single Hamiltonian can exh ibit behavior like this, with
many possible variations.
To analyze the evolution of states and energies as functions ofwe have two possible
cases: (i) we are following a non-degenerate state or, ( ii) we are following a collection of
degenerate states. The challenges are quite dierent and the refore we must analyze them
separately. Clearly both situations can occur for a single H amiltonian, depending on the
spectrum of H(0). To follow a non-degenerate state we use non-degenerate perturbation
theory. To follow a set of degenerate states we use degenerate perturbation theory . Since
Hamiltonians H(0)generally have both non-degenerate and degenerate states w e need to
consider both types of perturbation theory. We begin with no n-degenerate perturbation
theory.
1.1 Nondegenerate perturbation theory
We begin by describing the original Hamiltonian H(0). We assume this Hamiltonian has a
discrete spectrum with an orthonormal basis |k(0)/an}backeti}htof energy eigenstates, where kZis a
label that ranges over a possibly innite set of values:
H(0)|k(0)/an}backeti}ht=E(0)
k|k(0)/an}backeti}ht,/an}backetle{tk(0)|l(0)/an}backeti}ht=kl. (1.1.1)
We will let k= 0 denote the ground state and we order the states so that the e nergies
generally increase as the value of the label increases, so th at
E(0)
0E(0)
1E(0)
2E(0)
3... (1.1.2)
The equal signs are needed because some states may be degener ate.
In this section we focus on a non-degenerate state |n(0)/an}backeti}htwith xedn. This means that
|n(0)/an}backeti}htis a single state that is separated by some nite energy from a ll the states with more
energy and from all the states with less energy. In other word s the following must be part
of the sequence of inequalities in (1.1.2)
...E(0)
n1&lt; E(0)
n&lt; E(0)
n+1... (1.1.3)
If the chosen state is the ground state, we have instead E(0)
0&lt; E(0)
1.
As the perturbation is turned on by making dierent from zero, the energy eigenstate
|n(0)/an}backeti}htofH(0)will evolve into some energy eigenstate |n/an}backeti}htofH() with energy En():
H()|n/an}backeti}ht=En()|n/an}backeti}ht, (1.1.4)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
Note that the Hermiticity of Himplies that
Hnm= (Hmn). (1.1.31)
With this notation, equation (1.1.29) gives
/an}backetle{tk(0)|n(1)/an}backeti}ht=Hkn
E(0)
kE(0)
n, k/ne}ationslash=n. (1.1.32)
Since we now know the overlap of |n(1)/an}backeti}htwith all basis states, this means that the state has
been determined. Indeed we can use the completeness of the ba sis to write
|n(1)/an}backeti}ht=/summationdisplay
k|k(0)/an}backeti}ht/an}backetle{tk(0)|n(1)/an}backeti}ht=/summationdisplay
k/negationslash=n|k(0)/an}backeti}ht/an}backetle{tk(0)|n(1)/an}backeti}ht, (1.1.33)
since the term with k=ndoes not contribute because of the orthogonality assumptio n.
Using the overlaps (1.1.32) we now get
|n(1)/an}backeti}ht=/summationdisplay
k/negationslash=n|k(0)/an}backeti}htHkn
E(0)
kE(0)
n. (1.1.34)
This shows that the rstcorrection |n(1)/an}backeti}htcan have components along all basis states, except
|n(0)/an}backeti}ht. The component along a state |k(0)/an}backeti}htvanishes if the perturbation Hdoes not couple
|n(0)/an}backeti}htto|k(0)/an}backeti}ht, namely, if Hknvanishes. Note that the assumption of non-degeneracy is
needed here. We are summing over all states |k(0)/an}backeti}htthat are not |n(0)/an}backeti}htand if any such state
has the same H(0)energy as |n(0)/an}backeti}htthe energy denominator will vanish causing trouble!
Now that we have the rst order correction to the states we can compute the second
ordercorrection to the energy. Using (1.1.23) we have
E(2)
n=/an}backetle{tn(0)|H|n(1)/an}backeti}ht=/summationdisplay
k/negationslash=n/an}backetle{tn(0)|H|k(0)/an}backeti}htHkn
E(0)
kE(0)
n. (1.1.35)
In the last numerator we have /an}backetle{tn(0)|H|k(0)/an}backeti}ht=Hnk= (Hkn)and therefore
E(2)
n=/summationdisplay
k/negationslash=n|Hkn|2
E(0)
kE(0)
n. (1.1.36)
This is the second-order energy correction. This explicit f ormula makes the reality of E(2)
n
manifest.
In summary, going back to (1.1.7), we have that the states and energies for H() =
H(0)+Hare, to this order,
|n/an}backeti}ht=|n(0)/an}backeti}ht/summationdisplay
k/negationslash=nHkn
E(0)
kE(0)
n|k(0)/an}backeti}ht+O(2),
En() =E(0)
n+Hnn2/summationdisplay
k/negationslash=n|Hkn|2
E(0)
kE(0)
n+O(3),(1.1.37)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>18 CHAPTER 1. TIME INDEPENDENT PERTURBATION THEORY
Step 1.Recalling that /an}backetle{tn(0);|(H(0)E(0)
n) = 0, as we hit the O() equation with /an}backetle{tn(0);|
the left-hand side vanishes and we nd
/an}backetle{tn(0);|(E(1)
n,kH)|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht= 0. (1.2.23)
Since the basis states in VNare orthonormal, this implies that
/an}backetle{tn(0);|H|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht=E(1)
n,k,k. (1.2.24)
This equation holds for all k,= 1,...,N. Remarkably, this equation is telling us that the
basis|n(0);k/an}backeti}htmust be chosen to make the matrix Hdiagonal in the subspace VN! This
is required in order to get the perturbation theory going. Se ttingequal tokwe read the
values of the rst order energy shifts
E(1)
n,k=/an}backetle{tn(0);k|H|n(0);k/an}backeti}ht=Hnk,nk, (1.2.25)
where the last equality is a denition. The energies to rst o rder are then
En,k() =E(0)
n+Hnk,nk. (1.2.26)
A few remarks:
1. The above result for the rst order energy shifts is true always, even if the degeneracy
is not lifted. The degeneracy is lifted when
E(1)
n,k/ne}ationslash=E(1)
n,,wheneverk/ne}ationslash=, (1.2.27)
for all values of k,= 1,...,N. This assumption will be used in the later steps. If
the degeneracy is lifted, the basis states |n(0);k/an}backeti}htthat make Hdiagonal in VNare
called good states or a good basis. This means that they a re the basis states in
VNthat get deformed continuously as becomes non-zero. If the degeneracy is not
lifted to rst order the determination of the good basis has t o be attempted to second
order.
2. The perturbation His diagonalized in the subspace VN. The perturbation His
notdiagonal on the whole space H, only within the block representing VNisHa
diagonal matrix. Alternatively we can see this via theactio n ofHon the basis states.
Introducing a resolution of the identity, we have
H|n(0);/an}backeti}ht=/summationdisplay
q|n(0);q/an}backeti}ht/an}backetle{tn(0);q|H|n(0);/an}backeti}ht+/summationdisplay
p|p(0)/an}backeti}ht/an}backetle{tp(0)|H|n(0);/an}backeti}ht
=/summationdisplay
qE(1)
n,,q|n(0);q/an}backeti}ht+/summationdisplay
p|p(0)/an}backeti}ht/an}backetle{tp(0)|H|n(0);/an}backeti}ht
=E(1)
n,|n(0);/an}backeti}ht+/summationdisplay
p|p(0)/an}backeti}ht/an}backetle{tp(0)|H|n(0);/an}backeti}ht.(1.2.28)
This shows that the states |n(0);/an}backeti}htarealmostHeigenstates with eigenvalues equal
to the rst order energy corrections. The failure is an extra state along V.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch7</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare  
https://ocw.mit.edu 
8.06 Quantum Physics III 
Spring 2018  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch6</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>This is a dierent Hamiltonian each time we change the positions R of the nuclei. The associated 
Schr odinger equation for the electrons is 
" # n~2 X 2 (i) (i) r + VeN (R, r)+ Vee(r) (r)= E(i)(R)(r) . (6.10)ri R e R2m i=1 
The wavefunction for the electrons, as expected, is a function of the position of the electrons r, which 
appears as the argument of the wavefunction. Since the wavefunction depends on the nuclear positions, 
this dependence is included as a subscript. Finally, the superscript i labels the various wavefunctions 
(i)that may appear as solutions of this equation. The associated energies Ee (R) depend on the nuclear 
(i)positions and the label i. If we calculated all the R (r) we would have a full basis of electronic 
congurations and we could write an ansatz for the full wavefunction of the molecule: 
X 
(R, r)= (i)(R)(i)(r) , (6.11)R 
i 
where the (i) are the unknowns. Substitution into the full Schr odinger equation 
H(R, r)= E(R, r) , (6.12) 
gives an innite set of coupled dierential equations for (i)(R). This is too dicult, so we try to 
make do with a single term: 
(R, r)= (R) R(r) , (6.13) 
where we would generally use for R(r) the ground state wavefunction for the electrons in the frozen 
nuclear potential. If we have this wavefunction for all R, as we now assume, we also know the value 
Ee(R) of the associated energy. 
We will do a variational analysis. For this we will compute the expectation value h|H|i using 
(R, r)= (R)R(r). We will then utilize the known R(r) to integrate the electronic dependence in 
the expectation value 
Z Z 
hHi = d Rdr   (R, r)H (R, r)= dRdr   (R)R (r)H (R)R(r) 
(6.14) Z 
= d R   (R)He (R) , 
thus discovering the eective Hamiltonian He for the nuclear degrees of freedom. We begin the 
calculation by rewriting the original Hamiltonian: 
NX P2 
H = HN + He , HN = + VNN (R) . (6.15)2M=1 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>Since hHei' Ee(R) the full potential is 
Ee(R)+ VNN (R) 
 (6.41)| {z }
2e
R 
Experimentally we have R =1.06= 2.8 eV. A and E 
Ansatz is not very accurate, for small R wavefunction becomes ground state of Hydrogen atom not 
ground state of Helium, as it should. 
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 6: Adiabatic approximation 
B. Zwiebach 
June 2, 2017 
Contents 
1 Introduction 1 
1.1 AdiabaticapproximationinClassicalMechanics . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1 
1.2 Quantummechanicssystems . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4 
2 Adiabatic Evolution 5 
3 Systematic approach 7 
4 Landau-Zener transitions 9 
5 Berrys phase 12 
6 Molecules and Born-Oppenheimer 15 
6.1 Born-Oppenheimerapproximation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 16 
6.2 Followingthedirectroute . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 19 
6.3 The H2+ ion. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 20 
1 Introduction 
1.1 Adiabatic approximation in Classical Mechanics 
Lets go back to classical mechanics, with a harmonic oscillator performing motion but with (t) not 
constant. The hamiltonian of the system would be 
2p1 2H(x, p, (t))= + m2(t)x (1.1)2m 2 
where x and p are going to be functions of time. 
In general 
dH H H H = x+ p+ . (1.2)dt x p t 
Hamiltons equation of motion read 
H H =  =   (1.3) x , p . p x 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>The restoring force is determined by k, and it is due to the electron system, with no reference to the 
mass M. Since k has units of energy over length-square, we must have 
~2Energyk =  . (6.3)4 L2 ma
But k = M2, with  the frequency of nuclear oscillations so we have 
r ~2 ~2 ~2 
2  m m M2    ~  . (6.4)4 2 4 2 ma M m a M ma
We thus nd that the nuclear vibrational energies are 
r m Evibration  Eelectron . (6.5)M 
There are also rotations and their energy Erot is even smaller, as they involve essentially no distortion 
of the molecule 
L2 ~2`(` + 1) m ~ m Erot = '  2 = (6.6) Erotation ' Eelectron2I Ma2 M ma M 
Therefore we have the following hierarchy of energies 
r m m Eelectron : Evibration : Erotation = 1 : : . (6.7)M M 
6.1 Born-Oppenheimer approximation 
Consider a molecule with N nuclei and n electrons. The Hamiltonian takes the form 
N nX P2 X 2pH =  + VNN (R)+ i + VeN (R, r)+ Vee(r) , (6.8)2M 2m =1 i=1 
where M with  =1, . . . , N are the nuclear masses and 
P, R : nuclei canonical variables VNN : nuclei-nuclei interaction 
pi, ri : electron canonical variables Vee : electron-electron interaction 
R  (R1, . . . , RN ) VeN : electron-nuclei interaction 
r  (r1, . . . , rn) 
The wavefunction (R, r) for the molecule is, in position space, a function of all the nuclear positions 
and all the electron positions. 
In the limit when M/m  the nuclear skeleton may be considered xed, making the positions 
R are xed. The electrons then move under the eect of the nuclear potential VeN (R, r) with xed R, 
and the electron-electron Coulomb repulsion. The relevant Hamiltonian He for the electrons is then 
nX p2 
He(p, r; R)= i + VeN (R, r)+ Vee(r) . (6.9)2m i=1 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
https://ocw.mit.edu 
8.06 Quantum Physics III 
Spring 2018 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch4</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>38</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare  
https://ocw.mit.edu 
8.06 Quantum Physics III 
Spring 2018  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch2</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-06-quantum-physics-iii-spring-2018/resources/mit8_06s18ch2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>28 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
2. For each xed value of , the states have increasing Nas we move up in energy. The
numberNis the number of nodes in the solution of the radial equation, thats why
it is the degree of the polynomial in rthat features in the wavefunction (2.1.11).
3. The analysis of H(0)so far ignored electron spin. Since the electron is a spin one -
half particle there is an extra degeneracy: each of the H(0)eigenstates is really two
degenerate states, one with the electron spin up and the othe r with the electron spin
down. These states are degenerate because H(0)has no spin dependence.
4. We will have to supplement H(0)with terms that correspond to corrections that arise
from relativity and from the spin of the electron. This will b e the main subject of
the following analysis. It will determine the ne-structure of the hydrogen atom. The
corrections will break much of the degeneracy of the spectru m.
5. In order to understand better the spectrum and the propert ies of the Hydrogen atom
one can apply an electric eld, leading to the Starkeect or a magnetic eld, leading
to theZeeman eect. These external elds are represented by extra terms in the
hydrogen atom Hamiltonian.
Let us now discuss two dierent choices of basis states for the hydrogen atom, both of
which include the electron spin properly.
Recall that, in general, for a multiplet of angular momentum j, we have states ( j,mj),
withmjrunning from jtojin integer steps. All states in the multiplet are J2eigenstates
with eigenvalue /planckover2pi12j(j+1) and, for each state, /planckover2pi1mjis the eigenvalue of Jz.
Because the electron has spin one half, its states are labele d as
(s,ms),withs=1
2, ms=1
2. (2.1.13)
In the hydrogen atom the angular momentum can take dierent values, but the spin of
the electron is always one-half. As a result, the label sis often omitted, and we usually only
record the value of ms. For hydrogen basis states we thus have quantum numbers n,,m ,
andms. To avoid confusion, we have added the subscript to m, thus emphasizing that
this is the azimuthal quantum number for orbital angular mom entum. Since we are not
combiningtheelectronspintoitsorbitalangularmomentum , thestatesformtheuncoupled
basis:
Uncoupled basis quantum numbers: ( n,,m ,ms). (2.1.14)
The states are completely specied by these quantum numbers . As we let those quantum
numbers run over all possible values we obtain an orthonorma l basis of states.
It is often useful to use an alternative basis where the state s are eigenstates of J2andJz,
where the total angular momentum Jis obtained by adding the orbital angular momentum
Lto the spin angular momentum S:
J=L+S. (2.1.15)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>38 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
To evaluate (2.4.31), we rst do a Taylor expansion of the pot ential that enters the integral
about the point u= 0:
V(r+u) =V(r)+/summationdisplay
iiV/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
rui+1
2/summationdisplay
i,jijV/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
ruiuj+... (2.4.30)
All derivatives here are evaluated at the center of the elect ron. Plugging back into the
integral (2.4.31) and dropping the subscript electron we have
/tildewideV(r) =/integraldisplay
d3u0(u)/parenleftBig
V(r)+/summationdisplay
iiV/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
rui+1
2/summationdisplay
i,jijV/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
ruiuj+.../parenrightBig
.(2.4.31)
Allrdependent functions can be taken out of the integrals. Recal ling that the integral of
0over volume is one, we get
V(r) =V(r) +/summationdisplay
iiV/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
r/integraldisplay
d3u0(u)i+1
2/summationdisplay
i,jijV/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
r/integraldisplay
d3u0(u)uiuj+...(2.4.32)
Due to spherical symmetry the rst integral vanishes and the second takes the form
/integraldisplay
d3u0(u)uiuj=1
3ij/integraldisplay
d3u0(u)u2. (2.4.33)
Indeed the integral must vanish for i/ne}ationslash=jand must take equal values for i=j= 1,2,3.
Sinceu2=u2
1+u2
2+u2
3, the result follows. Using this we get
V(r) =V(r) +1
2/summationdisplay
iiiV/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
r1
3/integraldisplay
d3uf(u)2+...
=V(r) +1
62V/integraldisplay
d3u0(u)u2+... .(2.4.34)
The second term represents the correction Vto the potential energy:
V=1
62V/integraldisplay
d3u0(u)u2. (2.4.35)
To get an estimate, let us assume that the charge is distribut ed uniformly over a sphere of
radiusu0. This means that 0(u) is a constant for u&lt;u0
0(u) =3
4u3
0

1, u&lt;u 0,
0, u&gt;u 0.(2.4.36)
The integral one must evaluate then gives
/integraldisplay
d3u0(u)u2=/integraldisplayu0
04u2duu2
4
3u3
0=3
u3
0/integraldisplayu0
0u4du=3
5u2
0. (2.4.37)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>42 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
Working out the constants in terms of E(0)
nand rest energies we get
E(1)
njmj;spin-orbit=(E(0)
n)2
mc2n/bracketleftbig
j(j+1)(+1)3
4/bracketrightbig
/parenleftbig
+1
2/parenrightbig
(+1), /ne}ationslash= 0. (2.4.56)
SinceLvanishes identically acting on any = 0 state, it is physically reasonable, as we will
do, to assume that the spin-orbit correction vanishes for = 0 states. On the other hand
the limit of the above formula as 0, while somewhat ambiguous, is nonzero. We set
j=+1
2(the other possibility j=1
2does not apply for = 0) and then take the limit
as0. Indeed,
E(1)
njmj;spin-orbit/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
j=+1
2=(E(0)
n)2
mc2n/bracketleftbig
(+1
2)(+3
2)(+1)3
4/bracketrightbig
/parenleftbig
+1
2/parenrightbig
(+1)
=(E(0)
n)2
mc2n/parenleftbig
+1
2/parenrightbig
(+1),(2.4.57)
and now taking the limit:
lim
0E(1)
njmj;spin-orbit/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
j=+1
2=(E(0)
n)2
mc2(2n) =4mc21
2n3. (2.4.58)
We see that this limit is in fact identical to the Darwin shift (2.4.24) of the nSstates. This
is a bit surprising and will play a technical role below.
2.4.4 Combining results
For/ne}ationslash= 0 states we can add the energy shifts from spin-orbit and fro m the relativistic
correction, both of them expressed as expectation values in the coupled basis. The result,
thereforewillgivetheshiftsofthecoupledstates. Collec ting ourresults(2.4.46) and(2.4.56)
we have
/angbracketleftBig
njmj/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingleHrel+Hspin-orbit/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsinglenjmj/angbracketrightBig
=(E(0)
n)2
2mc2/braceleftBigg
34n/parenleftbig
+1
2/parenrightbig+2n/bracketleftbig
j(j+1)(+1)3
4/bracketrightbig
/parenleftbig
+1
2/parenrightbig
(+1)/bracerightBigg
=(E(0)
n)2
2mc2/braceleftBigg
3+2n/bracketleftBigg
j(j+1)3(+1)3
4
/parenleftbig
+1
2/parenrightbig
(+1)/bracketrightBigg/bracerightBigg
.(2.4.59)
These are the ne structure energy shifts for all states in th e spectrum of hydrogen. The
states in a coupled multiplet are characterized by ,jandmjand each multiplet as a whole
is shifted according to the above formula. The degeneracy wi thin the multiplet is unbroken
because the formula has no mjdependence. This formula, as written, hides some additiona l
degeneracies. We uncover those next.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 2
Fine Structure
c/ciclecoytB. Zwiebach
2.1 Review of hydrogen atom
The hydrogen atom Hamiltonian is by now familiar to you. You h ave found the bound state
spectrum in more than one way and learned about the large dege neracy that exists for all
states except the ground state. We will call the hydrogen ato m Hamiltonian H(0)and it is
given by
H(0)=p2
2me2
r. (2.1.1)
We take this to be the known Hamiltonian, meaning that we kn ow its spectrum. This
Hamiltonian is supplemented with corrections that can be st udied in perturbation theory.
That study is the subject of this chapter. We begin, however, with some review and
comments.
The massminH(0)is the reduced mass of the electron and proton, which we can
accurately set equal to the mass of the electron. If one wishe s to consider the case of an an
electron bound to a nucleus with Zprotons one lets e2Ze2inH(0). The Bohr radius is
the length scale build from /planckover2pi1,m, ande2
a0/planckover2pi12
me253pm. (2.1.2)
The energy levels are enumerated using a principal quantum number n, an integer that
must be greater or equal to one:
En=e2
2a01
n2, n= 1,2,... . (2.1.3)
Note thatH(0)is a non-relativistic Hamiltonian: the speed of light does n ot enter in it,
and the kinetic term is that of Newtonian mechanics. The ener gy scale relevant to the
25</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>26</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare  
https://ocw.mit.edu 
8.06 Quantum Physics III 
Spring 2018  
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>2.4. FINE STRUCTURE OF HYDROGEN 35
The rst correction is the relativistic energy correction a nticipated earlier. The second is
the spin-orbit coupling, and the third is the Darwincorrection, that as we shall see aects
only= 0 states.
Recall that the energy scale for H(0)eigenstates is 2mc2. We will now see that all the
above energy corrections are of order 4mc2thus smaller by a factor of 21
19000than the
zeroth-order energies. This suggests that for the hydrogen atom, the role of the unit-free
parameterof perturbation theory is taken by the ne structure constan t:2. Of
course, in reality we cannot adjust the value of 2nor we can take it to zero.
For the relativistic correction, recalling that pmc, we indeed have
Hrel.=p4
8m3c2 4mc2. (2.3.15)
For spin-orbit we rst rewrite the term, using
1
rdV
dr=1
rd
dr/parenleftbigg
e2
r/parenrightbigg
=e2
r3, (2.3.16)
so that
Hspin-orbit =e2
2m2c21
r3SL. (2.3.17)
For an estimate we set SL/planckover2pi12,ra0, and recall that a0=/planckover2pi1
mc1
:
Hspin-orbit e2
m2c2/planckover2pi12
a3
0=/planckover2pi1c
m2c2/planckover2pi12
a3
0=/parenleftBig/planckover2pi1
mca0/parenrightBig3
mc2=4mc2. (2.3.18)
We can evaluate the Darwin term using V=e2/r:
HDarwin=e2/planckover2pi12
8m2c22/parenleftbigg1
r/parenrightbigg
=e2/planckover2pi12
8m2c2(4(r)) =
2e2/planckover2pi12
m2c2(r). (2.3.19)
To estimate this correction note that, due to the function the the integral in the expecta-
tion value will introduce a factor |(0)|2a3
0. We will therefore have
HDarwine2/planckover2pi12
m2c2a3
04mc2, (2.3.20)
as this is exactly the same combination of constants that we h ad for spin orbit above.
2.4 Fine structure of hydrogen
The ne structure of hydrogen is the spectrum of the atom once one takes into account the
corrections indicated in (2.3.14). After the partial simpl ications considered above we have
H=p2
2m+V
/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
H(0)p4
8m3c2/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
Hrel.+e2
2m2c2SL
r3/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
Hspin-orbit+
2e2/planckover2pi12
m2c2(r)
/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
HDarwin. (2.4.21)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>40 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
The problem has been reduced to the computation of the expect ation value of V(r) and
V2(r) in thenmstate. The expectation value of V(r) is obtained from the virial theorem
that states that /an}backetle{tV/an}backeti}ht= 2E(0)
n. ForV2(r) we have
/an}backetle{tV2/an}backeti}ht=e4/angbracketleftBig1
r2/angbracketrightBig
=e41
a2
0n3/parenleftbig
+1
2/parenrightbig=/parenleftbigge2
2a01
n2/parenrightbigg24n
+1
2= (E(0)
n)24n
+1
2.(2.4.45)
Back into (2.4.44) we nd
E(1)
n,mms;rel=(E(0)
n)2
2mc2/bracketleftBig4n
+1
23/bracketrightBig
=1
84(mc2)
n4/bracketleftBig4n
+1
23/bracketrightBig
.(2.4.46)
The complete degeneracy of multiplets for a given nhas been broken. That degeneracy
ofH(0)was explained by the conserved Runge-Lenz vector. It is clea r that the relativistic
correction has broken that symmetry.
We have computed the above correction using the uncoupled ba sis
E(1)
n,mms;rel=/an}backetle{tnmm s|Hrel|nmm s/an}backeti}ht=f(n,). (2.4.47)
Here we added the extra equality to emphasize that the matrix elements depend only on n
and. We have already seen that in the full degenerate subspace wi th principal quantum
numbernthe matrix for Hrelis diagonal in the uncoupled basis. But now we see that in
each degenerate subspace of xed nand,Hrelis in fact a multiple of the identitymatrix,
since the matrix elements are independent of mandms(theLzandSz) eigenvalues. A
matrix equal to a multiple of the identity is invariant under any orthonormal change of
basis. For any 1
2multiplet, the resulting jmultiplets provide an alternative orthonormal
basis. The invariance of a matrix proportional to the identi ty implies that
E(1)
njmj,rel=/an}backetle{tnjmj|Hrel|njmj/an}backeti}ht=f(n,). (2.4.48)
withthesamefunction f(n,)as in(2.4.47), andtheperturbationisdiagonal inthiscou pled
basis too. This is clear anyway because the perturbation com mutes with L2,J2andJzand
and any two degenerate states in the coupled basis dier eithe r in,jorjz.
The preservation of the matrix elements can also be argued mo re explicitly. Indeed,
any state in the coupled basis is a superposition of orthonor mal uncoupled basis states with
constant coecients ci:
|njmj/an}backeti}ht=/summationdisplay
ici|nmi
mi
s/an}backeti}ht,with/summationdisplay
i|ci|2= 1, (2.4.49)
because the state on the left-hand side must also have unit no rm. Therefore, using the</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>2.3. THE DIRAC EQUATION 33
This equation is a bit reminiscent of the equation LL=i/planckover2pi1L, for angular momentum.
Back in the Pauli Hamiltonian (2.2.14), leaving identity ma trices implicit, and setting
q=e, we nd
HPauli=1
2m/parenleftBig
p+e
cA/parenrightBig2
+i
2mi/planckover2pi1q
cBe(x)
=1
2m/parenleftBig
p+e
cA/parenrightBig2
+e/planckover2pi1
2mcBe(x).(2.2.20)
The second term in this expanded Pauli Hamiltonian gives the coupling of the electron spin
to the magnetic eld and agrees precisely with the expected c oupling (2.2.5). We thus see
that the Pauli equation predicts the g= 2 value in the electron magnetic moment.
2.3 The Dirac equation
While the Pauli equation incorporates correctly the coupli ng of the electron spin to electro-
magnetic elds, it is not a relativistic equation. As discov ered by Dirac, to include relativity
one has to work with matrices and the Pauli spinor must be upgr aded to a four-component
spinor. The analysis begins with the familiar relation betw een relativistic energies and
momenta
E2p2c2=m2c4E=/radicalbig
p2c2+m2c4 (2.3.1)
This suggests that a relativistic Hamiltonian for a free par ticle could take the form
H=/radicalbig
p2c2+m2c4, (2.3.2)
with associated Schr odinger equation
i/planckover2pi1
t=/radicalbig
p2c2+m2c4. (2.3.3)
It is not clear how to treat the square root so, at least for sma ll velocities pmc, the
Hamiltonian can be expanded:
H=mc2/radicalbigg
1+p2
m2c2=mc2/bracketleftBigg
1+p2
2m2c21
8/parenleftbiggp2
m2c2/parenrightbigg2
+.../bracketrightBigg
=mc2+p2
2m1
8p4
m3c2+...(2.3.4)
Ifweignoretheconstantrestmass,thersttermisthefamil iarnon-relativisticHamiltonian,
and the next term is the rst nontrivial relativistic correc tion. For small momenta we will
treat that term as a perturbation.
More elegantly, Dirac wanted to nd a Hamiltonian linear in m omenta and without
square roots. This would be possible if one could write the re lativistic energy as the square
of a linear function of the momentum:
c2p2+m2c4= (cp+mc2)2= (c1p1+c2p2+c3p3+mc2)2.(2.3.5)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>2.4. FINE STRUCTURE OF HYDROGEN 41
diagonal nature of the matrix elements in the uncoupled basi s we get, as claimed
/an}backetle{tnjmj|Hrel|njmj/an}backeti}ht=/summationdisplay
i,kc
ick/an}backetle{tnmi
mi
s|Hrel|nmk
mk
s/an}backeti}ht
=/summationdisplay
i|ci|2/an}backetle{tnmi
mi
s|Hrel|nmi
mi
s/an}backeti}ht
=/summationdisplay
i|ci|2f(n,) =f(n,).(2.4.50)
2.4.3 Spin orbit coupling
The spin-orbit contribution to the Hamiltonian is
Hspin-orbit =e2
2m2c21
r3SL. (2.4.51)
Note thatHspin-orbit commutes with L2because L2commutes with any Liand any Si.
Moreover,Hspin-orbit commutes with J2and withJzsince, in fact, [ Ji,SL] = 0 for
anyi;SLis a scalar operator for J. It follows that Hspin-orbitis diagonal in the level
ndegenerate subspace in the coupled basis |njmj/an}backeti}ht. In fact, as we will see, the matrix
elements are m-independent. This is a nontrivial consequence of Hspin-orbitbeing a scalar
underJ. To compute the matrix elements we recall that J=S+Land
E(1)
njmj;spin-orbit=e2
2m2c2/angbracketleftBig
njmj/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle1
r3SL/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsinglenjmj/angbracketrightBig
=e2
2m2c2/planckover2pi12
2/bracketleftbig
j(j+1)(+1)3
4/bracketrightbig/angbracketleftBig
njmj/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle1
r3/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsinglenjmj/angbracketrightBig
.(2.4.52)
We need the expectation value of 1 /r3in these states. It is known that
/angbracketleftBig
nm/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle1
r3/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsinglenm/angbracketrightBig
=1
n3a3
0/parenleftbig
+1
2/parenrightbig
(+1). (2.4.53)
Because ofthe mindependenceof this expectation value(andits obvious msindependence)
the operator 1 /r3is a multiple of the identity matrix in each 1
2multiplet. It follows that
it is the same multiple of the identity in the coupled basis de scription. Therefore
/angbracketleftBig
njmj/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle1
r3/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsinglenjmj/angbracketrightBig
=1
n3a3
0/parenleftbig
+1
2/parenrightbig
(+1). (2.4.54)
Using this in (2.4.52)
E(1)
njmj;spin-orbit=e2/planckover2pi12
4m2c2/bracketleftbig
j(j+1)(+1)3
4/bracketrightbig
n3a3
0/parenleftbig
+1
2/parenrightbig
(+1). (2.4.55)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>36 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
We will study each of these terms separately and then combine our results to give the ne
structure of hydrogen. There are further smaller correctio ns that we will not examine here,
such as hyperne splitting and Lamb eect.
2.4.1 Darwin correction
Let us now evaluate the Darwin correction. Since this intera ction has a delta function
at the origin, the rst order correction to the energy vanish es unless the wavefunction is
non-zero at the origin. This can only happen for nSstates. There is no need to use the
apparatus of degenerate perturbation theory. Indeed, for  xednthere are two orthogonal
= 0 states, one with electron spin up and one with electron spi n down. While these states
are degenerate, the Darwin perturbation commutes with spin and is therefore diagonal in
the two-dimensional subspace. There is no need to include th e spin in the calculation and
we have
E(1)
n00,Darwin=/an}backetle{tn00|HDarwin|n00/an}backeti}ht=
2e2/planckover2pi12
m2c2|n00(0)|2. (2.4.22)
As is shown in the homework, the radial equation can be used to determine the value of the
nSwavefunctions at the origin. You will nd that
|n00(0)|2=1
n3a3
0. (2.4.23)
As a result
E(1)
n00,Darwin=e2/planckover2pi12
2m2c21
a3
0n3=4(mc2)1
2n3. (2.4.24)
This completes the evaluation of the Darwin correction
The Darwin term in the Hamiltonian arises from the eliminati on of one of the two two-
component spinors in the Dirac equation. As we will show now s uch a correction would arise
from a nonlocal correction to the potential energy term. It i s as if the electron had grown
from point-like to a ball with radius of order its Compton wav elength/planckover2pi1
mec. The potential
energy due to the eld of the proton must then be calculated by integrating the varying
electric potential over the charge distribution of the elec tron. While a simple estimate of
this nonlocal potential energy doesreproducetheDarwin co rrection rather closely, onemust
not reach the conclusion that the electron is no longer a poin t particle. Still the fact remains
that in a relativistic treatment of an electron, its Compton wavelength is relevant and is
physically the shortest distance an electron can be localiz ed.
The potential energy V(r) of the electron, as a point particle, is the product of the
electron charge ( e) times the electric potential ( r) created by the proton:
V(r) = (e)(r) = (e)e
r. (2.4.25)
Let us call/tildewideV(r) the potential energy when the electron is a charge distribu tion centered
at a point rwith|r|=r(see Figure 2.1). This energy is obtained by integration ove r the</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>2.4. FINE STRUCTURE OF HYDROGEN 37
Figure 2.1: A Darwin type correction to the energy arises if the electron charg e is smeared over a
region of size comparable to its Compton wavelength. Here the cent er of the spherically symmetric
electron cloud is at Pand the proton is at the origin. The vector uis radial relative to the center
of the electron.
electron distribution. Using the vector uto dene position relative to the center Pof the
electron, and letting (u) denote the position dependent charge density, we have
/tildewideV(r) =/integraldisplay
electrond3u(u)(r+u), (2.4.26)
where, as shown in the Figure, r+uis the position of the integration point, measured
relative to the proton at the origin. It is convenient to writ e the charge density in terms of
a normalized function 0:
(u) =e0(u)/integraldisplay
electrond3u0(u) = 1, (2.4.27)
which guarantees that the integral of over the electron is indeed ( e). Recalling that
e(r+u) =V(r+u) we now rewrite (2.4.26) as
/tildewideV(r) =/integraldisplay
electrond3u0(u)V(r+u). (2.4.28)
This equation has a clear interpretation: the potential ene rgy is obtained as a weighted
integral of potential due to the proton over the extended ele ctron. If the electron charge
would be perfectly localized, 0(u) =(u) andV(r) would just be equal to V(r). We will
assume that the distribution of charge is spherically symme tric, so that
0(u) =0(u). (2.4.29)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>2.5. ZEEMAN EFFECT 45
For the record, the total energy of the hydrogen states is the zeroth contribution plus
the ne structure contribution. Together they give
Enjmj=e2
2a01
n2/bracketleftBig
1+2
n2/parenleftBign
j+1
23
4/parenrightBig/bracketrightBig
. (2.4.65)
This is the ne structure of hydrogen! There are, of course,  ner corrections. The so-
called Lamb shift, for example, breaks the degeneracy betwe en 2S1/2and 2P1/2and is of
order5. There is also hyperne splitting, which arises from the cou pling of the magnetic
moment of the proton to the magnetic moment of the electron. S uch coupling leads to a
splitting that is a factor me/mpsmaller than ne structure.
2.5 Zeeman eect
In remarkable experiment done in 1896, the Dutch physicist P ieter Zeeman (1865-1943)
discovered that atomic spectral lines are split in the prese nce of an external magnetic eld.
For this work Zeeman was awarded the Nobel Prize in 1902. The p roper understanding of
this phenomenon had to wait for Quantum Mechanics.
The splitting of atomic energy levels by a constant, uniform , external magnetic eld, the
Zeeman eect , has been used as a tool to measure inaccessible magnetic el ds. In observing
the solar spectrum, a single atomic line, as seen from light e merging from outside a sunspot,
splits into various lines inside the sunspot. We have learne d that magnetic elds inside a
sunspot typically reach 3 ,000 gauss. Sunspots are a bit darker and have lower temperatu re
than the rest of the solar surface. They can last from hours to months, and their magnetic
energy can turn into powerful solar ares.
The external magnetic eld interacts with the total magneti c moment of the electron.
The electron has magnetic moment due to its orbital angular m omentum and one due to
its spin
=e
2mcL,s=e
mcS, (2.5.1)
where we included the g= 2 factor in the spin contribution. The Zeeman Hamiltonian i s
thus given by
HZeeman=(+s)B=e
2mc(L+2S)B. (2.5.2)
Conventionally, we align the magnetic eld with the positiv ezaxis so that B=Bzand
thus get
HZeeman=eB
2mc(Lz+2Sz). (2.5.3)
When we consider the Zeeman eect on Hydrogen we must not forge t ne structure.
The full Hamiltonian to be considered is
H=H(0)+Hfs+HZeeman. (2.5.4)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>2.4. FINE STRUCTURE OF HYDROGEN 43
Intheaboveformulatherearetwocases toconsiderforany xedvalueofj: themultiplet
can have=j1
2or the multiplet can have =j+1
2. We will now see something rather
surprising. In both of these cases the shift is the same, mean ing that the shift is in fact 
independent! It just depends on j. Callf(j,) the term in brackets above
f(j,)j(j+1)3(+1)3
4
/parenleftbig
+1
2/parenrightbig
(+1). (2.4.60)
The evaluation of this expression in both cases gives the sam e result:
f(j,)/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
=j1
2=j(j+1)3(j1
2)(j+1
2)3
4/parenleftbig
j1
2/parenrightbig
j/parenleftbig
j+1
2/parenrightbig =2j2+j
j/parenleftbig
j1
2/parenrightbig/parenleftbig
j+1
2/parenrightbig=2/parenleftbig
j+1
2/parenrightbig,
f(j,)/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle
=j+1
2=j(j+1)3(j+1
2)(j+3
2)3
4/parenleftbig
j+1
2/parenrightbig
(j+1)/parenleftbig
j+3
2/parenrightbig=2j25j3/parenleftbig
j+1
2/parenrightbig
(j+1)/parenleftbig
j+3
2/parenrightbig=2/parenleftbig
j+1
2/parenrightbig.
(2.4.61)
We can therefore replace in (2.4.59) the result of our evalua tion, which we label as ne
structure (fs) shifts:
E(1)
nj,mj;fs=(E(0)
n)2
2mc2/bracketleftBig4n
j+1
23/bracketrightBig
=4(mc2)1
2n4/bracketleftBign
j+1
23
4/bracketrightBig
.(2.4.62)
More briey we can write
E(1)
nj,mj;ne=4mc2Sn,j,withSn,j1
2n4/bracketleftBign
j+1
23
4/bracketrightBig
.(2.4.63)
Let us consider a few remarks:
1. The dependence on jand absence of dependence on in the energy shifts could be
anticipated from the Dirac equation. The rotation generato r that commutes with the
Dirac Hamiltonian is J=L+S, which simultaneously rotates position, momenta, and
spin states. Neither LnorSare separately conserved. With Ja symmetry, states are
expected to be labelled by energy and jand must be mjindependent.
2. The formula (2.4.63) works for nSstates! For these = 0 states we were supposed
to add the relativistic correction and the Darwin correctio n, since their spin-orbit
correction is zero. But we noticed that the limit 0 of the spin-orbit correction
reproduces the Darwin term. Whether or not this is a meaningf ul coincidence, it
means the sum performed above gives the right answer for 0.
3. Whilealargeamount ofthedegeneracy of H(0)hasbeenbroken, forxed n, multiplets
with the same value of j, regardless of , remain degenerate. The states in each j
multiplet do not split.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>44 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
4. SinceSn,j&gt;0 all energy shifts are down. Indeed
n
j+1
2n
jmax+1
2=n
max+1
2+1
2=n
n= 1n
j+1
23
41
4.(2.4.64)
5. For a given xed n, states with lower values of jget pushed further down. As n
increases splittings fall o like n3.
A table of values of Sn,jis given here below
n j S n,j
11
21
8
21
25
128
3
21
128
31
21
72
3
21
216
5
21
648
The energy diagram for states up to n= 3 is given here (not to scale)
S P D
= 0 = 1 = 2
............
n= 3
3D5/23P3/2 3D3/2
3S1/2 3P1/2
n= 2
2P3/2
2S1/2 2P1/2
n= 1
1S1/2Fine Structure Spectrum</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>2.5. ZEEMAN EFFECT 49
Actually H(0)is simple because the Zeeman Hamiltonian commutes with the z ero-th order
hydrogen Hamiltonian/bracketleftbigLz+2Sz, H(0)/bracketrightbig
= 0. (2.5.24)
We can thus nd eigenstates of both simultaneously. Those ar e in fact the uncoupled basis
states! We have
H(0)|nmms/an}backeti}ht=E(0)
n|nmms/an}backeti}ht
(Lz+2Sz)|nmms/an}backeti}ht=/planckover2pi1(m+2ms)|nmms/an}backeti}ht.(2.5.25)
and therefore the uncoupled basis states are the exactenergy eigenstates of H(0)and have
energies
Enmms=E(0)
n+e/planckover2pi1
2mcB(m+2ms). (2.5.26)
Some of the degeneracy of H(0)has been removed, but some remains. For a xed principal
quantum number nthere are degeneracies among 1
2states and degeneracies among such
multiplets with anddierent. This is illustrated in Figure 2.2.
Figure 2.2: Illustrating the degeneraciesremainingfor = 0 and= 1after the inclusion ofZeeman
term in the Hamiltonian. Accounting for the spin of the electron ther e two degenerate states in the
= 1 multiplet 1 1
2and each of the two states in the = 0 multiplet 0 1
2is degenerate with a
state in the = 1 multiplet.
The problem now is to compute the corrections due to Hfson the non-degenerate and
on the degenerate subspaces of H(0). The non-degenerate cases are straightforward, but
the degenerate cases could involve diagonalization. We mus t therefore consider the matrix
elements
/an}backetle{tnm
m
s|Hfs|nmms/an}backeti}ht, (2.5.27)
with the condition
m
+2m
s=m+2ms, (2.5.28)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>34 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
Expanding the right-hand side and equating coecients one  nds that the following must
hold
2
1=2
2=2
3=2= 1,
ij+ji={i,j}= 0, i/ne}ationslash=j,
i+i={i,}= 0.(2.3.6)
Therelations on thesecond andthirdlines implythat s ands cant benumbers, because
theywouldhavetobezero. Itturnsoutthat sandsarefour-by-fourhermitianmatrices:
=/parenleftbigg0
0/parenrightbigg
, =/parenleftbigg10
01/parenrightbigg
. (2.3.7)
Using (2.3.5), the Dirac Hamiltonian is simply the linear fu nction of momentum that is the
square root of c2p2+m2c4. We thus have
HDirac=cp+mc2. (2.3.8)
The Dirac equation is
i/planckover2pi1
t=/parenleftbig
cp+mc2/parenrightbig
, (2.3.9)
where  is a Dirac spinor, a four-component column vector tha t can be thought to be
composed by two two-component Pauli spinors and:
 =/parenleftbigg
/parenrightbigg
, =/parenleftbigg1
2/parenrightbigg
, =/parenleftbigg1
2/parenrightbigg
. (2.3.10)
The coupling to electromagnetic elds is done as before
i/planckover2pi1
t=/bracketleftBig
c/parenleftBig
p+e
cA/parenrightBig
+mc2+V(r)/bracketrightBig
, (2.3.11)
where the coupling of the electron to the scalar potential ( r) is included via
V(r) =e(r) =e2
r. (2.3.12)
ThegreatadvantageoftheDiracequation(2.3.11) isthatth ecorrectionstothehydrogen
Hamiltonian H(0)can be derived systematically by nding the appropriate Ham iltonianH
that acts on the Pauli spinor . The analysis, can be done with A= 0, since the stationary
proton creates no vector potential. The result of the analys is shows that
H=E, (2.3.13)
where:
H=p2
2m+V
/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
H(0)p4
8m3c2/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
Hrel.+1
2m2c21
rdV
drSL
/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
Hspin-orbit+/planckover2pi12
8m2c22V
/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
HDarwin.(2.3.14)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>2.1. REVIEW OF HYDROGEN ATOM 27
S P D F
= 0= 1= 2= 3
...............
n= 4
N= 3N= 2N= 1N= 0
n= 3
N= 2N= 1N= 0
n= 2
N= 1N= 0
n= 1
N= 0
The table features the commonly used notation where capital letters are used to denote
the various values of the orbital angular momentum . If we have Ldenote the generic
capital letter for angular momentum we have L() where
L(= 0) =S, L(= 1) =P, L(= 2) =D, L(= 3) =F,... . (2.1.10)
Thus, for example, an Sstate is a state with = 0, aPstate is a state with = 1, and a
Dstate is a state with = 2.
Any hydrogen eigenstate specied by the three quantum numbe rsn,,m, because, as it
follows from (2.1.9), the value of Nis then xed. The wavefunction takes the form
n,,m(x) =A/parenleftbiggr
a0/parenrightbigg
/parenleftbigg
Polynomial inr
a0of degreeN/parenrightbigg
er
na0Y,m(,),(2.1.11)
whereAis a normalization constant and N=n(+1). If you look at the wavefunction,
the value of ncan be read from the exponential factor. The value of can be read from
the radial prefactor, or from the spherical harmonic. The va lue ofmcan be read from
the spherical harmonic. For the ground state n= 1,= 0 andm= 0. The normalized
wavefunction is
1,0,0(r) =1/radicalbig
a3
0er
a0. (2.1.12)
Comments:
1. There are n2degenerate states at any energy level with principal quantu m number
n. This degeneracy explained by the existence of a conserved q uantum Runge-Lenz
vector. For a given nthe states with various s correspond, in the semiclassical
picture, to orbits of dierent eccentricity but the same semi -major axis. The orbit
with= 0 is the most eccentric one and the orbit with maximum =n1 is the
most circular one.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>46 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
Recall that in ne structure, there is an internal magnetic  eldBintassociated with spin-
orbit coupling. This is the magnetic eld seen by the electro n as it goes around the proton.
We have therefore two extreme possibilities concerning the external magnetic eld Bof the
Zeeman eect:
(1) Weak-eld Zeeman eect: BBint. In this case the Zeeman eect is small compared
with ne structure eects. Accordingly, the original Hamilt onianH(0)together with
the ne structure Hamiltonian Hfsare thought as the known Hamiltonian H(0), and
the Zeeman Hamiltonian is the perturbation:
H=H(0)+Hfs/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
H(0)+HZeeman. (2.5.5)
(2) Strong-eld Zeeman eect: BBint. In this case the Zeeman eect is much larger
than ne structure eects. Accordingly, the original Hamilt onianH(0)together with
the Zeeman Hamiltonian are thought as the known Hamiltoni anH(0)and the ne
structure Hamiltonian Hfsis viewed as the perturbation:
H=H(0)+HZeeman/bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright
H(0)+Hfs. (2.5.6)
You may thing that H(0)+HZeemandoes not qualify as known, but happily, as we
will conrm soon, this is actually a very simple Hamiltonian .
When the Zeeman magnetic eld is neither weak nor strong, we m ust take the sum
of the Zeeman and ne structure Hamiltonians as the perturba tion. No simplication is
possible and one must diagonalize the perturbation.
Weak-eld Zeeman eect. The approximate eigenstates of H(0)are the coupled states
|njmj/an}backeti}htthat exhibit ne structure corrections and whose energies a re a function of nandj,
as shown in the Fine Structure diagram. Degeneracies in this spectrum occur for dierent
values ofand dierent values of mj.
To gure out the eect of the Zeeman interaction on this spectr um we consider the
matrix elements:
/an}backetle{tnjmj|HZeeman|njm
j/an}backeti}ht. (2.5.7)
SinceHZeemanLz+ 2Szwe see that HZeemancommutes with L2and with Jz. The
matrix element thus vanishes unless =andm
j=mjand the Zeeman perturbation is
diagonal in the degenerate ne structure eigenspaces. The e nergy corrections are therefore
E(1)
njmj=e/planckover2pi1
2mcB/an}backetle{tnjmj|(Lz+2Sz)|njmj/an}backeti}ht1
/planckover2pi1, (2.5.8)
where we multiplied and divided by /planckover2pi1to make the units of the result manifest. The result
of the evaluation of the matrix element will show a remarkabl e feature: a linear dependence</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>26 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
bound state spectrum can be better appreciated using the spe ed of light to consider both
the ne structure constant and the rest energy of the electro n. The ne structure constant
is given by
e2
/planckover2pi1c1
137, (2.1.4)
and the rest energy of the electron is mc2. Then,
e2
a0=me4
/planckover2pi12=m2/planckover2pi12c2
/planckover2pi12=2mc2. (2.1.5)
This states that the energy scale of hydrogen bound states is a factor of 2smaller than
the rest energy of the electron, that is, about 19000 times sm aller. We can thus rewrite the
possible energies as:
En=1
22mc21
n2. (2.1.6)
The typical momentum in the hydrogen atom is
p/planckover2pi1
a0=me2
/planckover2pi1=e2
/planckover2pi1cmcp(mc), (2.1.7)
which, written as pm(c) says that the typical velocity is vc, which is low enough
that the non-relativistic approximation is fairly accurat e. Finally, we note that
a0=/planckover2pi12
m/planckover2pi1c=/planckover2pi1
mc1
=
, (2.1.8)
which says that the Bohr radius is over a hundred times bigger than the (reduced) Compton
wavelength of the electron.
The degeneracy of the hydrogen atom spectrum is completely q uantied by the relation
n=N++1. (2.1.9)
HereN0 is the degree of a polynomial in rthat appears in a wavefunction where the
leading dependence on rnear the origin is factored out. The quantum number 0 is the
angular momentum of the state. For each xed n, you can see that the number ranges
from zero to n1. And for each xed the eigenvalue of Lzism/planckover2pi1withmranging from
up to:
n= 1,2, ...  = 0,1, ... , n1
m=, ... , # of states with energy En=n1/summationdisplay
=0(2+1) =n2
The states of hydrogen are shown in this energy diagram, whic h is not drawn to scale,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>32 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
So far, this is all just rewriting with no change in physics. B ut new things happen when we
the particle is charged and we couple it to external electrom agnetic elds. The quantum
mechanical rule is that this inclusion can be taken care with the replacement
ppq
cA. (2.2.12)
Hereqis the charge of the particle and Ais the external vector potential, a function
of position that becomes an operator A(x) since position is an operator. In addition, if
there is a electromagnetic scalar potential  it contribute s an additional term q(x) to the
Hamiltonian.
With the replacement (2.2.12) applied to the Hamiltonian (2 .2.11), and the inclusion of
the coupling to the scalar potential, we get the Pauli Hamiltonian :
HPauli=1
2m()()+q(x). (2.2.13)
This time, using the identity (2.2.9), the second term survi ves
HPauli=1
2m[()1+i()] +q(x). (2.2.14)
We have /ne}ationslash=0because the various ido not commute. Note that the replacement
(2.2.12) applied to the original Hamiltonian (2.2.8) would not have given us the term.
To evaluate that term we use
()k=ijkij=1
2ijk[i,j]. (2.2.15)
The commutator here is
[i, j] =/bracketleftBig
piq
cAi, pjq
cAj/bracketrightBig
. (2.2.16)
As usual, the pcomponents can be thought of as derivatives acting on the spa tially de-
pendent components of A. Moreover, the Ais being only functions of position, commute
among themselves and we have
[i, j] =/planckover2pi1
iq
c(iAjjAi) =i/planckover2pi1q
c(iAjjAi). (2.2.17)
Therefore, back in (2.2.16)
()k=1
2ijki/planckover2pi1q
c(iAjjAi) =i/planckover2pi1q
cijkiAj=i/planckover2pi1q
c(A)k,(2.2.18)
leading to the elegant result:
=i/planckover2pi1q
cB. (2.2.19)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>25</slideno>
          <text>50 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
needed for the two states in the matrix element to belong to a d egenerate subspace. Since
L2commutes with Hfsthe matrix elements vanish unless =and therefore it suces to
consider the matrix elements
/an}backetle{tnm
m
s|Hfs|nmms/an}backeti}ht, (2.5.29)
still with condition (2.5.28). Ignoring = 0 states, we have to re-examine the relativistic
correction and spin orbit. The relativistic correction was computed in the uncoupled basis
and one can use the result because the states are unchanged an d the perturbation was
shown to be diagonal in this basis. For spin-orbit the calcul ation was done in the coupled
basis because spin-orbit is not diagonal in the original H(0)degenerate spaces using the
uncoupled basis. But happily, it turns out that spin-orbit i s diagonal in the more limited
degenerate subspaces obtained after the Zeeman eect is incl uded. All these matters are
explored in the homework.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>30 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
S P D
= 0= 1 = 2
............
n= 44S1
2
n= 33S1
2 3P3
23D3
2
(2) (6) 3 P1
2(10) 3D5
2
n= 22S1
2 2P3
2
(2) (6) 2 P1
2
n= 11S1
2
(2)
The number of states is indicated in parenthesis.
2.2 The Pauli equation
In the hydrogen atom the spin-orbit coupling arises because the electron is moving in the
electric eld of the proton. Since the electron is moving rel ative to the frame where we have
a static electric eld, the electron also sees a magnetic el dB. The spin-orbit coupling is
the coupling Bof that magnetic eld to the magnetic dipole moment of the electron.
We have discussed before, in the context of the Stern-Gerlac h experiment, the value of
the magnetic dipole moment of the electron. Recall the logic we used. In Gaussian units,
the classical magnetic moment of a planar current loop is giv en by=I
ca, whereIis the
current and ais the area vector associated with the loop. From this one qui ckly derives
that for a uniformly rotating particle with charge qand massmthe magnetic moment is
=q
2mcL, (2.2.1)
whereLis the angular momentum due to the rotation. For an elementar y particle, this
motivates the following relation between the spin angular m omentum operator Sand the
magnetic moment
=gq
2mcS (2.2.2)
wheregis a factor that is added to parameterize our ignorance; afte r all there is no reason
why the classically motivated formula for the magnetic dipo le should hold in the quantum
domain of spin. As it turns out, for an electron one has g= 2. Sinceq=efor an electron,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>2.1. REVIEW OF HYDROGEN ATOM 29
When we form swe are tensoring a a full multiplet to an smultiplet (here, of course,
s= 1/2). All states in sare eigenstates of L2and eigenstates of S2, soandsare good
(constant) quantum numbers for all jmultiplets that arise in the tensor product. Each j
multiplet has states with quantum numbers ( j,mj).
The coupled basis is one where states are organized into jmultiplets. While states are
no longer LznorSzeigenstates they are still L2eigenstates, thus the quantum number
survives. The coupled basis quantum numbers are therefore
Coupled basis quantum numbers: ( n,,j,m j). (2.1.16)
The (m,ms) quantum numbers of the uncoupled basis have been traded for (j,mj) quan-
tum numbers and we have kept the n,quantum numbers. The coupled states are linear
combinations of uncoupled states that involve dierent valu es ofmandms, those combi-
nations that yield the same value of mj=m+ms.
To nd the list of coupled basis states we must tensor eachmultiplet in the hydrogen
atom spectrum with the spin doublet1
2. The rules of addition of angular momentum imply
that we nd two jmultiplets:
1
2= (j=+1
2)(j=1
2). (2.1.17)
For= 0, we only obtain a j= 1/2 multiplet. We use the notation Ljfor the coupled
multiplets, with L=S,P,D,F for= 0,1,2,and 3 (see (2.1.10). The change of basis is
summarized by the replacements
1
2L()j=+1
2L()j=1
2(2.1.18)
or more explicitly,
01
2S1
2
11
2P3
2P1
2
21
2D5
2D3
2
31
2F7
2F5
2(2.1.19)
Thus, by the time we combine with electron spin, each = 0 state gives one j=1
2multiplet,
each= 1 state gives j=3
2andj=1
2multiplets, each = 2 state gives j=5
2andj=3
2
multiplets, and so on. For hydrogen, the principal quantum n umber is placed ahead to
denote the coupled multiplets by
Coupled basis notation for multiplets: nLj (2.1.20)
Using this notation for coupled basis multiplets the diagra m of hydrogen atom energy
eigenstates becomes:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>48 CHAPTER 2. HYDROGEN ATOM FINE STRUCTURE
This is sometimes called the projection lemma: the matrix el ements of a vector operator V
are those of the conventional projection of VontoJ. Recall that the projection of a vector
valong the vector jis (vj)j/j2.
Let us now return to the question of interest; the computatio n of the the expectation
value ofSzin (2.5.20). Since Sis a vector operator under Jwe can use (2.5.15). Specializing
to thez-component
/an}backetle{tnjmj|Sz|njmj/an}backeti}ht=/planckover2pi1mj/an}backetle{tnjmj|SJ|njmj/an}backeti}ht
/planckover2pi12j(j+1). (2.5.17)
We already see the appearance of the predicted /planckover2pi1mjfactor. The matrix element in the
numerator is still to be calculated but it will introduce no mjdependence. In fact SJis a
scalar operator (it commutes with all Ji) and therefore it is diagonal in mj. But even more
is true; the expectation value of a scalar operator is in fact independent of mj! We will not
show this here, but will just conrm it by direct computation . SinceL=JSwe have
SJ=1
2/parenleftbigJ2+S2L2/parenrightbig
, (2.5.18)
and therefore
/an}backetle{tnjmj|Sz|njmj/an}backeti}ht=/planckover2pi1mj
2j(j+1)/parenleftbig
j(j+1)(+1)+3
4/parenrightbig
.(2.5.19)
Indeed, no further mjdependence has appeared. Back now to (2.5.20) we get
/an}backetle{tnjmj|(Lz+2Sz)|njmj/an}backeti}ht=/planckover2pi1mj/parenleftBig
1+j(j+1)(+1)+3
4
2j(j+1)/parenrightBig
. (2.5.20)
The constant of proportionality in parenthesis is called th eLande g-factor gJ():
gJ()1+j(j+1)(+1)+3
4
2j(j+1)(2.5.21)
We nally have for the Zeeman energy shifts in (2.5.8)
E(1)
njmj=e/planckover2pi1
2mcBgJ()mj. (2.5.22)
Here the Bohr magnetone/planckover2pi1
2mc5.79109eV/gauss. This is our nal result for the weak-
eld Zeeman energy corrections to the ne structure energy l evels. Since all degeneracies
withinjmultiplets are broken and jmultiplets with dierent split dierently due to the
dependence of gJ(), the weak-eld Zeeman eect removes all degeneracies!
Strong-eld Zeeman eect. We mentioned earlier that when the Zeeman eect is larger
than the nestructure corrections we must take the original hydrogen Hamiltonian together
with the Zeeman Hamiltonian to form the known Hamiltonian H(0):
H(0)=H(0)+e
2mc(Lz+2Sz)B. (2.5.23)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>2.4. FINE STRUCTURE OF HYDROGEN 39
Therefore,
V=1
10u2
02V . (2.4.38)
If we choose the radius u0of the charge distribution to be the Compton wavelength/planckover2pi1
mcof
the electron we get,
V=/planckover2pi12
10m2c22V . (2.4.39)
Comparing with (2.3.14) we see that, up to a small correction (1
8as opposed to1
10), this
is the Darwin energy shift. The agreement is surprisingly go od for what is, admittedly, a
heuristic argument.
2.4.2 Relativistic correction
We now turn to the relativistic correction. The energy shift s of the hydrogen states can
be analyzed among the degenerate states with principal quan tum number n. We write
tentatively for the corrections
E(1)
n,mms;rel=1
8m3c2/an}backetle{tnmms|p2p2|nm/an}backeti}ht. (2.4.40)
We can use this formula because the uncoupled basis of states at xednis good: the
perturbation is diagonal in this basis. This is checked usin g Remark 3 in section 1.2.2. This
is clear because the perturbing operator p2p2commutes with L2, withLz, and with Sz.
The rst operator guarantees that that the matrix for the per turbation is diagonal in , the
second guarantees that the perturbation is diagonal in m, and the third guarantees, rather
trivially, that the perturbation is diagonal in ms.
To evaluate the matrix element we use the Hermiticity of p2to move one of the factors
into the bra
E(1)
n,mms;rel=1
8m3c2/an}backetle{tp2nm|p2nm/an}backeti}ht, (2.4.41)
where in the right-hand side we evaluated the trivial expect ation value for the spin degrees
of freedom. To simplify the evaluation we use the Schr oding er equation, which tells us that
/parenleftBigp2
2m+V/parenrightBig
nm=E(0)
nnmp2nm= 2m(E(0)
nV)nm.(2.4.42)
Using this both for the bra and the ket:
E(1)
n,mms;rel=1
2mc2/angbracketleftBig
(E(0)
nV)nm/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle(E(0)
nV)nm/angbracketrightBig
. (2.4.43)
The operator E(0)
nVis also Hermitian and can be moved from the bra to the ket, givi ng
E(1)
n,mms;rel=1
2mc2/angbracketleftBig
nm/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsingle((E(0)
n)22VE(0)
n+V2)/vextendsingle/vextendsingle/vextendsinglenm/angbracketrightBig
=1
2mc2/bracketleftBig
(E(0)
n)22En/an}backetle{tV/an}backeti}htnm+/an}backetle{tV2/an}backeti}htnm/bracketrightBig
.(2.4.44)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>2.5. ZEEMAN EFFECT 47
E(1)/planckover2pi1mjon the azimuthal quantum numbers. The states in each jmultiplet split into
equally separated energy levels! We will try to understand t his result as a property of
matrix elements of vector operators. First, however, note t hatLz+ 2Sz=Jz+Szand
therefore the matrix element of interest in the above equati on satises
/an}backetle{tnjmj|(Lz+2Sz)|njmj/an}backeti}ht=/planckover2pi1m+/an}backetle{tnjmj|Sz|njmj/an}backeti}ht. (2.5.9)
It follows that we only need to concern ourselves with Szmatrix elements.
Lets talk about vector operators. The operator Vis said to be a vector operator
under an angular momentum operator Jif the following commutator holds for all values of
i,j= 1,2,3:/bracketleftbigJi,Vj/bracketrightbig
=i/planckover2pi1ijkVk. (2.5.10)
Itfollows fromthefamiliar Jcommutators that Jisavector operatorunder J. Additionally,
ifVis a vector operator it has a standard commutation relation w ithJ2that can be quickly
conrmed:
[J2,V] = 2i/planckover2pi1/parenleftbigVJi/planckover2pi1V/parenrightbig
. (2.5.11)
IfVis chosen to be Jthe left-hand side vanishes by the standard property of J2and the
right-hand side vanishes because the Jcommutation relations can bewritten as JJ=i/planckover2pi1J.
Finally, by repeated use of the above identities you will sho w (homework) that the following
formula holds
1
(2i/planckover2pi1)2/bracketleftBig
J2,[J2,V]/bracketrightBig
= (VJ)J1
2/parenleftbigJ2V+VJ2/parenrightbig
. (2.5.12)
Consider ( J2,Jz) eigenstates |k;jmj/an}backeti}htwherekstands for other quantum number that bear
no relation to angular momentum. The matrix elements of the l eft-hand side of (2.5.12) on
such eigenstates is necessarily zero:
/an}backetle{tk;jm
j|/bracketleftBig
J2,[J2,V]/bracketrightBig
|k;jmj/an}backeti}ht= 0, (2.5.13)
as can be seen by expanding the outer commutator and noticing thatJ2gives the same
eigenvalue when acting on the bra and on the ket. Therefore th e matrix elements of the
right-hand side gives
/an}backetle{tk;jm
j|(VJ)J|k;jmj/an}backeti}ht=/planckover2pi12j(j+1)/an}backetle{tk;jm
j|V|k;jmj/an}backeti}ht, (2.5.14)
which implies that
/an}backetle{tk;jm
j|V|k;jmj/an}backeti}ht=/an}backetle{tk;jm
j|(VJ)J|k;jmj/an}backeti}ht
/planckover2pi12j(j+1). (2.5.15)
This is the main identity we wanted to establish. Using the le ss explicit notation /an}backetle{t/an}backeti}htfor
the matrix elements we have found that
/an}backetle{tV/an}backeti}ht=/an}backetle{t(VJ)J/an}backeti}ht
/an}backetle{tJ2/an}backeti}ht. (2.5.16)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>2.2. THE PAULI EQUATION 31
we have
= 2e
2mecS=2e/planckover2pi1
2mecS
/planckover2pi1=2e/planckover2pi1
2mec1
2=e/planckover2pi1
2mec.(2.2.3)
For numerical applications we note that the Bohr magneton Bis dened by
B=e/planckover2pi1
2mec9.2741021erg
gauss= 5.79109eV
gauss. (2.2.4)
(for SI values use Tesla = 104gauss). The coupling of an electron to an external magnetic
eld is therefore represented by a Hamiltonian HBgiven by
HB=B=e/planckover2pi1
2mecB. (2.2.5)
Our goal now is to show that this coupling, and its associated prediction of g= 2, arises
naturally from the non-relativistic Pauli equation for an e lectron.
Consider rst the time-independent Schr odinger equation for a free particle:
p2
2m=E. (2.2.6)
Since a spin one-half particle has two degrees of freedom, us ually assembled into a column
vector, the expected equation for a free spin one-half particle is
p2
2m=Ewith=/parenleftbigg1
2/parenrightbigg
. (2.2.7)
One sometimes calls a Pauli spinor. Note theres an implicit two-by-two identit y matrix
122in the Hamiltonian
H=p2
2m122. (2.2.8)
We canrewritethis Hamiltonian using Pauli matrices if we recall the ident ity
(a)(b) =ab122+i(ab), (2.2.9)
valid for arbitrary vector operators aandb. Taking a=b=p, withpthe momentum
operator, and recognizing that pp=0, we have
(p)(p) =p2122. (2.2.10)
This means that the Hamiltonian (2.2.8) can be rewritten as
H=1
2m(p)(p). (2.2.11)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
