<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-240-race-and-science-spring-2004/</course_url>
    <course_title>Race and Science</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Sociology </list>
      <list>Anthropology </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>From Population to Genome: Race after World War Two (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-240-race-and-science-spring-2004/resources/lecnotes_03_18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Duster argues that this is already being used in line with social categories of 
race and reinscribing them, though in new ways. How? (begins on p. 16, 
Molecular genetics and the new conflation of race and forensics) 
 
It is possible to make arbitrary groupings of po pulations (geographic, 
linguistic, self-identified by faith, id entified by others by physiognomy) and 
STILL find statistically significant allelic variations between those groupings 
 
when researchers claim to be  able to assign people to  groups based on allele 
frequency at a certain number of loci, they have chosen loci that show 
differences between the groups th ey are trying to distinguish  
 
so WHAT DOES THIS MEAN FOR RACE?  
 
Go back to the Bowker and Star: Prototyp ical racial categori es (which can be 
different for the FBI, for Scotland yard , etc.) are being used to divide up a 
group of people; these categories are then fed into questions about which 
genetic loci can help make the distinction; this DNA distinction is then used to 
identify people according to that prototypical category, which at that moment 
is conflated (perhaps) with an e ssential category  and perhaps the 
assumption that the racial category is  real, based in lineage, etc. But it 
doesnt need to be so based in  order to be recognizable.  
 
So, here were getting the potential for a reconstruction of RACE  (according to 
social categories) in a biogenetic idiom that doesnt explicitly appeal to 
lineage of heredity  (since there are many reas ons and histories that could 
account for the presence of SNiPs and he redity and lineage are not always the 
most parsimonious). 
 
So, its circular. Race becomes a self-fulfilling prophesy, with one powerful 
scientific account flattened into the tec hnology of  the chip. So, ideas about 
humours, bloodlines, germ plasms, crania do nt need to be in place for racial 
and racist categories to be re-biologi zed in the age of genomics! Discussion?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>DID RACE GO AWAY? Why not? Is POPU LATION inconsistent with RACE? 
 
Clearly not; even in the 1950 statemen t we see the same old Mongolian, 
Caucasian, Negroid categories, though  these are now declared temporary, 
impermanent (begging the question of whether they are or iginary, I think. 
Polygenist commitments were to be disavowed when if you could still use the 
same categories and claim they were plastic). Hooton and Coon held on to 
race 
 
THE PLACE OF GENES  
So, GENES take on a new visibility here, though ostensibly not as essences. 
Any account about human unity and di versity now must get constructed 
around the adaptational histories that would lead to the temporary fixing of 
new genetic comple xes of traits. 
 
 Interlude on sociobiology 
 
GENOMICS  
Haraway argues that we are moving in to a NEW REGIME of REPRESENTATION 
OF UNITY AND DIVERSITY IN HUMAN (and other) BIOLOGY: GENOMICS 
 
She argues that GENOMICS has a differe nt logic than that of POPULATION. 
Can someone explain what she means? 
 
First what is a genome? 
Full complement of genes that code for proteins in chromosomes. 
 
What is a gene? 
chromosomes made of DNA made of co dons that code for amino acids, 
which make proteins. Gene maps  are supposed to locate segments of 
the genome that code for stuff like hemoglobin. Gene sequences  are 
lists of the nucleotides (bases: purines and pyrimadines) that make up a gene. 
 
Haraway writes that If universal humanity was plastic  under the sign of the 
population at mid-century, then human na ture is best described as virtual at 
present (p. 348). Why is this?  Well, because, as she puts it, human nature 
is embodied, literally, in an odd th ing called a genetic database (p. 348). 
 
We think about genes through database s: something peculiar happened to 
the stable, family-loving. Mendelian gene when it passed into a database, where it has more in common with LANDSAT photographs, Geographical 
Information systems, international seed banks, and the World Bank than with 
T.H. Morgans fruit flies at Columbia  University in the 1910s or UNESCOs 
populations in the 1950s (p. 349). 
 
material instantiations of genomes: in a body , in yeast artificial 
chromosomes or bacterial plasmids, wh ich can hold and transfer cloned 
genes. The entire genome of  an organism might be held in a library of such 
artifactual biochemical info rmation structures (p. 351)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>In this practice, Embodied information with a complex time structure is 
reduced to a linear code in an archive outside time So what? 
 
What are implications for thinking  about human diversity and unity? 
 
She writes: the genome projects produc e entities of a di fferent ontological 
kind than flesh-and-blood organisms, natural races  or any other sort of 
normal organic being They produce DATABASES 
 
and genetic engineering is not eugeni cs (because, for one thing, its not 
about heredity and birth) 
 
Might be good to use EXAMPLES to figure out what she means. HGDP, 
Guaymi, Iceland, SNiPs on chips. 
 
1. Human Genome Diversity Project: the re sult of populati on geneticists 
critique of molecular geneticists grasp of how variation is distributed across human populations  
 
2. Guaymi case  is this about race? dont need race, even as project 
may be racializing. 
 
3. Iceland case: a private company was able to obtain the rights to a 
comprehensive genetic database of Ic elands population . So, the genetic 
database is privately owned. Icel and was thought to be relatively 
homogeneous (but Vikings!) 
 
 
Duster, Troy. 2001. The Sociology of Scie nce and the Revolution in Molecular 
Biology. In The Blackwell Companion to Soci ology. Judith R. Blau, ed. Malden, MA.: 
Blackwell Publishers Limited, pp. 213-226. 
 
SNiPs on chips.  
DUSTER argues that in the age of geno mics, we are seeing the reconstruction 
of race as a biological/genetic category , though this time not through appeals 
heredity or lineage. Race is being biologized/geneticised in new ways . He 
centers his argument on this te chnology called SNiPs on chips. What are 
those?
 
SNiPs are single nucleotide polymorphi sms  sites where peoples genomes 
differ from one another by a single nucleotide substitution (sickle-cell is an 
example). 
 
If youre interested in seeing whethe r a complex of SNiPs is connected to 
something like heart disease, youll want to look at a number of SNiPs at once. This is where SNiPs on chips come in. 
What are those?
 
DNA chips. Different bits of DNA are affi xed to a chip and then compared to a 
sample of DNA for a particular person (complementary base pairing). You can 
put together different DNA chips to look  for sets of different SNiPS. SNiP 
profiles.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21A.240  
Race and Science 
Spring 2004 MIT  
 
 
PART 1:  
THE ALCHEMY OF RACE: MAKING AND UNMAKING SCIENTIFIC RACISM 
Lecture 7. March 18 
 
PAPER # 1 DUE  
 
From Population to Genome: Race after World War Two 
 
Well be talking about the evaporation of typological race categories in evolutionary 
and population biology and in anthropology after Worl d War II  and particularly 
thinking about how this evaporation beco mes manifest in the UNESCO statements 
about race which weve already heard so much about. Weve already gotten glimpses 
of this move  in our readings of Kevles and Proctor  from seeing RACE as a 
typological category  enabling ranking and so forth  to seeing RACE as an illusory 
concept based on misapprehensions of the pr oper object of evolutionary inquiry: the 
POPULATION, characterized by shifting gene frequencies. 
 
The shift from POPULATION th inking to GENOMIC thinking. 
 
To summarize and anticipate: we want to  look today at the shift from RACE to 
POPULATION to GENOME in scientific discourse s about human biological unity and 
diversity. Were also goin g to be concerned with co ntinuities between these 
categories  and particularly with whether typological race categories actually do go 
away through these shifts. I think well find that they dont entirely. But I think well 
also see some NEW WAYS in which RACE gets articulated. 
 
Its useful to have the typology that Haraway provides us in mind as we go: 
 
RACE, POPULATION, GENOME 
(eugenics/population gene tics/molecular genetics) 
 
Haraway, Donna. 1994. Universal Donors in a Vampire Culture, Or Its All in the 
Family: Biological Kinship Categories in the Twentieth-Century United States. In 
Uncommon Ground: Toward Reinventing Nature. William Cronon, ed. New York: Norton, pp. 321-366. 
 
RACE  
on RACE as an organizing pr inciple: weve really gone  over this category and 
its various instantiations with a fine-toothed comb. And weve seen a bit of 
POPULATION thinking, too. But POPULATI ON is where I want to begin. The 
UNESCO statements are a good starting  point. Look at Provine and Montagu 
to help us along: 
 
summarizing the shift from TYPOLOGI CAL RACE thinking to POPULATION 
thinking:
Montagu: such differences as exist be tween different groups of mankind are 
due to the operation of evolutionary factors of differentiation such as</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>isolation, the drift and random fixation of the material particles which control 
heredity (the genes), change s in the structure of these particles, hybridization 
and natural selection 
 
from the biological standpoint, the species Homo sapiens  is made up of a 
number of populations, each one of wh ich differs from the others in the 
frequency of one or more  genes  a race from the biological standpoint, 
may therefore be defined as one of the group of populations constituting the 
species Homo sapiens   
 
The term race designates a group or population characterized by some 
concentrations, relative as to freque ncy and distribution , of hereditary 
particles (genes) or physical characte rs, which appear, fluctuate, and often 
disappear in the course of time by re ason of geographic and/or cultural 
isolation. The varying manifestations of these traits in different populations 
are perceived in different  ways by each group  
  
so WHAT IS RACE now? 
 
a population that differs from others  with respect to gene frequencies. 
note that differences are: 
IMPERMANENT and SUBJECTIVE (relative to the categories chosen [since 
focus on different gene frequencies/po pulations would result in different 
groups]). Kind of confusing since th e statement seems to simultaneously 
point to real groups at the same ti me that it emphasizes relativity of 
measure. 
 
compare Boas? RACE exists and does not at the same time . 
 
the focus is now shifted to what humans have IN COMMON: 
 
the one trait which above all others ha s been at a premium in the evolution 
of mens mental characters has been educability, plasticity. It is indeed a 
species characteristic of Homo sapiens  
 
differences between 1950 and 1952 statem ents? 1950 had cooperation in it 
and metal equality. 1952 dropped cooper ation and remained agnostic on 
mental traits. 
 
difference between race and population  thinking: Rather than phylogenies 
and types, it was processes and popula tions  constructed out of gene flow, 
migration, isolation, mutation, and selection  which were to be the 
privileged scientific objects  of knowledge (p. 202) 
 
It was this view, this focus on what  humans had in common, which shifted 
the research agenda of physical anthro pology from typological questions, to 
questions of adaptation. 
 
the search for a common human adaptati onal complex in early humans: the 
sharing way of life, hunting, bipedalism, brain growth. As Haraway points out, 
even as ideas about race were mute d, the search for the common human 
adaptational complex remained grounded in traditional ideas about sex role. Hence, Man the Hunter (recall Darwin on sexual selection!)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Crash Course in the Category of Race as Biological Phantom and Social Reality (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-240-race-and-science-spring-2004/resources/lecnotes_02_12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>eugenics movements 
segregation 
Asian exclusion acts 
Japanese internment 
 
but also civil rights 
affirmative action 
black power 
back to Africa 
la raza Chicano movements. 
 
All of these projects represented  what race was, organized  resources 
accordingly and importantly CREATED the categories of their own 
concern. 
 
And note that not all projec ts of racial formation are racist . 
What is racism? 
 
Whats the difference between an aw areness of race and racism? 
What do you think? 
 
Omi and Winant, have a helpful definition: 
 
a racial project can be defined as racist if and only if it creates 
or reproduces structures of do mination based on essentialist 
categories of race  (p. 71). In order to identify a social project 
as racist, one must in our vi ew demonstrate a link between 
essentialist representations of ra ce and social domination (p. 
71). 
 
So, back to Africa movement  in 1920s? depends: may have 
essentialist understanding of race, but is not linked to domination. 
 
Ku Klux Klan? has essentialist notions and seeks to reinforce 
structures of domination. 
 
bell curve and idea that different  racial groups have different 
IQ? yes. 
 
Farrakhan? potentially yes, since it is essentialist and depends 
in part on demonizing Jews. Ev en so, black supremacism, while 
racist, is not necessarily as powerful and frightening as white supremacism. 
 
affirmative action? no  not essentialist and not dedicated to preserving hierarchy. (p. 72). 
 
So, how does science  fit in? How have scientific projects been part of racial 
projects, been part of racial form ation? Can you think of examples? 18th 
century ranking of races, eugenics</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21A.240  
Race and Science 
Spring 2004 MIT  
 
 
INTRODUCTION 
Lecture 2. February 12 
 
Plan: develop a vocabulary for talking ab out biology, society,   classification.  
 
Crash Course in Category of Race as Biological Phantom and Social Reality 
 
Gould, Stephen Jay. 1977. Why We Should  Not Name Human Races  A Biological 
View. In Ever Since Darwin: Reflections in  Natural History. New York: Norton, (pp. 
231-236). 
 
Race has long been considered a biol ogical category of human difference. 
People thought that humanity was di vided into major lineages that had 
radically different evolutionary histor ies and that race described these 
divisions. Most biol ogists at least since the 1950s, however, do not view race 
as a biological category. It tells us no thing about the evolutionary history of 
the species. Goulds ar ticles summarize why. 
 
Gould writes: I contend that the co ntinued racial cl assification of Homo 
sapiens represents an outmoded approa ch to the general problem of 
differentiation within  a species (p. 231). 
 
Why? Well, what is a species? The most  common definition of a species is a 
group of organisms that is reproductively  isolated from other species; that is, 
cant breed with other species (e.g. dogs and cats). What this means, 
according to Gould, is th at dividing species into subgroups, into subspecies, 
into races (all these things are equivalent) requires that the person doing this 
division must make a decision about what sorts of characters will be of 
interest. The person who is classi fying these characters needs to choose  what 
they will be. 
 
So, naming subspecies is a largely subjective affair . 
 
As Gould puts it, There is no requir ement that a species be divided into 
subspecies. The subspecies is a ca tegory of convenience (p. 233). 
 
But of course, one might argue that th ere is obvious geographical variation 
among populations of humans. Bu t the question then becomes  do racial 
categories help or confuse our understanding of this variation ? 
 
Take one example of a character that is of ten used to classify  race: skin color. 
 
Can skin color serve as a useful in dex of subspecifi c differentiation?  
 
Maybe, but the problem is that this is  only one character among many that 
could be used to group human populations. When one begins to add other</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>1. how the category is defined in theo ry and seems to work in practice 
2. a story about how particular peoples lives were affected by the 
category (go through chapter for ex amples). Think here about stories 
of racial recl assification. 
3. describe how you think the category functioned prototypically and/or according to an Aristotelian logic as well as offering a broader view of 
what you think RACIAL FORMATION wa s like in Apartheid South Africa. 
 
 
1. how the category is defined in theory and seems to work in 
practice 
 
pay attention to Population Registration Act and the Group Areas Act. 
 
Both of these Acts assumed that races were natural kinds, that 
racial categories were Aristotelian  in character, the result of 
sorting out mutually exclusive traits through histories of clean 
lines of descent. The policy of  separate development was 
based on loose eugenic basis th at each race must develop 
separately along its natural path way and that race mixing was 
unnatural (p. 197) 
 
But when it came to enforcing these Acts, what happened? 
 
Pop Reg Act assigned people to lower race of the two parents 
when they reached age 16. But Group Areas Act asked that people be classified a ccording to fathers race in order to live in 
same household. 
 
There are potentially conflicting ideas about descent and 
inheritance here. How do you explain this? Bowker and Star say 
that when it came time to classify INDIVIDUALS, Prototypical  
categories were used. So, a child of two parents falls into race 
of lower parent, but a child must live with its father. Whats going on? Is this a conflict between Aristotelian categories and 
Prototypical ones? Or are there two different Aristotelian frames 
with different assumptions about gender? 
 
 
2. a story about how particular peoples lives were affected by the category (go through chapter for examples). Think here about 
stories of racial reclassification.  
 
Why was it possible, gi ven the sense that race s were pure immutable 
types, for people to be reclassified? 
 
One factor is of course the fact  that individual s are classified 
prototypically  in practice to avoid endless inquiries into their 
descent (Think about the Race Reclassification  Board). As 
Bowker and Star point out, many white south Africans did not want to face the possibility of being disenfranchised by finding 
black blood in their past (this is a real contrast to the one-
drop rule!). (p. 208)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>characteristics  blood types, eye colo r, for example, the categories get 
fuzzier, not neater. 
 
Gould puts it this way: variation in single traits is a pale shadow of patterns 
in variation that affect so many fe atures simultaneously. Moreover, the 
classical problem of incongruity arises. Maps constructed for other single traits almost invariably present different distribu tions (p. 234). 
 
Further, is a difference in skin color re ally a difference? Differences in skin 
color simply result from the productive activity of melanocytes in the skin  
not from their presence or absence, no r from differences in their number, for 
example. The fact that humans have skin color is a similarity rather than a 
difference. (albinism, is the result of melanocytes not producing melanin, not 
of the absence of melanin.) 
 
Gould, Stephen Jay. 1985. Human Equality Is a Contingent Fact of History. In The 
Flamingos Smile: Reflections in Natural History. New York: Norton, (pp. 185-198). 
 
Now, in Human Equality is a Contingent  Fact of History, Gould adds a few 
more steps to the argument agains t race as a biological category. 
 
And the title is worthy of comment. Wh at does it mean? It means that it 
COULD have been the case that  humans could have had strong 
differentiations  it could have been possible that Homo erectus  and Homo 
sapiens, for example, could both still exist. But thats not the way it turned out. Humans dont exhibit strong differe nces between populations (as in, say, 
dogs, where humans have enforced breed ing lineages in line with ideas about 
what should count as a purebred One might make an argument for dogs as 
racialized  but really only because the subjective categories of breeders 
have been reinforced in practice, in projects of breeding that have been much more rigorous than anything ever done in humans). 
 
In this article, Gould gives THREE re asons why there are no subspecies in 
humans: 
 
1. discordance of characters  which Ive already mentioned: We might 
make a reasonable division on skin colo r, only to discover that blood groups 
imply different alliances, or acidity of saliva, or presence of absence of sickle cell (which does NOT vary by latitude, as does skin color; doesnt line up. its 
associated with malaria) or ability to roll your tongue. There is NO CLUSTERING of traits in humans. 
 
2. fluidity and gradations We interbr eed wherever we move, breaking down 
barriers and creating new groups. 
 
3. convergences similar characters evolve independentl y again and again. 
So, for example, high concentration of  melanin has develo ped independently 
in various tropical populations. As has particular facial structure, limb 
proportions. 
 
Quick digression on the evolution of melanin concentration; 
 darker skin shields from high UV rays, in areas with a lot of sun 
    c a n c e r</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Marks, Jonathan. 1995. Racial  and Racist Anthropology. In Human Biodiversity: 
Genes, Race, and History. New Yo rk: De Gruyter, (pp. 99-116). 
 
Omi, Michael and Howard Winant. 1994. Racial  Formation. In Racial Formation in the 
United States: From the 1960s to the 1990s , Second Edition. New York: Routledge, 
(pp. 53-76). 
 
If race is not a biological category, an d is rather historic al and social, how 
should we understand it? Even if we  are persuaded that there is no 
biological reality, how can we account for the regularities (and irregularities) 
of its use? Omi and Winant suggest the idea of RACIAL FORMATION (and this 
is something they develop for the US). We  want to try to adopt their model as 
we look at the history of  race in this class. 
 
Omi and Winant ask us to consider the cr eation of racial ca tegories socially 
and historically. So, clearly, they want us to avoid thinking about race as an 
ESSENCE (they base this contention on their reading of arguments like Goulds). At the same time, though, they argue that we must not see it as an 
ILLUSION; just because it is socially produced does not mean it isnt real. What does that mean? 
 
They try to explain this though a concept they call RACIAL FORMATION: 
 
We define racial formation  as the sociohistorical process by which racial 
categories are created, i nhabited, transformed, an d destroyed. (p. 55) Own 
words? 
 
Importantly, racial formation is a proce ss that is both symbolic and structural; 
they write we argue that ra cial formation is a process of historically situated 
projects in which human bodies and so cial structures are represented and 
organized. (p. 56). from a racial formation perspectiv e, race is a matter of 
both social structure  and cultural representation  (p. 56). Racial formations 
are made of racial projects . A racial project is  simultaneously an 
interpretation, representation, or explanat ion of racial dynamics, and an effort 
to reorganize and redistri bute resources along partic ular racial lines (p. 56). 
 
So, for example, there was a racial formation  during American slavery 
that represented  the bodies of slaves as firstly uniformly black (even 
if particular slaves may have come from very different areas of Africa or have had a white father) and second ly as capable of hard labor in a 
way white bodies were not, and thirdly as less than fully human. These representations were articulated to a social organization  in which 
enslaved persons were commodities  who could be bought and sold, 
and in which norms of paternity, maternity, and family that applied to 
white people  that applied to slave HOLDERS  did not apply to 
slaves, newly racialized as black . The children of a slave woman 
were not hers, but rather the property of a master. 
 
Other examples? 
 
the conquest of the Americas by Europeans 
dispossession of Native Americans</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>note that Stephen Jay Goulds work is also engaged in racial formation  in 
this case, by saying that there is no biological basis for race  hes engaged 
in REPRESENTING RACE as biologically ephemeral. And hes got a notion that 
society has been organized around a misapprehension of how race works. 
 
So, read the Omi and Winant carefully and think about how you can apply it 
to the different moments that well examine. 
 
Ethnicity ? Often the self-defined, rather  than externally ascribed, 
categorization of peoples; so black is  racial, while Liberi an, Afro-Caribbean, 
Sea Islander, West Indian are perhaps more ethnic. White is racial, while 
German, English, Irish, are ethnic. Tricky though  and obviously something that changes over time an d context; i.e., Jewish. 
 
Bowker, Geoffrey C. and Susan Leigh Star. 2000.  The Case of Race Classification and  
Reclassification under  Apartheid. In Sorting Things  Out: Classification and Its 
Consequences. Cambridge: MIT Press, (pp. 60-64, 195-225). 
 
This article centers on a different sort of deployment of science in making 
race than biology. Here, the fo cus is less on heredity than the technologies 
of classification  through which race beco mes manifest (or not). 
 
And Ive given you some pages in their book in which they write about 
Aristotelian versus prototypical classifica tion. Can we try to figure these out?  
 
Aristotelian  classification works according to a set of binary characteristics 
that an object being classifi ed either presents or does not present. At each 
level of classification, enough binary features are adduced to place any 
member of a given population into on e and only one class (p. 62). [like 
Linnaean classifica tion in Marks] 
 
example: the idea that ther e are distinct races that can be sorted (Europeans, 
Asiatics, coloreds, natives/Bantus/Africans) 
 
Prototypical  characterization: go from abstra ct example to object. We have a 
rough idea and then see if it ma ps onto the object in question. 
 
 example: classifica tion of a given person into a race. 
 
Everyday classificati on of race in South Africa partook of both ideas. 
 
So, what Id like you to do now is divide in to four groups and do the following task 
for me: 
 
Take a racial category  from South Africa 
 
 Asian 
 White 
 Bantu/Black African 
 colored 
 
and together with your group, be prepared to tell the class</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>So In the case of apartheid, we see the scientistic belief in 
race difference on an everyday level and an elaborate formal 
legal apparatus enforcing separation [based on Aristotelian 
convictions]. At the same ti me, a much less formal, more 
prototypical approach uses an amalgam of appearance  and 
acceptance  and the on-the-spot visual  judgments of everyone 
from police and tram drivers to judges to perform the sorting process on the street (p. 201) 
 
Another factor is that the Aris totelian categories themselves 
explicitly contain their own sabotage in the category of colored. What do cases of th e reclassification of colored 
people tell us about the categories? 
 
Totally based on prototypical ideas. Where youve been to 
school, etc. And technologies used inconsistent and crude (combs, etc.). 
 
 
3. describe how you think the category functioned prototypically 
and/or according to an Aristotelian logic as well as offering a 
broader view of what you think RACIAL FORMATION was like in Apartheid South Africa. 
 
Omi and Winant write: from a racial  formation perspective, race is a 
matter of both social structure  and cultural representation  (p. 56). 
Racial formations are made of racial projects . A racial project is 
simultaneously an interpretation, representation , or explanation of 
racial dynamics, and an effort to re organize and redist ribute resources 
along particular racial lines (p. 56). 
 
How can we bring the strategic inconsistency  of racial cl assification  
of racial representation   that Bowker and Star point into dialogue 
with Omi and Winants attention to the politics of representation? What does inconsistency add? 
 
Helps show how contradictory forces work in representational practice. 
 
Bowker and Star write that the prototyp ical and the Aristotelian are conflated, 
leaving room for either to be invoked in  any given scenario (p. 223). And why are 
they conflated? Because the pure ty pes existed nowhere and racism existed 
everywhere (pp. 201-202). 
 
Further, The conflation [of Aristotelian and prototypical] give s a terrible power of 
ownership of both the formal  and informal to those in power (p. 204). When racial 
categories oscillate back and forth between these two modes, the consistency that has emerged has been less at the level of cate gories than in at the level of securing 
privilege. 
 
Next time:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>PART 1: THE ALCHEMY OF RACE: MAKING AND UNMAKING SCIENTIFIC 
RACISM 
 
3. February 19 
Blood, Sex, and Skeletons: Colonialism, Climatic Determinism, Cranial Capacity, and the Rise of Monogenist  and Polygenist Scientific Racism 
 
SKIM Darwin! 
 
Come to class with a page of thoughts about how RACE and SEX work together in 
the readings.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>lighter skin lets more vitamin D in, in areas with not as much sun 
    r i c k e t s  
 
Let me give you an example  that I think illustrates some of these points 
pretty well. Think about the evolution of dark skin in populations in sub-
Saharan Africa and in aboriginal Australia. 
 
Now, these are independent events. Aust ralia was not originally settled by 
humans who came straight from Africa. Direct ancestry in sub-Saharan Africa is not a reason that many Australian aborig inals have dark skin. In terms of 
genealogical relationship, Australian aboriginals have a more recent history in 
common with the people of mainland Asia  people in India, China, Laos, etc, 
with whom they share the most recent  common ancestry. As youll note by 
these examples, theres a very high probability that the ancestors of aboriginals developed darker skin as their relatives in Asian populations 
developed somewhat lighter skin. 
 
So, here we have 
CONVERGENCES: same traits develo ping in different populations 
 
DISCORDANCE: looking at skin color similarities in some African and Australian populations will blind you to other differences. Maybe a different 
categorization, say by blood type, would lead to  a different grouping. 
 
In many ways, both African and Australia n aboriginal groups have come to be 
seen as black because of a common hist ory of colonization by the British. 
And this has also affected the way they ve come to see themselves. In fact, 
many Australian aboriginals have linked themselves up with global black power movements. You might imagine a scenario, then, in which two people from these populations come together and happen to have children. What is 
the race of that child? This gets to Goulds point about FLUIDITY and GRADATIONS, humans interbreeding wh erever they go, breaking down 
barriers and creating new groups. 
 
Now, examining GENETIC DATA can help us understand all of these things  
and curiously, genetics, a tool that developed out of a concern with 
genealogy, actually has served to unr avel, shatter, many popular social 
beliefs about who is related to wh om, and how populations cluster. 
 
Gould on variation within  and between groups:  
We can measure so much variation amon g individuals within any race that 
we encounter very little new variation by  adding another race to the sample. 
In other words, the great preponderanc e of human variation occurs within 
groups, not in the differences between them  (p. 196). If some disaster 
occurred that killed all the human race except some very small group, wed 
still have 80 percent of human variation. 
 
And keep in mind that these groups ar e socially and historically designated! 
At different times in history, racial gr oups have been quite various. Irish and 
Italians have not always been white in the US for example. Well talk about the history of such variation in so cial racialization in this course. 
 
 QUESTIONS?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Blood, Sex, and Skeletons: Colonialism, Climatic Determinism, Cranial Capacity, and the Rise of Monogenist and Polygenist Scientific Racism (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-240-race-and-science-spring-2004/resources/lecnotes_02_19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>What is the story here, and what can you say about it in terms of race and 
gender ideas of Europeans at this time?  
 
doubly determined that the fo cus would be on sexuality. climatic 
determinism  survives: African labia and breasts  one writer said  became 
enlarged and elongated in the same way that the flora of that continent grew 
large and fleshy in its extreme heat (p. 171). 
 
says more about the fantasies of Europe an men; assumption that this person 
was a type 
 
I think part of whats important about this is that the origin of RACIAL categories absolutely must be under stood in the context of GENDER and 
COLONIALISM. 
 
 
Gould, Stephen Jay. 1993. American Poly geny and Craniometry before Darwin: 
Blacks and Indians as Sepa rate, Inferior Species. In  The Racial Economy of 
Science: Toward a Democratic Future, Sa ndra Harding, ed. Bloomington: Indiana 
University Press, 84-115. 
 
this is about pre-evolut ionary scienti fic racism. 
 
what are polygeny and monogeny? 
 
polygeny  (separate creations: Aggasiz) 
 
Aggasiz, abolitionist but polygeni st racist, opponent of evolution 
 what is the relation between religion and science in his work? 
 
Samuel George Morton: cranio metry and cranial capacity 
though Morton seemed to tamper wi th his data, Gould says that he 
had not committed fraud. Why? 
 
 an older tradition of skull stuff is alive here. 
 
Gould goes through Mortons data, argu ing that it was not conscious fraud, 
but that he was led to choose particular kinds of measurements: 
 
(how has Gould used racial categories in his own re analysis on page 105? (is 
he saying, OK IF you accept these cate gories...?) corrections for body weight, 
sex (he seems to take sex for granted!), sample size, etc.) 
 
note how race is sexed/gendered  in the pronouncements of the people Gould 
cites (effeminate  races) and how this is in turn scientized. 
 
primarily a creationist position. races are separately created species. proof? 
look at FORMS. Since forms are unchanging over time, this is the place to 
look. Skulls.
 
Monogeny : everyone has common ancestor.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>(p. 216: differences) 
(p. 226: lots of slippage into species. Its almost as though race and species 
are sometimes synonymous; he also  throws in subspecies [p. 227]) 
 
Where does Race come from? 
 
 sexual selection  as a major process: quote page 250 . 
 
How does this work? Lets unpack it. 
 
first, what is sexual selection? 
 
selection to account for secondary sex characteristics in males and 
females 
 
struggle between males for possession  of females (pp. 87-90); 
basically, male competition and then female choice 
 
competition, Darwin belie ved, generally occurred between males for access 
to female mates, and ch oice, he reasoned, was ex ercised by females from 
among the male mates available to them (Fedigan: p. 27) 
  
An interesting entailment of the way Da rwin framed things was that natural 
and sexual selection seemed only to be acting on males: competition 
selected for male armaments (size streng th weapons) and choice selected for 
male ornaments (colors, elaborate hea ddresses, beautiful voices) (Fedigan: 
p. 28). Female traits seemed to occur in the absence of natural and sexual 
selection. 
 
But, as Fedigan notes, Darwin later cont radicts this theory when it came to 
humans. In humans, Darwin argued, fema les were chosen by men after their 
competition and fighting. Basically, th en, men operated in the realm of 
natural selection and sexual selection,  and women were subject only to the 
less rigorous forces of sexu al selection, which just se lects them to be pretty. 
In a way, you might say that, in Darwins theory, women are selected to give 
birth to the men who are doing all the evolving through natural selection . 
 
Darwin helped to pioneer what I call the coat-tails theory of evolution: traits 
are selected for in males and women evolve by clinging to the coat-tails of 
men (Fedigan: p. 29). 
 
Darwin: Thus man has ultimately become  superior to woman. It is indeed 
fortunate that the law of equal transm ission of characte rs to both sexes 
prevails with mammals. Otherwise it is probable that man would have become 
as superior in mental endowment to wo man as the peacock is in ornamental 
plumage to the peahen. (Fedigan: 29). 
 
The Descent of Man s title should be taken literally! THE FAMILY TREE IS A 
BUNCH OF MEN! 
 
Now, what does all this mean about race? And can we make links back to the 
previous authors?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>well, he says  secondary sex characteristics differ much in the several 
races  (p. 320). WHY? 
 
PAGE 325 quote: there can be littl e doubt that the greater size and 
strength of man... 
 
PAGE 327: the half-human male pr ogenitors of man, and men in a 
savage state, have struggled together for many generations for the 
possession of females 
 
What is the importance of this po ssession of females? what sort of 
relationship does it put women and men into? passive female sexuality, active 
male sexuality
 
females become the conduits for male s to pass on the traits they have 
accumulated from natural selection and from competition with one another for females. 
 
Key quote page 328: The higher powe rs of the imagination as well as 
persistence will have been developed in man, partly through sexual selection  that is through the contest of rival males, and partly through natural selection  that is from, success in th e general struggle for life; and as in 
both cases the struggle will have been in maturity, the characters thus gained will have been transmitted more fully to the male than to the female 
offspring. Thus man has ultimately become superior to woman. (p. 328) 
 
So, racial difference , for Darwin, where does it come from? 
 
in part from the persistence and imagination of males of a particular group, 
as well as their choice of attr active female ch aracteristics! 
 
problem with Darwins argument: takes for granted what it wants to prove! 
assumes racial dispositions in or der to show how they've evolved! 
 
but still, females must be possessed (i.e., their sexuality controlled) in order 
for these traits not to be diluted, especi ally since, because of the law of equal 
inheritance, they also obtain then (coat-tails ). The racial identity is passed on 
through agency of males in control of females. This naturalizes the idea of 
patriarchy and makes it part of some of  the earliest evolutionary attempts to 
theorize race,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>FAMILY TREES would become the preferred image for thin king about human history, 
especially among people who subscribed to a MONOGENIC view of human origins. 
 
MONOGENIST DEGENERATION   
This idea that some peoples had degenera ted from a pure original form continued 
into the 1800s, even as many natural philosophers began to abandon the Bible and 
adopt Darwins theory of evolution. That is, the idea survived from being a religious one to becoming scientized. 
 
The old racial categories and ideas about inferiority continued. The idea was that 
some groups of people had been stunted, evolutionarily speaking. Adult Africans were like white children, for example. The idea was that some groups had 
EVOLVED  
MORE. 
 
Discussions of race move from humours to skulls. 
 
 
Schiebinger, Londa. 1993. Theo ries of Gender and Race. In  Natures Body: Gender in 
the Making of Modern Science. Boston: Beacon Press, (pp. 143-183). 
 
We begin to see a shift from explicitly religious ideological warrants for race 
to ones that make use of natural philosophy and the beginnings of what 
would come to be called biology . Weve still got lots of ideas about a created 
world , even as we see the first hints of a concern to assess human difference 
through MEASUREMENT. 
 
Schiebinger shows that Europeans had be gun to rank the races that were 
being consolidated by colonialism on the great chain of being (scala naturae: 
Linneaus was into this) , making use of an existing epistemology in 
Christianity, and they sought to buttress these claims with reference to measurements of 
skulls , pelvises, etc. She also argues that this work was 
done in the context of struggles over political participation. 
 
In the context of discussion over the nat ural; rights of men the exclusion of 
some people from these rights demanded  proof of natural inequality  and 
science obliged. 
 
The first section of this chapter is called Were women on the chain? 
The great chain of being. What does Schiebinger mean?
 
She says: notions of racial and sexu al relations rested on contradictory 
visions of nature (p. 146). How? (r ace: unilinear; sex: oppositional) 
 
 implications? SKULLS versus PELVIS; BRAIN versus GENITALS 
 
theories of Race were almost always developed by looking at male bodies 
(skulls in particular)(and skulls [the se at of reason] were used to make the 
great chain of being; usin g indices of prognathism)  
 
theories of Sex usually with respec t to contrasts between women and men 
within  their racial group, and almost always with respect to Europeans</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Although both monogeny and polygeny st arted out with an appeal to religious 
doctrine, polygeny was the far weaker  of the two, because the idea of 
separate origins went against scripture. 
 
But, as you see, a racist commitment to insuperable raci al difference could 
easily be accommodated in monogeny. How? 
 
some groups have DEGENERATED 
 
religious warrant? 
 climatic determinism, movement away from Eden 
 
scientific warrant? 
 climatic and geographic dispersal (Blumbenbach) 
 
some groups were stunted: the theory of  recapitulation (A dult blacks were 
like white children, Asians like white adolescents...) i.e. some groups had 
EVOLVED  MORE: here you get the FUSION of the CHAIN OF BEING AND THE 
FAMILY TREE (PICTURE) 
 
Heres a family tree from the late 19th century. 
 
Family tree started to get used in EVOLUTIONARY THEORY, particularly by 
DARWIN. 
 
WHAT SORT OF FAMILY IS THIS? 
WHAT ARE THE ROLES OF MEN AND WOMEN IN THIS FAMILY? 
AND HOW DO WE UNDERSTAND DIFFERENT RACES IN THE FAMILY IDIOM? 
 
 
Darwin, Charles. 1871. The Descent of Ma n and Selection in Relation to Sex. 
Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1981, (pp. 214-236, 240-250, 316-329, 381-
384)  SKIM 
 
Fedigan, Linda Marie. 1986. Bi ological Evolution in the Ni neteenth Century, from The 
Changing Role of Women in Models of Human Evolution. Annual Review of Anthropology 15: (pp. 25-66). --  READ ONLY (pp. 27-29). 
 
GROUP ACTIVITY 
 
Now we get to the major figure in biology: Darwin. Darwins theory of 
evolution by natural selection is found ed on a monogenist  view of organic 
history, and no less so when he forwards his theory of the evolution of 
humans. And its a theory about PROCE SS rather than types (ultimately, one 
might argue, it is this process logic that people later use to demolish race as a scientific category, but were getti ng ahead of ourselves here).  
 
What Ive excerpted here is stuff from Descent of Man, Darwins attempt to 
apply his theory of evolution to humans. 
 
We want to think about what RACE was for Darwin. Any starts?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>a place of melancholy souls, since black bile predominated in climates that 
were cold and dry like the Asian steppes. 
 
Since the Europeans thinking about these things were medieval Christians, it is not surprising that they thought the perfect climate was to be found in the 
Garden of Eden, from which humanity ha d been exiled after the sin of Adam 
and Eve. 
 
The prevailing belief was that as people had moved away from Eden they had 
DEGENERATED ; their humors had been thrown out of whack. SOME places, 
like ancient Greece, approximated Eden  more closely than others. People 
from these climates could try to rea pproximate a close-to-God state. Some 
places were lousy and the people wh o lived there were lazy or mean. 
 
 This whole cluster of beliefs is called GEOGRAPHICAL DETERMINISM 
 
Now when Europeans came upon the Am ericas, there was a huge question to 
be answered about who exactly the nati ve people were and what they were 
like. Was the so-called New World similar to Eden? Or was it a horrible hellish 
place? 
 
There was lots of controversy about the humoural balance of the indigenous people of the Americas. And the Americas were a key place for the 
development of 
RACE .  
 
PURITY OF BLOOD AND LINEAGE THINKING  
 
How did people come to belie ve that humoral traits coul d be INHERITED? Stay in 
Europe with me for a moment. King Ferdinand and Queen Isabels Castilian Empire 
on the Iberian peninsula in the 1500s. You may be familiar with this today as SPAIN. 
 
In the 1500s, Iberians were obsessed with an idea that they called PURITY OF 
BLOOD. And this was about religion . 
 
Christians who could trace their lineage ba ck to other Christians were said to 
be pure of blood; recently converted Ch ristians whose ancestors were Jewish 
or Muslim were suspect  could not be trusted to hold royal or clerical office; this was a legacy of the Spanish Inquisition. Those who were impure of blood 
were prevented from holding office, ma rrying Christians, and in many cases 
from traveling to the Americas . 
  
Why BLOOD? 
 
Blood was not just one of the humours , but was the substance that people 
believed carried heritable social characteristics do wn the generations. The 
proper flow of blood, in proper families, was felt to reproduce new people in 
proper places in the social order, in the social body. 
 
This idea was transferred to the Americas . 
 
But, now , geographical area became importan t. For the SPANISH COLONISTS there 
were three primary areas from which people could originate: EUROPE (Christendom),</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Because, in this system, women come into mens families though 
marriage, not the other way around. Women were considered the ones 
who could pollute the family line (while men could get mistresses 
pregnant, etc. without it reflecting on their family. 
 
this is a patrilineal patriarchal system  
   
So, control over women  was key to maintaining purity of blood.  
 
Whenever social position in a hierarchical society is attributed so-called racial and hence allegedly inherent, natural, and hereditary qualities, it is essential to control 
the reproductive capacity of its women in order to preserve its social preeminence. 
(p. 285). 
 
 This quotation is from 
 
Stolcke, Verena. 1994. Invaded Women. In Women, Race, and Writing in 
the Early Modern Period. Margo Hendricks and Patricia Parker, eds. London: 
Routledge, 272-286. 
 
in this system WOMEN have to SAFEGUARD RACIAL IDENTITYpotential traitors 
 MEN control WOMEN; men as paragons of racial identity   
 
I would add  that its with respect to particular  kinds of ideas about paternity and 
maternity and family; i.e. one in which men confer identity through their name (even 
as there is a sense of physical inheritance through both lines). ITS NOT NATURAL! Bastard is NOT a NATURAL category! 
 
So, lets pause: what is the racial format ion here? representation and organization? 
 
Representation: through religion, with the humours, and ideas about men and 
womens roles in so cial reproduction. 
 
Organization: a social hierarchy based on the religious past, the control of women by 
men, and geographical provenance of lineage. 
 
 
LINNEAUS AND THE FOUR FIXED RACES  
 
Back to Europe, where natural philosoph ers had continued their theories of 
geographical determinism. 
 
The founder of modern taxonomy, the Swi ss naturalist Carl Linn   also known as 
Linneaus  is important here. 
 
In 1758, Linneaus wrote Systema Naturae , in which he came up with the system of 
binomial naming  the designation of or ganisms by Latin genus and species name 
(like Homo sapiens , which he coined; and this is also, by the way, why Linn 
changed his name to Carolu s Linneaus, to fit into hi s own system. Wacky guy.) 
 
Linneaus sought to classify human varieties in this book  and he came up with 
four:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>AMERICA, and AFRICA  and so there were three major RACES of concern to them, 
which they called ESPANOL, INDIO, and NEGRO. 
 
By the end of the 1500s in the Americas, there had been intermarriage and mixture 
along with conversion to Chri stianity and the category th at was of real concern was 
MESTIZO.  
 
Mestizos  people who were the offspring of Spaniards and Indians [as they were 
called (remember, because Columbus was lo st!)]  held positions of power, but 
there was a big question amon g colonial rulers back in SPAIN about whether they 
could be TRUSTED. 
 
It was all about holding colonial office and being loyal to the people back in Spain. People who were too mixed migh t not be loyal. And that meant that colonial officials 
had to figure out what to do with them. So, people were cate gorized by LINEAGE. 
BLOOD was the symbol of FAMILY and LOYALTY . CATEGORIES of INTERMIXTURE 
 
So now the earlier GEOGRAPHIC DETERM INISM  with EUROPE, AMERICA, and 
AFRICA as the primary places of origin  joined PURITY OF BLOOD. And racial 
categories proliferated. RACE itself came in to existence. One etymology for the word, 
in Spanish, is RAZA. 
 
RAZA is from an old Spanish word, which initially referred to noble ancestry, though some say this meaning was later brought into juxtaposition with an older Castilian 
(Spanish) word which meant defect.  
 
The word "race" has been variously trac ed to the Latin ratio ("reason") or 
radix ("root"), and to the Hebrew for "head" or "origin," ras. Cf. Leo Spitzer. 
 
a. F. race, earlier also rasse (1512), a. It. razza = Sp. raza, Pg. raa, of 
obscure origin. 
 
In the context of the religious concerns of Inquisition Spain, where Jewish or Muslim 
ancestry was considered a defect, these meanings came together to make race 
about religious heritage. 
 
RACE itself came into existence as a SOCIAL CATEGORY. 
 
New Spain went crazy for race , for classifying everyone. I have some paintings here 
from the 1700s, which depict all the catego ries, and what happens when they mix. 
 
OVERHEAD 2: CATEGORIES OF INTERMIXTURE  
 
You might not be surprised to learn that ideas about GENDER were implicated in these ideas about PURITY OF BLOOD 
 
Women and men were posi tioned differently in  the social system. 
 
One Spanish Jurist put it this way: 
 
only women can bring bastards into the family  Why would that be? What 
kind of family is being talked about here?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21A.240  
Race and Science 
Spring 2004 MIT 
 
 
PART 1:  
THE ALCHEMY OF RACE: MAKING AND UNMAKING SCIENTIFIC RACISM 
Lecture 3. February 19 
 
I want us to look today at the rise of th e concept of race  with THREE things in 
mind: 
 
1. its transformation from a largely religious category  with origins in European 
Christendom  to a scienti fic category; were looking at major shifts in racial 
formations . 
 
2. the importance of sex, gender, and reproduction  for the consolidation of race 
across both religious and sci entific racial formations. 
 
3. skulls. 
 
What I want to do is explore this history of pre-scientific racial  formation and early 
scientific racial formation with you with the aid of the articles weve read, taking 
them mostly in order, but also  jumping back and forth a bit. 
 
Im going to start with a lecture, in which I will tell you about the invention of the 
concept of race in medieval Europe and how it gradually transformed from a religious 
category into one employed by scienti sts, or, as they were called natural 
philosophers. 
 
 
Blood, Sex, and Skeletons: Colonialism, Climatic Determinism, Cranial Capacity, and the Rise of Monogenist  and Polygenist Scientific Racism 
 
 
THE HUMORS AND GEOGRAPHICAL DETERMINISM  
 
In Medieval Christian Euro pe, it was believed that climate and geography could 
definitively determine peoples constitutions and dispositions. 
 
It was believed that there were four elements (earth, wi nd, and fire  and 
water) that corresponded to four humors  or fluids  in the human body: blood, phlegm, yellow bile (choler), an d black bile. The proper balance of 
these humors would lead to proper temperament, but improper balance would 
lead to a person being more or le ss SANGUINE, PHLEGMATIC, CHOLERIC, or 
MELANCHOLIC. 
 
OVERHEAD 1: HUMOURS  
 
European natural philosophers believed that different PLACES in the world 
were more or less suited to having a balance of humors, and some places 
would tilt you way out of balance. People thought that Asia, for example, was</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>when women WERE compared across racial  lines, it was always with respect 
to their sexual anatomy (particularly breasts and pelvis ) 
 
(I once heard Stephen Jay Gould remark that hed seen collections of great 
mens skulls in Europe, but never their penises). 
 
How did pelvises (pelvii?) enter into th e story? (pp. 157-158). First they were 
problematic (Africans appeared larger? ease of parturition), then they were 
tamed (Ease of parturition no longer suggested a larger African pelvis, but a smaller African skull[p. 158]). Finally they were used to solidify racial chain 
of being. But note what has to happen here  one must START with 
assumptions about the 
skull... 
 
So, again, how did women fit on the chain? 
 
Women and Africans were seen as sharing similar deficiencies when 
measured against a constant norm  the Elite European man (158). 
prognathism, for example. Stepans argument (1986 ISIS) detour.  
 
 
Stepan, Nancy. 1993. Race and Gender: the Role of Analogy in  Science. In The 
Racial Economy of Science: Toward a Democratic Future, Sandra Harding, ed. 
Bloomington: Indian a University Press, (pp. 359-376). 
 
metaphor  in science; analogy. Wh ats the argument here? 
 
that scientific description, often thought to be dispassionate and objective, often makes use of 
metaphors  and analogies: the metaphors functioned as 
the science itself; without them the science did not exist (p. 364). 
 
white women and non-white men: fe minine, juvenile, smaller heads 
 
Darwin says The female, in the formation of her skull, is said to be 
intermediate between the ch ild and the man (p. 317). 
 
established as signs of inferiority, the facial angle  could be then be 
extended analogically, to explain othe r inferior groups and races (p. 363) 
 
Schiebinger adds a step to  Stepans argument, though: This assessment (p. 
158), however, does not take into a ccount the contrasting ways in which 
European naturalists described women of different ethnic and cultural 
backgrounds.  
 
Schiebinger is arguing that females in general were considered a sexual 
subset of their race; unique female traits only served to confirm their racial 
standing (p. 160). 
 
While Stepans argument makes sense of some persistent regularities in European racial science, it  also assumes that the metaphorical grid within 
which things are seen is relatively airtight and self-consistent. It may not be. 
 
Schiebinger uses the story of Sarah Bartman   the so-called Hottentot Venus 
 to illustrate the ways that racial and sexual traits were crafted in concert.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>OVERHEAD 3: LINNEAUS FOUR RACES AND THEIR CHARACTERS 
 
EUROPEAUS   sanguineus 
ASIATICUS   melancholicus 
AMERICANUS  cholericus 
AFER    phlegmaticus 
 
Now, even though Linneaus has bequeathed  to us the naming system used in 
modern evolutionary biology, Linneaus himself  was a creationist and believed that 
these four categories had been created by God and that they were unchanging, fixed 
types (he was a POLYGENIST [believed in many origins]). As you read in the 
Hudson piece, online, Linneau ss rival Buffon was largely responsible for beginning to 
use the word race in this kind of classification. 
 
And Linneaus explicitly assigned to the di fferent varieties different temperaments, 
reaching back into the theory of humors. Europeans were sang uine, Asians were 
melancholy, Americans were choleric, Africans were phlegmatic. So, four geographic 
regions, four humor s, four races. 
 
 
BLUMENBACH, THE FIFTH RACE, AND THE FAMILY TREE
 
One of Linneaus students, Johann Friedrich BLUMENBACH elaborated this system in 
1795 in his book On the Natural Variety of Mankind , and he renamed the European 
as CAUCASIAN. WHY? 
 
On the basis of a new feature: the SKULL; less mutable, he thought. 
 
Blumenbach, also a creationist, thought th at the most perfect skulls belonged to 
people from around Mount Caucasus in what is now the nation-state of Georgia, in the former Soviet Union (whi ch he identified as part of Europe). These were the 
CAUCASIANS. He said of one female skull found in Georgia: really the most beautiful form of skull which  always of itself attracts every eye. 
 
Blumenbach reasoned that because these sku lls were the most beautiful, they must 
be a direct line to the first, perfect hum ans, Adam and Eve. Blumenbach believed 
that the Garden of Eden was near Mount Caucasus. 
 
After Adam and Eve got kicked out of Eden, their children diversified into the 
different races and some, according to  Blumenbach, DEGENERATED  in two BAD 
DIRECTIONS: ASIAN/MONGOLIAN and AFRI CAN/ETHIOPIAN; and, Blumenbach 
believed, AMERICANS were intermediate  between CAUCASIANS and ASIANS, and a 
new category  which Blumenbach invented  because he needed an intermediate 
form  the MALAY, were halfway between CAUCASIANS and AFRICANS. 
 
OVERHEAD 4: BLUMENBACHS FIVE RACES 
 
So, suddenly, with FIVE RACES, the id ea of the four humors goes away. 
 
We get the image of a FAMILY TREE   with some branches reaching up and others 
straggling off to the side.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Germ Plasm: American and British Eugenics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-240-race-and-science-spring-2004/resources/lecnotes_02_26/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>group one will focus on Galton, Pearson, Davenport 
group two on eugenic policies  sterilization, IQ testing 
group three on reform eugenics and the instability of race 
 
*** 
 
GROUP ONE  
 
Galton  coined eugenics  
Hereditary Genius 1869, interested in MEN and their BRAINS, reputation flows from 
heredity 
page 6, 11: phrenology and humoral balanc e of Galton (older racial parameters!), 
interest in Hottentots, shapes of skulls 
 
Whenever you can, count.  (p. 7) wanted to use STATISTICS to understand 
heredity (and note that the word statistics, denoted, in Galtons time, state 
numbers  indices of population, trade, manufacture, and the link  the gathering 
of which aided the state in the shaping of sound public policy (p. 12). variation from 
the mean . 
 
This use of STATISTICS factored out the CA USES of variation, ASSUMING them to be 
HEREDITARY. 
 
 For Galton the scientist, the profession al classes were the prime repository of 
ability and civic virtue, and his eugenics made them the keystone of a biological program designed to lead to the creation of a conservative meritocracy (p. 9) so, 
aristocracy and working-class not as good. 
 
believed in regression to the mean: It was in consequence impossible that the 
natural qualities of a race  may be permanently change d through the action of 
selection on mere variation (this was actually against Darwins theory).  
 
 what is A RACE here? an archetype, a fixed thing. 
 SCIENCE measures it objectively... 
 
Pearson  
British socialist background 
In Pearsons view, Darwinism buttressed Herb ert Spencers doctrine of individualism 
and provided a justification of laissez-faire capitalism. But in the England of the 1880s, reformers were forging Darwinism in to a weapon against laissez-faire. 
Pearson soon followed suit, by  substituting competition between national groups for 
individual struggle Pears on came to equate morality with the advancement of 
social evolution, the outcome of the Darw inian struggle with the ascendancy of the 
fittest nation (p. 23). 
NATION is often used synonymously with RACE . 
 
enabled by the fact that Pearson seek s to measure RACIAL DIFFERENCE through 
STATISTICS, numbers generated by the STAT E, which is the representative of the 
NATION. 
 
Nation should be bred from the best  stocks (p. 32). PROFESSIONAL CLASS.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Pearson felt that capitalism was to blame fo r the deterioration of Britain; the demand 
for cheap labor pressed poor people to have many children. Private charity was 
worse still, and encouraged continued profligacy on the part of the poor. Natural 
selection, he believed, had been suspended and replaced by reproductive selection 
which gave the battle to the most fertile, not the most fit (p. 34). 
 
CONTRADICTION HERE? 
 
Place of women  in Pearsons theory? (Male Female cl ub). Socialist ideas, supporter of 
womens rights, sexual eman cipation, voluntary motherhood.  Only if women had 
full education, job opportunities, sexual educ ation, reproductive options, could they 
freely make eugenic mate choi ces (if they could support themselves, they wouldnt 
be forced to marry prematurely; if they ha d scientific training, they could tell a good 
man when they saw one). 
 
The views of British eugenicists like Pearso n incarnated prevalent British ideas about 
the differences between classe s; much of this had to do  with upper and middle class 
prejudices about unfettered lower class sexuality. 
 
What is RACE here? national eugenics: the  study of agencies under social control 
that may improve or impair the racial  qualities of future generations either physically 
or mentally (p. 37).  
 
race is nation, race is a general category of physicality. vague.  
 
Davenport  
In the US, concerns with race mixture an d with the possible de generation of Euro-
American stock came into vogue as the US  was infiltrated by  immigrants from 
Eastern Europe. 
 
Charles Davenport founded a eugenics rese arch center (this meant starting an 
archive of human pedigrees [useful for tracing inheritance of Mendelian units 
{Davenports eugenics was somewhat different from Pear sons and Galtons which 
were more biometric}]) in 1904 at Cold Spring Harbor. 
 
Davenport believed that immigrants (races like Jews, Irish Catholics, Italians, etc) 
threatened the nations germ plasm. 
 
Aside about Weismann  sequestered germ cell line . disallowed Lamarckian 
inheritance (define). But used to buttr ess claims about genetic essentialism, 
dismissing environment. 
 
so, germ plasm, protoplasm, became a racial essence. 
 
protoplasm as a scientific term  that also functioned as cultural representation of 
genetic essence  
 
Like many of his colleagues, Davenport eq uated national and racial identity, and 
assumed as well that race determined behavior . He held that the Poles, the Irish, the 
Italians, and other national groups were all biologically different races; so, in his 
lexicon, were the Hebrews (p. 46).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Believed that the European nations sent over disproportionately large numbers of 
the worst human stock (p. 51). 
 
Good human stock to be found in the middle-class. 
 
NEGATIVE EUGENICS: immigration restriction, sterilization 
 
Davenport also advocated wh at was to become the mainline eugenics view of the 
role of women in population betterment: motherhood in the se rvice of the nation, 
the race  (often completely conflated [actually, I dont think conflated is the right 
word; nation and race are not empirically di stinct things waiting to be conceptually 
decoupled; as categories, th ey were mutually constitute d, and though now we think 
it important to distinguish them, I think it was by no means clear at the turn of this 
century how they were going to get delineated ]). Women should not enter higher 
education because this would divert their energies from their natural duties (this 
Victorian stuff wont go away). 
 
GROUP TWO  
Gospel becomes popular: people filling out records of family traits, to be sent to 
Davenport. local organizations, lik e the Race Betterment Foundation 
 
Fitter families contests at Kansas fair. 
 
Eugenics congresses with illustrious participants.  race hygiene (what is RACE? 
seems to oscillate between meaning the HUMAN RACE, a NATION, those people who 
are or should be MOST REPRESENTATIVE OF THE HUMAN RACE. This oscillation, this slippage is HOW race comes to mean so ma ny things; it becomes a flexible term. As 
a cultural representation, it becomes extraordinarily fluid. 
 
The continued use of STATISTICS continues to conflate environment, heredity, and 
ideas about things. In Omi and Winants terms, we could see this as a tool for 
cultural representation , a tool that appears to be objec tive because it is quantified 
and backed up by credentialed experts wh o claim that they are best suited to 
interpret it. 
 
def of civilization in Britannica : The organic betterment of the race through wise 
application of the laws of heredity (p. 63). 
 
RACE seems to be slipping in and out of  synonymy with NATION, SPECIES and the 
location of racial esse nce is in PROTOPLASM. 
 
NATURE  a source of moral  lessons: a cultural representation filtered through 
science  
 
Diversity of ideological attachments to  the project; DIFFERENT RACIAL/CLASS 
PROJECTS 
 
social-radical wing: abolish class difference and the best stocks will be revealed! (87) 
suffragettes: women need to  be allowed independence so they can make eugenic 
decisions 
mainline: women are baby-machines, cla ss distinction must be kept in place</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>(contrast between social-radicals and mainline: is kind of like sexual selection ideas 
in Darwin -- like animals and humans!) 
 
belief that artificial selection was replacing natural selection in human evolution )(p. 71). 
 
CONTRADICTORY IDEAS about FITNESS 
 
what does KEVLES suggest are the social causes of EUGENICS in US? 
 
idea that immigrants were breeding more  in US, that they were breeding from 
less fit portions of their group. idea that these social inefficient were taking 
TAXPAYERS MONEY. WELFARE. SOCIAL STUCTURAL CONCERNS 
 
At the beginning of the century, there wa s a decline in the US white birth rate 
owing to urbanization, and Teddy Roosevelt in ferred from this that the upper-class in 
the US was committing race suicide and that race purity must be maintained. (p. 
74). Early 20th century feminist projects of  birth control were often co-opted into 
this rhetoric and what was a right for the privileged became a duty for the poor (Angela Davis 1981). 
 
Irish Catholics become a race in part because of ideas about their supposed 
rampant reproductivity? 
 
Aside about Margaret Sanger  
Margaret Sanger, initially a socialist who saw birth control as a necessary step in womens emancipation, saw the bearing and rearing of many children as the cause 
of womens oppression. 
 
As time went on Sanger brought her conc erns with birth cont rol for middle-class 
women into line with a concern about population control for minority and lower-class 
women. 
 
When Sanger left the socialist party, he r ideas became more connected to eugenic 
ideas. In 1919, Sanger summarized one of the goals of birth control thus: more children from the fit, less from the unfit (p . 90) (this designated  mental defectives, 
etc) (In 1939, she and others planned a Neg ro Project which was aimed at reducing 
the birth rate among blacks {Sangers whol e position on this was kind of complex 
[well, not really]: she claimed that while n egroes were not inferior to whites, the 
sector of the negro population which was reproducing the fastest was that sector 
which least knew how to exercise prudent choice about how many offspring to have; 
the negro project would target these people. 
 
In sterilization  of the feeble-minded, a large numbe r of poor people were targeted, 
as you saw. Given the racial hierarchy of the US, this also meant that large numbers 
of Negroes and Indians were sterilized. 
 
 If natural selection yielded the Darwinian fit, only artificial selection, - by 
governmental means, where appropriate - could multiply the eugenically fit. 
 
IQ 
mental age/chronological age</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>contrast with earlier uses of STATISTICS  
 
Their eugenic ideas were co nnected less to class and ra ce issues than those of 
mainline eugenicists.  Muller, Haldane, and Huxley believed in  conscious social 
direction of human biological evolution, an d they thought that they were developing 
the tools to understand how to weed out de leterious alleles (population genetics had 
excellent mathematical models for single locus genetic traits), which manifested 
themselves in undesirable phenotypes. 
 
On the way to the revolution, some few things might be done ; eugenic counseling 
might aid couples in deciding if they wanted to bear children together; the state 
might help eugenically fit families finance having kids (this sense that fitness is best judged by humans rather than in the co urt of reproductive  success continued); 
mental deficients might be sterilized (now that I list it, it all sounds very much like the usual totalitarian project). 
 
FISHER 
RA Fisher had a bizarre idea to help fit families {those hereditarily intelligent 
enough to abstain from reproducing in a social environment which punished them 
for doing so [no accident, I suppose that their intelligence would be served by a refined moral sense [but too bad it went along with low fertility; how paradoxical and 
troubling!]]}: Fisher suggested governmental support for eugenically fit families that would guarantee them no drop in standard of living with more children; if it took an 
upper class family $100,000 to raise one kid,  the government should provide them 
with $100,000 if they decide d to have another one). 
 
the eugenic paradox: If success in the Darwinian sense meant high fertility rates, then in modern Western society evolutio nary success went toge ther with social 
failure, and social success with evolutionary defeat (p. 182). 
 
Fisher: Professionals we re destroying their racial stoc k as rapidly as any communist 
would wish to see the intelligentsia extirpated  
 
The eagerness to foster higher fertility among the eugenically valuable fortified 
reform eugenicists in their embrace of me lioriative economic measures or socialist 
reconstruction. Yet to some on the eugeni c left, particularly biologists, social 
measures would not by themselves make the eugenicists utopian dream of mans 
eugenic improvement a reality. (Kevles 1985). 
 
For Muller and Haldane, a sexu al revolution needed to ha ppen alongside a social and  
scientific revolution. So, explicit talk of race starts to vanish. BUT ideas about 
gender, roles of women and men dont change too much. 
 
Next time : 
were going to go back in history somewh at and look at another venue in which 
science was making pronouncem ents about race, this time anthropology  led by 
Franz Boas in early 20th century and sociology of W.E.B. DuBois. This is a parallel 
history and I want us to think about some of the ways the category of race was 
distinguished from culture   and therefore reified  in the context of debates about 
American belonging, immigration.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21A.240  
Race and Science 
Spring 2004 MIT 
 
 
PART 1:  
THE ALCHEMY OF RACE: MAKING AND UNMAKING SCIENTIFIC RACISM 
Lecture 4. February 26 
 
In three weeks, PAPER # 1 is DUE. Let me give you a sense of how to think about it. 
I write on the syllabus: Students will write three 7-page papers, choosing from a 
selection of topics to be provided by the instructor for each paper. What kinds of 
topics will those be? Let me give you a sense of what these might be like  just so you can start to tune in. Ill pr ovide the real topics next time. 
 
1. Explain the place of sex, gender , and reproduction in two eugenic 
movements/moments docu mented by Kevles. 
 
2. Discuss similarities and di fferences between Boas and Du Bois on matters of race 
classification and science. Consider contexts of immigration, segregation, and health. 
 
3. Compare and contrast notions of racial hygiene in Brazilian and Nazi/German eugenics. Be sure to discuss the plac e of the nation in each case. 
 
4. Use Bowker and Stars ideas about Aristo telian and prototypical  classification to 
examine the workings of race for Blumenbach, Boas, and Gould.  
 
Germ Plasm: American and British Eugenics 
 
Kevles, Daniel J. 1995. In the Name of Eugenics: Genetics and the Uses of Human 
Heredity. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, chapters  I-IX, XI-XIII (pp. 3-147, 
164-211). 
 
This is a big book with lots of history, taking us from early social Darwinism through mid-20th century population ge netics. Some of this later stuff I had you read wont 
be directly relevant to today, but sets the st age for later history well do in this class. 
 
Anyway, we need to think about how to ma ke all of this history manageable for 
discussion.  
 
So, I have a plan  one which will get us through the different positions enunciated 
in the history of eugenics, allow us to th eorize some the histor y weve read about, 
and also allow you to get to know each other some more. 
 
Divide into three groups: 
 
Galton-Pearson-Davenport chapters 1-3
 
Gospel becomes Popula r-Eugenic Enactments chapters 4-7
 
False Biology, A Reform Eugenics-Brave New Biology chapters 9, 11-12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>**** 
 
I would like each group to consider the following questions collectively. What Ill do is 
give you about 20 minutes to discuss these amongst yourself. At the end of that 
time, well hear a summary from each group. These should be about 15 minutes or 
so. 
 
1. What are some continuities  and discontinuities  between the theories and practices 
of the eugenics movements youve read abou t in the chapters for which your group 
is responsible and the racial  ideas that we looked at last time (in terms of 
sex/gender, class, nation)? Think also about differences and similarities from earlier 
eugenics, if youre in groups 2 or 3. 
 
2. To use Omi and Winants terms, can you characterize the racial projects  of the 
different people Kevles writes about? And can you identify the racial formation  of 
which they were a part? 
 
Let me refresh your memory on Omi and Winant: 
 
We define racial formation  as the sociohistorical proce ss by which racial categories 
are created, inhabited, transf ormed, and destroyed. (p. 55) 
 
we argue that racial formation is a proce ss of historically situated projects in 
which human bodies and soci al structures are repres ented and organized. (p. 
56). from a racial formation perspe ctive, race is a matter of both social 
structure  and cultural representation  (p. 56). Racial formations are made of 
racial projects . A racial project is simultaneously an interpretation, 
representation, or explanatio n of racial dynamics, and an effort to reorganize 
and redistribute resour ces along particular racial lines (p. 56). 
 
Now, you may have noticed that race as  such figures differently in different 
moments, and you might see something like class or nation eclipsing or 
overdetermining race sometimes; so, feel free to speak about class 
formation, too. Because Kevles is a co mparative history of the US and the UK, 
some of these differenc es are not surprising. 
 
3. Can you say something about the relationship between science  and race in these 
moments; how does science construct  or deconstruct  race? And as part of that, tell 
us something about the various meanings of race  you detect in the periods youre 
responsible for. You might even pick out passages in which that term is used. 
 
Just a few comments about Kevles: As yo u may have noticed,  he organizes his 
history around individual people  kind of Great Man theory of history, even when the men arent so great! And he uses the word Man to stand for humanity, which is 
annoying. And he often offers a kind of  psychological explanation for peoples 
adherence to eugenics.... Im asking you to squeeze out a more sociological, historical, theoretical story by asking you to use Omi and Winant. 
 
So, about 20 minutes to discuss these question s, search for quotes, etc. Then well 
hear a report from each group  try to get everyone to speak; however you like (by chapter, question, etc.). If you can think of any questions youd like to discuss with 
the class as you go along, things youre no t sure of, interesting ambiguities that you 
think we can talk about, do that.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Army IQ tests as the fit really signif icant contribution to the study of race 
differences in mental traits (p. 82). 
 
RACE starts to be associated with differe nces in INTELLIGENCE. measurement again. 
IQ as heritable. national decline became a decline in Intelligence. Again, concerns of 
the professional academic class interested  in these things became the measure for 
all. 
 
critics; Catholics against biological reductionism 
 
GROUP THREE  
 
Reform Eugenics: politics on the left and right  
There begins to be dissonance between  eugenics and the new genetics. Human 
genetics begins to be trea ted mathematically, statistics are no longer about an 
inferred heredity, indirectly  assayed though family hi stories, but about gene 
frequencies. Mathematical models of how genes work in populations can be tested 
against statistical data. 
 
Human genetics (and gene tics generally) were brought under the yoke of 
mathematics, and evolution, long described from the point of view of reproductively successful individuals and pros perous or declining species, came to be described as 
changes in gene frequenc ies over generations.  
 
Many of the population geneticists involved in this revamping were socialist 
eugenicists  [NOT R.A. Fisher]. These reform euge nicists, as Kevles  calls them, were 
confident that eugenics programs could work  to better the species, but that real 
hereditary inequality couldnt be properly seen until the social pl aying field was even; 
not till there was a classless society could eugenics make any sense . 
 
Because these people didnt buy idea that ex isting social divisions by ra ce and class 
were determined by innate inequality, they favored talk of populations to talk of 
race. (p. 175).
 
In weird way, these ideas lay behind th is notion of EUTELEGENESIS(p. 188). You 
really COULD treat people as though they were just bags of ge nes (of course what 
this does is fetishize sperm). 
 
Evelyn Fox Keller has discerned in this a masculine bias of mathematical 
population genetics. In this discourse, all individuals are structurally equal, all 
just bags of genes. Keller writes that, Effectively bypassed with this representation were all the problems entailed by sexual difference, by the 
contingencies of mating and fertilization that resulted from the finitude of actual populations and also, simultaneo usly, all the ambiguities of the term 
reproduction as applied to organisms that neither make copies of themselves nor reproduce by themselves (1992b:132). 
 
 Brewer called eutelegenesis the the socialization of the germ plasm (p. 
190). 
 
population genetics: a cultural representation part of a racial project that 
sought in part to dismiss prevailing race prejudice as misleading about actual 
genetic facts</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Skin Color, Bodily Form: Laws of Science and Laws of the Land in the Context of Immigration, Assimilation and Early 20th-Century American Anthropology (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-240-race-and-science-spring-2004/resources/lecnotes_03_04/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21A.240  
Race and Science 
Spring 2004 MIT 
 
 
PART 1:  
THE ALCHEMY OF RACE: MAKING AND UNMAKING SCIENTIFIC RACISM 
Lecture 5. March 4 
 
Summary of so far : Close weave between theo ries of race and ideas about proper or 
natural SEX/GENDER  roles and behaviors. Weve seen  this all the way from early 
pre-scientific ideas about race  through Darwin on sexual selection up to eugenics. 
 
Concerns with measuring the relative worth  of races  first through ranking on the 
great chain of being, then through craniome try, then through an assessment of their 
evolutionary fitness. 
 
Weve looked at changing SUBSTANCES  of race. 
 
Last time, we looked at the history of eugenics in the United States and in Britain, 
which showed us how ideas about race we re articulated to ideas about NATION and 
CLASS. And today , I want us to look at two histories PARALLEL to eugenics. These 
are: 
 
1. history of race in early American anthropology and sociology (Baker, Boas) 
and 
2. histories of immigration, citizenship law (Jacobson) 
 
Youll have noticed from the Jacobson re adings on American nativism, and the 
American making of the term Caucasian as a scientific synonym for white, 
anthropological visions  and revisions  of race take place in political context  of 
American debates about IMMIGRATION and CITIZENSHIP and more particularly about IMMIGRATION and CITIZENSHIP 
LAW
 
So, American anthropology comes into existence amidst anxieties and debates about 
racial categories and the political an d legal debates about immigration.  
 
I want you to see these two histories as contexts for one another   looking at how 
racial categories created in public debate about immigrat ion, for example, affected 
how anthropology took on the categories AND looking at how public discourse about 
immigration and citizenship drew from, ignored, or reshaped anthropological 
categories. 
 
In thinking about these two histories as mutually constitutive CONTEXTS, Its useful 
to reflect on what W.E.B. Du Bois said about RACE: perhaps it is wrong to speak of 
race at all as a concept, rather than as  a group of contradictory forces, facts and 
tendencies (Baker 1997: p. 112). This as a call to understand race not simply as 
an idea, but as a messy part of everyday life. 
 
So, If our past two classes have been tryi ng to get you to think about how scientific 
articulations of race also have simultaneously spoken in the registers of gender,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The LAMARCKIAN: inheritance of acquired characteristics, co uldnt distinguish 
between cultural and biol ogical inheritance (before ideas about heredity). 
POLYGENISM: idea that God had cr eated human groups separately 
EVOLUTIONISM: but with idea that so me groups are more evolved than 
others. 
 
It was all of these that FRANZ BOAS  was interested in demolishing. 
 
How? 
 
1. Separate biology from culture. 
 
2. Use Darwinian theory to refute Lamarck, 
 
3. Argue for the unity of humanity 
 
4. Argue that evolution does not imply ranking (that is an old great chain of 
being idea) and that cultures must be studied on their own terms. 
 
Lets go back to Halls idea about 
 
"The combination of racial bloods is not a mere matter of biology or 
physiology...because physical inheritance does not include mere physical 
mingling of the bloods, but [also] that subtle atmosphere of associations, of 
home traditions, of family recollections and ideals and aims, that are so inseparable." 
 
Boas would SEPARATE these strands 
 
RACE, LANGUAGE, and CULTURE have different  histories. 
 
Boas is responsible for defining CULTUR E in the way we think about it today. 
Before Boas, CULTURE meant opera, oil paintings  and only Europeans had 
it. 
 
But, having separated CULTURE from BIOLOGY, what did this make RACE for 
BOAS? See his 1913 article, in which he demonstrates that children of 
immigrants to US look different from their parents. (an intervention in 
immigration debates) 
 
What did RACE become for BOAS? Plastic 
 
Whats really tricky here is that RACE still exists for BOAS 
 
 -MOVEOVER, RACE IS always negative for BOAS. 
 
This means that hes still trapped in the game  that there is something 
there in biology; hes still using the categories of his day (see Baker 119) 
 
W.E.B. DU BOIS  had a different approach. What was it? 
 
perhaps it is wrong to speak of race at all as a concept, rather than as a 
group of contradictory forces, facts and tendencies (Baker 1997: p. 112).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>classification employ ed by those in power to cons olidate social hierarchy (see 
discussion in Jacobson): 
 
Ozawa  (1922): you may be white, but you are not Caucasian science 
Thind  (1923): you may be Caucasian, but you are not white common-sense 
 
Caucasian did accomplish something that the more casual notion of 
whiteness could not: it brought the full authority of science to bear on white 
identity. (p. 94).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>class, nation, and state, today, I want you to think about the relation between 
SCIENCE, RACE, AND LAW. 
 
 
Skin Color, Bodily Form: Laws of Sc ience and Laws of the Land in the 
Context of Immigration, Assimilation and Early 20th-Century American 
Anthropology 
 
Jacobson, Matthew Frye. 1998. Race and Amer ican Nativism, from  Anglo-Saxons and 
Others, 1840-1924. In Whiteness of a Different  Color: European Immigrants and the 
Alchemy of Race. Cambridge: Harvar d University Press, pp. 68-90. 
 
Stocking, George, Jr. 1994. The Turn -of-the-Century Concept of Race. 
Modernism/Modernity 1:1: pp. 4-16. 
 
Baker, Lee. 1997. Rethinking Race at the Turn of the Century: W.E.B. Du Bois and 
Franz Boas. In From Savage to Negro: An thropology and the Construction of Race, 
1896-1954. Berkeley: University of California Press, pp. 99-126. 
 
Boas, Franz. 1913. Changes in Bodily Form of Descendents of Immigrants. In Race, 
Language and Culture. New York: Th e Free Press/Macmillan, 1966, pp. 60-75. 
 
Jacobson, Matthew Frye. 1998. Becomin g Caucasian, 1924-1965 &amp; Naturalization 
and the Courts. In Whiteness of a Different Color: European Immigrants and the Alchemy of Race. Cambridge: Harvard Un iversity Press, pp. 91-109, pp. 223-240. 
 
 
ANTHROPOLOGY AND SOCIOLOGY  
 
Lets start with the Stocking piece: 
 
G. Stanley Hall, president of Clark University, remarking on a paper he heard in 1895 on "The Scotch-Irish in America"  
 
made it clear that much more was involved in the "commingling of bloods" than simply physical charac teristics. "The combination of racial bloods is not a 
mere matter of biology or physiology...because physical inheritance does not include mere physical mingling of the bloods, but [also] that subtle 
atmosphere of associations, of home traditions, of family recollections and ideals and aims, that are so inseparable." 
 
"Blood"--and by extension "race"--inclu ded numerous elements  that we would 
today call cultural; there was not a clear line between cultural and physical elements or between social  and biological heredity 
 
Stocking is showing us how many, di fferent, separate fe atures of human 
social life are confused, confla ted by Hall, mixed together. 
 
Stocking argues that there were four traditions of thinking about human 
difference that were used 
 
The ETHNOLOGICAL: language, food, custom, etc,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Race is fully sociological; invented in the context of power and inequality. (p. 
111). 
 
And THIS is where the context of I MMIGRATION LAW in the UNITED STATES 
during this period comes in. 
 
 
IMMIGRATION AND NATURALIZATION  
 
The concept of race forged and re-forge d in the context of who could count as 
a citizen capable of rati onal self-government an d immigration debates. 
 
1840-1924, question of who could be a Citizen of the US depended upon 
whether people were considered capable of self-government, organized 
around what we would now call region al/national identities (Germanic, 
Mediterranean, Hebrew, Irish, Italian,  etc.) but which back then were 
racialized  identities. 
 
To naturalize  and note the word! Ge tting citizenship AS IF being born in 
US (US grants citizenship on birth on land  not all nations do this; e.g. 
Germany): 
 
1790 any alien being a free white person 
1870 added aliens of Afri can nativity and person s of African descent 
1882: Chinese Exclusion Act, explicitly  excluded Chinese, (who had been 
coming from Canton because of the Go ld Rush in California) lasts until 1943 
[about when Japanese internment starts!)) 
 
Celts, Hebrews, Italians becoming less white in terms of who should appear 
on shore, but more white in terms of who could be citizens (p. 75). 
 
Immigration Restriction League 1893 (p. 77). 
 
anti-miscegenation laws  (some state laws on books until 1967, 1948 in CA) 
 
some of these laws specified that  a US citizen woman, if she  
married an alien ineligible for citizenship would lose her citizenship 
(only other thing you lose citizenship for is TREASON)  
treated women as property of a race; white women property of white 
men. 
 
of a piece with anti-immi gration laws, regulating reproduction of the 
nation and its favored constituents. 
 
also kept races distinct by forc ing immigrant groups into their own 
communities, thereby reproducing co mmunities of people who were 
judged according to those categories. 
 
Davenport: nation as race  at Cold Spring Harbor 
 
1907 gentlemens agreement: stopped immi gration of Japanese people to US.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>1911 Dillingham Commission Report on Races and Peoples ; used 
Blumenbachs 5 races, but also reco gnized 45 races among immigrants 
coming to the US (p. 78). (p. 79: quote of use in analyzing Boas 1913!!! 
[names the very categories hes using] ). 
 
Dillingham commission saw immigrants as parents  of future Americans (since 
citizenship is conferred by birth!), and so inquired into their fitness to be 
included in national germ plasm ( eugenic  concern) (pp. 82-83). 
 
1924: Johnson Act: 2% quotas for immigrants based on 1890 census. 
 
After 1924, a shift from ranking specific races like Mediterranean or Irish 
to the beginning of the consolidation of  a Caucasian racial formation; all 
these types BECOME Caucasian.  
 
Caucasian supposedly a mo re scientific term than white (more than 
skin-deep) [Jacobson p. 94] 
 
Race politics get reorgani zed around black-white 
 
as scientists asserted over and over  that Aryans, Jews, Italians, 
Nordics, and the like were not races , their myriad assertions themselves all 
buttressed an edifice founded upon three grand divisions of mankind 
Caucasian, Mongoloid, and Negroid  whose differences by implication 
were racial (Jacobson p. 103) 
 
Races of Mankind exhibit 1943: nationa lities are not races, the Jews are not 
a race, etc. what is an American? EXHIBIT WAS A LESSON IN CIVICS . 
 
Naturalization and the Courts 
 
Why is whiteness so important, legally? 
its about assignation of property rights 
whiteness AS property (Lockean property  in self, and right to own property)  
legal disputes: Hey, Im white! 
 
Between the 1870s and the 1920s the court generated their own 
epistemology of race that drew fr om scientific doctri ne, from popular 
understanding, from historical reasonin g, from common-sense ideas, from 
geography, from precedent (p. 226 quote) 
 
Ah Yup 1878 applied to be white: judge said that he was Mongolian and 
couldnt be Caucasian 
Halladjian  1909 Armenians judged white becaus e they were Caucasian even 
if not European but their inclusion was still based on the fact they were lighter than many Europeans  like th e Portuguese  and also that white 
meant anyone who wasnt African 
 
Lets take a look in depth at two famous court cases in which people sought to be classified as whi te/Caucasian in order to naturalize as citizens. 
These demonstrate the slide between  Aristotelian and Prototypical</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Health and Hygiene: Latin American Lamarckism, Nazi German Darwinism (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-240-race-and-science-spring-2004/resources/lecnotes_03_11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>NOW, were NOT going to work this qu estion out; the question of WHY the 
Holocaust happened is perennial  was it  modernity, capitalism, misreadings 
of Darwin, fascism, hum an nature, Germanness? We wont be able to get at 
that. We cannot in this class answer WHY the unspeakable horror of the 
Holocaust happened in any definitive way. 
 
what we might  be able to speculate a bit more  on  what is more germane to 
our purposes  is another  question about COMPLICITY: 
 
B. WHY didnt SCIENTISTS/ANTHROPOLOGISTS do anything? Or WHY did it 
take them so long? What was the role of anthropology and human biological 
science in Nazi Germany? 
 
These are the questions taken up by the Proctor and the Barkan. Proctor 
argues, against the grain of the usual sch olarship, that Nazi  notions of race 
science were not completely different from ideas in circulation elsewhere. 
Indeed, he argues that our attempts to  label Nazi race science as pseudo-
science excuses us from giving a proper historical  account of how science 
functions in social and political context. Id like us to start, then, with the Proctor. 
 
PROCTOR:  begins by asking: How could it happen? (p. 199). 
 
Anthropologie  had come to be seen as providing a cure for many of the ills 
facing German society (p. 145). Mende lian genetics was used as a warrant 
for the idea that these ills were fixed in different lineages of people, were 
essential to racial germ plasms. 
 
Characterize Eugen Fischers  ideas about RACE (p. 146). 
 
Fischer believed that physical and spiritual racial traits were inherited 
according to classical Mendelian inheritance by independent assortment 
 
Races mix without blending. Races might mix, but they could never blend. 
So, the Jews were a mixture of the Oriental and the African 
 
INTERESTING that the dominant traits are those from the lower races (see 
chart on p. 159). THIS is wh at leads to degeneration. 
 
Whats striking here is the incredible flexibility of the race concept. Different stereotypes can be deployed  at different moments. 
 
And of course, in order to do this ki nd of racial science, there must be 
categories. And here we see what Bo wker and Star characterized as the 
mixing of Aristotelian and prototypical categories. 
 
Eugen Fischer said that it was dangerou s to advance a political cause in the 
name of science or to conflate science with po litical doctrine (p. 173). 
 
Obviously, this is hypocrisy. But it actually rephrases Proctors argument that Nazi race science was not an anomaly insofar as it was shot through with</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>and infant welfare and made commo n cause with campaigns against 
alcoholism, tuberculosis and VD (p. 81)  (intoxicants as sources of racial 
decay. Alcoholism) Eugenics came  to mean heath in general. 
 
Principles of public health  were extended into the sciences of heredity. Goal 
was the prevention of the environmen t from being a source of hereditary 
degradation in humans and the sanitization and civilization of the 
reproductive instinct (p. 80) 
 
So, what was RACE here in this notion of the RACIAL POISON? 
Population/nation that could be transf ormed by proper social hygiene. How 
would you compare this to the eugenic pr ojects we looked at in the Kevles? 
 
LAMARCKISM 
 
Why was Lamarckism popular in Latin America? (p. 64) 
 
Belief that social environm ent and health care coul d affect germ plasm was 
congenial to the medical  sciences, which dominate d scientific di scussion in 
Brazil. 
 
Desire to believe that changes in so cial environment would have lasting 
effects (p. 73). 
 
Politically, neo-Lamarckism also often came tinged with an optimistic expectation that reforms of the social milieu would result in permanent 
improvement, an idea in keeping with the environmentalist-sanitary tradition 
that had become fashionable in the area (p. 73). 
 
A complex mixture emerged, with Darwinism responsible for natural selection 
and Lamarckism responsible for the ori gin of the fittest Human effort had 
meaning, progress could occur. This was embedded in the Brazilian ideology of order and progress 
  
It ALSO provided a flexible model of disease etiology that underscored the 
physicians own agency. (p. 75) Also seemed to explain heredity of congenital 
syphilis and alcoholism. 
 
Why else might this be important in Brazil at this time? And Latin America more generally? 
 
Brazil had been used as an example of the deleterious effect s of race mixing 
 
Lamarckism was an interesting way to argue against geographical determinist 
views of tropical climates leading to degeneration (itself a kind of Lamarckism!) 
 
many Latin American hygienists turned to the gains made in sanitation to 
challenge the traditional view that race and climate in Latin America combined 
to produce degraded and backward nations (p. 89) 
 
The Brazilians said: The tropical environment itself might actually be a 
salutary force. Its only dysgenic so cial surrounds that produce degeneration.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>4. racial ideologies already in place.  The idea that Brazil was a mixture of 
European, Indian and African races . Brazil was also interpreted by 
Europeans as a site of tropical  decay and racial dege neration (remember the 
humours ?). Brazilian eugenics had to engage with these ideas, either by 
embracing them, sidestepping or comp licating them, or somehow reversing 
them. 
 
Perhaps a good way into discussing Brazilian eugenics  and its differences 
from the US and European versions weve looked at is to reflect on Stepans 
quotation of a contemporary British auth ors reflection on the matter (p. 64) 
 
Apparently the Brazilians interpret the word eugenics less strictly than we 
do, and make it cover a good deal of what we should call hygiene and 
elementary sexology, and no very clear distinction is drawn between 
congenital conditions due to prenatal injury and diseases which are strictly 
genetic.
 
Stepan argues that this was not simply the result of Brazilian science being 
behind European and U.S. scien ce. In European and US eugenics 
remember, genes and environment had been differentiated  into distinct 
domains. 
 
CULTURE/BIOLOGY: the division in the US around which people would fight.  
 
Weismann had shown the germ line to  be independent of somatic line 
 
Mendel had supplied the rules by which genes sort themselves in heredity. Latin American eugeni cs didnt fully buy into these findings.  
 
Boas had tried to DIFFUSE RACE as a category, arguing that BIOLOGY is 
plastic. 
 
What happened in Latin America, and in Brazil more specifically?  
 
Exploring the idea of RACIAL POISON  might be a useful way to get at this 
stuff. What was a racial poison?  
 
These poisons were called racial beca use, though the habits and diseases 
were often first acquired in one individuals lifetime, they were believed to 
lead to permanent, hereditary degeneration that in the long run could affect 
entire populations or nations (p. 85). 
 
How was this poison to be und erstood to affect heredity? 
 
Tradition of Peuriculture: poisons present at the moment of conception 
had negative effects on th e germinal materials (p. 78) mother-child unit the 
focus of attention (thi s idea from France). 
 
Eschewing a hard and fast distinction between heredity and the environment, [Latin American doctors] paid considerable attention to the 
milieu in which reproduction occurred, because it was seen as a source of reproductive poisons that  could have disastrous consequences for future 
generations. So, eugenics became linked to obstetri cs, population policies,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>politics; so was the counter-argument. Bu t this of course doesnt make them 
completely symmetrical, either. 
 
Barkan, Elazar. 1988. Mobilizing Scientis ts against Nazi Racism, 1933-1939. In 
Bones, Bodies, Behavior. George Stocking, ed. Madison: University of Wisconsin 
Press, 180-205. 
 
what obstacles did Boas meet in trying  to get a statement about race made 
by the associations of which he was a part and by the scien tific community in 
general? 
 
people to whom he turned did not want these issues brought into the realm of 
politics. And Boas, as a Jew, kept disqualifying himself from committees... in 
order to be seen as objective 
 
What finally turned the tide and allowed many scientists to feel they could 
speak against Nazi race science was an article, about physics published in 
Nature  The Pragmatic and Dogmatic Spirit  in Physics (see p. 197). Why was 
THIS seen as offensive? 
 
Now, scientists could fasten on the idea that science was not to be based on 
national ideas and could flourish only where ther e was intellectual freedom. 
THIS is of course is about PROTECTING the perceived apolitical character of 
science, RATHER than any kind of acknowledgment that the science of human races was political in and of itself. 
 
So, Nazi ideas about race could be indirectly  denounced as pseudo-science. 
Physical anthropology in the US did not have to speak as one about the 
facts of what race was or wa s not in order to condemn German 
anthropological theories of race. (ind eed, many physical anthropologists had 
ideas about race not dissimila r from German anthropologists)  
 
NEXT TIME: Were going to travel into the realm of the genomic.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21A.240  
Race and Science 
Spring 2004 MIT  
 
 
PART 1:  
THE ALCHEMY OF RACE: MAKING AND UNMAKING SCIENTIFIC RACISM 
Lecture 6. March 11 
 
PAPER # 1 questions? 
    
Health and Hygiene: Latin American Lamarckism, Nazi German Darwinism 
 
Stepan, Nancy Leys. 1991. Eugenics in Latin America: Its Origin s and Institutional 
Ecology, Racial Poisons &amp; The Politics of Heredity in Latin America in the 1920s. In 
The Hour of Eugenics: Race, Gender and Nati on in Latin America. Ithaca, NY: Cornell 
University Press, pp. 35-101. 
 
Nancy Leys Stepans book, The Hour of Eugenics: Race, Gender and Nation in 
Latin America is a nice companion to the history Kevles gave us in In the 
Name of Eugenics . We see how eugenic ideas articulated to very different  
racial formations in diverse places. 
 
One useful thing Stepan does here is refuse to see Latin American eugenics 
simply as a shadow of  or worse, a kind of degeneration  of  European and 
U.S. eugenic discourse. Using the metaphor  of ecology, she wants us to see 
Latin American eugenics on its own term s, in its own history, located with 
respect to particularly Latin American  concerns and institutions, not as a 
scientific formation whose shape is simply the result of Latin American science 
lagging  behind science in Europe and th e U.S., which are somehow seen to 
lead the way to real truths behind heredity and race. 
 
Her book presents three case studies:  Brazil, Mexico, and Argentina  of 
which Ive had you read one, about Brazil. Id like to discuss this a little bit 
and then tell you something about the Mexico case. Then well get to the 
Nazis. 
 
BRAZIL . 
 
What are factors that form the context for Brazilian eugenics? 
 
1. WWI (concern about national regeneration) 
 
2. underdevelopment and neo-colonial  inequality: the creation of an 
extremely poor underclass in a highly ra cialized and class- stratified nation. 
 
3. state and concerns of science and medicine  also conditioned Brazilian 
Eugenics. Here, eugenics was associated not with biometrics or Mendelian 
genetics, but rather with medicine   including psychiatry (mental hygiene), 
legal medicine (linked to concerns about criminality), and obstetrics.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>this view also serves to encourage wh ite immigration, which was desired (p. 
90). The argument here is that tropics arent bad for white people! 
 
Moreover, it allowed Brazilian doctors to argue, as some did, that race 
mixing could be healthy  if races were exposed to proper environments! 
 
Lamarckism could account fo r degeneration as well as  regeneration seemingly 
without essentializing either. 
 
Compare this Lamarckian model to what  weve seen with Boas, the opponent 
of the Mendelian, genetically essent ialist eugenics movement? Was Boas a 
Lamarckian? 
 
No, not really, not at all. The malleability he located was in the phenotype, not the genotype. 
 
MEXICO.  
 
Mexican eugenics emerged in the afterm ath of the Mexican revolution, from 
1910-20, in a leftist revolutionary contex t. And the socialist eugenics that was 
emerging in other parts of the world was an inspiration to the Mexican 
context. 
 
But one of the more interesting features  of Mexican eugenics and its views on 
race was the idea that there could be such a thing as constructive 
miscegenation  that national po pulations for example, might be 
strengthened by race mixing. This turned dominant stereotypes of racial 
degeneration in Latin America on thei r head. Argued against ideas of Latin 
America as a zone of decay through mixture. 
 
Where did this come from? Boas ian influence was important. 
 
Manuel Gamio  was an important Mexican anthro pologist. He was a student of 
Boas and argued that there were no racial differences between different 
indigenous groups in Mexico, just cu ltural differences. However, these had 
common histories and might be brought back together, assimilated into a 
common national identity. 
 
This idea of fusion was racialized in the work of Jose Vasconcelos who forwarded the idea of the RAZA COSMICA. 
 
Jos Vasconcelos  (minister of education, revo lutionary, 1920s) accepted the 
argument that the difference between Indians and mainstream was cultural, 
but far from encouraging detailed stud y of the differences like Boas and 
Gamio, he proposed that policies be de veloped to mexicanize the Indians as 
soon as possible. He urge d the immediate learning of  Spanish and the almost 
mystical goal of developing a mestizo culture in which all Mexicans would 
participate as equals (from Stepan) 
 
But in spite of his culturalist view, he imagined this mestizo identity in a BIOLOGICAL IDIOM. Interbreeding would pr oduce a hybrid race that took the</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>best from each stock. (this idea late r took hold in Brazil, too...more Boas-
trained scientists...) 
 
cosmic race would be (p. 147): 
NEW a final stage in race formation 
COSMIC all races would be fu sed into a new racial unity 
LATIN AMERICA was the logical place for this to happen, since it was already 
well advanced and all races were present 
 
spiritual eugenics: the most beautiful of each race would seek mates like 
themselves (Darwins sexual selection!) 
 
Similarities/differences from ideas in UK and US eugenics and race thinking? 
 
still maintained that race existed and that homogeneity was the answer. While ennobling the indigenous peop le, they hoped to assimilate and 
eliminate the biological type of the Indian 
 
also denigrated Negroes and Chinese. 
 
 
Proctor, Robert. 1993. Nazi Me dicine and the Politics of Knowledge. In The Racial 
Economy of Science: Toward a Democratic Future, Sandra Harding, ed. Bloomington: 
Indiana University Press, 344-358. 
 
German eugenics was, like Brazilian based on medicine, and on the notion of 
hygiene . 
 
The Germans were also concerned with  the idea of being PURE OF BLOOD. 
 
They adhered to the Weismannian view  of CULTURE/BIOLOGY and assigned 
everything to BIOLOGY, which they ca lled RACE. And, as weve seen, there 
are disturbing connections between eugenic movements in the United States 
and those in Germany, with the scientists talking to each other. The readings 
I assigned also point out that Franz Boas was involved in trying to mobilize scientists against Na zi race science. 
 
And this proved difficult. And this connects, I think to he question that always comes up in the wake of the Holocaust, which is: 
 
the question of COMPLICITY, whic h often comes up in two ways: 
 
A. WHY didnt ordinary citizens DO anything? 
 
often the argument is about what Hannah Arendt called the banality of evil. 
notions of essential human inequality became part of everyday life, part of 
the most everyday ways of thinking. 
 
this argument gets extended  in recent writing about the continuing place of 
BLOOD IMAGERY in GERMANY; the symbo lism that sustained Nazism is STILL 
in circulation in the German imaginary. The argument here is that it has become part of the CULTURE, part of the LEGACY (we can see what we think 
of that).</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
