<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/</course_url>
    <course_title>Rocket Propulsion</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Physics </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Future Developments (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_37/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>37</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Open cycle, cannot (should not) o perate f rom ground.  
 
Can be lau nched ch emically t o orbit (inactive), the n be used as upper stage.  
Shielding only shadow, will requ ire large exclu sion zone about vehicle ( 10 Km , 
except in pr otected cone) 
 
New design by Carlo Rubbia claims scala bility to small siz e. A thin films 
surroun ding H2 channels, says can  build crit ical engine for 30 KW H. 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 37 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 2 of 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Orbital Mechanics: Review, Staging (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_32/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>32</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>which can be in tegrated to 
 
  
        (13) ()= +n1 2VC 1  
 
 Here C  is a constant of integration. The solution (13) satisfies V =  0 when  
= 0 (verti cal start) for  all C (n&gt;1 ), so C m ust be calculated by imposing a particular 
trajectory angl e  (or ) at some spec ified velocit y V (or, fro m later results, at 
some ti me or al titude). 
 
The ti me t i s calculated from E q. (8): 
 
   ()n2 2 Vd Cdt 1 dgcosg = =+ 
 
or, imposing t = 0 at  = 0. 
 
 
           ( 14) +=++n1 n1Ctgn1 n1 
 
 
 
Similarly, the altitude z follows from =dzVsindt: 
 
   ()2
2n32n1 CdzVsindt dg+= = 
 
 
or, wi th z = 0 at  = 0 += +22 n2 2n2Czg2n22n2      ( 15) 
 
 
We can  use this model t o calcu late grav ity losses.  Starting from (10), and using the 
relationships (12), 
 
   GVg=2
21
1
+ 0C
g
n2 21+ () d 
 
 
or   += +n1 n1
GCVgn 1n1      ( 16) 
 
 
We coul d now use (14)  to cal culate the consta nt C by specifying the  time to turn  to a 
given angle ( ). Alternat ively, we ca n eliminate C b y division of (16) and (14) : 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 4 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Assuming c i = c (same all stages), then 
     n
n
i1 ii1 11 1c V cln lnc =   +  +      ==         
()+= 1 n V
nnc
ii11ec  V
nc
iG1
ce1+
=&lt;&gt;  ()&lt;&gt;=1
n
Gii 
 
 
   = +=&lt;&gt;+    ii1VVcln1 ln cln lncn
ic  iiV Vlncn c  =&lt;&gt; 
 
 
So, inV
V Vnc nn n lnnc L i nc
ii ii1 i1 i1
IOPTM eeeM    &lt;&gt; 
== =    = = =   1 &lt;&gt; &lt;&gt;        
So, less  when stage is less structur ally efficient. iV
 
 
 = &lt;&gt;  
 nV
L nc
IOPTMeM 
 
 
Note:  
 
 
L
0MlnM0V
= &lt;Meani ng of  
 
 
Generall y: Max   given  
=i
i1tonf(x)
=&lt;=ji j
j1 tomng(x)G jj
jf g =  
 
 
j i
ji i         and 
ii iiG gdG dx dxxx = = = j
jjiig f
xx 
 
 
 = = = =    ii
i j ij ij j 
jii j i j ii igg ffd x dx dx dGxx x
 
j
jatoptimumf
G=  So, Sensitivity of payload ratio to overall 
V changes (after re- optimizing) 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 10 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>2
32211 edt (1ecosE) dE(1ecosE)dE
a 1e 1e= =
           21e sinE
1ecosE=sinEd(1ecosE+)(cosE
2esinE)
(1ecosE) 
 
=3tEe sinE
a      =2
2 1e dE1e d1ecosE 
 
From (**)   2a(1e) Pr1ecos==+2(1e)(1ecos) ra(1ecosE)  =  
 
 
 
 
=  aeacosEr(cos) 
 
a= (cosEe)a  (1ecosE)cos 
 
=cosEecos1ecosE 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 16 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Define E by =+22 1e Ettan1e 2 +=1e Ett a1e 2n  
21dE1e 2dtE 1ecos2+= 
 
()3322dt
a1 e=
 ()2
2 2
21e E1t an1e 2
1e E1tan2++
++1e dE/2
1e+
2Ecos2 
 
++  + + +   == + = + +  ++   +2
22 2
22
3
21e E1t an1e 1e E1e E 1e 1cosE1e1cosE 1e 2dt dE cos sin dE dE21 e 2 1e 2 1e 2 a1 e 1e E1tan2

 
( )  = =+ 2
3 21ecosE 1e 1 edt cosEdE1e 1e a1 e 1edE 
 
 
=3dtEesinE
a    (t from  perigee passage ) 
 
 
= +11eE2  tan tan1e 2with               
 
                     from  which      + +== =
++ +++2 22
221e E1t an 1tan 1e(1e)tan1e 2 22
2sEE1 e1tan 1 tan 1e(1e)tan21 e 2 2co  
 
 
22 21e1cos (1cos)1cos 1etcoscos1t t cosE1e 1cos1cos (1cos)1e+  ++= = = +++ + 
 
 
+=+2e2coscosE22ecos        +=+ecosco       sE1ecoscosEecos1ecosE     =+ =21e1e * cos1ecosE
 
 
So, directly 
 
 
= 
232
2
32 2(1e)dt d(1ecosE)
a( 1e)           = =22 2(1ecosE)(cosEe) 1e sinEsin1ecosE 1ecosE 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 15 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Here w e assumed th rust to be align ed with velocity. This is call ed a grav ity 
turn, and is not the most general  maneuver. It is, however, the m ost econom ical 
strategy for tur ning, since any  lateral component o f thrust uses propel lant without 
adding flight energy. 
 
Formal integration of (7) no w give s 
 
t
0
0mVc ln gsindtm=       ( 9) 
 
and so the grav ity loss is 
 
   = y
Grav.
0V gsindt      ( 10) 
 
 
Of course, the particular ()t to be  used here must come from  simultaneously 
solving (8) with (7). This solu tion cannot be don e in simple  analytical terms w hen 
thrust is constan t, since a nonl inear 2nd order  differential equ ation is involved. But, 
interestingly, there is a relat ively simple solu tion when he thrust accelerat ion =Fam 
is assu med constant (i.e., throttling down  as mass is consu med). Although this is n ot 
a very realistic option, it still is useful in giving information abou t the initial rot ation 
of the trajectory near the ground, which happ ens before the mass has time to 
change m uch. 
 
Eliminate time by dividing Eqs . (8) and (7) by each other, which separates the  
variables V and : 
 
   dV agsindVg cos=       ( 11) 
 
 
We introduce =ang and also change a ngle variable t o 
 
 = tan42; =
+2
21sin
1;  =
+22cos
1 
 
 =
+22dd
1         ( 12) 
 
The vari able  varies between 0 when  (initial confi guration) to 1 when 
 (orbit insertion). Substituting in (11) and simplif ying,  =090
=00
 
 
   ()2dV d2dn1V 1= ++ 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 3 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Say =  6K/kmgR0.006x2870.176g9 .8==  
 
and n = 3 
() ()110.176
MAX 0 q 10.176 31P0.808atm= =  
 
 
1 atm      ( )20.808x14.7x12 1710psf ==  
 
 
 
Also, then () Maxq2v2 n1g =g0RT
g  ()=q'2
Max2Mn 1 (based on  C0, at ground) 
 
 
Based on local T, ()()2 0
Maxq
02n 1 T 21Mn 1T
1
T= = g0RT
g 
 
 
()
q'2
Max
g2n 1MR1g=
  ()=2 2x2M1.410.176   MaxqM1 .862=
 
 
 
Drag Losses : Like gravity losses, drag losses ar e important only near t he ground , 
peaking so mewhat ab ove . Therefore, they should  be estimated and added 
to the  1st stage  budget alone. The drag loss  is defined by  analogy to  as the 
decrease in velocity due to th e accumulated drag deceleration: (MAXzq)
V GV
 
    
=       ( 22) ""
D
0DV dtm
 
Drag i s D = q CD A, where A i s the frontal  area, and  CD varies with veh icle 
shape and Mach number (from about 0 .02 at low M to  a peak of per haps 0 .15 in 
transonic flow, then decreasin g again ). For est imation purposes on ly, we will use a 
mean =D DCC  and write (22) a s 
 
    D0
D
0m AC dzV qMm v=      ( 23) 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 7 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>dv dlnmc gdt dt=       ( 3) 
 
and integra ting, 
 
   0
0mVV Vcln gtm==      ( 4) 
 
The ideal, or grav ity-free v elocity incremen t is the familiar 0
idealmVc lnm=  (5) 
 
But the pre sence of gravity redu ces the velocity increment b y =GravityV gt (6) 
 
which can be made in significant if t is sh ort, but can be v ery import ant otherwise. In 
the limit  when the thrust is barely  enough to cancel weight, the vehicle just hover s 
indefinitely with no velocity gain. 
 
In pract ice, the sign ificant item is the f uel used in the firing, which is 
contai ned in the m ass ratio m 0/m.  
 
The common proce dure is then to first ignore gravity, as i f the firing was 
impulsive (t=0),  and calculate the V required for the mission under this 
assumption. In our sim ple ascent example, the mission  is to reach a v elocity V, 
starting at V0, and so the impu lsive V is simply  V-V0. From (4) then 
 
o
imp.mcln V gtm=+      ( 6) 
 
and so the extra  is added on  as a correct ion, with the implicat ion of 
additional f uel being used for a gi ven V-V 0. =Grav.V gt
 
In a more gen eral asce nt trajectory (but still over a f lat Earth, since gravity 
losses occur only near the beginning of flight, before the path becomes nearly 
horizontal ) we wo uld have 
 
       = dv F      ( 7) gsindtm
 
  
 =dV gcosdt   (8) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 2 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Review of O rbital Dyna mics  (Single center) 
 
 
 
 
pr1ecos=+  ( from  perigee) 
 
 
 
 
== 2ce 1aab ; 
 
Apoapse (a pogee, aphelion): apr1e== ap11rr p 2a1e 1e+= +=+ 
Periapse (peri gee, perihel ion): pp0r1e==+ 22p2
1e=
a 
  
 () =2pa 1e 
 
()(para 1e,ra1e = =+)    true a nomaly
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 11 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Energy Co nservation :  21vE2r= ()=GM 
 
At perigee ()2
p1vE2a 1e= 
At apogee ()2
a1vE2a 1e=+  ()
()2
p
aEv a1 e
vEa1 e+ = ++  * 
 
 
 
Angul ar momentum conservati on:  =rv h (or 2rh=) 
 
 at perigee: ()p ha 1ev =  
 at apogee: ()a ha 1ev =+   ** p
av1e
v1 e+= 
 
equate (*)  = (** ) ()
()2Ea1 e 1e
1eEa1 e+ += ++ 
() ()+ +  += + 2
21e 1eEE1e a a1e 1e 
 
   ()
() ()+ + =    2
21e 1eE1 1a1 e 1e 1e 
 
 
 4eE
()21e()a1 e=
2e
()1e  =E2a  indep. of e (given a) 
 
 
and then 
()2
p21
a1 eaa1e += =e  a
p
pa p2r 1eva1 e rrr+ == + 
      a nd  p
a
pa p2r 1ev==a1 e rrr 
+ + 
 
 
and  () ()2 1eha 1e a1ea1 e += =   or =hp  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 12 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Optimum Stagin g 
 
 
 
 
 
 
si ii MM=  
i i1 L ii MM M+==  
 
  i
i
ii iV
L
LS f i MM  MeM
+= =
 
+i1M 
 
+=Vi
Ci i1
i
iMeM   
=Ln 1 2 L
n1 n2 1 1MM MM....MM MM
 
 
=
= i
iVn
C L
ii1
1MeM 
 
 
Maximize subject to   (assume =iiV V i is independent of M. In reality it may  i
           depend on ab solute mass.) 
 
 
 i
iV
C L
ii
i i 0Mln V lne VM
i     ==        
 
For each i, 

=
i
i
i
iV
c
i
V
i c
i1ec
V
e  
=i
iV
c
ii1c1 e 
 
 
i
ii
i11cVC ln+  
+=i
iV
c
i
i11ec     =  

 
 
Then, find   from  n
i
i
i1 i11ccln V
=+=
   , then find iV from  
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 9 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 32: Orbit al Mechan ics: Review, St aging 
 
 
Mission Pl anning, St aging 
 
The remaining lectures are devoted to Mission Planning and Vehi cle Desi gn, w hich in 
reality occurs even be fore the rocket engi nes are fully specif ied (although iterations 
continuously proceed t hrougho ut the proce ss, and engine charac teristics do affect 
the mission plan). 
 
Very roughl y, the iteration steps i n planning a l aunch mission are: 
 
(a) Estimate t he requi red TOTALV  using impu lsive thrusting formulae, plus add-
ons for  gravity losses, d rag losses, turning  losses, etc. 
 
(b) Distribute this  optimally amon g veh icle st ages (since all orbit  launches 
so far requ ire multiple stages in  order to avoid carrying e mpty ta nkage in the 
later stages). 
 TOTV
(c) Using the mass f ractions from (b) , perform more det ailed flight simu lations 
and refine the partial and to tal V for the mi ssion. 
 
 
During stage (b),  the total V is assumed to be uncha nged when the ma ss 
distribution for the  stages is varied. This is n ot strictly true, becau se often the 
mission optimi zation leads to c hanges in the altitude and velocity at which the 
various firings are ex ecuted an d, as w e will see, this may alter the various s.  V
This is t he role of  stage (c) abov e. 
 
Another poi nt to be ma de is that stages a nd firings ma y not map o ne-to-
one. A given sta ge may be t urned off, allowed to coas t, and then re-ignited. Or the 
firing of t wo consec utive stages ma y occur with no interruption (or mi nimal 
interrupti on), so  that both can be i dealized as occurring in the same p lace. As long 
as the s are st ill regar ded as in sensitive to mission  profile details (as per th e 
comment above), these distinctions do not impact the sta ge mass calculations, b ut 
they can be of great pr actical importance no netheless. V
 
Impu lsive Thrusting-Gravity Losses. Because o f the large accelerat ions imparted by 
rocket engines, their firing s are us ually short, from u nder one minute to about 10 
minutes. I n fact, there is a performance i ncentive in minimizing the fi ring time, as  
long as th e accelerat ions remain  below  structural or ot her limits. This can  be most 
easily seen in the co ntext of a verti cal ascent a gainst gravi ty. The vehicles equati on 
of motion is the n (ignor ing drag) 
 
   =dvmF mgdt      ( 1) 
 
and   dmFm ccdt
==       ( 2) 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 1 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Path angle: 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 ()resin v drtanvr d 1ecos+===++  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Circular orbits       ra=vr=  32v rT 2v  ==        check, 
 
 
 
Time in  orbit (elliptic case)  
 
 
()()=+
2
332d1ecosdta1 e 
      2
21c os 1cos22 1t+ = =
+
 
 
() ()3232ddt
1ecos a1 e=
+     = tan t2 = =
++2
2221cos 1
1t 1tt =
+22dtd
1t 
 
 
  ()
() ()22
2222
221 tdt 21 tdt
1e 1e 1t eet1t1e+ +
2+  ++++== 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 32 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 14 of 16</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Review of Equilibrium Thermochemistry (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 12: Review of Equilibri um Thermochemist ry 
 
 
Thermochemistr y of Combu stion for Propulsion Devices  
 
12.1.1 I ntroduction  
 
The general principles that go vern chem ical reactions (spe cies conservation, 
enthalpy ba lance and c hemical equilibr ium) have been  introduced in previous 
subjects. In the next three Sect ions we will briefly examine the applicat ion of these 
principles to Propulsion. 
 
The sketch in Fig 12.1 indi cates the main regions.  
 
 
Fig. 12.1. Main  region s in a liqu id-fuel combu stor 
 
 
In a comb ustion chamb er which co uld belo ng to a ramjet or rocket, o r, with 
minor variations, to many other technical dev ices w hich ut ilize hot gas flows. It is 
frequent to supply fuel (and somet imes ox idizer as w ell) in liquid form, and so the 
first region involves a series  of colliding liqu id jets or sprays, designed to break up 
these liqu ids into fine droplet s. These n ow find themselves immersed in the ho t 
combustion gases, and evaporate rapidly,  a step which m ust necessa rily precede 
actual chem ical react ion. Mixing o f the oxid izer and fuel va pors typically proceeds via 
the stro ng turbulence e xisting in the combusto r, and  once this mixing has act ually 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 12 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 1 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>(5) Iterate back to  step (3) until con vergen ce is obt ained.  
We illustrate these principles be low. 
 
Ref.12.1 .1 G. Van Wylen and  R. E. So nntag , Fundame ntals of Classical 
Thermodynamic , Appendix A. 11, 3rd Ed., SI Version, J. Wiley &amp; Sons, 1985 . 
 
 
12.2 Example Calculatio n of Therm ochemic al Equilibrium in a Rocket Chamber  
 
12.2.1 I ntroduction  
 
In the Space Shuttles Main Engines (S SMES), the rocket combustion chamber 
operates at p = 210 atm and a n oxidizer-t o-fuel mass ratio O/F = 6, the reacta nts 
being cryog enic  and . The stoichiomet ric ratio for full combu stion 2H2O
22 21HO HO2+
 would be O/F = 8, so this is n ow only sligh tly fuel-rich, and we 
expect  a very h igh combu stion temperat ure. In the next few sect ions we will an alyze 
this case step- by-step, in  order t o bring out the important points of a ny such 
calculation. Practical problems of  this nature are rou tinely solved by mean s of 
complex compu ter programs based on  the presen t methods or on more gen eralized 
iteration schemes,  but, of  course, entail ing the same basic physics. O ne such 
standard code is the so -called CEC, Ch emical E quilibrium Code, developed and 
maintained by NASA  (Ref. 12.2 ), which in its normal configurati on, can handle about 
200 species simultaneously. 
 
12.2.2 A tomic Species  Concentrati on 
 
In orde r to more easily keep track  of mass conservation, it is useful to work  with the 
numbers o f moles,  of the various chemical pro duct species in an arbitrary total 
mass of gas . This same mass of ga s orig inates from a set of numbers of moles  of 
reactants,  and we must impose that, no matter what reacti on shi fts occur, the 
number of atomicin
jn
 moles for e ach kind of a tom (O, H, N, C, ) is the same before 
and after reaction. As a n example, suppose  we have combustion of hydrogen in 
oxygen , with  unknown amou nts of water, molecu lar an d atomic oxygen , molecu lar 
and atomic hydrogen an d hydroxyl ( OH) radicals f ormed.  The oxidiz er/fuel ratio is 
prescribed to be, say , R, so that, if we arbitrarily select  = 1/2 , the n 
2ON
 
=
2H32x1/2R2N  ;  
2H8NR=    (12.2-1 ) 
 
The reaction is  
 
+ +++++
22 2 H 22 HO2 O 2 O H 2 H O81H O nHOn OnOn HnHnOHR2    (12.2-2 ) 
 
 
Note that the list of can didate reaction product s is arrived at from  our 
background  knowledge of what species actual ly do occu r in significant quantities. For 
instance, we might not include  or O if R  were low enough to make the mixture 
fuel-rich, such  that under those con ditions, oxygen  species wou ld be mainly depl eted.  2O
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 12 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 6 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Since for each co nstituent , we also have   vpcc R=
 
=== vpccR31.918.3123.60J/mole K, giving  
 
 == =p
vc31.911.35223.60 c 
 
(Notice  is not  the average of  the individual s) 
 
12.1.3 Reac tions Cl ose to Stoi chiometry (or with Preheate d Reactan ts) 
 
In other applicat ions, where mat erials limits are either absent or can be overcome by 
appropriate  cooling of walls, the reacta nts m ay be in pro portions close to 
stoichiomet ric, so as to  generate v ery high gas temperatures.  Examples are: 
 
(a) Rocket com bustors  (operated typi cally on the fuel-rich side,  but only 
moderat ely so)  
(b) Ramjet  combu stors (where, in addit ion, the air is strongly heated by the 
ram effect) 
(c) Piston engines (fuel-lean for gasolin e engines, but near-stoichiometric in 
Diesel engi nes) 
(d) Weldin g torches 
 
In these cases one cannot easily predict th e final composit ion of the burnt gases,  
since the relatively complex molecu les like ,  (or even , ) tend to 
break down in to simple r ones which are more  stable at high tem peratures ( such as 
OH, H, O, etc.). Thus, in addition to mass and energy conservation,  one needs to use 
also2Ho2CO2H2O
 the laws of  chemical equil ibrium to  determine the te mperature and other 
properties o f the gas products.  In most re al situations, many molecu lar species may 
be presen t at the high temperat ures of the flame, and so more t han one equ ilibria 
are simu ltaneously to be con sidered.  In these cases,  iteration is requ ired t o obtain 
consistent s olutions. A procedure which, with som e judgment, us ually works,  is as 
follows:  
 
(1) Identify the  possible molecular species in the p roducts,  classify them into 
major  and minor  (minor species would be those that are expected to be 
present in smal l concentration).  
          
(2) Neglect at first the minor  species,  use procedures si milar to those  in the     
previous example to obtain the major species conce ntration and a n 
approximate temperature.  
 
(3) Write chemica l react ions which would produce one minor species at a  
time from  only major ones. Calculate their equilibrium constan ts at the 
approximate temperature of  step (2), and use the equil ibrium laws to 
calculate the concentrations of  the minors . 
 
(4) Correct the majors concentrat ion, and do a new enthalpy balance to   
obtain an i mproved temperature.  
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 12 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 5 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>elementary reactions,  they can be built up fro m tabulated  values of the sta ndard 
chemical po tentials (or Gibbs f ree ener gies) of  the intervening species.  The 
equilibrium constan ts are given in our example by 
 
 
  +
=
200 0
HH O HO
11
2Ke xpRT2    (12.2-18 ) 
 
 
  
=2 200
H H
22
Ke xpRT     (12.2-19 ) 
 
 
  +
=
22 200 0
HO H
31
2Ke xpRTO
    (12.2-20 ) 
 
 
  
=200
O H
42
Ke xpRT     (12.2-21 ) 
 
 
where each  is the chemical pot ential of speci es i at 1 atm.  pressu re (standard 
chemical po tential), at the given temperat ure T, and R is the universal gas co nstant 
in consistent units. ()0
iT
 
 
12.2.4 Conservation of Energy  
 
Since the re actions occ ur at constant pr essure, if we assume a w ell-insulated 
combustor,  the enthalpy of the products  must equal that of the react ants. If ()ihT is 
the molar enthalpy of the  species at temperature T, we m ust have in our 
example: thi
 
 
() () () () ()
22 2 2 2 2 Hi O i HOHO O O OO81hT hTnhTnhTnhTR2+= + +  
 
()() ()
22H H HH OH OH nh TnhTnhT ++ +   (12.2-22 ) 
 
 
Notice the l eft hand side of t his equati on represents the enthal py of the reactan ts (8
R 
moles of , 2H1
2 mole of ) at their injection temperature, 2OiT, whereas the right 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 12 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 9 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>()=
22
O
4
OPKTP       (12.2-12 ) 
 
where each  represents a partial pr essure. T hese can be  expressed in terms of the 
given totaliP
 pressure P and the mole numbers  : in
 
 =2
2HO
HOn
PPn (=++ ++
22 2 HO O H H OH nn nnnn) 
  
 
         =2
2O
On
PPn 
 
 
          =OH
OHnPPn       (12.2-13 ) 
 
  .  
  .  
  .  
 
And theref ore the equili brium relat ions become 
 
 
  () =2
21/2
HO H
1
HOnn nKTnp      (12.2-14 ) 
 
 
  () =
22
H
2
HnnKTnp       (12.2-15 ) 
 
 
 
  () =22
21/2
HO
3
HOnn nKTnp      (12.2-16 ) 
 
 
  () =
22
O
4
OnnKTnp       (12.2-17 ) 
 
 
The equ ilibrium constants , , ,  still depen d on temperat ure. If 
temperature is known a-priori (or assumed at  some step in an iteration process), are 
can either look their values up in some co mpilation of chemical prope rties (such as 
Table A. 12 of Ref. 12.1), or more rat ionally, given  the man y possible combin ations of 1K2K3K4K
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 12 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 8 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>However,  if we st ill did i nclude them, with the proper equ ilibrium con stants, 
we wou ld still find some small con centrations of these molecu les presen t. We wou ld 
simply ign ore them for practical pu rposes,  as we ign ore other exot ic, but potentially 
real species, like , , etc. 2HO3H
 
The atomic  species are H and O a nd in order to  conserve atoms, we must impos e: 
 
H-con servation : 
22HO H H OH162n 2nnnR=+ ++   (12.2-3 ) 
 
O-con servation :    (12.2-4 ) 
22HO O O OH 1n 2nnn =+ ++
 
 
12.2.3 Eq uilibrium Relations  
 
These are two equations in volvin g the six un known  s. Clearly because of 
the presence of  the  decompositi on products O, H and O H, (plus  if fuel-rich or 
 if lean), conservation alone can not tell us the composit ion of the burnt gas. We 
need f our extra relatio nships, and these are the equil ibrium conditions (laws o f 
mass-action) f or four elementary reacti ons selected so as to involve these 
decomposit ion product s, as well as  some of the major pr oducts , , , . 
These could be,  for example,  in
2O
2H
2HO2CO2H
 
 +2 21HO HOH2R        ( 12.2-5) 
 
         ( 12.2-6) 2H 2RH
 
 +2 21HO H O2R2
O       ( 12.2-7) 
 
         ( 12.2-8) 2O 2R
 
or any linear combin ation of them. 
 
For each  of the elemen tary react ions above,  an equ ilibrium relationship must 
be satisfied. According to Ch. 16, these take the f orm 
 
 ()=2
21/2
HO H
1
HOPP
KTP       ( 12.2-9) 
 
 
 ()=2
H
2
HPKTP       (12.2-10 ) 
 
  
 ()=22
21/2
HO
3
HOPP
KTP       (12.2-11 ) 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 12 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 7 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>hand side represents t hat of the products, with each  evaluated at T, the final 
equilibration temperat ure, to  be found. This is wh at is oft en called t he adiabat ic 
flame temperature for the given O/F and pre ssure. ih
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 12 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 10 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>achieved i ntimate molecul ar level interdi ffusion within the turb ulent eddies, reacti on 
occurs usually on a time scale w hich is sh ort compared t o those for vaporiz ation and 
mixing. 
 
The comb ustion chamb er design must take into account the kinetics of these 
steps to  arrive at a dimensi on which guarantee s compl etion of the combusti on 
reactions without waste of volume. If this is so, t he last  portion of the combu stor 
contai ns at any time a mi xture of c ombusti on products  which have reached a st ate of 
thermodyna mic equi librium, a nd which are about to flow into thei r working devi ces, 
be it a simple n ozzle, a turbine (also preced ed by i ts nozzles) or other  confi gurations. 
 
Equilibrium does n ot necessarily  mean complet e combu stion since, at high 
temperatures, various decomposition reacti ons are therm odynami cally favored.  In a 
high speed Ramjet with a subsonic comb ustion chamber the incomplet eness of the 
combusti on is so extreme due to the high temperature prevailing- that, beyond a 
certai n flight speed, no net heat rel ease can be  obtai ned. 
 
It is import ant to distinguish betw een this kind of combu stion incompl eteness, 
which is unavoidable at  high temperatures, and is due to the acti vation of reverse 
reactions, a nd a more c ommon but avoidabl e incompleteness, which occurs when the 
combu stion chamber is inadequ ately sized and the vaporizat ion-mixing-reaction 
processes are not comp leted in the residenc e time allowed to each fluid particle. 
 
A first objecti ve of our a nalysis is to determi ne the act ual gas condi tions 
(temperature, composition) at the exit of an equilibrated comb ustor, for a set of 
prescri bed reactant flow rates.  These fl ow rates, toget her with the discharge no zzle 
geomet ry, also det ermine a combust or pressu re, which we will here assu me as an  
independently prescribed quantity. 
 
Beyond this poin t the flow typically  expands  and cools more or less 
adiabat ically. As it does so,  there is at  least  a tendency to shift its chemica l 
composit ion, usually in the sense of  comple ting the  incompl ete combusti on, since the 
lower temperature now  inhibits decomposi tion reacti ons. T hus, there may be a s ort 
of afterb urning effect  along the nozzle expansi on, and this someti mes contri butes  
significantly to increase t he performan ce of rockets or ra mjets. It is worth noting 
here that , even if all the reacti ons that  were not completed in the cha mber were 
complet ed in the nozzle, thus still releasing all the heat of combu stion, the 
performan ce level achieved would be low er than if no decomposit ion had ever 
occurred i n the first place; thi s is because in a ny thermod ynamic cycl e less work can 
be extracte d from heat added at lower than at higher temperatures. In any eve nt, it 
often happe ns that the nozzle recombi nation reacti ons are too sl ow (due to their 
occurring at a reduced temperature, which sl ows down reaction rates) to keep pa ce 
with the rapidity of the nozzle expa nsion proce ss. In that case the flow is said to be 
chemical ly frozen, and it comes out of  the nozzle exit in a state of su bstantial non-
equilibrium, main taining a composit ion close to what it had in the chamber.  This is 
the opposite extreme to the case  when a ll the recombin ation react ions actu ally do 
occur along the flow (e quilibrium  expansi on). Actual  perfo rmance al ways fal ls 
between these two extremes (more performanc e than that for frozen expa nsion, less 
than that for equilibrium expansion), and since the spread bet ween th em may  not be 
too large, it is useful to bracket the actual  result by perfor ming both  frozen and  
equilibrium flow calcu lations, both of which, as w e will see , involve only  considerat ion 
of the end points of the expansi on. Anything in between en tails much more complex 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 12 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 2 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>calculations, due to the need to follow in detail the kinetics of a variety of chemical  
reactions. 
 
12.1.2 Com bustors Far from Stoichiometry  
 
Stoichiomet ric proportions of fuel and oxidizer are those for which, if the react ion 
were complete, no exc ess of either would ensue. It is clear t hat this would then 
ensure max imum heat release per uni t mass, and hence hi ghest adiabatic flame 
temperature. Eve n under condi tions of incomplete reaction, maximum temperature 
usually does occur  near stoichiometric condit ions, a nd falls off for ei ther fuel -rich or 
fuel-lean condi tions. 
 
For some i mportant types of comb ustors the fuel/air ratio is pu rposely  select ed to be 
very far from stoi chiometri c, so as to keep the final temper atures below acceptable 
materials limits. Exam ples are: 
 
(a) Jet engi ne combustors (operated fu el/lean) 
 
(b) Gas generators for rocket turbopumps (operated typically very fuel-rich). 
 
In cases such as  these the final te mperat ure and other properties of the reacted 
gases can b e obtained from simple mass and energy balances, since their 
composit ion can usually be obt ained by in spection by ass uming complete combus tion 
with excess oxidizer or fuel, as the case may  be. This is becau se decomposit ion 
reactions responsible for co mbusti on incompl eteness are n ot very ac tive at t hese 
moderate temperatures. 
 
Exampl e 
 
The liqu id hydrogen  fuel in the Space Shuttle main engine is pressurized to the very 
high comb ustion chamb er pressure by a turbopump which is driv en by a turbine. The 
gas driv ing this turbine is gen erated in a preburner, into which the flow  rates of 
oxygen a nd hydroge n are (at maxi mum power ) 
 
LOXm
=43 Kg /sec   
=LHm 40.2 Kg/sec 
 
Since this is v ery fuel-rich, we can safely assume al l of the  is con sumed,  and we 
have t he reaction 2O
  
 () + +22 21xH O HO1xH22 
 
where the x is given by the oxidizer/fuel ratio: 
 
 
 ==13243 8 2
40.2x.2x  x = 7.5 
 
So that + +22 217.5H O HO6.5H22 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 12 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 3 of 10</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Liquid Propellants (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Desirable: Low m.p ., high , c, b.p. (for high H in coolin g) 
      Stability (negative ) fH
      Low vapor pressure (high b.p.) 
      Hypergolic ity 
      Non-toxicity 
      Storabi lity 
      Non-corrosive 
Exam ples of use: 
 
NA NTO Lox H2O2
 
 Titan II Atlas X-15 
 
 Shuttle OMS Jupiter 
  
 Space biprops RD-170 
  
 Proton? RD-180 
  
  Delta (St.1) 
  
  Fastrac(X 34) 
  
  RS-76 
  
  SSME 
  
  Vulcain 
  
  RS-68 
  
  RL-10  Hydrazine LH MMH RP-1 UDMH  
 
Monoprops. J-2 Space biprops Atlas Titan II (50 % N2H4) 
 
 SSME Shuttle OMS Thor Lunar Lander 
 
 Vulcain (Ariant)  Delta (St.1 ) Proton? 
 
 J7 (Japa n)  Titan I 
  
 RL-10 (Centans) 
  Saturn  
 RS-68(EELV ) Delta IV 
  RD-170  
   RD-180 
  
   Fastrac (X-34) 
  
   RS-76  
With 
LH With 
RP-1 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 19 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 2 of 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 19 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 3 of 3  NA NTO  L ox H2O2 
 
 Titan II Atlas X-15 
 
 Shuttle OMS Jupiter 
  
 Space biprops RD-170 
  
 Proton? RD-180 
  
  Delta (St.1) 
  
  Fastrac(X 34) 
  
  RS-76 
  
  SSME 
  
  Vulcain 
  
  RS-68 
  
  RL-10  
 With 
RP-1 
With 
LH</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Effects of Particles in Nozzle Flow (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>NOTE : Alternatively, and easi er to do, yo u can use 
 
 


= 
1
e
ec p
cPu2 CT1P 
 
with () pC 10.373180 0.3712602469 = + =  J/Kg/K 
 
(So M is not really needed) 
 
As a check, R1.13368.31424690.13360.02857 1M=
=  J/Kg/K as it should. 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 6 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 10 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Problems  
 
Problem 2 
 
As noted  in class, the e ffect of carry ing a ma ss fraction x of f ine solid part icles in the 
expanding gas in a roc ket nozzle c an be a ccoun ted for by using an average specif ic 
heat rati o 
 
 
()
()1
1+
=+pg s
vg sxc xc
xc xc  
 
and an aver age molecular mass 
 
1=gM
Mx 
 
 
For  the high temperature specif ic heat is  23AlO .sc=1260J/Kg/K
Consider a solid rock et with () 1.171.25, 0.01, 18/mol. == =g ecPP M g   
For a 20% aluminum loadin g in the propel lant, x is of  the order of  37%.  
Calculate the mat ched specif ic imp ulse of  the rocket and compar e to what it would 
be for the same  but wi th no particles. 3300 , =cT K
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 6 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 7 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 6: Heat C onduction: Thermal Stre sses 
 
 
Effect of Solid or Liquid Par ticles in Nozzl e Flow 
 
 
An issue in highly aluminized solid rock et motors. 
 
2Al +223O AlO23 
 
m.p. 207 , b.p. 298  2CD0CD
 
In modern formulations , with 20% Al by mass, the  mass fraction of the 
exhaus t can be 35-40 %. This material does not  expand23AlO
, so there must be a loss in 
exit velocity, hence in Isp. 
Assume ma ss flows  (gas)  (solids), no n-converting gmi
smi
. 
 
The moment um equation is  
 
gs gs mdumduAdp0 ++ii
= 
 
Call s the (mass of sol ids)/(vol ume) (not the density of the solid, theory) 
 
gg g ss s udu udu dp0 ++ =   
 
Define a ma ss flux function 
 
s ss
gg ssgsu mxuumm==++i
ii
 
 
gg g sxudu du dp01x+ +   = 
 
gg gs
gdp xudu udu1x= 
 
The energy equation  is similarly, 
 
 
()() ( ) pg g gg ss ss 1xcdTudu xcdT udu 0 + + + = 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 6 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 1 of 10</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Performance to GEO (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_34/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>34</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Is it true that plane ch ange sho uld be al l done at end  of GTO? 
 
Actually, a small t urning combin ed with initial 1V (say, from LEO) costs very little 
loss, even though Vis then large.  Try splitting into a V1i and 21ii i = 
 
 
1G TO 1 GTO22
1c p cp Vv v 2vvcosi = + 1 
 
        12 VV V =+ 
()
2G TO 2 GTO22
2c p ca Vv v 2vvcosii = + 1 
 
 
()
()1 2
11 2 2c1 ca 1
22 2 2
1cc 1 c c 12vVsini 2vVsinii dV0di 2v V2vVcosi2v V2vVcosii+ +  = +  + P
PP a a= 
 
1c
1vR= , 
2c
2vR= , 2
p
11 22RvRR R=+, 1
a
21 22RvRR R=+ 
 
 
Call 2
1R
R=  
 
 
()
()1 1
1 111 2sinii 2s ini1 1
22 112 2121 2 cosi cosii11 1 1 + + =
+  +  ++ + + 
 
 
 
2
1+21sini
()1 222 1212 cosii11
+ = + +   1+()2
122sinii1 2 cosi11  +   + +    
 
 
422006.142656370500= =+  21.311481=+ 
 
 
()
()1
1
110.52916Sin28.5i1.31148 Sini 6.14265
1 11.71999 21.31148 Cosi10.28001 20.52916Cos28.5i
6.14265=
+  +  
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 34 
Prof. Ma nuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 8 of 13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 34: Performance to GE O 
 
 
VCalculations for Launch to Geostationary Orbit (GEO) 
 
Idealized Direct GTO Injection
(GTO = Geosynchronous Transfer Orbit) 
 
Assumptions: 
 
- Ignore drag  and "gravity" losses 
- Assume impu lsive burns (instantaneous impu lse deliv ery) 
- Assume all elevations &gt;0 at launch are acceptable 
 
Launc h is from a l atitude L, di rected due East for maxi mum use of  Earth's 
rotati on. The East ward added vel ocity due to rotation is then 
 
RE E vR cosL463co = = sL (m/s)     (1) 
 
If the launch elevation is , and the desi red vel ocity after  the first burn is V1, 
the rocket must supply a velocity incremen t 
 
22
11 R 1R VV v2Vvcos = +       ( 2) 
 
 
 
 
 
The trajectory will then lie in a plan e LOI t hrough  the Earth's center which 
contains the local E -W line. In order t o be able to perfor m the plane  change to the 
equatorial p lane at GE O, we select the elevatio n  such as to place the apogee  of the 
transfer orb it (GTO) at  the GEO  radius 1/32
GEO 2TR  42,200km
4= = 
(T = 24 hr,  = 3.98610 14 m3/s2) 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 34 
Prof. Ma nuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 1 of 13  DV1 v1
avR</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>No plan e chan ge is in volved yet, so 
 
GEO E
2
pp GEO P2R RVRR R R=  +     ( 13) 
 
 
This places t he spacecraf t on an ell iptical GTO orbit , still in the origin al plan e, with 
apogee at . The speed at this apogee is: GEOR
 
P
a,GTO
GEO P GEO2RvRR R=+      ( 14) 
 
 
and so,  
 
 
22
a GEO a,GTO GEO a,GTO Vv v 2vv cos = + L 
 
 
PP
a
GEO GEO P GEO GEO P GEO2R 2RV2RR RR R RR = + ++cosL 
 
 
P P
a
GEO P GEO P GEO2R 2RV1 2 cosRR R RR= + ++L    ( 15) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 34 
Prof. Ma nuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 6 of 13  DVa
va,GTOvGEO
L
Fig. 5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Since OL is perpendicular to OI, the view in the plane of  the orbit is: 
 
 
 
 
 
The polar equation of the trajectory is pr1e cos=+ , &gt; 0 
 
In our case  (corresponding to EpR=2=). The elevatio n is given by 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 34 
Prof. Ma nuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 2 of 13  North
LO
RGEO
IGTOEQUATORWE
a
EQUATORIAL GEO ORBITV1
Fig. 1
RGEORErLaV1
q
oI P
Fig. 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>()2
/2/2dr esintan erd 1e cos ==  = = =   +  
 
 
and, i n turn, the eccentricity foll ows from  (at =) 
 
E
GEORR1e=   E
GEORe1R=  
 
and so E
GEORtan1 0.849R==     ;          ( 3) 040.3=
 
The angu lar momen tum (per unit mass)  is E hp R ==  . 
 
Equating this to  ,  E1RVc o s
 
1
EVco sR=         ( 4) 
 
(i.e., the horizontal proj ection of the lau nch velocity is the local orbit al speed,  for any 
apogee radius,  in this case)  GEOR
 
 
Combi ning (3) and (4),  2
E
1
EG ERV1 1RRO    =+         (5) 
 
 
and this can now be substituted i n (2): 
 
 
2
2 E
1R
EG EORV1 1 v2vRR = + + R
ER 
 
 
2 2
E
1R
EE GERVv 1RR R  = +    O     ( 6) 
 
 
Upon arri val at I, t here will have  to be a second burn that will simultaneous 
accelerate the rocket to GEO
GEOvR= , and rotat e the pl ane to equatori al (
). i=L
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 34 
Prof. Ma nuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 3 of 13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>( )
()1 1
1 10.16280 Sin28.5i Sini
2.71999 2.62296 i 1.28001 1.05832 Cos28.5 Cos i =
   
 
 
0
1i2.26 =  optimum    0
2i26.24 =
 
 
()
112
copV2 2 112 2 212 cosi cosv1 1 1 1 =+  ++    ++ + + i 
 
 
11 2
copV12.71199 2.62296cosi 1.21001 1.05832cosiv 6.14265= +  
=+ 
 
0.301780.23227 0.53405 =  -  small improvement  
 
Compare t o same w ith  = 0 1i
 
1crefV0.29838 0.23868v=+0.53706=  -  small improvement  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 34 
Prof. Ma nuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 9 of 13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Example: Effects of doin g a small plane change 2i simultaneous with the second  
(apogee-raising) firing in a 3 -impulse direct  GTO inject ion. 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 34 
Prof. Ma nuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 10 of 13  1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 101.51.511.521.531.541.551.561.571.58
0.10.150.20.25
(R2-RE)/RE=0.05
Di2(deg)(R2-RE)/RE=dVTot/vcE
Total dV for three-impulse launch from L=28.5 deg to GEO. Here vcE =sqrt(mu/RE)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>The apogee velocity is , given by a,GTOv
 
()GEOa,GTO 1 E E Rv =VcosR= R       ( 7) 
 
 
and so a GEO a,GTO GEOa,GTO Vv v 2vv cos22= + i 
 
 
EE
a
GEO GEO GEORRV= 1+ -2 cosLRR R              (8)  
 
 
This secon d burn is probably  provided by  the spacecraft itself, or else by the 
launcher's u pper stage.  
 
 
IDEALIZ ED TWO - BUR N GTO INJECTION  
 
One difficulty with the direct  injection scheme is t he fact that  GEO insertion at I 
must occur on the first pass, beca use the GT O perigee is act ually below the Earth's 
surface (see Fig. 2). Most oper ators prefer a temporary park ing of the spacecraft in a 
GTO orbi t which has a perigee above the gro und, so as  to make fu nctional tests a nd 
adjustments prior to the final apogee bu rn (over a period of 2-4 weeks). A  
modification of the launch seq uence to accom modate this is: 
 
(1) Fire Eastwa rds with selected for a l ow apogee (200 km  above ground ) at the 
equatori al crossi ng. 
(2) Fire again at equatorial cro ssing to raise the apogee to R GEO (no plane change) 
(3) At one o f the apogee passes, perfo rm the final (circularization + plane change 
burn). 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 34 
Prof. Ma nuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 4 of 13  Di
DVa
va,GTOvGEO
Fig. 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 34 
Prof. Ma nuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 13 of 13  Di2(deg)1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 100.190.1950.20.2050.210.2150.220.2250.23
0.25 (R2-RE)/RE=(R2-RE)/RE=0.05dV3/vcE
dV3 for three-impulse launch from L=28.5 deg.to GEO. Here, vcE=sqrt(mu/RE)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 34 
Prof. Ma nuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 11 of 13  1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
Di2(deg)(R2-RE)/RE=(R2-RE)/RE=
0.050.25dV1/vcE
0.9450.950.9550.960.9650.970.975
dV1 f or three-impulse launch f rom L=28.5 deg to GEO . Here vcE=sqrt(mu/RE)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 34 
Prof. Ma nuel Martinez-Sanchez              Page 12 of 13  1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 100.330.340.350.360.370.380.390.4
Di2(deg)(R2-RE)/RE=0.05(R2-RE)/RE=0.25
dV2/vcE
dV1 for three-impulse launch from L=28.5 deg to GEO. Here vcE=sqrt(mu/RE)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Nozzle Design: Method of Characteristics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_4_5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4-5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>1111o  +++ =  ur n
su sr s n s
 
 
 
() ()1sin sin =  rsssr
n 
 
 
  =  nds n ssn 
 
 
11 s i n
u  + =  u
ss n r
         
 
 
 Homentropic: ==dp  22
spc d c
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 8 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sanchez   Page 2 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Numerical Application
 
1
12 o o
aa
a aPP 12100 1 M M 1P2 1 P 
     == +  =             
 
Take  
0.3
1.3
a21.3 , M 100 1 3.5540.3= =  =
 
 
 Then  
2
11
aM1Kt a n t a n M 1K=   
2  12 . 3K210 . 3+== = .769
 
Also  
 oo
at67.35 67.35 =  =   
 
 
2
1o
aM1K tan 141.01K= = 
 
 
   
22a
K2
tar 11
h141.01cos cos2.769 K==
  
  a
tr34.41h=  
.769   and so
 
ometry,  h a=ra sin 
 
a
a
ar
M=  From the ge
 
    
   ah 1=a
th
h=9.684 
t34.41h3 . 5 5 4    
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 8 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sanchez   Page 9 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Select:   12 3 41.44 20.76 40.09 59.41++ + +== = =oooII I Io
 
 
Point M ()+I=+o ()-I=o ()o ()o ()o ()+o ()o 
1 1.1 +1.44 -1.44 1.44 0 65.38 65.38 -65.38o 
2 1.439  20.76 -1.44 11.10  9.66 44.02 53.68 -34.36 
3 1.726  40.09 -1.44 20.77  19.33  35.41 54.74 -16.08 
4 (and 4w ) 2.013  59.41 -1.44 30.43  28.99  29.79 58.78 -0.80 
5 1.726  20.76 -20.76 20.76  0 35.41 35.41 -35.41 
6 2.013  40.09 -20.76 30.43  9.67 29.79 39.46 -20.12 
7 (and 7w ) 2.315  59.41 -20.76 40.09  19.33  25.59 44.92 6.26 
8 2.315  40.09 -40.09 40.09  0 25.59 25.59 -25.59 
9 (and 9w ) 2.641  59.41 -40.09 49.75  9.66 22.25 31.91 -12.59 
10 (and 11 ) .3 59.41 -59.41 59.41  0 19.47 19.47 -19.47 
 
 
Notes
Points 1-4: same  
Point 5: Here =(a boundary condition) and 0 += 20.76 
Point 6-7: same  
Point 8: Here = and = 40.09 0+
Point 9: same  
Point 10: Here  and = 59.41 0= 
 
Note the very shallow angles of the m+ lines (from 4, 7, 9, 10)  which will put point 
10 far to the right, and point 11 (at slope (m+) of 19  even farther. .47o
 
Locating the points geometrically   
 
 
 
()() ca cb a xx t a n xx t a n yy+ = b
 
 
aba b
cy y x tan x tanxtan tan+ +=+ 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 8 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sanchez   Page 12 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>(1) Calculate (  from the angle )cx, r ()()ab, +  
 
() ()+ +  +  =   + ab a
ab a bx tan x tan r rxxt a n xxt a n r r xtan tanb 
 
and  ()= bbrr xxt a n
 
(2) axxmcos+= 
 
bxxmcos= 
 
(3) Advance invariants  based on w, w+  , at a, b: 
 
()
()aa
a
a
bb
b
bsin sinww mr
sin sinww mr+
 + = + +  =      (r at c, computed in (1)) 
 
(4)  () () MM w , M= = 
 
(5) Iterate from (1) with  averaged between (a, b) and c: ,
 
() ()
() ()ac
bc2
2 + 

+ + +
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 4-5 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 16 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Example of Application: Ideal 2-D g Nozzle at Design Condition  plu
 
 
  
 
Along 
 
 
  aa m,=   
 
 Simple region (Prandtl-Meyer fan   
In particular, at inlet M=1, so   centered at lip L) 
 
 
 throat a=   
 
2d1tand 1==
r
r M   
 
 
 
 
 
 
From geometry, t2+=   
 
a = Sub.    aa2+ += +  
 
ta=       2=+    
 
 
2
11 2 1
211tan tan 1 tan2 1 1  = +    =  MKM KK M 1+
 
2 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 8 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sanchez   Page 7 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>XRS-2200 Engine Data 
 
 
 
 
Thrust, lbf 
  
 At Sea Level     206,500 
 In Vacuum     268,000 
 
 
Specific Impulse, sec.  
 
 At Sea Level     339 
 In Vacuum     439 
 
 
P r o p e l l a n t s       O2, H2 
 
Mixture Ratio (O/F)     5.5 
 
Chamber Pressure, psia     857 
 
Cycle        G a s  G e n e r a t o r  
 
Area Ratio       5 8  
 
Throttling, Percent Thrust    40-119 
 
Differential Throttling     + / -  1 5 %  
 
Dimensions, Inches  
 
 Forward End     133 high x 
       8 8  w i d e  
 
 A f t  E n d      4 6  h i g h  x  
       8 8  w i d e  
 
 Forward to Aft    79 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 4-5 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 20 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>2-D Simple Regions
 
Consider a uniform  region; the flow from it enters 
some disturbed region, like a wall turning. One of 
the m families originate in the uniform region (m+ 
in example) and carries a constant  invariant, e.g. 
oo += +  everywhere downstream. Along one  
of the other  ch
nce aracteristics (m- here), we carry a 
constant (which varies fr om ch. To ch. of that 
family); we can evaluate it at the wall, for insta
 
 
ww=   along each m- line and 
()woo w w o so 2 o = +   
 
then   
w longeachm
= + +  =   =
 = +     = +  =  
 
o  (and hence M, ) are constant along each m =    +
 
()ooww w w
oo ww oow2 2 along each m
2a
 
- ands , and these m- lines are 
ightstra  (const. +). 
 
 
This is a Simple Region  (one of the invariants is constant). The turning of the flow is 
 dictated by how  changes on a m+ line, as different m- lines are crossed. Since on a
m+ we have oo += + , changes of  are equal and opposite to those in  ( 
increases as M  does in the expansion, so  decreases (increase negatively) at the 
same rate.) So, we can interpret  as the magnitude of the isentropic flow turning i
a simple region, i.e., when nothing varies along one characteristic family. 
 n 
alculation of  (M) 
 C
 
 
22dd 1d12 =  +uM T
uM T 
 
 
 
but  d1= MM
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 8 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sanchez   Page 5 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>s o  
 + =  2 1 s i n
cu
su s n r1p 
 
 
  
and, from s eq. of motion, =1p uuss so you can eliminate 
p
s: 
 
 
21s  +  =  uu u
su s n rcin  2
21s1 in  + + = uu
us n c r 
        M2-1 
 
    
    
 21 sin  +=Mu
us nr   (4) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Introduce the Mach angle 11
211sin tan
1==
 M M  
21tan
1=
M  
 
 
 
Then (2)   21tan o  +=Mu
un s  
 
 
And (4)   21t antan   +=Mu
us n rsin 
 
 
Introduce the Prandtl-Meyer function ()M by 
 
 
 
  2 dd   (to be integrated later) 1 = uMu
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 8 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sanchez   Page 3 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Boundary with Prescribed Pressure 
 
 
c
rr12PP
r11M2=
+ ,  
 
and ,  () MM w=
 
so  (given ) ()PP w=oP
 
or  () ww P=
 
So, if P is fixed on a boundary (contact surface), we can assign w there  (just as we 
assign  on a solid boundary) 
 
                              
     
 
From known point a,  
 
aaww =   
 
So  () aa wP w= + 
 
and this determines the slope of the bo undary, and that of the reflected m+ 
 
() aa w2 w P w+ = +   
 
More General Contact Surface Condition  
 
If the outside fluid is also supersonic, we  must solve on both sides of the contact 
surface, making sure P and  are common at each boundary point 
 
 
    
    
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 4-5 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 14 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>Gives adequate performance but less than ? nozzle. Not really 
justified. (Hoffman, J. D. J. of  Propulsion 3 (March-April 1987): 150-
156. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 4-5 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 19 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>2
1 1tan=MKK 
 
 
2M1 1tantan== KKK 
 
 
 
2cos sind1d
tan cos cos  == = drd r K KKKdr rKKK 
K
 
 
2Kconst.
cos=

r
K       
 
 (throat height)   
t 0,r h= =2t
K
cos=

hr
K For 
 
In particular, at end of expansion  
2
a 1
aa1tan=  =MMM KK, then 
        
 
 
 
2t=hr   and    aK
acos
 Ka
aa a
asi==hr nr
M   
       aa aa 2
a1cos 1= = xr r
M 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 8 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sanchez   Page 8 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>2.2530.25= = K  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
111.21 13tan tan 1.21 1 1.435 ;3 =  =oo o0= 
 
11913tan tan 9 1 59.413 ;3=  =oee 0=
=  =  oo 
 
  
  
 
  
  
 At inlet: =oI (also at 4) 1.435
  
At exit:  (also at 4, 
7, 9, 10) 59.413+=+= + =o
ee I 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 442 1.435 59.413 57.978 28.989 = + = =o
At 4, then,    442 59.413 1.435 60.848 30.424 =+ = =o
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 8 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sanchez   Page 11 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>2-D Spike Nozzle with  PPaa design&lt;  
 
 
 
 
Pressure forces from hot-gas bathed surfac es are the same as at design. Net thrust 
is increased because the  contribution  is reduced: aPaePA
 
() des. a a e des.FF P P A=+   
   (just as for a bell) 
and so  vac des. a e des.FFP A=+
 
 
Practical Nozzle Designs  
 
Ideal nozzle are too long, last portion has small wall angle, so small thrust 
contribution. With small ?, maybe negative  contribution. So, options : 
 
(a) Constrain length, ask for contour that gives highest thrust/given L. 
Methods of calculus of variations (Raw  nozzle, Ref :  Exhaust Nozzle 
Contour from Optimum Thrust, Jet Propulsion 28 (June 1958): 377-382. 
Exit flow non-parallel, non-uniform, computationally high. 
 
(b) Ad-hoc method (widely used) is to truncate contract  an ideal nozzle. 
  
(1) Design wall contour for desired ecPP  
(2) If longer than desired L truncate it to some intermediate area ratio. 
(3) Contract this truncated nozzle to desired length 
 '' ' cd esi
ab b
di dxLxx xxL==red
eal 
(4) Translate profile to right metal kink at P smoothes out. 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 4-5 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 18 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>and 2
a
aa
tx 1rc o s 3 4 . 4 11h3
.554= =    a
tx
h=33.02 
 
 
 
 
Very long and pointy, should be truncated. 
 
 
 
Non-Simple Regions . When the characteristics of both families intersect some 
upstream disturbance, they affect each ot hers invariant, and characteristics are no 
longer straight, and no longer carry cons tant flow properties (except for their own 
invariant) 
 
 0-1-4 is a simple region 
  
 0-4-41 is uniform 
 
 1-4-10 is non-simple 
 
 4-41--11 is a simple region 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Then we need to calculate in a step-by-st ep manner, carrying to each point the two 
invariants I+, I- from neighboring upstream points, along the m+, m- lines from them 
to us. After this is done, we know the new segments of m+, m- from our point (slopes 
,+  ), so we can extend the grid as we go. Notice the flowfield properties can 
be found first everywhere and only then we  need to come back and place the points 
geometrically. 
 
Example : Design a 2-D ideal nozzle to expand from near sonic conditions (M 0 = 1.1) 
to M e = 3. Use only 4 characteristics. Us e a corner expansion as a starter, 
=1.25 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 8 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sanchez   Page 10 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>()()() ab ab
cb cbyy xx t a nyy xx t a n t a ntan tan+=  =+ 
 
 
() ba a b
cy tan y tan x x tan tanytan tan++ =+ 
 
 
 
 
  
  
 put x a, ya into 1, 2                           
  
Run 2     x c (st. in 7)  taninto 3 
  
Run 3     y c (st. in 7) 
 xb, yb into 4.5  
 
tan into 6 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Finding the (x,y)s is very laborious. Accuracy can be increased by averaging 
together the angles at the ends of each segment, which can be done because those 
angles come from the first pass. For instance, ac bc,22++==  .
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 8 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sanchez   Page 13 of 20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>() (11 22Pw Pw=)
+P
P
w Pw P+ + = + 
 
12=   
 
From m know  1 () 11Iw++=+
 
From m know  2 () 22Iw=
 
So, II  () () 12 1 2
 
12 SolveforP w ,w  
  known now 
() ( )and 12 12wP wP II
22++ +=++
 
 
Modifications for Axisymmetric Conditions  
 
()
()sin sinwr m
sin sinwr m+
 + =  =  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 4-5 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 15 of 20</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Turbines (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_27/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>27</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>If two stage s are used, one can over-turn  the flow in the first rotor, so that it 
leaves wi th a component o f velocity con trary to rotation. The second stator then can 
re-direct this flow without accelerat ing it, and sen d it into yet another pure impu lse 
rotor. It ca n be sho wn that  this velocity compou nding (see Sect ion 3. of this lect ure) 
will yield four ti mes as much  torqu e as the  single impu lse stage su ch as those in Fig. 
1b so t hat the flow is re-expanded  in the second nozzle (pressure co mpounding). 
This only doubles the pow er of the single stage, but improves the efficiency. The 
SSME f uel turbopump  turbine is essenti ally of this type, al thoug h there is some n on 
zero reactio n (R  0.22). 
 
For prelimin ary design purpose, Re f [46] (Refer to the list of the References in 
Lecture 25) presents (,  diagrams similar to those  in use for pumps. One of 
these is reproduced in Fig. 2. The quantities Q and gH in the defi nitions of  ds and ns 
(Eqs. 3.34-3.35) are now to be sp ecified more ful ly: the volumetri c flow rate Q is at )s snd
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 27 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 2 o f 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 27: Turbi nes 
 
 
1. Rocket turbine design e mphasizes power density, because  of the over riding 
concern for mass saving. Effi ciency, while clearly a co nsiderat ion, takes a less 
promin ent role t han in aircraf t turbine design . This tends to favor low reaction 
turbines and wh en multi-staging, velocity compou nding over pressu re 
compoundi ng. 
 
The degree of reaction of a turbine stage (stator nozzles plus rotor blades) 
is the frac tion of the fluid stati c enthalpy drop which occurs in the roto r (see 
section 2. of this Lecture). In an  impu lse turbine, the degree of reaction is zero, 
meaning that the gas e xpands and accelerate s as it turns  in the sta tor passages, 
and then is merely redirected at co nstant thermodynami c state b y the movi ng 
rotor blades. The stage velocity tria ngles are shown in Fig 1 , which also  includes 
the case o f a 50% reac tion turbi ne for comp arison. I n both cases, the flow leaves 
axially. The torque (a nd hence the power) i s proporti onal to the c hange in the 
tangen tial component o f the absol ute vel ocity. Fig 1 sho ws that this change i s the 
wheel speed R for the 50% reaction  turbine, but is 2  R for the impu lse 
turbine. It is also clear, however,  that flow vel ocities are higher in the impulse 
case which will lead to larg er viscous losses. A lso, the la ck of acceleration in the  
rotor passage w ill favor flow separat ion on the suction side.  Altogether, the more 
powerful impu lse st age is also less efficient. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 27 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 1 o f 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>c=absolute vel. 
 =relative vel. 
 
 Assum e axial exhaust   
 (design cond. ) 
 
 
 =i IN 1Torquecsinr
m 
 
 ()= =istage
IN 1P Powerrcsin
m 
  
      ()= OUT 1 rc tan 
 
  =OUT IN 1 cc cos
 
 
 
xc=cons t. through stage  
 
()  == =  22 2 2
2 stator IN OUT OUT OUT
1 2
1P cc c c 11t an22 2 cos 
 
()
() = =stator OUT 1
stageP ctan 11RP2 r 
 
Also, ()
()=  = stage OUT 1
2Pctan P
r r
 
So, =1R    () =21 R  More work/stage with less reaction 2
 
 
R=0 (impulse turbine) =2 
R=1 (50%  reaction)   2=1
 
 
Also, = ,   so,   =
=1
2tan
1tan=OUT xcc
rr For, 50%  design, =12  
and =2
OUTrtan       F or impulse, =ta  cn 2tan12
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 27 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 5 o f 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>3. Velocity Compounding:  Follows thi s diagram starti ng from  the exhaust (at 
bottom )    
  
     
 
 
 St. 1 
        
   Rotor 1 Power =  
   2m(4r 2r)R6m(R) +=ii
 
 St. 2 
       
     Rotor 2 Power =  
     2m(2R)R2m(R) =ii
 
     Total = 8  =  2m(R)i
 4Singleimpulse   
    
     1st stator must give  
4r tangen tial velocity. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 27 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 6 o f 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>4. Blade root  stress : 
                      
2
bPr A drdAdr=() dr22 2
1b 21P( rr2=1) 
                             
22 2
21 b1(r)0 P (rr)2= =2 1
) 
 
2 2
2 1 A( rr=    2
1bA
2= 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 27 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 7 o f 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>turbine exit static con ditions, and the energy gH is the total-to-sta tic isentropi c 
enthalpy dr op: 
 
 
                             1
.
.1
  =     te
pT ti
ttiPgH cTP     (1) 
Notice that , as in the case of a pump,  the produ ct   has a  simple connotation:  ssnd
 
                                    
028= =
ssRndC     (2) 
 
 
where 02=c gH is someti mes call ed the spo uting velocity. The velocity rati o 
 01
2=
Rc  is often  used as a desi gn paramet er. For opti mum effi ciency,  it should 
be about 0.4 in an impulse stage, 0.2 for a velocity-compound doubl e stage, or 0.7 
for a 50 % reaction stage [40]. The  optimum rotational speed of the turbine was in 
the pas t higher tha n that for the dr iven pumps, which required h eavy gearin g. The 
steady ad vancements in inducer de sign ha ve more recen tly allowed mou nting both 
turbine and  pumps o n one sha ft, with major m ass savings . 
 
             Whereas pum p impellers (except for hydrogen) are rarely stress lim ited, the 
reverse is true for turbines, where the bl ade root axial stress and /or the disc rim 
hoop stress  tend to limit speed. The radi al root stress is ap proxim ately (see Sec. 4 of 
this Lecture) 
 
                               2
6bA
2=      (3) 
 
where A is the annulus flow area and bis the den sity of th e blade mat erial, which is 
dictated by  the flow rate an d inlet gas den sity. There is thu s an incentiv e to use 
materials, such as dire ctionally solidified su perall oys, tha t retain a high stre ngth at 
the uncool ed operati ng condi tions. 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 27 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 3 o f 7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Pressurization and Pump Cycles (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_24/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>We notice from (5) that the gas tank mass is nearly  independent of its in itial 
pressure: a higher  allows a smalle r volume  (Eq. 3), but requires thicker 
walls (Eq. 4). Values of  5-10 times  are comm on. To  compare the m ass of 
the gas  tank to that of the mai n propellant tan ks, assume = 0.2, GoPGV
GoPPP
GeGoP/P5
3=  
(He gas) a nd p pLR= 6. For e qual material ratio ( ), Eqs. (5 ) and (6) then give 
GTK
PTKM1.64M= , indicating that the gas reservoi r is likely to be  the heavi er 
compon ent (although addin g anti-slosh baffles, in sulation, etc. may modif y this 
conclusion). 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 24 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 4 o f 5 High 
Pressure 
GasREGULATOR
PP PP
PG(t)
VGVP(t)
Fig. 2 . Schema tic of gas pressurization systemOXIDIZER
FUEL</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>The mass of the propellant itself  is p TK MVp=, where th e densities of  oxidizer 
and fuel have been ave raged to p. To compare to th e min imum tan kage mass,  
assume ste el construction, with 423.410(m/sec)   and = 20 atm. Eq . (5) 
then gives  and Eq. (3.6) gives   for a 
total of 296  Kg / mpP
3
GTK TK M/ V 184Kg/m = ,3
GTK TK M/V 112Kg/m, =
3. This is t o be compared t o the mean propel lant density; for 
N2O4-UDMH  this is of the order of 1 000 Kg /m3. Thus, not counting flanges val ves, 
regulators, etc., the tankage mass  is 30% of the propella nt mass,  a figu re which 
is excessive for any am bitious miss ion. Advanc ed composite materials can reduce  
this mass si gnificantly, however, Titanium is used most ly. 
 
An alternative method to reduce the re quired gas reservoir mass is to heat 
the pressu rizing gas prior t o injection into the propel lant tank. This can  be 
accomplish ed through heat exchanging, perhaps using the gas as a nozzle 
coolan t, or by including in the gas a very small amount of oxygen a nd hydroge n, 
below  the flammabi lity limit, and then  passing the gas through a catal ytic bed 
reactor. In either  case, as suming a gas temperatu re rise  T is accomplish ed, a 
term  needs  to be ad ded on the rig ht hand side of Eq. (1), where (MGvMc T G(t)) 
is the gas mass tha t has flowed through the heater. This yi elds eventually a 
modified expression for the gas reservoir volu me: 
 
PV
TP1 -PT


p
G TK
Go Ge
Go=
+V     (7) 
 
As an example, 1% O 2 plus 2%  H2 (by m ole) in He yields upon re action  
, which nearly cuts in half the requ ired gas t ank volume (and mass) . 
One problem w ith heating met hods is t he poten tial for errat ic variations in feed 
pressure if propellant sloshing cools the  press urizing gas in an unstea dy manner.  T230K 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 24 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 5 o f 5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 24: Pressuri zation and Pump Cycles 
 
 
Thrust Ch ambe r Pressurizati on 
 
1. Introducti on 
                       
The most te chnically demanding pa rt of a modern high pressure liquid 
propellant rocket is the chamber pressuri zation system. C onsider for example the 
cluster of four R D-170 engines po wering the  Energia fi rst stage. Their shared 
oxygen pump must de liver 1792 Kg/sec (1 .63 m3) of LOX at 614  atm pressure to  
the comb ustors, for  a power of 176 ,000 HP. The whole eng ine weighs 9500 Kg. 
Similar ly, the SSME LH  pump (see Fig. 3 in lecture 25) deliv ers 73 K g/sec of LH 
(1.06 m3/sec) at 470 atm pressure, for a po wer of 76 ,000 HP. The SSME mass is 
2870 Kg , of which the LH turbop ump is 344 Kg. And these flow rates are both 
dwarfed by those of the old F1 Saturn en gine, which sw allowed a small r iver (3.5 
m3/ sec) of LOX, albeit at a more modest pressure. 
 
Because of the importance of this s ystem, we will devote thi s lecture to 
engine pressurization cycles and comp onents. 
 
 
2. Gas Press urization Systems  
 
The simplest wa y to achieve the re quired thrust chamber pressure is to 
provide a small, high p ressure gas  reservoi r, whi ch, at firing time, pressuri zes th e 
propell ant tanks. The tanks m ust then be thick enough to  support the thrust 
chamber pr essure, plus  the injector  drop. I n addition, the g as reservoirs are also 
relatively heavy. T hus, the performance of a gas-pressur ized rocket lags that of a 
pump-pressurized rocket (where the tanks can be m uch lighter), as shown in Fig. 
1 (from Ref . 40). We notice here that the relative size of the gai ns due to a  turbo 
pump s ystem become overpowering for high V rockets,  b ut may no t be worth 
the extra  complexity for smal l V    
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 24 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 1 o f 5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>NOTE: If isothermal exp.,  GP G UU Uo +=  and the n ()( )GG pP Go PtVPVtPV +=G 
 
which can be re- written for an ideal  gas as 
 
 vPUsingU1=   () ()GG pP Go Pt V PVtPV + =G    (2) 
 
 
This relat es  to  at an y time during ope ration. If the final gas pre ssure 
is (large enough to still overcome the regulator and injector drops), a nd if GP(t)PV(t)
GePTKV 
represents the whole tankage volume, we  obtain for the gas reservoir volume 
 
 
p
G
Go GePVPP=TKV      (3)  
                                        
(no for isothermal case) (mor e generally in between) 
 
The min imum mass of th is gas rese rvoir, assumed spherical of radius RG, can 
be esti mated by  noting that its wall thickness t G must be  
 
go
G
GWPt2=GR       (4) 
 
 
where  is the worki ng stress of the wall material . If the  density of this wall 
materia l is GW
GW, we obtai n for the gas  tank mass 
 
 
pT K GW
GTK
GW Ge
GoPV 3M2 P1P=
     (5) 
 
A similar calculation can be made fo r the ma ss of each o f the propellant tanks. I f, 
for simplic ity, both, oxidizer and fuel tanks are  assumed to be geometrically 
similar an d made of  the same materia l (a cylindrical body  of length Lp, capped b y 
hemispheres of radi us Rp, with equal Lp/Rp for both ), the n the propel lant tank  
mass is 
 
 
     pp PW
PTK pTK
PW pp1L /R 3MP3 2 1L /R4+=+V 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 24 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 3 o f 5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Fig. 1. Payload ratio for typical gas pr essurization and pu mp pressurization 
 
 
Thus, gas pressurization continues to play a role, particularly in small space-
based engines, such as monopropella nt maneuvering and attitude control 
thrusters. A relatively la rge and sophisticated exampl e is the Shuttle OMS/RCS 
system. 
 
If a gas pressurization system is adop ted, a choice must be made between 
regulated or blow-down gas delivery. The regulated type is used most often, 
because it avoids chamber operation over an extended pressure range, which may be lead to stability problems. On th e other hand, blow-down operation does 
result in a simpler and lighter system, with less gas inventory, and is standard in hydrazine monopropellant applications. 
 
Consider a regulated gas feed syst em, schematized in Fig. 2. Let  be the 
decreasing pressure in the gas reservoir, of constant volume  and  the 
regulated tank pressure, where ()GPt
GVpP
()pVt is the increasing ullage volume in both 
propellant tanks. The in ternal energy of the gas at some times t is  and 
the work of gas expansion in dt is . Therefore, integr ating in (0,t), 
(assuming G PU+U
pPd Vp
adiabatic  expansion) 
 
 
Gp p p GUUP VUo ++=      (1) 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 24 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 2 o f 5 0.40
0.20
0
0 10,000 20,000 30,000 40,0001002000.60
Pump Fed
Pressure Fed
Mission Velocity (fps)0Payload Weight/Gross Weight
Percent Im
provem
ent w
ith Pum
p-Fed Engine</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Convective Heat Transfer: Other Effects (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>eL
t ww
t
cc0pcT QT dx11 2S1TTmcT= = R i (15) 
 
 
where we  have used the result in equation (3 ). For th e loss of  static energy, we have 
the resu lt in (13). Using both in (14), 
 
 
 
 
   =   +          1 1LL
2 ee ww
ep c t t
cc c00PP TT dx dxu2 cT12S1 2S1TR P T P R 
 
 
or   
      =              1 1L
2 e w
ep c t
cc0PP T dxu2 cT1 2S1 1PT Pe
R (16) 
 
 
We see now that the f actor 
1
eP1P occurri ng in the integral of (1 6) is just the 
therm odynamic relief we had  mentioned ea rlier, which makes the l oss of kinetic 
energy be less than the heat loss. In deed, this factor  becomes zero as , so, as 
anticipated, heat losses near  the exit are irre levant. e PP
 
 
To simplif y the writing, use 
 
 =    1
2 e
ep c 0
cPu2 cT1P  
 
and define  
 
() 
   = =   1 1
ee
0,e x,e
cPP1a nd 1P Px : 
 
 
 =    L 2
x,e e w
t 2
c0 ,e e 0 0u T dx12S1TR u (17) 
 
 
and, agai n, the ri ght-hand-side minus the x,e
0,e
 factor woul d be the relative heat 
loss ( equation 3). Numerical evalu ation shows t hat the modified integral in  (17) is 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 8 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 5 of 6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>1) Non-Space missions  Rocket Type 
Atmospheri c/Ionospher ic Soundi ng Solid Propell ant, 1-4  stages 
Tactical Missile Solid Prop., 1-2 stages 
Medium-Lo ng Range Missiles  Solid or Liquid Prop., 2 -3 
 stages (very high
 accelerat ion)  
 
2) Launc h to space Solid, liquid or combin ations, 
      2-4 stages (2-4g) 
 Possible: hybrid, 2-4 s tages 
 
 
3) Impu lsive V in space  Small Solid Prop. (Apog ee 
(time-critic al maneuvers, kick, etc ) 
energy change from ellipt ic orbit s, Bi-propellant (storable)  
plane chang e from el liptic orbits, l iquids, Monopropell ant 
non-fuel-limited situations...)  (storabl e) liquids, 
V  1000 m/s Future: Nuclear therma l 
 
4) Low-T hrust V in space  
(Mass-limit ed missions V  2000  m/s Solar-electric systems: 
non ti me-criti cal missions,  Arcjets (a b it faster, less Isp) 
small, continuous orbit corrections  Hall, Ion (sl ower, hi gher Isp) 
near-ci rcular orbi ts...) PPT (preci sion maneu vers) 
 Nuclear-electric system s 
 Direct solar-thermal 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 1 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 3 of 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Prop ulsion  
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 1: Introducti on 
 
 
 
Types of Rockets (En gines) 
 
 
- Depending on gas acceleration mechanism/force on vehicle mechanism. 
 
 Thermal  Gas pushes directly on walls by P (pressure) fo rces 
    Nozzle accelerates gas by P forces  
     (most large rockets, chem, nuclear , some electric) 
 
 
 El ectrostati c  Ions accelerated by JG
E field 
    (a) Electrostatic force (push) on electrodes 
     ( Ion engines) 
    (b) Force (push) on magnetic coils throug h gas  jG
 
     ( Hall thrusters) 
 
 El ectromagneti c Gas accelerated by GJG
jB forces 
    Force (pus h) on coils or cond uctors  
     ( MPD thrusters, PPTs) 
 
16.512 co ncentrates o n Thermal  
 
 
- Dep ending on en ergy source: 
 
 
      S olid Propellant 
 
Chemical ( always thermal ) Liquid Propellant Monopropell ant 
         B ipropellant 
 
     H ybrid 
 
 Nuclear (Thermal) 
 Nuclear (Electric)   can be Thermal, ES or EM 
 Solar (Thermal) 
 Solar (Electric)   can be Thermal, ES or EM 
 
16.512 deals mostly  with Chemi cal. 
 
 
- Depen ding on Thr ust level  (per unit mass) 
 
- High thrust ( 1g) for launch, fa st space maneuvering (16.5 12) 
- Low thrust (10-5  10-2 g) for efficient in-space maneuvers (16.522) 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 1 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 1 of 3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rotordynamics Problems (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_29/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>29</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>The tangentia l force f per unit length along the perimeter is the n approximated as  
 
ffH      (16) 
 
although it must be pointed o ut that this  equa tes work  loss to efficiency loss, a nd 
hence it ignores pressure ratio variations also induced by the of fset. The clearance 
perturbation  varies in proportion to the o ffset e, and sinus oidally with 
azimuth  , and so, upon projection in the dire ction perpendicular t o the offset, and 
integration, one obt ains  
 
2==e QFR fH Re
H     (17) 
 
where 2=Q Rfis the turbine to rque. The direct force  is predicted to the  zero. &amp;F
 
The existence of these forces was confirmed experimentally in Ref. [64] and , 
in more detail, in Refs [59,60] where it was found that, in addition to the above 
mechanism, a second  source of cro ss-forc es is a tange ntially rotate d pressure  
nonuniform ity is acting  on the turbine h ub. The contri bution of this component is 
additive to the basic Alford/Tho mas effect, and amounts  typically to 40% of  the total 
cross-force. In addition, bo th mechanisms also give st iffening f orce co mponent s 
(along wi th offset direction). 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                       Lecture 29 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                 Page 10 of 13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>3. Sources of Rotor-Dynamic E xcitation: Cr oss-Cou pled Forces 
                      
The most  important e xcitation mechani sms are rel ated to the  production of 
cross-forces  when the shaft is of fset from its central locat ion. Before describin g some 
specific examples, the generic dynamic e ffects  of these cr oss-forces will be 
discussed. 
 
Qualitatively, if a cross- force F y resul ts from a  shaft offset ex, this force exerts a 
torque F yex with respec t to the nominal shaft center. It  is well know n that any linear 
vibration in the x-y plane can be re solved into a forward a nd a backward circular  
oscillat ions. Of these two, o ne (the forward  component i n Fig 2. is reinforced by t he 
resulting torque Fyex, which, being produ ced by  the displacemen t itself, will rem ain 
synchronized to it. This is the basic instability mech anism.  
 
 
 
 
 
For a simple linear ized analysis, suppose  the fluid effects  are such  that a 
general transverse dis placement ( ex,ey) and displacement rate  of the shaft 
produces fo rces ( F,
x yee

x,Fy) according to 
 
 
                     
       = +                  xx xy xx xy xx
yy xy xx xy xx
yKK C C Fe
Fe KK C Cexe   (1) 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                       Lecture 29 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                 Page 4 of 1 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 29: Rot ordynamics Pr oblems  
 
 
1. Turbopump Rotor Dynamics   
 
Because of high po wer density and  low damping in rocket turbopumps , these 
machines exhibit in the ir most extreme form  a vari ety of vibration effects, which are 
either absent or mas ked by  normal  dampi ng mechani sms in other turbo machi nes. 
The low  dampin g is especia lly prominent in liquid hydrogen  pumps, becau se of the 
very low viscosit y and den sity of this mediu m. Oil squeeze film damper s are 
precluded in any cryogenic medium. 
 
The general  frame work  of Rotor  Dynamics is now  well established, through a 
combin ation of classical an alysis and detailed n umerical s imulation [49, 50, 51] . 
Intensive efforts on the applic ation of t hese the oretical methods to  a specific rocket 
turbopum p are describ ed by Ek[52 ], and were instrumental in  pointing the way to a 
series of  improvemen ts that resolv ed a seriou s dev elopme nt problem in  the SSM E. 
The greates t difficulty in this field remai ns the precise characterization of the fluid 
forces acting on the rotor at compo nents su ch as seals, turbines , or impellers. Once 
these are specif ied, numerica l models of  great  power and versatility can be brough t 
to bear for analyzing the dynamics of a given configuration. Because o f the 
remain ing uncertainties in the  basic forc es. Eks 1978 reco mmendation [52 ] remains 
valid today: Predict ion of stability in a new design  must be v iewed with skepticism.  
A predict ion of instability should, however, be taken very seriou sly. 
 
 
2. Forced and Sel f- Excited Vibrations 
 
Three are two types of rotor dyna mics problems: 
 
(a) Resonances  which usually occur when the rotating speed c oincides with one o f 
the natural (critical) frequ encies of  the rotor (including its support ing 
structure). These fall in the category of Forced Vi brations, in whi ch an excitation 
force produces deflection response s of an amplit ude which in creases as t he 
excitation frequency approaches a critica l frequency. If the excitation is at exact 
resonance, the amplitude grows linearly in  time at fi rst, and then, if viscous 
dampin g exist s, it approach es a limit  which is inversely proport ional to the 
dampin g factor. Removal of  the excit ation removes the  response. The  exciting 
forces are typically rela ted to rotor mass imbal ance or geomet rical imperfections. 
Resonances  rarely pose serious problems , unless the steady operating point lies 
very close to one critical. On the o ther ha nd, since the s tructure is made as l ight 
as pract ical, many natural modes u sually exist, several of them eit her below  or 
not far above the operating range. Efforts are made in the  design p hase to create  
a relat ively wide ran ge of resonance- free speeds around the normal operating 
point. Passage t hrough criticals, if made rapidly enough, is not a seve re 
condition. 
 
Table 3 (Ref [53 ]) shows the cri tical frequenci es of the SSME fuel turbopu mp. 
Notice that  several  of the sha ft modes ar e split into adjacen t pairs of  critical 
frequencies because of the lack of symme try of the casing  struc tural s upports, 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                       Lecture 29 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                 Page 1 of 1 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>even though the bearin g structure itself is symmet ric. This asy mmet ry is in  
general  a benefi cial effect , and pro vides a sort of effective damping [54]. 
 
 
(b) Self- Excite d Vibrations  These are autonomous oscill ations, in which th e shaft 
vibrates at one of its natural frequen cies (not equal to the shaft speed), a nd due 
to some po sitive feedback mecha nism, absorbs energy from an external source 
(usually the fluid) into the vibrational mode.  Exact balan cing does n ot remov e 
this type of vibration. Once initiated, if damping is in sufficient, the vibration will 
increase ex ponentially in amplit ude until some n onlinear mech anism in tervenes, 
or un til rubbi ng occurs . Self-excited vibrations are al so call ed rotor-dynami c 
instabilities or sub- synchronous vibrations. The latter design ation is due to the 
fact that they are most often observed  in the lowest shaft mode when the 
rotating speed is w ell above the frequency of th is mode.  For some mech anisms of 
excitation, the ratio of t he rotati on speed at on set of i nstability to t he frequenc y 
of the vibration excited is a simple integer, 
 
COUPLED H PFTP ROTO R AND CASE MODES 
 
Mode Frequency(Hz) Descri ption 
1          - Rotor free s pin, X 
2 47.0 Case rocking, Y 
3 100.8 Case rocking, Z 
4 196.4 Case rocking + bending, Y 
5 197.5 Diffuser torsion 
6 249.8 Case rocking + bending, Z 
7 287.6 Rotor transl ation, Y 
8 321.0aRotor transl ation, Z 
9 375.1 Rotor rocking, Z 
10 424.0aRotor rocking, Y 
11 463.7 Rotor axial, X 
12 488.7 Case + roto r rocking, Z  
13 513.6 Rotor bending, Y 
14 515.0aRotor bending, Z 
15 554.8 Turbine case torsion, X  
16 574.7 Diffuser bending, Y 
17 577.4 Diffuser bending, Z 
18 599.4 Case + roto r rocking, Y 
19 650.4 Case torsion, X 
20 657.3 Case axial, X 
21 694.9 Turbine case bending, Z 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                       Lecture 29 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                 Page 2 of 1 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>62. J.S. Alford,  Protesting Turbo machinery from Self-Excited Rotor Whirl, J. of 
Engineering for Po wer, Oct. 1965 . 
 
63. H.J. Thomas  Unstable  Oscillatio ns of turbine Rotors Due  to Steam Leakage  in 
the Clearance Of  the se aling Glands and t he Bucket s. Bull.  Scient ifique A.J.M.,  
Vol. 71, 19 58, pp  1039 -1063. 
 
64. K. Urlicks,  Clearance Fl ow Generated Transverse Forces at the Rotors of 
Thermal T urbomachine s. NASA TM -7729 2, Oct.1983. (Translated from 
Doctoral Dissertation at the Technical Univ. of Munich, 19 75). 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                       Lecture 29 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                 Page 13 of 13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>The coefficients xxKand xyK are the direct and cross -coupled stiffness, 
respect ively. Notice that the cylindrical symmet ry has been expl oited to reduce to 
two the number of sti ffness factors, and that a positive xxK is restoring, and will 
augment th e structural stiffness  K0, although, in general, 0&lt;&lt;xxK K
,. Similar 
comments apply to the damping c oefficients ,xx xy CC  except that xxCmay be of the 
same order as any additional damping C0. 
 
 
Define a co mplex displacement 
 
ex + i ey = z        ( 2) 
 
then   ()
02
00 2
2
()
0 2()
() 
+
 =+ + ++

= + xx yx
xxx xyy xx x xyy
KK e y
xyx yyx xx ydeMK KeKe CCeC
dt
deMK e CeCCe
dte
  (3 a, b) 
 
 
Add i x (3b) to (3a ):  
 
 
()() ()2
0 2=+ ++ xx x y xy y xdzM KKeie Keie
dt 
     z   -i z 
 
 
2
00 2() ( )
=++++xx xy xx xydzMK K iKzCC iC
dtz 
          K    C 
 
 
0CKzzzMM++ =DD D       (4) 
 
 
Put now (unstable if 
=itzz e I&lt; 0)  20 +=C KiMM  (5) 
 
 
       
  
                                                                         
                                         (6) 2
22= +CCiMMK
M
 
 
Call  
0xy
xxKKK=        
0xy
yyKKK=         0
01
2xx CC
KM+=       
01
2xyC
KM=       
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                       Lecture 29 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                 Page 5 of 1 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>4. Some E xamples of Cross-Cou pled Force G eneration 
 
Among the mechanisms whic h have been identified as contributors to the 
produ ction of destabilizing cross- forces are ( a) Pressure non-uniformity in labyrinth 
and other seals;  (b) Non-uniform driv ing force in  turbines due to tip leak age ef fects 
[59, 60 ]; (c) Non  uniform pressure and dri ving force in pump impe llers, also related 
to leakage effects [55, 56]. Other effects are reviewed in Ref [57] . Rather t han 
attempting here a gen eral cov erage of  this rath er rich  field, we will only explain in 
some detai l the labyrinth seal  and bladeti p effects,  which, aside from thei r 
importance in practical cases, ca n be seen  as prototypes of the relevant physics. 
 
(a) Lab yrinth Seal s. The existence of flow swirl at th e entrance to an offset labyrinth 
seal (and, i n modi fied form, to ot her seal s as wel l) gives ri se to a rotati on of t he 
pressure pa ttern prod uced by the offset, and hence prod uces cross -coupl ed forc es. 
Two princip al effects ca n be identified here [58]. One  of these can be described as 
follows: the  fluid in the gland of t he seal (a single-cavity labyrinth, for simplicity) 
circulates azimuthally in the varying area  created by the shaft offset (Fig. 3). 
 
 
 
Fig. 3: Kinematic quan tities associated with  a labyrinth seal. The s haft is spinning at 
an angular frequency , while simu ltaneously undergoin g a circu lar pre cession  of 
amplitude e and freque ncy . 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                       Lecture 29 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                 Page 7 of 1 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>References Cited  
 
48. F. Ferlit ia et al. Rotor Support for the STME Oxygen Turbopump . Paper AIAA 
92-3282. 2 8th Joint Pro pulsion Conference, July 1992. 
 
49. J.P. De n Hartog, Mecha nical Vibrat ion, McGraw-Hill book Company, 19 56. 
 
50. Childs,  Dara W.  Turbom achine Roto r Dynamics: Phenomena, Modeling and 
Analysis , Wiley Interscience, N .York, 1993 . 
 
51. J.M. Vance, Rotordyna mics of Turbomachinery , Wiley, New Yor k, 1988. 
 
52. M.C. Ek  Solution of the Subs ynchronous W hirl Proble m in the High-Pressure  
Hydrogen Turbomachi nery of  the Space Shuttle Mai n Engine .  J. of Spacecraft, 
Vol. 17, No. 3. 
 
53. G.R. Muelle r, Finite Elements Model s of the Space Shuttle Mai n Engine  NASA 
TM-78260 , Jan. 1980. 
 
54. F. Ehrich  The Role of Bearing S upport Sti ffness A nistropy In Suppression of 
Rotordyna mic Instabilities. ASME 12th Biennial Conf. on  Vibration and Noise. 
Montreal, Canada, Sept. 1989. 
 
55. Jery, B. Acosta, A. J., Brennen, C.E. and Caughey, T.K.  Hydrodynamic 
Impeller Stiffness, Damping and Inertia in the Rotordyna mics of Centrifugal 
Flow Pump s. NASA CP-2338, 1984, pp.137-16 0. 
 
56. Chamie, D.S., Acosta, A.J., Brenne n, C.E. a nd Caughey , T.K. Experimental 
Measure ments of Hydronami c Radial Force s Stiffness Matrices for a Centrifugal 
Pump Impeller, ASME JI. Of Fluids Engineer ing, Vol.107, N o. 3, 1985, pp 307-
315. 
 
57. F. Ehrich a nd D.W Childs,  Self-Excited Vibrat ions in High Performance  
Turbo machinery, Mech. Engineering, ay 1984. 
 
58. Knox T. Mill saps, The impact of Unsteady Swirling Flow in a Single-Gland 
Labyri nth Seal on Roto rdynmics Stability: Theory and  Experiment. Ph.D. 
Thesis, MI T, 1992. 
 
59. M. Martinez Sandues,  B. Jaroux,  S.J. Song and S.  Yoo Measurement  of 
Turbines Blade-Tip Rotor dynamic Excitation Forces J. of  Turbomachi nery, 117, 
3, July 199 5, pp. 384-393. 
 
60. S.J. Srig and M. Ma trinz-Sanchur, Rotordya namic Effects  due to Turbine-Tip 
Leakage : Part I, B lack-Scale Effects. Par t II, Radius Scal e Effects and 
Experimental Verif ication . J. of Turbomachinery, 119, 4, Oct 1997 , pp. 695 -
714. 
 
61. D.W. Childs,  Dynamic Analysis of Turbulent Annular Sela s Based on Hirs 
Lubricat ion Equa tion ASME J. of Lubrication Technology, V.105, No. 3, 1983, 
pp. 437 -445. 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                       Lecture 29 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                 Page 12 of 13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>to the  gland fluid as t hey mix, in a manner si milar to the o peration of an ejector 
pump.  This effect i s strongest at  point D (Fig. 3), where t he gap i s widest, a nd 
weakest at point B. Thus, a  positive pressure gradient P
 will exist at D, an d a 
negative one at B, agai n leading to  a pressure maximum at A a nd to a cross-force  
along the perpendicula r axis(). Since this effec t does not  depend on  fluid velocities 
relative to the whirling frame, it does not show whirl veloc ity dependence, a nd does 
not co ntribute to dampi ng()xxC. A simplified anal ysis, negl ecting tangential velocity 
variations, gi ves for t his effect 
 
                 
          ()=+ &amp;2
i2
2VVRFRhl h 1ge      (14) 
 
 
 
()2
2;
1 = =
+ iiPV V VV e RFR gh hl g P   (15) 
 
 
Because of  the import ance of inlet  swirl in promoting seal cross-force s, de-
swirling fins  can be use d ahea d of the seal,  if this is at  all pract ical. Experiment s [58] 
have validat ed the abo ve cross-f orce me chanisms,  while al so pointing out the 
importance of other second ary effects, particularly  for direct stiffness. 
 
Both force  components are greatly magnified in sm ooth seals with very sm all 
clearance [52, 61]. W hether the  added cross- coupling or t he added st iffness is m ore 
important w hen one of these is substituted for a labyrinth, must be directly assess ed 
throug h dynamic analysis for each specific case.  
 
 
(b) Turbine B lade-Tip Effects.   It wa s independe ntly po inted by Alford [62] and 
Thomas [63] that  the sensit ivity of blade-tip losses to blad e-tip gap in turbines 
should produce f orward-whirling cross f orces. The basic m echanism is simple: When 
the turbine rotor is offset from its center, the blades on t he side where t he tip gap is 
reduced will gain efficiency, and  hence pr oduce more tangential driving force  than 
average, and the  opposite wi ll happen on the side where g ap opens up. Integrating 
these forces around the periphery yie lds, in addition to the  desired torque , a side 
force in the forward- whirling direction (see Fig. 4). It is easy to transl ate this 
argum ent into an e xplicit equation for the cross -force. Let ()/=H   be the 
sensit ivity of blade ef ficiency to relative tip clea rance /H, where  is the clearance 
and H is the  blade height . This factor is of  the order of 1-5 , depending  on design and 
operating point. 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                       Lecture 29 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                 Page 9 of 1 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>One import ant quest ion which re mains experim entally unans wered is w hether 
or not the Alford/Tho mas forces show a significantly sensit ivity to whirl speed,  i.e., 
whether they provide xxC component  for the stiffness ma trix. The original  argument 
would predict  no such sensit ivity. A fairly obvious ex tension, ac counting for cha nge 
 to the basic blade speed cose Rcan be  shown to yield a m odified Alford fac tor 
  
1'=H
R      (18) 
 
where 2() Qm R
= is the turbi ne work coefficient, which is close t o 2 for impulse 
turbines.  Since 0.2 HR  and  (whirl to spin ratio) is , we see that 0.5
' 0.05  , which would not be si gnificant. O ther velocity-dependent effects ma y 
arise f orm time lags in t he azimuthal redi stribution of  flow approaching a whirling  
rotor; these  would also be of order HR, but no direct experime ntal evide nce exist s 
for their magnit ude. Ref [60] does provide a t heoretical model f or this effect however 
the Alford-Thomas forces can be very large, requiring da mping log decrements of the 
order of 0.1  in typical rocket turbo pumps. 
 
 
 
                                            
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                       Lecture 29 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                 Page 11 of 13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>or an exci tation thres hold exists at a n integer mul tiple of the 
excited frequency  [55]. However, t hus is not universally the case, a nd, in fact, no 
such simple ratio or thr eshold seems to exist for the  most i mportant mechani sms 
(seal or turbine blade-tip e ffects).  It is true,  however, t hat the rate of  energy 
input into the vibration increases w ith power level of the turbopu mp, and hence 
with its speed; thus, the machine damping may be s ufficient to  comp ensate for 
this effect at low rotation speeds, bu t, as speed in creases,  a threshold w ill 
appear,  beyon d which the operat ion is un stable. Table 3
 
The two typ es of vibration described can be ea sily distinguished in tes ts by 
plotting a series of vibration spectr a at increas ing rotational speed (a cascade 
diagram, Fig. 1). Here 
 
       
  
Fig. 1. A  cascade diagram showing  one mode only. Forced v ibrations related 
to imbalance are seen at =, with a resonance when cr=. Also shown 
is a su b-synchronous, self-excited vibration at cr= . 
 
 
 is the shaft speed,  is the angular frequ ency of t he vibration, and  is the 
critical or natural frequen cy (only one shown). As in dicated,  no self-excited 
vibration is visible until  reaches so me threshold, and th en the instability 
becomes more an d more promin ent. The amplit ude itself depen ds on con ditions 
when the spectrum is taken (variation rate of cr

 dwell time at the given condition, 
etc.), but the f requency information is still quite useful. 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                       Lecture 29 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                 Page 3 of 1 3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Turbopumps (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_26/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>26</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>where         
 
 
    
()2
11
2=
NPSP
R   ;    sin
1cos= +tZt
t0    ( 16) 
 
 
and  is the inducer leadin g edge blade an gle, which, at design  conditions, is close 
to and is typically . The data lies clo se to the line 1tan 0510 3=tZ. With small 
angle approximations for  andt, this can be sho wn to be eq uivalent to 32= , 
interm ediate between Stangel ands recom mendations [40] for LH and LOX. 
 
With the inducer diameter chosen f rom the above criteria,  the shaf t speed is 
limited [40] so as to keep the ind ucer tip speed below 17 0 m/sec (LOX) or 340 
m/sec (LH). Th is is done in  order to con trol cavit ation in the blade- tip leakage vort ex 
[40]. This speed limitation may conflict with the desi re to pl ace the (,  point on a  
favorabl e spot i n the efficiency maps. In that case, the N PSH mus t be raised,  either 
by parti al pressuri zation of the tanks, or, as in the SSME, by the use of separate  low-
pressure bo oster pumps.  These are only ro ugh guidelines, and , the precise allow able 
limits depend upo n detailed desi gn of t he induc er. Progress  in inducer design has 
been a paci ng item in allowing turb opump speed to increase, t hus reduci ng weight 
(as well as in creasin g life). )ssrd
 
 
References cited : 
 
40. M. L. Joe Stangel and. Turbopump s for L iquid Rockets Engines . Ninth Cliff 
Garrett Tur bomachinery A ward Le cture, A pril 7, 1992. SA E/SP-92/92 4. 
 
41. Turbopump  Systems for Liquid Rock et Engines , NASA S P-8107, A ug. 1974. 
 
42. Liquid Rocket Engine T urbines , NASA SP-8 110, Jan 1974. 
 
43. Liquid Rock et Engines Centri fugal Flow Turbo pumps, NASA SP-8 109, Dec. 
1973. 
 
44. E.M. Greitzer,  The Stability of Pumping Systems, ASME, Tran sactions, Jl. of 
Fluids Engineering 103 (1981), pp.193-242. 
 
45. J.L.Kerrebrock, Aircraft Engines a nd Gas T urbines , MIT pre ss. 1992  (Sec.5-
7). 
 
46. O.E. Balje,  Turbomach ines: A Gu ide to Design, Select ion and Theory, J. 
Wiley &amp; Sons, Ne w Yor k, 1981. 
 
47. L.B. S tripling,  Cavitation in Turbopumps, pt. 2, Trans. A SME, Series D, J. 
Of Basic Engineering (1962): 339 . 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 26 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 8 o f 8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>1
4
s 1
2D(gH)d
Q=        (9) 
 
 
()12
s 3
4Qn
gH=        (10) 
 
 
In the U. S. literature, D is ex pressed in feet, Q in gpm and   in rpm, and g is 
omitted. This procedure , of questionable practically, result  in relat ed paramet ers D s, 
Ns given By Ns= 2728  ns, Ds = 0.01 985d s. 
 
Notice that 
 
 
               
()ss 12Dnd
gH=        (11) 
 
 and hence, from  (7), 
 
               ss2nd=
       ( 12) 
 
 
or, in English unit s, ssND108.3= . Since for centrifugal pumps, we found &lt;1, 
we can see that their domain is a ( ) map is &gt;2 (or ). 
ssn,dssndssND108&gt;
 
            The con siderabl e empir ical eviden ce on  pump performan ce has been  distilled 
(Ref.46)  by constru cting ( ) maps o n which favorable reg ions are shown for 
various typ es of m achine. A very generalized example (take n from  Ref. 41)  is shown 
in Fig. 3, where lines of con stant peak efficiencyssn,d
 are shown for a  wide variety of 
pumps. These use a set of  clearance,  tolera nce, roug hness , etc. factors, an d are t o 
be taken  only as indicative, si nce actual  design may depart from  adopted values. We 
notice in Fig. 3 the line , denoted as t he limit for dynamic pu mps, in 
accordance to our disc ussion above. Radi al and axial pump designs nearly merge, 
although the axial t ype is in dicated for the highest specif ic speed,  which as Eq.  10 
shows , may be simply a reflection of l ow head rise, as for e xample, in the inducer100ssND
 
stage s featured commonly at the inlet of ce ntrifugal pumps for ca vitation 
suppression.  Table 1 gives the f eatures of  the high press ure SSME pumps, and the 
resulting ( ) points are in cluded in Fig 3,  where they are se en to lie roughly on 
the  = 0.8 line. ,s sND

 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 26 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 5 o f 8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>The p umps must be de signed so a s to avoid c avitation, which both, d egrades 
performance, and  causes damage to reusable  articles. Cavi tation risk exi sts at the 
pump in let, where th e liquid pressure is lowest , and it increases wit h both, the fluid 
velocity and the speed of the pump inducer blades meet ing the  fluid. The inducer 
diameter needs to be large enough to reduce the inlet fluid dynamic he ad 21
2mC to 
some fracti on of the excess i nlet pressure over saturati on P1-Psat, 1. This last  quantity 
is called the Net Positive Su ction Pressure (N PSP), and is usually given as a s uction 
head NPSH= NPS/()g. 
 
 
 Hydrogen Pump  Oxygen Pump 
 
P (N/m2) 1.38 107 (per stage) 3.30 107
H (m) 20,000 2,930 
Q (m3/sec) 0.96 0.229 (per side) 
 (rad/sec) 3674 3246 
D (m) 0.308 0.16 
ns (Ns) 0.386 (105 0) 0.703 (192 0) 
ds (Ds) 6.61 (0 .0131) 435 (0.086 6) 
 
Table 1. Characteristics  of the SSME high-pres sure fuel and oxidiz er pumps 
 
 
 
The ratio: 
                                      () ()
2
21 /2
2= =
m
mNPSP NPSP
C gC     (13)  
 
is called the Thoma parameter,  and empiri cal eviden ce [40,41] indicates that it 
shoul d be grater than 1 for LH , 2 for LO X and 3 for water and storable prope llants. 
The more fa vorable situation for hydrogen appears to be r elated to a greater vapor 
suppression ef fect due to evaporate chilling when bubbles start to  form. 
 
Several other parametric representations of cavitation dat a exist. Thus, Refs  
[40] a nd [41] use  a suction specific speed  Ss defined as in Eq (10), but with H 
replaced by the NPSH, and with correctio n for flow blockage by the hub. This 
parameter can be s hown to  be related to Thomas param eter  and to   
(R1/= tmcR
1= induce r radius) by 
 
3
42.981=
s
tS        (14) 
 
In English units, the numerica l factor is 8132. The data  on cavitations onset 
for a variety of liquids show tha t  remains approximately constant for each, as 
noted above. Independ ently, Ref. 47 shows cavitations results in the form 
 
()=tfZ        (15)               
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 26 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 7 o f 8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The q uantity r2
p
2V1 tanR
2 =   is sometimes called t he head co efficient. I n 
terms of , 
                        
                          ()2
2RHg=         ( 7) 
                
 
 is typically  between 0.2 an d 0.8. Values greater tha n unity could be obtained if 
the blades were designed to learn forward  (20&lt;), but the n P would increase with 
Q (thro ugh the effect of V r2). This p ositive slop e of the P vs. Q characteristic is 
known to produ ce instabilities in the pumping system [44]. These are generally 
dynamic in nature, and  depend to some exte nt on the characteri stics of the rest of 
the system (free volume, throttling effects, etc), but it is relat ively easy to 
understand their origin  from a qu asistatic argument: if the pump  temporarily deli vers 
more flow than can be disposed of in steady state by the do wnstream components , 
and if its c haracteristic has a po sitive slope ()P
Q
, the pump  pressure  rise will also 
be higher than  normal. The dow nstream pressu re will therefore tend to increase f or 
both reasons , and a ru naway situation ensues. In addit ion to this system in stability, 
there i s also a tende ncy for flow m aldistribution anal ogous  to rotati ng stall, since the 
flow is then unstable with respect  to mass inte rchange be tween parallel streamtubes 
[45]. 
 
Eq. (6) would predict  a linear dependence o f head on fl ow rate. In  reality varyi ng the 
flow at a  given speed will vary t he internal  flow angl es with respec t to bl ades, and 
will therefore result in variations of the slope HQ. Examples of this be havior are 
shown in Fig 2 (Re f. 41), where t he flow coeffi cient is defined as 
 
                                     
()2
2
2
2Q
R2Rb=
      (8) 
 
                                                      
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 26 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 3 o f 8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>The throttling range  is defined by the point of maximum head,  below  which operat ion 
is unstabl e. Similar (but stronger)  restrictions apply to axial desi gns, s uch as that 
used in the J-2 LH pump, and so these desi gns tend  to be limited to appl ications 
which requ ire very limited throttling. 
 
The pump is designed to specified head rise H or (P) and volu metric flow Q. 
These q uantities can be used to construct the non di mensional quanti ties call ed 
specif ic diameter and specif ic spee d: 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 26 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 4 o f 8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 26 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 6 o f 8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 26: Turbopumps 
 
  
Turb opump Components 
 
                   The mech anical components  of the pressuri zation cycl e (pumps a nd 
turbines) are next to be considered. An e xcellent recen t survey of this area is giv en 
in Ref.40. A  more comprehensive, but older survey is contained in a series of NASA 
SP report s [41-43]. Pumps an d turbines will first be discu ssed separately , and their 
integration will then be ex amined. 
 
  
(a) Pumps  
 
Almost all existing rockets have  centrifugal  turbopumps. These deliver  more 
P per st age than ax ial flow pumps, with only slightly less eff iciency. Only if 
multistaging becomes necessary is there a possible incentive to go to ax ial pu mps; 
this happe ns with LH
2 fuel, where, due to the low density, the P per stage is li mited 
by the attai nable rim speeds. 
   
In general , the desi gn attempts to maxi mize operati ng speed, si nce this 
reduces th e pump siz e, and hence the weight. Pump speed is lim ited by  several 
effects, most importan tly cavi tation at inlet. Others are ce ntrifugal str esses (either at 
the impell er or in  the driv ing turbine) , limiting periph eral speeds f or bearin g and 
seals, and a voidance of critical speeds. 
 
Head rise  is used common ly instead of pressure rise to express the 
performance of pum ps. We can define head  rise as the  height to which one could 
raise one Kg of fluid with the amo unt of ideal work per Kg done b y the pump: 
 
H =2
1P
s Pdph/gg=      (1) 
 
The rise is direct ly related to the pump work, even if the fluid has sign ificant 
compressibility: 
 
 
Work/mass = 
pgHh=     (2) 
 
                                        
and this is one of the advantag es of its use. Ob viously, if  = const.,  
 
PH ,g=          
pWork P
mass=     (3)  
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 26 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 1 o f 8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The head rise is directly to the peripheral spee d of the im peller disk. The fluid enters 
axially near they impel ler hub, with no angular momen tum; it leaves the impel ler 
with absol ute tangen tial speed R2  Vr2 tan 2, where 2 is the back-leaning blade 
angle at the rim Fig 1, and V r2 is the fluid radia l exit velocity, related to t he volume 
flow rate as   
 
Q = 2R2b2 Vr2       ( 4) 
 
 
The torque needed to drive the impeller  is the net ou tflow rate of an gular 
momentum , and the work rate is this, times . Thus, 
 
 
Power = ()2r2
2
2VmR 1 tanR2 i
     (5) 
 
 
and si nce we also have Power = 
pgHmi
, the head rise is  
 
 
                       ()2
2 r2
p
2R VH1 tgR=   2an     ( 6) 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 26 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                        Page 2 o f 8</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Basic Turbomachine Performance (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_25/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>25</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>The staged combustion cycle provid es the highest levels of  rocket 
performance, but at the cost of great ly increased complexit y. This is both, because of  
the many du cts and valves in volved,  and because of the very high pump exit 
pressures. A secondar y potential difficulty, which is shared by the expander cycle,  is 
that the turbines are un choked and t here is a possibi lity of low-frequency instability 
developing. 
 
Consider a simpl ified schematic (Fig.  5) of a fuel-rich cycle analogous to that 
of the SSME.  The injector pressure, P i, the turbine inlet temperature,  , and the 
overall O/F ratio,  r, are prescribed.  The heat in put and pressure drop i n the cooling 
circuit (Q cool, Pcool) are a lso assumed given. We wi sh to determine the required 
pressure rise PFP by the fuel pump, as we ll as the O/F in the pre-burne rs (rPB) and  
the fuel spli t SF between  them. The pressu re rise in  the oxidiz er pump is simply 
. tiT


OP i TK PP P =
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 25 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sa nchez              Page 7 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>turbine exh aust is ducted to t he main combustor injectors, together with the 
remain ing LOX (SSME) or kerosene (RD-170). The ch oice of fuel-rich preburners is 
precluded by carbon de posits on turb ine blades and othe r surfaces when 
hydrocarbon  fuel is in volved.  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 25 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sa nchez              Page 6 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 25: Basic T urbomac hine Performance  
 
Turb opump Pressu rization Systems 
 
1. Cycl es 
 
For higher performance, mechanical pumps must be used to feed the 
combustion chamber. I n turn, thes e pump s requ ire driv e pow er, which is alw ays 
provided by t urbines using excess thermal ener gy in the propellants (a lthough  
electr ical m otors have been considered for small rockets). The ma nner in which hot 
gas is prov ided t o drive the turbines serv es to distinguish amon g sev eral 
pressurization cycles , of which the most import ant are summarized in Fig. 1. (From 
Ref. 41). The most com mon of these are the bi-propellant gas generator (G.G.) 
cycle, the e xpander cycle and the staged combustion cycle. 
 
(a) The Gas Ge nerator Cycle  
 
The GG cycle was used in the F1 engine, and is also in  use in the Delta II, 
Atlas and Ti tan rockets. In this cycle, a sm all fraction of the pressu rized oxidizer and 
fuel are diverted to a medium-temperature burner (Gas Generator), which pro duces 
typically  very fuel-rich gas t o drive the turbine or turbines. These are designed with a 
large press ure ratio, and their exhaust is either dumped o verboard, o r injected at 
some poi nt into the mai n nozzle to provide some extra thrust. Nevertheless, this 
cycle is in herently somew hat lossy , in that the turbine gas is n ot fully utilized in the 
main combustor.  On the other ha nd, the power control is relat ively straightforward, 
and there is lit tle interaction of the feed system  with the rest of  the rocket. A ny 
propel lant combin ation can be used, all pow er levels are su itable, and any desired 
pressu re lev el can be obt ained alt hough the Isp loss increase with pressure (1.5 -4 sec 
per 100 atm). The me chanical power required to drive the pump s is 
 
 = +OP FPox FP
oP ox FP FP PPm m      (1) 
 
where  are the pressure  rise in the oxidizer pump (OP) and fuel pump  
(FP), respec tively which have efficiencies  OP FP PandP
OP FP,. Also ox F, are t he liquid den sities. 
If the gas generator mass flow rate is , the (si ngle) t urbine power is 
GGm

=' '
GGT TP Pm cTnTT      ( 2) 
 
in which T is the turbine isentropic efficiency (6 0-80%), '
TT is its thermodynamic 
expansion e fficiency  
()1
1
='
''TT ie n P/P
        ( 3) 
 
which depends o n pressure ratio  and GG gas  specify heat ratio, ie nP/P '. Also,  is 
the specif ic heat of this gas, and T ti  its temperat ure, which is cont rolled  through 
stoichiomet ry to values acceptable  by uncooled turbines (700-1100K). '
Pc
 
Ref. 41:  Turbopump System for Liquid Rocket Engines. NASA SP-8 107, Aug. 197 4. 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 25 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sa nchez              Page 1 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>(c) Staged C ombustion Cycle  
 
For rockets where high chamber pr essure as  well as hi gh efficiency is desired, 
the staged combustion cycle is the preferred choice. One could think  of this as a 
modif ied ex pander cycl e, in which a small amount of  oxidizer is added to the fuel 
after the co oling circuit, thus  increasing th e availab le enthalpy f or the turbine drive.  
 
As in the expander cycl e, all of  the propel lant is en tirely used in  the combu stion 
cham ber. U nlike the ex pander, t hrough, any oxidizer-fuel  combination can be use d. 
Two prominent examples of  this cycle ar e the Space Shuttle Main E ngine (SSME),  
and the Russian RD-17 0 booste r engine (Figs. 3 and  4 from Ref. 2). In the SSME, the 
pre-burners are in corporat ed into separat e fuel and oxidiz er turbopu mp assemblie s, 
and process most of the f uel (LH) with a small f raction of the oxidiz er (LOX), 
produ cing a ligh t vitiated hydroge n turbine drivin g gas.  In the RD-170,  the pre-
burners process all of  the oxidiz er (LOX) and a  fraction of the fuel (ke rosene) to 
produce a fuel-lean gas which drives the sing le central turbine. In bo th cases, the 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 25 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sa nchez              Page 5 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Equating  and  yields the required . Suppose now the turbine exhaust is 
expanded to the same exit pressure  as the m ain flow. The exhaust speed is the n PPTP
GGm
eP
 
()1
21 =  '
'
GG Pt.out e te cc T P/P
    (4) 
 
where 
 
(1='
t.out n TTT TT )      ( 5) 
 
 
This speed is gen erally lower than the main  flow exit speed,  
 
1
2 1
= =pc e c cc T ; (P/P)
    (6) 
 
where c p and  belong to the nozzle gas, and ,cPcT, are the chamber pressure and 
temperature. The relative Isp loss is : 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 25 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sa nchez              Page 2 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>The shaf t power balance f or the fuel turbopum p is 
 
()'1
'
1 1    =+     r
r
i FP
FP B ptinFT
FF P tiP PSr cTP    ( 15) 
 
where FT is the turbine eff iciency and 'ti= belongs to  the pre-bur ner gas. A 
similar ba lance can be written for the oxidiz er turbopum p, and, by division, we ca n 
solve f or the f uel split SF. 
 
1
01 =+ +   OP OPB FT F FP
F
OT FP OP OPBPPS r rP
   PB    (16) 
 
 
After rPB has been calculated from  (14), SF is given by (16), and then (15) can be 
used as a check o n the assumed FPP. In realit y, an outer iteration loop is  required 
by the fact that ' and cpti themselves depend sensitively upon t he preb urner 
stoichiomet ry, rPB. With the ap proximations cpH2  7.67 cal / mol / K , and 
10.63 cal / mol / K 
2pHoc
 
'7.67+0.37
5.68+0.37=PB
PBr
r         ( 17) 
 
and then  (for H2-O2), 
 
1'
'1=tiRcM
 ; M = 2 (1+rPB) g / m ol    ( 18) 
 
As an example, Fig. 3.8  shows som e results in which we have u sed  
 
0=refTK    0OTK FTK hh
 
and also 
 
=6, r   atm atm, ,=8str =2OTKP =1FTKP81.21x10J/Kg, =fh   =1100K,tiT =0.741FP  
=0.781,op  0.696,=OBP  0.790,=FT  0.729,=OT   
, 0.15 =coolPPc   PB c P=0.05P, 
5=7.4010J/kg,coolQ   ii c P=P-P=0.1P c
 
As sho wn in Fig. 6, the pressure rise in the fuel pump increases more steeply than 
the chamber pressure, just as  it did in the expander cycle. However,  very high 
pressures a re now a ttainable. The FPP for the  SSME is shown for reference. Notice 
how the pre-burner stoichiomet ry is essen tially fixed by Tti , and does not vary m uch 
over the pressure range.  
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 25 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sa nchez              Page 10 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>inlet pressu re , is related to t he fuel pump pressure rise nPFPP and the cooling 
circuit loss,  by coolP
 
= +FP ti cool TK PP P P      ( 9) 
 
while the oxidiz er pump has . The s haft power balance the n gives OP inj TK PP P = 
 
()1 1
11  +  + =  F
F T cool TK FT K
T
ox OP FPO/F
      (10) 
 
where 
 
                      ==  = =inj FP Fti
TK TK injcool cool injT T
ti injP cTP/P, P/P, ,andPP    (11) 
 
 
Assuming 01TK cool OP NF =., =0.2,= =0.7,O/F=5    and Fo x/=69/1140 =0.0605  , 
the rel ationshi p betwee n  and T, as given by (10) is sho wn plotted in F ig. 2. As  the 
figure shows, the turbine inlet pressure increases rapidly when  drops below abo ut 30 
(at which point 1
T=1.33). In fact, as  also shown in Fig. 2, the quantity  has a 
minimum value of  approximately 1 7.76 when 1
T= 2.68, below wh ich no solu tion 
exists.  The turbine inlet temperat ure tiT is 200K i n the RL-10 . Using also  
 and  = 14,600 J/Kg/K, we calculate from (11)  1390 / 
Pinj (atm) and so t he maximu m3
TF=0.7,=69kg/m PFC 
  is 1390/17.76 =78 atm . For reference, the RL-1 0 has 
 = 32 atm,  40 atm, which corresponds to injP
CPinjP = 35. Of course, as (11 ) indicates, 
higher  values could be achieved if  injPtiT could be inc reased further. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 25 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sa nchez              Page 4 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>The analysis is best  done iteratively. If PFP is temporari ly assu med know n, 
then the turbine inlet pressure i s  
 
ri TK FP cool PB PP P P P =+    ( 12) 
where  is the pressure drop in the pre-burn er (mainly associated  with injection). 
The requ ired rise in  the oxidiz er boost er pump is then PBP
 
OBP ti PB i PP P = +P      ( 13) 
 
The energy balance in one of  the pre-burners is written as  
 
 
()
001 ( ++ ++++=+  
f OP OBP FP PB
PB OTK FTK cool PB Pti ti ref
OP OBP F FP stPP Prrh h Q h rCTTr  ) (14) 
 
 
where  hOTK and hFTK are the e nthalpies of  oxidizer an d fuel in their tank s (this ignores 
the low pre ssure booster pumps)  rst  is the stoichiomet ric O/F ratio and hf the fuel 
heat value at the ref erence temperature Tref . The specif ic heat o f the fuel-rich burnt 
gas is c pti. Eq. (14) can be solved for rPB if FPP is assumed k nown. 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 25 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sa nchez              Page 8 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>1
 GG sp GG
spI c m
Icm
      ( 7) 
 
 
and ca n be calculated once the turbine exhaust pressure  (and hence the turbine 
pressu re ratio)  is select ed. A tradeof f is involved h ere: if  is not very low , too 
much mass must be diverted (large teP
teP
GGm
m
 in Eq. 7), where as if   is too low , the 
exhaus t provides almost no additional thrust (small teP
GGc
c in Eq. 7). An optimum can 
theref ore be f ound. 
 
As an example, consider the LOX-R P1 F-1 cycle, for which =1844 Kg/sec, 
 and 
 Also, . The GG 
is estimated to have  and , while the main  gas has 
. The cham ber pressur e is = 95 a tm, and at the exit,  
= 0.68 atm. Use of  the equations above yi elds, after some searching, an optimum 
turbine pressure ratio of 23, for which oxm
22 7 7
FOP FP ti m=777Kg/sec,P=1.0610N/m,P=1.2410N/m,T=1061K

OP FP T =0.746,=0.726,=0.605.  33
ox F =1145Kg/m,=810Kg/m  
'=1.35'
pc=2140 J/Kg/K
P =1.25,c=2080 J/Kg/K cPeP
sp
spI
I = -0.01 11. The actual F-1 engine had a 
turbine pressure ratio of 16.4. 
 
 
(b) The E xpander Cycle  
 
For en gines, utilizing hydrogen  (and possible methane) as fuel,  the gas 
generator can be elimi nated. Inste ad, the fuel  is simply route d from the exit manifold 
of the nozzle coolin g circuit to the turbine inlet. This is possible becau se hydrogen is 
supercritical at the p ump exit, and it simp ly expands smoothly into an ordinary gas 
as it picks up heat. T he resulting Expander Cycle is simple and e fficient (the fuel is 
fully utilized in the thrust chamber) . This cycle is used in the RL-10 engin e and in the 
start-up seq uence of the Japanese LE-5 engine (which then transitions to gas -
generatory operation). 
 
The prin ciple lim itation of this cycle is t he relat ivity small amou nt of heat 
availab le from regen erative cool ing, which limits applicab ility to chambe pressu res 
under appr oximately 7 0 atm. A  simple an alysis can  demon strate this point. The 
pump po wer is given b y Eq. (1) and the powe r derived from the fuel-driven turbi ne is 
 
1
1  =    F
Finj
TF TPFi
iPPm cTP


      ( 8) 
 
where , the injector pressure, is also the turbine exhaust pressure.  The turbine injP
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 25 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sa nchez              Page 3 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 25 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sa nchez              Page 11 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 25 
Prof. M. Martinez-Sa nchez              Page 9 of 11</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Liquid Cooling (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_9/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Stress es in Cooled N ozzle W alls 
 
 
Ribs carry weak in-
plane stress. 
 
Wall mu st carry  
the large ho op 
stress d ue to , 
. In addition, hot 
side will expand 
more, forcing back 
(cold) side to 
higher tensi on. So,  
use hi gh  steel 
for back (1) layer. 
Front (2) layer needs to be good th ermal con ductor; use Cu or W-C u alloy  (higher 
strengt h). Cu has higher expansi on coeffi cient gP
Pl
ul
Cu steel &gt; , which adds to the eff ect 
of higher T, an d ends up put ting this lay er in compression . This can be relieved by 
hot assembly, so  that the Cu is pre -stretched  when cold. 
Fig. 1
 
 
Plane strai n At any z, within one of  the m aterials. 
 
()()() 0z1T zE =+T      ( 1) 
 
where  can be interpreted as t he temperature at w hich the strai n  is defined to 
be zero, with zero stress. Si nce the  shape rem ains planar, 0T
constant =  (at least 
within the layer). 
 
Write (1) for both layers. We now assemble  them with a tight fit, but zero stress es, 
0atT, which from now on means the assem bly temperature . Upon heating or cooling,  
thermal st resses w ill arrive, even with no loadin g or T gradien ts. 
 
 
 =0 by definition at   
 assembly Both layers now have t he same (constan t)  
 
()()()1
11 1 0
1z1 TzE  + =T      ( 2) 
 
()()()2
22 2 0
2z1 TzE   + = T       ( 3) 
 
For metals,  varies little, so take 12==. 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 9 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 5 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>is the most thermally lo aded one, o ften the coolant flow is split, with one part 
entering at the nozzle exit and another prov iding extra cool fluid by e ntering just 
downstream of  the throat. 
 
A typical con struction for the coolin g channels is sh own in Fig. 2. 
 
 
 
The load- bearing part of the structure is mil led longitudinally with channels of 
varying dep th and width (to obtain varyin g liquid velocity), a nd a high thermal 
conductivity thin layer of a Copper alloy is then braz ed on th e inside. 
 
 
Design Considerat ions 
 
Two aspec ts need to  be verified in the design of the cooling s ystem: 
 
(a) The coolan t should have su fficient thermal capacit y to absorb t he heat load 
without exceedin g some crit ical temperature, which may be a chemical 
decomposit ion limit (thermal crack ing for hydrocarbon s) or the boilin g poin t 
(although , with care,  boiling can b e sometimes tol erated or expl oited for i ts 
strong heat absorption properties). 
 
Suppose  is the calcu lated t otal heat loss f rom th e gas. As seen in a 
previous lecture, this amounts  to 1-3% o f , more for the  smaller 
engines. S uppose al so the f uel only is used as  coolant, wi th a flow rat e . 
The LOSSQ
pcmcTi
Fmi
OF ratio is defined as F
ox F
FmmOF mm
m= =ii
ii
i, and so FmmO1F=
+i
i
. If 
the liquid f uel has a spe cific heat  , its temperature rise from inlet  to 
exit of the cool ing circuit  will be given by coolc T
 
F LOSS cool Qm c=i
T (1) 
 
F LOSS
pc cool
TOTQ mmcT cTO Q 1F= + i
i
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 9 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 2 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>()() 21 0 2c 12
12TT q
EE 1 h 1 = + l
lor        ( 10) 
 
 all of  this, q is taken as a giv en. It can be calcu lated from the given , , plus 
,  and , : 
  
 
In
hawTTl
ghl 2t2k
 
aw
2
g 2 hh klTTqt 11=
++l        ( 11) 
quations (7) and  (10) relate . We need one more equation 
orce balance 
2h 2c 1 ,,  E
 
 
F  
 
 
 
 
 
( )2Tz  is lin ear in  z, so will ()2z Since . For for ce calculations, then, we can  use the 
ean value m
 
2c 2h
22=   +       ( 12) 
The net balance then is   
 
11 2 g 22t2tPD2Pt +=+ll (13) 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 9 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 7 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>()22
22
c 2EI 4EIF
2==2l l 
 
where =3
21IH12t. 
 
Dividing by , 2 AHt=
  
()buckling buckling23
2 22 2
2
2 2
214E Htt 12E3 Ht = = 2l l2    ( 16) 
 
To proceed, st art by elimin ating 2c between (7 ) and (10 ): 
 
()() 21 0 12 h 2 2 2
12 2TT t qqEE1 k 1 h 1    = +  l
l 
 
 
()()() 22 1 0 22 2 2
2h 1
12ET EE t1qE1 hk 1 =+ ++  l
lT   (17) 
 
or, recalling (11), 
 
 
() ()() ()2
21 2 0 22 2 2
2h 1 aw
2 1
g2t1
ET T EE hkTTt 11 E1 1
hh k+  =+ + ++l l
l
l (18) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 9 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 9 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Prop ulsion  
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 9: Liquid Cooling 
 
 
Cooling of Liquid Propell ant Rockets  
 
We con sider on ly bi-propellant liquid rockets,  since monopropell ants tend to be small 
and operate  at lower te mperatures. In a bi -propellant rocket, both the  oxidizer and 
the fuel streams are in principle available for c ooling th e most expos ed parts of the 
chamber and n ozzle prior t o being injected. This is called  regenerative coolin g, 
because the heat loss from the gas  is recove red (regenera ted) into the liquid, so no 
heat escape s. This is no t to sa y no thermodyna mic loss is incurre d, though (heat is 
transferred from very hot gas to cool l iquid, which implies irreversibility and loss of  
work potential). 
 
Of the two streams,  the f uel is normally used for coolin g. This is f or two reason s:  
 
(a) Fuels tend to have higher speci fic heats, so mo re heat i s removed for a  given 
of the coolant, and T
 
(b)  Leakage fr om an oxi dizer stream i nto the normall y fuel-rich comb ustion gas 
can prod uce a local flame that can b e catastrop hic, whereas leakage from a 
fuel line into the same fuel-rich gas is in ert. In addit ion, exposin g hot met al 
to oxyge n or strong  oxidants always carries some risk of accelerated chemical 
attack,  or even ignition. Some exc eptions do exist where  oxidizers are used 
for cooling, though. 
 
A typical arran gemen t is as sh own below  (Figure 1) .  
 
 
 
 
The fuel at high press ure from the fuel pump  (FP) is sent through  a series of narrow 
passages ca rved into the nozzle and chamber walls, picks up the wall heat fl ux from 
the gas, and is delivere d even tually to the injector mani fold. Since the nozzle region 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 9 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 1 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>p LOSS
c
TOT coolc Q OT1QC F  = +       T      ( 2) 
 
which mu st be kept within limits. For ex ample,  say LOSS
TOTQ
Q=0.02 , p
coolc
c=1, 
O
F=4, =3000 K; we obtain cT T0.02153000 300K = = . This may or 
may not be acceptable; for a cr yogenic coolan t it would most likely be, but a 
hydrocarbo n fuel, exiting the p ump at 300 K will then leave the cooling circuit 
at 600K, pr obably too high for chemical stability. 
 
 
(b) The local  cooling rate at  the m ost exposed location (the throat) mus t be 
sufficient to avoid decomposit ion or boil ing even at the con tact poin t of the 
liquid with the wall. The thermal sit uation in a cut through the front wall of 
the cooling passages is as schematizes in Fig. 3. 
 
 
 
 
The  temperature is shown dashed beca use, as we  know it is not the 
actual gas temperature outside the gas boundary layer, but is the one driv ing 
heat. The liqu id bulkawT
 is at a temper ature Tl, which is below  that of th e wet ted 
wall ( ), bec ause heat has to be driven throug h according to wcT
 
 
        ( 3) (wc qh T T = l)l
 
 
where h is the liqu id-side film coef ficient, that can be  calculated, for instance, 
from Bartz formula using liquid properti es. The  samel
 heat flux is supplied 
from the gas thro ugh the gas-side  film coefficient: 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 9 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 3 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>The temperature  will be nearly constant (adiabat ic outer condition).  ()1Tz  ()2Tz  will 
 vary linearly with z, according to  
 2
2kdz =dTq         ( 4) 
We wri te (3) at  and subt
  
2 z0,zt == ract: 
()2c 2h
2w h wc
21T TE =      ( 5) 
nd integrate (4) to  
  
 
a
wh wc
2
2TT qkt=         ( 6) 
so tha t 
  
22 2
2c 2h
2Etq1k=       ( 7) 
Also (2) reads  
  
 
()1
10
11TET +l , which can be com bined wi th  
 =
()2c
2w c 0
21TE=+T  
 
 give () ()2c 1
2wc 1 2 10 to
121T T TEE=  l     (8) 
eat transf er from  wal
wc qh T= l
  
 
H l 2 to l iquid gives 
 
 
 )Tl        ( 9a) (
or  wcTTh=+l
lq         ( 9b) 
ubstitute into (8) 
  
S
() ()()2c 1
21 0 2
12q1TEE h=+ 
l
l T  
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 9 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 6 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>()ga w wh qh T T =        ( 4) 
 
and yet the same f lux must cross the wall by conduc tion: 
 
wh wc T Tqk=       ( 5) 
 
where k is the wall ther mal conduct ivity, and  its thickness. 
 
Re-wri ting (3)-(5) as aw wh
g
wh wc
wcqTTh
TTk
qTTh=


q = 

=
l
l 
 
and adding , we obtain  
 
 
aw
g11TThk h= ++l
lq; 
 
 
 aw
gT Tq11
hh k=++l
l       ( 6) 
 
 
which we ca n then use to calculate inte rmediate  temperatures from (3), (4), 
(5). Clearly, what we have done i s adding the  series t hermal impedances 
g1
h, k and 1
hl of the gas boundary layer, the metal, a nd the liquid.   
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 9 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 4 of 12</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ablative Cooling, Film Cooling (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>FF
FF F
FFmm RuA TPM==ii
       ( 2) 
 
and the total cross-section is kno wn: 
 
cFAA A+=         ( 3) 
 
We need some additional information to find . The two momentum equations are 
(neglect ing friction): Fu
 
 
 c
cc
c F
cc FF
F
FFdu dPu0dx dxdu duuudx dxdu dPu0dx dx+= 
= 

 +=

 
 
 
c FF
cc Fudu
udu=
         ( 4) 
 
 
Both,  F and c, have been evolving as drops evaporate and burn. We ma ke now 
the approxi mation of a ssuming their ratio  to re main const ant (equal to the fully-
burnt value). Then (4) integrates to  
 
 
 2
c F F
2
Fc cuu
u u=c
F= 
        ( 5) 
 
 
Substi tute into the ratio (2)/ (1) 
 
  FF c FF F F F
cc c c F cccuA A mm
uA Amm= =ii
ii 
  
 
or  F c F
cFcAm
Am=i
i
         ( 6) 
 
and also FF F
cc cu
u=
         ( 7) 
 
This last  ratio FF
ccu
u

 is cal led the film cool ing paramet er, : FM
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 10 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 8 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Film Cooling of Rockets 
 
 
 
 
 
For applicat ion of data on slot-injected films, we need to define the initial film 
thickness  s, velocity , density FuF, or a t least m ass flux FFu.  
 
 
 
 
Assume we know the flow rates  and , where  is the  core fl ow and  the 
film flow. We also k now the fully-burnt temperat ures and molecu lar weights 
( ). cmi
Fmi
cmi
Fmi
cF c T,T;M,MF
A 
The areas o ccupied at the fully burnt secti on are not known; let them be A, . 
From conti nuity, cF
 
cc
cc c
ccmm RuA TPM==ii
       ( 1) 
  PcP= is common  to both 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 10 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 7 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>which is what  we found before. The other terms are muc h smaller, except at very 
small t ime. 
 
 
For thermal protection of solid  rocket nozzles read sec. 14 .2 (pp. 550-563) of 
Sutto n-Biblarz, 7th ed., especially, pp. 556 -563. 
 
 
A key conce pt is ablative materials. They  conta in a C-based homogeneous matl. 
embedded in reinforcing fibres of s trong (anisotropi c) C. Best is C/C, strong 
expensive  fibre since no zzle can ge t to 3600  K, can be 2 D or 3D. Also g ood is C or 
Kelvin (Aramid)  fibres + phenolic plast ic resin s (for large noz zles) 
 
 
 
 
 
For the s huttle RSRM, the throat  insert (C  cloth p henolic) regresse s ~ 1 inch/120  sec, 
and the c har depth is ~ 0.5  inch/1 20 s.  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 10 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 6 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Prop ulsion  
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 10: Abl ative Cooling, Film Cooli ng 
 
 
Transient Heating of a Slab 
 
Typical problem: Uncooled throat  of a solid propel lant rocket  
 
 
 
Inner l ayer retards hea t flux to the heat sink. Heat sinks T gradually rises during 
firing (60-200 sec) . Peak T of heat sin k to remain  below  matl. limit. Back  T of heat 
sink to remain  below  weak ening poin t for structure. 
 
Prototype 1-D problem: 
 
 
 
 
Can be sol ved exactl y, or can do  transient 1- D numeri cal computati on. But it is 
useful  to look at basic issues first. 
 
Thermal  conduc tance o f   g B.L.=h
Thermal  conduc tance o f front layer 1
1k=  
Thermal  conduc tance o f layer i i
ik= (i= thickness, = thermal  conducti vity) ik
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 10 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 1 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>1
4F
F
FcxReMs=        ( 13) 
 
where x is the distance down stream of  the film in jection (here we assume this is 
from the burn-out  secti on), and  
 
FF
F
FusRe=         ( 14) 
 
and , from before ( FF Fcc uM u= )
 
From , there are sev eral semi- empirical corre lations for . A recommendati on from 
R &amp; H is  
 
c
F23
r
p 0.8
p1.9P
c
10.329c=

+       ( 15) 
 
(or 1= if this gives &gt;1) 
 
which is supported by air data of Seban. 
 
 
 
Exam ple  
 
Say FF F
F
cc cTM10 .8; 0.8 1.6M 1.61.265T2 M 0.5== ====
 
 
FF
cmm0.19m m= =ii
ii1 
(0.01) (0.0101) 
 
 
 
Say D=0.5 m  =tc ompl.comb xx 0.5m
 
 
  == = = =62
6
33
cc F
ccP=70 atm=7.0910N/m
7.0910 0.020T3200 K 5.33K = g/m; 8.53Kg/m8.3143200
M2 0g/mol; 1.2 
 
 
cM0.=2 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 10 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 10 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>This is comfortable. Suppose awT 3300K= , 0T300K= , and we fire for 120 sec: 
(60)  
 
 (60) 
()120
230
2T120 3300 3000 e
= =1520K May need 4 cm  (989)
 
 
which is still (OK) for Copper (melts at 1360 K, but no stress bearing, so can go  to 
~900. Also OK for steel on Carbon str member). 
 
 
 
NOTE :  
 
 
()22
2
5
20.021.1sec4 49.410= =, so, indeed, layer 2 a dapts quic kly to B.C.s   
 
uniform 52 2
22k 3609.410m/sc8900 430==  . 
 
 
A More Exa ct Solution  
 
Consi der  turned on at t=0. The B.L. has a film coefficient , and the first 
layer has , , so th at awTgh
11k ()g 1
geff1 1
g
1h kh
1hk=+. Layer 2 has  thickness , and has  
, 2
2k2, , . The back is in sulated. 22
 
Then one can prove that layer 2 has a tem perature di stribution 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 10 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 4 of 12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>(This exam ple shows o ne could ge t good film cooling with much less than 10 % flow 
in the film, maybe wit h only 2%) . 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 10 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 12 of 12</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Examples of Chemical Equilibrium (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 13: Exampl es of Chemic al Equilibri um  
 
 
13.1 Numerical Iterat ion Proced ure 
 
For the S huttle mai n engine, we take R = O/F  = 6, and P = 210  atm. To get s tarted, 
we negl ect , ,  and , so that Eqs. (12.2-3) and  (12.2-4 ) reduce to 
2OnOnHnOHn
 
+=
22HO H82n 2n3 
 
  
2HOn1=
 
which give , 1/3 and (since all ot her s are ta ken to  be zero , n = 4/3). 
2HOn1=
2Hn=in
 
The en thalpy before reacti on was  (assuming very cold reactants , i.e. ), 0
iT0 K=
() () =+
22H O41Hh O hO32=-15,632 J (for the 4
3 moles of , 2H1
2 mole of ). 2O
 
For the products  to have the same en thalpy, the temper ature mus t be very 
high. Using  the table in Ref. 12.1 (p p. 692- 693) we have the trial values tab ulated 
below: 
 
T(K) 3400 4000 4200 
 
2HOh  (J/mole) -92,973 -58,547 -46,924 
2HOh  (J/mole) 103,738 126,846 134,700 
22HO H1hh3+  -58.394 -16,265 -2,024 
 
 
Since we must obtain an enthalpy of -15,632 J, these values indicate a 
temperature very close to 4000  K. Linear  interpolation between 4000  and 4200  K 
gives 
 
  T = 4009 K 
 
We can  now use this temperat ure to calcu late the four equilibrium constants 
 through . These are given in Table 12 of Ref . 12.1. With some interpolation, we 
obtain: 1K4K
 
  () =1/2
1K0 .974atm  () =2K2 .61atm 
 
    () =1/2
3K0.589 atm () =4K2.286 atm 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 13 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 1 of 5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>At this poin t we can  obtain  our first nonzero estimate of th e minor species 
concentrati ons. From Eqs. (1 2.2-1 4) throug h (12.2-17 ), 
 
 
 == =2
2HO
OH 1 1/2
Hn n1 4/3n K 0.974 0.138p 200 n 1/3 
 
 
 
 == =2H
H2nn 4/3x1/3n K x2.610.076P2 00 
 
 
 
 () == =   2
2
222
2 HO 2
O3
Hn n1 4/3n K 0.589 0.021n p 1/3200 
 
 
 
 == =2O
O4nn 4/3x0.021n K x2.286 0.018P 200 
 
 
 
We are now at  the end of the f irst loop of our iteration procedure. We can 
next re-calc ulate  and  from  the atom conse rvation equations, i ncluding the 
new minor s we j ust computed. With the ne w complete set of s, we can re -
calculate the enthalpy at a fe w temperat ures and interpolate for a new set of s, 
etc. We will do one more cycle in some det ail to illustrate the nature of the typical  
results and the way they may tend to osci llate or diverge. Beyond t hat, a tab ulated 
summary of t he succee ding result s will suf fice. 2HOn
2Hn
inin
jK
 
 
Corrected , , n: From Eqs. (1 2.2-3 ) and (12.2 -4), 
2HOn
2Hn
 
  ++=  =
22HO H40.076 0.138n n 1.22632 
 
  = =
2HOn 12x0.021 0.018 0.138 0.802 
 
Hence    = =
2Hn1.2260.8020.424
 
and    =+ +++= n1.2260.1380.076 0.0210.0181.480
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 13 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 2 of 5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Correct ed temperat ure: 
 
Since t he part ial deco mposit ion of   and  into the minor species is an 
endot hermic process,  the ne w temperature will be lower.  Using t he tables of  
enthalpies and t he com puted m ole num bers we calculate 2HO2H
 
 
h(2800 K) = 0.8 02 x (-126,533) + 0.4 24 x 81,370 + 0.1 38 x 121 ,729 +   0.076 x 
269,993 + 0.021 x 90,144 + 0.01 8 x 301 ,587 = -22,338  J 
 
 
h(3000 K) = 0.8 02 x (-115,466) + 0.4 24 x 88,743 + 0.1 38 + 129,0 47 + 0.076 x 
274,148 + 0.021 x 98,098 + 0.01 8 x 305 ,771 = -8,769  J 
 
 
Since we sti ll want h = -15,632 J, linea r interpolation gives a tempera ture  
 
 ()200T2800 15,63222,3382899K8,769 22,338=+  + =+ 
 
It is clear t hat at this new, much lower temperat ure, there will be much less of  the 
minor species, since t he new eq uilibrium  const ants, (  through ) will b e small er. 
Since it  was t he presence of  these minor sp ecies that  forced a reduction from 4009 K 
to 2889 K, we wo uld next obta in a refined T a gain relativ ely high, and the  process is 
likely to overshoot  at each it eration step. This suggests  that we can a ccelerate 
convergenc e by adopti ng as  a new trial tem perature t he average of t he last two: 1K4K
 
  4009 2899T 3454 K2+==   
 
Corrected minor species:  The new equilibriu m consta nts (at 3480 K) are: 
 
   ()1/2
1K0.251atm = ()2K0.316atm =  
 
 ()1/2
3K0.184atm =   ()4K0.454atm =  
 
and, proceeding as before, 
 
   OHn 0.0250=Hn0.0297=   
2On 0.0079=    On0.00105=
 
Table 13. 1 summarizes t hese two iterations, and shows the next  few iterations as 
well, lead ing to the pra ctically converged va lues of  the last  line. The mole numbers 
are then converted to mole fracti ons b y simply dividing each by n (Table 13.2). 
Notice that the numbers of m ole given in Table 13.1 have  been converted to m ole/kg, 
by dividing the n numbers used so  far (which correspond t o 
+ =8x0.00108 1x0.016 0.018693 Kg of reactants) by thi s mass 0 .01869 Kg . 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 13 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 3 of 5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>TABLE 13 .3 Entropies at 3630 K 
 
Species Entropy at 1 atm 
KJ / (Kmole)K Partial Pressure 
atm Entropy at own 
pressure KJ  / 
(Kmol e)K 
2HO 293.905 142.8 252.66 
2H 210.070 52.9 177.08 
OH 261.771 7.4 245.13 
H 166.668 5.9 151.91 
2O 292.223 0.58 296.75 
O 213.715 0.48 219.82 
 
 
The total entropy in our control mass ( 4/3 moles of   plus 1/2 mole of , in the 
form of t he s listed in the last  line of Table 12.2. 1) is then 2H2O
iN
 
  == ii
iS sN17.050KJ/Kg/K
 
Ref. 12. 2 Computer Pr ogram  for C alculation of  Complex Chemical Equilibrium 
Compositions, Rocket Perform ance, Inci dent and Refl ected Shocks  and Chapm an  
Jongnet De ctorations, by S . Gord on, NASA A ccession No . M84 -10621, NASA  Lewis 
Research Center. 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 13 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 5 of 5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Non-Equilibrium Flows (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>required, cannot  be calcu lated as the local valu e of gRT , but must be found from 
the basic Eq. (14.2). Also, of co urse, the x i values are unde rstood to be unknown in 
principle, and are,  in fact  results of each  local equ ilibrium calcu lation. 
 
 
14.5 Equilibrium Flow Example ( Shuttle Main  Engine) 
  
For the same chamber conditions as in  Sec. 14 .3 and once  again assuming 
matched ex it condi tions thro ughout, the resul ts of a calculation using a simple 
computer program are as sho wn in Table 14. 2: 
 
 
Pe/P0 0.001 0.0005 0.0002 
Pe (atm) 0.21 0.105 0.042 
Te (K) 1216 1058 877 
()2HeX 0.250 0.250 0.250 
()2HOex  0.750 0.750 0.750 
()2Oex  0 0 0 
()0ex 0 0 0 
()0Hex  0 0 0 
()Hex 0 0 0 
Ug (m/sec) 4407 4511 4626 
Isp (sec) 449 460 472 
 
 
 
Ae / A* 69.7 118.5 239.4 
P* (atm) 120.7 120.7 120.7 
T* (K) 3422 3422 3422 
()2*
Hx  0.2502 0.2502 0.2502 
()2*
HOx  0.6968 0.6968 0.6968 
()2*
Ox  0.0015 0.0015 0.0015 
()*
0x 0.0010 0.0010 0.0010 
()*
0Hx  0.0282 0.0282 0.0282 
()*
Hx 0.0222 0.0222 0.0222 
 
 
TABLE  14.2 Equilibrium flow nozzle perf orman ce 
LOX-LH, O/F =  6, P0 = 210 atm, T 0 = 3640  K. 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                                    Le cture 1 4 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                                             Page 6 of 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>So,     2
tt tdd u d
uu==
t 
                       2 t
t
su dpu1
d P= =




    Mt = 1 
                                                                                 (both, e quil. and frozen) 
 
 
Froze n and Equil. Speed of So und 
 
 
2
sTds ac dT==


sRT 1dd+= 
  
 
 
                                  and  gPRT=
 
 
Froze n:         Rc                  gonst=dp d dT
pT=
 
 
 
TCgTR dP d
P=

dP
P  ()pRCgpdp dC
p+ =
 
          Cv 
 
 
()p 2
gg
sv sC dp PRT a TRT
d C==   = =
   
      
  
 
  ()T 
 
 
Equil. :  gRR  
M=
+ =
dp d d dT
pT 
 
 
PTC
+ =

 gTR dp d d
pdp
p   
 
 

=

vPdp d dCC
p 
 
                   
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                                    Le cture 1 4 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                                             Page 3 of 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>()
 = 
 
  sdp P dT1
dd
 
 
 
In equi l., during expans ion   (reco mbination)  
and  (expan sion) 
&lt; &gt;2 dP0,a
d 
  
where the o nly novelty is that  itself is variable , and must be taken to be the local   
. 
 
A general  calculation p rocedure can be as  follows: 
 
(1) Given P 0, T0, S0, all x is, R 
(2) Specify an exit pressure P 0 
(3) Calculate T0=T(P0, s0; xi)  
(4) Calculate he, e, ue=()0e2h h 
(5) Calculate the specific impulse. For a rocket, 
 
()
+ == =+eg a e g a
sp e
ee e eemu PPA PP FgI uuA um    (14.4) 
 
 
where P g is the external (ambien t) pressu re? All t he above is in depen dent 
of size. If a particular th rust F is d esired (or an 
spFmgI=i
), we must also 
find the required throat area A* : 
 
 (6) Loca te Px using one of the procedure (a)  or (b) above . 
 (7) Calculate () =**
MAXu u, i.e., f rom method (a) above. 
 (8) 
()
=

MAX* mA   ;  ()
=g MAX*
eeu A.u A 
 (9) Thrust coefficient = =F *
0Fo
PA 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                                    Le cture 1 4 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                                             Page 4 of 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 14: Non-Equi libriu m Flows 
 
 
Reacting N ozzle Flow  
                        
14.1 Introd uction  
 
As indicated i n the introductory  discussion of section 12.1, the actual 
expansion process in a rocket or ramjet no zzle is intermediate between the extre mes 
of frozen and equilibrium flow, with the latter produ cing higher perf orman ce due 
to recovery of some of the chemical energy  tied up in the decomposit ion of complex  
molecu lar species in  the chamber - a k ind of afterburning effect. 
 
The two limit s, frozen and equilibrium flow sh are an import ant propert y: 
both are isen tropic f lows ( if we ignore f riction or heat losses) . This is becau se, in the 
frozen case  no chemical cha nge during expa nsion), there are no rate processes at all 
occurring, the molecu les preserv ing their iden tity all the way, while in the equ ilibrium 
case, in which reactions  do oc cur, their rate is so high  (compared to the expansion 
rate) that conditions adjust continuously to main tain equilibrium at the local pre ssure 
and en thalpy level, with the res ult that the whole process can be regarded as 
reversib le (and hence isen tropic). For any more real istic intermediat e conditions, in 
which reactions may pr oceed at rates compar able to that of the expansion, these  
finite rate reacti ons produc e an irreversi bility, and a  consequent e ntropy increase. 
 
In this Sect ion we will discu ss in detail an example of  each , frozen and 
equilibrium expansion. We w ill use for this purpose t he resu lts of the equilibrium 
chamber calculations of Sec. 13.1 , relative to th e space Sh uttle Mai n Engine. 
 
 
14.2 Froze n Flow Calcul ation 
 
The simple i deal gas model w e have used throughout most of this cour se 
(consta nt molecular mass, co nstant specific heats) i s an example of a frozen  flow 
model,  since it is impl ied by t hese assumptions that no chemica l change t akes place.  
Thus all of our co nstant results belon g in this cat egory, and can be used as a first 
approx imation for nozzle flow calculat ions (using for instance the value of  and M 
computed for the combustor). However, even with no chem ical changes, the spec ific 
heats of the various mo lecules do change with temperature, generally  decreasing as 
temperature decreases in the  range enco untered in  nozzles. This mean s that 
() pv p p g CC CCR = =  is not  a constant, sinc e , the gas const ant, does not  vary 
due to the constanc y of the molecular mass. gR
 
For a more precise calc ulation, we make use o f the const ant-entropy 
condition for frozen flow. Suppose, for instance that the nozzle exit pressure  is 
specified. This pressure , together with the c hamber  entropy are  enough to de termine 
all other thermodynamic variables of  the f rozen gas at  the exit plane,  in part icular it s 
enthalpy h e per unit  mass.  Since the chamber enthalpy ho is already known, we can 
find the exit velocity by the steady-st ate energy equat ion: 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                                    Le cture 1 4 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                                             Page 1 of 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>14.3 Froze n Flow exam ple (Shuttle Main Engine) 
 
Using a simple compu ter program,  and starting from the chamber co nditions 
established in Sec 13. 1, the procedures ab ove lead to the results sho wn in Table 
14.1. We have assum ed matched  exit condi tions throughout (Pg = P e) 
 
 
Pe/P0 0.001 0.0005 0.0002 
Pe (atm) 0.21 0.105 0.042 
Te (K) 998 862 707 
ue (m/sec) 4227 4320 4421 
Isp (sec) 431 440 451 
Ae/A* 62.9 106.3 213.0 
P* (atm) 118.6 118.6 118.6 
T* (K) 3316 3316 3316 
 
TABLE 14.1 Frozen flow performance of  nozzle, 
from P0 = 210 atm, T0 = 3640 K, (LOX  LH 2, O/F = 6). 
 
 
For reference, the Shuttle no zzle has an area ra tio of *
eAA = 76.5, which 
would give a (matched ) froze n specific impulse of about 435 sec, according to Ta ble 
14.1. 
 
If we had simply used t he constant  approximat ion, using (from Se c. 
13.1)  =1.191 and  M = 13.48 g/mole, the exit velocity wo uld have be en simply: 

 

   =       1
e
e 0
0P 2RuT 11M P 
  
For the case of  Pe / P0  =0.0005, this would have given a n exit velocity = 4316  
m/sec, which is quite cl ose to the 4 320 m/sec shown in Table 14.1. Thus, in this 
case, cons tant  is a good model, but this may not be true in even higher 
temperature cases,  like in electric ally heated gases (arc-j et rockets). 
 
 
14.4 Equilibrium Flow Calcu lation 
 
Here we must impose at each pressure below P 0 the same equilibrium 
condi tions that were us ed in Sec. 1 3.1, with the difference tha t the entropy, not the 
enthalpy, is n ow prescribed.  The mole fractions ( .) are  now 
variable alo ng the expa nsion, a nd so are therefore the molecular mass,  the specif ic 
heat and 2HH OH x, x,x,etc
. The calculational  difficulty resides precise ly in the need to perform the se 
repeated equi librium calcul ations, but, once  again, computer programs are availa ble 
to ease the  burden. 
 
Otherwise,  the procedure is entirel y analogous to that out lined in Sec. 14. 2 
(steps (1) through  (9)). The one noteworthy  difference is that the speed of sound, if 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                                    Le cture 1 4 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                                             Page 5 of 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2
0e1hh u2=+e 
 
()e0u2 hh =e
H x,x
)        ( 14.1) 
 
 
The process  by which h is found  once P and S  are given depends o n the data 
available. Tables or graph s (Mollier charts) are t he simples t method, but these are 
unlikely to exist for the part icular composit ion of interest. More fundamen tally, one can 
repeat the steps at the end of Sec. 13.1, when S was calculated after the gas 
composit ion was converged u pon. In this case, the com position (i.e., x, , etc) 
is fixed throughout ("frozen"), and for each P,  we will try variou s temperat ures unt il S, 
the entropy, equals the chamber valu e. 2HH O
 
In addit ion to the exit conditions, it is usually of interest to calcu late the 
throat co nditions, si nce it is the t hroat area th at determ ines the m ass flow rate.  Two 
alternative procedu res can be followed for this: 
 
(a) Try a ra nge of pressures about 1/2  the chamb er pressure, calculate the 
corresponding (o u2  and densit y hh =  , and look for a ma ximum of u. 
This occu rs at the throat. 
 
(b) For the same P range, calculate the lo cal speed  of sound, find where it is 
equal to the local v elocity u. The local speed of  sound is giv en in general by  
 
()sPa=        ( 14.2) 
 
and for frozen flow this can  be sh own to have the familiar form 
 
 
g a R= T        ( 14.3) 
 
 
Conditional Throat : 1A  , u = ()c2h h 
u=

 
 
dA d du0
Au==
 at throat 
 
 
                      S = const. 
t
tc t c t tt21d
du dh d
22 uh h hh u= = =

 11
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                                    Le cture 1 4 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                                             Page 2 of 7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Impulsive and Low-Thrust Maneuvers in Space (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_35_36/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>35-36</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Miss distanc e or Impact Param eter  
 
(ae)sin( )(ae)sin  = =   21(ae)1
e= 
 
or 2Pe
e1=
2
2e1
e   
2P
e1=
 
 
 
Excess  hyperbolic velocity       ()()2e1
V2 Eap== = 
 
 
                      used in many bo oks, reports 2
3"C"v=
 
Orbit characterized by any pair of parameters, like 
(p, e) ,  , (v , (vp(v,) ,) ,), p(,v) , p(,) 
 
Exam ple : Given  (v  ,  -a = ,)2v    2
2 ve1a= = 
 
     then   2
11 2 1v 12sin 2cote12cote = = =  
 
 
Planet ary Spheres of  Influence  (SOI)  
 
Locus o f points for which the ratio of (the Suns disturbing  acceleration of the 
relative vehicle-planet m otion) to ( the planet-induced  vehicle acceleration) equals 
the ratio of (the planet-induce d acceleration of the relative vehicle-Sun motion) (the 
Sun-ind uced vehicle accelerat ion). 
 
 
This attrac ting ce nters, one vehicle 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                  Le cture 35-36 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                   Page 2 o f 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>while the Earths circular velocity is s
E
SEvR= . This is m ore than , i.e., the 
spacecraf t must leave the E arths vicinity traveling back wardsav
 in the heliocen tric 
frame. Later on it will overtake Earth as it accelerates in the transfe r free-fall 
trajectory. The magn itude of this backwards velocit y, which  is the hyperbol ic excess 
velocity  when viewed from Earth , is  
 
 
                       SV
,E E a E
SV SE2Rvv vv1RR
= = +
      ( 5) 
 
The si tuation for time near launch,  and when viewed in the E arth frame is as 
shown in the following sketch: 
 
 
 
 
                       
Conversati on of 
energy in the 
Earth s frame gives 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
2 2
,E PE E
PEv v
22 r =      ( 6) 
 
 
where  is the velocity after appl ication of the es cape fi ring at . Before this 
firing, the space craft was in orbit, at  PEPEr
CE
PEEvr= , and so we find 
 
2 E
PE ,E
PE2vvr=+       ( 7) 
 
and theref ore the single impulse needed to enter the ITO  is  
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                  Le cture 35-36 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                   Page 6 o f 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 35-36: I mpulsive and Low- Thru st Mane uvers  in Space  
 
 
See Lecture s 3-4 o f 16.522 (Space Propulsion) for coverag e of Low Thrust 
Maneu vers and Re-posi ting within an orbit . 
 
We add here materia l on Hyperbolic Orbits  and Interplanetary Transfer . 
 
 
Hyperbolic trajectories : 
 
r = p
1ecos+   e  &gt; 1 
 
Asymptotes  :  = -1  ecos cos = - 1
e  11cose
== 
 
               h P=    still valid  
 
 
 
 
Instead of semima jor 
axis a&gt;0  distance from 
perigee to center is (-a), 
and we still have 
 
                     
E02a=&gt;  
 
  
Also  
()()()22pa 1e ae1 == 
 
Similarly, distance |focus - 
center| is ( -a)e (it is ae in 
ellipse) 
 
 
Turning angle: 11112( ) 2cos 2 cose2 e
  == =    
 
112sine= 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                  Le cture 35-36 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                   Page 1 o f 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Exam ple: Hohmann transfer from Earth  to Ve nus. Assume no plane c hanges are 
involved (in reality the Elliptical plane of the planetary orbi ts doe s not coincide with 
the equat ion plane of eit her, but we ignore t his complicat ion). 
 
As a prelimi nary, notice that this t ype of (minimum v) maneuver requ ires a 
specific EarthVenu s configuration at launc h; this configur ation occurs  once every  t 
days, given by  
 
vE11t511 11
224.7365.3 TT= = =
 
84
  days    (1) 
 
 
The Earth head angle at launch (  in the sketch) is calcu lated by st ating that the 
time in the ITO (half the ellipses peri od ) i s the sam e as that taken by Venus 
between V o  and V i : 0d
 
 
 
()3232
SE SV SV
0
ssRR R 12
22+ =+ 
     
     ( 2) 
 
 
or 
 
32
SE SV
0
SVRR12R+=          
    
    (3)  
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Using R sv = 0.7223 a.u , this gives . 0
054.0=
 
In the heliocentri c part of the trajectory, the apohelion veloci ty (which the 
craft m ust have as it leaves Earth) is 
 
 
s SV
a
SE SE SV2RvRR R=+      ( 4) 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                  Le cture 35-36 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                   Page 5 o f 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>2
PE ,E E
1P E CE
PE Ervvv v 2 1r = = +    ( 8) 
 
 
The point within LEO where this firing must occur is given, as sho wn, by 2, where 
112sine= is the total hyperbolic t urning angle. Since ()P,E P,E 2
,E
Erre1 1 va =+ =+ we 
have all the elements to  calcu late this angle. 
 
After travelin g in the ITO,  the spacecraf t will approach  Venus with an 
overtaking excess velocity 
 
s SE
,p v
s,v SE SV2Rvv v 1RR R= =  +   ( 9) 
 
 
 
 
 
and, working no w in 
the Venus frame 
                   
   2 2
p.v .v v
vv v
22 r
=   (10) 
 
 
   v
c.v
vvr=     (11) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
So that the circular ization v is 
 
 
2
pv ,v v
2, v c,v
vvrvvv v 2 1r

 = = +    (12) 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                  Le cture 35-36 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                   Page 7 o f 7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Solid Propellants: Other Topics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_17_18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17-18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>This produces a curve of  vs. p, wi th pmp
APm
m
 as the r unning para meter (for a  fixed 
Dox, particle diamet er). 
 
Notice how Tf,AP and  depend on the combination p D APm
ox rather than  on the 
separate variab les. However, since  contai ns the fac tor p directly, the final 
burning ra te of  is of the form  APm
pm
 
 = p f(p D pm
ox)        ( 48) 
 
where f is some compl icated function. This is an  import ant scalin g law  (not poin ted 
out in Lengelle et als paper). To verify it, we can use the data reported in Fig. 31 of 
the paper. 
 
 
For Dox =5, we have m
P(cm) 10 30 100 300 
p(mm/sec) 7.8 21 61 92 
PDox (atm ) m 50 150 500 1500 
( )p/pmm/ /atm  sec  0.78 0.70 0.61 0.307 
 
 
For Dox =90, m
 
P(cm) 10 30 100 300 
p(mm/sec) 5 7.2 10.2 20.0 
PDox (atm ) m 900 2700 9000 27,000 
( )p/pmm/ /atm  sec  0.5 0.24 0.102 0.0667 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 14 of 15   10 100 1000
Pressure (atm)Burning R ate (mm/s)100
10
180% 90mm AP-CTPB80% 5mm AP-CTPB
Computed burning r ate
Fig.3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>pgf
gmc x
b c,b c,b AP
ffpp
AP
APQQmeQQmm
m 




==
1
1      ( 43) 
 
Also, the factor pgf
gmc x
e
+,AP
 can be  expressed, using (21) as 
 
 ()AP p AP pg f,AP
gAPmc x m/m m
g f,AP s,APm
ccT T
eQ  
  
=+
1       ( 44) 
 
 
Combining (42), (43) a nd (44) 
 
()() 11
1


      ++ = +   p
APm
mp gf ,AP s,APAP
H,AP D,AP g f,AP s,AP c,b
cpA
AP
APcT T mhh cT T QQmm
m

P      (45) 
 
 
Here we recall that Q c depends on Ts,AP (Eqs.  (18), (19) a nd (8)) 
 
 () ()cs ,AP s,AP Q. T .T cal + =  266 0328 835 115 0328 123 /g
P
P  (46) 
 
For the present purposes, it is su fficient to ass ume a val ue for T s,AP somewhat above 
835K; this could be refined la ter by matching  heat fluxes  at the liquid surface. We  
adopt for m ost of the following T s,AP=925K. 
 
Given T s,AP, we can  see that Eq. (45) uniquely relates to T f,AP to . The 
following calcu lational procedu re can  than be f ollowed: p A m/m
 
(a) Take a val ue of  (typically in the range 0.2-0.6) p A m/m
(b) Solve (45) for T f,AP (non-linear equ ation, requires some in ternal iteration) 
(c) Solve (41) for the gro up 
 
 
()g,f f E/ RT
g
ox
dg g,fc epDAA+
 +2
8      ( 47) 
and, hence,  for the product pDox. Given p Dox, This gives p. 
 
(d) Calculate  from Eq. (22). APm
(e) p
p AP
APmmm
m


=
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 13 of 15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The mass  flux (g/cm2/sec) bur nt is 
 
  =pppm
        ( 2) 
 
wherep is the mean  densit y 
 
 AP b
p
b AP
AP bm m
m m+=
+
  b AP
pA P1=+
b
       (3) 
 
 
where AP is the mass frac tion of AP, and b1AP= is that of the binder.                                         
 
 
Note: AP = 1.95 g/cm3, b = 0.91 g/cm2
 
 
The mass fluxes of the individual  consti tuents are, si milarly, 
 
 =APAP APm
  ;  =bbbm
    (4) 
 
 
From (1) a nd (2), 
 
 
  11== +b AP
AP b
pp
pp AP AP bbpm
  
 
 
and since ii i i
ii
piVM MM
VV VM/===   
 
 
  b AP
pA P1=+

 mmm
b       ( 5) 
 
 
 
For al uminum l oaded propell ants, we noted t hat 
the A particles are eje cted when the binder 
holding them burn s through. Looki ng at the 
simplified geometry below, i t can be seen t hat the 
mean bur ning speed p would be the  same if the 
binder were real ly filling in for the A. 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 3 of 15  AP
AP
AP
Al bb</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>We then ge t the appro ximate expression 
 
 bA AP
pA P b1 +=+A
 , 
 
identical to the Eq. (1), even with A particles. Eq. (5) also f ollows, with AP 1 in 
place of b. The only difference is that the mean density p in =pppm
 is modi fied 
by the A 
 
  1
=+ + A b AP A
pA P b AI
  
 
 
Separate Burning o f AP
 
Heat penetrates into the recedin g AP particle to a small de pth only. This can  be seen  
from the heat bal ance written in the receding fram e: 
 
 
 
 
 
=APAP AP APdT d dTcdxdx dx  0  Define  =dc
 (heat diff., cm2/sec)  
 
  
()()0
AP AP AP0 AP AP 0dT T dTTd Td TTdx dx;= =    
AP AP
AP APdx xd 0
0
s0TTTT ce eTT/
=  =
 
 
Note: pdc msc calgK321.2x10 /,0.31 // . 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 4 of 15  TsSurface 
fixed
AP movinguAP
T = Tox</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>where x f is the locat ion of the main  flame, at which the energy of  combustion 
fQ cal 700 /  g is released (q=0 above  it,  below  it): pf qm Q
=
 
()
q

 
=pgf
gmc xx
pfmQ e       ( 25) 
 
 
At x=0, on the binder surf ace, the heat flux q(0) is used to pyrol yze the binder at the 
rate  (p.u. area), a nd if Q bm
c,b is the required heat (cal/g), we obtai n q(0) = , 
or bcbmQ,
 
,
 
=pgf
gmc x
fbp
cbQmm eQ       ( 26) 
 
 
The pyrolisa tion heat Qc,b is composed of that required to heat the  binder form  T0 to 
Ts,b, plus the heat of  decomposition Qs=360 cal/g: 
 
  ( () cb b sb 0 Qc T T,, 360 = +bcc alg 0.39 //k  )    ( 27) 
 
 
For T s,b=1100K, Q c,b=675 cal/g. 
 
 
Eq. (25) is also use ful to estimate the rate of arrival of he at from  the main flame at 
the location of  the AP f lame (x=x f,AP): 
 
() pgf fAP
gcx x
pfAP f qQ e,
,
=mm
       ( 28) 
 
 
and, from th is, the AP flame t emperature, using a modif ication of Eq. (12): 
 
     ( 29) ( ) APHAP DAP g fAP sAP fAP mh h cT T q,, , ,
++ =,
K, 
or  
 
        ( 29b) ( )ad
APg f,AP f,AP f,AP mc T T q
=
 
where  is the value of Tad
f,APT f,AP with no qf,AP present ( as we  found). 1205ad
f,APT
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 9 of 15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Note: We m ust have ) cDhh+=sh
 
We can combine these values to obtain the Adiabatic Fla me Temperature  of the 
AP fl ame:  ad
fAPT,
 
 D,APh  
 
  ( )()ad
gf APsAP cT,, 0.7 0.3 T 0 +++ =H,AP D,AP s,AP C,APh h h h
algK 0.3// =
1205+   (12) 
 
 
which, using for the gas a specif ic heat 
 
  cc  g
 
 gives T=ad
fAP K,         ( 13) 
 
 
Rates and  AP flame structure.  The rate of pyrolization is found experimentally to 
depend on the sur face temperature acco rding to an Arrhe nius-type expression 
 
         ( 14) ,/
,=sAP s E RT
APSAPAem
 
with = 20 Kcal/mol = 96000  g/cmSAPE, SAPA,2/sec 
 
The reaction rate for the premixed AP f lame obey s a simila r law, except that, bein g 
primar ily a bimo lecular react ion, its rate is proport ional to p2: 
 
 , ,/ 2
,=gAP fAP ER T
gAP pA e
       ( 15) 
 
with p in atm,   in g/cm3/sec, a nd with 
 
A15Kcal/mol; =g,PE
gAPAc msec32
,650g/ // = atm 
 
If the velocity g of the gas norm al to the surface were known, Eq. (15) would allow 
calculation of the flame standoff distance, f,APx
. The time to b urn the gas is 
/=g

ch
 , and then 
 
 
,
2
,/+ 
== =gAP
gE
RT gg
AP gch gg
gAPe
pAf,x     (16) 
 
(and noti ce ) 
= APgg m
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 6 of 15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>g
g g
gg gDd Dccg  =        ( 32) 
 
which can be su bstituted into (31): 
 
 pg
f
dgmcxA
2
8OXD        ( 32) 
 
The final gas temperature (af ter the ma in flame) can be estimated now from  
 
 f
APf,AP bs,b f
gQTTc++ =T       ( 34) 
 
Using AP = 0.8, b = 0.2,  = 1205  K,  = 1100  K,  = 0.3 cal/g/K,  ad
f,APTs,bTgc
Qf  = 700  cal/g. We calculate  = 3250 K. fT
 
Actual ly, Eq.(33) is appropriate only w hen the diffusion time (distance) is much more 
than the reacti on time (distance),  as at high P (short  reaction times), and/or l arge 
AP particle diameters (long diffusio n times). In the op posite limit, xf is real ly dictated 
by the chemical reaction ti me (distance ); similar to Eq.  (16), this distance can be 
written as 
 
 g,f
fE
p RT
f,r
g,fmx
pA
+
=2e        ( 35) 
 
 
The values of Ag,f and E g,f are not gi ven b y Langell et al. This is especial ly 
regrettable for Eg,f which is very sen sitive. We here take tentati vely  
Ag,f = 650g/cm3/sec/at m2, as for AP, and determining E g,f by matc hing approximately 
one of  the small-diamet er data points quoted in t he paper.  This leads to 
 
         ( 36) 294g,fE. Kcal/mol
 
For the general case, then,  we take xf to be the sum of the reaction and di ffusion 
distances: 
 
 g,f
fE
g RT
pfo x
dg g,fcxm D eA pA + 
= +
2
21
8      ( 37) 
 
Solution Procedure.  Given 0o x A P,T,D,P, we want to cal culate , as well as several 
of the intermediate variables. The equation s are f airly complex , so some it eration 
must be de vised. First, from the averaging law (Eq. (5)) with pm
bA P  =1 , 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 11 of 15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Plotting no w bot h curves as (p/p) vs. (pDox), they do coincide : 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 15 of 15  1
0.5
0.2
0.1
100200 5001000 2000 5000 10,000Dox = 5mmDox = 90mm
pDoxup/P(mm/sec/atm)
(atm x mm)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>g,
2
,
= AAP
f,APE
AP RT g
gAPAPgmen
pAmc 
 
 
or  ()AP
gAP f,ADE
g gf AP sAP RT
AP
gcA cT T
mp e ncQg,
, , ,1   
  = +
  A
    ( 22) 
 
 
So, for A P alone , where   is kn own, and TfAPT,1205 K s,AP can be esti mated (no t too 
much highe r than 835 K), the  regression  rate i s proporti onal to press ure ( ). APn 1
 
Pyrolysis of Inert Binder . A similar form ulation can be used for the calculation of t he 
heating rate  due to the main flame, which serv es to pyrol yze the  surface of t he 
binder (and also to elevate th e temperature of  the AP f lame). 
 
 
 
The paper by Lengell et al. 
Simplif ies the model by 
treati ng for this purpos e the 
flow of gas  as 1-D  (even 
though it really is 2-D or 3-
D due to the heterogen eity 
of the surf ace. It also 
assigns a uniform mass flux  
mp above both, AP and 
binder. This is qu estionable,  
but well press on. 
 
 
 
 
Similar to Eq. (17 ), we have no w 
 
  pggdT d dTmc 0dxdx dx=  
 
 
 
and, defining gdTqdx=  the m agnitude of t he (surface- directed) conduc tion he at flux, 
 
pg
gmcdqq0dx
=
f       ( 23) 
 
We in tegrate the con dition       ( 24) () pfmQ qx
=
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 8 of 15  AP BinderXF,  AP
Ts,bTs, APTF,APWf, APWf Tf
Xf</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 17-18: Soli d Propell ants: Other T opics 
 
 
Combu stion of Solid Propell ants 
 
For a gener al discussion, read S utton, Chapter 13. A detailed model of combustion of 
composite propellants is presented next. 
 
Combu stion of Composite Pr opellant  
(Ref: G uy Lengell, Jean-Robert Duterque,  Jean-Cl aude Godon, Jea n-Fran cois 
Trubert, ONERA, Solid P ropellan t Steady Combustion  Phy sical Aspect s. In 
AGARD-LS -180-Comb ustion of Solid Pr oplellants,1991 (TL507.N867, no. 180)) 
 
 
Composi te propell ants are heterogenous mi xtures of o xidizer grai ns and 
powdered aluminum fuel, both  embedded in a  rubber-like binder, which is also a  fuel. 
The most common oxidizer by far is Ammoni um Perchl orate (AP ), (CO4NH4), a 
crystalline substance with  = 1.95  g/cm3, cp = 0.3 1 cal/g/K, thermal  diffusivity = 
cm()3 62.5x104.55x10 =pd0TC2/sec, and an estimated m.p o f 835K. AP is ground  
to sizes from a few to around 100 m. The f iner grades are dangerous, so grinding is 
done just prior to fabri cation. AP has M = 116.5 g/mole and 55% by mass is oxygen. 
 
The al uminum is also ground to similar sizes at t he last minute. Al  is a very  
exothermic f uel, producing A2O3 which is liquid at the flame temperature ( 3500K), 
and co ndenses later to a solid. 
 
The binder is often polybutadiene (s ynthetic rubber), eithe r Carboxyl 
Termin ated (CTPB) or Hydroxyl Termin ated (HTPB). The composit ion of CTPB is 
C7H11.24O0.2 , with thermal con ductivity 4 /3.6x10()()=calsec
cmKp , 30.97/ = gcmp
, 
 0.39// =pcc algK
 
Best performance is obtained with very high p ercentage  of AP, altho ugh 
mech anical properties r equire a mi nimum of binder, a nd AP concentration ranges 
from  70% by mass when there is A (16%), the balance being binder (14%), to 
about 80 %-85%, with no A (as in smoke-less composit ions), the balan ce then 
being all bin der. 
 
Overview of  Combustion Mechanism   The burning of AP-binder propellants (no  A) is 
a complex series of  phenomena, and the  detailed geometry of  the grains does matter 
(size, particularly). At P  20 atm, AP itself can deflagrate exothermical ly, and it 
decomposes part ly in a thin liquid layer on the surface of a grain , partly in an AP 
flame a few above it. The heat of decomposition raises T to m 1205K b y itself; 
heat from the outer flame (more below) can raise the AP flame temperature well 
above this, however. 
 
Around the AP grai ns, the heat  from the main flame decomposes the  binder, 
which gener ates a m ixture of s hort-chain hydrocarbons, while absorbing abo ut 360 
cal/g, plus the energy to heat  it to the surf ace temperature Ts 1000K-1100 K. 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 1 of 15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>bAP
pp
AP
APm
mm
m


=
1
1        ( 38) 
 
But b
pm
m
 is also calcu lable from Eq. (26); this involves x f, which is given by  Eq. (37): 
 
 () p g,f s gg
p ox
gg g g,fE/ QT mc c
mDA pA bf
c,bpQ meQm
 +  +
=2
2exp
8       ( 39) 
 
Equate (38) and (39) and solve for  : pm
 
 
()pA PcA P
g
c,b AP
p
g,f f g
go x
dg g,fQ m/mnQ
m
E/ RT ccDA pA


 =
 
 +
2
21
1
exp
8A
     ( 40) 
 
This is similar to t he expressi on Eq . (22) for . In fact, the ratio of both  equati ons 
provides a relat ionship bet ween APm
p
APm
m
, and Tf,AP with Dox and p as parameters: 
 
 
() ()g,AP f,APpA PfA P
E/ RTc,b APp
g,AP g f,AP s,AP AP g,f f g
ox
cdg g,fQm /mnQme
A cT T E/ RT c mn pDQ AA




 = 
  ++ +221
11
exp1
8A
A       (41) 
 
The AP flame temperature T f,AP depends, i n turn, on p
APm
m
, as can be seen  by 
combi ning Eqs.  (28) and (29): 
 
 
 ()() pgf fAP
gmc xx
AP pHAP DAP g fAP sAP f mh h cT T mQe

  
  ++ = ,
,, , ,    (42) 
 
Here, we no tice that the factor pgf
gmc x
e

 is 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 12 of 15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Estimating the Mai n Flame Distanc e. Let Dox be the diameter of  the o xidizer particle. 
The surface of  the part icle evolves oxidizing gas (after AP flame), while the binder 
around i t generates f uel gas. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
These inter-diffuse to form a 
diffusion-flame, similar to tha t 
from a Bunsen burner (but inside-
out). The ra dial d istance covered 
by a s ubstance diffusing with a 
diffusivity D, in a time t, is of the 
order of Dt2. We say the 
flames end is at the point when 
this equal s Dox/2 (times som e 
factor of  order 1, to  account  for 
real geomet ry): 
 
 ()/ ox
ddDAD tA  12212 
 
 
 
 
 
Equating the time t to g
fg f
px/ x
m=  (notice we again use the overall mass flux  
here), pm
 
  / oxpdg fDAD x/m
1222 
 
or 
 
  ()pOX
f
dgmDx
AD
=2
8       ( 31) 
 
 
The diffusivity D is inversely proportional to  the gas density, so that gD is 
independen t of P at a given T (a nd weakl y dependent on T). Thus, (31) gives a main  
flame distance which is  independen t of press ure, and scales with the square  of AP 
particle di ameter. 
 
 
 
To a good a pproxi mation, the mass diffusivity D is equal to the heat diffusivity: 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 10 of 15  Xf
Doxfuel
gasoxidizer
    gas
AP</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>A separate expression for  can be obtained from the fact that the AP flame has to 
supply to  the vaporizing surface  the required  heat of reaction, so  if the flame moves  
too far, the reaction is too slow, and vice  versa . The net (convecti on + cond uction) 
heat f lux in the gas between  surface and flame is consta nt (no heat e volves ther e) fx
 
APggdT d dtmc 0dxdx dx=  (ggcc algKc alsec40.3//, 1.9x10 ///=  cmK) (17) 
 
with the boundary  conditions T=T S,AP at x=0  and 
 
 
( AP APgc HA
x0dTmQ m h Qdx,
=== + ) P S  (18) 
 
 
Here Q s is the net heat required to take  the AP from  liquid at T s to gas eous products 
(before the AP flame ) 
 
  
 Qs = 0.3  x 493 + 0.7(-375) = -11 5 cal/g     ( 19) 
 
 
Integrating (17) with (1 8), 
 
 
=  AP AP APgg gS,APdTmc T mcT mQdx
c 
 
 ()AP AP
SAP c
ggdT m mTT Qdx,
 = 
 
and imposing T= TS, AP at x = 0 again, c
gQcc=, so 
 
 APg
gmc
x
c
S,AP
gQT-T ec1
=
       ( 20) 
 
 
The AP flame is at x = x f, AP, where T reaches T fAP (adiabatic Tf for AP al one, but 
maybe higher if  there is heat supply  from  the main flame). Solving for xf,AP then, 
 
()gf AP sAP g
f,AP
cAPgcT T
xnQmc, ,1+ 
 =
A     ( 21) 
 
 
This must be the same as (16) . Equating them, 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 7 of 15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>This shows an exponential tempera ture decay in to the solid,  with a 
characteristic thermal thickness *
APdx=. Assuming 1/=cms,   
, this gives 321.210 /APd cmsec31.210 12= =*x cm m. 
 
 
The top f ew microns of  the AP are molten whe n its temperature exceeds 
 (which may n ot happen if  the pressu re is so low , under 20atm , that the 
flame-surface dist ance is too large t o provide su fficient heating to it. Note this rate is APT 835 K 
 
 
()() ()*/= = = sA P AP s 0 APAPAP s
odTqx TTdx 0 cTT, so 
 
 
()(835298 =s AP MINqc  )  typically . 
 
 
In this molt en layer, abou t 70% of  the AP undergoes complet e decomposit ion 
to final (onydizing) gase ous prod ucts, accordi ng to 
 
 
NH4CO4  0.285 N  2 + 0.12 N2O+ 0.2 3NO + 1.62 H2O + 0.76HC + 0.12C2 + 1.015O2  
(7) 
 
 
whereas the remain ing 30% su blimat es as a mixture of ammonia, NH 3, and 
perch loric a cid, HCO4; this mixture then completes the decom position to the final 
products  of (7) in a premi xed (AP) flame about 1m
 from the surf ace. 
 
 
Let us look at the energetics of  these ef fects: 
 
(a) Enthalpy pe r gram to b ring AP to its surface (molten) tem perature ( including 
some intermediate phase transi tions): 
 
(sAPT, 266 0.328 835 = + H,APh
) (cal/g)     (8) 
   
(b) Heat of the sublimat ion into NH3 + HCO4 
 
476to510 =s,APh
 cal/(g/sublimed) (493 avera ge)   (9) 
  
(c) Heat of combustion of NH3 with HCO4 
 
850to885 = C,APh
 cal/(g.reacted) (heat releas ed)  (10) 
 
(d) Heat releas ed per gram of A P direct ly degraded in  the liquid phase: 
 
calg 375/ =D,APh
        ( 11) 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 5 of 15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The O 2-rich gas generated in the AP flame co-flows ou twards with the binder 
decomposition produ cts, with interdiffusion along the  way. This is a diffusion flame, 
and the fina l combustion ta kes place in it, raising T to abo ut 3540 K. 
 
 
When there is Aluminum, the A Particles 
are ejected when the binder holding them 
recedes; they the n burn at several 
hundred m from it; duri ng this burning 
they agglomerate to several tens of  
m(they are liquid, m.p =930K, but 
remain encased in A2O3 until this shell 
breaks at 2 300K, then the A spews  
1m microparticles which b urn quickly) 
 
 
 
 
 
From the surf ace regression point o f view, A burns instantly, as its particles are 
ejected. 
 
 
Overall  Burn Rate from Burn  Rates  of Constituents
 
Let p be the mean surfa ce regression speed (cm/sec), a nd AP, b the 
correspon ding rates for the AP and the binder individually and in isolat ion. Although 
the geometry  is more complex , we can idealiz e the propellan t as a lay ered medi um, 
with alternative thicknesses AP, b. The time to bur n through both AP and b is  
 
 
  APb b AP
AP b
pA P bt+== +=+ tt 
  
 
 
Calling ,1 == =++b AP
AP b AP
AP b AP b    the volume fracti ons of the consti tuents  
 
  1 =+b AP
pA P b         ( 1) 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 17-18 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 2 of 15   AP
solidliquidAP flame
(1200-1600 k)
binderDiffusion flame
(Main f lame ~
3450 k)
 
 
 t = 0 t = 2x10-4s t = 4x10-4s t = 6x10-4s t = 8x10-4s 10-3sec</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Solid Propellants: Design Goals and Constraints (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 16: Soli d Propell ants: Design G oals and Cons traints 
 
Solid Propellant s 
 
Read Suttons , Chapter  12 
 
Doubl e Base  (DB)  Nitrocell ulose + Ni troglycerine +  Additives (for  opaci ty, plasticity, 
). Both NC and NG are explosives, dangerous sometimes  
 
JPN NC 51.5%, NG 43%, Di ethyl phthalate 3.2% , Ethyl centralite 1%, H2SO4 1.2% + 
carbon bl ack + can delilla wax 
 
Composit e Modified Double base (C MBD)  DB + Amm onium perchl orate (AP)  or 
Aluminium (Al) 
 
Composi te (C)  AP (som etimes A Ni tr) + Synthetic Rubber binder (fuel) + Al. Safe r 
than DB 
 
Other Comp osite contai n nitrami ne explosive (RDX, H MX), replacing some AP 
 
 
Type Isp (s) at 
1000/14.7 psi     Tc (K) p 
(g/cm3) 
 Al % r (cm/s) 
@1000 psi  Fabricat ion 
DB 220-230 2530 1.60 0 1.14 0.3 Extruded 
DB-AP-Al 260-265 3866 1.79 20-21 1.98 0.4 Extruded 
CTPB/AP/Al  260-265 3370-3490  1.76 15-17 1.14 0.4 Cast 
HTPB/AP/Al 260-265 3370-3490  1.85 4-17 1.02 0.40 Cast 
 
 
The addi tion of Aluminum i s not necessari ly benefi cial, as the following exampl e 
shows : 
 
Problem 3. Adding Aluminum to t he formul ation of a solid rocket pro pellant increases 
the gas  temperature, b ut incurs performance p enalties related to the solid parti cles 
that are generated. 
 
Consi der a simple model  for the ef fect of  adding a mas s fraction x Al of Aluminium, of 
the form  
 
oc
cT1rxT=+  ;  x= 1.85       ( 1) Alx
 
 
where r  1.41 is a separately calculated coefficient, coT is the  flame temperature 
without aluminum (~2 500K), and  x is the  solids fraction  in the gas (the 1.85  factor 
accounts fo r the oxyge n in the Al 2O3 particles). 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                 Le cture 16 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                               Page 1 of 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Consider also a linear ized model for the ef fect of  the particulates, of  the form 
 
oe
eu1fxu=   (at fixed Tc )     (2) 
 
 
where f is as derived in class: 
 
 
f = ()1
se
pg c1l n(1) cP11 ; 1 (smallparticles)22c P
1 (largeparticles)
   + =      
   
 
 
(a) Show that the optimum loadin g is giv en by 
                
        ()OPT
OPT AlOPTx r2fx; x3rf 1.85= =       (3) 
 
 
(b) For ()e
gg s AlOPT
cP J0.01, 1.25,M18g/mol,c1260 ,calculatex forPK gK= = = =  
both small an d large part iculates. Commen t on results. 
 
 
Problem 3  Solution  
 
Ignori ng the exit pressure effect  (or at matc hed condi tions),  
 
 
      g Isp = v e = 1
e
pc
cP2CT1P
 
 
 
which is proportional to cT. The rest of the dependence  are affected by 
particulates, but that is count ed separately in t he loss analysis.  So we have 
(counting b oth effects) p(,c)
 
 
(a)       ()ev1 fx1r + x 
 
            To opti mize, take the l ogarithmic derivative and eq uate to zero 
 
           
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                 Le cture 16 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                               Page 2 of 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>f1 r01fx21rx+=+ 
 
 
2f(1rx)r(1fx) +=                       r - 2f = 3rfx 
 
 
OPTr-2fx=  3rf                   and then   ()OPT
AlOPTxx1.85=    
 
 
 
 
(b) For small part iculate f = ()()s
pg1l n1 c 1112c       +          ,  and using the gi ven 
values, 
 
 
 = 1 - (0.01 )0.25/1. 25 = 0.6012   ;  pg1.258.314C 2309 J/Kg/K0.250.018==  
 
 
1 1260 0.3988 ln(0.3988)f 1 1 0.39342 2309 0.6012 = + =    
 
 
OPT1.4120.3934x31.410.3934=   OPTx 0.3746=
 
 
and then the Aluminum fracti on should be   
 
()AlOPT0.3746X0 .20251.85= =    20.3% Al loading  
 
 
For the case of larger particle, the cl ass derivation showe d f=1, a nd so  
                                        
                                     OPT1.4121x031.411= &lt; 
 
This nonsensical resu lt simply  means there is no good Al loadin g in this case.  
The losses due to the partic les are stronger than the gains due to  increased 
temperature, so no Aluminum sho uld be adde d.  
 
Fortunately, the particles are small,  not large.  
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                 Le cture 16 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                               Page 3 of 3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ideal Nozzle Fluid Mechanics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 3 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 10 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>(b) e
aP (full nozzle)P0.4&gt; ,   
 
calculate  ()
()''
''
'0.4 ==
=
ee
ee
e
ttMM P P
AAMAAa
 
 
 
then ()'
'
vac=ae
FF e
otPACC MPA 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 3 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 9 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>where  due only to the variation of  in (1), while  because of 
mass burnout. The quantities  and ()=FFCC taP ()=mm t
FvacCe
tA
A depend on  (or nozzle geometry), but 
are time-invariant. Substituting (1), (2) and (3) into (4), eM
 
 
00 =     ttbbea
Fc t F vac
tcAP dt dtVP A CmA P m 
 
or  
0
00=
tba
c F
F tt vac bbtctPdt
PmA VCdt dt APAmme   (5) 
 
 
 
We now make the approximation that the trajectory will change little when we vary 
 (and hence , eMFvacCe
tA
A). We can then regard the time integrals in (5) as fixed 
quantities while we optimize . Define the non-dimensional variables eM
 
 
0
00;=
tba
c F
tbb
ctPdt
Pm Vvpdt dtPAmm=t  (6) 
 
 
so that (5) becomes 
 
() (= e
Fevac
tAvC M p MA)e  (7) 
 
 
and we can now differentiate v w.r.t  (holding p=const.) eM
 
e
F t vac
ee eA
C A v0MM M  = p =   (8) 
 
 
From (2) and (3), the factor ()

+
 
+1
212
1 appears in both terms of (8) and can be 
ignored. We then have 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 3 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 5 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>+= 1
21112eMp 

 
 =    1
2111eOPTMp  (9) 
 
Notice that the exit pressure is given by 
 

 =
+121
112e
c
eP
P
M     (10) 
 
 
and so the optimum exit pressure turn out to be 
 
 
= e
cOPTPpP     (11) 
 
 
However, if 0.4&lt;ao
cP
pP, this would imply 0.4&lt;e oPaP, and there would be flow 
separation at the highest  (on the ground). To avoid this, the optimality condition 
must be amended to aP
 
 
Greater of , 0.4  =    aeo
ccOPTP P
PP     (12) 
 
 
with a similar expression for : eM
 
 


       =                 11
21 2Least of 1 , 2.5 111c
eOPTaoPMpP (13) 
 
The limiting condition in which the whole burn occurs at Pis simple.  ao
 
We then obtain 
 
 
0
0=
tbao
a c
tbcPdt
P Pmpdt P
m=o     (14) 
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 3 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 7 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>()
 
+
   + +      =    +     1
212
211 12
112e ee
ee
eM MMpMM MMe 
 
 
()
()
  
  +
    +  + + =          + ++  1
212
2
32 2 221 11 1 1 222 11 1 1 22
1 22 1 11 1 11 2 22eeee
e
eeeeeM
eMMpMM MM MMMM
 
 
Multiply times +3
22112eM
 , and note that () 
 ++= 11
21 21 
 
 
() ()
 
   +        +  + = +  + 
       12
22 2
22112 111 111 1 122 2e
ee e
eeM
MM p M
MM2
eM
 
 
 
 
Expand &amp; simplify 
 
() ()()
 
  +  +   =
144444444444244444444444 312
22
221111 2 11 1122 2 2e
ee
eeM
MM p
MM2
eM  
   2
221 11=e
eeM
MM 
 
 
Cancel the factor 2
21e
eM
M (M  is clearly not an optimum!) 1=e
 
=+1
21112e pM  
 
or  
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 3 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 6 of 10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>=ea
FF v
tcMeAPCC  AP
 
 
Note: 
  
For , =eaPP
  
()()
 
 +
 ==+  +1
21
* Matched
22
1 112ee
F
euMC
cM 
 
 
For  ()0==eaPP()
+
 = +1
21
Max,Vac22
11FC  
 
 
 
Choice of Optimum Expansion For a Rocket Flying Through an Atmosphere 
(varying) aP
 
The thrust coefficient =F
ctFCPA was derived in class in the form 
 
= ae
FF vac
ctPACCPA      (1) 
 
       ()

 +
+=+  +1
21
21
2
1 112ee
Fvac
eMMC
M   (2) 
and we also found 
 ()
 
+
 +
=+1
212111 2
1
2ee
teMA
AM    (3) 
 
 
The thrust-derived velo city increment is  
 
00= =ttbbF
Fc tC FVd t P Ammd t   (4)  
 
16.512, Rocket Propulsion   Lecture 3 
Prof. Manuel Martinez-Sanchez   Page 4 of 10</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Convective Heat Transfer: Reynolds Analogy (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Prop ulsion  
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 7: Convective Heat Tr ansfer: Reyn olds Analogy 
 
 
Heat Tr ansfer in Rock et Nozzles  
 
General  
 
Heat transf er to wal ls can af fect a  rocket i n at least two  ways: 
 
(a) Reduci ng the performance. This tends to be a 1-3% e ffect on  only, and is 
therefore secondary. spI
(b) Creating great difficulties in  the design of hot-side structures that have to 
survive heat fluxes in the  range. 7810 10w/m 2
 
The prin cipal modes of  heat transfer to nozzle and combust or walls are 
convection  and radiation . Of these, convec tion dominates, and radi ation tends to be 
import ant only for part icle-laden flows from solid prope llant rockets. 
 
 
Convective Heat Transfer  
 
We w ill rev iew here the compressible 2D  boun dary layer equations in order t o extract 
information on wall heat transfer. 
 
 
 
 
The governi ng equations are (i n the B.L. approximation) 
 
 
Continuity  ()() uv0xy+= (1) 
 
X-Momentum   xy uu puvx yxyy y    ++ == u
 (2) 
 
Y-Momentum  P0y= (3) 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 7 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 1 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>One gets, 
 
()tthroatS 0.00133=  (0.00124 using  instead of  txtcxx) 
 
Using the   option (small rockets) eR 4000&lt;
 
 
()t 0.68 throat 0.2
eff
e throat throat0.0293S
ux T
T=
  &lt;&gt;   
 
 
and using again , etc, eff t c xx=x
 
 
we get ()tthroatS 0.00102=   (0.000933 using ) tx
 
 
For comparison, the fully developed pipe flows form ulation woul d give 
 
N0.2 0.80.2w 0.9*g 0.2 et
te 0.2
ep c t
1atthroatR TA 0.026 cSuc P T A D  ==    &lt;&gt;   
 
()tthroatS 0.000958=  
 
This is close t o the R4  results above (and, indeed , the coefficients are for 
). But this a ppears coincidental00&lt; 0
0 R4 00&lt; , based on the fact that for most nozzles, 
. txR
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 7 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 16 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>The group 
prK 1
cP= shoul d be set equal  to unity, for consistency  with the stated 
approxi mations. Th us  
 
t
w
whqy= 
 
Use now equation (11): 
 
()e
etw
w wtw
ee w whh uuqh hhyu u   = + =     y 
 
and notice that 
wu
y is the wall shear stress, w. So  
 
 
et w
w
ehh
qu
=w        ( 13) 
 
 
which is also called Rey nolds an alogy . A more  compact for m of this can be written in 
terms of t he Friction Coefficient 
 
 w
f
2
eec1u2
         ( 14) 
 
and the Stanton number 
 
 
()ew
t
ee t wqS
uh h=
         ( 15) 
 
with the result (from (13)) 
 
 f
tcS2=         ( 16) 
 
One important point ca n be ma de about the result (13): 
 
The heat flux to the wall is driv en by the enthalpy (or temperature) dif ference 
between Total  external and Wall  values, not between static values. This can be n on-
intuitive. Consider t he situation near the exit o f a highly expanded space nozzle, 
where the bulk temperature  may have dropped to, say, 3 00K due to the stro ng 
expansion from a cham ber temperature of, say, 3000 K. The wall could be made of 
Tungsten so  as to be ab le to sustain rela tively high temperat ure and cool it self by 
radiation to space, so  could be, say, 1500K. Is the nozzle wall being heatedeT
wT  or 
cooled  by the 300K ga s? The answer is tha t it is being heated , beca use 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 7 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 5 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Note that whenever 
e et wh &gt;
wh&lt;uh  there develop s an intermediate temperature 
maximu m. But in any case, the wall slope is as  if the line were comin g from h, not 
from h. The case when h  is more revealing even: et
e e
 
 
                
  
 
 
Now the wall slope is seen to be  positive (heat into the wall), despit e h  (as 
long as hh ) e wh&lt;
&gt;twe
 
So, the qua dratic portion of the  Crocco rela tionship is respon sible f or the extra wall 
heat; this can  in turn be t raced t o viscou s dissipat ion, which accumulates in the 
boundary layer and elevates its te mperature,  so that the wall is  heated even when 
the outside temperature is low (as long as t he flow has  high speed) . 
 
Modification for P1  r
1&lt;
1 
We leave f or now the issue of the non zero pr essure gradi ent, ex cept to note that it 
introduces s mall modifications dow n to the throat. The devi ations of P from unity 
are small, and, for gase s P  (~ 0.9 for turb ulent flow). This breaks the perfect 
balance between dissipation and c onduction responsible for Croccos  analogy, in the 
sense of favoring conduction of the dissipated heat. As a  second co nsequence,  the 
temperature overshoot is reduced, and so is the wall slope of  T and the heat f lux to 
the wall. The direct effect of higher conduc tion (Pr
r
r&lt;) is acco unted for 
approximately by modifying Reyno lds analogy to  
 
 
 f
t
rcS2P0.6=          ( 19) 
 
 
The second ary effect (r educed ove rshoot) is  accounted fo r by replacing the driving 
enthalpy diff erence h  by hte wh haw w, where h is the Adiabat ic-wall en thalpy, 
defined as  aw
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 7 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 7 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>For large ro ckets,  tends to be , so the hi gh  formulas sho uld 
be better, despite the common use  of Bart zs formulae, whi ch are bas ed on t he low 
 formul ation. Fort unatel y, differenc es tend to be smal l, and are marked often  by 
other u ncertainties (sur face films, fluid properties). exthroatR710 108
eR
eR
 
Exam ple and Comparisons: 
 
Consi der nozzle 22 2
t tRR R R 1Rx tanx x4tanx 2tan=+ = 
 
 
with origin  at 22
cc
cRR Rxx2tan==t 
 
and o c
tR1.5,15R= =  
 
and going through throat at t
tRxx2tan== 
 
Using =1.25 and the  option, we find eR 4000&gt;
 
xt
R 1.875 0.9 t5eff 12
22
t t throat xc
Rtx 1.125 0.6979 xMdRR 10.125M 0.65150.0464M    =         ++     
 
 
where ()o
tt t o
t1Rx R 4tan15 xRR R xtan15R=+ 


 
 
 
and ()2.252
12 t11 0.125M RMx1.125 RM+=  
 
 
The integration  gives eff
tthroatx1.0892R=  
 
 
Compared to tc c
ttxx x1.153 and 0.713RR ==  
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 7 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 14 of 16</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Dynamics of Turbopump Systems: The Shuttle Engine (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_30/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>30</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>22302= OTP OT OP OPdI
dt      ( 1) 
 
 
In a hybrid system whe re 02 is in rad/sec, t in se conds, and  the torq ue in lb-
in, the constant IOTP has a val ue 1
0.916 (which implies I OTP = 422 lb min2). 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 30 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 2 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 30: Dyn amics of Turbopump Syst ems: T he Shuttl e Engine 
 
 
Dynamics of the Space Shu ttle Main En gine Oxidi zer Pressuri zation Subs ystems  
 
Selected Sub-Model  
 
In the complet e SSME engine, all variables af fect each  other in complex  ways. 
In order to test our  fault detecti on algorithms, a dynamic subsyste m is desired, with 
reduced ord er, but with the unmod elled states  interacting as weakly as possible w ith 
those modell ed. Attention was focused on  the liquid oxygen subsyst em for two main 
reasons: 
 
(a) The O/F  ratio at rated p ower is 6, so that the LOX dynami cs sho uld dominate 
over the LH  effects whe rever they i nteract, and 
 
(b) The turbopump pre-burners are run very fu el-rich in order t o limit the turbine 
inlet temperatures below  the met allurgical limits of the  uncooled blad es; 
small ex cursions of the LOX flow to the pre-burners are the n immediat ely 
translated into large and pot entially critical turbine temperat ure excursions. 
 
In our submodel we therefore focus at tention on the LOX  turbop ump, which 
feeds both, the main LOX injectors, and (aft er the boost stage) the two turbi ne pre-
burners. Also modeled are the dynamics of the LOX feeding line to  the pre-burne rs, 
as well as to t he main  LOX valve and main  injector, plus the LOX pre-bu rner itself 
and the main c hamber pressure. V ariations of the LH-related st ates should indeed 
couple weakly to the LOX sy stem, mainly through LH flow variations onto the pre-
burners (insensiti ve, since they are fuel-rich), an d into the main cham ber (choked  
flow, no  feedback). 
 
The Dynami c Equations 
 
There are three types of dynami c equations to be consid ered: 
 
(1) Rotati onal dynami cs of the LOX turbopumps. 
 
(2) Equations expressi ng the liquid inertia under pressure difference variations 
(analogou s to inductance in  elect ric circu its). 
 
(3) Equations expressin g the abilit y of cavities to store fluid due to its 
compressibility under p ressure fluc tuations  (analogous to c apacitive effects). 
 
 
(1) Rota tional Dynami cs 
 
  If I OTP is the moment o f the inertia of th e Oxidizer Turbo Pu mp (OTP) rotor,  its 
angular velocity, 02
2OTthe to rque deliver ed by the O TP turbine, 
2OPthe torq ue 
absorbed by the main oxidizer pump st age, an d 
3OP the torque absorbe d by the 
oxidizer boo ster pump, then 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 30 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 1 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>(2) Inerti a of LOX i n pre-burner co mmon sup ply line  
 
This is a prot otypical equ ation of ty pe (2), and, in order to il lustrate the 
underlying physics, w e well give here a brief  deriv ation of it. 
 
Consider a pipe of length L and cro ss-section A , fed by the booster pump 
discharge at a pressure P OD3, and having a me an pressure  PPOS (Pre-bu rner Oxidizer 
Suppl y). Frictional forces al ong the pipe, and at bends  and restrictions, co ntribute a 
total pressu re drop 21,2

 where  and  are the LOX density and velocity, and 
 (of order unity) is a pressu re loss coef ficient. The liqu id is then acted on in the 
forward direction by a net force 2
31
2.OD POSPP A. The mass of liqu id in the 
pipe is ,AL and we m ust have 
 
()32
2=  OD POSdALP P
dt  A
A 
 
Now, the flow rate i n the pipe is 3=i
OPm, so the eq uation can  be re-written as  
 
2
33
3 22=  i
OPOP
OP POSdmLP P m
dt A
A 
 
 
or                                                     
            ( 2) 3
32
3
OP
OP OP POSLd mPP KmAd t
  =  
 
where  22=K
A
        ( 3) 
 
In units of /secmlb  for m and lb  for P, the cons tants have  the values 2/in1
100=L
A, K = 
0.000813. This implies  3.86=L
A 1in and ()2
0.026 1 . =Ain   
 
 
(3)Fluid Capacitance in prebu rner LOX supply line 
 
This is a pr ototypical equation of type  (3), and we al so provide a deri vation 
below: 
 
Considerin g again  the POS su pply line, it receiv es LOX flow at  a rat e m 
from the booster pump, and discha rges  into the fuel preburner (FP) and m into 
the oxidizer pre-burner (OP), plus a smal l amount   which is diverted t o cool the 
pump. Un der dy namic conditions, there is a (gen erally non-zero) net inflow 
3OP

FPOm
OPO
2OPCm
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 30 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 4 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Appendix D. Characte ristic Times (approx.) fo r the SS ME Dynamic Model 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 30 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 10 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 30 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 11 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Appendix C. State Variab les in a simulat ed Throt tling Sequence 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 30 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 9 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Appendix B. Steady S tate Values from the SSME Thermo dynamic Mo del 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 30 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 8 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>32 .OP FPO OPO OPC mm m m m Let V be the mass store d in the pipe, where 
2
4=DVL is the volume av ailable. Then we must have 
 
()
=dVmdt        ( 4) 
 
Even though LOX i s a liquid, it has finite compressi bility at the very  high 
pressu res inv olved here. This is meas ured by the thermodynamic parameter 
 
10 1 62 1510 3.410 / =  dKP a
dP
inlb
  (5)  
 
In general, the volume V also v aries sligh tly under pressu re fluctuations, but it 
can be s hown that this effect  is secondary. We therefore rewrite (4) as  
 
   ()321   =  OP FPO OPO OPCPOS
POS
LOXdP dVm m
dP dt
m m   
  
 
 
In the same uni ts as be fore, t he factor ()1   
   POS
LOXdV
dP
 has a value of 
1. Using 
38,12062 13.410 /,dinlbdp
 this implies a l ine volume V = 409 in, which 
combin ed wit h previously estimated 3
/ 3.86= LA  1in, yields 40L  in,  in 
These are not expected to be exact dimens ions of the POS line, because the model 
lumps together several secondary inertios  and capacitances, but they do appear 
reasonable.  Incidentally, from the previous result  we no w esti mate 
 again a reasonable value for a  pressure loss factor. 10A2.
()20.0261 ,inA
2.8,
 
The Compl ete Submode l 
 
In addi tion to the  three  equati ons derived above, there are th ree others of the 
fluid inertia type and thr ee others of the fluid capacitance type. The co mplete 
submodel , in the same unit used so  far, i s shown in Table.on  next page. 
 
Equations (6), (7), (8) are the one s just derived. Eq . (9) deals with the inertia 
of the LOX moving thro ugh the valve and the  injectors of  the Fuel Pre burner (FP) 
under the fluctuating drive of the pressure difference , less the  press ure 
drops in  the valve and in the injectors. These drops ha ve the characteristic  m form, 
just as  in Eq. (2 ), but, in addi tion the valve open area fraction POS FPP P
2
/ FPV AA  appear  squared 
in the den ominator, as it should accordin g to Eq. (3 ). This area fraction will act as one 
of our control variab les. 
 
Eq. (10) is iden tical in  structure to Eq. (9), but refers to the fluid inertia in the 
LOX dome of the Oxidizer Preburne r (OP). Once again, the OP valve area fraction 
/ OPV AA  appears he re as a control variab le. 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 30 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 5 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>The remain ing inertia-type equ ation is Eq.  (13), which refers t o the LOX 
moving through the Main Oxidizer Valv e (MOV) under the drive of the difference 
between the main oxidizer discharge pressure , , and the  main combustor 
pressure, P c, less the  sum of the pr essure drop s in the MO V (assumed 100% open) 
and the injectors. 2ODP
 
The remaining three capacitance-type eq uations are Eqs. (11), (12) a nd (14). 
Eq. (11) de scribes accumulation of gas in th e Oxidizer Preburner (O P), with mass flow 
 (the un-modelled fuel  flow into the  OP) plus  (the LOX flow into the OP) 
enteri ng, an d almost al l of the gas  flow input to the o xidizer turbi ne, , leaving. 
OPFm
OPOm
2
OTm
 
 
Table: DYNAMIC S OF LOX PRESSURIZA TION SU BSYS TEM 
 
 
Equation 
No. Equation Description Time 
Const ant 
(sec.) 
 
(6) 2
221
0.916= O
OT OP OPd
dt 3 Rotati onal 
dynamics of 
OTP 0.058 
(7) 2
333 10.000813
100
= din
OPOD POSOPPP mdt LOX inertia in 
preburner 
supply line 0.00013 
(8) 
321
38120  
= OP FPO OPO OPCdPPOSmm m m
dt Mass s torage 
in preburne r 
supply line 0.0020 
(9) 2
210.02488 0.1948
2 /

=  


i
FPO
OPO
FPVdm
POS FPFPO mPP m
dt AA LOX in ertia in 
injector dome 
of FP 0.0048 
(10) 2
2
0.260 1.463
/


 = 
OPO
OPO POS OP
OPVdinOPO mPP m
dt AA LOX in ertia in 
injector dome 
of OP 0.0034 
(11) 
210.9980
10,000 
=+ OPF OPO OTdPOPmm m
dt Mass s torage 
in Oxidizer 
Preburner 0.0143 
(12) 
12 21 11.085
3000 
=+  +FT OT OTdP
FTFmm M m
dt2 Mass s torage 
in fuel ducts to 
injector 0.0050 
(13) 2
210.001715
25

= MOVdm
OD CMOVPP m
dt LOX inert ia in 
main inject or 
dome 0.0078 
(14) 
11
4000 
=+ FM OVcdPmm m
dtCN Mass s torage 
in main 
combustor 0.00074 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 30 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 6 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Equation (1 2) de scribes the gas ac cumulation in the two large ducts  which 
bring t he partially oxidiz ed hydroge n to the main chamber inject or dome.  Feeding t his 
volume are t he (unmodel led) discharge  flows o n the main Fuel Turbine  and of 
the low pre ssure Fuel Turbine , plus the  discha rge of th e main Oxidiz er Turbine,  
; leaving t his volume is basical ly the main Fuel Injector flow , plus some 
smaller LH cooling flows, up to 1.085 . m
FT2



FT1m
m
OT2m
FI
m
FI
 
Finally, Eq. (14) go verns the changes in the  main combustor pressure, P c , 
due to mas s accum ulation. The ma ss inputs are the fuel and oxidizer inject or flows 
( ), while t he mass loss is t he nozzle flow rat e . 
,FI MOV mm
CNm
 
 
Characteristic Times  
 
For each of the dynamic equation s (6)-(14 ), we can estim ate the 
charact eristic time const ant, which provid es same prel iminary appreciat ion for the 
dynam ics of the system. For t his purpose , we balance the rate term with one of the 
dominant te rms on the right; fo r instance , for Eq. (6), the time constant is 
2
2,
0.9=
OT
12O with  and 2O2OT
time constr aints are included in Ta ble. The preburner supply line f low and the m
combustor pressure are seen to a djust rapidl y (under 1 msec).  Filling and emptying of  
the Oxidiz er Preburner is relat ively slow ( 14 msec), and the shaf t spee d of the OTP is 
very slow (58 msec). A ll other dynamics are comparable in speed with time cons tants 
of a few msec.  evaluated at t heir nom inal values ( rated power ). These 
ain 
 
Calculation of no n-state variables  
 
The seq uence of algebraic computa tions (no additional dynamics) required to 
calculate th e right-ha nd-sides of Eqs. (6)-(14) is sum marized in Appe ndix.  T he data 
for these calculat ions ar e the values of  the nine state variables,  the values of t he 
control variables (preburner valve openings ), and a few unmodelled variables arising 
from the fuel side of  the overal l system. The lat ter are generally kept  at their no minal 
values. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 30 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 7 of 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 30 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 3 of 11</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Liquid Motors: Stability (Low Frequency) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 22: Liquid M otors: Combusti on In stabili ty (Low Frequ ency) 
 
 
 
Combu stion St abilit y 
 
1. Gener al Discussi on 
 
Elimination of instabilities has been h istorical ly one of the largest  compon ents 
of all new liquid rock et developmen t progra ms. This is because there has been lit tle 
reliab le methodology to  ensure stability throug h design, a nd also bec ause of the 
potentially catastrophic consequences of  instability. The situ ation has improv ed to 
some extent because  of the va stly enlarged si mulation capa bilities existing now. As 
we will see,  this area is in timately related to that of spray  combu stion, where a 
similar situation has prevailed.  As in  the combust ion area,  the adv ances in recen t 
years are promis ing, but not yet sufficient to provide rel iable tools f or a priori des ign, 
at least  again st the high-frequency instability problem.  
 
In a system  with the  very large energy  density of a rocket combustor, there 
are bound  to be many  mechani sms by  which a small fraction of this energy can be 
channeled into undesirable osci llations. The resu lting instabilities are u sually 
categorized into low frequency and high frequency types. The former in volve 
pressure os cillations which are slow eno ugh compare to the acous tic passage time 
that the whole ch amber part icipat es in phase, while the latter exhibits acou stic 
behavior, with differe nt parts o f the combusto r oscill ating with different phase or 
amplitude. In either case, the instability arises w hen energ y (or sometimes mass) 
can be ad ded to the gas  at, or  near, peaks in its pressure o scillation (t his is the 
classica l Rayleigh criterion for instability, as explain ed) for example in  Refs. (21) and 
(26)*. This implies a sy nchronization of tw o mech anisms,  one which generates the 
energy or mass in so me unsteady manner , and another one which allows the gas 
pressure and other thermody namic qua ntities to osci llate. These two mechanisms 
must have comparable time constants for the mutual feedback to develop. 
 
The acoustic modes of typical rocket combus tors have wa velengths w hich are 
some fracti on of their linear si ze, and a wave speed (the speed of sou nd) of the 
order of 20 00 m/sec.  Thus their frequenc ies are in the KHz range, and hence the 
oscillat ion time consta nt is 10-4 to 10-3 sec, a nd potential couplings are to be so ught 
to energy o r mass rele ase mechanisms with ti me consta nts of that order. To be more 
precise, it must be noted that a ti me lag in the release of  combustion energy (such 
as, for example at omization, evaporat ion, mixing or react ion delay s) will not per se 
provide cou pling with the acou stic field. There mu st also be a sen sitivity of the he at 
release rate, and he nce of the time delay, to the pressure or other wa ve qua ntity. 
Since, in general, only some of  the addit ive time lags sh ow such a sen sitivity, and 
then maybe  only for a  fraction of t he effecti ve lag, it is found that the exci ted 
acoustic mo des have time consta nts which are  a fraction o f the time lags 
themselves. As an example, E q. (22 of  lectur e 19) gives for a droplet with =100 0 
kg/m3, ln (l + B)=5 and  3 x 10-5 kg/m/sec a vaporization time of 8.2  msec. 
Yet, this size dropl ets coul d de-sta bilize acoustic modes of about 1KHz frequency, as 
reported, fo r instance i n Ref. 27. A
gD
* See Ref. List and end of Lecture 1 9
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 22 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 1 of 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Other exci tation mech anisms for high frequency waves have been reported. 
Gas-phase propellant mixing delays in rapi dly evaporating cryogenic s may be o f the 
required or der an d show sensit ivity to acou stic fields. C onversion of vortex energy to  
acoustic dipole rad iation upon  impin gemen t of a vortex street or a tur bulent shear 
layer on an obstacle can also be a destabil izing factor [28], although this mech anism 
may also work as a da mper, if the  phase is arranged appr opriately. On the other 
hand acous tic frequenci es are normall y too high to  allow involvement of elements 
outside the chamber it self, such as the liquid-handling equipment or the overall 
rocket str ucture. Also, chemical reaction  times in well-mixed gases te nd to be 
shorter tha n 0.1-1 msec, and  are not usually involved either. 
 
The low  frequency types of  instability, by contrast, usually results from 
coupling of oscillat ions of pressure in the whole chamber to elements outside  of it. 
These can be the injectors, the liquid lines (or the liqu id in them), the turbopu mps, 
and, in the instability called POGO, the whole rock et structure. There is su bstantially 
more u nderstanding of these th an of the fast instabilities, and analytical techniques 
were developed early on [26 ] to help avoid them i n the design process. Ma ny of the 
low-frequency instabilities can be described in  terms of  a single, non-sensitive, 
combustion delay; as discussed, this dela y can be several times longer tha n its 
sensitive fraction. In oth ers cases, the mecha nism may be more complex, perhap s 
involving different delay s for the two propell ant streams.  
 
The literature also men tions an intermediat e and ben ign type of instability, 
which is a hybrid sometimes described as e ntropy wa ve. Acous tic oscillations may 
modul ate differentl y the oxydi zer and fuel injection rates, creati ng pat ches of  varying 
stoichiomet ry and tem perature. These co nvect with the mean flow, and, upon  
impingement o n the convergi ng nozzle, may s ynchronize with and reinforce the 
acoustic wa ve, which then propagates back to the injector region . Since part of the 
mech anism is acou stic and part con vective, the frequency falls bet ween the first 
acoustic lon gitudinal mode an d the flow passage t ime. 
 
The effects of these in stabilities ra nge from si mple v ibratory and acou stic 
disturbance s to very ra pid burnout of walls. The most seve re effects ar e associated 
with high-frequency instabilities of  the tangential chamber mo des. The se create 
sloshing gas moti ons w hich compl etely disrupt the bo undar y layer near the i njector  
end of the chamber,  and can lead t o failure in a mat ter in secon ds. Thus, most  effort  
has gon e into understanding and eliminating tangential mode in stabilities. Low 
frequency instabilities, if allowed to proceed,  can also be st ructurally damagin g, but, 
as noted,  they can  often be desi gned out,  and if not, there  are reli able 
countermeasures against them. 
 
 
2. Meth ods of Analysis for Low Frequenc y Instabiliti es 
 
The compilation by Harr je and Reardon (R ef. 26)* remains the best so urce of 
information on this topic. The analysis t ypically  separat es into a chamber port ion, 
balancing the gas ge neration, stor age and disposable, plus a se ries of submodels 
detailing the response of various o ther parts of the syste m, such as injectors, 
pumps, et c. For prelim inary analysis, linear perturbation m odels are used, and  Ref. 
(26)* s hows a variety of subsys tem response  functions adequate for  this purpose. 
 
* - D.T. Harrje and T.H. Reardon (Editors ) Liquid Propellan t Rock et Combustion 
Instability, NASA S P-194, 1972. 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 22 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 2 of 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>As a simple prototype, we discuss  here the co upling of c hamber and injector 
alone (single stream). I t is assume d that vaporization of the liquid happens a time v 
after injection, which may be a ref lection of the time del ay for atomizing into 
droplets, plus the droplet evaporation time  given by Eq . 22 (Lecture 19), altho ugh 
this part would be bette r modeled as a di stributed, rather than a lumped lag.  
 
Let PC and TC be the c hamber pressure and  temperature, both of which are 
taken to be uni form, and VC the chamber vol ume. The vaporization rate is: 
 
                                            ()()
= viv mt mt      (1) 
 
while the g as disposal  rate throu gh the nozzle is as gi ven by ctmP A/c
= . We 
then have 
 
                                          ()cic v
gcPPdVm tdtRT c

=  ctA   (2) 
 
 
The injection rate through  an effective in jector orif ice ar ea A i, with a  pressure 
P0 behind it, is 
 
                                          ()0 2 iL c i m      ( 3) PPA
= 
 
 
where l is the gas liqu id dest iny. Linearization of these equat ions, assumin g 
constant R g, Tc, P0 and c*, gives 
 
 
     () 1
2' ''
cv cc c
c gC ocPt VdP PmRT dt PP P  =         (4) 
 
 
where () 0 2ctcl i m  is the mean mass flow rate , PAPPA
c
==  cP is the mean  
chamber pr essure, and   its pert urbation. We c an defi ne a cham ber evacuati on 
time '
cP
 
                                         c
c
gcPV
RTmc
=       ( 5) 
 
 
and an injector overpressure parameter 
 
                                        0c
cPP
P=       ( 6) 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 22 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 3 of 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Allowing a non  zero (posit ive or n egative) imagin ary part of , we ca n obtain the 
results shown in Fig. 1. In gen eral, stability is en hanced by increasin g injector drop 
or chamber residence time (i n relation to t he evaporat ion lag). As sh own in Fig. 2.3b, 
the sta ble or neutral  oscillations ha ve frequen cies of the or der of . As 
an example of the kinds of de lays encountered in  LOX- LH rockets, we  reproduce Fig. 
2 (from Ref. 26). ()12 4Rvf/ 
                                   
 
                                  
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 22 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 5 of 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>So, three cases: 
 
1. 1 vc
cP' m0.52Pm
= = 
 
Gas mass p roduction in phase  with gas expulsion (as wit h ). cP'
 
2. () 1 i c v
cP' m'0.5 e2Pm

&gt; = 

vm' lags , chamber begins emptying before
ontm'  new gas is int roduced Stable. 
 
3. () 1 v i c
cP' m0.5 e2Pm
+
&lt; = 
 

vm' leads  , New gas  starts  accum ulating be fore it can be expelled. This 
can be
ontm'
 unstable,  if the  is smal l enough compared t o c v.  
 
 
Notice that the sensitive (to pressure) part  of this time lag is 0.1 to 0.2 of  the total 
lag. According t o the result s in Fig. 1, the marginal ly stable oscil lations with the total 
delay of Fig. 2, (and with ) would be at approximately a frequency 0.2
-31.7270
101f= Hz2 
 
 
 
Fig. 2 Experimental value s of combustion time lag for supe rcritical chamber pressure 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 22 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 6 of 6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>PDF - 1 MB</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 11 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 13 of 14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 11 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 11 of 14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 11 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 10 of 14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 11 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 14 of 14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 11 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 12 of 14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 11 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 8 of 14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 11 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 9 of 14</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Mechanical Design of Turbomachinery (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_28/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>28</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 28: Mechanical De sign of Tur bomachin ery 
 
Integration and Rotordynamics of Turbo Pumps 
 
1. Integration and Mechanical Compo nents 
 
As noted  before, t urbines and p umps are often  moun ted on a commo n 
shaft. If the oxidizer and fuel have similar den sities, their respective pumps ca n 
also be on  one shaft. This is t he case in  the MK-3 Atlas and D elta II boost er 
turbopum p, which, however, has a  geared turb ine-pump tr ansmi ssion. The 
Russian R D-170 takes a further integration step by having  a single tur bine drive 
both, fuel and oxidizer pump, all o n a sin gle shaft. In additi on, these pumps feed 
not a single thr ust cha mber, but a  cluste r of four in the case of the Energia 
vehicle (Fig 4, Lec.  24). Engines u sing LH fuel require different speeds  for the  
oxidizer and fuel  pumps. The first of these engines, the RL-10,  had a  single-stage 
oxygen pump on o ne shaft, gear driven by a  second s haft on which were 
mounted a 2-stage hydrogen pump and the drive turbine. More recent engines 
(LE-7, SS ME) feature s eparate sha fts for the o xygen and fuel , each ca rrying its 
own drive turbine. 
 
Bearing design and bearing placement have a significant impact  on the 
overall turbopump char acteristics. Existi ng engines use ro ller element bearings, 
and in rece nt designs , these are lubricat ed and cooled by the propella nt being 
pumped, which simplifies the co nstruction. O n the ot her hand, this departure 
from traditional bearin g pract ice ha s necessitated extensi ve research on 
compat ible materials. Ref [48] desc ribes work on adva nced ball bearings for the 
future Space Transportation Main Engines (STME) and  the SSME Alternate 
Turbopump  Devel opment (AT D). The lubrication concept  relies on  sacrif icial wear 
of the bearing cage (bronze-60 % Teflon), and its transfer from t he rolling 
elements to  the race way surface. 
 
Roller e lement bearings can provide so me stiffness, through a ngular contact 
design, bu t the bulk of the axi al thrust of the p umps a nd turbines must be 
hydraulically balanced, either by ba ck-to-back pump arrangements with no 
feedback, o r, as in the SSME turbopumps , by providing hydr aulic feedback  to 
some surface acting as the balancing pi ston [40]. Future de signs are likely to 
feature hydrostatic bearin gs, which rely  on a very thin fluid film to support  the 
rotor wi thout solid contact with the casi ng. The advantag es of t hese bearings are 
summarized in Table 1  from Ref [40]. T he most important are the removal  of the 
surface speed lim itation of ball bearin gs an d the much higher radial stiffness. The 
surface speed is expressed by the DN prod uct in co nventional bearings, a nd, as 
Table 2 in dicates, is in the range of  (mm)  612 10  (Rpm). T his limitation 
forces the  designer to seek bearing loca tions w ith the  smal lest possible diameter,  
such as o utboard of the pumps a nd turbin es, but these b earing locations tend to 
lower the 1st natural frequency , and to interfer e with flow approach to  the pumps . 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 28 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                               Page 1 of 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Item Hydrostatic bearing Ball bearing  
 
Speed limit  None 2.0M DN LH 2 
1.75M DN LO2 
 
Life limit  Unlimited steady state  
 
Transient rub concern  
 = 2h 
Design cons traints Supply pres sure ava ilability Shaft diameter for torque 
transmission 
 
Direct stiffness 1 to &gt;5M lb/in.  0.5 to 1M lb /in. for duplex 
pair 
 
Dampi ng 50 to &gt;500 lbs
in. 2 to 5 lbs
in. 
 
Rotor-dyna mics No cons traints for opti mum 
position  
 
Adjustable stiffness  and 
damping Position constraints 
 
No adjustable damping  
 
Table 1. Hydrostati c bearing benefits 
 
 
As in all turbo mach ines, seals are required to reduce or prevent leakage of 
fluids aroun d the shaft from hi gh to low pressure areas. T he high linear speeds o f the 
rocket turbopump surfaces, as well as, in some cases, the  oxidizing nature of the 
fluid, dictates the use of non-con tact type sea ls, whi ch, by their natu re, allow a 
nonzero leak age rat e. Thus, in oxidizer turbopump w ith the fuel-rich turbin e on same 
shaft, there is a need to introduce some h igh-pressu re inert gas in to a region  
separati ng the two fluids, with seal s provi ded to minimize leakage (an d hence 
inventory) of this purge gas.  Multi-tooth laby rinth seals are st andard in  jet engines,  
and were incorporat ed at various poin ts in the original SSM E turbo pumps.  However, 
after a seq uence of red esigns to co rrect vi bration problems most of these have be en 
replaced by very low cl earance smooth cylin drical seals, which have much  higher 
radial stiffness an d significantly contribute to raisin g the low est natural frequencies 
of the rotor (in fact, the se seals can be vi ewed as a tran sition to hydro static beari ng 
designs). 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 28 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                               Page 2 of 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le ct
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                               ure 28 
Page 3 of 3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Performance to LEO (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_33/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>33</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>or ()
 + + =+22
112
2E
RR
ER
RVv vVcosRR  
  tan= =1tan
tanRRvvVsin sin coscos 

 ++ =+  22
2
222cos
tantanRR
R
ER
vvvsin RR sin coscosER 
 
 

    + +  =    +    2 2
22
12tan tan tanE
R
ER
R sin sin sinv cos cos cos cosRR 
 
 
  ++ 2
2
221tan tansin sincoscos
+2
tansincos22cos 
 

+2
211
tansin  
 

2
2sin
sin   
= + 2
222
11
tan tanE
R
ER
Rvs inRR 
 
 

=
+1tan
1
tan2RE
EvR R
R sin
R 
 
 

=
+tantan
1
2RE
EvR R
R cos
R 
 
 
Check :  )   0
028.5
61.8L
i=
=057.47= = =
 01tan 1.7308
4070.63770.84318053 
 
() =0059.9860 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 33 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 7 of 9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>=
11
tan cos1tanRvV  
 
 
 

 +=  + +2
2
1 1t2/
2/RR E
E
R
Evcos v RRVcos RR RRvRRan 
 
 
=Rv
Rcos
v  
  +++ +  2
22122/ 2/
2RE R
EE EvR R v RR
RR cos RR cos cos RR

E 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 33 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 9 of 9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>=
+2
21
tan
1
2E
R
EcosL
cosi
RR cosLvR cosi
R 
 
 

=


+ 
22
tan
1
2R
E
EcosLcosi
vcosLcosi
RR
R
R 
 
 
 
Directly: () =1 R Vv
sin sin 
 
 
=
1 tanRv sincosV 
 
 
 
==
2
111tan
RRcos sin
vvcos cosVV 
 
  a nd  =cosicoscosL 
 
 
 
()()
() ()

== =
+ ++   2
22 2 2
2 211
1tan1
2R
RR
RvCosLCosi
Cos
CosL Cosi
vCosL vcosLcosi cosLvCosLCosi 
 
 
 

=
+tantan
12/RE
EvR R
cos RR  

=+ =+
 +2
2
21t1tan 1
12/RcosvR R
cos RRan 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 33 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 8 of 9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 33: Performance to LE O 
 
VCalculations for La unches to Lo w Earth Orbi t (LEO) 
 
Ideal E arth-to-orbit launch 
 
  ='
12 E VcosRvR
 
 =2' 2
12
22EVV
RR 
 
         =2
11
2ERVcosRR 
 
 
 


=
2
1 2
22
1RRV
RcosR  
 
  
 

=
1 2
21
2
1E
EER
RVR RcosR 
 
=cvR 
 
 
 
 
  = = =           22 2 2
2 211
'2 2
11E E
EE
c
EE ERR
RR R RRVv v cos cosRR R R R R RRcos cosRR 
 
12 VV V =+ ()  
   =+ 
22 2221 12'
11 /Vcos
cos cos R 
 
 
R
R=   ()  = ++1211 /Vc os
cos R      (increasingf.of) 
 
 
()  =++2121 /MIN
EV
RFor  0=   
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 33 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 1 of 9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>(b) Orbit  inclin ation 
 
For 0= (launch due East), i = L. For a ny other azi muth, higher inclination. 
 
 
 
 
=RvR cosL 
 
 () =1 RvV
sin sin 
 
 =1 RSinvV sincosCos  cossincos  
 
 =+1
1tan
RVsin
Vcos v 
 
 
 
=
+ 1tantan
1Rv
Vcos 
 
 
Given two a ngles and the side included, find o pposite angle 
 
() ()    =  +  =0090 90 90 90 cosicos cos sin sincosLcos cosL
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 33 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 5 of 9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Exam ple: Continuing from previ ous exam ple, 
 
= = = 0
E 28.5 407 /,'500 RR Lv msR Km  
 

=
+1tantan4071Vcos,   =0.87882 cosi cos 
     from  previous tabl e 1V
 
 
 0 030 060 090 0120 0150 0180 
 0 028.54 057.49 087.10 0117.49  0148.55  0180 
i 028.5 039.5 061.8 087.5 
()0
0113.9
66.1 ()041.4 ()028.5 
 
  retro-orbi ts (westward s) 
 Lecture 33 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 6 of 9   
030 060 090 
028.50  057.39   
039.4 061.7  
 
slightly different inclination 
 
 
In realit y, we probably requ ire the orbit  altitude, the orbit  inclination and then lau nch 
azimuth  must be calculated 
 
=cosicoscosL  =1cosicoscosL
  
+= =2
2
2211tancosL
cos cosi 
 
= =+2
1
2tan 1cosRVsin cosL
Vv cosi 
 
 
=2
21cosisin
cosL 
 
 
with 
 
=  +22
12
R RR
RV vsin vcosRR      += 11 tan tanR Vcos v Vsin 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>11.05R
R==  1.1 1.05 2 4 6 10 15.6 
/V
R 1.02041 1.046511.18164 1.28446 1.44868 1.49934 1.529781.53626
 
 
Effects of Earths Rotation     
 
(a)  reduction V
 
 
 
 
 =463/sec Rm  
 
  is launch  azimuth w.r.t  
 East  
 
 (0=, near-horizontal  
 launch) 
 
 1V = roc ket-im parted V 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Starting velocit y (abs.) is now 
 
()() ()  = + +22
11 12 v V RcosL V RcosLcos
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
So,  replaces  in previ ous formulation 1v1V
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 33 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 3 of 9</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Liquid Motors: Injection and Mixing (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_21/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 21: Liquid M otors: Injection and Mixing 
 
This is a v ery complex  issue, which continues to receive a great deal to research 
attention, due to its import ance for: 
 
(a) Performanc e, and 
(b) Stability of combu stion. 
 
The single-droplet models of the previous le cture only begin to  scratc h the surface  of 
this problem.  A recent rev iew by Sirignano is in cluded and recommen ded for readin g 
in order to appreci ate the curren t state of this topic. 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 21 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 1 of 1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Liquid Motors: Stability (High Frequency); Acoustics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_23/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Acoustic Ab sorbers: Resonators  
 
The sc hematic shows a device 
which is a variat ion on the 
Helmholtz Resonator co ncept. 
 
Consider first the half-
cycle du ring which flow is leav ing 
the resonator ( &gt;0). The 
pressure inside the resonator is 
PR, while at the en trance to the 
narrow inlet duct, it is 
m
21
2='
RRPP v, due to the 
(subso nic) accelerat ion towards  
the inlet. The den sity chan ges  
can be eq uated to 2c/ (c = 
speed of so und in the r esonator).  
 
 
The mass balance is then 
 
 
   
2
=RRVd Pmdtc       ( 1) 
 
and the momentum bal ance in the duct is  
 
   () ()='
ii RdALv APPdtc
v 
 
or, using , 
=i m A
 
   2
22
= i
RC
iA  mPPdt L Adm      (2) 
 
Consider n ext the other half-cycle, when the cav ity is filling (m&lt;0). The 
pressu re at the chamber- side of  the duct, which is now the flow inlet is 
(2 1
2= '
ccPP v), whereas that at the e xit of the d uct is now just PR. Eq. (1) still 
holds, whereas the mo mentum bal ance is now 
 
 
   2
22
= +i
RC
iA  mPPdt L Adm      (3) 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 13 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>A possi ble choi ce of geom etry is then to take a n inlet diameter of, say, 5mm, and a 
cavity vol ume 
 
 25 31340005 26310m 263cm4==  =RV. . . .2 
 
If this is shaped as a c ubic cavity, its side is about 3 cm. These dimensions are 
sketched  (roughly to  scale) below. 
 
 
 
As a fi nal note, remember that the 
lumped pa rameter  ideal ization 
used in the theory may not be very 
precise. Only sem i-quantitative 
accuracy  is to be expec ted, but the 
trends s hould be correct and  the 
analysis can be u sed for prelim inary 
design, to be refined th rough 
numerical si mulation or ph ysical 
testing. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
How man y acoustic dampers:  
 
 2 1
2
=+RR mv PV   =R 
 
 () 1
2
=+R R
Rd dPmv v Vdt dt   
=
imvA 
=
imvA 
 
With no  dissipation 
 
 (
= i
R CA dmP Pdt L)  
=i
RA dmPdt L  
iLmA
 
 
 2
=RRVd Pmdtc   2
=R
RdP cmdt V  2R
RVP
c 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 18 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>We now differentiate (2) and (3), and unify the two half-cycle momentum equati ons 
as 
 
   2
22


= 
i c R
imA dP dP dm dm
Ld t dt dt dt A 
 
Substi tuting Eq. (1) here, 
 
 
   2
2
2


++ =i i c
iRmA AdP dm dmcmLA dt LV Ldt dt    (4) 
 
 
This equ ation is non-linear in  , but we can obta in reasonable results for  steady 
state operation if we replace 
m

m by its time average over  one cycle. T he analysis 
reduces t hem to t hat of a forced  linear oscillator, except that m needs to  be 
calculated self-consistently rather than being a  prescribed quantity. 
 
 
                       
  
 
 
Assume solutions of the form 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 14 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>(13) i nto (10): 
 
 
  + =+   vp' ' M' p 'cT qttpM t11 1
t  
== gp' RTR TM p 
 
 
()  
v Tc+= + + vv
ggM'/MR' cp' cq ptt t MR R 
 
      pc 
 
 
()  = +   pM'/M'p ' pqtt cT11
11
t     ( 14) 
 
 
Sub. Into  (8) 
 
()  + + =  pM'/Mp' p u'qtt cT11
11 mx    (15) 
 
Differenti ate w.r. t. t: 
 
()    + + =   pM'/Mp' q p u' m
tx tt cT22
2211
11 t t2
    (16) 
 
 
but, from 1 2,   22
2= + u' p' f
xtx x       substitute in (16) 
 
 
()    + +=    pM'/Mp' q p p' f m
tx tt x cT222
22 211
11 t   (17) 
 
 
Now ()21 == g pcT RT c  (c=speed of sound)    (18) 
 
 
()()2222 2
221    = +  '/p' p' fcc m qp ctt tx
x   (19) 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 6 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>Using 2
222
22 
 + = +   i i
Ri RmmcA cAiLV LA LV LA2
i , this yields a bi- quadratic 
equati on for  
m in terms of  the amplit ude 
cP of the pressure fl uctuations in the 
chamber. T he algebra is simpler in  non-dimensi onal terms. Define 
 
 
 =R
niLV
cA        ( 12) 
 
 
22
1
2
c
R
iPV
LAc
        ( 13) 
 
 
We then  obtain () ()2 222
2 42 2 1m1 1224  = ++     i
RcApV , and substituting in 
(10), the  damping ratio is 
 
 
() ()22
2
2422 22
11=
+ +p/
p      ( 14)   
4 
 
 
Several points can now be made: 
 
(a) For any frequency, the dampin g increases w ith pressu re fluctuation intensity. 
This is a fa vorable circu mstance be cause we need the damping most when 
combusti on is rough.  Mathemati cally, t his is a consequence  of the non-
linearity of the equ ation. Physically, energy is d issipated both d uring 
aspiration and d uring e xpulsion of gas from t he cavi ty, (by the mixing out  of 
the jet kine tic energy), and it is clear that more energy is dissipated when the 
driving pressure differences are str onger. 
 
(b) Although the algebra is  still tedious, differentiation of (14) shows that  is 
maximum at =1, i.e., when the cavi ty is tuned in resonance wi th the 
pressure fluctuations (by selecting parameters so tha t n=). Putting =1 
in (14) gives 
2 1
22
==c
R
MAX
iPVp/LA c
             (15) 
 
which again sho ws  increasin g with fluctuation in tensity. 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 16 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>()2
222
200    +=  +       R
R RR
i iP dL dLmV c c m V PdtA dtA c =  
 
  ()
()2
22
2
2
222 22
+ == +RR
i R
R R
iLcm V PA V LmPA cc
  
 
 
With dissipation 
 
 
 2


=
i
R
immA dmPdt L A

  2 
icLmA 
 
 ()2
=R
RdP cmdt V   RRVP 
 
 
 
()2
2 2
2
2 2222
+    = RR
i
idLcm V P mdtA
m
cA

 (energy dissipat ion rate) R 
 
 
Average  3
222

=R
im
A    mm
 
=2 
 
 
At resonance, 

=i
cAmPL   2
=ii
cLA AP
mm 
 
 
   22
=i
cAmP
m  2 2
=ic mA P 
 
 
  3 32 322
2
2212 12
2 2 ==   / /
i
Ric c
iAAP P
A  
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 19 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Fig 1. An n- diagram, sho wing instabi lity zones fo r various m odes. 
 
 
Here are sh own the loci of  margin al stability for severe modes of  a combu stor, 
on a map of in teraction index n vs. sensitive lag . Each point on one of t he lines 
corresponds  to a par ticular oscillation freq uency , and these frequenci es are found  to 
be within 10% of the undisturbed acoustic fre quency of the mode. The goal of the 
designer i s to mani pulate the factors influenci ng n and 
 in order to place the 
operat ing poin t outside all t he stable reg ions of the various modes.  
 
The parameters  and n (into which is lumped t he modif ying effects of 
velocity or ot her sensitivities) are basical ly empirical, and a large data base has been 
laboriously accumulated on their dependenci es upo n many design factors. As  an 
example, Figs. 2(a ) and 2(b) (Ref. 26) s how data on 
 for coax ial injectors, for 
which n 0.5 throughout. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 2 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>For a si nusoidal wave of the type 
 
         ( 25) () it kx
e p'(t)Rpe=

 
with  compl ex and  k real, we t hen have 
 
222 
+ = pk cpiQ
         ( 26) 
 
 
Define   1
2
 =iQ;h
kc kcp       ( 27) 
 
 
and re-write (26) as  h+=221 0     ( 28) 
 
 
which has the complex  solution  21=+ h h    (29) 
 
 
We now  ask what form h should have for s tability. First, we note t hat at the 
stability thr eshold ,  is real, and so () h / =21 2 must  also be real . From (27),  
this means that iQ must be in phase  (or counter -phase) with  
p, namel y, volume 
addition rate mus t be 90o ahead o f or behind  pressure os cillations: 
 
 
 
 
 
More generally, re -write (28) as  h+=12 0, and put explicitly , RI hh ih=+
RIi =+ : 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 8 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>2222++ + =
+RI
RI R I
RIiih ih
i
0      ( 30) 
Separate real and imaginary parts: 
 
 
2220+ =
+R
RR
RIh
 
        ( 31) 
2220++ =
+I
II
RIh
 
 
 
From (31b),  II
RIh
i
= ++2 21 112
      ( 32) 
 
 
This sho ws that whene ver , Ih&gt;0I&lt;0. Since 0= &lt; IRti t it
I p' e e e ,   
implies in stability. Also, from (27b),  implies Ih&gt;0
RQ
p

&gt;
0, which mean s that the 
volume ad dition rate Q(t) m ust have a positive projection on pressure p(t) , 
namely, a part  in-phase with it. This is a conf irmat ion of the phy sical in tuition that 
releasing volume when pressu re is h igh must be de-stabi lizing. We r epeat that this 
may mean heat addition, ga s addition (vaporization) or  molecu lar ma ss redu ction 
rate (decomposition of  complex molecules). 
 
Let us  now consider briefl y the ef fect of  body  forces f. Returning to (19) and  
defining the  compl ex quanti ty. 
 
  if
kp
=         ( 33) 
 
we can see that (28) is expanded to the form 
 
  () h  + =221 0       ( 34) 
 
For neutral  condi tions (stability thr eshold), we  must  have real I(= 0), so, 
taking the imaginary part of (34), 
 
  IIh+= 2 0
I        ( 35) 
 
In the abse nce of  force s, we fou nd that  would lead t o instabil ity. We see n ow 
that if Ih&gt;0
I h =2, which is negative, then the proce ss stabilizes at least to the point 
of neutral stabil ity. From (33), the con clusion is that 
Rf
p

&lt;
0 is stabil izing, i.e., the 
body forces  should be  in the bac kwards di rection (agai nst H velocity) when  press ure 
is high, and vice-versa.   
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 9 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 23: Liquid M otors: Stability (High Frequen cy); Ac oustics 
 
 
Combu stion Instabili ty: Hi gh Fr equency  
 
Methods of  Analysis for High  Frequen cy Instabilities 
 
Prior to the advent of large- scale computations, the mos t successful 
theoretical developmen t in this area w as the sensitive time lag theory of  L. Crocco 
[26]. More than a det ailed ph ysical t heory, this was a model in  which a few basic 
parameters were introduced from i ntuitive considerat ions, and then used t o correlat e 
experimental observations on stabi lity th resholds. T he principal parameter was the 
sensitive time lag,  during which the various rates which eventually resulted in 
vapori zation at the total time lag T after i njection were ass umed to vary with 
pressure, veloc ity, stoichiometry, etc. T his variation was characterized by means of 
other import ant paramet er, the sensitivity index. For pressu re sen sitivity, this is 
 
()RatesnP=ln
ln      ( 1) 
 
and the defi nition of  is such  that the vari ations in gas ge neration rate due to this 
sensitivity are giv en locally by 
 
   mm Pt Ptnt Pm 
 =='()'()    (2) 
 
Similar sen sitivity indices can be in trodu ced for velocity, etc. Once this paramet erization 
is accept ed, it is on ly a matter of mathematical modelin g to obtain the stability limits of 
a given acou stic wave or cav ity. This modelin g cou ld be lin ear or ev en allow  for non-
linear ities in the gas dynamics. It i s one of th e streng ths of this theory  that the acoustic 
part of the problem, namely, combustor ge ometry, steady state combustion and heat 
release, etc. are separated from the unste ady combusti on effects,  which allows fo r 
generalization of test results and accu mulation of mean ingful stability data. 
 
The resu lts of calcu lations using the linear sen sitive time lag theory are 
displayed as sho wn in Fig. 1 (Ref. 26). 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 1 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Starting with the early of Priem and Gu entert [29], these methods have been 
progressively replaced by detailed numeric al time-dependent si mulations of  the 
combustion process. T he complexit y of these processes is such that, even now these 
simulations still contain large e lements of modelin g and approx imation, and are 
generally limited to one or t wo select ed spat ial dimen sion plus time. 
 
A recent example of this approach is de scribed in Ref. 30 . Here the emphasi s 
is on the tangential acou stic modes.  A det ailed 2- D fluid mech anical model ( in the 
transverse plane) is coupled to a s eries of empi rically derived droplet vaporization 
laws for U DMH and  N2O4. The flow i s turbulent, modeled using a K-  approx imation, 
and the dro ps are allowed to slip, exerting drag forces which are com puted from 
empirical drag coeffi cients, and also modi fying the vapori zation rates due to 
convecti ve heat tra nsfer. The drop- heating transients are ignored. The computati ons 
yield det ailed time histories of  all the fluid paramet ers, and comparison s to limited 
test data  on parametri c effects o f pressure and  injector type  are found to be 
favorabl e. 
 
A simi lar compu tation, but for longitudinal modes on ly, is described in  Ref. 27. 
Here t he spat ial depen dence is on  one dimen sion only (axial), but the droplet  
interactions are calcu lated in somew hat more detail, including drop th ermal in ertia. 
These calcu lations show st rongest instability when the ratio of the acou stic period t o 
the dropl et vapori zation time is 0.15, w hich, as noted before, can be  interpreted as 
indicating a sen sitive ti me lag which is a frac tion (0.1- 0.2) of the total vapori zation 
time. The c alculations also show c ases of  entropy wa ve excitation, fo r which the 
frequenc y corresponds closely to t he convective time in  the chamber. 
 
In what follows, we pro vide a si mplified anal ysis of the aco ustic effec ts of 
several com bustion-related phe nomena (heat release, mas s additi on, etc.), and then 
use this in conjunction with Croccos t heory f or an assessmen t of stability in a simple 
1-D situation. Some gen eral con clusions abou t stability and dest ability effects are 
also drawn from the a coustic analysis. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 4 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 3 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>Average chamber  acoustic energy 2
2
=c
ccP
V
c

 
 
 
()32 2
2
3211 2 2
22 2 2
== = ii R
I / ch.
c ccccAN A NcNcVP VP     
 
 contribution of I of 
chamber, d ue to N 
resonators 
Also, ()()==i
nncR
RAcLV  
 
 
()2
31
2==I i c
c
ncNAcV
 1
cPc
 2
31
2=R
Ri
ic
cLV NcLVAAVP
 
 
 
22 000Hz =   4
2612510 1
120 1.21.2510==
cP .
c
 Exam ple 
 
   37210m=L.5326310m=RV.622510m4=iA 
 
and say  3V0 1m=c .
 
1
2=
c
35 67210 26310 2510 120 2710N01 4   =N.. ..5 
 
 
So,for c .=01, need 3730 dam pers. 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 20 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Control of Instabilities 
 
Despi te all efforts at  avoidance thr ough design, the need r emains for devices 
that will help damp th e many potential modes of instability in any given  rocket 
combustor.  A new  technology for a ctive control is n ow evolving [31], in which 
feedback co ntrolled acoustic gener ators are used to cancel unstab le waves. Since the 
growth can be detected  at small amplitude,  it may not be necessary to inject very 
large acoustic powers for this purpose.  Nevertheless, the mainstay of current 
practice is based on pas sive damping methods . A good desc ription of these method s, 
with design guidelines, is given in Ref. 32. 
 
The most import ant high frequency stabilization devices are in jector head 
baffles and acoustic ab sorbers. Baffles are radial or circumferential barriers attached 
to the injector head an d extending 0.1-0.2 diamet ers in  the axial dir ection. An 
exampl e of a baffl ed injector i s that of the SSME (Fig. 3, from Ref. 2 ). The exact  
mech anism by which baffles en hance stability is not well understood, which has led 
to some divergence in design . It appears t hat the effect is relat ed to the sen sitivity 
of the droplet velocity cross-over p oint, wh ich occurs quite close to the injector face, 
and it may involve disruption of the tange ntial gas moti on associ ated wi th tangential 
modes, or s hifting of the local  acou stic frequencies t o values above the characteristic 
drop vaporization frequencies. 
 
Acoustic ab sorbers are cavities on th e chamber w alls with relat ively narrow 
connecting  channels to the chamber, so as to dissipate powe r during pressure 
oscillations in their vicinity. Their action is much better understood th an that of 
baffles, and  designers c an proceed with so me confidence, using methods described, 
for example in  Ref. 32. Absorbers are of ten locat ed on the cylindrical walls, near the 
injector, or as corner slots betwe en injector and c ylinder. The y can also take th e 
form of a continuous do uble wall with a n array of holes periodica lly arranged to 
connect to the chamber . The absor ption co efficient of a well-des igned absorber can 
be high ove r a relatively wi de freq uency band , so as  to contribute d amping to the 
most prevalent modes. Sometimes several different absorbers are used, each tuned 
to a di fferent frequenc y. Fig. 4 (Ref. 32)  shows a baffled injector wi th corner 
absorbers, and Fig. 5  (Ref. 32) s hows an exte nded acoustic liner. 
 
A simplif ied analysis of an acoustic absorber is described next. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 12 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Looking at one instant of time vs. distance: 
 
 
 
 
So, the bod y forces are  in quadrat ure with the pressure gr adient force ( ), and  
are taki ng energy a way from t he wave moti on. P
 
 
The  Sensitive time lag theory  (Harrje and Reardon, p.1) 
 
Basic scenario: 
 
- Drops injected at Tt complete evapor ation and combustion at 
 
- However, fr om Tt to t, no complet e evaporat ion occurs, on ly 
precursor processes. sensi tive lag. 
 
- The rate of evaporatio n + combus tion duri ng  is sensitive to pressure and/or 
velocity. For p, () lnratesnlnP      ( 1) 
(n= sensi tivity index) . 
 
- The d uration  of actual evap. + comb. change s in time, in respon se to t hese 
rate chan ges. However,  the total mass bu rnt is that of the drop, and it is 
assumed their mass (and their nu mber) are independent of P,  in the 
chamber. 
 
 
Say, R  is the relevant rate. Under quiet or mean co nditions, RR=. When PP, 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 10 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>=it
e mR me,  =   it
Re R PR Pe ,etc.    (5) 
 
Eq. (4) becomes 
 
 
 22



 + + =
i
c
iRmA Aic m i pLA LV Li       (6) 
 
while Eq. (1) gives 
 
  
2

=R
RViP
c
m       ( 7) 
 
and sol ving (6) and (7) together, 
 
 
  2
2
2
=
+i
R R
c
i
RicA
P LV
P mcAiLV LA

      ( 8) 
 
From thi s, the natural frequency  of the oscillations is seen to be =i
n
RAcLV  (9) 
and the da maging factor  is given by 
2
=n
im
LA , or 
2
=R
iim
LV
LA c A    (10) 
 
 
For the rectifi ed sine wave (t), we can see th at 
m2
 
=mm, and from (7) a nd (8), 
 
 
 2
22
2
222 
==
+i
RR R
R c
i
RicA
VV LVmP
cc
mcAiLV LAP  
   (11) 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 15 of 21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>()()()()22222
21511      +=+     p'u' p' q mCT c c p x xt x x tx x
  (20) 
 
 
22
2(9)  + u' p' f
tx t=t t    (21) 
 
 
Subtract, di vide by : 
 
()()
     =  +     M'Mu' u' fcc m qptx t tx2222
22111    (22) 
 
Note the combin ation ()()
+M'M
cm qpt21  
 
 
Adding heat , addi ng ma ss, or having a decr ease rat e of molecu lar ma ss, all are ( up 
to factors ) equivalent acoustic disturbances. 
 
To close the  probl em, one needs to relate the perturbati ons (m , q, f, '
t
) to 
the sta te variables ( p',',u',T' ), by looking at t he particular mech anisms 
(vapori zation, comb ustion, etc ), and how they depend on pressure, veloc ity, and  so 
on. 
 
 
General C onditions for Instability 
 
Looking at Eq. (19), we see that  the effect s of gas mas s generati on m, heat  
generation q and  molecular mass change '/
t  are simi lar. All of them have the 
effect of increasin g the local volume, and we suspect therefor e that when these 
quanti ties (acting toget her) peak when the pre ssure also p eaks, we wi ll have 
unstable
 condition. 
 
To exami ne this, define the quantity 
 
 ()()
=+ M'M
Qc m qpt21       ( 23) 
 
and ignore f or now  the local disturbing forces f.  Then 
 
 222
2 2 = p' p' Qct tx        ( 24) 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 23 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez              Page 7 of 21</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Rocket Nozzles and Thrust (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Define 
 
 
x
=
irAe
euudA
u
m
 ;  x
x= eeAe
e
ePdA
PA 
 
and use  
 
2sin=dA r rd   
 
For ideal co nical flow, ,,ruP  are constant over eA. Then 
 
2 2
0
01cos sin 2sincos2
1cos2sin== = 
 rAee rr
rAeud A rd
uu u
ud A rd
   
   
 
or  
     
1cos
2+=eruu 
  
 
Also, since const  on the exit surf ace,  =eP =eePP  
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 2 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 3 of 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>In general then, define x
=
ne
Aee
ne
AeuudA
u
udA
 
 
 and  = x
xee
Aee
ePdA
PA 
 
 
() = +i
x ea e e Fm u PPA  
 
 
If things are nearl y constan t on spherical caps, modi fy control volume to 
spherical wedge: 
 
 
 
 
 
=i
r
AemudA 
 
 
() () ()x x
int.
.  =    ax e a e r
AAeesolidsPPdS PPdA uudA  
 
  ==x xcos coserdA dA uu  
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 2 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 2 of 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>() ()() xx x +  =   ae a n
A A eePPdA PPdA udAu  
..ss
  
         F 
 
()x=+ i
ea e e Fm u PPA 
 
 
=i
nAemudA 
 
 
x
=
nAe
e
nAeuudA
u
udA
 
 
 
x
x=
eAe
e
AePdA
P
dA 
 
xx=AeAd A
aP 
 
At design, P  (and paralle l flow beyond). Also  =e xeu
Then un iform  =i
exFm u
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 2 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 4 of 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Prop ulsion,  
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 2: Rocket Nozzles and Thrust 
 
 
Rocket Thrust (Thermal rockets) 
 
 
 
 
 
=i
ne
Aemu dA
e
Solid A A eesurfacesPdS PdA uudA
=
ne 
 
 
  () = xx x
int.ee n
(Tanks included)      dm i
 
 
Note:  so subtract, x x.,int,aa es
AePdS PdA 0
 
 
() () xx x
int.=  +    ae a e
Solid A A eePPdS PPdA uudA  
 
 
 Thrus t F 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion   Lecture 2 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez   Page 1 of 7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Combustion of Liquid Propellants (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_20/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>In a fuel- rich en vironment, vapor from a f uel dropl et diffuses without 
reacting into the surrounding gas, wh ile heat diffuses inwards t o supply the latent 
heat of  evaporation. In the same envi ronment,  vapor from  an oxi dizer drop 
comes in contact, and r eacts with the fu el-rich gas at some  distance fr om the 
droplet, formi ng a sph erical flame, from  which heat  diffuses both  ways, while 
reaction products diff use outwards and also sta gnate in layer arou nd the droplet . 
A simi lar de script ion appli es to a locally  oxydizing env ironment. It will be 
sufficient to anal yze, for exampl e the case of  a fuel drop i n an ox ydizing 
environment, from which we can easily  derive other cases by suitable re-
interpretations. 
 
As a prelim inary, some relationships will be der ived between the overall 
stoichiometry (oxi dizer/fuel  ratio, or OF, by m ass), a nd the mass frac tions of 
products  and excess o xidizer or fuel  to be fou nd in the burnt gas far from the 
droplets. Let t he actual mass rati o be OF, a nd the stoi chiometri c mass fracti on be 
OFs (later call ed i for short),  Assuming excess oxidizer, and complete combustion 
(a roug h assumpti on), the reacti on can be mas s balanced as 
 
 
1 (Fuel) + OF (Oxi dizer)    (1+OF s) (Products) + (OF-OF s) (Oxidizer) 
 
 
and so the mass f raction of excess ox idization at infinity is 
 
 
ss
ox,
ssOFOF OFOFY(1OF)(OFOF)1OF==++  + 
 
 
Similarly, for fuel-rich operat ion, 
 
 
1
OF (Fuel) + I (oxidizer) ()
ss11 11P roducts (FOF OFOF  + +   
  uel) 
 
 
and the mass fracti on of excess fuel at infinity is 
 
 
s
F,
s11
OFOFY
11OF
=
+
s11
OF OF
+ ()s
sOF OF
1OFOF=+ 
  
 
 
which could be al so form ally obtai ned from   OX,Y  by reversing the  roles of fuel 
and oxidizer (including 1OFOF ) 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 20 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                  Page 2 of 1 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Impose also  ,  solve for ()ox F Yr r0==
Fr: 
 
ox,
FYln1r=+
 i
       (6) 
 
                    
 
which is a relat ionship bet ween  and rF (rF turns out to be proporti onal to , 
i.e., a blow ing effect) 
 
The distribution of both, mass fluxes and mass fractions ar e displayed below: 
 
 
 
 
We now  need the heat flux bal ance, both inside and o utside the flame: 
 
R &lt; r &lt;r F  -  Taking T = Tv as the (temporary) enthalpy zero, the  conv ected  heat 
flow inside the flame, where only fuel vapor moves, i s ()p v cT T . The cond uctive 
flow is 2dT4rkdr , The total, flowing inw ard (negative) is used at r = R to vaporize 
liquid, at L (latent heat) per unit m ass: 
 
()2
prdTcT T4rk Ldr  =     (7) 
 
 
()()p
vC dT LTTd1r4k 4k + =      (8) 
 
                  again 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 20 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                  Page 5 of 1 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>()
FpF v r
F
pQL cTTTT e 1c
  =     (14) 
 
 
which is t he needed ex tra relat ionship to complemen t (6) and (10) 
 
Eqs. (10) an d (14) can be simplif ied if 
Fr is subs tituted from  (6): 
 
R
Fv
ox, pLeTT 1Y c1i


 = 
+     (10) 
 
 
()pF v ox,
F
pQL cTTYTTc i
 =     (14) 
 
 
Eliminate TF  between these two equations: 
 
 
 
        R
v
ox, pLe QLT1 TY c1i


+ =
+R
ox, ppLe1Y cc1i

+ox,Y
i 
 
 
    
 
 
R
p ox,Le
c Y1i
+ox,Y1i+
ox,
v
ppYQLTTci c
 = ++    (15) 
 
 
Solve for R, and use pc
4k=: 
 
 
ox, p v
pQY ic(TT) 4kRln1c L +  = +

    (16) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 20 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                  Page 7 of 1 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Other cases  
 
 
For a fuel drop in a fuel-rich background , everyt hing is the same if  we make 
Q=0 (no flame), and, of course, ignore  and FrFT. In fact, the only equation 
needed is the  heat flow balance ( Eq. 9), w hich, usingFrr&lt; T() T=, gives   
 
R
v
pLTT e 1c
 =  
 
and so, f inally 
 
()pvcT Tln1RL  =+ 
 
 
or  ()
p4kRln1Bc= +    (as in (17 )), 
with 
 
pc(TT)BL=v     (23) (F/FCase)
 
 
Again,  this is as in (18) if Q=0.  
 
So, the fuel drop evapo rates faster if it is in an oxidiz ing environment  (larger 
B). The reason,  clearly,  is the extra heat ing from the nearly f lame in that  case. 
 
For an oxidiz er drop in  an oxidiz ing background  (0/0), we have a very  similar 
situation (no flame) , so, once  again, ox is given by (17 ), with B given b y (23), 
but now  and L m ust be reinterpreted to be  those for the o xidizer l iquid. vT
 
Finally, for an oxidiz er drop in a fuel-r ich background , we return to the first case 
(fuel drop in oxidiz ing gas), and switch the roles of  fuel and oxidiz er throughout .  
For, example, Q must be the heat of reaction per unit oxidizer mass,  must 
be replaced  by ,  becomes ox,Y
f,Y st. i(O/F)= 1i, and  refer t o the oxidiz ing 
liquid. v(T,L)
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 20 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                  Page 11 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>In the literature, this is written as 
 
 
p4kRln1Bc= +       (17) 
 
 
with   B   ()ox, p v QY icTT
L +       (18)    
 
(the Spau lding parameter) . 
 
We have sol ved for , and can go ba ck to (6) to get the  flame radius 
 
               
()
F
ox,ln1BrRYln1i+=
 +
      (19) 
 
 
and to  (10) to get  TF. From (15), (18), Rl1B=+, and then, from ( 10), 
 
 
ox,
Fv
po x,BY i LTTc1 Yi
=++     (20) 
 
 
            
 
 
 
  
                
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 20 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                  Page 8 of 1 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>2vx
2u=. 
 
 
As an example, f or the middle graph 00.5= , so using O/F = 0 in Eq. (38) 
we cal culate ()2
2vL10.50.60.52u 21.5= =  or 20.267 = . This coincides 
with the result in the figure. 
 
 
Notice how the droplet s are in itially slowed do wn by gas d rag, but later, as 
the gas  evolves and  accelerate, the y are pulled along. Nea r the e nd of 
vapori zation, the rates  accel erate, because the droplets are so light. 
 
 
 
 
 
Evolution of evaporating droplet size  and velocity. Here the reference  for 
velocity is that of  the gas after co mplete evaporation, and for length,  refv
ref refv l2 v=
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 20 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                  Page 15 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>and write (33) as 
32d1 O/F
bd 1O/F += ++     (35) 
 
 
This is a linear, first-orde r equation for (), although with non-con stant 
coefficients. It ca n be integrated by standard m ethods, like  paramet er variat ion. 
Imposing () ()0
oD
DD
2u
ut 0u,or 1 ,u== ==  the solution is found  to be 
 
 
b3 Dou 2b 2b112 (32b)(1O/F) (32b)(1O /F) =+ +   + + 2
 (36) 
 
 
One more in tegration will yield the vaporiz ation length: 
 
 
()v 1
D2 v
00Lu dtu d
==         (37) 
 
 
After simplif ication, this gives t he result 
 
 
Do
2v 2u L1 251u1 bu 1O/F =+   + +b
     (38) 
 
 
 
Notice that , from  (22) and (32 ), the param eter b can  be written as 
 
 
()()
()2
gp lp 0 v
2
Rel l0
gc/k cR 19b2kln1B 4ln1B R2
9  == =+ 
+ 
 
or  rP9b4ln(1B)=+      (39) 
 
For B=30 a nd Pr=0.8, this gives b =0.52. 
 
 
Spaulding d efined a related parameter 2b= and presented res ults for the 
monopropell ant case. We can red uce to that case by se tting O/F=0 . Result are 
shown in the next figure for 0.5=  (b = 0.25). The  parameter 0 is 0D
2u
u, and 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 20 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                  Page 14 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>References-Cont . 
 
18. R.D. Sutto n, W.S . Hines and  L.P. Combs,  Development a nd Applica tion of a  
Compre hensive Analysis of Liquid Rocket Co mbustio n, AIAA JI., Vol. 10, no . 
2, Feb. 197 2, pp. 194 203. 
 
19. P-Y Liang, S . Fisher and Y.M. Chang,  Comprhe nsive Model ling of Liquid 
Rocke t Combustion Chamber. J. of Propulsion, Vo l. 2, no.2, March-Ap ril 
1986, pp  97-104. 
 
20. M.S. Raju a nd W. A Sirignano,  Multicomponen t Spray  Computatio ns in a 
Modified  Centerbody Combustor , J. Propul sion Vol. 6, No . 2, pp 97 -105, 
March-A pril 1990. 
 
21. F.A. Williams, Combustion Theory , Benjam in/Cum mings P ublishing Co., Inc., 
2nd Ed., 1985. 
 
22. W.A. Sirignano,  Fuel Droplet Vap orization  and Spray  Combustion Theory, 
Progress in Energy and Combustion Science , Vol. 9, 1983, pp.291 -322. 
 
23. D.B. Spauld ing, Aero. Q uarterly, 10 , 1. (1959). See also Ref. 21, Sec. 11.15. 
 
24. H.H. Chiu, H.Y. Kim and E. J. Croke,Internal G roup Co mbustion of liquid 
Droplets , Proc. 19th International Sy mposium on Combustion, 1983. 
 
25. P.Y. Liang , R.J. Jens en and Y.M. Chang,  Numerical A nalysis of SS ME 
Preburner Injector Ato mization and C ombustion Process . J. of Propulsion , 
Vol. 3, No. , Nov-Dec.1 987, pp . 508-514. 
 
26. D.T. Harrje and F .H. Re ardon (Editors). Liquid Propellan t Rock et Combustion 
Instability, NASA S P-194, 1972. 
 
27. R. Bhatia a nd W.A. Sirignano,  One dime nsion al Analysis of Liq uid-Fueled 
Comb ustion Instab ility, J. of Propulsion, Vol 7, No. 6 , Nov-Dec. 1991, pp 
953-961. 
 
28. G.A. Flandro, Vorte x Driving Mechanism in Oscillator y Rocket Flo ws, J. of 
Propulsion, Vol. 2, No. , May-June 1986, pp . 206-214. 
 
29. R.J. Priem and D.C. G uentert, Combustion Instabili ty Limits Determi ned by a 
Non linear T heory an d a One-di mensional Mode l. NASA  TND-1409, Oct. 
1962. 
 
30. M. Habiballa, D. Lo urme and F . Pit. PHEDRE-Numerica l Model for 
Comb ustion Stabil ity Studies A pplied to t he Ariane Vik ing Engine. J. 
Propulsion, Vol. 7, no . 3, Ma y-June 1991, 322 -329. 
 
31. T. Poinsot, F. Bourienne, S. Candel an d E. Esposit o, Suppression of 
Comb ustion Instab ilities by Act ive Control . J. Propulsion, Vol.5, No. 1, Jan-
Feb. 1989, pp. 14 -19. 
 
32. NASA S P-8113, Liquid Rocket Comb ustion S tabilization Devices , Nov. 1974. 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 20 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                  Page 16 of 16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 20: Combus tion of Liqui d Propell ants 
 
 
Simplifi ed Drop-Wise Liquid Combu stion Theory  
 
 
1. Introducti on 
 
In this lect ure w e examine in more depth the fluid phenom ena which 
dominate th e operati on, and hence  the de sign, of a liquid rocket. We  start by 
considerin g the two phase aspect s of combu stion, which usu ally determine the 
combu stor size. Next we ex amine the stability of combu stor operat ion and th e 
design  modif ication required t o achiev e it. Heat  transfer to walls, wall 
compat ibility and wall cool ing form the next topic. We conclu de with some 
notions in nozzle aerodynami c design a nd nozzle  optimization. 
 
 
2. Drop Vaporization an d Spray Combu stion 
 
Returni ng to Fig. 12.1  (lecture 12) , we note a gain the exi stence of  a zone A C 
where the propellants go from a se ries of  liquid jets issu ing through a mu ltiplicity 
of small in jector holes, through break up of these jet s into droplet s, impin gemen t 
(in some designs) of jets or  droplet streams on each other, dispersion of the 
droplets into a recirculating mass of combustion products, evaporation of the  
droplet s, interdiffusion of the vapors an d kinetically controlled combu stion. These 
are obviously complicated processes, and a comprehensive analysis good enough 
for first pri nciples desi gn requi res large-scal e computati on [18, 19 , 20]. In fact, 
the largest number of  existing liquid rocket co mbustors,  those dati ng from befor e 
1970, were developed mainly through empi rical methods, suppl emented by very 
extensive te sting. Improved modeling an d com putational c apabilities have more 
recently permitted a more direct approach, with fe wer hardware iterations, but 
theory is still far from complet ely developed in  this area,  and serv es at this poin t 
mainly to ascertai n trends a nd verify me chanisms. For a n in-depth discussion o f 
liquid propell ant combust ion, see Ref s. 21 an d 22. Here w e will only review the 
fundamen tal concepts which un derlie current spray comb ustion mod els. 
 
 
2.1 Singl e-Drop Combust ion  
                                                   
Even wh en liquids are origin ally injected into the chamber,  actual combu stion 
takes place in the gas phase, follow ing vapo rization of both, ox idizer and fuel. In 
fact, vaporization is usually the ratec ontrolling step in the whole process, 
although  its rate i s itself af fected b y the reacti ons occ urring near each dropl et. In 
a few ins tances, both pr opellants enter the chamber as ga ses or easily vaporized  
liquids, and then gas ph ase mix ing is the limiting step. (An example is the  Shuttl e 
SSME, where the hydro gen is vapo rized in the cooling circuit, and the oxygen  is 
partially vaporized by the hydrogen in a co-fl owing heat exchanger arrangement 
ahead of the injectors, the rest being atomize d and evaporated shor tly after 
injection). 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 20 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                  Page 1 of 1 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Imposing T(R) = T v , this integrates  to 
 
 
T - Tv= 11
Rr
pLec
1
      (9) 
 
 
and, in particular, at r = rF 
 
 
TF - T v = f11
Rr
pLe 1c
 
      (10)  
 
                
 
which also relat es  to r F, but also introduces TF , the flame temperature, 
as a th ird un known. We w ill need the heat flux balan ce for r &gt; r F to co mplete the 
formulation. For this purpose, we now move the enthalpy zero to T=T F, the flame 
temperature. The total heat fl ow (convecti on plus diffusive) is now (in)
 
()2
pFdTcT T4rkdr     
 
and this must be the heat released at  the flame front , minus the heat sent 
inwards fro m the flame to t he liquid. T he form er is Q (Q= heat of combustion 
per unit fuel mass). The  latter woul d be L, except for the extra  
due to the change o f enthalpy refer ences. Al together, ()pF v cT T 
 
() (2
pF p F vdTcT T4rk QLcTTdr)     =    (11) 
 
 
or  ()() ()p
Fpc dTTT QLcTTd1r4k 4k 
F v  + =     (12) 
 
 
Integrating with ()T=T as a boundary  condition, 
 
 
()()pF vrr
F F
pQL cTTTT 1e TTec  
 = + 
   (13) 
 
and part icularizing at r = rF  (T=TF), 
 
 
 
  
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 20 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                  Page 6 of 1 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Consi der a spheri cal fuel droplet of radi us R a nd densi ty l. Its rate of  
vapori zation is 
 
2dR4Rdt =  
 
and the main  purpose of  the analysis is t he calcu lation of  from  given R and  gas 
properties. Let  by the mass fracti ons of fuel and of com bustion 
products  in the regi on R &lt; r &lt; rFl  between the drop and the flame location (no  
oxidizer is t o be found there, so Yf + Ypr = 1). These two constituents are both 
convected by the mean outwards fl ow, and diffuse according to  their  ()()f pr Yr,Yr
concentrati on gradi ents. Since the product s do not penet rate the dro p surface, 
the net ou tflow of f uel at radi us r is equal  to the total  mass flow, and is given by  
 
2 f
ffdYY4 rDdr = 
 
where  is the diffusivity in the products. The net flux of products  remain zero i n 
this region (but not their concen trationfD
pr f Y1 Y=). Imposi ng that  approaches 
zero at the flame radiu s, the above equation integrates to  fY
 
f
Fl11
rr
fY1 e=  (R &lt; r &lt; rFl) 
 
 
where                
 
()f
f 4D= 
 
and the pro duct fD is taken to be  constan t. 
 
 
While this gives information abou t the composit ion of the gas n ear the 
droplet , the more impo rtant results come f rom a simi lar mass balan ce outside th e 
flame radi us (r &gt; rF). 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                                  Le cture 20 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                  Page 3 of 1 6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Selection of Propellant Mixtures (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-512-rocket-propulsion-fall-2005/resources/lecture_15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>16.512, Rocket Propulsion 
Prof. Man uel Martinez-Sanchez 
Lecture 1 5: Selecti on of Pr opellant Mi xtures 
 
 
Solid Propellant Rocket Fundament als 
 
Solid Propellants Rocke ts 
 
Read Sutton c h.11  basic performance 
 
Surface regression rate , empi rically correl ated to gas  pressure as  r

 
n
c rap
=           n ct
pc b *PAma PA
c
= =  
(n &lt; 1)        
1
1n
* b
cp
dAPa cA =
   n&lt;1 for stability 
 
                                                                               
              
 
                     
             
 
 
 Booster m otor  
 
 
 
 
 
 Space Engin e (IUS) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 Tactic al motor  
 
 
 
 
 
 
16.512, Rocket Propuls ion                                                                             Lecture 15 
Prof. Manuel  Martinez-Sanchez                                                                                 Page 1 of 2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
