<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/res-15-003-shaping-the-future-of-work-15-662x-spring-2016/</course_url>
    <course_title>Shaping the Future of Work (15.662x)</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Economics </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Public Administration </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction: Challenges and Opportunities as You Enter the Workforce</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/res-15-003-shaping-the-future-of-work-15-662x-spring-2016/resources/mitres_15_003s16_chapter1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>10 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
Trends in job satisfaction also track this breakdown in the social 
contract. Figure 1.6 uses data from the Conference Board, a highly re-
spected business research organization, to track national trends. For the first time since the Conference Board began collecting these data in the 1980s, less than 50 percent of the workforce report that they are satis-
fied with their jobs. Note that the biggest decline and the lowest level in satisfaction is reported by young workers. In 2013, only 28 percent of workers under age 25 expressed satisfaction with their jobs. 
Taken together, these data paint a challe nging picture. They te ll us that 
economic conditions exert a strong influence on the ability/willi ngness of 
employers to create jobs. These same forces, along with other factors we 
will discuss later, affect the quality of the jobs firms create and sustain. But employers dont operate in a vacuum. Ra ther, they operate in a broader 
ecosystem of potentially powerful institutions the government, labor 
unions/consortia, societal norms and expectations, educational systems, and so onthat also influence to some extent the number of jobs and to a 
large extent the quality of jobs that are cr eated and the quality of the sup-
port system for those who for whatever re ason lose their jobs. In the post-
war period, these forces were such that the American Dream was intact for 
most people. Since the 1980s, however, things have taken a turn for the worse on wages and other conditions affecting job quality, and since the 
 
 
Figure 1.6 National trends in job satisfaction, 1987- --2013 
Source: The Conference Board.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>THE NEXT GENERATIONS AMERICAN DREAM 17 
say and we know how to do this. Hes right. Weve learned a great 
deal about how to make these workforce development programs workby getting employers in a community or industry to band together, work with these schools, provide on-the-job and classroom learning op-portunities, and then provide jobs and career advancement opportuni-ties to graduates. Making the funding of these programs contingent on showing that these features are in place would go a long way toward spreading high-quality programs across the country and eliminating any skill gaps business says it now faces. 
Then we come to that highly expensive yet valuable asset called a col-
lege degree. American universities remain one of our national treasures
institutions that are still the best in the world . The problems are that they 
are beyond reach for too many and that debt burdens limit the ability of too many graduates to enjoy the benefits a c ollege degree sh ould provide. 
But we have fortuitous opportunities unfolding in the form of universities around the world that are anxious to experiment with various forms of online or distance-learning media. Th e challenge lies in translating the 
initial burst of innovation in onli ne university courses into sustainable 
models that in fact provide access to lower-cost and higher-quality college experiences for students around the world. The online course that Im 
drawing on here is just one small experiment along these lines. Lets get many others in process and watch and learn from them as well. 
These are the investments in education that business, government, la-
bor, and educational institutions will need to make on a large scale to build the human and social capital American employers and workers need in order to be competitive in global markets. They are also investments that individuals will need to make on a lifelongor at least a career-longbasis. Without a world-class education and world-class capabilities, individual workers will find it hard to compete with lower-cost workers in other countries and employers will be reluctant to invest in American jobs. 
Using Technology to Complement and Support Work 
At the dawn of the industrial revolution in Britain, major technological 
advances threatened the livelihood of those who worked in the home-based weaving industry. This led some workers, who became known as</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>THE NEXT GENERATIONS AMERICAN DREAM 9 
Pope Francis I ask you to ensure that humanity is served by wealth and not ruled by it. The 
growth of equality demands something more than economic growth, even 
though it presupposes it. It demands first of all a transcendent vision of the person. . . . It also calls for decisions, mechanisms and processes directed to a 
better distribution of wealth, the creation of sources of employment and an 
integral promotion of the poor which goes beyond a simple welfare mentality. Pope Francis Message to World Economic Forum in Davos, News.Va, 
January 21, 2014, http://www.news.va/ en/news/pope-francis-message-to-world-
economic-forum-in-da.  
Senator Marco Today, the debate on poverty is primarily focused on the growing income gap 
Rubio between the rich and poor. From 1979 to 2007, income for the highest-earning 
Americans grew more than it did for anyone else. From 1980 to 2005, over 80% 
of the total increase in income went to the top 1% of American earners. 
These are indeed startling figures, and they deserve attention. But they do not give us a complete view of the problem before us. 
Yes, the cashier at a fast food chain make s significantly less than the companys 
CEO. The problem we face is not simply the gap in pay between them, but 
rather that too many of those cashiers are stuck in the same job for years on 
end, unable to find one that pays better. 
And it is this lack of mobility, not just income inequality that we should be focused on. Rubio Delivers Address on Fiftieth Anniversary of War on 
Poverty, Marc Rubio website, January 8, 2014, 
http://www.rubio.senate.gov/public/index.cfm/press-releases?ID=958d06fe-16a3-4e8e-b178-664fc10745bf. 
President Barack We know that peoples frustrations run deeper than these most recent political 
Obama battles. Their frustration is rooted in their own daily battlesto make ends meet, 
to pay for college, buy a home, save for retirement. Its rooted in the nagging 
sense that no matter how hard they work, the deck is stacked against them. And its rooted in the fear that their kids wont be better off than they were. And that 
is a dangerous and growing inequality and lack of upward mobility that has 
jeopardized middle-class Americas basic bargainthat if you work hard, you have a chance to get ahead. Remarks by the President on Economic Mobility, 
White House website, December 4, 2013, http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-
office/2013/12/04/remarks-president-economic-mobility.  
CEO and venture Weve had it backward for the last 30 years. . . . Rich businesspeople like me 
capitalist Nick dont create jobs. Rather they are a consequence of an ecosystemic feedback 
Hanauer loop animated by middle-class consumers, and when they thrive, businesses 
grow and hire, and owners profit. Thats why taxing the rich to pay for 
investments that benefit all is a great deal for both the middle class and the rich. Too Hot for TED: Income Inequality, 
National Journal , May 16, 2012. 
Warren Buffett, The Forbes 400, the wealthiest individuals in America, hit a new group record for 
CEO, Berkshire wealth this year: $1.7 trillion. Thats more than five times the $300 billion total in 
Hathaway 1992. My gang has been leaving the middle class in the dust. A Minimum Tax for the Wealthy, New York Times , November 25, 2012, http://www.nytimes.com/2012 
/11/26/opinion/buffett-a-minimum-tax-for-the-wealthy.html. 
Figure 1.5  Comments on income inequality</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>CHAPTER 1 
The Next Generations 
American Dream: What Can 
Be Done to Achieve It? 
Work hard in school, get as much education as you can, play by the 
rules, and you will do well in life. That was the advice I got from my parents, and it clearly served me, and the majority of my baby boomer cohort, quite well. We were fortunate to graduate from high school, vocational school programs, or college into an economy that was grow-ing, pushing new technological frontiers, and providing ample opportu-nities to pursue our interests. We were able to live the American Dream. 
I wish my generation could promise our children and grandchildren 
that they would have similar opportunities. But if we are honest, at this moment, we cannot. A majority of Americans now feel that the country has been going in the wrong direction for at least a decade and expect that members of the next generation will have a lower standard of living than ours. (When I use the term next generation, Im referring roughly to people who are 18 to 33 years old todaythe so-called millennialsbecause they have come of age after the turn of the century.) 
Is this outcome inevitablethe result of a global economy, advanc-
ing technology, or some other forces outside our control? I dont think so, unless, of course, we do nothing. But reversing course will take a cross-generational effort that involves baby boomers who want one more chance to leave a more positive legacy and next-generation workforce members and leaders who want to regain control of their destiny. 
This book is designed to support this type of cross-generational  
effort, first by starting a conversation with next-generation workers about what they want from their jobs, careers, and family livestheir dreams and aspirations. Then comes the hard part: figuring out what</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>24</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
Resource: Shaping the Future of Work (15.662x)
Thomas A. Kochan
The following may not correspond to a particular course on MIT OpenCourseWare, but has been
provided by the author as an individual learning resource.
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
they and leaders of the institutions that shape work and employment 
opportunities need to do to help the next generation realize its goals. 
Is there anything to learn from what made it possible for baby 
boomers to live the American Dream? I believe so, not so we can try to simply replicate these conditions but so we can understand how to adapt and update them to fit with the needs and demands of todays economy, workforce, and environment. In fact, the basic argument running through this book is this: 
 
 The key reason for the challenges the workforces of today and to-
morrow face is that the rapid pace of change in globalization, 
technology, and demographics has outpaced many of the public pol-
icies, business strategies, and organizational practices that were  
designed in an earlier era to govern work, pay, and employment 
relations. Closing this gap by updating these policies, strategies, and 
practices is essential if the next generation is to regain control of its 
destiny. 
Preview: Policies and Business Models to Support 
Great Companies and Great Jobs 
To whet your appetite for this argument, let me illustrate two things: first, how outdated our employment policies are; and second, how the models guiding business strategies of corporations need to change. 
Most of our labor and employment legislation dates back to the 
New Deal of the 1930s. That flurry of action was a direct response to the Great Depression and a belated response to the shift from farming to an industrial economy. Not surprisingly, given work and family pat-terns at that time, the framers of this legislation and the workplace prac-tices that followed had a model of the typical worker in mind. That worker was as a male production employee who worked full time under close managerial supervision in a large domestic firm. Conveniently, he had a wife at home to attend to family and community responsibilities. 
Today, in contrast, we have an economy that is knowledge driven and 
values innovation. The workforce is diverse. Nearly as many women as</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>8 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
Table 1.1 Total changes in real earnings, 2000-- -2011 
 Group Employment share (%) Earnings change (%) 
Less than high school 8.4 ---12.5 
High school graduate 27.4 ---4.1 
Some college 27.8 ---8.9 
College graduate 23.2 ---8.5 
Masters degree 9.5 ---3.7 
MD, JD, or MBA 1.9 +2.2 
PhD 1.8 +3.4 
Source:  Jonathan Haskel, Robert Z. Lawrence, Edwa rd E. Leamer, and Matthew J. Slaughter, 
Globalization and U.S. Wages: Modifying Classic Theory to Explain Recent Facts, Journal of 
Economic Perspectives  26, no. 2 (2012): 119-- -140. 
 
 
Figure 1.4 Annual income share of the top 1 percent of the U.S. 
population 
Source:  Emmanuel Saez, Striking It Richer: The Evolution of Top Incomes in the United 
States, updated with 2009 and 2010 estimates, March 2, 2012, http://elsa.berkeley.edu/~saez 
/saez-UStopincomes-2010.pdf. 
A glance at the earlier years covered in Figure 1.3 suggests that wages 
and incomes didnt always lag behind growth in productivity. Indeed, 
from the mid-1940s through most of the 1970s, these two economic indicators moved pretty much in tandem. This fact will feature promi-nently in our discussion throughout these chapters. The tandem move-ment of wages and productivity over the three decades following the end of World War II captures the essence of what I will call the postWorld War II social contract at work (I will define this contract in Chapter 2). Clearly this contract broke down in the 1980s and has remained broken ever since. We will have to figure ou t what the next generations social 
contract could look like.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>THE NEXT GENERATIONS AMERICAN DREAM 23 
and report current events through their political filters. So  too do the host 
of more liberal-leaning blogs, think tanks, and journals. It is time to reen-
gage across interest group lines and across generations. 
I created an exercise to support this type of dialogue and tried it out 
in the online course. Students were assigned to serve as representatives of 
one of four next-generation groups: the workforce, business, govern-ment, or education. Their task was to negotiate the Next Generation Social Contract. I will report the results of these initial negotiations in Chapter 6 and I have made this exercise available on our website www.speakupforwork.com. I invite you to download it and invite others to join you in multiparty negotiations in your community. See if you can reach consensus on the features of a new social contract that is at-tuned to the needs and interests of today and tomorrows workforce, economy, and society. 
Hopeful Signs 
Is this just a pie-in-the-sky thinking or is progress possible? Im optimistic. 
American society has responded to such crises before; it has a well-earned 
reputation for being a collection of pragmatic innovators rather than a group of ideological antagonists. 
Another positive sign is the uptick in interest in entrepreneurship 
among students I encounter and teach at MIT and hear from around the country. Many in the current wave of hopeful entrepreneurs aspire to build mission-driven organizations that address significant social and/or environmental challenges in addition to experiencing financial success. This is extremely important and exciting, given that we know that new firms are an important source of innovation, new jobs, and business norms. Supporting this new wave of entrepreneurship will be an important part of how the next generation invents a new social con-tract that is appropriately matched to current realities. 
As before, out of crisis will come opp ortunity and out of necessity will 
come invention. The crisis is clear and the opportunities are there for the taking. But first we have to understand the lessons from history so that we heed Santayanas warning (Those who do not remember the past are condemned to repeat it) and not repeat mistakes from the past.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
 
Figure 1.1 America: Which way to compete?  
wrong in American business and a positive way these frustrations can be 
turned into collaborative actions that create change. The reason the Mar-ket Basket employees gained such broad and deep public support is that they were seen as fighting to preserve what I illustrate in Figure 1.1, some-thing I and others call a high road business strategy and set of workplace practices that can deliver good profits to shareholders, good jobs and ca-reers to employees, and good prices and service to customers. This is what the American public wants to see in business and at work today and in the future. So the public, customers, and employ ees all rallied together to 
keep Market Basket from sliding from the high-road to the low-road strategy. Our challenge is to make the high-road model for business strat-egies and employment relations the norm, not the exception to the more dominant approach that treats employees as just another cost to be mini-mized, tightly controlled, and disposed of when not needed. 
So lets get started, first by painting a quick picture of the challenges 
and opportunities facing young people entering todays labor force. 
A Two-Dimensional Jobs Crisis 
The first decade of the twenty-first century earned the sad title of the lost decade. Workers of almost all occupational and income levels were the losers in two dimensions: the quantity and quality of jobs. If the second decade aspires to be known as the re covering decade, we still have a long 
way to go. Despite encouraging gains in 2015, the economy still has not generated enough jobs to make up for those lost in the Great Recession of</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>THE NEXT GENERATIONS AMERICAN DREAM 5 
2007 to 2009 and to absorb the number of young people who have  
entered the labor force since then. Even worse, the quality of jobs being created is, on average, lower than those lost in the recession. 
Figures 1.2 and 1.3 tell these stories. Figure 1.2 tracks how many jobs 
were lost during the Great Recession and how many still need to be cre-ated to keep up with the growth in the labor force since the beginning of the recession. The line that dips deepest in the chart and drags on for years before returning to the level where it started represents todays reality. 
The other lines provide a comparison with recessions of earlier years. It took a record six years from the start and nearly five years after the end of the Great Recession to recover the jobs that were lost. Every prior post-recession recovery did this at a faster pace, as the lines capturing their growth rates illustrate. The good news is that 2014 and 2015 have been banner years for job creationfinally! But this is still the worst job crea-tion record of any recession since the Great Depression of the 1930s. Lets hope 20142015 are the models for the future, not 20092013.  
 
Figure 1.2 Job losses in past recessions compared to the Great 
Recession of 2007-- -2009 
Source: Center on Budget and Policy Priorities, Chart Book: The Legacy of the Great Recession, 
updated November 10, 2010, http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&amp;id=3252.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>22 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
highly developed economy and democracy to provide parents with the 
supports they need to meet their dual work and family responsibilities. From there we can work on updating wage and hours laws, labor rela-tions laws, and other outmoded policies. And we can insist that gov-ernment practice what it preaches by requiring government contractors who supply goods and services made in the United States and abroad to pay fair and acceptable wages and comply with accepted employment standards. An increase in the nations minimum wage is also long over-due, as is demonstrated consistently in polling data and in proactive states and cities that have acted to increase their minimums while Wash-ington remains deadlocked on this and other employment issues. 
How to Make This Happen? 
We need to build on what we have learned about what works and what is 
broken in American workplaces, but information and even new ideas are only starting points for producing change. We need to alter the political discourse and build a broad coalition of voices and interest groups calling for changes that work for their specific needs and interests and for the common good. And we need to keep on innovatingbringing new ideas forward that are not chained to past practices, organizational arrange-ments, or traditions. Call this a crowdsourcing approach, if you will, or whatever new ways work for generating ideas from our collective wisdom. 
This requires getting these different voices and interest group leaders to 
engageperhaps to reen gagewith each other in honest dialogue. Per-
haps out of such discussions would emerge a common narrativea vision for the future that otherwise divergent groups might rally around and use to drive change. This used to happen when labor was stronger and business leaders had a broader view of their roles and responsib ilities. Together they 
forged and sustained the postwar social contract. But over time, sad to say, 
cross-group dialogue largely stopped as business, labor, youth, and other 
groups all retreated into comfortable conversations with themselves. Now even the media caters to these na rrow constituencies. Fox News and the 
Wall Street Journal s editorials tell conservatives and Tea Party advocates 
and anyone who opposes President Obama just what they want to hear</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>THE NEXT GENERATIONS AMERICAN DREAM 21 
This is not to say that all the strategies labor has used need to be 
abandoned. History suggests that doing so would only lead us to rein-
vent them at some point later on. And in fact existing unions and pro-fessional associations and a variety of other worker advocacy groups are already developing and incubating new approaches and combining them with tried and true methods from the past. The key is to inform the current generation of what worked before, what lessons past experiences hold for the future, and then let a thousand flowers bloom. 
Government as a Catalyst for and Complement to Innovation and 
Good Jobs 
What role for government? One of the key lessons from our history is 
that, to paraphrase 1980s speaker of the house Tip ONeill, all innova-
tions are local . (He was an old Boston politician and his exact phrase was 
all politics are local.) 
Almost all federal policies, including the cornerstones of the labor 
legislation passed as part of President Roosevelts New Deal in the 1930s, were based on innovations that first were developed, tested, and carefully studied in state and local governments and/or the private sector. The good news is that a tremendous storehouse of innovation has emerged and been tested at these local levels of th e economy in recent years. The 
task now is to wake up, indeed shake up, national policy makers who are in a position to put in place laws and guidelines that are well matched to the needs of the next-generation workforce and economy. 
The key is to make government a catalyst and a complement, not an 
obstacle, to innovation, change, and fairn ess in work and employment 
relationships. This is not rocket science, but it will require a groundswell of voices from the next-generation workf orce and allies in business, labor, 
and education who want to step up to these challenges and opportunities. Nothing short of a wholesale set of changes  in legislation and enforcement 
strategies and active cooperation on the part of government policy officials and the commitment of those on the front lines of business, labor, and education to enact these changes in go od faith will do the trick. 
As one of the examples used at the be ginning of this chapter suggested, 
a top priority will be to end the embarrassing situation of being the last</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>6 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
How does this affect young people entering the labor market? As late 
as 2014, nearly 40 percent of college graduates were not finding jobs 
that would allow them to put the knowledge and skills they learned in college to work. They are what we call underemployedthey are working in low-wage retail, restaurant, or other service jobs that dont require a college degree, dont put their skills to work or provide oppor-tunities for further learning and development, and likely pay wages that are hardly sufficient to meet their college debt payments, much less start a career and/or a family. To make things worse, a significant body of research indicates that the imprint of starting a career in this type of depressed labor market lasts for a long time, in some cases ones entire working career. Not finding a career position with a decent starting wage and opportunities for continued learning and advancement imposes significant and in some cases permanent damage. 
Young students in the online course provided some first-hand expe-
riences with this. One coined a name for it: working nomads: 
I think the concept of working is dramatically changing in my generation ([born in the] 80s and younger), and the change couldnt [be] understood by [an] older generation. We want to work at a stable organization, but [those] jobs are vanishing so have to work as an unpaid intern or part-time worker. . . . Working nomads are a growing tendency of todays working trends, I think. . . . . So, does this trend entirely change our job structure or [is it] just a temporary trend? Im not sure, but we should focus on this tendency to understand our generation and todays world. 
Figure 1.3 tells the story of the second dimension of the jobs crisis. 
Look at the 30 years since about 1980, during which earnings have es-sentially flat-lined. Over the course of those years, the productivity of American workers grew by a healthy 80 percent, but family income grew by about only 10 percent and average hourly wages inched up only about 6 percent. The data in Table 1.1 indicate why the first decade of this century earned its lost decade label. Real wages (wages adjusted</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>THE NEXT GENERATIONS AMERICAN DREAM 3 
men are working. People can expect to move across employers multiple 
times in their careers and in and out of full-time and part-time work so they can attend school and/or take care of family responsibilities. It is not even always clear who the employer is, given the advent of franchise, con-tractor, and outsourcing arrangements. Yet most of our laws and the regu-lations and procedures used to enforce them still reflect the earlier era. 
The United States is the only large  industrial economy that still lacks a 
national policy on paid family leave. The task of updating our policies, business strategies, and workplace practices to suit our knowledge-driven economy and diverse labor force is huge, essential, and long overdue. 
The example that illustrates how U.S. business models need to 
change comes courtesy of a courageous group of employees at Market Basket, a New England grocery chain with 71 stores and 25,000 em-ployees. Their actions highlighted a debate that needs to be raised all across America: namely, what is the purpose of a businessonly to make money for shareholders or to make money and provide good jobs 
for employees and good service and fair prices for customers? For six weeks in the summer of 2014, executives, store managers, clerks, truck drivers, and warehouse workers of this family-owned business stood side by side outside their stores demanding that their CEO be reinstated and the business model that made the company thrive and supported good jobs, low prices, and great customer service be maintained. Their cus-tomer base cheered them while they had to shop elsewhere at considera-ble inconvenience and expense. Never before have we seen such a broad coalition of workers and customers unite to save a business from short-sighted shareowners hoping to extract more cash for their pockets. But they did so at considerable risk, because the managers and supervisors who protested had no legal protections under our outmoded labor law, the Wagner Act, which dates back to 1935. 
Yet they persevered. Under the combined pressure of this coalition, 
along with a tremendous outpouring of community support and crea-tive use of social media to maintain solidarity, the board of directors relented and sold the company to the beloved CEO who brought back the workforce, the stores customers, and community goodwill. 
I will build on this case at various points in this book because it  
illustrates both the frustrations many in society experience about what is</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>THE NEXT GENERATIONS AMERICAN DREAM 15 
their dreams and aspirations are and what they are prepared to do to 
realize them. And we have to hear from those who have experienced the demise of the American Dream and understand not only what made that dream durable for several decades but also what caused it to end so abruptly. Finally, we need to engage leaders of business, government, labor, and education in a dialogue, indeed in a negotiation, about their interests and what they are prepared to do to get the economy and the labor market moving in directions that work for all. 
What Can Be Done? Lessons from  
Three Decades of Research and Experience 
The ideas for what I think needs to be done, outlined below, come from over 30 years of research and direct involvement in the worlds of work and employment relations. Over this time my research, teaching, and work with government agencies, companies, and unions has had a sin-gular theme: the search for innovations that improve the performance of our economy and the quality of work and family life. I will draw on lessons learned from these experiences in the chapters that follow. I pre-sent these ideas here not as final solutions but as thought provokers and conversation starters. The goal is to encourage you to engage in this dis-cussion and in doing so widen the circle of voices calling for change and working actively to make good things happen. 
Some might argue that globalization and technological change or 
some other force of nature inevitably means that recent trends will con-
tinue. I would agree that this will be the case if we let the status quo continue unchallenged. But I dont believe this is inevitablenot if we act now in well-informed, coordinated, and strategic ways. 
Yes, globalization and advances in technology are part of the forces 
at work here. But they are not really anything new. Similar disruptions and a similar need for fundamental changes in policies, institutions, and practices were experienced when technological and economic advances ushered in the transition from an agricultural to an industrial economy in the early years of the twentieth century. During that transition, too, it was a long time before changes were put in place that allowed the work-force to adjust and benefit from the new economy. Today we are well</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>12 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
blocked nearly everything but the presidents compromise economic 
stimulus package, which avoided the total financial and economic col-lapse of the banking system and sparked a partial recovery. 
So today most young people, indeed most people of all ages, are dis-
illusioned with all politiciansRepublicans, Democrats, the president, 
and especially the do-nothing Congress. A majority (52 percent) of mil-
lennials would replace all members of Congress if given the chance, and 47 percent would replace the president.
2 Gallup and other polling ser-
vices similarly report that confidence in most American institutions has fallen to all-time low levels. Congress gets only a 10 percent confidence rating, organized labor gets about 20 percent, and big business gets 22 
percent.
3 Other polls indicate that the majority of Americans share the 
view that the next generation is destined to experience a lower standard 
of living than their parents.4 
Destiny or Opportunity? 
So I have covered the bad news, the jobs crisis young workers face as 
they enter the labor market today and their lack of faith in the leaders 
and institutions that govern work and employment. But with crisis 
comes opportunity. Indeed, one bit of good news is that the chorus of diverse voices noted in Figure 1.5 voicing concerns over income inequal-
ity suggests that we may be at a point where people, like those coura-
geous Market Basket employees and customers, are ready to do some-thing to address these issues. In fact, over the course of 2015 a few 
glimmers of hope emerged with companies such as Walmart, McDon-
alds, and others announcing their intentions to raise wages above the required minimum wage. Regardless of whether one attributes their  
 
                                                            
 2 John Della Volpe, IOP Releases New Fall Poll, 5 Key Findings and Trends in 
Millennial Viewpoints, Harvard University Institute of Politics, December 4, 2013, 
http://www.hks.harvard.edu/news-events/news/articles/millennial-viewpoints. 
3 Confidence in Institutions, Gallup.com, n.d., http://www.gallup.com/poll 
/1597/confidence-institutions.aspx#1. 
4 Elizabeth Mendes, In U.S., Optimis m for Youth Reaches an All-Time Low, 
Gallup.com, May 2, 2011, http://www.gallup.com/poll/147350/optimism-future-
youth-reaches-time-low.aspx.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>20 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
Kaiser Permanente. As noted earlier, the CEO of Market Basket, Arthur 
T. Demoulas, has now become the poster child for advocating what have been called high-road or high-performance strategies and em-ployment practices that work for multiple stakeholders. You may work for an organization like this. We need to learn what makes these exam-ples successful for all stakeholders so we then can get on with the task of turning them into the norm rather than the exception. 
Worker Power But Not Just Your Fathers Unions 
You might be surprised, but in what follows I will argue strongly that 
the next generation will need its own sources of bargaining power to regain control of its destiny. In the postWorld War II era it was labor unions and collective bargaining that gave large number of workers the power needed to improve working conditions, advance their standard of living, and build a strong middle class. Union advocates like to remind us (correctly) that they brought us the weekend and many other benefits we take for granted at work today. Most young people today have no knowledge of and perhaps little reason to even think about unions as anything other than some relic of a bygone era. Yet as we will see, collec-tive actions on the part of young workers will be necessary if they are to turn the country around to meet their aspirations and expectations for good jobs, careers, and family lives. 
But it cant be just your fathers or grandfathers labor movement
it will need to be a more nimble, flexible, and less constrained set of 
networks and organizations that can empower workers to find good jobs and discipline employers to meet their expectations while also providing 
opportunities for employees to update their capabilities throughout their 
working lives. Indeed, one of the greatest opportunities and needs facing the next-generation workforce is to invent these new forms of advocacy, 
voice, representation, and support. As part of this project, we will ex-
plore experience to date of using worker-centered apps that rate employ-ers and jobs on the qualities young workers value mostand identify 
which employers to avoid because they come up short on these qualities. 
This could be one new source of bargaining power for the new tech-savvy and mobile generation. Others will need to be invented as well.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>THE NEXT GENERATIONS AMERICAN DREAM 7 
for increases in the cost of living) either declined or did not increase for 
high school or college graduates. Only those at the top of the occupa-tional ladder with advanced degrees experienced modest wage growth. 
 
 
Figure 1.3 The social contract, 1947-- -2013 
Source: Josh Bivens, Elise Gould, Lawrence Mishel, and Heidi Shierholz, Raising Americas 
Pay: Why Its Our Central Economic and Policy Ch allenge, Economic Policy Institute, June 4, 
2014, http://www.epi.org/publication/raising-americas-pay/. 
 
Where did all the fruits of increased productivity go in the last  
30 years? Figure 1.4 tells this well-known story. Most of the income growth went to the top 1 percent or less of the populationthe Occupy movement (young people who protested in 2012 that too much of the nations income was concentrated in the top 1 percent of the popula-tion) had its facts right (Figure 1.4). America is now suffering from the highest level of income inequality of any time since the 1920s. Little wonder that politicians from across the political spectrum, from Presi-dent Obama to Republican Senator Marco Rubio, are talking about the need to address this problem. They and many others, including a signif-icant number of leading economists, business leaders, and even Pope Francis, worry that persistence of this divide will do more than just limit economic growth: it could also threaten the future of our democracy, just as extreme inequality has done in other countries in years past. (See Figure 1.5 for a sample of voices on this issue).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>14 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
My dream includes a job where I do important work (working in 
health care data analytics)something that gives back to the 
community. . . . I dream of having a work/life balance that melds together. . . . I hope that Im able to utilize technology to make work more accessible and eventually have the option to work from home. I do hope to be able to find a company that has a re-tirement plan where the company contributes some percentage to the plan. In some regards, I hope to have some of the same bene-fits that my parents hadhealth insurance, retirement plans, etc. Most importantly, I want to have passion for my work, I want my work to help people and I hope to make a decent living while 
making the generations before me proud. 
Another young woman made a similar point: 
I selected that I wanted autonomy out of working. I want flexi-
bilityI want to work hard, but I also want to do many differ-
ent projects and make various amounts of money doing so, while sometimes taking breaks from working at all that are more than 
just the 2 weeks provided in a year. 
These data and comments suggest that members of today and to-
morrows workforce share many of the same concerns of prior genera-
tions, perhaps with a higher weight on having an impact and having adequate flexibility to integrate their work and personal lives. Sloan School MBAs who took the on-campus version of the course in order to engage with the next-generation workforce interpreted these data to suggest that as managers they will need to listen to their employees, en-gage them in solving problems that really matter to the organization and to society, and to be flexible in how, when, and where people work so they can both be productive and attend to personal and family affairs. 
Opportunities for the Taking 
So the labor force of the future is ready to take on the challenges they are inheriting. Our responsibility is to give them the opportunities to do so. We need to listen to the voices of the next generationto learn what</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>24 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
So in Chapter 2, I take up the history of the postWorld War II so-
cial contract by exploring where it came from, what made it last for three 
decades, why it broke down, and what lessons it offers for the future. 
In Chapter 3, I ask what changed in the 1980s, why those changes 
happened, and why we should care. We should care because the 1980s were a critical turning point in the history of work. The old industrial 
economy and the institutions, norms, and policies that supported it grad-ually (and in some cases abruptly) gave way to the emergence of todays 
global economy driven by knowledge innovation. It was also a time of significant technological inno vationthe age of information technology 
began to take hold in big ways. And finally, it was a time of tremendous 
transformation in the role of the corporation in America and in labor-
management relations. I record those changes in some detail because many (if not most) of them are with us today and will need to constitute 
starting assumptions as we look to ways of shaping the future of work. 
In Chapter 4, I catalog the range of innovations that came out of the 
crises of the 1980s and in the years since then, up to today. These are the seedbeds of innovation for the future. Many have yet to grow to a 
scale large enough to have a big impact on the workforce and on society as a whole, yet history tells us that these local innovations might at some 
point be ready for the national stage. 
Then in Chapter 5 I sample some of the innovations unfolding to-
day. Some of these take the form of start-ups that put digital technolo-gies to work in new ways that disrupt old ways of doing business and 
working. Some of these provide great jobs and some do not. Some are focused on solving important social problems and making a profit and 
some are committed to all three goalssolving a big problem, making 
profits, and providing good jobs. So the challenge remains to teach cur-rent and next-generation entrepreneurs that they too have choices in 
how they envision and build their organizationsright from the start. 
Chapter 6 pulls all this together by first reporting on the results our 
students generated in their efforts to negotiate the next-generation social contract. Then I bring toge ther what we have learne d from our history, 
from research to date, and from the voices of the next generation to suggest 
a narrative and set of actions that, if taken together, could bring the realiza-
tion of the American Dream within the reach of the next generation.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>THE NEXT GENERATIONS AMERICAN DREAM 19 
the new machines and put them to good  use for humankind . I certainly 
prefer typing these words in a warm house with a cup of coffee by my side 
to having to go out on cold dark winter mornings to milk cows and clean 
their stalls! 
Good Businesses and Good Jobs 
Let me be blunt and clear. The values and business strategies that have 
dominated in most American corporations in recent decades will need to change in big ways if the next-generation workforce is to thrive and the environment is to be saved. For the past several decades, American busi-ness has narrowed its focus to a singular objective: maximizing short-term shareholder value. Some have labeled this the financialization of the American economy, arguing that pleasing Wall Street has essentially become the top priority of U.S. firms. Business must be challenged to go beyond a focus on maximizing short-term shareholder interests to refo-cus on a more balanced set of objectives that involve people and the planet as well as profits. This will require overcoming the prevailing teaching about the role of the corporation that has dominated economics and business school curricula for the past two decades. An entire genera-tion of managers and executives has been indoctrinated with the view that their primary, if not sole, responsibility is to attend to shareholder interests and, even worse, attend to and shape their own compensation and rewards to be aligned with short-term shareholder value. 
It will also require a concerted effort to rebalance power in organiza-
tional decision making. Corporate norms dont rise or fall simply be-cause of good intentions. Power also matters. How this shift in power will occur will be a major question for discussion and a major challenge for those who have the biggest stake in the future (an issue I tackle in the section that follows). 
The good news is that we have learned how to do this directly from 
the businesses that have bucked this trend and focused on managing their affairs in ways that produce good financial results and good jobs and career opportunities. Every industry has its favorite examplesin the airline industry, it might be Southwest; in retail, it might be Costco; in software development, it might be SAS; in health care, it might be</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>THE NEXT GENERATIONS AMERICAN DREAM 13 
 
Figure 1.7 Students aspirations regarding work 
Source:  Student responses to survey administered through the online course The American 
Dream for the Next Generation,  MIT Sloan School of Management. 
 
actions to a somewhat tightening labor market or a response to pressures from strikes of fast-food workers and national protests, these are good first steps in the right direction. Lets hope there will be more to come. 
A second reason for hope comes from the motivations and aspira-
tions of young people themselves, reinforced by the views expressed by many students in the online class. While they may be disillusioned with American politicians, many are still positive about their own futures and are motivated to address the big problems they and others face at work, in their families, and in society. Take a look, for example, at how stu-dents ranked their goals and aspirations for their future jobs. 
At the start of the course, I asked participants to rank order their as-
pirations/priorities for work. The data in Figure 1.7 show that partici-pants want to address big problems at work and at the same time have a sensible work-life balance. While doing well financially is also im-portant, these data, like the findings of other surveys of young and more experienced workers, show it is not at the top of the list. 
The wide distribution of responses suggests that no single aspiration 
dominates. Qualitative comments reinforced this view. This extended quote from a young woman illustrates how she (and she seems to speak for others) sees these different aspirations fitting together:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>16 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
into another transition from an industrial economy to an innovation- 
and knowledge-based economy that is playing out on a global stage with 
perhaps even more far-reaching effects than the previous transition. 
As in the early twentieth century, institutional inertia and political 
stalemate has resulted in a mismat ch between changes in the economy, the 
workforce, and the world of work and the policies, governance arrange-
ments, institutions, and practices that govern work and employment rela-tionships. Our taskindeed, our opport unityis to create a better match. 
The Foundation: Lifelong Education for All 
What will it take to change this? For a start, nothing short of a funda-
mental set of changes in how we get educated, when we get educated, 
and who gets educated. The mantra has to be not quite (but almost) cradle-to-grave education for all. The rhetoric about lifelong learning 
will need to become a reality if the workforce of the future is to compete 
on a global stage. And it has to start very early in life. There is clear and 
convincing evidence that investments in pre-kindergarten education pay 
off in the form of less crime, higher graduation rates, and greater earning 
potential. It is encouraging to see a consensus building around the need to broaden access to early childhood, pre-kindergarten education in such 
diverse places as New York, Oklahoma, and Georgia. 
Then we have to keep up the pressure for innovation and change in 
elementary and secondary schools. The Race to the Top incentives and requirements imposed by the Obama administration have spurred 
more innovation in public schools and more collaboration than ever between teachers, their unions, and school administrators who are  
focused on improving student achievement and school performance. 
Efforts are currently under way to expand these collaborative efforts in Massachusetts, and the hope is that this initiative will serve as a model 
for the rest of the country. 
In his 2014 and 2015 State of the Union addresses, President 
Obama called for increased financial support and better coordination 
and improved results in the technical training provided to high school graduates and current members of the workforce through community colleges and vocational schools and allied institutions. He went on to</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>18 SHAPING THE FUTURE OF WORK 
Luddites, to attempt to destroy the new machines. Many technological 
scares of this type have come and gone over the years, always displacing some workers. These changes disrupt some individuals and their fami-lies, but they eventually spur further economic growth and create new job opportunities for workers with the right skills. We are facing this kind of situation in the wake of current and likely future advances in digital technologies. 
We will need to embrace advances in technology while we work to 
assure that they function to complement and not eviscerate work. Our mantra will need to be that it is people who give wisdom to these ma-chines, to borrow a Japanese phrase. Some experts predict, with good reason, that the coming wave of digital technologies will eliminate large numbers of good jobs. They are right, just as generations before ours worried about similar advances in technologies that freed people like me from farm labor; automated large numbers of difficult, repetitive, and sometimes dangerous production jobs; and transformed or eliminated office and clerical jobs such as chart-room workers in health care. Our challenge is to win the race with, not against, new technologies by in-venting new ways to use them and by training workers and modifying work systems in ways that enhance the lik elihood that technological in-
vestments will realize their full potential. In the best health care organiza-tions, such as, for example, Kaiser Permanente, as technology changed how work was done, chart-room clerical workers were trained and trans-ferred to new jobs that used electronic medical records technologies to promote preventive care and remind patients to get regular checkups. 
We need to bring this type of new mindset to would-be inventors and 
designers of next-generation techno logies. For too long, engineers have 
been trained to focus primarily on how to cut labor costs. While this has its 
benefits, so too would incentives  to invent and develop new technologies
indeed, new entrepreneurial organization sthat use the skills of creative, 
dedicated people to tackle the globes greatest environmental and human problems. Innovation and entrepreneurshi p are critical to job creation. The 
key is to make this a priority in our university, government, and private-
sector laboratories and educational programs. If we combine this initiative 
with lifelong education programs and creative id eas for structuring work 
(discussed in later chapters), Im confident that we will win the race with</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>THE NEXT GENERATIONS AMERICAN DREAM 11 
Great Recession the challenges have extended to a shortage of jobs.  
Employers are squeezed and, as I will discuss later, unions have lost much of their clout, and government policies and educational systems havent kept pace with changes in the economy or the nature of work. As a result, it has become difficult to realize the American Dream today, and it promises to get much more difficult for the generations to come unless something is done to change the path were on. 
The Political Dimension:  
Is Washington Asleep or in Gridlock? 
If a modern-day Rip van Winkle were to wake up today after a 30-year nap, she or he would very likely look at these facts and ask Why have the leaders of our economic and political institutions let our economy and society slide for so long? Were they all asleep with me? 
And I suppose we would respond: Good question, but no they were 
not totally asleep. Instead they have been stuck in ideological gridlock for at least the last decade and in some cases, in particular the relation-ships between business and labor leaders, for even longer. The sad reality is the country is more divided politically today than at any time perhaps since the 1930s. 
Rips equivalent might then ask, But what about all the hope Ive 
read about with the election of Americas first African American presi-dent in 2008? Wasnt that a historic achievement and a marker of greater things to come? The answer to this equally astute observation would be yes, many of us thought so. That was especially true of young people. They were a powerful force in helping to elect Barack Obama. Sixty-six percent of young voters supported him. Many worked hard on his cam-paign, and many thought that the combination of the economic crisis he inherited and the positive energy the election gave to the nation would produce transformative changes in policies and practice.
1 Unfortunately, 
the gridlock not only continued, it got worse. Republicans in Congress 
                                                            
1 Scott Keeter, Juliana Horowitz, and Alec Tyson, Young Voters in the 2008 Elec-
tion, Pew Research Center, November 13, 2008, http://www.pewresearch.org 
/2008/11/13/young-voters-in-the-2008-election/.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Out of Crisis: Innovations in the 1980s and Beyond</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/res-15-003-shaping-the-future-of-work-15-662x-spring-2016/resources/mitres_15_003s16_atrophy/From</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Old Social Contract: What Made It Work and Why did It Break Down?</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/res-15-003-shaping-the-future-of-work-15-662x-spring-2016/resources/mitres_15_003s16_newdeal/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Secretary Perkinss staff developed parallel laws that required government contractors and employers in 
government -financed construction projects to pay prevailing wages; these l aws were also enacted.5 
What can we learn from this experience that would help inform where we need to go?  I believe 
the key lesson to
 take away from this New Deal history is that if we are to go beyond the divided 
policies that are always associated with labor legislation in the United States, the following 
elements must be in place: a strong policy champion, a government department staffed with employees who can provide deep analysis of labor issues, and access to the expertise created by 
academics who have helped invent the private and state -level innovations that provide the 
evidence that proposed policies work.  
 
5 See Jonathan Grossman, Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938: Maximum Struggle for a Minimum Wage, Monthly 
Labor Review  (June 1978), http://www.dol.gov/dol/aboutdol/history/flsa1938.htm .  
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Source: Frances Perkins, The Roosevelt I Knew  (New York: Viking Press, 1946).  
 
Where did her ideas come from? She didnt make them up. This brings us to our first lesson that 
can inform efforts to build a new social contract going forward.  
All innovations are local. Most of our federal labor and social legislation was first conceived, 
incubated, and tested at the state level and/or in private -sector settings.  
Frances Perkins knew first -hand that there had been a good deal of experimentation with these 
programs in progressive states such as Wisconsin, New York (where Perkins had been commissioner of the state department of labor when Roosevelt was governor), and Massachusetts. Many of these 
programs were first developed by academics from the University of Wisconsin under the tutelage of 
Professor John R. Commons. He earned the title of Father of the New Deal, since many of his ideas, 
carried forward by his students, found their way to Washington in the Roosevelt administration.  
Consider, for example, how unemployment insurance and Social Security came into being. This 
is how historian Arthur Schlesinger Jr. told the story. Shortly after taking office, President Roosevelt gave 
his Secretary of Labor, Frances Perkins, the green light to go to wo rk on the agenda she had laid out for 
him prior to accepting his offer to become, as she was later called, Madame Secretary. She went to 
work on the idea of creating an unemployment insurance system by drawing heavily on experts from 
Wisconsin who had worked with John R. Commons to first propose an experienced -based state 
system in 1921. Commons students Paul Raushenbush and Elizabeth Brandeis Raushenbush (the 
daughter of Supreme Court Justice Louis Brandeis), University of Wisconsin professor Edwin Wi tte, and 
Arthur Altmeyer developed a plan that called for state -level administration of unemployment insurance 
funded through a payroll tax that was pro -rated based on the level of unemployment a firm 
experienced. After considerable debate over the technic al details of this approach, the Roosevelt team 
adopted it and the president endorsed it.  
In parallel, another group tackled the broader question of how to create an old- age insurance system 
and some means of providing for the families of workers who died or became permanently disabled. The president had already expressed his views to Madame Secretary on this issue. According to 
Schlesinger, Roosevelt said to Frances Perkins: I see no reason why every child, from the day he is born, 
should not be a member of the social security system. . . . From the cradle to the grave they ought be in 
a social insurance system. He went on to describe his views on how this insurance system should be 
financed: If I have anything to say about it, it will be contributed . .  . both on the part of the employer 
and the employee, on a sound actuarial basis. It means no money out of the Treasury.
2 
2 Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr., The Age of Roosevelt: The Coming of the New Deal, 1933 1935, vol. 2 (Boston: 
Houghton, Mifflin, 1958), 308.  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>President Hoover  was doing too little to combat the Depression. Farming families in Texas and 
Oklahoma who could no longer cope with the combination of the depression and years of drought 
began the trek westward toward the promise of a better life in California that motiv ated John 
Steinbecks Grapes of Wrath. It all looked quite hopeless, and in fact, to those who valued our American 
way of life and political system, it looked quite dangerous. Radical insurrection seemed just around the 
corner!  
 Losing a job was disastrous in the 1920s and 1930s. There was no unemployment insurance and 
no health insurance. Keeping your job likely meant a cut in wages and work hours. One report indicated that by 1933 nine out of ten companies had cut wages, 60 percent of the work force was working part time, and family income had dropped by 40 percent.
1  
 That combination of frustration and desire for change led to political change. After the 
Republicans had controlled the White House for ten years, Democrat Franklin D. Roosevelt was elected.  
He ushered in what would become known as the New Deal.  
While Roosevelt didnt come into office with a clear agenda for change, at least one of his 
advisors did. Frances Perkins famously warned the new president that if he chose her to be his Secretary 
of Labor she would press for legislation to provide unemployment insurance, a national minimum wage, 
and a program of retirement insurance and disability insurance. (See Box 2 -2)  
Box 2 -2 
Frances Perkinss Vision and Agenda  
Roosevelt came right to the point. Ive been thinking things over and Ive decided I want you to 
be Secretary of Labor.  
Since the call from his secretary, I had been going over arguments to convince him that he should not appoint me. . . . I said that if I accepted the position of Secreta ry of Labor I should 
want to do a great deal. I outlined a program of labor legislation and economic improvement. 
None of it was radical. It had all been tried in certain states and foreign countries. But I thought 
that Roosevelt might consider it too ambitious to be undertaken when the United States was 
deep in depression and unemployment.  
In broad terms, I proposed immediate federal aid to the states for direct unemployment relief, 
an extensive program of public works, a study and an approach to the estab lishment by federal 
law of minimum wages, maximum hours, true unemployment and old -age insurance, abolition 
of child labor, and the creation of a federal employment service.  
The program received Roosevelts hearty endorsement, and he told me he want me to carry it 
out. 
1 https://web.archive.org/web/20131205173514/http://www.digitalhistory.uh.edu/learning_history/children_depression/
depression_children_menu.cfm . 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Box 2 -1 
The New Deal Foundations  
Four Pillars of The Ne w Deal Labor Policy  What They Did  
Unemployment Insurance  Provided income to unemployed workers for a 
temporary period of time with the expectation 
they would either be rehired or find a new job as economic conditions improved.  
Social Security and Disability Insurance  Provided retirement benefits to employees who 
meet a minimum number of years worked and benefits to workers who become disabled and 
unable to work.  
National Labor Relations Act  Protected the right of workers to form 
independent union s and engage in collective 
bargaining  
Fair Labor Standards Act  Established a national minimum wage and 
overtime pay requirements for a work week of more than 40 hours.  
 
The New Deal  
 Imagine it is 1930 and you are about to finish school and enter the labor force. What is going 
through your mind?  
You came of age in the roaring 20s when the economy was booming. President Calvin Coolidge 
told you the business of the country is business, and the booming stock market proved his point. But 
somehow you dont  feel so optimistic. Your family shared only a little bit of the growth in the mid -1920s 
(wages went up about 8 to 10 percent, but the giant portion of the gains went to the top 10 percent of 
the population). And whatever income gains your family made were  quickly wiped out by the events 
following Black Tuesday in October 1929, the day the stock market crashed. By the end of 1930, real 
wages for average workers were no higher than they had been a decade earlier. Unemployment was 10 
percent and rising rapidl y. If your family was part of the 13 percent of the population that lived and 
worked on a farm, you were in even worse shape: You had steadily lost income throughout the 1920s 
even in the face of the business boom.  
And then came the Great Depression. At its worst, 25 percent of the work force was 
unemployed. Homelessness grew to the point that a name was invented to describe the communities of 
shanties homeless people created with anything they could find: Hoovervilles. The point was clear: 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
https://ocw.mit.edu
Resource: Shaping the Future of Work (15.662x)
Thomas A. Kochan
The following may not correspond to a particular course on MIT OpenCourseWare, but has been
provided by the author as an individual learning resource.
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: https://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>The rest is history. In January 1935, Roosevelts social security and unemployment insurance bill 
was submitted to Congress. It was h otly debated, often in terms that should sound quite familiar to 
those who have followed the debates over Obamacare.  
A leading business group, the National Industrial Conference Board  said: Unemployment 
insurance cannot be placed on a sound financial b asis. It will facilitate ultimate socialist control of life 
and industry. Alfred Sloan of General Motors said The dangers are manifest. The new bill would 
undermine the American way of life by destroying initiative, discouraging thrift, and stifling individual 
responsibility.3 Republicans in Congress such as Representative John Taber of New York channeled 
these views:  
Never in the history of the world has any measure been brought in here to insidiously designed 
as to prevent business recovery, to ens lave workers, and to present any possibility of the 
employers providing work for the people The lash of the dictator will be felt and twenty -five 
million free American citizens will for the first time submit themselves to a fingerprint test.4 
In the end, after a long debate and a number of amendments the Social Security Act of 1935 was 
enacted. It provided unemployment insurance, old age insurance, and disability insurance programs. Little did these policy makers or their supporters and critics in Congress  know that some fifty years later 
Republicans and Democrats alike would describe Social Security as the third rail of politics that was 
never to be touched.  
If this social legislation was controversial, consider the most difficult of all parts of the New  Deal 
to be enacted legislation to protect workers rights to join a union and engage in collective bargaining 
over their wages, hours, and working conditions.  
This was not one of the pieces of legislation Roosevelt or his cabinet members initiated or even  
initially supported. Instead, its chief sponsor was Senator Robert Wagner of New York. The Wagner 
Act (formally the National Labor Relations Act), passed in 1935, shared two similarities with other parts 
of the New Deal: It built on local- level innovati ons, in this case in the private -sector clothing, coal, and 
railroads industries, and it was informed by the work of labor economists and historians who had studied and help guide collective bargaining programs in the era before the New Deal.  
The final plank of the New Deal labor legislation, the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938, instituted 
the nations first minimum wage ($.25 per hour), required employers to pay overtime for a work week of more than 44 hours (later lowered to 40 hours), and abolished most  child labor. President Roosevelt 
strongly supported this legislation, which Secretary Perkins and her staff at the Department of Labor had developed. Business strongly opposed it. Labor leaders were lukewarm in their support, fearing in part that government -mandated minimum wages would undermine unions and collective bargaining. 
3 Schlesinger, The Age of Roosevelt: The Coming of the New Deal, 1933 1935, 2:311.  
4 Schlesinger, The Age of Roosevelt: The Coming of the New Deal, 1933 1935, 2:3 11. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>The New Deal  
Quick Summary  
In th
e 1920s, the economy boomed and business flourished, but the majority of Americans were 
left behind. Then the economy fell into crisis of the Depression. The Roosevelt administration 
considered British economist John Maynard Keyness macroeconomic the ory that government needed 
to spend money to get the economy back on track and tried to pursue it in a half -hearted fashion. It 
succeeded in stabilizing the economy and helping those most in need by enacting a comprehensive set 
of labor market and labor relations policy reforms.  
The New Deal labor legislation created unemployment insurance, social security retirement and 
disability pensions, minimum wages, and regulation of hours through overtime premiums beyond forty hours per week. Finally, but perhaps m ost importantly for the longer run, it created a labor relations law 
and policy that both enabled workers to join and sustain unions that were capable of bargaining for 
wages, hours, and working conditions and a set of policies for resolving labor- manageme nt disputes. 
(See Box 2 -1 for a summary.) These achievements laid the foundation for a new social contract for the 
American economy and work force. But they were not enough to usher that new social contract in. It took a set of actions on the part of workers, employers, unions, and government policy makers to build 
on this foundation during and after World War II. The result of the New Deal foundation and the collective actions that built on it was a postwar social contract that worked well for most parties  (less 
well for women and minorities than for men) for three decades a period that in hindsight looks like a 
golden era for the American economy.  
Lets look in more detail at how this all happened.  
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Emerging Models of Worker Voice and Advocacy</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/res-15-003-shaping-the-future-of-work-15-662x-spring-2016/resources/mitres_15_003s16_futurewrk/Preparing</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>New Emerging Models: New Firms, New Jobs, New Technology, and the Future of Work&#160;</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/res-15-003-shaping-the-future-of-work-15-662x-spring-2016/resources/mitres_15_003s16_saturn/The</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides/>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
