<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/</course_url>
    <course_title>Social Theory and the City</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Sociology </list>
      <list>Urban Studies </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Homo-Faber Project - R. Sennett</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 4: Homo-Faber 
 
The class discussed a draft work-in-pr ogress written and presented by the 
Instructor. Homo-Faber is the first of a three-volume series dealing with the issue 
of how people learn about themselves by negotiating with things, and it examines 
craftsmanship specifically. The piece ex amines the process of learning in the 
process of designing or playing musical instruments as one characterized by interpretation and enquiry, control, and release. Students were asked to comment on, criticize, and present their questions about the theoretical content 
of the piece.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Proyecto Cities - Stephen Ramos
The Limit of Place - Nomita Sawhney</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn12_r_sawhney/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Part 2: The Limit of Place 
 
Summary: 
 
During the second half of class, discussi on focused on a draft work-in-progress 
written and presented by Nomita Sawhne y. Her work explored the different 
perceptual levels through which cities  are experienced beginning with memory 
and amnesia, moving through desire as the impetus for creation, and ending with 
an understanding of the city as a being or organism. The paper grappled with the 
question of how to balance the need for memory with the desire to create new 
forms, to fill the gap between what exists and what is perceived to be missing. It 
also addressed the erasure of ancient systems of city building in the East, 
specifically India, which related the city abstractly to the human body. The class 
focused primarily on the question of how to capture memory in  the form of the 
city and how that memory is perceived.  
 
 
Theoretical issues und erpinning the content: 
 
- Memory 
o Why is it important? 
o Relation between memory and presence 
o How is it conveyed 
 Theory of ruins 
 When something is in a destroyed state, we are more 
attentive to it than when it is whole 
o What makes something memorable? 
- Amnesia and Creation 
o Creation as an act of amnesia 
 Anton Ehrenzweig, The Hidden Order of Art  
 Moments of unknowing gi ve the freedom to create 
o Creating as a release of  tacit knowledge 
- Amnesia versus Erasure 
o Erasure is a positive act to deny there was anything there before 
 To build, one must destroy 
 No room for juxtaposition 
 Jacques Derrida</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 12:  
 
Part 1: Regional Cities 
 
Summary: 
 
During the first half of class, discussi on focused on a draft work-in-progress 
written and presented by Stephen Ramos. His work examined his experiences 
working in Madrid, Spain on the Proyect o Cities initiative launched by the 
University of Pennsylvania in 1997, and it extracted questions about regionalism 
and regional planning that formed the basis of the presentation and discussion. 
The class explored historical models of regional planning, fr om the Garden-City 
model to the Randstadt, polycentric model.  
 
 
Theoretical issues und erpinning the content: 
 
- Hierarchic versus Polycentric 
o Which is better? 
- Charles Tilly,  Coersion, Capital and European States, AD 990-1992 . 
o Polycentrism = capitalism 
o Hierarchical = coercion 
- Virtues of Hierarchy: 
o Coordination 
o Identity 
o Diversity 
o Density 
- Sociological Problem with Polycentrism 
o Illusory: 
 Unequal division of labor 
 Unequal division of capital 
o What kind of hierarchy is best? 
 
 
Example Cities: 
- Tokyo  Hierarchical or polycentric? 
- London  Hierarchical 
- Randstatt  Polycentric 
- Basque Region, Spain  Polycentric 
- Los Angeles  Hierarchica l (unplanned polycentrism?)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Architecture of Repression - Olga Touloumi</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn10_touloumi/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 10: "The Architecture of Repre ssion: war machines and state apparatus 
in the EU summit meeting, Thessaloniki,"  
 
Summary: 
 
The class discussed a draft work-in-pr ogress written and presented by Olga 
Touloumi. In her paper Olga explored the physical transformation of Thessaloniki 
during the 2003 European Union Summit, which took place there, in terms of 
Gilles Deleuze and Flix Guattar is (D&amp;G) distinctions of war machine  and State 
apparatus  and smooth versus striated space. She analyzed the impact of the 
physical barriers erected around the city as  well as the police lines guarding the 
location of the meeting as striations and analyzed the movement and actions of 
the protestors to determine whether t hey were able to smooth the space as 
D&amp;Gs theory would suggest. The class discussion examined what alternative 
theories might also help illuminate the questions raised in the paper about power and space.  
 
 
Theoretical issues und erpinning the content: 
 
- Foucaults theories of inversions of power 
- Ritual in protest 
- Panopticon 
-  
Additional References: 
- Gustave Le Bon, The Crowd: A Study of the Popular Mind . 
- Sigmund Freud, Mass Psychology  
- Elias Cannetti, Crowds and Power. 
- Charles Tilly 
- George Rud, The Crowd in History.  
 
Exercises: 
- Create diagrams of crowd movements.  
- Analyze the morphology of the barriers that were present.  
- Compare the ways that the forms of  protests have changed over time.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Photographs in Urban Planning - Steven Moga
Immigrant Spaces in the European City - Jennifer Mack</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn13_moga_mack/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Part 2: Immigrant Spaces 
 
Summary: 
 
During the second half of class, discussion focused on a working paper 
published as part of the Rosemarie Rogers Working Paper Series at the Inter-
University Committee on In ternational Migration, Ice Skating and Island Hopping: 
Refugees, Integration, and Access in a Segregated City , and a draft work-in-
progress, Fast Food / High Speed / Hip Hop: Migrants and Globalized Spaces in 
European Cities written and pr esented by Jennifer Mack. In the former, she 
analyzed a Red-Cross sponsor ed program intended to integrate immigrants into 
mainstream Swedish cult ure by bringing Swedes and immigrants together to 
learn about Sweden and explore sites import ant to Swedish identity. She found, 
however, that when asked to draw a m ental map of Stockholm, immigrant 
program participants were not inclined to in clude traditionally Swedish locations 
in their maps. Rather they emphasized t he importance of spaces that were not 
inherently Swedish as their most important destinations . Jennifer explores this 
concept in greater depth in the second essay and brings in examples from immigrant communities in Spain and Germany as well. 
 
Theoretical issues und erpinning the content: 
 
National identity 
Hip hop and globalization 
Spaces of hip hop 
Generational differences 
Integration and resistance</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 13:  
 
Part 1: Photographs in Urban Planning 
 
Summary: 
 
During the first half of class, discussi on focused on a draft work-in-progress 
written and presented by Steve Moga. His work explored the subject of 
photography and how it can be used to impact the work of planners. He 
presented a series of photographs t hat he had encountered while he was 
working with the photography collections at the Los Angeles Public Library. 
Discussion focused on the issues that arise from photography: who is seeing, 
what is being shown, how it is reality, how  it is a manipulation of reality, etc. and 
how those issues impact planners who wo rk with photographs as documents and 
photography as a tool.  
 
 
Theoretical issues und erpinning the content: 
The observer vs. the observed 
Truth vs. ideology 
Aesthetic versus documentary nature of photography 
Text vs. context 
 Roland Barthes theories as expressed in Camera Lucida 
 
 
Example Photographers: 
 
Walker Evans 
Robert Frank 
Jacob Riis 
Lewis Hine 
Dorothea Lange</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Up/Down vs. Above/Below</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>- The issue the piece raises is: What are the limits of buildings in shaping 
the experience of someone else? How powerful is the built environment in 
shaping people? 
o Has profound implications for the design profession 
o Response 1: Negative Determinism: Design can prevent humans 
from hurting themselves but cannot actualize them 
o Response 2: Objectivism: A des igner must act on his/her own 
experience and not on the experience of others.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 3: Up vs. Down 
 
The class discussed the theoretical posit ions presented in student responses to 
the second assignment. Student volunteers read aloud their responses, and the 
class was asked to react to the papers. Issues raised in the discussion are listed 
below. 
 
Paper 1 - Lara Belkind:  
- The paper gave the classic story of t he evolution of the meaning of up and 
down as a power relationship 
o At one time (pre 20th c.), being near the grou nd but not on it allowed 
for the dramatization of power  
o Later (20th c.), removal from the ground plane and the visual 
dramatization became an expression of power 
- This experience can be made sense of in terms of cones of vision 
- Morphology plays a role in the relationship 
- The role of technologies in getting up and how they influenced the change 
in the dynamic of power was discuss ed (e.g. the elevator, the airplane) 
- Even in the 20th c. there is still a notion t hat being above is not simply an 
escape: 
o Pan-optic control exists through vision. 
- An alternate view of down (her e presented as degraded space) can be 
found in Roman culture, where below  was a significant symbolically 
orienting direction. 
o This led to a discussion of the difference between the Greek and 
Roman concepts of the grid: 
 Greek: each place in the grid is  equal in value to all other 
places; 
 Roman: certain places in a grid are of greater symbolic 
importance than others.  
 
Paper 2  Annis Whitlow: 
- Her theoretical project explored th e subjects percept ion of itself 
o Up: self-magnification 
o Ground: contingency 
o Down: self-protection 
- This is a procedure of how Simmel described the mental life of the 
metropolis. 
- The underlying assumption is that humans have an interpretive dynamic, 
that they carry a measure of internal tools they apply to specific conditions 
- Discussion of the revulsion of the o versocialized view of man (Dennis 
Wrong).  
o Ian Hacking wrote The Social Construction of What? , which 
discusses the limits of social construction</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Inventing the Modern Suburb in California and Denmark - Thomas Oles</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn11_oles/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 11: "Inventing the Modern Suburb in Californi a and Denmark: Sunset 
and Bo Bedre , 1960-1970" and Note Toward a Theory of Enclosure  
 
Summary: 
 
The class discussed a draft work-in-progr ess written and presented by Thomas 
Oles. His main work, Inventing the Moder n Suburb in California and Denmark, 
examines the differences in how two places embraced Modernism in very 
different terms during the 1960s and how  the major magazine of each place 
prompted and shaped its develop ment of Modernist subur bia. The second essay, 
Note Toward a Theory of Enclosure tackles the more elusive question of how to 
design an enclosure typology that embrac es differences amongst members of a 
community. The class discussion focused primarily on the second essay and the question of how patterns of enclosure can stifle a communitys ability to absorb 
and support population diversity.   
 
 
Theoretical issues und erpinning the content: 
 
- Enclosure vs. Boundary 
- Biological: Border vs. Boundary (Stephen J. Gould) 
o Active edges 
- Inside vs. Outside 
o Who is trying to enter? 
o Who is inside? 
o The child in space 
- The Democratic Enclosure 
- Transparency and Opacity 
- Liminal Boundaries 
o John Randal McDonald: Postori no/Erickson Houses; Racine, WI, 
1953. 
o Does this create a sense of liminal difference? 
- The hedge as social contract 
 
.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Stealth Gentrification - Lara Belkind</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn5_belkind/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 5: Stealth Gentrification: Ca mouflage and Commerce on the Lower East 
Side 
 
The class discussed a draft work-in-pr ogress written and presented by the 
student Lara Belkind. Lara pr ovided a summary presentation of her work, which 
looked at the way that artists and represent atives of counter-culture have subtly 
transformed marginal neighborhoods into sites of gentrification by appropriating 
the urban form of those communities to give themselves authenticity as people 
outside the mainstream cult ure. Students were asked to  comment on, criticize, 
and present their questions about the theor etical content of the piece.  
 
Theoretical issues und erpinning the content: 
- Authenticity: What does it mean to be authentic?  
- Mediation: What is being m ediated? Who is mediating? 
- Invisibility  
- Center vs. Periphery (vertical/horizontal) 
- Boundary</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Racial Politics of Urban Celebrations - Annis Whitlow</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn8_whitlow/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 8: "The Racial Politics of Urban Celebrations: A Com parative Study of 
Philadelphias Mummers Parade and Odunde Festival"  
 
Abstract: 
 
Discourses about the constructi on of identity, the politics of identity, and the role 
of design in controlling human behavior and expressing power have thus far 
been confined to separate realms of inquiry . This thesis will examine where these 
discourses intersect and how their inters ection plays out in society as old 
conceptions of race and identity are challenged by demographic shifts and new 
immigrant populations. Festival s, as spatial expressions of identity that image city 
spaces, provide an important perspective on this topic. Philadelp hia, as a former 
capital city that continues to struggle with race and identity in its politics, acts as 
a compelling backdrop for my case  studies. The Mummers Parade and the 
Odunde Festival are two New Ye ars celebrations that m ediate racial/political and 
ethnic/cultural identities fo r the citys white and bla ck populations respectively. 
This thesis considers both festivals fr om their historical context and compares 
their current form in terms of spat ial and non-spatial indicators (route, 
demographics, funding, and organizational structure) . From this analytic 
framework emerges a picture of how political identities are constructed spatially, 
how the process of identity construc tion both challenges and reinforces the 
dominant political structure,  and how the process can br idge political differences 
and maintain them. 
 
 
Theoretical issues und erpinning the content: 
 
- Sociological/Anthropological t heory can structure the phenomenon 
observed in the thesis. 
o Rituals of space and inequality 
 Dramaturgical sociology 
 Masks and Inverted Domination 
 Role Playing 
 Rituals of Recovery 
o Ritual vs. Spectacle 
 Ritual is identity  
 Spectacle is a debasement of public life</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Center vs. Periphery</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 2: Center vs. Periphery 
 
The class focused on developing the theor etical arguments presented in student 
responses to the first assignment. Student volunteers read aloud their responses, 
and the class was asked to discuss their theoretical propositions and arguments 
around a set of basic questions: 
 
1. What are the underlying assumptions that this argument relies on? 
2. Are additional criteria needed to strengthen the argument? 
3. What challenges to the theoretical  propositions in the argument need to be 
addressed in its elaboration? 
4. How do the arguments di ffer from one another?  
5. What common ground do the differ ent arguments share, if any?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Spaces of Knowledge within the New York City Subway - Elliott Felix</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn6_felix/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 6: Between Production and Consumpt ion: Spaces of Knowledge within 
the New York City Subway.  
 
The class discussed a draft work-in-pr ogress written and presented by student 
Elliot Felix. Elliot provided a summary presentation of his work, a text that 
provides theoretical basis for his current Masters thesis in Architectural Design. 
He began by describing the city through its multiplicity leading to specialization, 
(over)stimulation, and a kind of intellect ual grayness in which one has more 
allegiance to pace than place.  These c onditions lead to a heightened awareness 
of difference and of Self versus  Other and thus an understanding of the 
stranger as a kind of permanent condition of the city - you are always a stranger 
to someone, and you are always surrounded by  those who are strangers to you. 
He then posited that the New York City Subway system functions as a 
intensification of that city  in terms of move ment, artificiality,  disorientation, and 
dislocation, and as an underground space, the subway can be thought of as a 
prophetic condition providing a glimpse of  what is to come above-grade in terms 
of how people relate to each other and their environment. Toward this end, he 
proposed taking unused or vestigial subway platforms within currently operating stations and transforming them into s paces of knowledge production and 
consumption in a new kind of public lib rary that would leverage the existing 
culture of reading on the subway, provi de places of interaction among people 
and artifacts, and further the democratization of knowledge. 
 
 
Theoretical issues und erpinning the content: 
 
- The stranger and the uncanny 
- The prophetic nature of underground activity 
- Knowledge vs. information 
- Mobility  Social and Physical 
- Democratization of K nowledge/content Production 
- Design: Form vs. Program 
 
Important Questions: 
 
1. Is the notion of the stranger a producti ve way in to larger ideas about the 
city? If not, how might the design thin king be better related to these larger 
ideas? 
2. Is this an opportunity to make more  libraries or is the end-point of the 
design for people to learn more about the subway (and by the same token about other libraries)? 
3. Is it a purely a reflexi ve project? Does it matter  what is inserted into the 
subway context or that its a library or does the mere insertion of anything 
aberrant tell one something about that thing and the subway?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>4. How does one inspire peopl e (with architecture) to get more knowledge? 
5. Can the subway be underst ood as a communication system?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Theorizing a Center for Universal Design - Nadya Nilina</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn7_nilina/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 7: Theorizing a Center for Universal Design. 
 
This class session embarked on the project of working from a design brief to a 
theoretical proposition underpinning the project. Nadya Nilina presented the brief 
from which she is building her M.Arch  thesis project: a request for design 
proposals for an art center on Roosevelt Island in the East River between 
Manhattan and Queens that would be universa lly accessible to patients at the 
Coler-Goldwater Hospital, the Roosevelt Island Visual Arts Society, and other 
residents wishing to use the facilities. The site is at the sout hern tip of the Island 
in the ruins of the Smallpox Hospital, which was closed in 1955. Class discussion examined the issue of universal access; individual versus collective spaces, and 
how to create limits for the design project.  
 
 
Theoretical issues und erpinning the content: 
- Universal vs. Democratic 
o Inclusion vs. Participation 
- Exposure (of disability) vs. Integrat ion (of disabled) vs. Distraction (from 
disability) 
- Reversal: creating a universally unpleasant space 
- Independence and isolation 
o How to design for community? 
- Sennett, The Fall of Public Man  
o Haussmans Parisian streets 
o Serendipity can follow sweeping gestures</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>c. Difference Theory 
ii. Deals with the question How can we get unlike people to 
share a common culture? 
iii. Pierre Bourdieu: The process by which people distinguish 
themselves is a kind of constr uctivism, an act of establishing 
inequality and contest. 
1. The Misery of the World is a study of how people at 
the bottom of the economic  ladder use the built 
environment to distinguish themselves culturally. 
d. Critical Realism  The Frankfurt School  
i. Walter Benjamin: The city o ffers a space of display that 
invites the eye to criticize.  
1. The data we have for a critique of society must be 
displayed in some imagistic form such that the image 
is the site for criticism of the city. 
ii. Foucault takes this up and subverts it by claiming that the 
eye is incapable of functioning as a critical organ.  
e. Two additional movements are relevant but havent been taken up 
by sociology: 
i. Natural Communities Theory (Biology) 
1. Founder: Humberto Maturana 
2. Emphasizes the natural world of the city and the 
ecology of man-made communities 
3. It is currently highly biol ogical and not yet taken up by 
sociologists 
ii. Narrative Theory (Humanities) 
1. When we talk about the relationship between time 
and place, time has no agency in telling stories, i.e. 
no person or persons are active in the telling. 
 
Collaborative Student Work 
1. This course is intended to teach students not simply how to read theory 
and discuss theorists as subjects, but rather to help them develop 
themselves as thinkers and writers. 
a. We will use this seminar as a workshop for students works in 
progress.  
i. We will work out the theoretical  implications of each others 
work as a group 
ii. We will function as a works hop rather than a lit review 
b. We will grapple with what is theoret ically at stake: i.e. how do you 
move from a theoretical proposit ion into the realm of cities? 
2. I would like to get the seminar invo lved in the network in Europe as well. 
Students should remain connected to this  group even after the semester is 
over.  
3. The purpose is to enable the current  generation of urbanists to become 
public intellectuals through:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>a. Communicating with others 
b. Learning to be collaborative  rather than competitive 
c. Learning how to be colleagues</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>d. All were recovering from Marx ism and its inability to address the 
condition of the city. 
i. All three schools have focused more on space than on built 
form (i.e. they are more about geography than architecture). 
ii. They attempt to imagine the city as space, not solid 
substance. 
iii. They have exhausted this path of inquiry. 
b. A new line of inquiry can now  be opened that deals not with space, 
but with built form.  
i. Its questions include: 
1. What is a just factory office? 
2. What is a school building that improves education? 
3. What is a democratic window? 
ii. In my own work, I am trying to deal with how theory can deal 
with things rather than location. 
iii. If the last century of thinki ng has been characterized by the 
tendency to dematerialize the city, disembody it, this new 
project aims to rematerialize our understanding of cities by 
focusing on built form.  
3. Part 2: Cities have best engaged 4 types of theorizing: 
a. Marxism 
i. It makes claims about the materi al word that social scientists 
must take seriously (unlike Adam Smiths theories, which 
focused on process) 
ii. Its irony is that while it pr ovides an analysis of what goes 
wrong in the capitalist city, it does not provide any vision for 
an ideal Communist city 
iii. The emergence of Post Coloni al theorists in the 1960s who 
equated cities with colonization short circuited Marxist theory 
away from the idea of the cosmopolitan as a project for 
Communism 
b. Public Realm Theory 
i. 3 versions of the public realm: 
1. Juergen Habermas (derived from Weber): the public 
realm is constituted by the ways people reason about their social/economic/gender/etc. status. 
2. Hannah Arendt: eschews the notion of identity in the 
city. The city is a place where people ideally ought to be equal because they are strangers to one another. 
Actual identity is unknown, so it should not bring 
about inequalities in the public realm.  
3. Walter Benjamin: A dram aturgical approach to the 
public realm that emphas izes the conditions under 
which strangers become expressive to one another in 
crowds. The public realm is a place of presence and 
display rather than a place of decision making.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 1: Introduction to the Class 
 
Instructor Background: 
 
Richard Sennett is Chair of the Citie s Program at t he London School of 
Economics (LSE). He has begun a joint appointment that allows him to spend his 
fall semesters at MIT teaching this cour se. His presence here is part of an effort 
to bring MIT into a network of urban studies scholars based in schools around Europe.  
 
Course Introduction: 
 
This course is a seminar on social theory and the city. It will not be a set of 
lectures but rather will be driven prim arily by discussion and student input. The 
class itself is loosely structured into 3 parts: 
1. Theory of the City 
2. Map of Theoretical Issues 
3. Collaborative Student Work 
 
Theory of the City 
1. Why is theory an issue? Why is it necessary?  
a. Because most social practi ces are unknowing, or tacit.  
i. Michael Polanyis idea of  tacit practices argued that 
practices that are a part of moving in space, working through 
boundaries and groups dont become habits but knowledge 
practices that dont need to be examined.  
b. Urban conditions depend on this tacit knowledge 
i. There is little discursive interaction between strangers in 
cities. It is not necessary fo r people to tell each other what 
they are doing and why. 
ii. Urban space is regulated through willed unknowing.  
iii. Order is created by relying on keeping things tacit. 
c. Theorys role is to force into ex plicit discussion these tacit habits: to 
make explicit what is held tacit. 
i. Theory  in scare quotes  is a highly undemocratic and 
self-referential activity.  
1. Its role is to close o ff discussion from the mass of 
people involved in the unknowing practices discussed. 
2. It is characterized by oppression and fear. 
ii. Theory, in this new conc eption, requires a political 
commitment to reveal and expos e tacit practices without 
humiliation. 
1. Doing theory is a project of expression that</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>a. Puts an enormous burden on the person doing 
it, and 
b. Creates a profound ethical / political dilemma: 
How do you theorize  make explicit that which 
is tacit  without humiliating those who are 
engaged in the unknowing, tacit practices? 
 
Mapping Urban Theory (as it now exists) 
1. The discourse about what cities are in terms of social and political theory 
is only about 1 century old. 
a. Though cities are thousands of years old, changes in the last 
century meant that moder n cities have no real reference in terms of 
scale and politics to what had come before. 
2. Part 1: 3 schools of urban studies  took form over the century: 
a. The Berlin School 
i. Max Weber, Georg Simmel (T.A. to Weber), and Walter 
Benjamin 
ii. Not marked by one shared philosophical pre-supposition 
iii. The experience of Berlin itself gave rise to 3 sets of 
foundational problems: 
1. Weber: The relationship between urban places and 
the status of law.  
c. Rights and place are tied to cities. 
2. Simmel: The city as a point  of reflection of sociology 
3. Benjamin: The city as a site for thinking about 
narrative cultural practice s and narrative imaging. 
b. The Chicago School (at the University of Chicago before WWI) 
i. Founder: Robert Park, a journalist who studied with Simmel 
in Germany. Included Louis Wirth and Ernest Burgess (who 
generated the study of urban ecology) 
1. The School looks at the spatializing of social and 
economic differences. 
2. Its theoretical proposition:  How territory cuts loose 
from natural difference; how social and economic 
differences are imposed on the natural geography of 
the place; how traditional ideas in social / political theory get instantiated. 
c. The Paris School (1950s  1970s) 
i. Major players : 
1. Henri Lefebvre  tried to create democratic socialism 
using the city as a space of production ;  
2. Guy Debord and the Situationists  a rebellion against 
the Communist left ;  
3. Michel de Certeau  a priest who passed through the 
Communist party ; and  
4. Michel Foucault  a deeply anti-Marxist thinker.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Structuring Beyond Architecture - David Foxe</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-329-social-theory-and-the-city-fall-2005/resources/ssn9_foxe/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.329 Social Theory and the City 
 
Session 9: Structuring Beyond Architectu re  DRAFT, M.Arch Thesis, David M. 
Foxe 
 
Abstract: 
 
This project investigates ways to  conceive and design positive 
relationships between internal structure and the urban realm ; to analyze 
how the structuring of i ndividual projects can cont ribute to the whole of 
communities and cities rather than remain ing isolated resolutions of internal 
concerns. Often infrastructure   literally something which is beyond the scale of a 
typical structure  is conceived within  the realm of engineering, and tasks of 
structural design are ther efore isolated into discr ete, optimized solutions. 
Drawing on precedents of Te chnological Modernism at  various scales, this 
project seeks to focus on how  individual architectural works can use the process 
and design of structure to become catalysts beyond their literal limits, to show the 
importance of structuring beyond architecture .  
 
Under this framework structural technol ogy becomes a means for elements of 
architectural design to become inter dependent, and therefore greater than their 
sum, rather than a collection of independ ent, unrelated ideas. This investigation 
thus situates the role of technology wit hin a proposal for arch itectural quality at 
the intersection of value structures, physical structures, and urban structures. 
Architecture is therefor e the boundary, the liminal space between the scales of 
structure within a place, and urban life beyond a project.  
 
Examples cited in thesis proposal: 
Unit Block System by Alden Dow 
Monsanto House of the Future 
Shore (Belt) Parkway, Brooklyn, NY 
by Robert Moses/Aymar Embury/Gilmore Clarke 
Spodek and other works by Waclaw Zalewski 
Milwaukee Art Museum by Santiago Calatrava 
 
Theoretical issues underpi nning the content through the course of the discussion: 
 
- Form as a result of me tamorphosis vs. rupture 
o Rupture as a reversal 
o Resiliency of physical/political power 
o Designed rupture as a statement 
 Is rupture always a bad thing? 
 Lefebrve: Build social fabric through conflict 
 Coser: Conflict creates stronger bonds than 
agreement 
o Possibilities for meta morphosis as organicism</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>o Biological models, not biological forms 
- Physicality of form and memory 
- What are the norms? What is the community (that is being impacted by 
the structures)? Consider (and per haps contrast) these various other 
approaches: 
o Christopher Alexander. A Pattern Language:  Towns, Buildings, 
Construction . New York, NY: Oxford University Press, 1977. ISBN: 
0195019199.  
o William Whyte. City: Redisco vering the Center. New York, 
NY: Doubleday, 1988. ISBN: 0385054580.  
- The degree to which dissonance is built into design  
- Form as a result of process.   
 
Focal Examples: 
- Les Halles, Paris 
- Markets generally 
 
Suggested Exercise: 
Take the theoretical proposit ions of the piece and order them using no examples. 
Can the theory hold itself up through thes e propositions alone? What is the logic 
that emerges from these propositions?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
