<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-089-technology-and-innovation-in-africa-fall-2014/</course_url>
    <course_title>Technology and Innovation in Africa</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>History </list>
      <list>Innovation </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Textiles (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-089-technology-and-innovation-in-africa-fall-2014/resources/mitsts_089f14_lecture5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>STS.089    Technology  and  Innovation  in  Africa	 	 Fall  14  
Lecture  5  - Textiles  and  Cotton  (Qutn)  
Prof.  Clapperton  Chakanetsa  Mavhunga	 	 MIT  OpenCourseWare  
Intro:  Cotton  &amp;  Cotton  Textile  Production  
	 	 What  arguments  were  advanced  by  Chivalier  and  Dalziel?  
	 	 Chivalier:  social  and  economic  history  as  history  of  technology  
	 	 Dalziel:  the  incoming  and  locally  originated  (spinners,  weaver,  dyers,  tailors,  and  embroiderers)  
	 	 What  three  aspects  does  Colleen  E.  Kriegers  article  focus  on?  
	 	 sources  of  evidences  what  sorts  of  evidence  does  the  author  use?  
  dating
 
 
  observations
 
 
Africa  and  the  History  of  Old  World  Cotton  (Gossypium  Herbaceum )  
	 	 Questions  from  readings  
	 	 What  were  I.B.  Hutchinsons  speculations  on  the  origins  of  cotton  varieties?  
	 	 In  1954:  he  speculated  that  the  plant  was  indigenous  to  southern  Africa  but  Arabs  discovered  
it  and  took  it  back  to  Arabia  for  domestication.  
	 	 in  1974,  another  speculation:  there  were  two  species,  Gossypium  arboretum  and  Gossypium  
herbaceum ,  domesticated  from  the  same  wild  ancestor.  Herbaceum  domesticated  in  Ara
bia/Baluchistan  from  a  wild  ancestor  the  knowledge  then  diused  from  there  into  Africa.  
	 	 What  is  the  status  of  the  research  now  and  what  do  these  speculations  say  about  images  of  Africa?  
	 	 The  state  of  research  by  non-Africans,  of  course  supports  this,  and  that  herbaceum  was  
domesticated  in  3,000  BC.  
	 	 Scholars  pick  and  choose  from  Hutchinsons  two  positions,  even  adding  arrows  on  his  maps  
to  show  diusion  pathways  of  the  two  cotton  species  entering  sub-Saharan  Africa  via  the  
southern  Arabia  and  the  Red  Sea.  
	 	 What  does  Kriger  say  to  this?  
	 	 Diusions  are  far  too  simplistic  
	 	 Questions  of  sources:  Nubia  and  Meroe  
	 	 The  earliest  radio-carbon  cotton  dates  from  Nubia  in  the  Nile  Valley  (there  are  lint-bearing  seeds  
and  cotton  ber  dating  back  to  2600-2400  BCE,  but  no  evidence  of  cotton  textile  use  or  manu
facturing  until  much  later)  
	 	 Dates  for  Meroe:  280  BCE  to  350-540  CE  many  textile  fragments;  could  have  been  logical  made  
or  imported,  grown  or  wild.  We  just  wont  know.  Kroger  speculates  that  cotton  was  grown,  
spun,  and  woven  in  North  Africa  in  300  BCE  - 400  CE.  
	 	 To  most  scholars,  Africa  is  a  continent  where  everything  that  is  good  is  supposed  to  have  come  
from  outside:  from  the  Levant  or  from  Europe  to  North  Africa  because  of  its  accessibility  by  land  
to  the  east,  the  seed  of  civilization  was  always  thought  to  have  then  spread  from  there  to  West  
and  Southern  Africa.  But  this  diusionist  speculation  is  now  doubted.  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
STS.089 Technology and Innovation in Africa
Fall 2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lecture  5	 	 Textiles  and  Cotton  (Qutn)  STS.089,  Fall  14  
	 	 The  rise  and  spread  of  Islam  (6th  - 9th  CE)  was  the  lighting  rod,  it  is  said,  for  the  spread  of  
cotton  from  Nubia  and  Aksum  (Ethiopia)  to  West  Africa.  
	 	 Two  centers  of  cotton  production  in  West  Africa,  ca.  900-1500  
	 	 Linguistic  evidence:  gathered  the  generic  words  for  cotton  in  126  West  African  languages  from  
dictionaries,  word  lists,  and  botanical  sources  showed  that  there  were  at  least  two  distinct  centers  
of  early  cotton  production  in  West  Africa,  around  the  10th  century:  
1.  Cluster  of  Niger-Gambia-Senegal  watersheds  and  areas  contiguous  to  the  Sahel  
2.  Around  Lake  Chad  
	 	 Fit  perfectly  within  the  ight  path  of  Watsons  routes  of  crop  diusion  during  the  Islamic  period  
before  1500.  In  a  sense,  this  highlights  the  role  of  human  mobilities  as  a  carrier  of  technology.  
Textile  Manufacturing  in  West  Africa  
	 	 Archaeology  shows  cotton  manufacture  in  West  Africa  by  at  least  the  11th  century.  
	 	 Written  accounts  of  travelers  like  the  Andalusian  al-Bakri  (1068)  gave  us  the  rst  description  of  cotton  
manufacturing  in  West  Africa;  cloth  was  used  as  currency.  
	 	 It  was  made  not  from  cotton  crop  grown  in  the  elds  but  the  cotton  tree,  a  perennial.  
	 	 Spinning  was  done  entirely  by  hand.  
	 	 Cotton  was  one  of  many  materials.  Others  were  wood,  silk,  leather,  grass,  bark,  palm  leaf  cloth.  To  
make  the  kyenkyen  cloth  in  Asante,  for  example,  they  would  soak  and  pound  the  inner  bark  of  a  
particular  tree  species.  
	 	 Treadle  looms  on  the  Ivory  and  upper  Guinea  coats  
	 	 by  the  16th-18th  centuries,  Cabo  Verde  islands  manufacturers  were  famous.  
	 	 African  cotton  and  indigo  was  commercialized  into  plantations  worked  by  enslaved  Africans,  which  
then  exported  cotton  to  the  Gambia,  Casamance,  and  Cacheu  Rivers.  
	 	 relied  on  enslaved  Africans  indigenous  knowledge  and  techniques  to  scale  up  from  mere  crop  
production  to  spinning,  dyeing,  and  weaving.  
	 	 Indigo  dyeing  was  popular,  too,  and  techniques  in  dyeing  continued  to  shift.  
Discussion:  European  Travelers  Bear  Witness  to  African  technological  innova
tions  
	 	 Cadamosto  on  the  Gambia  (1456):  witnessed  raw  ber,  handspan  thread,  and  handwoven  textiles  with  
locally  grown  cotton.  Elites  wore  cotton  clothes  and  commoners  wore  goatskin,  which  were  either  plain  
white  or  loom-patterned  with  stripes  of  blue  or  red  yarns.  
	 	 Pacheco  Pereira  in  Sierra  Leone  (1490s):  cotton  grown  on  the  Cabo  Verde  islands  using  enslaved  
Africans  exchanged  for  animal  skins,  palm  oil,  and  unusually  colored  shells.  
	 	 incoming  trade  and  local  textile  industry:  cloth  imported,  but  also  woven  locally  on  a  vertical  loom  
	 	 exported  to  markets  on  Gold  Coast,  Gabon,  Angol,  Sao  Tome,  West  Indies,  and  Brazil;  striped  cloth  
exchanged  for  gold  on  the  Gold  Coast,  indigo-blue  cloth  exchanged  for  ivory  and  captured  Africans  in  
Gabon  and  Angola  
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Books &amp; Letters (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-089-technology-and-innovation-in-africa-fall-2014/resources/mitsts_089f14_lecture22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 22 Books: From Tools of Empire to Tools of Self-Liberation STS.089, Fall 14 
Basutoland, two schools with a reputation for academic excellence. There was much self-criticism, calls for 
more teachers, less evangelists, and African demands for a better curriculum on the Lovedale and Booker T. 
Washington or Tuskegee model. In 1902, Rev Peter Kawa of the Church of England: 
We want that system of education which recognises the fact that there is dignity in labour, 
and we detest that system, where all the educated natives are expected to be either missionaries 
or school masters.... We want practical schools rather than these too many Normal Institutions. 
We prefer Agricultural Schools, where our Native youths would be led to follow the agricultural 
pursuits. I am not averse to literary education, and am strongly of opinion that these native lads 
who are able, should be taught the higher branches of study; for minds are not all alike... Let 
giant intellects have by all means what is generally termed Higher Education, but let the masses 
be taught to make bricks, tables, dishes, wagons, shoes, and above all let them be thorough with 
their spade and ploughs. 
And one Motswana chief summed it all up nicely: The book learning is no help to give to the people to live; 
the books told us some of the things which we may expect when we...die... Now we nd what is to be done 
and what the books mean; a new prospect is now opened before us. 
Industrial Education: Booker T. Washington in Africa 
Booker T. Washington (1856-1915), founder and principal of Tuskegee Normal Industrial Institute, Alabama, 
and an African-American, was convinced his self-help and industrial education philosophy was what blacks 
in Africa required to get civilized through individual initiative and instruction in the principles of a higher 
moral life. 
For him, the native of Africa, had to come to the tree of civilization, Tuskegee, and see, learn, return, 
and transplant the seed. Enthralled by this message, politically active and educated black elites in South 
Africa traveled to Tuskegee in the 1890s and 1900s to eat the fruit at source. ANC political organizer, Pixley 
Seme, captured the mood in a letter to Booker T: We need your spirit in Africa. The central gure in 
this exchange was John Langalibalele Dube, Zulu educator, rst ANC president, who visited Tuskegee in 
1897. When introduced to an audience and asked to say a few words, he declared: The greatest need of 
my people is industrial education. And Washington found Dube superior material to take on an energetic 
Christian civilization, someone who saw a pragmatic alliance with white paternalists in SA as essential for 
black economic participation in society and eventual political equality. 
Dube went on to establish his own institute: the Zulu Christian Industrial School, in 1901, outside Durban. 
Students wanting to enroll rst toiled in the institutes 30-acre elds growing ground nuts, corn, potatoes, 
bananas, beans, oranges, and peaches to pay their teachers salaries. They learned arithmetic and English 
to be able to function in the workplace, and gave a certain amount of labor to the Institute during their 
enrollment. John Dubes motto was: As in Booker Ts institution, so here... no money is expended for out
side labor which the pupils can be made to do for themselves. He also went on to establish a Zulu language 
newspaper, Ilanga lase Natal , to articulate black issues and advance the industrial education ethos. 
Lets be clear about why Booker Ts model was popular in Africa among the colonial authorities. 
The school was a site for the engineering of African children into disciplined (read: subservient) colonial 
subjects. Children were made to recite racist poems like Bongwi the Baboon, sing Christopher Columbus 
was a Great Man who went to America on a sauce pan, serenade David Livingstone, the great man who 
discovered the Mosi oa Tunya (Victoria Falls), and understand the valungu (whites) truth that the black 
person had no history (Chinodya 1989). Ocial games like PT (physical training), soccer (boys), netball 
(girls), running or athletics (boys and girls), high, long, and triple jump, and choir or singing comprised the 
staple of inter-house (intra-school) and inter-school competitions. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>STS.089  Technology and Innovation in Africa Fall 14 
Lecture 22 - Books: From Tools of Empire to Tools of Self-Liberation 
Prof. Clapperton Chakanetsa Mavhunga MIT OpenCourseWare 
Those of us who grew up in rural Africa see the home, the village, the mountains, the valleys, and the rivers 
as educational and technological spaces where these innovations occurred on a daily basis. Such spaces are 
indeed the universities, the laboratories, or the factories of psychomotor activities within which many of 
Africas leaders in politics, business, academia, sport, music, and many other endeavors are raised. The 
valley where children herd cattle, the pools where they sh, the forests in which they hunt and pick fruit, the 
dusty streets where they play with their self-made plastic football all these are sites in which the African 
child is taught critical life skills through showing and doing, but not the exam or the pen. Out of them arises 
a spirit of experiment, adventure, risk-taking, and ambition, inspired by a desire to escape grinding realities 
of being born poor through sheer hard work and seeking answers in novelty even while ones feet are rmly 
planted in the elastic cultural traditions of ones ancestors. 
The Coming of European Education: What Happened to this Prac
tical Education? 
If we listen to Robert Moat, writing in 1833, there is doubt where the blame should go: Their intellectual 
faculties seem so benumbed that it is astonishing to see how destitute they are of the principle of curiosity. 
This, of course, is easily accounted for from their habits of indolence and sensuality. (Moat in Chirenje, 
1833). Failure, therefore, was a result of the dull carnal apathy of a race sunk in sensuality. 
The British and the Germans considered even a minimal ability to read the scriptures the height of ed
ucational achievement. Girls outnumbered boys in LMS schools throughout the nineteenth century, as boys 
were required to go to the seasonal cattle posts while household chores kept the girls nearer home. School 
attendance was irregular because of household chores, pastoral, agricultural (heading cattle, watching over 
grain crops elds besieged by birds); the curriculum too detached from the values and economy of Africans 
just too bookish to make any tangible sense. By 1900, only two thousand people were full members of 
the LMS church out of a population of over one hundred thousand a sizeable number of Christians and 
traditionalists sent their children to LMS schools. For the latter, the white mans schools only supplemented 
the traditional education process which culminated in the initiation (bogwera for boys and bqjale for girls) 
and was indispensable to the transition from youth to adulthood. They brought with it pride and traditional 
wisdom; children who chose to become bathu balehuku (children of the book) and refused to participate 
in the ceremonies were venerated by the bathu balechulo (traditionalists) and caused considerable friction in 
Tswana households (Moat). 
The LMS tried to improve the quality of education by opening a teacher training school for evangelists 
at Kuruman in 1872. But the number of its graduates remained small and of low caliber for the rest of the 
nineteenth century; none of the Kuruman graduates became teachers. A report done in 1893 showed that all 
the twenty-seven students who had graduated since 1872 had left the profession. Some reverted to the more 
viable traditional occupations, such as cattle herding and game hunting; others drove wagons for whites or 
engaged in the lucrative business of conveying wood to the gold and diamond mines and ivory, feathers, and 
hides to various South African markets. 
Denied inuence in such matters as curriculum development, some Tswana parents expressed their dis
approval by keeping their children home. Those who could aord the $20 fee sometimes sent their children 
to Lovedale, run by the Free Church of Scotland at the Cape, and to the Paris Evangelicals Morija in 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 22 Books: From Tools of Empire to Tools of Self-Liberation STS.089, Fall 14 
As social engineering tool, Native or Bantu Education was designed for the uncivilized (blacks), and 
to mark their dierences from the civilized (whites). In one race, a child was born uncivilized; in another, 
a child was born civilized. Education had to be beaten into the uncivilized, hence corporal punishment was 
applied instead of persuasive incentive in white schools. The white education ocers encouraged physical as
saults of children in the name of discipline. Colonialized as well as patriarchal parents encouraged it (Matibe 
2009). This was a substantial dierence with indigenous knowledge. 
Turning the Colonizers Tools into Instruments of Self-Liberation 
Booker Ts other famous prot eg e was Davidson Jabavu, educationist, graduate of University of London. 
In 1913, the South African Minister of Native Aairs commissioned Jabavu to go and study the methods 
being used at Tuskegee with a view of adopting them in connection with the education of the natives of 
South Africa. Jabavu would be a key gure in founding South Africas biggest Tuskegee, the National 
College at Fort Hare, todays University of Fort Hare, the laboratory that would churn out many an African 
leader in the 1930s-50s, including Nelson Mandela, Albert Luthuli, Tanzanias Julius Nyerere, Botswanas 
Seretse Khama, Zambias Kenneth Kaunda, Zimbabwes Robert Mugabe, and Desmond Tutu as chaplain. 
Z. K. Matthews was one of the African faculty members from 1936 to 1958. Fort Hare was a melting pot of 
Christian convictions, communism, and Pan-Africanism; out of this concoction African nationalism emerged. 
The University of Fort Hare was the bridge between Black America and Black Africa. Visiting black in
tellectuals (African and African-American) from Howard, Fisk University (Nashville), Penn School (South 
Carolina), Hampton, and Tuskegee visited Fort Hare to lecture and debate issues of black struggle. 
Fort Hare was of course not unique. In Southern Rhodesia there was St. Faiths Farm in Mutasa, where 
Christianity, liberalism, and self-reliance met. In South Africa itself there was Lovedale, Adams College, 
and, of course, Dubes Industrial School. Adams, St. Faiths, and Fort Hare became hotbeds of African 
nationalism from the 1940s onwards. St. Faiths was shut down in 1959, only to resurrect as Cold Comfort 
Farm, which would itself be closed in 1964. 
Ironically, institutions like Fort Hare had been built to stem the spread of communism and anti-colonial 
resistance through an industrial education that frowned upon intellection, but ended up becoming hubs of 
Pan-Africanism and African nationalism. Booker Ts prot eg es Seme, Dube, and Jabavu had an anti-labor 
pro-capitalist, anti-Marx mentality; they were the black capitalists, who felt it was not their place for blacks 
to defer to protest in order to change society. Rather, they should equip themselves with the weapons to 
compete and outwit the white man at his game of civilization. Jabavu argued that Africans attracted to 
Bolshevism and revolution should be directed to a needed antidote the Young Mens Christian Association! 
And institutions like Fort Hare, designed for just such a purpose, became quite the opposite. Later on in 
the 1960s, this Christian Marxism would be very pronounced in the work not only of African nationalists, 
but also churches and individual priests supporting guerrillas and the masses struggling for independence. 
The World Council of Churches (WCC), Catholic Commission for Justice and Peace, the Catholic Institute 
for International Relations, and individual priests like Adrian Hastings (Mozambique) and Donal Lamont 
(Zimbabwe) are good examples. At the same time, some churches and bishops were passionately support
ive of colonial regimes and loathed national liberation movements, whom they dismissed as agents of the 
Anti-Christ (communism). 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
STS.089 Technology and Innovation in Africa
Fall 2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Music (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-089-technology-and-innovation-in-africa-fall-2014/resources/mitsts_089f14_lecture8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 8 Music STS.089, Fall 14 
meal). Food and material possessions did not substitute for collective belonging; and food and material 
possessions were contents of a vessel called ukama (community). That is why chivanhu (culture) said that 
vana vanyamunhu (children of the same ancestor) must eat, drink, work, and pray together. 
The collective was the water; only within it could the sh (the individual) nd strength, hence simba rehove 
riri mumvura (the shs strength is in the water). Then, like one organism, one body with many dierent 
but mutually coordinating parts, the village descended on the eld as one, each bringing their own mapadza 
(hoes) ready to weed and matemo (axes) ready to chop. The individual increased his or her mechanical 
means from a pair of hands to tens and hundreds of hands making the task light. 
Singing and song lubricated dicult work into fun and sport, pacing it, giving it rhythm, and taking the 
mind away from the arduous task, and placing it in a parallel universe of recreation and entertainment, 
thereby shutting it from communicating evil thought of nungo (laziness), kuzeza (dreading the task), and 
kuneta (tiredness). Singing transformed and coordinated this critical mass of individuals and their limbs 
into one vast organism marching in lockstep. The food provided the fuel for the body and mind to remain 
energized and to perform the work at hand. 
The release of beer to the workers was paced and dispensed in quantities designed to give them simba 
(strength) without driving them into kudhakwa (drunken stupor) that neutralized eciency. The volume 
of the singing picked up, powerful arms swung the hoe this way and that. Soon work became just another 
excuse, another occasion, to drink, eat, and party. Work became a medium of entertainment. Soon the work 
itself was nished, and there was only beer, food, and singing to be partaken. With the hand, feed, and 
body now freed from the small matter of hoeing, ngoma (drums), mbira (hand pianos), and hosho (percus
sion gourds) were brought out, magagada (ankle percussion gourds), and dancing headgears were brought out. 
The maridzahosho (expert drummers) and vanagwenyambira (expert mbira players) set store, and makate 
(beer pots, singular gate) came out, and the community danced late into the night. As each individual at 
long last retired home without any goodbyes (for adhakwa haaoneke /a person who is full/drunk does not say 
goodbye), they sang discordantly along the way home, staggering this way and that, their voices dragging, 
perhaps imitating the equally complicated striding of their beer-wizened feet. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
STS.089 Technology and Innovation in Africa
Fall 2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>STS.089  Technology and Innovation in Africa Fall 14 
Lecture 8 - Music 
Prof. Clapperton Chakanetsa Mavhunga MIT OpenCourseWare 
Europeans did not go deep into African music to understand its place in peoples lives as such. They looked 
for the melodic and rhythmic characteristics and the outward-looks signs (aesthetics). This tradition of 
looking and judging African music is particularly clear in the 18th-20th centuries. They saw it as largely 
pagan and worship of ancestral spirits, warlord, release of tensions and conict of everyday life. 
In the late-19th century, mobilizing African knowledge was used to conrm western anthropological thought: 
structure and function, labor, structure between young and old men for the control, production and sup
ply, women are held responsible, the controlling and dominant group of elders, challenging and emergent 
generation. Its this struggle between modernity and tradition. 
The Uses of Music Among the Tsonga 
Music is used in all of the following ways: the birth of a child, a marriage, a mans going hunting, the 
taking in of harvest, to help guide the moral order of society, to aid in the reduction of social stress, the 
announcement of eligibility of an individual (for pre-marital sex relations, for marriage, for passage to the 
spirit-world, etc.), group conviviality, the acquiring of prestige, the validation of power, the maintenance of 
lineage solidarity, and the disposal of maize surpluses. 
Music, dance, and drink are a rite of incorporate, of physical union, and a sacrament of communion. Hence the 
important of call and response the leader calling, the rest chorusing. There are childrens songs, drumming 
school songs, circumcision school songs, puberty school songs, exorcism songs, work songs, funeral songs, 
praise songs, epics, and solo instrumental music. The dances are xichayachaya for men, xilala for women, 
rhambela phikezano for both, but the Tsongas national dance is muchongolo which involved men and women. 
Non-work-related dances were conducted at specic times of the year, viz., after the harvest and before 
the planting to eh crops. They were to ask for fertility of everything from the ancestors and to thank them 
for it. Hence the Tsonga tipping the calabash and pouring contents onto the ground, chanting This is for 
the land! in reference to the earth that produces crops and in which the ancestors are buried. And the small 
ute or whistle (nanga ) is made of the leg-bone of chapungu , the bird-of-heaven or lightning bird (known as 
the battler eagle), because it zigzags, swooshes and swishes as it ies, in a whistling sound. This whistle, the 
Tsonga believe, possesses the power to bring rain and to protect the utes owner against lightning, which 
occurs regularly in this Southern African countryside. 
Among the Tsonga, communal vocal music and drumming would sour the beer so it was not to be held 
near where women were brewing beer from nkanyi or marula fruit. 
Music as Lubicant, Smoothening Hard Labor into Workatainment 
Also called nhimbe (chiShona) and humwe (in chiTshangana), jakwara (work party) was a day set aside for 
collective work to plant, weed, and harvest the elds of the orphaned, the widowed, the elderly, the poor, 
and the master farmer. Because chara chimwe hachitswanye inda (one nger cannot crush lice), it made 
sense to mobilize the community to create a large labor force. 
The beneciary of this collective labor brewed beer and hosted a work party to provide not only an in
centive to come but also the energy to continue working. Beer and food aplenty were served; after all, adage 
ukama igasva hunozadziswa nekudya (friendship is an empty calabash, it can only be lled up through a 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Food Production in Africa (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-089-technology-and-innovation-in-africa-fall-2014/resources/mitsts_089f14_lecture4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>STS.089  Technology and Innovation in Africa	 Fall 14 
Lecture 4 - Food Production in Africa
 
Rice: The Transatlantic Slave Trade as Technological Process
 
Prof. Clapperton Chakanetsa Mavhunga	 MIT OpenCourseWare 
Our special focus here is rice and how this crop made it to these shores. 
The Atlantic Slave Trade: Timeline 
	 	 1502 :  First  reported  African  slaves  in  the  New  World  
	 	 1640-1680 :  Large-scale  introduction  of  African  slave  labor  in  the  British  Caribbean  for  sugar  produc
tion  begins.  
	 	 1791 :  The  Haitian  Revolution  begins  
	 	 1794 :  The  French  National  Convention  emancipates  all  slaves  in  the  French  colonies  
	 	 1804 :  January  1:  The  Republic  of  Haiti  is  proclaimed  
	 	 1807 :  British  Parliament  bans  the  Atlantic  slave  trade  
	 	 1820 :  May  15:  U.S.  law  makes  slave  trading  piracy,  punishable  by  the  death  penalty,  dispatches  four  
vessels  to  patrol  the  coast  of  West  Africa  for  slaves.  This  lasted  four  months  and  was  recalled  after  
Anglo-American  disagreement.  
	 	 1831 :  A  large-scale  slave  revolt  breaks  out  in  Jamaica  brutally  repressed.  
	 	 1833 :  Great  Britain  passes  the  Abolition  of  Slavery  Act,  providing  for  emancipation  in  the  British  
West  Indes  set  to  take  eect  August  1834.  (Following  emancipation,  a  6  year  period  of  apprenticeship  
is  permitted.)  
	 	 1837 :  Britain  invites  the  U.S.  and  France  to  create  an  international  patrol  to  interdict  slaving.  The  
U.S.  declines  to  participate.  
	 	 1888 :  Slavery  abolished  in  Brazil,  ending  slavery  in  the  Americas.  
Slavery  in  America:  A  Selective  Timeline  
	 	 1619 :  First  Africans  arrive  in  Virginia  
	 	 1640-1680 :  Beginning  of  large-scale  introduction  of  African  slave  labor  in  the  British  Caribbean  for  
sugar  production  
	 	 1774 :  Connecticut  and  Rhode  Island  prohibit  further  importation  of  slaves  (although  Rhode  Island  
merchants  remain  in  slave  trade  to  other  colonies).  
	 	 1776 :  Society  of  Friends  (Quakers)  abolishes  slavery  among  members  
	 	 1777 :  Vermont  Constitution  prohibits  slavery  
	 	 1780 :  Massachusetts  Constitution  adopted  with  freedom  clause  interpreted  as  prohibiting  slavery.  
Pennsylvania  adopts  gradual  emancipation,  freeing  slaves  born  after  1780  upon  their  28th  birthday.  
	 	 1784 :  Connecticut  and  Rhode  Island  pass  gradual  emancipation  laws.  
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
STS.089 Technology and Innovation in Africa
Fall 2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lecture  4	 	 Food  Production  in  Africa  STS.089,  Fall  14  
	 	 1788 :  Connecticut  prohibits  residents  from  participating  in  slave  trade.  
	 	 1789 :  U.S.  Constitution  ratied  with  clause  equating  slaves  to  3/5ths  of  a  white  citizen  and  provision  
that  slave  trade  would  end  within  20  years.  
	 	 1793 :  Eli  Whitneys  invention  of  the  cotton  gin  sets  the  stage  for  expansion  of  slavery  in  the  American  
South  and  short-staple  cotton  becomes  an  economical  product.  
	 	 1798-1808 :  Decade  of  greatest  importation  of  African  slaves  into  U.S.,  totaling  approximately  200,000.  
The  transatlantic  slave  trade  was  not  only  a  traumatic  mobility  of  Africans  as  dehumanized  people  only,  but  
also  their  technologies  or  knowledge.  The  enslaved  Africans  were  being  captured  and  turned  into  exchange  
commodities  for  their  labor  value,  and  exported  across  the  Atlantic  as  such.  The  dehumanizing  nature  of  
this  trade  has  been  and  continues  to  be  explored.  
Triangular  trade  
The  slave  trade  was  one  site  of  a  trade  triangle,  which  went  as  follows:  
guns  were  invented  in  China    guns  were  perfected  in  Europe    guns  were  exported  to  Africa  to  buy  African  
captives  as  slaves    slaves  were  exported  to  the  Spanish,  Portuguese,  French,  and  English  colonies  to  grow  
crops  (namely  sugar,  tobacco,  and  cotton)  to  Europe  to  re  the  Industrial  Revolution    the  Industrial  
Revolution  produced  more  guns    guns  were  exported  to  Africa  to  buy  even  more  slaves  
The  Role  of  Music:  Lightening  the  Burden  of  Work  
My  concern  here  is  to  focus  more  on  the  mobility  of  ideas,  with  the  trade  acting  as  a  conveyor  belt  for  
the  transfer  of  technology  by  Africans  to  the  New  World.  This  enquiry  is  part  of  two  knowledge  mobilities:  
between  Africans  and  Europeans  and  Africans  and  Native  Americans.  This  was  so  because  Native  Americans  
and  enslaved  Africans  worked  in  the  plantations  side-by-side,  and  shared  agricultural  knowledge.  
The  plantation  elds  and  slave  quarters  are  most  revealing  about  the  cultural  innovations  Africans  brought  
from  Africa,  which  they  now  used  as  coping  devices  in  a  changed,  coercive  environment.  In  indigenous  
African  religion,  one  calls  his  or  her  ancestors  in  times  of  trouble  or  hardship,  and  asks  them  to  guide  the  
way.  After  triumph,  music,  religion,  and  celebration  also  go  together.  People  from  Cameroon,  the  Ivory  
Coast,  Guinea,  Cape  Verde,  and  Senegal  bought  their  beliefs  to  places  such  as  New  Orleans.  
The  enslaved  were  a  diverse  culture,  each  with  its  own  musical  repertoires.  They  included  music  rituals  
like  the  ring,  whereby  people  gathered,  played  instruments,  sang  in  a  call-and-response,  and  danced.  Music  
was  inseparable  from  prayer  and  communion  with  the  ancestral  spirits;  now  it  eased  the  pain  of  captivity.  
Aboard  slave  ships,  captains  forced  slaves  to  sing  and  dance  to  keep  them  in  good  shape  so  that  they  could  
arrive  alive  and  sellable.  But  they  were  also  wary  lest  drums  incite  rebellion  or  be  used  as  technologies  of  
secret  communication.  So  the  slave  masters  banned  them.  Interestingly,  the  drumming  continued  without  
the  drums  through  hand  clapping  and  foot-tapping.  Bodies  became  instruments,  drums.  
Food  and  Rice  
The  debt  that  America  owes  to  the  technologies  of  the  enslaved  rival  in  the  area  of  agricultural  innovations  
is  signicant.  Whereas  Europeans  had  brought  the  spade  and  the  plow  to  the  New  World,  the  African  intro
duced  the  hoe  to  turn  over  the  soil.  The  hoe  was  a  product  of  the  African  mining  and  metallurgical  traditions  
of  the  ancestors  back  in  Africa.  Here  it  was  entering  Western  science-based  engineering  and  manufacturing  
now  via  the  plantations.  The  hoe  was  also  used  in  preparing  a  cornmeal  dish  called  fufu,  perhaps  the  most  
widespread  meal  in  Africa.  It  has  many  names,  each  according  to  the  language  of  its  makers  and  eaters:  
fufu  in  West  Africa,  ugali  in  Kenya,  and  Tanzania,  nshima  in  Zambia,  nsima  in  Malawi,  sadza  in  Zimbabwe,  
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Lecture  4  Food  Production  in  Africa  STS.089,  Fall  14  
they  already  had  a  vast  reservoir  of  knowledge  of  mangrove  rice,  enslaved  Africans  became  the  critical  actors  
in  the  transition  from  swamp  cultivation  to  oodplain,  irrigated  rice  in  South  Carolina.  It  was  only  the  
enslaved,  women  more  so,  who  knew  the  art  of  rice  milling,  the  only  ecient  way  to  extract  the  grain  from  
its  shell  before  the  coming  of  the  mechanized  mill.  
The  example  of  rice  encourages  us  to  think  of  Africans  as  not  mere  users  of  technology  or  beneciaries  of  
technology  transfer,  but  also  as  originators  that  transferred  technology  to  the  West.  The  Jola  (Diola)  people  
of  Senegal,  Gambia,  and  Guinea-Bissau  had  tilled  the  soil,  and  to  make  dikes  and  furrows,  for  rice  planting  
using  the  kajandu  or  kayendo,  a  long-handled  fulcrum  shovel.  The  men  worked  with  the  long-handled,  large  
concave-bladed  hoe,  while  the  women  spread  the  manure,  sowed  (casting)  the  seed,  transplanted  seedlings,  
and  cut  the  ripe  rice.  
Why  this  matters  today?  
  the  diusion  of  knowledge  in  a  time  of  heightened  global  mobilities  (migration)  and  mobile  technologies  
  rethinking  the  contribution  of  Africa  to  global  technologies  and  its  building  blocks.  
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lecture  4  Food  Production  in  Africa  STS.089,  Fall  14  
papa  in  South  Africa,  phaletshe  in  Botswana,  posho  in  Uganda,  and  luku,  moteke ,  semoule ,  and  bugari  in  DR  
Congo.  Most  of  the  Africans  enslaved  in  America  came  from  Africas  western  littoral,  where  this  corn-based  
meal  was  called  fufu.  The  enslaved  Africans  had  brought  no  pots  or  pans  and  owned  none,  so  they  cooked,  
better  yet  fried,  on  the  hoe  what  came  to  be  called  hoecakes.  To  add  taste  and  hold  the  cornmeal  together,  
they  mixed  it  in  plantains.  
Africans  may  have  been  severed  from  the  lands  they  farmed  but  the  European  enslaver  did  not  sever  the  
knowledge  of  farming  from  the  Africans  heads.  They  carried  it  with  them  in  their  to  the  Americas.  This  role  
of  Africans  as  organic  vehicles  and  architects  of  technology  transfer  to  the  New  World  has  only  been  recently  
appreciated.  The  story  of  rice  in  South  Carolinas  plantations  is  a  good  example.  Previously,  scholars  like  
Peter  Wood,  author  of  Black  Majority ,  characterized  the  relationship  between  the  enslaved  Africans  and  rice  
as  a  parallel  and  temporal  association,  hence  his  depiction  of  the  cereal  as  White  Rice.  Some  had  simply  
spoken  of  the  enslaveds  contributions.  Those  that  said  the  most  could  only  remark  about  slaves  who  had  
experience  growing  rice  in  West  Africa  were  probably  instrumental  in  the  successful  creation  of  early  rice  
plantations.  The  narrative  remained  one  of  white  planters  as  the  innovators  and  pioneers  against  amazing  
odds.  
In  Black  Rice,  Judith  Carney  declared  that  America  owes  enslaved  Africans,  and  indeed  West  Africa,  a  
huge  debt  of  gratitude  for  bringing  expertise  in  rice  cultivation  to  its  shores.  Where  Wood  had  talked  of  
White  Rice,  Carney  deantly  inserted  to  concept  of  Black  Rice  to  specify  who  the  inventors  were.  For  the  
rst  three  decades  since  the  establishment  of  the  English  settlement  in  South  Carolina  in  1670,  settlers  had  
realized  that  rice  imported  from  Asia  thrived  in  the  inland  valley  swamps.  Throughout  the  1700s,  rice  became  
the  mainstay  of  South  Carolinas  economy;  the  rice  economy  subsequently  extended  to  Georgia.  Being  at  rst  
ignorant  of  swamp  rice  production  initially,  these  planters  quickly  saw  that  the  Africans  they  had  enslaved  
from  the  traditional  rice-growing  region  of  West  Africa  possessed  this  rare  expertise.  Soon,  they  started  
transferring  this  technology  from  Africa  in  a  more  deliberate  way,  targeting  for  capture  and  shipment  women  
and  some  men  specically  from  those  rice-growing  regions.  These  imports  from  the  Rice  Coast,  the  Wind
ward  Coast,  the  Gambia,  and  Sierra  Leone,  possessed  a  double  technological  value  (labor  and  knowledge)  
and  therefore  fetched  higher  prices  on  the  slave  market  and  were  advertised  as  accustomed  to  the  planting  
of  rice.  These  technical  experts  were  then  deployed  to  transfer  their  technical  knowledge  of  rice  growing  
through  their  hard  labor  for  no  personal  beneciation.  They  prepared  the  land  into  irrigation  canals,  selected  
and  planted  the  seed,  tended  the  crops  against  pests  and  weeds,  reaped  and  processed  the  grain.  At  planting  
time  they  line  up  on  the  edges  of  the  eld,  and  then,  with  their  ancestral  call-and-response  singing  style,  they  
rhythmically  paced  themselves,  hoeing  in  unison.  Come  harvest  time  and  it  was  the  women  who  pounded  the  
grain  with  pestles  in  large  wooden  mortars,  then  separated  the  cha  from  the  grain  using  winnowing  baskets.  
The  narrative  of  the  plantation  owner  as  the  rice  planter  yielded  to  another  that  now  centered  on  the  
enslaved  as  the  carriers  riziculture  from  Africa  to  South  Carolina.  In  fact,  the  enslaved  were  the  link  in  the  
physical  continuity  of  rice  growing;  they  linked,  through  the  coerced  mobility  of  their  bodies  between  two  
continents,  two  sites  of  rice-growing:  their  erstwhile  mangrove-lined  elds  in  West  Africa  and  the  plantations  
of  South  Carolina.  All  technologies  they  carried  in  their  heads  from  West  Africa  and  transferred  to  the  white  
mans  plantation.  They  had  also  cultivated  rice  in  sluices,  ditches,  and  banks  in  the  rain-fed  wetland  and  
tidal  ecosystems  of  the  Niger  and  Gambia  rivers  of  West  Africa.  Now  they  did  the  same  in  South  Carolina  
and  Georgia.  
As  Carney  shows,  ancestral  knowledge  of  rice  cultivation  played  a  critical  role  in  the  enslavement,  ship
ment,  and  plantation  experiences  of  Africans.  The  question  is  whether  they  were  in  fact  recruited  as  skilled  
laborers  in  a  cropping  system  planters  had  already  ingeniously  developed,  or  whether  slaves  expert  in  rice  
cultivation  so  that  they  could  show  Carolina  planters  how  to  adapt  a  preferred  dietary  staple  to  diverse  
lowland  settings.  Carney  says  two  things  to  this:  not  only  was  the  origin  of  rice  cultivation  in  South  Carolina  
African;  enslaved  Africans  from  West  Africa?s  rice  region  tutored  planters  in  growing  the  crop.  Because  
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>African Entrepreneurship (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-089-technology-and-innovation-in-africa-fall-2014/resources/mitsts_089f14_lecture12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 12 African Entrepreneurship STS.089, Fall 14 
Situated on the River Ayensu, about forty miles west of Accra, Winneba was originally a shing town and 
the gateway to a fertile farming area. In addition, the inhabitants became known as excellent canoe makers 
and traders. Disinclined to become a sherman or farmer, the young man (now using the name Ghartey, a 
corruption from Gyateh) struck out on his own and gained employment as an apprentice for a Dutch rm 
trading at the nearby palm oil port of Apam. European contacts were, therefore, important in Gharteys 
development, but he lacked formal schooling. For a total of fourteen years, Ghartey worked as a cooper 
for the Dutch rm of Stoover Brothers at Apam, and from this he obtained a knowledge of basic business 
methods. His son, King Ghartey V, recalled in an interview with the writer how his father subsequently 
spent a period at sea, working as a deck hand on various English, Portuguese, and Dutch ships, where he 
gained further experience, some of it harsh, in the ways of the European commercial and seafaring world and 
learned ve languages Fanti, Ga, Guan (the language of Winneba), Dutch, and English, plus a smattering 
of Portuguese. He accumulated enough savings to purchase his own store at Anomabu. By the time of the 
demise of Stoover Brothers, Ghartey had amassed sucient capital to buy out his parent organization. As a 
result, he gained control of the sizeable trading establishment at Apam, together with a network of thirteen 
branch factories, which he then combined with his own budding import-export rm, Ghartey Brothers, at 
Anomabu. This partnership, along with the Sarbah rm of Cape Coast, became one of the best-known 
examples of African mercantile entrepreneurship in the Gold Coast. He was elected as the best qualied to 
hold the paramount stool rst king president of the Fanti Confederation, the African protonationalist 
group that included John Sarbah, F. C. Grant, Jacob W. Sey, J. F. Amissah, W. F. Hutchison, and other 
merchants, chiefs, and professional men of the central districts (Dumett). 
Ghartey grew up near the heart of some of the richest oil palm forests of the central coastal states. His 
wealth was based primarily on the export of palm oil from the Efutu, Fanti, Agona, and Gomoa states and 
on the trade in gold dust and ivory from Asante, but his operations expanded to include nearly every port 
town of the British Gold Coast Colony. Like the other merchants described here, he made use of kinship 
and friendship ties with other kings and chiefs, including those of Asante. Ghartey Brothers set standards 
for their competitors in innovation, nancial daring, and the development of new lines of business enterprise. 
Ghartey was reportedly the rst to ship palm kernels from the Gold Coast, using his branch factories at 
Achowa and Sekondi in the Ahanta state of the western region; and he is said to have experimented with 
machine crushing of kernels, which for a time became a signicant local industry. He also participated in a 
mechanized gold-mining venture in the Wassa district of the western Gold Coast in the late 1870s, and he 
attempted to develop a timber-cutting industry in the Winneba region. King Ghartey IV helped to open the 
rubber forests of Assin and Denkyera to the rst commercial tapping of wild rubber by indigenous traders in 
the 1880s and was able to retire a wealthy many decade slater. The evidence also attests to his participation 
in a wide variety of civic, philanthropic, and educational activities. King Ghartey IV did not live to see the 
sudden burgeoning of cocoa as the Gold Coasts number one export crop, but his son informed me that a 
brother, J. B. carried on the tradition Q. Ghartey, family entrepreneurial by managing a large cocoa farm 
at Asemankese in Akyem-Abuakwain the early 1900s (Dumett). 
Conclusions
 
Regarding Dumetts Argument on Nodal Points and Niches
 
Inextricably bound up with locational advantage in the spread of new skills in trading and production were 
important changes in the external economic environment generated by technical and structural changes in 
Atlantic commerce during the second half of the nineteenth century. During the 1850s and 1860s we nd 
a of the niche wherein of widening entrepreneurial larger groups indigenous merchants might exercise their 
talents. These changes, whose impact varied from place to place along the Guinea Coast, derived in part 
from rising European industrial demand for new tropical products, notably palm oil and palm kernels, and 
in part from the advent of the new steamships, whose faster service and larger cargo capacities stimulated 
trade and drew the localized economies of West Africa more fully into the currents of the world capitalist 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 12 African Entrepreneurship STS.089, Fall 14 
The Gold Coast: On the Gold Coast this emphasis was largely reversed. The trade was both highly 
structured and localized and the degree of interaction conned both spatially and socially. According to 
Henige: the traders did not develop from individuals to a class, contrary to Kwame Daaku (1970, also Kea 
1974 and Boahen 1974), who saw them as a new class (Henige) 
The Niger Delta (Nigeria-Benin Area) : developed from less centralized and structured communities in 
response to new exigencies and opportunities. Even less social and political intercourse between European 
and African here than on the Gold Coast, and for the Niger delta we should think in terms of African po
litical and economic responses which were the stronger, the more successful, and the more durable precisely 
because they were able to develop with little attendant acculturation (Henige). 
African Entrepreneurs 
John Kabes 
The mobility, the adaptability, and role of middlemen as mediators allowed them to become entrepreneurs, to 
serve European companies in capacity while retaining entrepreneurial independence to do their own thing on 
the side. An able individual might manipulate conditions to his own long-term advantage, and John Kabes 
(or Cabessa) of late-17th century is an example of an African trader and political leader who beneted from 
them (Henige, 3). He was born in the 1640s-50s, and was certainly old and growing sickly and inrm by 
1716 and deceased by June 1722. His career as trader and as political leader shows him as one of the major 
gures in Dutch-African, English-African, Dutch-English, and African-African relations in the Gold Coast. 
He started out as a prot eg e of the Dutch traders, was brought to Komenda by the English to serve as their 
broker, and ended up as an independent trader (Henige). His own interests corresponded with those of the 
British, without submitting his will to them; it was a business calculation. 
Although the Europeans denigrated the waterside blacks as having nothing of their own to trade with 
in terms of gold, ivory, or slaves (Henige), Kabes (and others like him) in fact served as producers of both 
goods and services for the English at Komenda and other nearby points, in addition to operating as mid
dlemen for goods going into and coming from the interior. The English expected him to provide corn in 
adequate quantities to victual the garrison at Komenda, with any surplus going to Cape Coast Castle and 
other points on the coast. Another local commodity supplied by Kabes, probably under contract, was 
shells from the vicinity of Takoradi which were used to produce lime to prepare mortar for building and 
maintaining the English forts. But in terms of operating as a primary supplier it was Kabess ability to 
provide manpower to the English garrison that was most important. In I69I, when the English made an 
abortive eort to re-establish the factory abandoned three years previously, the English agent emphasized 
how important it was to appease Kabes, without whom, he added, nothing will be done. He supplied the 
Company with workmen to bring stones to the site, to cut wood, and to oer some deterrent to the Dutch 
who were threatening to prevent work from proceeding. Kabes was adept at extorting payments and bonuses 
at critical times in the progress of construction, fully realizing, one might suppose, the heavy dependence 
of the English on both his resources and his good will. Kabes was both an intermediary and producer of 
merchandise, shaper of tastes as well as disseminator of goods to satisfy them (Henige). 
William Nahr Ocansey 
I use here the standard denition of a merchant as one who engages in an overseas, long- distance, or 
inter-regional import or export business as well as in local trade. Other denitions which were used on the 
Gold Coast during the period 1850-1900 were a man who did a large volume of trade and a businessman 
who lived in a large house. Some of these men worked as part-or full-time agents for European trading 
houses. A leading merchant of the southeastern Gold Coast was William Nahr Ocansey, whose headquarters 
was at the town of Ada in the Adangbe area located near the mouth of the River Volta. A completely 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>STS.089  Technology and Innovation in Africa Fall 14 
Lecture 12 - African Entrepreneurship 
Prof. Clapperton Chakanetsa Mavhunga MIT OpenCourseWare 
Does the concept of entrepreneurship make sense in Africa? 
Critics felt the concept of entrepreneurship was too deeply embedded in Schumpeterian circular ow mod
els and the imagery of Western industrialism to have meaningful application for peasant or transitional 
economies. Many have become skeptical as to whether the rise of a Western-educated middle-class elite can 
any longer be viewed as the indispensable vehicle for development once extolled in the literature of capital
ist economic growth. And several neo-Marxist and other scholars have criticized the rise of an indigenous 
West African mercantile group as being not developers but a comprador class which served as a vehicle for 
economic imperialism and the penetration of their countries by European interests (Dumett, Kaplow 1977, 
Rodney 1972). 
Worth brief attention are attempts by anthropologists to devise various subcategories-e.g., small-scale 
versus large-scale, or innovating versus imitating entrepreneurs, in order to rene the term for ap
plication to Africa. Most ideas are transmitted by emulation or diusion, and most entrepreneurs are at 
dierent times both innovators and imitators. Keith Harts subdivision into traditional entrepreneurs and 
Westernized entrepreneurs seems to make more sense (Katzin 1964, Hart 1970). It is easy to pick out 
those traders and middlemen who were immersed in the traditional sociocultural milieu, who were basically 
rural, who travelled far upcountry to open new markets, and who had little contact with Europeans. By the 
same token, one can identify those African merchants who became acclimatized to life in the coastal towns, 
who built stores, traded overseas on their own accounts, and served as conduits between the indigenous 
and European sectors of trade. Even this typology presents problems, however. There were few traders in 
the Gold Coast/Ghana then or now who were not aected to some degree by non-African inuences; many 
entrepreneurs whether small market-stall operators, owners of eets of lorries, or cocoa brokers textendash 
t into a gray area midway between the two categories (Dumett). 
What are the risks of democratizing or severely limiting the term entrepreneur
ship? 
Dumett says that the tendency in some recent [Global South] studies to suggest that every small-scale 
shopowner, hawker, or street peddler is an entrepreneur deprives the term of useful analytic force. An 
entrepreneur certainly does not have to be an industrialist; he can be a trader, farmer, or skilled craftsman. 
Yet, one should keep in mind the classic denition of the entrepreneur as a leader, a change agent who 
combines the basic factors of production and distribution-land, labor, capital, or transport-in new ways 
(standard denition as oered in Say 1821; Schumpeter 1934, Hawley 1907). This touches on other crucial 
questions. What are the conditions and causal elements which transform an ordinary trader into an en
trepreneur? What qualities contribute to a prosperous and enduring business enterprise? What elements 
link entrepreneurship to a nations commercial expansion and general economic development? What are the 
barriers to sustained mercantile activity and the reasons for entrepreneurial decline? (Dumett) 
What distinguishes an entrepreneur from everybody else in society? 
Those attitudes which distinguish unusually eective or successful traders, merchants, farmers, or artisans 
from others in the society: the leading innovators in rapidly industrializing countries were often relatively high 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 12 African Entrepreneurship STS.089, Fall 14 
self-made man, though he could neither read nor write, he built up a lucrative trade based on export of 
palm products to England and Germany and inward shipments of European cloth, tobacco, and liquor, plus 
local sh and salt, to central and northern Ghana. Ocansey operated in the tenuous marginal zone between 
the indigenous production centers of the Lower Volta (including the Anlo Coast of present-day Togo) and 
the seaborne trading system dominated by leading British houses such as Alexander Miller Brothers and F. 
and A. Swanzy; this region was dicult because the expatriate rms had easier access to the wholesalers, 
brokerage houses, and credit institutions of the United Kingdom. In addition, the Swanzys owned two or 
three steamships and large sailing vessels which shipped cargo direct to Europe and America; to hold its own 
for several decades against European economies of scale was traceable to its expert use of local technologies, 
coupled with its position of prominence within the surrounding Adangbe region and its network of more than 
fty traditional traders and middlemen (Dumett). What were the wellsprings for the commercial wealth of 
Ada and the entrepreneurial talent of its people? The salt trade of the nearby Songow (or Songor) Lagoon, 
which developed into a highly organized industry, utilizing cadres of laborers (in the early days slaves) under 
the direct control of the traditional ruler of the Ada kingdom. 
Several elements inherent in the traditional sociopolitical structure also played a part in W. N. Ocanseys rise 
to prominence. To substantiate my royal lineage hypothesis, it is important to note that he was a younger 
brother of the king of Ada. He exploited this relationship to the fullest in purchasing local supplies of salt 
and sh for interior African markets, in building an organization of itinerant agents and boatmen, and in 
acquiring capital for investment in canoes and in land for warehouses and branch stores. Lack of formal 
education was no barrier, as Ocansey hired trained clerks to do his letter writing and bookkeeping. Use of 
kinship networks was crucial to the expansion of trade; You see, said Moses Pupulampu, descendant of 
a nearly twentieth-century family of Ada traders, this is one reason our grandfathers had so many wives. 
W. N. Ocansey attained success gradually as a palm oil exporter during two decades of rising prices and 
demand for the product in Europe. The advent of regular steamer service and lowered freight rates also 
helped him to run a prot. Pivotal to his success was his ability to negotiate with the most important inte
rior palm oil producers of the day the Krobo people in their common (Adagbe) language. By the 1860s 
he was managing a complex network of some twelve trading stations or lodges, each with a store manager, 
supporting cadre of laborers, and itinerant agents. At the height of its prosperity the Ocansey rm control 
led branch factories at the towns of Keta, Beh Beach, and Danu Beach on the eastern (Anlo) shore of the 
Volta estuary, as well as establishments at Agrave, Adidome, Battor, Weycoomabe, Amanoo, Tolesem, Ada 
Foa, Pram Pram, Akuse, and Kpong in the western or Adagbe zone of inuence. Agents and middlemen 
with whom father and son did business were Tetteh Ocansey, James Amartey, J. C. Ocansey, T. C. Ocansey, 
H. Solomon, Tetteh Dabah, J. F. Tamako, R. D. Totimah, O. T. Azzu, T. C. Dosooh, Tetteh Amler, and 
T. Adodatee. A feature of this expansion, often associated with the transition from traditional or ad hoc 
entrepreneurship to the cognitive entrepreneurship of modern mercantile organization, was regular record 
keeping and management of accounts. The Ocansey papers at the Ghana National Archives indicate that 
the ability of clerks to maintain invoices, bills of lading, records of commissions and wages paid, receipts 
of sales and purchases, and ledgers of debit and credit on a consistent basis was essential for success (Dumett). 
The Ocansey rms slow decline can be traced to a combination of natural disasters and external fac
tors, including loss by re, shipwreck, robbery, and involvement in warfare against the neighboring Anlo 
people. William Ocansey showed amazing resiliency in rebounding from many of these misfortunes, but in 
the end succumbed to general loss from the declining palm oil trade coupled with default on credit by local 
middlemen and oppressive treatment by European competitors (Dumett). 
R. J. Ghartey 
The life of R. J. Ghartey, one of the leading nineteenth-century merchants of Winneba and Anomabu in the 
central Gold Coast, reinforces several of our hypotheses concerning advantages of location and the synthesis 
of traditional and Westernizing sociopolitical elements in the development of entrepreneurship. Born Kwamin 
Akyempong, he was the son of Gyateh Kumah, the Odefo, or king, of the Winneba state during the 1820s. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 12 African Entrepreneurship STS.089, Fall 14 
status subgroups who had suered loss of traditional power or who had traditional channels of advancement 
denied to them (Dumett, Hagen 1962, LeVine 1966, McClelland 1961). 
Dumetts Critique 
Hagen, in particular, perpetuated some inaccurate stereotypes concerning the supposedly authoritarian, 
static, and non-innovational nature of traditional societies prior to modernization (Dumett). Of course, in 
applying his notion of subordination to Africa, one could assume that the European colonialists constituted 
a new ruling elite which repressed the aspirations of potential leaders from the traditional society. But the 
facts suggest that, for British West Africa, legitimate European trading connections, built up during the 
mid-nineteenth century, brought more new opportunities than impediments and that the oppressive impact 
of formal colonial administration came mainly at the end of the period (the 1890s) covered in this essay. As 
for the McClelland model, it seems unlikely that most human action can be reduced to a single paramount 
psychological determinant need for achievement any more than it can be reduced to a purely economic 
one, such as acquisitiveness. In a trenchant critique of the methodology of the achievement motivation school, 
R. K. Godwin has pointed out the logical fallacies involved in jumping from the measurement of the attitudes 
of individuals to that of an aggregate personality, and from there to the level of the total social-cultural unit, 
whether class, ethnic group, or nation (Godwin 1974, Schatz 1971, Hart 1975). Indeed, a number of scholars 
have pointed out that tests of attitudes and beliefs may be of limited value in predicting overt behavior. 
Critique of Dumett 
Dumett then commits a mistake of his own. He will the underlying determinants for the rise of particular 
groups to trading dominance in many parts of West Africa can be traced to locational factors and favorable 
changes in the economic environment; says there often a very close connection between success in trade and 
family ties to a king or chief. He emphasizes the signicance of geographic and environmental elements, not 
the peoples abilities or their knowledge professoriates: From my work on African merchants and traders 
of the Gold Coast, which has centered thus far on two major groups the Fetu and Fanti merchants of 
the central region, and the Adangbe traders of the River Volta it seems likely that geographic location, 
which placed certain groups in a favorable position to respond to economic stimuli, was the central and 
controlling factor. Sure, the nodal trading points were critical as springboards for entrepreneurial activity 
and economic development, more so on the Gold Coast, but we cant take the achievements of Africans and 
simply attribute them to proximity or location. I will return to this later in the lecture. 
The 17th and 18th Centuries 
The arrival of European traders and trade goods on the coasts of West Africa and the entrance of these 
areas into international trading networks constituted, albeit in a limited way, an exercise in acculturation; 
the development of middlemen who mediated political, cultural, and economic relations between Africans 
and incoming Europeans (Henige). 
Upper Guinea: the lan cados (of full Portuguese blood) initially dominated trade, but they intermar
ried with Africans. A second group dominant in trade were the grumetes , generally of African descent and 
often semi-independent. They owned a sense of corporate self-identity, living in their own villages and prac
ticing an Africanized form of Catholicism (Henige). 
Sierra Leone : Here, similar situation, but besides the lan cados and grumetes, trading families useful 
kinship ties with the existing political system but attempted to maintain a certain sociopolitical distance by 
settling on the many islands of the area and by adopting some English cultural patterns (Henige); emphasis 
on all sides was on individuals rather than on corporate institutions. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 12 African Entrepreneurship STS.089, Fall 14 
in 1865 that he had begun his career as an agent for the London rms of Forster and Smith, but when he 
found that he had made little prot under this arrangement he used the experience to take up trading on 
his own account. Similarly, George Blankson, son of Chief Kuntu of Egya, served his apprenticeship under 
one Thompson, an indigenous merchant of Winneba (Akita 1955) whose activities had extended as far as 
Kumasi, capital of Asante. Such emphasis on youthful retailing experience as a key to later accomplishment 
in overseas trade is remarkably similar to the histories of many English and American merchants of the 
eighteenth and nineteenth centuries (Dumett). 
How not to connect politics and entrepreneurship 
Dumett attempts the possible correlation between individual business success and close kinship ties with 
traditional rulers: a signicant number of leading entrepreneurs of the 1870s and 1880s were members of 
their local royal lineage; that is, they were the sons, nephews, grandsons, or grand-nephews of kings and 
chiefs. It is nonetheless true that members of royal lineages were accorded deference and favors, both in 
social life and in business, denied to ordinary people; the prestige of aliation with a royal line facilitated 
entrance into large-scale trade by providing: (1) access to capital through loans, (2) access to resources (such 
as lagoon salt beds), (3) contacts with peasant producers in the interior, (4) assistance in local employment 
of workers, and (5) aid in laying a groundwork of business organization (Dumett). 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
STS.089 Technology and Innovation in Africa
Fall 2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 12 African Entrepreneurship STS.089, Fall 14 
system (Dumett). 
Transformation in Niches 
For small-scale African traders, previously inhibited from entering overseas trade as principals, the new 
steamers (both liners and tramp vessels) oered a fourfold advantage: (1) more frequent and regular stopovers 
at small towns along the coasts, (2) independence from prevailing winds and oshore currents (which had 
inhibited east and west trade along the Guinea Coast), (3) improved carrying capacities combined with 
willingness of captains to accept produce shipments in smaller parcels, and (4) for a time at least, reduced 
freight rates, induced by the healthy rivalry between the African Steamship Company and the African Steam 
Navigation Company, which continued until the coming of rate-xing cartels in the 1890s. The net eect of 
all these was a widened entrepreneurship. Changes opportunity structure for young men anxious for careers 
in commerce at principal towns up and down the West African coast (Dumett). Of course, opportunities are 
created by people; they do not come before innovation. 
The traditional systems are not necessarily anti-modern. 
Contrary to Dumetts assertions that If it can be accepted that advantageous location and new economic 
opportunities were the fundamental determinants of entrepreneurial supply, it is still necessary to identify 
the intervening variables which enabled particular traders to prot and survive in large-scale enterprise 
(Dumett). It is fundamentally awed its as if all good things come from outside, and all incoming things 
are modern and local ones are not. 
Dumett talks further that the adaptibility of indigenous social structures and the transmission of huckstering 
skills through traditional role models and institution. Key elements were peers, the immediate family, wider 
kinship networks and the chieftainship; entrance into retailing or related vocations was not restricted by 
such criteria as ethnic origin, class, clan, or the like; socialization of young men in a milieu where the prot 
motive was not disparage. 
He puts too much emphasis on European inuences, and doesnt go far enough in displacing the West
ern ratio as a central aspect of African entrepreneurship. As a reinforcing element, European-style education 
could play a part in the process. Some of the most prosperous local merchants, especially those in the major 
port towns of Accra and Cape Coast, were educated at colonial or Christian missionary schools. Many 
obtained a grasp of commercial arithmetic and English grammar, and some were uent in more than one 
European language. Other facets of Westernization are: many of the indigenous merchants were active in 
local (mainly Methodist) churches and English-style voluntary associations, that they maintained friendships 
with Europeans, and that some took English, Dutch, or Danish surnames have led several commentators 
to speak of a strong transcultural element in West African coastal society. Though not without signicance, 
these elements were not an indispensable key to entrepreneurial success. Much more important were the 
interactions and intermarriages between members of the leading African bourgeois families. They became 
a tightly knit group and were conscious that they were a vital force for the socioeconomic and political 
transformation of the colony (Dumett). Dumett indeed de-emphasizes European educational inuence on 
entrepreneurship, saying that previous accounts have erred in overemphasizing the role of formal schooling 
and Europeanization as major determinants of successful commercial careers in the Gold Coast. Part of the 
problem for the historian stems from the fact that it was the literate people of Accra and Cape Coast who left 
the fullest records of their activities. However, most of the African merchants and traders listed here lacked 
formal schooling, and one scholar has questioned the assumed literacy of some of the best-known members 
of the coastal middle-class elite (Dumett, ref. to Limberg 1970; Bevin 1956). Many of these merchants and 
traders agents remained embedded in the traditional African culture. Many of those Africans who became 
prosperous entrepreneurs R. J. Ghartey, John Sarbah, W. F. Hutchison, Samuel Collins Brew had been 
apprenticed at an early age to work as retail store clerks, buying agents, or laborers either for their fathers, 
other relatives, or for European rms. Thus Henry Barnes, an indigenous merchant of Cape Coast, recalled 
6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Bibles (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-089-technology-and-innovation-in-africa-fall-2014/resources/mitsts_089f14_lecture21/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 21 The Bible in African Hands STS.089, Fall 14 
The Bible in African Hands 
Sechele, Bakwena, and the Bible 
African rulers combined their secular duties with preaching. Moreover, he described himself as specially 
suited to teach because he knew the scriptures well. Sechele in particular mastered the alphabet in just one 
day and became an eager student of the scriptures, who then went on to interpret them, rather masterfully, 
in like of the experience of his own Bakwena people. He read the Bible exhaustively, and raised some rather 
uncomfortable questions for the missionaries. For example, in 1854, Robert Moat could not readily answer 
Secheles challenge that he explain to the Kwena why the missionaries had made him discard all but one of 
his wives, while Solomon and David had so many wives and concubines, and were still men after Gods own 
heart. Sechele grew so dissatised with the educational opportunities in Bechuanaland that he proposed to 
study theology in England, a scheme he shelved owing to his shortage of funds. Several pupils were repelled 
by the doctrinal assumptions in the Congregational and Lutheran creeds as well as by inept teaching. Several 
catechists complained to the missionaries that they closed their eyes and tried to talk to Jesus without success. 
Several traditionalists maintained that the Tswana needed no such instruction since they had evolved their 
own methods for communicating with God. A Kwena rainmaker rejected Livingstones homily that Christ 
alone could provide rain. But God has told us that there is only one way by which we can pray to him 
acceptably: viz., by Jesus Christ, Livingstone said. 
And the rainmaker said: Truly. And he has told us dierently. God has been very good to both white and 
black. To the white he has given the knowledge of guns, gunpowder, horses, and many other things which 
we know nothing about. He has given you wisdom too. We see it. To us blacks he has not been so liberal, 
but he has given us the knowledge of rain-making; you have it not. Now we dont despise those things God 
has given you, though we are ignorant of them. Nor should you despise what he has given us, though you 
dont known or understand them. 
In 1897, fty years after his rst encounter with Christianity, Secheles elder Kosidintsi still refused to 
get converted, No, Monare [sir],I can not allow it I shall die as I have lived, and God who knows my rea
sons will judge me righteously. And the priest, the Reverend Williams, was impressed: Nothing could move 
him, and we came away admiring the old man for his consistent attitude. And of Sechele, the departing 
Reverend Price could only say, with resigned admiration: I shall feel in parting from him that I am parting 
from one who has on the whole treated me with much kindness and generosity. 
Kgama and the Bible 
As we saw, Kgamas ascension to the Ngwato throne owed to a clash between balehuku (children of the book) 
and balechulo (traditionalists). Kgama assumed the oce with messianic pretensions bound to impinge on 
the white missionaries clerical role. For example, in 1890 Kgama warned a missionary not to meddle in 
Ngwato politics, saying: Now I am chief of the country. You are a teacher. I cannot allow any teacher to 
act and speak as if he was a chief of my town The Lord Jesus Christ who made you a teacher has made me 
a chief, and He knows how I try and have always tried to rule my people for their good. 
There were serious conicts between Kgama and Reverend James D. Hepburn in 1891, which revolved 
around whether the chief or the missionary should have ultimate control where secular and Christian pre
rogatives overlapped. Hepburn asserted that he was the spiritual leader of the Ngwato church, while Kgama 
maintained that as a Christian head of state he was baptised into the Lutheran church by German mis
sionaries in 1860 he was responsible for constructing new school buildings, as he was for any public work. 
But Hepburn refused to yield, and according to some Ngwato informants even fomented sedition. For ex
ample, when his communicants asked him, Should the chief call out our regiment as usual, are we to obey 
the chief to go and do whatever he asks?, Hepburn is reported to have replied, No you must not obey 
the chief; you are the servants of Christ, and you must obey Christ alone. Kgama saw himself as Christs 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
STS.089 Technology and Innovation in Africa
Fall 2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 21 The Bible in African Hands STS.089, Fall 14 
came about at the invitation of the Tswana rulers. And each time the chiefs were impelled less by religious 
motives than by military and economic considerations. Missionaries were known to procure and repair guns, 
weapons which had assumed an important role in hunting and warfare. Some chiefs hoped to learn how 
to manufacture weapons themselves, and other show to make rain by using the white mans method of 
building dams, an important skill in a semi-arid environment. Little wonder that early missionary reports 
depict the Tswana as more impressed by the white mans technology than by his Christian doctrine. 
In 1817, Hamilton sinks a well to drive this point home. Mothibi did eventually receive the gun he had 
been promised. Tswana rulers took considerable pains to provide their new guests with food, shelter, and 
some amenities. In return they expected to use them as middlemen in acquiring guns and only marginally as 
teachers. Mission schools taught reading, writing, and arithmetic, with classes conducted in crude buildings 
constructed by workmen provided by the chief. In more desperate cases wagons, trees, and the chiefs court 
improvised as classrooms. Pupils used stone walls, planks, and parts of broken boxes to write on. Wives of 
missionaries conducted sewing lessons in their homes. 
Political Reasons 
Livingstone had baptized Sechele in 1848 despite great opposition from Secheles subjects, who maintained 
that baptism would compromise his position and all that it stood for. But Sechele had made up his mind to 
align his chiefdom with the British, and he was willing to sacrice some of the metaphysical attributes of his 
oce in return for protection against the aggressive Afrikaners. Sechele had strategic as well as diplomatic 
problems; chief among them was the incessant menace of the Afrikaners, who poached on Kwena territory 
and occasionally skirmished with Kwena soldiers. In a shrewd diplomatic move, Sechele sought to neutralize 
his antagonists by involving them in the religious life of his chiefdom. He asked the president of the South 
African republic, Andries Pretorius, to provide him with missionaries. Pretorius was attered; moreover, 
he saw the request as a perfect means to expand Afrikaner inuence and territory in Central Africa. He 
persuaded the Hermannsburg Society, which had been working in Natal since 1854, to accept Secheles invi
tation, and in 1857 the society sent Schroeder to the Kwena chiefdom; not to be outdone, Chief Sekgoma of 
the Bamangwato sent a similar plea. 
The arrival of German Lutherans incensed British missionaries, and in 1857 Robert Moat asked Sechele 
if the Germans were evangelizing in his country and the chief pleaded ignorance. But a few years later, 
Sechele concluded that an alliance with the British was more useful than one with the Afrikaners in preserv
ing a measure of his sovereignty, and he mounted a campaign to expel the Hermannsburgers and to restore 
the LMS. Sechele and his btother Kosidintsi wrote to the LMS directors in London: we do not desire the 
teaching of the Germans and will receive the teaching of the English alone. The LMS dithered, and Sechele 
persisted in his requests for an English moruti . 
Why Were African Leaders Wary of European Missionaries? 
Yet despite these technological feats, the Tswana remained indierent to Christianity. In 1822 Hamilton 
reported, I would be very glad if I could inform you that Gods work is going forward in this place, but I 
must write nothing but the truth. So far as I know, no one of these heathens are seeking after God. Below 
the outward show of friendship lay an iceberg of resentment. Mothibi was afraid Christians might undermine 
his authority. Many kept from coming to hear the gospel, and children were kept from school. He was afraid 
that sooner or later the missionaries would usurp political power; this is what the church did, seeing strong 
state power as an obstacle to evangelism. 
At Shoshong, the rift between the traditionalist Chief Sekgoma and his Christian sons, Kgama and Kgamane, 
culminated in the civil war of 1866, one of the most tragic encounters between Christianity and traditional re
ligion in Tswana history. Although the balehuku party lost to Sekgoma, LMS agents subsequently supported 
Kgama in a plot to depose the Ngwato chief, Macheng, which was successfully carried out in 1872. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>STS.089  Technology and Innovation in Africa Fall 14 
Lecture 21 - The Bible in African Hands 
Prof. Clapperton Chakanetsa Mavhunga MIT OpenCourseWare 
So far we have dealt with two technologies that were introduced to Africa from outside. In the case of horses, 
the smaller ones were original to West Africa, but the bigger ones were shown by Fisher to have come from 
the Levant. In the case of guns, we saw them coming into South-Central Africa (the upper Zambezi area of 
Zambia) from Angola, thanks to the Portuguese-African trade that began in the 1500s and continued well 
into the 20th century, fuelled, of course, by the trade in Africans as slaves. 
Now, todays lecture/discussion tries to connect horse and gun to a larger discussion of how African leaders 
(whom we discussed under indirect rule) and their communities both solicited, deployed, managed, and 
dened things from means and ways of executing certain self-contrived objectives. Bibles and priests and 
next lecture books and writings fall nicely into that expos e. I wish to state clearly where the initiative of 
technology transfer such a bad word! lay, if such is to be the term to describe it: with Africans them
selves, as designers of their own, self-contrived destiny. 
Thus Botswana in the lives and times of Bangwato chief Khama and Bakwena chief Sechele might be read 
as a site where Africans were engaged in dening outsiders and things from outside according to their own 
strategic interests. What interests were these and how were they met through the bible and its European 
bringers to Botswana? 
Our source : J. Mutero Chirenje, Church, State, and Education in Bechuanaland in the Nineteenth Cen
tury, International Journal of African Historical Studies 9, 3 (1978), 401-418 
European Missionaries among Batswana: An Outline 
The earliest missionaries the LMS sent to Batswana in the early were more interested in ivory than in 
evangelism. By Batswana, I mean dierent peoples speaking the same language, Setswana Bathlaping (the 
sh people), Bakgatla, Bangwato, Bakwena, Bahurutshe, Batawana, and so on. One Setswana speaker is 
called Motswana; more than one is Batswana. The place that Batswana live is called Botswana. 
1840s : LMS expansion into northern Tswana chiefdoms 
1841 : Livingstone arrives at Kuruman 
1844 : he opesn Mabotsa mission in Kgatla territory with a subsequent station at Chonwane (the Knewa 
capital) 
1851 : Livingstone leaves to start his expeditions to the Zambezi and Central Africa 
No white missionaries replaced him, but from 1857 the German missionaries arrived at the invitation of 
the Batswana chiefs playing the British o against the Germans and Afrikaners. Hurt by this, the British 
expanded more rapidly, as most of the British missionaries in Bechuanaland, especially Robert Moat and 
John Mackenzie, were strongly committed to extending the British empire. 
Why Did Batswana Leaders Invite Missionaries? 
Technological Reasons 
In 1816, Read observes that the chief is the center of everything done in the [Tswana] tribes. He is the one 
who can pray to God. Missionaries had the ability to oer Mothibi foreign goods, handkerchiefs, beads, and 
tobacco, and sent Mothibi and gun. The chief either breakfasts, dines or sups with me almost everyday 
and was fond of bread. He thought of introducing wheat farming as a bait to lure people to the gospel. 
A special feature of the missionaries presence among Batswana was that in all but one case, Mothibis, it 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 21 The Bible in African Hands STS.089, Fall 14 
representative at Shoshong. Yet Kgama, whom whites had lavished with praise for his Christian leadership, 
felt he had sucient credentials to lead the church, and in consequence transferred all LMS church meetings 
to his court. To Hepburn, this move was the height of interference in church aairs, and his temperamental 
character could not bear it. he left abruptly for Cape Town for good in December 1891. 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Pre-Colonial African Cities (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-089-technology-and-innovation-in-africa-fall-2014/resources/mitsts_089f14_lecture13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 13 Pre-Colonial African Cities STS.089, Fall 14 
rwemabwe (stone walls) around their homesteads. He brought his ancestors with him; he brought Dzimbahwe 
with him, for when vaKaranga migrated from one place to another, they took soils from the graves of their 
ancestors and their ancestral homesteads and reburied them in new cemeteries and new homesteads. That 
way, there was no alienation between ancestor and living forebear; the ancestors not only came along with 
the itinerants even as they stayed watch on those left home. They also guided the itinerants, for as indicated 
elsewhere, life let alone journeying among vaShona (vaKaranga) was guided mobility (kutungamirirwa ). 
Thus, when all trade shifted away from the Limpopo-Save axis to the feiras (markets) along the Zambezi 
via the courts of Munhumutapa, such good omens were attributed never to supply-and-demand or political 
power alone, but to kutungamirirwa nemhondoro (ancestral spiritual guidance). 
The Falsehoods Begin 
When civilization took the form of sophisticated technological innovation, the white traveler usually found 
this too good to have been come from the mind and hand of the black man. First emphasizing that they 
found certain buildings in ruins (thereby blurring the quality of the craftsmanship), the white man next 
moved quickly (having asked no one) to conclude that they had no further information about such ruins 
and their history. Thus rendered of murky origins, the ruins could then be subject to instant, on-the-spot 
speculation as the traveler sat munching a roasted buck or bualo sirloin steak by the campsite. The En
glishman Theodore Bent readily decided that the builders of Dzimbahwe were southern Arabians. 
Shona Ancestors : Bent (1892): they were negroes, naked except for panther skins; they led their teeth 
and were cannibals; they fought with long lances and had ambuscades for game. They had no religion except 
that sort of witch doctor occasionally addressed them and bade them remember the prowess of their ancestors. 
Shona Ancestors: Hungwe/Chapungu and Gora/Vulture: The outer wall of this temple was deco
rated with birds carved on the summit of soapstone beams ve or six feet in height; of the six and from its 
beak we can easily see that it is intended to represent a vulture. Two have decorations down the back and 
round the neck, and one has four circles out on it, two on the wings and two below, presumably to represent 
incubation and fertility. (Bent 1892) 
Frederick Selous 
The German Heinrich Schlichter (1893) disagreed: only a very rude people possessing no written characters 
and doing all their building by eye and without measurement could have built such a bad structure. Selous 
speculated: 
Well, we will suppose that two or perhaps three thousand years ago a commercial people pen
etrated from Southern Arabia to Mashonaland. They were acquainted with the requirements of 
the civilized nations of Asia at that period and understood the value of gold. This metal they 
discovered amongst the hills and in the streams of Mashonaland. It time these Arabian merchants 
gained a footing in the land and taught the black aborigines to mine for them. Their principal 
station was at Zimbabwe, where they built, with the forced labour of the aborigines, a temple for 
the worship of Baal, and a strongly-built and well-situated fortress. But I take it, that, like the 
Arabs in Central Africa at the present day, these ancient Arabians brought a few or no women 
with them, but took a very handsome allowance of wives from amongst the aboriginal blacks. 
For a long period intercourse was kept up with Arabia, and during this period the gold seekers 
spread over the whole of South-eastern Africa from the Zambesi to the Limpopo, everywhere 
mixing with the people, and teaching them their own rude arts of wall-building and gold-mining. 
In the course of time, we will suppose, that events happened in Arabia which put an end to 
all intercourse with the distant colony in Mashonaland, and as time went on, as the alien race 
were still in small numbers, compared with the aboriginal blacks, and as they had none of their 
own women with them, they gradually became completely fused, and nationally lost among the 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 13 Pre-Colonial African Cities STS.089, Fall 14 
ments Zhizo farming communities, the name being simply a placeholder for a people whose name will never 
be historically known. In the seventh century CE, these two communities had settled enough to produce 
commodities to trade with the Indian Ocean coast. Among the innovations generating such surplus were 
iron, copper, and gold mining, smelting, and smithing, as well as ivory hunting and carving. These outcomes 
of local innovation were traded with Asian merchants for Chinese and Indian wares like glass beads, cloth, 
and ceramics. By the seventh-ninth century CE, this local production and surplus value had attracted the 
attention of the Arabian traders, who set up settlements along the eastern seaboard and increasingly acted 
as middlemen between the production centers in the hinterland and incoming overseas merchants ( Hall 1987). 
The Zhizo are the ancestors of vaKaranga of southern Zimbabwe, who in the tenth century A.D. es
tablished centralized political systems, starting with locations archaeologists denote Schroda (placeholder 
name) at the Shashe-Limpopo conuence. These settlers then moved to another site placeholder-named 
Bambandyanalo further west (but south of the Limpopo), perhaps economically distressed at the declining 
trade with the Swahili. In any case, archaeologists speculate, Bambandyanalo probably became over
crowded after the eleventh century, forcing its rulers to shift the settlement to Mapungubwe, again south 
of the Limpopo, in the twelfth century. By 1300, the centers of power had shifted to Dzimbahwe (Great 
Zimbabwe). It is often assumed that these farmers spread out into the Chivowa, Gumanye, and Dzimbahwe 
hills of what is now Masvingo not in the sense of walking there (foot-migration) but incremental spread of 
new homesteads, villages, elds, and pastures in that direction (Pikirayi 2001). Recent careful attention 
to the conduct of power among vaKaranga (including speakers of chiZezuru, chiKorekore, chiManyika, and 
chiNdau) suggests that dierent successors to the throne did not have to move to the White House or State 
House in the western sense, but rule from their own homesteads. It seems likely that Chikowa, Gumanye, 
Dzimbahwe, and even Manyanga (seat of later Rozvi power) were homesteads of succeeding incumbents, 
contrary to earlier interpretations (Pikirayi 2001; Human 2005). 
For this reason, speculations that mid-fteenth century shifts in the geographic locus of power were a result 
of the declining power of a specic, xed dynastic center where every incumbent ruled from may well be 
wrong. The state itself could well have continued to ourish, except that it was being rerouted through 
control points the new ruler designated. This may account for the proliferation of not one but many dz
imbahwe; each incoming incumbent ruled from one (Maund 1891, 1892). The traditions of Munhumutapa 
suggest that Nyatsimba Mutota, a prince and heir, had left Dzimbahwe (Great Zimbabwe) to nd salt in the 
Mavhuradonha Mountains (Mt. Pfura?). Instead he established his own capital there and began ruling from 
there, as did his successors. This new seat of power, archaeologists and historians say, thrived on the demand 
for gold and other local products that the Portuguese settlements on the Zambezi provided, thus shifting 
trade away from the Save River route leading between Dzimbahwe and Inhambane. The out-migration of 
Mutota is also attributed to environmental decline. 
However, in chiKaranga (what is now called Shona culture), it is the tradition that when a father has 
many sons, they never settle within the homestead, but to found their own as they become men, marry, and 
prepare to start their own families. Either the father accompanies the son and drives the peg (hoko) into the 
ground marking the homestead and giving it stature (chiremerera ), or the son, being a warrior-prince, took 
a detachment of ghters under his command and marched on foot or on bullback, to a far away place, to con
quer, subdue, and drive a peg in the ground marking his own homestead, village, and province. Sometimes 
it simply became a province of his fathers vast domains (part and parcel of Karanga territorial expansion), 
or an independent domain (Zvarevashe). 
When establishing a village, a chiefdom, or a kingdom, the founder had to fortify his sovereignty not merely 
with military force or political oces in charge of every kingdom. Sovereignty chiKaranga-style was not 
merely a material, geophysical, political, or interhuman thing; the spiritual was, alpha to omega, the back
bone and armor of power, life, and livelihood. The powers of the chief and the whole dzinza (clan) and imba 
youshe (dynasty) resided in makona (clan medicines). Zimbuya guru (great ancestress), popularly known as 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 13 Pre-Colonial African Cities STS.089, Fall 14 
aborigines.... At any rate I am absolutely convinced that the blood of the ancient builders of 
Zimbabwe still runs (in a very diluted form if you like) in the veins of the Bantu races. (Selous 
1893). 
In other words, it was not even possible for Selous to speculate that the black race might have built Dzim
bahwe. If any such existed in their genes, then even such genes were not originally from Africa but of outside 
origin: 
On my theory the blood of the ancient worshippers of Baal still runs in their veins; very much 
diluted, no doubt, but still in sucient strength to occasionally produce amongst them men with 
light-brown skins and high features, and sometimes of great intellectual power. After a certain 
lapse of time, when the higher race had become entirely fused and practically lost amongst the 
lower and more numerous aboriginal people, the worship of Baal died out, and was superceded by 
the old religion of ancestor worship which still prevails.... But I maintain that the wall-building 
and gold-mining, originally learnt from the ancient Arabians, were carried on continuously from 
the rst inception up to the middle of the present century (Selous 1893) 
No Evidence of High Civilization 
Selous concluded: 
In the foregoing pages, I have endeavoured to show that there is no evidence that any high form 
of ancient civilisation ever existed in South-Eastern Africa at all, whilst many facts go to prove 
that the two industries or arts which are supposed by many to separate the ancient inhabitants 
of the country from the Bantu people living there at the present day, namely, gold-mining and 
wall-building, have only been abandoned very recently (Selous, 1893: 316). 
The original builders of the temple came from a country where that form of worship is known 
to have been practised in very ancient times; but I do not believe that this foreign race, in its 
pure state, spread over the whole country between the Zambesi and the Limpopo, and did all 
the gold-mining and wall-building that has been done in that vast territory, and was then utterly 
destroyed and supplanted by a more barbarous people. The evidence available seems to me to be 
far stronger in favour of the theory which I have advanced of the gradual fusion of a numerically 
small number of a race of traders and merchants, who were themselves in a low state of civilisation, 
with the aboriginal inhabitants of the country. Thus alone can I account for many things: the 
long continuance and the gradual deterioration noticeable in the wall-building in Mashonaland; 
the ingrained inherited impulse which causes the Barotsi of the Upper Zambeesi, who are an 
oshoot of the Baritsi of Mashonaland, to still carve the same chevron patterns on their pottery, 
on their knife sheaths, and on their wooden pots and bowls, that the ancient worshippers of Baal 
represented in stone-work round the Temple of Zimbabwe and carved in soapstone hundreds or 
thousands of years ago. Add to this that the wooden bowls themselves still retain the same form 
as the ancient ones carved in soapstone; that the wooden carvings of animals made at the present 
day, and the rude bas-reliefs on the soapstone bowls are the products of the same school of art, and 
the fact that the Bantu races inhabiting Mashonaland and adjoining countries to-day are subject 
to atavism or reversion to a type of man, which is Asiatic or semitic rather than negroid, and it 
seems to me that only one theory is possible, which is that the ancient builders of Zimbabwe were 
not rst destroyed and then supplanted by an inferior race, but that they became gradually fused 
with a lower race, which still bears traces of its admixture with the more intelligent people.... It 
is not to be wondered at that the native races inhabiting [Mashonaland] should have abandoned 
some of their arts and industries, and become the timid and broken-spirited people which they 
are now (Selous 1893: 317) 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 13 Pre-Colonial African Cities STS.089, Fall 14 
Madzimbahwe beyond Dzimbahwe 
Selous 1893: 
I maintain that, so far from there having been an abrupt transition from a people who built the 
temple of Zimbabwe to a race who never put one stone upon another, the inhabitants of Makonis 
and Mangwendis countries in South-eastern Mashonaland, only ceased to surround their towns 
with well-built stone walls during the last generation, when they found that these walls oered but 
an inecient protection against the Zulu hordes of Manikos, and his son, Umzila, by whom their 
country has been continually ravaged during the present century. The more ancient the towns 
appear to be, however, the better, speaking generally, they have been built; and in Makonis 
country, at any rate, there is clear evidence that there has been a gradual deterioration from a 
people who were capable of building walls which will compare with any part of the great Zim
babwe, to the very inferior hut-building barbarians of the present day. Makonis [Father of the 
present chief] town as it now stands is a monument of lth and uncleanliness, and is undefended 
by anything but a small fence. His old town which I also visited, aand from which I believe he 
was driven by Umtasa, was surrounded by a moat and loopholed mud wall, whilst the town, 
which it is said was built by his ancestor, Chpadzi, was surrounded by a well-built, hoopholed 
stone wall. This is one of the best old walled towns I have seen. I visited it for the rst time in 
October, 1890, and again last year. There are many other walled towns in the district, some of 
them reminding one strongly of the fortress on the wall at Zimbabwe. 
Let me here make an extract from my diary, bearing date October 19th, 1890. On that day I 
left Makonis and passed some very curious old ruins. First, there was a hill on which were built 
several concentric walls and the stone foundations of round huts, the whole being surrounded by 
a moat. A little further on, there was a small kopje composed of a few large blocks of granite, 
some of which were piled up in the centre in the form of a tower. The whole of this kopje was 
enclosed by a very well-built wall about 200 yards in circumference, 8 feet in thickness, and 10 
feet in height. The stones composing this wall have the appearance of having been cemented to
gether with mud, which is the rst time I have ever noticed anything of the kind in South-eastern 
Africa. Through this wall there were four entrances, apertures about 4 feet in height, and 2 1/2 
feet in breadth. These apertures were let into the base of the wall, and were roofed over with 
large at slabs of granite. Inside this wall were the foundations of numerous round buildings. 
These foundations were all very well built of closely tted pieces of squared granite, and were 
about 18 inches in depth. The huts that were built upon them must have been at least four times 
the size of the huts used by the natives at the present day.... In the centre of Umtasas deserted 
town on the Chodzani River, a town which he built himself, and from which he was driven a 
few years ago by the Abagaza, will be found a similar hut foundation, very carefully built of 
small slabs of granite, beautifully tted without mortar or cement, which proves that the art of 
building (315) walls of carefully tted granite stones is not even yet dead amongst the Mashonas. 
However, let me return to the walled town of Makonis ancestor. Besides the four entrances 
into the stronghold, there were numerous small holes let into the wall, some of which may have 
served as loopholes through which archers discharged arrows, but others, from their position I 
judge to have been intended for drains to carry o water. This stronghold is said to have been 
built by Chipadzi, the ancient chief of all this part of the country and an ancestor of Makonis. 
The name of the walled town is Chiteketi. 
About half a mile from this old walled town was the burial-place of Chipadzi, one side of which 
was enclosed by a beautifully built wall about 10 feet high, of evenly laid and squared granite 
stones, most carefully tted together without mortar or cement of any kind. This wall was an 
exact facsimile of the best built portions of the great Zimbabwe, and no one who has examined 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
STS.089 Technology and Innovation in Africa
Fall 2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>STS.089  Technology and Innovation in Africa Fall 14 
Lecture 13 - Pre-Colonial African Cities
 
African Architectures: Rethinking the Architecture of the House of Stone
 
Prof. Clapperton Chakanetsa Mavhunga MIT OpenCourseWare 
Vedzimbahwe is ChiKaranga for those of the houses of stone. It is a name that all the various groups that 
speak the common root linguists call ChiKaNdaMaZeKo (ChiKaranga, chiNdau, chiManyika, chiZezuru, 
and chiKorekore) speak. The house of stone was a signature of their collective lineage, while the common 
language acted as one of several technologies of fostering commonality and nationhood. The name Zimbabwe 
(chiZezuru for big house of stone) is derived from the name dzimbahwe . Hwe is short for ihwe (stone), which 
in chiZezuru is pronounced bwe or ibwe. As they looked around for a symbol to rally dierent ethnic groups 
including non-ChiKaNdaMaZeKo groups like amaNdebele and amaTshangana (19th century migrants from 
KwaZulu, South Africa) and maHlengwe (migrants from Musambike, or Mozambique)the black nationalists 
ghting for independence in the 1950s chose dzimbahwe and its walls, which became the name of a republic 
in 1980, called Zimbabwe. 
The word Shona was a name European itinerants gave to people who spoke ChiKaNdaMaZeKo. They 
lived in the high plateau between the Limpopo and Zambezi rivers, before the coming of the foreigners or 
ntebele (SeSotho), under the leadership of Mzilikazi ka Mashobane, in the 1840s. European travelers then 
corrupted ntebele into Ndebele and naturalized it as a designation for Mzilikazis followers. The original 
meaning of Shona is tshona (Zulu for to go under; amatshona (those who go under) was the name the 
Zulu-speaking followers of Mzilikazi gave the ChiKaNdaMaZeKo-speaking peoples collectively, in reference 
to their tendency to take refuge in and ght from caves. Mzilikazis people came increasingly to derisively 
refer to amatshona as amasvina (those who are always dirty) or amaroli (literally blanket draggers) or 
orabarola ngubo (those who drag their blankets), meaning slaves (Taberer 1905, Selous 1893). I will use 
vedzimbahwe as a deep vocabulary that elders used to refer to all ChiKaNdaMaZeKo-speaking peoples as we 
grew up. 
Itineraries to and from veDzimbahwe 
Dzimbahwe was a product of the migration of Bantu starting 3,500 years ago from northwestern Africa 
through eastern and central Africa, across the Zambezi to populate southern Africa. Today descendants of 
the Bantu identify themselves as indigenous people and the owners of the land from whom white settlers 
forcibly grabbed the land from 1890 onwards. However, the original inhabitants of South Africa, Zim
babwe, Lesotho, Mozambique, Swaziland, Botswana, Namibia, and Angola are the San, who call themselves 
Sho, Basarwa, or Khwe, whom the Bantu displaced. The rst wave of Bantu arrived on the Zimbabwean 
plateau about the fth-sixth century CE, settled and established farming communities in areas like Ziwa and 
Gokomere. By the seventh century CE, these people had spread out all the way to the Mozambican and 
South African coastlines. Another wave of migrations from West Africa moved through the equatorial forest 
and settled in the western Zimbabwean plateau, eastern Botswana, and northern South Africa in fth-sixth 
century A.D. (Brandt 1984; Ehret and Posnansky 1982; Vansina 1995; Oliver 2009; and Ehret 2001; Alves 
et al. 2011; Castr`  et al. 2009). 
Both waves of Bantu migrations had spread out by seventh century CE to take advantage of the favorable 
geophysical environment of the central watershed. The Ziwa farmers moved onto the area around what is 
now Harare to farm on the fertile soils and pastures, well nourished by the good rains and almost perennial 
streams. The Gokomere farmers settled in the woodlands on the south-southwest edges of the watershed 
in the Matopo hills and the Shashe-Limpopo basin up to Musina. Archaeologists call these successor settle
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 13 Pre-Colonial African Cities STS.089, Fall 14 
carefully both these relics of a bygone age, can doubt for an instant that they were both built 
by the same race of people. This place is the Zimbabwe or temple of Makonis people, and is 
spoken of by them as The Zimbabwe. Here in time of national trouble the chief slaughters 
cattle, and makes propitiatory oerings to the spirit of Chipadzi, and private individuals make 
oerings of goats, fowls, or pots of beer. Now there is no tower or indeed anything to make one 
believe that this Zimbabwe was ever connected with Phallic worship. It was probably built long 
after the great temple, when the Arabian element had become lost amongst the more numerous 
aboriginal race, and when the people had replaced the worship of Baal by the still older form of 
ancestor-worship. 
The enclosure is probably simply the burial-place of Chipadzi, but the wall could not have 
been better built had it been the work of the actual builders of the great temple.... The word 
Zimbabge or Zimbabghi (the form used by the natives in the neighbourhood of the ruins) is in 
all probability derived from the words umba or imba, a building, plural zimba, and mubge, 
stones, these words being used at the present day in Mashonaland. Thus Zimbabge means the 
buildings of stones, and there were no other buildings except grass thatched huts, came to have 
a special signicance and may be best translated by the English word Temple. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 13 Pre-Colonial African Cities STS.089, Fall 14 
mbonga or sviba, kept these charms and was the most important person in the community after the chief. 
To consummate the powers of makona, the king had to have intercourse with one of his sisters, who was 
to remain single even celibate except for ritual purposes for the rest of her life. In-so-doing, she became 
keeper of makona and the most important woman in that community, to be defended to the death if ever 
under military attack. 
These spiritual fortications do not usually constitute the narratives of Dzimbahwe or Munhumutapa pre
cisely because their writers were either expatriate scholars engaged in surface rather than deep readings of 
African cultural practices, or African scholars who simply rehashed such narratives. The latter group, com
prising pioneering black scholars like Gilbert Pwiti, Innocent Pikirayi, and Weber Ndoro, may probably revisit 
their interpretations in light of a younger generation of archaeologists and historians who take chiKaranga 
seriously not just as a source of information for their own erudition, but as philosophy (Chirikure 2010; 
Mavhunga 2014; Chikowero 2015). What if Dzimbahwe was abandoned because the war medicines of the rul
ing house had been comprised, had become powerless, the oracle said so, it was haunted by zvipoko (ghosts), 
or there were too many varoyi (witches)? What if the heir to the throne (perhaps Nyatsimba Mutota himself 
or his son Nyanhewe Matope) could not return to his forebears? dzitsi (stem, or homestead) to rule from 
there, but chose to rule from Dande instead? None of these interpretations in any way prevents us from 
accepting that such movement and relocation of the seat of power enabled the new ruler to capture and 
monopolize trade with a presence that had displaced the Swahili as middlemen: the Portuguese. Nor does 
it prevent us from seeing this innovative strategic relocation as one among several others in the Zambezian 
neighborhood, with the settlement of Ingombe Ilede on the Kafue-Zambezi conuence also exporting copper 
to the east coast in the late fourteenth century, one century prior to the rise of and its own demise at the 
hands of Munhumutapa (Pikirayi 1993; Pwiti 1996). 
The biggest impediment to an innovative and critical introspection into Zimbabwes and indeed southern 
Africas precolonial history is the almost slavish acceptance of Marxist modes of production and state-centric 
interpretations of human-human and human-environment interactions. Archaeology serially focuses on the 
state and the economy prime among other things, to the extent that the rise and fall of civilizations are 
reduced to economics and the environments capacity to keep it going. That metanarrative has been the 
single most serious impediment to archaeologys otherwise best-placed capacity to anchor a history of African 
technology and innovation. The reason may well be that it is inevitably still also trapped in evolutionistic 
templates that force African archaeologists to have to start their chronology from a Western-centric notion 
of how things began, as opposed to an African notion of time and the origins of things. 
Thus the story become one of the mobility of the physical environment from big bangs and volvanic erup
tions (de-spiritualzed as the white man would want it to be), then the origins of species (as Darwin said and 
Robert Leakey and others prophesied), then hominid evolution, then hunting and gathering, then making 
tools in stone, then iron, then building in stones, then farming, then state formation, and so on. Nowhere in 
this scheme is the African perspective of the origins of the earth and its constituents ever considered; it is 
already presumed a myth, a ction. From Zhizo, to Bambandyanalo, to Mapungubwe, to Great Zimbabwe 
to Mutapa, it is already one teleology towards a version of cultural evolution already appropriated in the 
Western register. There is nothing more to say. 
To return to migrations it seems that the issue of foot mobilities in the founding of Dzimbahwe across 
Zambezia is not one of migrations per se but also of families outgrowing their natal home and, as children 
became adult, marrying and setting up their own household as culture dictated. As chiKaranga says, chava 
chigondora chava chimombe, kusagona kutunga urema hwacho (a bullock is a bull, inability to ght is its 
own laziness). Mutota was staying true to this dictum. As he marched north towards Mount Pfura to realize 
his own manhood, he carried with him the innovative traditions of his ancestors, and in so-doing carried 
dzimbahwe with him, and built it in Dande. So did many other veDzimbahwe (the name given to male 
vaKaranga): they carried the architectural tradition of stone masonry with them and built their on rusvingo 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Mining &amp; Metallurgy (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-089-technology-and-innovation-in-africa-fall-2014/resources/mitsts_089f14_lecture11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>STS.089  Technology and Innovation in Africa Fall 14 
Lecture 11 - Mining &amp; Metallurgy 
Prof. Clapperton Chakanetsa Mavhunga MIT OpenCourseWare 
Two main aims: 
1.	 To build on the conversation on music, beer, witchcraft, and healing human power over forces that 
might seem at rst sight uncontrollable and see how they gure in technology and innovation in Africa. 
Does spirituality stie of inspire/govern the conduct of innovation? 
2.	 Picking on a theme of apprenticeship that has eeted in and out of our discussions so far, to understand 
its role in technology and innovation, and the family and kinship network as an important institution of 
informal(ized) innovation in Africa. 
Trivializing African metallurgical innovations 
J. Flint (1974) : By 1800, the West African iron mining and smelting industries, upon which the blacksmiths 
had once had to rely completely for their raw material, were almost at an end, ruined by the competition of 
cheaper and purer iron bars imported from Europe. 
Denis Williams (1974): Denis Williams caricatured traditional African iron smelting in general as a 
mysterious transformation of earth into metal. To him, the African iron producer was a prisoner of the 
supernatural world. This, according to him, explains the backwardness and the static condition of African 
technology, especially vis-a-vis European technology. Nancy Neaher, Leonard Pole, and Merrick Posnansky 
disagree with Williamss iron hunger and the alleged changelessness of African practices. 
Miller and van der Merwe (1994): In light of the reassessment of evidence for very early smelting 
in Agadez, it is reasonable to believed that the knowledge of metal working was introduced to sub-Saharan 
Africa from outside, despite the paucity of archaeological evidence in those areas that might have acted as 
conduits for the spread of this technological knowledge. 
Pre-colonial Mining 
More (1974) on Metal Age People : Not only did the people of Africa, before the advent of the Eu
ropean, mine and prospect for various metals, but they were also capable of working iron, copper, tin, and 
gold and of making bronze and brass. It therefore seems to me more appropriate to refer to them as Metal 
Age peoples rather than as Iron Age peoples, which is the term commonly used. 
Candice Goucher : Such a view does not take into account the state of European metallurgy at the time. 
European imports actually required an expansion in the repertoire of West African blacksmiths, including 
gun repairs and gunsmithing; expensive, repairs by African blacksmiths. 
Spirituality and Metalworking 
As Onwuka Njoku has shown with respect to the Igbo, ironworking was highly ritualized and shrouded 
in mystique; supernatural forces were solicited to participate in and supervise the production process. 
Therefore, any description or analysis which omits the magico-religious context of the production process 
is bound to paint an incomplete picture; it would be impossible to appreciate the depth and strength of 
this traditional industry without rst understanding the mystical elements associated with it. Conceptions 
of the qualities or powers of iron and the ritual acquisition of the means to handle iron by the smith; the 
production process indicates how Igbo metalcraftsmen forged a working synthesis between technology and 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 11 Mining &amp; Metallurgy STS.089, Fall 14 
Wise commissioned the demonstration in the District Commissioners front garden, the setting was largely 
articial. By dividing the articles between the physical steps and the rituals, he contributed to the detach
ment of smelting from its place in daily life. In doing so, he drew upon Father Roberts recently published 
work (Wise, 1958). 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 11 Mining &amp; Metallurgy STS.089, Fall 14 
originated in the south, in the Mambwe clan of Sinkambe (Wright). Usually priest-chiefs were identied with 
iron-smelting and magic; Stefano took over from his father as the master smelter, having been invested with 
the ntangala , the secret medicines necessary to the practice and authority of a master. By that time, he had 
experience as a msole , the principal assistant, was married and had at least one child. He and his wife were 
baptized Christians, but adherence posed no obstacle to his conduct of the traditional rituals of iron smelting, 
which were not criticized by the village catechists who were responsible for directing the swelling numbers of 
Christian adherents in the interwar years. When the time came to rebuild the ilungus , Stefano established 
them close by his year-round residence at Ikumba instead of at Makuzani, a march of several hours. The skill 
to direct this construction came from observation and participation, not merely in boyhood when his father 
had last built, but also by volunteering as an assistant when other masters called for helpers in such projects. 
Apprenticeship and Graduation : At the end of training, apprentice passed through a ritualized gradu
ation ceremony: ima otutu or ihe otutu , the blessing of the hammer; and a passing out ceremony, required 
to produce the core tools with which the graduand would start o on his own an anvil, a hammer and two 
pairs of tongs; not to be bought on the market. The graduand could also be put through a prociency test, 
to produce on the spot any item which one of the assembled smiths might ask him to. it was a standardized 
practice standardized by adherence to taboos, ritual procedures, call and response chanting or music, even 
instrumental play, and a strong tendency for mastery to descend through families. 
Arming the Tools : Afterward, he and his new tools were presented to the lineage shrine to receive the 
deitys blessings. Rules and ethics of the profession and graduands rights and responsibilities rehearsed to 
him by priest, who gave the graduand a drink of water into which a hammer had been dipped. He also 
made four strokes of native white chalk, nzu, on the chest of the graduand, invoking the god of iron to guide 
this young bird...about to y, to strengthen his wings, sharpen his beak, and open his eyes, so that 
he could be productive in the places of work he sought. After all, people will not eat sand, and by their 
special gifts, the new smiths would fend for himself (Njoku). 
Smelters and Smiths : two main phases of iron production, namely smelting and smithing. Iron ore 
embedded in rocks, and smelting is the process of extracting the ore from its non-ferrous matrix. Smithing 
is the forging of iron and other non-ferrous metals into items for human consumption. In some commu
nities, smelters were also smiths; in others, they were separate occupations. Smelting was undertaken by 
lineage-based work groups, not individuals. It was energy-sapping work involving four key stages: wood fuel 
production, furnace construction, ore prearation, and the loading and ring of the furnace charge. Each of 
these stages was preceded and sometimes accompanied by magico-religious observances in which the god of 
iron was fervently called upon to supervise the process to ensure a successful and accident-free smelt. 
Abstinence while Smelting : village participation involved helping with the massing of raw materials 
and giving domestic support to the smelting team. Some women and children participated, although more 
women remained behind to deal with the female tasks of harvesting the millet. Women normatively did not 
in any way participate in the active smelting, and their sexual duties were in abeyance owing to the obligation 
of the leaders, at least, to remain celibate throughout the season. This discipline continued to be a point of 
professional dignity for Mzee Stefano. The team donned leather singlets, they sweated and were smelly, they 
enjoyed their ribald jokes and songs [referring to sexual matters in an amusingly rude or irreverent way]. 
But womens work, in brewing millet beer and cooking, cannot be eliminated from the equation of labour 
considerations, and proximity to home lent exibility in distributing eort among many tasks (Wright). 
What motivated people to join in building furnaces and turning out to produce the stockpiles of raw mate
rials also has an initial answer that seems straightforward. A cow was slaughtered when a new furnace was 
to be build, and beer and food were supplied while the clay from anthills was brought and kneaded and the 
constructed progressed (Wright). The sacricing of a chicken and sprinkling of its blood by a pre-adolescent 
girl, and the burying of protective medicines (ingila ) also occurred. The nal touches, just short of comple
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 11 Mining &amp; Metallurgy STS.089, Fall 14 
the supernatural; to explore the inner logic of the magico-religious phenomena of the industry; the dearth of 
written documentation seems to compel reliance on oral information. 
Technology and Religion : Traditional Igbo iron technology was embedded in a web of rituals and re
ligious ideas. To the contemporary mind, this is an antithesis, as technology and religion are regarded as 
opposites. Technology is the application of science and is seen as founded on rationality and tested mastery 
of the laws of nature. Religious beliefs and rituals, on the other hand, are thought to be symptomatic of a 
peoples inability to comprehend and master nature. They are, therefore, said to be built on ignorance and 
blind faith. Is this, then, to say that traditional Igbo iron working was not based on rational and scientic 
foundations; that the iron producers were helplessly controlled by invisible forces in a production process 
they neither comprehended nor mastered? (Njoku, 1991). I would like us to see the rationale from the 
ironworkers perspective, not ours. 
What is skill in the presence of the spiritual?: Without mystical powers from his deity, the smelter 
would not be able to perform the mystery of turning earth into iron, nor a smith the mystery of forging iron 
into tools, weapons, ornaments, or the articles of ritual. 
Incoming Technology and African Innovation : As Njoku shows, Ogun (the iron deity of the Yoruba) 
governs not just iron products of his priesthood, but incoming technology as well. Ogun has become the 
patron of taxi, bus and lorry drivers, who hang his emblematic representation in their vehicles. Yoruba 
drivers reputedly go out of their way to run over dogs as oerings to Ogun. Again, sacrices to Ogun can 
be made and oaths sworn upon car engines... When an Igbo person buys a new car, he usually launches it 
by libation. But the libation is not made to the iron deity or the car technology but to the buyers chi, that 
is his personal deity and to his ikenga, the god of achievement among the Igbo. 
Apprenticeship 
Marcia Wright (2002), through the story of Mzee Stefano, master smelter in Upa, Tanzania, beautifully 
writes: 
The ethno-archaeologists spearheaded by Peter Schmidt must consequently be challenged on a 
number of scores, including their erasure of individuals whom they subsume into categories of 
craftsmen and ritualists rather than regard as men with choices and activities beyond iron-
working. Mzee Stefano belonged to the generation that saw Upa become overwhelmingly 
Catholic. Reaching the peak of his life in the 1930s, he was not only a smelter observing the tra
ditional rituals of smelting, he was also an appointed sub-chief, blacksmith, farmer, and Catholic 
in good standing. 
The Ise Hoe: The emblematic tool in Upa, the large hoe weighing between 3 1/2 and 4 pounds, was 
used by men to break up the grasslands into sods that were turned inward, forming green manure mounds, 
intumba. This work usually took place in the later part of the rainy season, in March and early April. The 
mounds were spread for millet planting in November or early December. It was the ise hoe that was a key 
element in bridewealth assortments and in many ways symbolized manhood. When dedicating a furnace, 
smelters explained that they spread on its oor bark from the trees that would be cleared for agriculture. 
This treatment made the furnace strong and together with a ritual spreading of millet porridgeby an in
nocent child helped to assure that the hoes from the furnace conveyed fertility (Wembah-Rashid 1969). A 
lighter-weight hoe served as the female tool for weeding the millet elds. Spears, knives, arrow-heads and 
bells rounded out the repertoire of blacksmiths. 
Wright on Mzee Stefanos Apprenticeship : elsewhere in Africa, descent or heredity were critical to re
production of skill within families; in Upa, in principle, it was open to all who wanted to practice; in reality, 
however, followed family lines; The pattern of furnace construction, charging, and carrying out attendant 
rituals had been handed down to him from his father, who had it from his grandfather. This paternal line 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 11 Mining &amp; Metallurgy STS.089, Fall 14 
tion, entailed decorating the furnace as if it were a bride and singing special (often bawdy) songs. Although 
everyone helped with this phase, it was exclusively men and usually junior men who moulded and cut the 
clay for the tuyeres , the vents placed in the openings at the base of the furnace (Wright). 
Smelting continued in 1936 because demand for hoes remained vigorous, and imported tools tended to 
be scarce or not appropriate to the heavy work of creating intumba mounds. For all the ocial projections 
that duka shop sales would make redundant the blacksmiths who forged indigenous iron, the ranks of iron
workers were actually replenished between 1936 and 1943 (Greig 1937), (Wright). 
Given that men were to some extent bottled up in Upa and available to make more intumba mounds 
for greater production of food, the work of women in their gendered tasks of weeding, harvesting, and win
nowing increased commensurately. Altogether, establishing furnaces nearer the village at this time made 
consummate good sense (Wright). 
Testimony to the way in which culture responded to the local colonial situation. Notwithstanding major 
contributions to the migrant labour force on the sisal estates, numbers of the male population remained re
gionally committed, dening their lives as artisans servicing a complex grassland agricultural system through 
the production of tools (Wright). 
The Christian Onslaught : Wright undertakes a reassessment of ve standard published authorities ethno
graphers, Adolphe Lechaptois, Albert Wyckaert, and J.M. Robert, and two administrator-observers, R.C.H. 
Greig and Robert Wise. Where possible, archival sources will gure as a means to expose more fully the 
observers assumptions, strengths, and limitations and the ways in which published accounts have been mis
read by late twentieth-century Africanists. Father Wyckaert arrived in the Tanganyika Vicariat in 1906, just 
as the apostolic vicar, Bishop Lechaptois, was fully engaged in gathering the materials for an ethnographic 
study (Wright). Lechaptois speculated that smelters were a residue from a once more advanced civilization. 
At the same time as conceding that certain young men already preferred porter age or other wage labor 
to the hard and unprotable work in iron smelting, he also reported that where the poeple could compare 
indigenous and imported iron, they preferred the indigenous. To pluck a few passages from the whole work 
without assessing a missionary leader and enterprise that looked to take over rather than transform the 
culture leads to continuous misreading. Wyckaert made the most important contribution to our knowledge 
of iron smelting and associated crafts. He took every opportunity to follow in Lechaptoiss ethnographic 
footsteps. He had found an ideal setting for studies of iron smelting in the Parish of Mwazye, where he 
became a missionary priest in 1909 and Father Superior in 1910. In his article Christian Smiths and Pagan 
Smiths, published in 1914, the Mwami , or master smelter, emerges as a rival priest and moralist. 
It became Wyckaerts project to promote smelting by Christian masters who pledged to do without the 
traditional rituals and medicines. In 1918, Christian villagers departed with the rst Christian master to 
accept the terms, Lui Chawalanga. When the attentive missionaries visited the smelting site to help gure 
out why several charges failed to produce reducible iron, they dismissed suspicion that failure was caused by 
the witchcraft of rivals, blessed by the furnace, and point out certain technical reasons for the failures. 
The missionaries could smile on harvest festivals that mixed traditional and Christian features. Catechists 
continually negotiated between strong cultural imperatives, such as widow inheritance, and the inux of the 
young preparing for conrmation whom, without overt parental opposition, they instructed that monogamy 
alone was Christian. 
Christian Faith and the Demise of Ritual : The young master whom Greig observed as the owner 
of the furnace under construction was a Christian, who seems to have made asides to the District Commis
sioner to the eect that the ritual performance was not necessary to the metallurgic process. It was the elder 
smelters serving as principal councillors, wasole , who guarded it as essential (Greig, 1937). When Robert 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
STS.089 Technology and Innovation in Africa
Fall 2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Leadership &amp; Culture (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-089-technology-and-innovation-in-africa-fall-2014/resources/mitsts_089f14_lecture17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>STS.089  Technology and Innovation in Africa Fall 14 
Lecture 17 - Leadership &amp; Culture: Indirect Rule 
Prof. Clapperton Chakanetsa Mavhunga MIT OpenCourseWare 
The (Ab)use of Endogenous Governance Systems 
There were such fundamental dierences between the French and British systems that, even if both did 
make use of chiefs, it is not possible to place the French system of native administration in the same 
category as British Indirect Rule. It is true that both powers had little alternative to the use of existing 
political authorities as a means of governing their vast African empires, and in most cases these authorities 
were headed by chiefs. What is important is the very dierent way in which these authorities were used. 
(Crowder) 
Northern Nigeria 
The British in Northern Nigeria, which became the model for indirect rule, believed that it was their task 
to conserve what was good in indigenous institutions and assist them to develop on their own lines. The 
relation between the British political ocer and the chief was in general that of an adviser who only in 
extreme circumstances interfered with the chief and the native authority under him. However, where chiefs 
governed small political units, and in particular where their traditional executive authority was question
able, the political ocer found himself interfering in native authority aairs more frequently than ideally he 
should. This was true in many parts of East Africa and in parts of Yorubaland, where the borderline between 
advisory and supervisory in the activities of the political ocer was not always clear. Though indirect 
rule reposed primarily on a chief as executive, its aim was not to preserve the institution of chieftaincy as 
such, but to encourage local self-government through indigenous political institutions, whether these were 
headed by a single executive authority, or by a council of elders. (Crowder) 
Lugard himself had insisted on a reform of the indigenous taxation system and of the administration of 
native justice when he was Governor of Northern Nigeria and believed that, while the colonial government 
should repose on the chiefs, their administration should be progressively modernized. And, though his suc
cessors left them largely to themselves, Sir Donald Cameron, Governor of Nigeria from 193I to 1935, who 
had introduced indirect rule to Tanganyika and held similar beliefs to those of Lugard, was shocked by the 
situation in Northern Nigeria, where he felt the emirates were fast developing into Indian-style native states. 
There was thus a minimal undermining of the traditional sources of authority. The main change for the Fu
lani Emirs of Northern Nigeria, for instance, was that they now owed allegiance to the British Government 
rather than to the Sultan of Sokoto, and collected taxes on its behalf, though they retained, in most cases, 
70% of the amount collected for the administration of their native authority. 
There were notable exceptions, especially in Eastern Nigeria, where the absence of identiable executive 
authority in most communities made indirect rule as practiced in Northern Nigeria almost impossible to 
apply. In such societies, there was British assiduity in trying to discover chiefs or invent them. The British 
system depended on the advisory relationship between the political ocer and the native authority, usually 
a chief. The British political ocer in Kano actually called on the Emir when he had business with him and 
paid him the compliment of learning Hausa so that he could speak to him directly. 
Contrast the position of the Emir of Kano with that of the Alaketu of Ketu in Dahomey. By tradition, 
he was one of the seven most important rulers in Yorubaland, on an equal footing with the Oni of Ife and 
the Alan of Oyo. A friend who visited him while Dahomey was still under French rule found him waiting 
outside the French Chef de Subdivisions oce and kept him waiting a little longer. (Crowder) 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 17	 Leadership &amp; Culture: Indirect Rule STS.089, Fall 14 
Criteria fo r Chefs de Canton 
It i
s clear then that the French explicitly changed the very nature of the powers of the chief and that his 
functions were reduced to that of a mouthpiece for orders emanating from outside. The Chefs de Canton 
(&amp;c.) are recruited: 
i.	 for preference from among the descendants of old families traditionally or customarily destined to 
command 
ii.	 from among notable natives, literate if possible, who have rendered services to the French cause and 
who are tted to ll these functions by their authority or inuence in the country 
iii.	 from among the Chefs de Canton (&amp;c) who have satisfactorily carried out their functions for at least 
four years 
iv.	 from among old soldiers who have completed more than the normal terms of service and who qualify 
for special treatment 
v.	 from among local civil servants (clerks, interpreters, &amp;c.) who have worked satisfactorily for at least 
four years in the public service 
The following are the disciplinary measures applicable to Chefs de Canton (&amp;c.) 
i.	 reprimand by the Chef de Department 
ii.	 temporary withholding of salary 
iii.	 temporary interdiction 
iv.	 reduction of salary 
v.	 dismissal 
Since the chiefs did not, except in rare cases, represent traditional authority and since they were the agents 
of the colonial power for carrying out its more unpopular measures, such as collecting taxes and recruiting 
for labor, they were resented in most parts of French West Africa. While they retained no traditional judicial 
authority such as that of their counterparts in British West Africa in their Native courts, they were agents 
of the law and in this case the unpopular system of summary administrative justice known as the indigenat. 
(Crowder) 
In Light of Complaints about the Corruption of Traditional Leaders... 
Hence it was not surprising that when, in 1957, just before the independence of Guinea, Sekou Toure (then 
Vice-President du Conseil) decided to do away with chiefs. The operation was eected with remarkably 
little protest from either the indigenous population or from the French administration that had made use 
of them. The chiefs no longer possessed political traditional authority and had become mere agents of 
the administration. This is a far cry from Nigeria of the day, where in the North the opposition party 
(N.E.P.U.) were trying unsuccessfully to rouse the people against the chiefs and where the Government of 
Eastern Nigeria. In African countries where the British had imposed chiefs, as in Eastern Nigeria and parts 
of Uganda, their prestige had in fact gone up, but this has certainly not been true in the former French 
territories. (Crowder) 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 17 Leadership &amp; Culture: Indirect Rule STS.089, Fall 14 
1905, w as adventitious and based as much on expediency and reexive response as on any close appreciation 
of the dynamics of the traditional political structure. 
In b
oth Agona and Gomoa, substools claimed and eventually received paramount status with the former 
paramount stool lapsing into subordinate status. In Agona (that is, Fante, and not Asante Agona) the 
Nyakrom stool was recognized as paramount over Agona state in 1931, replacing the Nsaba stool, which had 
been recognized as paramount by the British in 1905, and apparently by the Agona themselves long before 
that. 
The British, who also were familiar with the printed versions of this episode, accepted the Nyakrom rulers 
assertion that his ancestors once held the paramountcy but the decision to transfer recognition was based 
on what appeared to the colonial authorities to be widespread dissatisfaction with the Nsaba ruler. The 
experiment (as, from the British point of view, it was) was not a success. Of the ve Nyakrom amanhin 
between 1935 and 1944, two were destooled, two others abdicated to avoid destoolment, and the fth was 
killed in a motor accident. Not surprisingly the British regarded the situation as a real nightmare and 
reconstituted Nsaba as the paramount stool in 1945. But aairs in Agona had become too complex to be 
resolved so easily and eventually both Nsaha and Nyakrom were recognized as paramount stools by the 
National Liberation Council in 1968. (Henige) 
Traces &amp; Their Uses 
Were the widely variegated succession patterns discussed here the result of colonial exigencies or do they 
represent merely the continuation, perhaps even in attenuated forms, of aspects of Akan political culture 
before the advent of colonial rule? The rst problem concerns the nature of our sources for traditional 
stool politics during the colonial era. Little of our information about Akan succession practices whether 
pre-colonial or colonial is derived from unbiased data. The available records consist primarily of testimony 
given during stool, succession, and jurisdictional disputes and enquiries into public disorders. 
In putting forward this view it is important to remember that the testimony advanced in support of succes
sion changes usually cited pre-colonial precedents. Some of the anomalies of succession practices in Onsu 
have been attributed by Crook to the willingness of the Onsu traditional authorities to play the colonial 
game; that is, to be percipient enough to recognize British predilections and to seek to conform to them by 
citing traditional precedents. (Henige) 
New Wine, Old Bottles 
Was this colonial game a new departure or did it represent a continuation of previous activities with only a 
change in the identity of the paramount? The introduction of new elements like the questionnaires stimulated 
what were likely to have been new responses, but were these not perhaps more in the nature of new wine in 
old bottles? (Henige) 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
STS.089 Technology and Innovation in Africa
Fall 2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 17 Leadership &amp; Culture: Indirect Rule STS.089, Fall 14 
Paternalism/Separate De velopment vs Assimilation/ evolu e 
Wh
y this great dierence in approach by the two powers to the question of native administration, given that 
both for reasons of economy had to administer their vast African possessions with the aid of chiefs? The 
dierence has much to do with dierence in national character and political traditions. While few would 
disagree that the British were inspired by the concept of separate development for their African territories, 
there is still much debate as to how far the French were inspired by the concept of assimilation even after 
its formal abandonment as ocial policy in favour ofapolitique dassociation. (Crowder) 
David Henige &amp; the Complexity of (In)direct through Chiey Political Systems 
in Ghana 
Here, then, the problem should not be considered so much as deviation from a norm since these stools, 
mostly established after the arrival of the Europeans on the coast, were inuenced as much by earlier Guan 
practices and by intrusive European institutions as by those of the Akan. 
In 1939, the District Commissioner at Cape Coast thought that the Mkusukum electors may seek a candi
date from some other family should the present stool family [Twidan] not produce a satisfactory candidate 
in the near future and he advised them not to change without government sanction. (Henige) 
Interference &amp; Instrumentalization of African Endogenous Governance Systems 
In Dadiesoaba, an Asante stool, there was a change from the rightful line at some indeterminate time. In 
Ajumaku, the State Council decided in 1931 to change the line of succession since it was dissatised with 
the manner in which the Stool Family [has] conducted the aairs of the State. The Council advanced the 
argument that the unwanted stool family had only been caretakers after all and that the change was no 
more than a return to an earlier, more correct, state of aairs. 
Any change in ruling line, no matter how permanent it had become, could easily be interpreted as orig
inally having been intended as a temporary expedient. Occasionally this argument, when advanced by the 
original ruling line, was successful. But if the new line had been ruling for a reasonably long period, 
the colonial administration usually rejected the plea for reversion unless other considerations supervened. 
Changes in ruling line have almost certainly occurred in other Akan paramount stools; regrettably, though, 
the data for these are less full and unambiguous. (Henige). 
Distortions &amp; Caricatures 
Although because of broad eligibility, succession undoubtedly circulated widely in the precolonial period, 
the perception of a rotating system of succession was probably the result of the practice of the Gold Coast 
government after c. 1915 to require that a questionnaire be completed before an election could be conrmed 
and gazetted. Among the questions were those asking how many houses were eligible to ll the paramount 
stool and the house to which the applicant belonged. 
We know that one Kwamina Hammah had been enstooled in 1889 and that his ancestor Hammah had 
been destooled about twenty years before that, after which members of a dierent house (or abusua?) seem 
to have ruled. After 1889, however, only members of the restored line had been elected. (Henige) 
Direct Interference to Regularize Stools as Structures of Indirect Rule 
In their dealings with African traditional authorities, the British sought to impose a hierarchical system at 
the apex of which a large number of rulers were recognized as amanhin or Head Chiefs and granted juris
diction over a number of other stools. The implementation of this structure, principally between 1895 and 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Crafts of Witches (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-089-technology-and-innovation-in-africa-fall-2014/resources/mitsts_089f14_lecture10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 10 The Arts of Witching STS.089, Fall 14 
people see muti placed there as zvitsinga to aict the intended target when he or she steps upon it. Most 
aictions among vedzimbahwe are usually believed to start at night. 
These beliefs, which have governed peoples conduct but are never questioned or dared, go beyond witchcraft 
precisely because infractions are believed to cause pestilence or harm to the infringer, his family, or the entire 
community. Among the Ndebele and vedzimbahwe , burning intwala or inda (lice) or inwele/vhudzi (hair) 
was taboo; one would suer from epilepsy (Davies and Quinche 1935). Anyone who sat in the doorway or 
in his fathers place or seat would never grow. Anyone who drank water while standing would be struck by 
lightning. Nobody was allowed to sit pamaphwa or isikuni (on the hearthstone). Sitting on the hearth
stones, throwing sand into the pool, or burning imizi (a rush used in basket and mat making) also induced 
cold, windy weather. Playing with the tail of a slaughtered cow or ox brought stomachache to all who ate 
the meat. Jumping over wood-ashes was forbidden; any who did it would pass bloody stool or urine. Any 
who sat on the road would get boils. If anyone spilled milk into the re, the cows would develop cracked 
teats. The lambs and kids would die if anyone killed a turtledove. Nobody was supposed to cross a eld in 
which nyimo (Bambara nuts) had been sown, lest they all wither. Any who held a dogs or cats tail would 
develop sore eyes. Anyone who treaded on a grave would have aching feet. And if one poked the re with a 
knife, his mother would develop sore breasts. Eating the spinal cord of animals was taboo; the person would 
easily feel cold. Any boy or man who put a piece of wood that had isikukuku or chikukuku (a swelling on 
a tree stem due to parasitic activity) into the re would develop swollen testicles. No storytelling was to 
happen during summer, otherwise the crops would suer pest infestation and fail. Hitting cattle dung was 
entirely forbidden: the cattle would develop constipation. When working in the elds, eating while standing 
was forbidden; the birds would nish all the corn. Pointing to the gathering rain clouds with ones ngers 
would make the rains go away (Davies and Quinche 1935). 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 10 The Arts of Witching STS.089, Fall 14 
Ndlovus humor and ambitions should not distract us from the point he is making: that ignorance and a 
priori dismissal of witchcraft beliefs risk foreclosing a productive discovery and engagement with its log
ics and operations materially and on the mind. In general, the task he sets before us is dierent from 
the ethnophilosophy, ethnomusicology, ethnolinguistics, anthropological, and ethnohistory projects, which 
sought to understand the aethsetics, structure, and functions of African culture for academic or colonizing 
purposes. The scholars involved in that project were outsiders for whom Africa presented as fascinating 
eldwork space to engage in participant observation with the native informants giving their informa
tion to the expatriate ethnographer. These researchers were there to put the ethno into the graph. 
These ethno-siudies by Africanists were so obsessed with witchcraft to reveal the savagery of the native. 
They merely described witchcraft in such minute detail to explain why Africa was so messed up; witchcraft 
became the anti-thesis of the technological, the scientic, the civilized, and the Judeo-Christian (Junod 1927). 
I see witchcraft as a craft, a domain of secret knowledge, and a technological space that must be understood, 
not in a judgmental, moralistic, or pejorative us versus them way. 
Anti-Witchcraft: African Pest Management Technologies 
In part to protect against witchcraft, when a family or community was migrating to a new homestead or 
village, the choice of settlement in or migration from a given area could not be made without the consulta
tion, approval, and instruction of vadzimu . In fact, they were requested to guide the journey, to keep the 
home secure from pests, along with minda (elds) and pfuma (livestock wealth) (Nyevera 1983). At the 
commencement of the migration, the father of the household would kneel down in the house and recite a 
prayer asking for guidance. 
Upon arrival, right after informing the ancestors of their gratitude for the new home they had been guided 
to, the elders proceeded to invite a nanna to conduct a ritual called kupinga mush (medically securing the 
homestead or village against pests). The rational was that musha unoda kupfekedzwa (the homestead or vil
lage needs to be clothed), so that people from outside could respect it, kwete kuita sedambiro remadzvinyu 
(not to be like a playground for lizards). The procedure involved the use of many tree species. It entailed, 
for instance, planting mishenjere or locating the homestead near trees like mubvumira and mutandangozi 
that refracted ngozi (avenging spirits) and those like mukonde (euphorbia) that refracted mheni (lightning). 
Mutarara was used to protect the village against witches, pegs made from wood of the mutarara tree, and 
dipped into medicine [and] driven it all around the village by a medicine man (NADA 1945). For that 
reason, mutarara could not be brought into the village for use as huni (rewood) under any circumstances 
(NADA 1945). 
The hoko that the nanga drove into the ground still required the sanctication of the ancestors for it 
to work. So when he was gone, the elders oered the nal prayer, asking the ancestors to now come and 
look after the homestead, to arm the hoko. We can now see why witches prayed to the ancestors to disarm 
the hoko and let them in. 
The association of pests and pestilence with the night is also interesting for two reasons relating to human-
animal relations. In the rst instance, night was an aid to pest control: it was the time when some deadly 
insects would be sleeping, and people could, like witches, move through the insects habitat without being 
seen or molested. Tsetse is one example of such a pest. In the second, however, the night (especially the 
dark night) is generally associated with pestilence. That is when the witches come out and patrol. Whether 
anyone has actually seen them in action is open to conjecture. I havent. However, naked women are found 
at a victims home or inside a cemetery at dawn. A nanga called in to cleanse the village smells out a 
witch who confesses to eating someones child, husband, wife, or mother. In their sleep, people see witches 
bewitching them. Owls perch on rooftops at night in their dozens, and are interpreted as accompaniments 
of the witch busy down below, bewitching the sleeping occupants (and not looking for the big rats running 
across the yard from their barrows in one grass-thatched roof to the next). In the morning, at the crossroads, 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 10 The Arts of Witching STS.089, Fall 14 
They will confess that they usually undertake expeditions as far as South Africa, Botswana, Zambia any
where there is a relative to be bewitched. They will reveal that they y in winnowing baskets, nocturnally 
taking o from and landing in graveyards, and completing their return journey the same night. Nobody not 
privy to their nocturnal shenanigans will know, until a mission goes horribly wrong, the sun sets while they 
are still in a graveyard, in the house of a relative, and so on. They are totally naked, with all their wares 
the winnowing basket among others and are arrested for loitering around vari musvo (naked). Usually the 
courts will call witchcraft experts (or nanga ) to testify, and once these experts conrm it is witchcraft, the 
indecency case is dismissed (Naked Basket Flight, Woman Flew in Basket, Zimbabwe Witches 2012). 
It is very easy to read such stories and simply say, This is cuckoo! and move on. Without recourse to 
Western scientic reasoning, anybody who does not believe in witchcraft or spiritual forces will simply say: 
Short of digging the whole grave up to get to the corpse, it is impossible for witches to get to and start 
eating the esh. Also: A reed basket is simply too fragile to carry a human body through the air. In any 
case, how does it even take o and y without propulsion? A Western physics perspective would be: It 
has to have a force that allows it to defy the force of gravity and achieve self-propulsion once in motion. 
Could there be an African or chidzimbahwe theory and law of forces at play that Western physics cannot 
explain? Or is that physics common to all, and that commentators have simply not bothered to investigate 
further in order not to be found justifying the scienticity of witchcraft, which colonial commentators have 
marked as a symbol of the Africans primitiveness before Europe gave them the gift of civilization? 
This was the brave challenge that the retired Zimbabwean journalist Saul Gwakuba Ndiovu posed in the 
wake of a spate of witchcraft incidents involving winnowing baskets, even though nobody has actually seen 
one in action ying through the sky and captured it visually: 
If it is indeed true, and there is no doubt that it is, there is a need to investigate the Gokwe 
witchcraft story to nd out whether or not it has a potential for the economic and/or social 
development of Zimbabwe. Taking the Gokwe-Budiriro incident as an example of what Zimbab
wean witchcraft can oer the aviation industry, a research centre could be established with some 
witches playing major roles for which they would be duly paid. The Government could play a 
facilitators role, leaving the eld to private individuals and companies to research, invest, pro
duce and market the products and services. If winnowing baskets (njiselo ) can actually transport 
people from Gokwe to Harare (and at night at that) it means that shorn of its negative aspects, 
this particular type of Zimbabwean witchcraft can be turned into a most useful and usable tech
nological wizardry. This is an obvious challenge to the countrys universities and ought to be 
treated as an opportunity towards technological progress and advancement in modern methods 
of travelling. Investigative journalists should now develop this story from its very start up to 
its logical conclusion. Its very start is the society in which the alleged witches live and practise 
their secretive science. The logical conclusion is eect (or eects) of witchcraft on its victims. 
(Ndlovu 2013) 
For Ndlovu, treating these reputed competences of witches as cuckoo, crime, or hearsay not only fails to get 
at the science of this advanced winnowing basket aviation. Treating witchcraft in general as such forecloses 
our access into many forms of secret skills and knowledge that can, he says, help make this world a better 
place for its people, ora and fauna (Ndlovu 2013). In a very lighthearted way, Ndlovu ends by saying that 
winnowing basket incidents should inspired Zimbabwe to establish an academy for: 
the manufacturing of modern witchcraft products that can be exported with the passage of time 
and as technological enlightenment removes the black shroud of secretiveness from Zimbabwean 
traditional technological wizardry. Young people with a vision will not fail to see an advantage 
in opening taxi and bus companies at Gokwe, and be ready to enter what we may call the Win
nowing Basket Transport Age. Meanwhile, the rst Zimbabwean university to take part in the 
rst public Winnowing Basket Demonstration Flight will go down in the countrys technological 
history annal as the countrys educational institution of destiny. (Ndlovu 2013). 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Lecture 10 The Arts of Witching STS.089, Fall 14 
nature that we might not consider subject to human manipulation, that is, as technologies for conducting 
the craft, or art, or witching. These are potent tools varoyi (witches) cast upon people, livestock, and crops 
in the form of uroyi (witchcraft). Vedzimbahwe (also called the Shona people) say it happened this way. 
First the witches prayed to their own ancestors, then to those of their intended victims for permission to 
just pass through their village (Togarepi, 1983)). 
They capitalized on any existing ancestral anger towards the living. If vadzimu could allow varoyi to spray 
uny e (itchy substances) or nh ata (eas) on the mortals sleeping in the house, the pain would induce them 
to brew that beer all the much faster, and the ancestors would quench their thirst. Children who grew up 
without ever experiencing itches would have no sturdiness. Varoyi implored vadzimu to step aside and let 
them through the spiritual fortications that the nanga had installed during kupinga musha , to remind the 
complacent mortals of their obligations to the ancestors. The night belonged to the witches. That is why 
no mudzimbahwe or Ndebele called anyone at night; his voice would be taken away by witches (Davies and 
Quinche, 1935). 
So eventually the ancestors relented to protect their own interests, and the witches entered the village 
to remind the living of their obligations to their spiritual forebears. To enter the village was one step, 
getting into the individual homestead was quite another, for besides the makona (medicines) of the village, 
each homestead had its own hoko (medicine pegs). Upon getting to the entrance of each homestead, varoyi 
sought permission from the family ancestor asking him to remove the fences, make the homestead wide 
open, that we may do our work. The witches were only here to punish, to give them rash to scratch, so as 
to see another side of life. They craved to see tears, to wake their victims up, so that they can open their 
eyes (Togarepi, 1983). 
This, then, was the general theory (not myth) of human and animal health and pestilence among vedz
imbahwe and their neighbors. The witch commanded both spiritual and herbal powers, just like the diviner 
(the only person qualied to diagnose a case (kushopera ) and dispense with the necessary muti). Both were 
practitioners of medicine, one deploying it to cause illness and take life, the other to save and prolong it. 
Sickness was therefore believed to result from witchcraft, with muroyi spraying or hiding it in the huts, 
courtyard, and cattle pens, in the footpaths leaving to the river, well, or elds, or under the trees where 
people did their daily work. The witch also cast mamhepo (airs, or hallucinogens) or zvitsinga (disease
causing implants) on their victims. Only the nanga (healer) could remove mamhepo by burning herbs and 
ordering the mweya yakaipa (bad airs, mamhepo ) to leave the stricken body, and the chitsinga by biting 
the spot where it is buried in the esh and pulling it out. To ward o mamhepo and zvitsinga, a zango or 
dumwa (amulet) was hung around a newly-born childs neck or waist (Posselt 1935, Junod 1906). 
Kuroya is neither a function of personal volition nor supernatural means, but an act...intimately connected 
with natural agencies which [the witch] commands (Posselt). There is the muti or medicine that muroyi 
administers to the intended victim through unconscious ingestion, inhalation, and skin contact. There is 
nothing cuckoo about that at all. Then there is the witchs carrier that includes such animals as the hyena, 
baboon, and sh otter (Ibid.). It is not outside the realm of material possibility that the witch is in fact an 
expert in taming forest animals to become organic vehicles. For long-distance sorties, witches have also been 
known to ride on rusero or tsero (winnowing basket), vedzimbahwe s own version of a ying saucer. Their 
mission: to bewitch the living and the healthy into sickness or to feast on rancid human esh (Holy Spirit, 
2012). 
From This is Cuckoo Towards The Logics and Science of African Witchcraft 
Every year in Zimbabwe, there are women found nude outside a relatives house, far away from their own 
homes. The police arrest them for public indecency; when questioned, they will say they were on a witching 
mission, something went horribly wrong, and the sun set on them, and the witch-spirit deserted them. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
STS.089 Technology and Innovation in Africa
Fall 2014
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>STS.089  Technology and Innovation in Africa Fall 14 
Lecture 10 - The Arts of Witching 
Prof. Clapperton Chakanetsa Mavhunga MIT OpenCourseWare 
This lecture is focused on two types of crafts opposed to one another, namely witching (kuroya in my na
tive tongue, chidzimbahwe or chiShona) and anti-witching (kuroyonora ) or healing (kurapa ). What Adeline 
Masquelier calls a host of sorcerers (mayu , plural maye ) who struck people, cattle and trees alike with deadly 
re every rainy season, who hid in the clouds and ew through the skies. She talks about the protective 
steps (special medicines) the Hausa Mawri people of Arewa, Nigeria, took to protect themselves when they 
still believed completely in bori (spirit possession), before they became Muslims, who believe that lightning 
is sent by Allah. Yet even those converted have not completely severed their ties to spirits, but now believe 
that lightning is caused by a family of bori spirits. Victims of lightning are therefore deemed oenders, not 
victims. But even devout Muslims fear the sorcery of lightning. 
Witching is therefore a exible, adaptive craft. It adapts to the coming of Islam, to market forces; bori 
is certainly no shrinking violet; invoking the spirits does not contradict faith in the Koran. The family of 
noble spirits (Tooru ) still govern the winds, the clouds, lightning and rain and indeed the Niger River itself. 
The bakin bori (black spirits) live in the sky from which they control the clouds which bring the rain; those 
spirits throw lightning on people who have oended them. 
The spirituality of the Zarma people of the Zarma-Songhai region of Niger on the one hand builds nicely on 
the theme of African meteorology that we starting exploring previously. Thus the watam bakwai (seventh 
month) ceremony involves a test to determine if, where, and in what quantity the rain will fall that year. 
Milk is given to the spirits to prevent them from sending lightning down on the people. 
The Zarma spirits are headed by Harakwai, the father and judge, who sends his sons to deliver punish
ment. His oldest, Kirai, throws no lightning, but is fearful nonetheless; he is Dongo the mad one. His 
younger brothers actually do the throwing; theres Moussa, a.k.a. sarkin gaugawa (the king of haste), fast 
and fatal. There is Suleymane, potent and harsh. Then there is Bela, the destroyer and the re controller; 
Belas brother, Hausakwai, decides what and who shall be hit or burnt. He has four eyes, hence, Dodo. 
Then there is Yandu, the blacksmith who kills by continually hitting until he reaches the brain. 
Their tools are the thunder stones (kankara ), or neolithic axes recovered by bori specialists from the site 
where lightning has struck; it is claimed they are products of the blacksmith Yandus forge. If Bela is in
volved, the ball is covered with re, and the spirits weapons resemble needles if the target is human. If 
Kirai, Suleymane, and others are nished, they will leave a sign three handfuls of grain aside, untouched. 
If they hit a goat, they put a dead lizard on the animals back. The stones can only be dug up by a healer, 
who claims them as prized exhibitions and markers of his prowess. 
The reading I assigned for today, Adeline Masqueliers Lightning and the Avenging Spirits, speaks to 
a wider phenomenon of the uses of forces that are on the face of it beyond human control, and yet here they 
are as instruments in humankinds hands. Last week I retreated to my own research to initiate a conversation 
to see the larger context within which societies manipulate such forces. I also did this because I would like to 
land a more experiential perspective as an Africa, where Masquelier and other non-Africans might approach 
Africa as empirical fodder for Western theory. The reason for this course is to explore the African voices 
and to see what meanings of technology we might derive from them. As you may notice, around p. 20, 
Masquelier ends up speculating, with the I think. 
Let me start my exploration by casting the witch as a pest, a human-spiritual pest, mobilizing forces of 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
