<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-036-technology-and-nature-in-american-history-spring-2008/</course_url>
    <course_title>Technology and Nature in American History</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>History </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>A brief history of ecological change in North America in the eighteenth century</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-036-technology-and-nature-in-american-history-spring-2008/resources/wk2_outline/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Week 2: Colonial American Land Use 
12 Feb 2008 
 
A Brief History of Ecological Change in North America to the Eighteenth Century 
 
1. Deep history of ecological change in North America 
a. Geological transformations 
i. Continental drift 
ii. Rocky Mountain formation 
iii. Glaciation 
b. Debates over Paleoindian presence 
i. Date of arrival 
ii. Megafaunal extinction 
1. Overkill 
2. Climate change 
iii. Native American population at contact 
c. The ecological Indian 
 
2. Native American relationships to non-human nature 
a. Practices 
i. Geographical and seasonal variation 
1. New England 
2. The South 
3. Great Plains 
ii. Use of fire 
b. Principles 
i. Preserving species population and diversity 
ii. Subsistence (not market) agriculture 
iii. Symbolic value ascribed to the land 
1. Rituals, story-telling, place-naming 
2. Relation with and conception of animals  
3. Exchange 
a. Alfred Crosbys Columbian Exchange 
i. Epidemics 
ii. A biological revolution 
b. Knowledge systems and practices 
i. The Rice Coast 
c. Technologies and skills 
i. Firearms and the skulking way of war 
ii. The American axe 
d. Cultural beliefs and practices 
i. Property rights 
ii. Relationship between human and non-human nature 
e. Commodity exchange 
i. Fur 
ii. Forests</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . STS.036 Technology and Nature in American History
Spring 2008</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>For further reading  
 
Alfred Crosby, The Columbian Exchange: Biological and Cultural Consequences of 1492  (Westport, 
Conn.: Greenwood Publishing Co., 1972). 
 
Shepard Krech, The Ecological Indian: Myth and History  (New York: W. W. Norton, 1999). 
 
Theodore Steinberg, Down to Earth: Natures Role in American History  (New York: Oxford 
University Press, 2002).</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>&#8220;Devilish iron horse&#8221; and &#8220;Aeolian harp&#8221;: artistic responses to industrialization</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-036-technology-and-nature-in-american-history-spring-2008/resources/wk5_outline/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . STS.036 Technology and Nature in American History
Spring 2008</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>e. Excerpts from Henry David Thoreau, Economy, Walden, 1854 
1. I would rather ride on earth in an ox cart with a free circulation, than go 
to heaven in the fancy car of an excursion train and breathe a malaria  all 
the way.  
2. Our inventions are wont to be pre tty toys, which distract our attention 
from serious things. They are but  improved means to an unimproved 
end, an end which it was already but t oo easy to arrive at; as railroads 
lead to Boston or New York. We ar e in great haste to construct a 
magnetic telegraph from Maine to Texas; but Maine and Texas, it may be, have nothing important to communicate.  
 
3. Henry D. Thoreau and the making of Walden  
a. Thoreaus path to Walden 
i.  Studious of natural facts (Emersons eulogy for Thoreau, 1862) 
ii. American literary Transcendentalism 
1. Build, therefore, your own world. As  fast as you conform your life to 
the pure idea in your mind, that wi ll unfold its great proportions. A 
correspondent revolution in things w ill attend the influx of the spirit. 
(Emerson, Nature, 1836) 
b. On Walden Pond (July 4, 1845 to September 6, 1847) 
i. I went to the woods because I wished to live deliberately, to front only the essential facts of life, and see if I could not learn what it had to teach, and not, 
when I came to die, discover that I ha d not lived.  I wanted  to live deep and 
suck out all the marrow of life  to driv e life into a corner  (Where I Lived 
and What I Lived For) 
c. Thoreaus Concord 
i. Boston to Fitchburg Railroad (reached Concord in June 1844) 
ii. Telegraph line 
1. At the entrance to the D eep Cut I heard the telegr aph wire vibrating like 
an Aeolian Harp.  I instantly sat do wn on a stone at the foot of the 
telegraph pole--&amp; attended to  the communica tion. (Thoreau, Journal , 
September 12, 1851) 
d. The writing and publication of Walden  
i. Journal  (over 2 million words in 21 volumes) 
ii. 6 revisions in 7 years 
iii. Published in the summer of 1854 by Ticknor &amp; Fields</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Week 5: The Aesthetics of the Industr ial Landscape in Antebellum America 
4 Mar 2008 
Lecture outline 
 
 
Devilish iron horse and Aeolian harp: Artistic Responses to Industrialization 
 
 
1. Seeing the railroad in the American landscape 
a. Railroad as the icon of the new industrial age 
b. The ideology of progress  
i. John Gast, American Progress , 1872 
ii. Currier &amp; Ives, Across the Continent Westward th e Course of Empire Takes Its 
Way, 1868 
c. Harpers  magazine Artists Excursion on the B&amp;O (June 1858) 
d. Paintings by Hudson River School artists 
i. Thomas Doughty, A View of Swampscott, Massachusetts , c. 1847 
ii. Asher B. Durand, Progress , 1853 
iii. George Inness, The Lackawanna Valley , 1855 
iv. George Inness, Delaware Water Gap , 1859 
v. George Inness, On the Delaware River , 1861-63 
vi. John Frederick Kensett, Hudson River Scene , 1857 
vii. Thomas Prichard Rossiter, Opening of the Wilderness , c. 1858 
 
2. Literary responses to the Age of Machinery 
a. Leo Marxs Machine in the Garden  thesis  
b. Nathaniel Hawthorne, The Celestial Railroad, 1843  
c. Herman Melville, The Tartarus of Maids, 1855 
d. Ralph Waldo Emerson 
i. Early optimism regarding technology as a source of creative inspiration and a 
prosperous democracy 
1. Machinery and Transcendentalism agree well ( Journal , 1843) 
2. Railroad iron is a magician's rod, in its power to evoke the sleeping 
energies of land and water. (The Young American, 1844) 
ii. Later concern that too much reliance on technology would weaken the soul 
1. Things are in the saddle, / And ride mankind. (1847) 
2. I cannot accept the railroad and tele graph in exchange for reason and 
charity. (1851) 
3. Machinery is good, but mother-wit is better.  Telegraph, steam, and 
balloon and newspaper are like spectacl es on the nose of age, but we will 
give them all gladly to have back again our young eyes. ( Journal ) 
4. The age has an engine  but no engineer. ( Journal , 1853)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Conservation and the scientific management of nature</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-036-technology-and-nature-in-american-history-spring-2008/resources/wk9_outline/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>2
 
3. Creating national parks  
a. First parklands created for wilderne ss recreation and hun ting, not wilderness 
preservation 
i. Yellowstone National Park (1872) 
ii. Adirondack Forest Preserve (1885) 
b. Scientific surveys and popular illustrations of the grandeur of the American West 
c. Railroad backers: Jay Cooke of the Nort hern Pacific supported the formation of 
Yellowstone National Park 
d. A new kind of tourism (railro ads and mountain resorts) 
 
4. Inventing Yellowstone Na tional Park (est. 1872) 
a. 2 million acres in a rectangular region overlapping Wyoming, Idaho, and Montana 
b. This will be the grandest park in the worldthe grand, instructive museum of the 
grandest Government on Earth. Nevada Territorial Enterprise  
c. Advocates for Yellowstone may have thought they were preserving a wilderness area.  
But it is more accurate to say that they we re inventing it.  In Yellowstones case, 
creating wilderness meant rendering the Native Americans, who laid claim to the area, 
invisible when, in fact, they had long us ed it for hunting, fishing, and other means of 
survival.  Preservation of the countrys national parks and Indian removal proceeded in 
lock-step motion.Theodore Steinberg, Down to Earth: Natures Role in American 
History  
i. Reservations, treaties, executive orders all displaced Native Americans to make 
way for wilderness tourism 
d. Criminalizing game hunting 
i. Local land use (by Native Americans and rural whites) 
ii. 1896 U.S. Supreme Court decision [7-1, Ward v. Race Horse ] overturned the 
1868 treaty that allowed Indians to h unt on unoccupied govt land and revoked 
their right to hunt ga me on federal lands. 
iii. Hunting became poaching, foraging became trespassing, cutting trees became 
timber theft, and setting fires became arson.   
e. Military order in Yellowstone 
i. Cavalry presence from 1886 to 1916, when the National Park Service took over 
ii. Uncle Sams soldiers were the most effective forest police.John Muir 
iii. Military management of the park 
1. Restricted entry 
2. Fire suppression 
3. Fencing 
4. Policing game poaching  
5. Conservation and the gospel of efficiency 
a. Efficiency imperative in the Progressive Era 
b. Frederick Winslow Taylor and scientific  management (beginning in the 1880s)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>4
For further reading  
 
Karl Jacoby, Crimes Against Nature: Squatters, Poachers, Thieves, and the Hidden History of 
American Conservation  (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2001). 
 
Roderick Nash, Wilderness and the American Mind  (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1967).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>1
STS.036 
8 April 2008 
Lecture outline 
 
Conservation and the Scientif ic Management of Nature 
 
 
1. Redefining wilderness 
a. From wasteland to be conquered (through mid 19th c.) to Edenic landscape to be revered 
and protected (late 19th c.) 
b. The closing of the frontier 
i. Census of 1890 
ii. Frederick Jackson Turners frontier thesis 
iii. Turners American exceptionalism: the pi oneer transforms the wilderness, but 
the outcome is not the old Europe.  The f act is, that here is a new product that 
is American. 
c. Nostalgic lament over the loss of wilderness and pioneer values in a fast-paced modern 
urban-industrial society. 
d. A national cult of wild erness by the early 20th c. 
i. Boone &amp; Crockett Club (est. 1888) by Theodore Roosevelt 
1. Motto: Fair chase and conservation 
ii. Sierra Club (est. 1892) for the purposes of exploring, enjoying and rendering 
accessible the mountain regions of the P acific Coast.  (John Muir, president) 
iii. Boy Scouts of America (est. 1910) by wealthy newspaperman William Boyce, 
popular nature writer Ernest Thompson Seton, and others 
e. Wilderness in the popular cons ciousness in the early 20th c. 
i. Increasing association of wilderness with  the frontier and pioneer traditions of 
America that were believed to be the source of national de mocratic character 
ii. Belief that wilderness was a source of masculine stre ngth, toughness, and 
primitivismattributes that ensured survival in a Darwinian framework 
iii. Ascribing aesthetic and moral value to wilderness landscapes, increasing 
emphasis on wilderness landscapes as sites of contemplation and worship   
2. The publicizer of wilderne ss: John Muir (1838-1914) 
a. Childhood and religious upbringi ng on the Wisconsin frontier 
b. Education: I was only leaving one University  for another, the Wisconsin University for 
the University of the Wilderness. 
c. Machine shop accident, an epiphany, and 1,000 mile trek from Indiana to the Gulf of Mexico (1867) 
d. Arrives in San Francisco (March 1868) 
e. Articulating a wilderness preservation agenda 
i. Yosemite National Park (est. 1890) 
ii. First president of the Sierra Club (est. 1892)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . STS.036 Technology and Nature in American History
Spring 2008</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>3
 
6. National forestry expert: Gifford Pinchot 
a. Training: interdisciplinary study of forestry at Yale, then observation of sustained-yield 
forest management in France and Germany 
b. Pinchots critique of industrialists careless depletion of natural resources in the U.S.: 
the nation was obsessedby a fury of development.  The American Colossus was fiercely intent on appropria ting and exploiting the riches  of the richest of all 
continentsgrasping with both hands, reaping where he had not sown, wasting what he 
thought would last forever. 
c. Forestry within the federal government 
i. Chief of the USDAs Division of Forestry (1898) 
ii. Head of Bureau of Forestry (1901) 
iii. Head of U.S. Forest Service (1905) 
d. White House conference on conservation (1908) 
e. Pinchots principles of conservation 
i. The first principle of conservation is  development, the use of the natural 
resources now existing on this continen t for the benefit of the people who live 
here now.   
ii. The natural resources of the Nation ex ist not for any small group, not for any 
individual, but for all the people. 
iii. Forestry is handling trees so that one crop follows another. 
iv. The job was not to stop the axe but to regulate its use.  
7. Ecological consequences of conservation 
a. Forest management 
i. Trees 
ii. Insects 
iii. Fire 
b. Wildlife extermination 
i. USDAs Predatory Animal and Rodent Control Service (est. 1915) 
1. Hunters in Wyoming killed 40,000 animals (coyotes, wolves, bears, bobcats, lynxes, mountain lions, prai rie dogs, gophers, squirrels, jack 
rabbits) (1916-1928) 
ii. Deer overpopulation in Grand Canyon Na tional Game Preserve in Arizona 
(1906-1924) 
1. Federal hunters killed almost 5,000 c oyotes, nearly 800 mountain lions, 
and over 500 bobcats (1916-1931) 
iii. Mice infestation in Ke rn County, CA (1924) 
 
8. Conclusion 
a. Changing role of the federal government from  donor of public land to private interests 
(19th c.) to overseer and regulator of large sections of public lands (20th c.) 
b. Racial, class, and environmental politics 
c. National parks as highly e ngineered environments 
i. Management and conservation of game animals 
ii. Tourism industry 
iii. Attempted reintroduction of Native Americans and buffalo to Dot Island in Yellowstone National Park</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Imposing an industrial order on the antebellum landscape</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-036-technology-and-nature-in-american-history-spring-2008/resources/wk4_outline/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . STS.036 Technology and Nature in American History
Spring 2008</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>d. Steamboats 
i. Fultons Clermont  (1807) 
ii. The switch to high-pressu re steam engines (1816) 
iii. Steamboat explosions 
e. Railroads 
i. Adopting and adapting British t echnology to American terrain 
ii. The Lowell engine-works 
iii. Conquest and settlement of the West</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Week 4: Industrial America in the Countryside 
26 Feb 2008 
Lecture outline 
 
Imposing an Industrial Order on the Antebellum Landscape 
 
1. Rationalizing the landscape 
a. Jeffersonian vision of an agrarian republic 
b. Jefferson: Cultivators of the earth ar e the most valuable citizens (1785) 
c. U.S. Rectangular Land Survey (1785) 
 
2. New sites and modes of production 
a. Industrial expansion and natural resources in the Atlantic corridor 
b. Regional specialization 
c. Land and labor in the American factory system 
i. Water-powered mills in the countryside 
ii. The social world of the mill 
iii. Paternalism 
1. Patrick Tracy Jackson (1780-1847): The village steeple is the 
unfailing companion of the waterwheel.  
2. The Brandywine Iron Works 
a. Rebecca Lukens (1794-1854) 
3. Lowell textile mills 
a. The Boston Associates 
iv. Worker resistance and labor activism in Lowell 
1. Strike of 1834 
2. Strike of 1836 
3. Lowell Female Labor Reform Association (est. 1844) 
4. Industrial accidents 
5. The Lowell Offering  (1840-1845) 
 
3. A new transportation infrastructure 
a. General Survey Act (1824) 
i. Army Corps of Engineers 
ii. B&amp;O Railroad 
b. Roads 
i. Turnpike companies 
1. Philadelphia and Lancaster Turnpike Co. (est. 1794) 
ii. Internal improvements 
iii. The Cumberland (National) Road (1806-1852) 
c. The canal craze 
i. Benjamin Franklin: Rivers are ungovernable Things . . . Canals are quiet and 
always manageable. (1772) 
ii. Early canal projects (1785-1815) 
iii. The Erie Canal (1817-1825)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>How food became fast, or, industrial agriculture in the twentieth century</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-036-technology-and-nature-in-american-history-spring-2008/resources/wk13_outline/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
STS.036 Technology and Nature in American History
Spring 2008
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>STS.036 
6 May 2008 
Lecture outline 
 
Week 13The Landscape of Food 
 
 
How Food Became Fast, or, Industrial Ag riculture in the Twentieth Century 
 
 
1.  Major trends in the history of agriculture 
a. Rise of industrial agriculture 
b. Decline of the family farm 
 
2. Brief history of agriculture in the 20th century 
a. Pre-WWI golden age 
b. Depression in the 1920s 
c. Legacy of the 1930s 
d. Farm crisis of the 1980s 
 
3.  A new consciousness 
a. Michael Pollan, Naturally 
b. Social movements: slow food, community -supported agriculture, mainstream 
organic 
c. Popular critiques of consumption and production ( Fast Food Nation, Supersize 
Me, King Corn)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Levittown and the building of the suburban family ideal</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/sts-036-technology-and-nature-in-american-history-spring-2008/resources/wk12_outline/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms . STS.036 Technology and Nature in American History
Spring 2008</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>STS.036 
29 April 2008 
Lecture outline 
 
Levittown and the Building of the Postwar Suburban Family 
 
1. The making of the affluent society 
a. Postwar economic boom 
b. Demographic shifts 
i. Baby boom peaked in 1957 
ii. Migration from inner citie s throughout the 1950s 
c. Postwar housing boom and rising rates of home ownership 
d. Federal governments support of suburban development 
i. GI Bill (1944) 
ii. Home mortgages through VA and FHA 
iii. Tax code revisions to allow mortgage interest and property tax deductions in the 1940s 
iv. Minimized risk for large-scale developers 
v. Interstate Highway Act (1956) 
 
2. Levittowns and the mass production of suburban housing 
a. Levittown, NY (late 1940s): 4,000 acres, over 17,400 houses, 82,000 people 
b. Levittown, PA (1950s): 5,500 acres, over 17,30 0 single-family homes, over 70,000 residents 
c. We planned every foot of itevery store, filli ng station, school, house,church, color, tree, 
and shrub.William Levitt 
d. The General Motors of the housing industry 
 
3. The cultural politics of Levittown 
a. A new ideal of domesticity 
b. Racial discrimination in the postwar housing market 
i. We can solve a housing problem, or we can try to solve a racial problem.  But we 
cannot combine the two.William Levitt 
c. Cultural conservatism and conformity 
i. No man who owns his own house can be a Communist.  He has too much to do.
William Levitt  
4. Levittown and the suburban landscape 
a. Standardized landscape aesthetic 
b. Standardized interior spaces and an ethos of efficiency 
c. Technologies of domestic labor  
5. A new ecology of the suburbs 
a. High-energy suburban home 
i. Air conditioning 
ii. Lawn maintenance 
b. Suburban sprawl 
i. Mudslides in southern California 
ii. Wildfires 
c. Septic systems: technically simple but ecologically complex 
i. Infectious disease outbreaks, groundwater contamination, pollution of streams 
ii. Increasing scrutiny from scientific research, public health organizations, popular press 
iii. The suburban roots of environmentalism</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>For further reading  
 
Adam Rome, The Bulldozer in the Countryside: Suburban Sprawl and the Rise of American Environmentalism  
(New York: Cambridge University Press, 2001).</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
