<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/</course_url>
    <course_title>The Law of Corporate Finance and Financial Markets</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Economics </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Business </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Buying a Publicly-held Company II (PDF)
Guests: Stu Cable and Jim Matarese, Partners, Goodwin Procter</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 11: 3/10/04 
Guest: Jim Matarese, Partner, Goodwin Procte r (scheduled guest Stu Cable was unable to 
attend) 
	Fiduciary duties 
	Recap 
	Tie law to practicalities. 
	The CEO cant be in room due  to conflict of interests  beware of law suits, and 
avoid financial interests. 
	Cronism: social relationships, (non-financial) 
	When choosing a committee, a void people with social ties. 
	How much responsibility does the Board of Directors have to ensure that when a 
Board Director says, I am impartial?
-A reasonable amount. They need to prove it to jurors.  
	Should you consider what will  happen to the employers? 
	Assuming straight cash, if you got $24.50/ share or $23/share, what do you do? 
	Shareholders want the highest price. 
	Bottom line: At the end of the day, the corporation is the stockholder. You dont 
look at other constituents. 
	Only when there are slight differenc es in price (pennies!) is it okay. 
	THEREFORE: GET BEST PRICE. 
	The Board works with the acquirer to mitigate harm to employees. 
	Now, assume transaction is in Stock. 
	Now you have to do an independent an alysis of the acquirer. How do you 
compare corporation?
	You need to quantify synergies of cost savings (additional revenue and market positions) 
	Look at the future of that stock. 
	Look at the liquidity, size of company, ha ve an opinion on how markets will react 
 will stocks drop? 
	Go back to company Ts Board in a reasonable time frame: Can you put 
stockholders in better position?
	You need a smoking gun: They will take  usually the higher price regardless of 
stock/cash.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>You have to tell shareholders  everythingother bids, etc.  
	If there is a document that says there was a lower bid, there will be a lawsuit. 
They dont care if they win  they just want to encourage you to settle. 
	How does the Board of Directors get a gua rantee that company D can deliver? 
o	Ask a bank to get you a letter of credit. 
o	Have banker do an analysis to s ee how much company D can raise. 
o	Commitment letters (opinions from various bankers) 
o	Have a default plan 
o	Charge a fee if financing falls through. 
	Beware of antitrust. 
	You wouldnt take higher bid if there is execution risk. 
1.) Act in good faith 
2.) Best interest of shareholders. 
3.) Reasonable, prudent care 
Business judgment rule: made up by courts, wh ere courts will give Directors the final 
decisions if the Board is prudent. The stockhol ders have the burden to show that the 
Board has not self interest. 
	There are levels of judicial review. 
	Revlon: maximize shareholder value. You need to get the best price possible. 
(Does not apply to stock transactions.) 
	No Revlon duty for stock-to-stock transact ions. In theory, you could take a lower 
bid (if long term interest of shareholder is considered). 
	Fairness: excise Direct or who has interests. 
	There is significant time betw een filing and shareholders 
	If it is a stock deal, what should you do? 
o	Have a fixed exchange ratio transa ction (it takes the upside and the 
downside) 
o	Fixed number of shares is bad when  there is downward price pressure. 
	Fiduciary out: walk away  from transaction.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Basic Terms of a Purchase Agreement (PDF)
Guest: Terry Mahoney, Partner, Leboeuf Lamb Greene&#160;&amp; McRae</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec9/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 9: 3/3/04 
Guest: Terry Mahoney, Partner, Leboeuf Lamb Greene &amp; McRae 
Page 23: work our way through purchase agreement. 
Stock Purchase Agreement prep ared by Kirkland and Ellis. 
1.) Buyers counsel prepares agreement (Seller responds) 
2.) Negotiation. Ask  
- Why did buyer pick specific language?
-How does the seller respond?
 In agreement, Article 2: has the price. How do we figure out price 
-value of assets 
-growth potential (needs to  generate earnings) 
-multiple of cash flows (earnings) 
	The buyer wants to put as many conditions as it can. 
	Seller wants no conditions. 
	If you breach a covenant you get sued. 
	Reps (representation) ties into  the conditions to close. 
	Page 37: Were in c onditions to closing. 
	Look at 3:1.A 
	Reps are true on the day you sign and close (w/o taking into account disclosure on 
pg. 56) 
	Page 56: Look at Representation: The last  Rep made by the seller says that the 
above will be true on the closing date, unless I tell you otherwise in writing. 
	The buyer is saying I came up with a pric e based on the information you gave me 
 this is true  if not its a different game. 
	Its given the buyer a chan ce to regenerate. If we come to closing, and the 
company blows up, then Rep isnt true.  
	These conditions have no material adverse effect. 
	These covenants try to tackle this. 
	Buyer knows that things change. 
	Avoid cock-tail with the bankers. 
	It is difficult for both the buyer and seller. It is based on the fate of your opponents (do they have a good history?) 
	Obligation of good faith: it covers cocktail  with bankers. Did the people operate 
in and above the Boards manners?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Covenants: 
* Seller is alert here! 
	Buyer wants seller to take good care of th e assets. Why would seller cross this 
out? 
	Once the seller signs, thats it. 
	Seller must continue to conduct its business in the ordinary course. 
	Any time you have 2 provisions dealing with the same stuff it is bad because 
court will want to give it more power. Since they will say what was covered in 
E was covered in A. 
	Why is material so important? 
o	Without material, if Xerox says no  buyer could say I dont want to close 
because you didnt get every single 3rd parties consent. 
	Page 46, Figure 5.7 
	Be in accordance with GAAP. 
	Tell us everything you know. Dont hold back secrets. 
	Buyer vies this as a risk-allocation provi sion. IF something crops up it is your 
(seller) problem. 
	For example: Should B assume warranty obligations  B says NO, but warranty 
expense is an ongoing expense, and you should have a reserve of it.  
How do you determine the proper multiple? 
	Market multiple ( you get all of the junk with it) 
	Page 56, Section 5-23. 
	Everything you tell us  should be true. 
	If this was a honesty clause, and not a risk clause, then you cant burn anything. 
 IF business went south  WHY?
-B/c of market? 
-Other competition?
-Pricing pressures?
-Is it the sellers job to teach buyer about the market?
	Everyone should do their homework. 
	Page 62: Indemnification Clause: If you breech a covenant or Rep, I, the Buyer 
get to sue the Seller. Without  this clause you can still sue people. It allows you to 
recover your attorneys fees. 
	There is a risk business people take to buy an asset, because someone else will 
buy it. Thats why if you st ate 80M, youll take 40M.  
	If people think that somethi ng went wrong, they will sue.  
	How do you defend 80M? Perhaps historical basis or relative? 
	Legal fees: 1-2% of purchase price  driven by practice (powerful!)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Building a Hedge Fund Portfolio (PDF)
Guest: Tim Diggins, Partner, Ropes&#160;&amp; Gray</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec20/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 20: 4/28/04 
Guest: Tim Diggins, Partner, Ropes &amp; Gray 
	Pools: what used to be regulated in  the world of finance is not anymore 
	Pool = an independent entity 
Only Trustees are watching the assets of the firm. 
Investment Company Act of 1940: provided th ing you cant do. I.e. limits on the extent 
on which the pools assets can be used for distribution to the shareholders.  
Private pools (hedge f unds) avoid regulation 
	beneficiary: person who is en titled to economic benefits 
	Record: name shows up on shareholder as an owner.  
	a mutual firm is governed by how they sell their shares 
o	does not apply to hedge funds 
	advisors who run hedge funds will one day be other investigation 
o	how they charge fees 
Compensation; 
	Mutual fund: advisor receives an investment managers fee 40-50 bp. 
	Hedge fund: advisor gets management fee 100 bp-200 bp and carried interest: if 
management shares in the upside.  
Hedge funds: a managed pooled vehicle that is not a mutual fund 
	you can short 
	there are hedge funds that  hedge that dont though 
	you meet broker and buy stock (D elivery vs. payment trade) 
	you get the stock 
	There is a risk that you have a trade secu red, but 3 days later the exchange doesnt 
work. 
	Risk from the Exchange 
	Principal transaction: credit ri sk is from counterparty only 
	I want US treasury broker who acts as a principal and goes to backroom 
	Soft dollars</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>In the old days brokerage dollars were fixed. 
	If you are an investment advisor to a mutual fund 
o	Who gets benefit of soft dollars 
o	Congress investment advisor can use soft dollars for research and 
brokerage services. 
o	Congress says you have to  put 50% collateral.  
	Futures contracts: I will buy from you 500 things 90 days from now at todays 
price 
o	You can leverage up 
o	You need to put an initial margin at 5% 
o	Deal with it every day 
o	Interest is embedded 
o	You can use this for indexes an single securities 
Unregulated notional contracts: 
I rate swaps 
	As long as fixed rate is greater th an floating rate, you make a spread 
	Hedge funds are not limited by who they can trade with 
	Goldman Sachs has prime brokerage arrangements 
Portfolio 1: 
Long equities-US/foreign 
Short 
Leverage bonds: domestic and foreign 
Portfolio 2: 
Long equities (60%) 
Short 
Leverage bond (30%) 
F/X hedging  unregulated 
* Hedge funds are hard to set up  entrepreneurial drive</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Commercial Lending and Securitization (PDF)
Guest: Matthew Furlong, Partner, Bingham McCutchen</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 19: 4/26/04 
Guest Speaker: Matthew Furlong, Partner, Bingham McCutchen 
80% Acct. Receivable 
60% Inventory 
55% Real Estate 
45% Intel Prop 
40% Equipment 
Borrowing base sum: limits the amount a borrower can borrow at a given time.  
Who is a creditor? 
Anyone who is owed a money judgment 
Lender: lends to the borrower Can be voluntary or involuntary 
Law doesnt make a distinction between some one who is injured and who has a claim, 
and someone who borrows. 
Unsecured: unless creditor gets specific cred itors claim they have no claim to assets. 
Secured: given designated property creditors interest in an asset 
 Ex. Mortgage 
 If value of a home goes down they owe you money.  
 Ramification remedies availabl e to two different types. 
 Sec: repossession of a sset: i.e. auto lender 
	How do unsecured creditors get paid?
1.) Once a creditor has a claim they have to go to court to prove it 
2.) Find out what assets the debt or has, and finds its worth 
3.) Another court order. So sheriff can seize assets.  
Secured advantage: 
1.) Priority 
2.) In any bankruptcy or liquidation secured person gets priority over unsecured 
3.) Lots of lenders charge on unsecured term s and get higher interest b/c there is no 
default. I.e. credit card. 
Speaker talked about: 
 Voluntary credit relationships 
 Secured credit relationships</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Asset-backed commercial paper: the durat ion of the instrument. Shortest term 
type of instrument (70-90 days). You match underlying assets you want to match 
it in such a way that you dont ha ve to constantly re-finance. 
	Bankruptcy of seller.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>a bond offering: 
o	typically 5-10 month range 
o	publicly held 
o	favorable covenants 
o	tight reign of borrowers 
o	flexible pricing 
2 basic kinds of bank loans: 
a.) term loan: 1 lump sum of money and paid over time. 
b.) revolver: designed to help compan ies with capital (like a credit card) 
Nature of secured status 
1.) attendant: granting of a security interest 
2.) borrower grants lender a secured interest 
 Attendant recognizes there is a voluntary act to give something to a creditor 
o	Creditors and debtors should be aware 
	2nd perfection: step by which you put the world on notice of your exalted status 
o	let people know you exist 
o	How? 
	Uniform Commercial Code: uniform  across all 50 states. Applies 
to personal type property. Filing of  a 1 page document in Secretary 
of States office. Applies to in tangibles as well as tangibles.  
	Reduces transaction costs 
	Different types of loans: 
	Cash flow loans: made based on premise that they are going to be paid by on 
going cash flow of the busine ss (i.e. student loan).  
	Asset based loans: credit decides to exte nd credit is based on the value of assets 
owned by the business (or generated). 
	Borrowing base: a way to capture value 
Assets are assets that ge nerate future cash flow. 
SPE= special purpose entity. 
Warehouse 
	These are limitations where outside directors administer entities.  
	Typically know one knows when a person writ es off a loan that it will get bundled 
with other payments.  
	Frequently invests demand credit enhancement 
	For example: over-collateralization. Va lue of assets in SECvalue from 
securities.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Contracts (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>-Inside council has problem when it comes to compliance boss pushing boss 
- But if they had called outside law firm, this wouldnt have happened.  
	No such thing as a quiet withdrawal. 
 What should the CEO have done to Moser?
-Put him under supervision?
-Demote him?
-Disclose?
o	1st: fix it internally 
o	2nd: Hit the bad people 
o	3rd: Tidy things up 
o	4th: reevaluate situation 
o	5th: Then go to regulators . And explain to them what youve done and 
ensure that it wont ever happen again. 
Outside council gives you leverage. 
Staying Out of Trouble: 
1.) Company you keep is key:  
	Stay away form ethically-challenged people. 
	People who enforce white collar crime ha ve harder times. Its opaque. So you end 
up processing minor and major stuff.  
	Consultants (people come to you when they are in trouble) 
	Tell clients in the beginning: 
o	Make an assessment early on (set clear expectations) 
o	No cover-ups 
o	100% compliant 
2.) Dont do anything stupid. (ex. Arth ur Anderson shredding documents) 
	give us full disclosure 
	if youve lied to us, we will send you to jail policy holds 
	99/100 times tell the truth (if you lie, you will get caught) 
	Evaluate your instincts 
Contracts: (law of the Deal) 
* Freedom of contract: you ag ree then law enforces it. 
Ex. Marriage: I do (law then  tells you what you have to do) 
Ex. Doctor-patient 
HOW DO YOU GET A CONTRACT? 
1.) Agreement Meeting of the minds 
2.) Consideration: You scratch my back, and Ill scratch yours , reciprocity, 
courts dont like bosses who overreach. 
3.) Legal capacity. 2 parties should have the capacity to enter the contract.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 4: 2/17/04 
Hard edge 
-Overview 
-Punishing companies 
-Punishing managers 
-Managing a crisisBhopal, Solomon 
-Staying out of Trouble 
Contracts 
-Overview 
-Formation 
-Interpretation 
-Breach/disputes/remedies 
1.) Prevent/ameliorate all harm 
	Help those people in Bhopal  of course, you are res ponsible; you will look bad 
if you dont. 
	Other plants? You dont want another accident next week. 
	Its a common concern/dilemma. 
 Assume you are a managerWhat do we do?
-Dont do anything. 
-Or help out? 
2.) Public Announcement? 
	But what will we say early on? 
	America has a system of discovery i.e.  corporation have no privacy and things 
will come out in deposition in open court. 
3.) Reach out to a variety of companies. 
4.) Counsel 
5.) Gather facts, Internal Investigation 
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 
* Whos in charge though? 
-Maybe outside lawyers?
-Or inside lawyers? 
-You tell person whos directly related? 
o	No, b/c withstand internal scrutiny 
o	Argue for credibility of the company</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>4.) Formalities (i.e. written, handshakeevi dence that there was a contract. ) 
5.) Intent to be bound (3 hours walk w/ friend example)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>o	Has to be someone who is completely  divorced, operationally from all the 
decisions that were made. 
o	Give me him a budget. Select a team . Hopefully, you had a crisis plan 
already. 
Solomon Brothers (SB): 
	Supervisor: Meriwether 
	Road Trader: Moser 
	Special trade in firm 
	Arbitrage group 
	Trying to buy government securities of more than 35% 
	He submits false bids in the clients names 
	Moser  Meriwether  Boss   CEO 
	Meriwether  Boss  CEO is to the top inside co uncil. They try to figure out 
what to do. Should they report to th e authority? They dont do anything. 
1.) How does it break open? 
* Concerns about auctions for Treasury bonds. 
	Concerns on part of regulators. 
	They try to call in the top bankers 
	CEO does internal investigation (hire an outside law firm) to appeal regulators 
	Lawyers ask compliance problems 
	CEO calls a press conference. We are horrified to discover that there is 
misconduct. We will get rid of clerks that covered it up. 
	BUT: Why didnt they say anything earlier? He spoke after 2 months. 
	He was sitting on top of unequivocal, clear knowledge. 
	This gets referred to U.S. Attorn ey who is inclined to indict. 
	But problem is: if a firm has been co nvicted in a crime regulation government 
security, they cannot par ticipate. I.e. GONE, (wont  survive indictment). 
 Board of Directors of SB 
-Get rid of everyone who was involved 
-Make public statement that you are going to revamp 
-Grovel (turn themselves inside out) 
-Programs of compliance 
-Waive turning-client privately 
-Squeaky-clean team
	Internal investigation: Moser did it again a couple of times. Perhaps he had tacit 
permission. 
	Investigation turns out clean except for Moser. 
	Adequate supervision. 
	Nobody goes to jail. They are ju st forced to retire.  
	How could this have been better?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Key Players, Stages and Deal Structures (PDF)
Guest: Terry Mahoney, Partner, LeBoeuf, Lamb, Greene&#160;&amp; McRae</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 7: 2/25/04 
Merger: you can merge companies by finding a paper with the Sec of  State of Delaware. 
	New corporations possess all the rights, privileges, properties. 
	Lease goes over to new company 
	There is an ongoing debate whether patent  law applies to pa tent licenses (and 
there are two views federally as well) 
3rd party 
consent Liabilities SH approval Dissenters 
Rights 
Asset Yes No, BUT Majority No (in 
Delaware), but 
it depends 
which state 
Buys Stock of You sometimes YES 100%. (you NO 
Company need consent. It need this much 
depends on to own all the 
clauses company) 
Merger ??? YES Majority YES 
Forward ??? YES, but you Majority YES 
Merger wont injure 
parent 
Backward Sometimes? YES, BUT Majority YES 
merger 
	Just because you have to pay the tax man, doesnt mean you cant collect from the 
seller. 
	Theres a transfer of all assets 
	Employees work for a new company 
	Economically efficient: to pass cost of insurance 
	Policy is that consumer shouldnt bear blame 
 Dont pick upsellers taxes. 
 
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 
Privately negotiated businesses 
Process begins:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>1.) handshake, agreement on price. Phone to call to lawyer: Weve agreed to busy 
business B for $x. 
2.) Letter of Intent, LOI, (no need to have it). But, its a good thing psychologically. 
There are some provisions, but for the most part is just milk toast. 
(Refer to handout) 
Part 1: not-binding  not much substance 
Part 2: Paragraph B: Se ller isnt going to shop, as buyers does its homework. 
	People are very positive during the time of LOI 
	Nothing needs to be spelled out in detail , but there should be important  points 
that may be helpful to you later on.  
3.) Due Diligence: the selling company gathers up all the papers that relates to its 
company.  
	Acquisition page checklist page 6:  includes contracts, surveys. 
	Dont hide the fact to em ployees that you are thinking of  selling. If many sales, 
the CEO should sell each smoothly, do its homework, and avoid the disruption. 
	Fixed asset list (Professor said to ignore this part) 
	Buyer may insist on having their sellers  financial records audited. But this 
auditing isnt a huge concern. They will look at tax reforms, because you get a conservative income.  
	Organization schedules: the m eat of the story is told in the disclosures schedule: 
listing of contracts, law suits, employee-benefit plans 
	Sellers are confused about the schedule thing  
	If an important contract isnt in the schedule doesnt count. 
	Schedule is being prepared wh ile most the agreements are 
	Schedule may get a lot of people making additions  lots of changes can mess up 
things. 
	How long between LOI and signing agreement? 
o	6 weeks (but they are getting longer , but not because they are getting 
complicated) 
o	Mahoney thinks its technologys fau lt. The speed of which people are 
trying to do things is causing careless errors.  
	If one doesnt fall covenants, one get sued. 
	It takes 30-45 days between signi ng and closing, because youre getting 
regulatory approvals (filing papers , mechanical nature things).</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Contracts&#160;(cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Interpretation: 
	Filanto case in Italy 
	Chilwich selling boots to Ranzoexport in NYC 
	Deal falls apart 
	Chilwich gives paper to Filanto (who doesnt sign it) 
	Can Chilwich say to Filanto that we have to settle this in Russia? 
	Filanto says NO 
	Goes to Russia. Most persuasive court looks  at it and says this is a mess. Filanto 
should have taken action. 
	Court evaluates how reasonable is  the clause to go to Russia? 
	The end customer is from Russia 
	What is a reasonable delay? Answer: reasonable time. 
	When you go into a contract dispute, you need clean hands.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>iii.	Therefore, you want Sellers  law firm to say, Based on 
investigations, we represent to you that CEO has capacity to do 
this deal. 
iv.	This law firm will be conservative 
v.	If all steps are clean, you can do the deal.  
Formalities: 
Penzoil. 
What is the purpose of formalities? 1.) Gives specifics/evidence 
1.) Intent to bound/clear line 
Getty Case: Texaco vs. Penzoil. 
	Penzoil claims that Getty made an agreement to sell the company to Penzoil. 
	Announced to public 
	Texaco offers a better offer, and Getty takes it. 
	Penzoil claims that Getty and them had a contract 
	Texaco may be liable for damages 
	Key Question: Was there a binding agreement? 
	If the parties intended to have a contr act before the signing maybe there was a 
deal. 
	How does the court decide if the jury was right? 
	What does the court look at?  Look at page 63, last full paragraph. 
	Court says, Was there partial period th at the party disclaiming the contract 
accepted? 
	Penzoil says start period, I was hustli ng. We wont tell Getty you can have your 
cake and eat it too. 
	You cant manipulate formalities.  
	Court spends time looking at press releas e. Looking for some clear expression of 
each of the parties. 
	Make reasonable inferences. 
Court looks at grammar. 
	A reasonable jury would have  said, We have a deal. 
	Express agreement: we can infer 
	Implicit agreement: from general commercial practice. 
	Contracts have to have legal purpose. 
	Indemnification 
	If you get into legal trouble, as the cor poration, the company will pay the lawyers. 
	But corporation may not be doing well and have little cash. 
	So: Insurance Company will support you. It is important protection. Almost all 
corporations will provide indemnification insurance. 
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 5: 2/18/04 
No readings. 
Agreement 
Consideration 
Intent 
Capacity 
Formalities 
Legal Purpose 
Did she have the power to bind the banks? -Credit line for $500,000 
	You would get credit, b/c shes an agent who has authority, but  she actually had 
APPARENT authority. 
	You can rely on the agents APPARENT authority. 
	But with the Fed Ex example, its different. 
	Called distinguishing the cases: one principle is  unique to one case,  
	Not many. 
	You shouldnt have trusted the Fed Ex empl oyee. He is not in the business to sell 
vans or computers. 
	Therefore, you can rely on agen ts apparent authority, but ONLY 
REASONABLY. 
	If corporation wants to sell substantially all of its assets, it needs to get permission 
from shareholders or Board of Director s. (One doesnt have  the capacity to do 
this) 
BUYER: 
	Risk averse. How does he figure out if seller has capacity to sell the factory? 
	Try to figure out if it will have an im pact? Factors? Sales? Financial Matters? 
How do you find out about these things? 
1.) Get access to information about, due diligence  look at files. 
2.) But, what happens if the company do esnt have that many records, and 
you are scared to go to the se ller (you dont trust him ) 
3.) Ask for certain kinds of statements/premises in the documents. But you 
have the problem that you are still taking risks. 
4.) Objective Third Party opinion. 
5.) I want seller to say to its law firm, Write a letter addressed to the buyer. 
Its called an OPINION LETTER. 
i.	It says, No outstanding taxes, etc 
ii.	CEO has capacity to do the deal</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Law of Duties (cont.) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>delegation in the Mills Case 
 Loyalty to Board (but lawyers say to the Firm) v. loyalty to management. 
 Inside Directors v. outside Directors. 
 Business Judgment Rule (see page 19, second paragraph)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>safety is highly a matter of negotiati ons with govt regulators (fundamentally 
different type of inquiry, but you can  win on a cost-benefit  analysis) 
	Internal policies are like New Years Resolutions fleeting. 
	You have to have reasonable standards. 
Question by student; How do you live with standards? 
Ans: Some companies have problems articulati ng why they have diffe rent standards. In 
general, as prosperity go es up, so do standards.  
Companies tend to decentralize the decision process. 
Limited liability: A shareholder is liable onl y for its investment. Is this a problem?
UCC US can say you are interfering w ith the essence of a corp. (ll) 
Yes: passive shareholder (ll) 
UCC US set the whole thing up and is heavily  involved.  Shareholder will not protect 
them. 
Wickline: 
HMOs Prospective review: you firs t consult your consultants 
Polznsky: attending physician 
Glassing: works for HMO 
Arguing that Polensky didnt ask. 
	HMO loses the holding, but they won. 
	You cant write out specific rules. 
	Fiduciary rules (2 kinds) 
o	Care 
o	Train doctors 
o	Research 
	Fiduciary duties are to patients, but they are not absolute. 
	Conflicts are not necessarily tempting. (they can be structured) 
	Fiduciary in Mills (collegial) 
	Manage the corporation (but , what does this mean?) 
	non-delegable duty</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 2: Monday 2/9/04 
1. Bhopal 
2. Negligence 
3. Mills/Fiduciary duties 
4. cause/harm 
Non-contractual liability 
Torts 
 duty to respect protected interest (reasonable care) 
 failure to meet the duty 
 harm to another 
 caused by the failures 
 Liabilities/damages 
UCC India built a plant 
 What do we want to know if  how UCC U was negligent? 
 Perhaps the design was negligent? 
 Failure to exercise due care = negligence 
a.) working relationship 
b.) information 
2.) How do you find out what as reasonable care? 
Tort law is common sense: 
a.) look at UCC practice elsewhere 
b.) look at industry standards 
c.) safety regulationscompliance 
d.) internal policies 
FDA Case: 
 has many gaps 
 only the clunkers dont get through 
 representative of other agencies 
 govt has limited resources and chooses to focus its attention on specified things 
 govt regulation wont save you 
What if you do comply with safety regulations?</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>International M&amp;A and Joint Ventures (PDF)
Guest: David Walek, Ropes&#160;&amp; Gray</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>The control mechanisms 
o	Voting regulations 
o	How many Board seats 
o	Super-majority provisions 
o	Selection of management 
o	Types of return (preferred, etc.) 
o	You want to prevent deadlocks 
	deal with the owners hip of the venture: 
o	could be going into new country 
o	switching industries 
o	need another facility 
Tagalong: if majority wants to sell ou t, they have to take minority along 
(reciprocal of a drag) 
III. Lawyering 
	Initially historically, foreign lawyers ar e less involved with business deals (they 
tend to be gatekeepers) 
	US lawyers find ways to work around the law.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>IP: these days this is the key reason why people are buying companies 
o	Trade secrets 
o	Software 
o	Brands 
o	Chemical compounds 
	The degree of IP protection is  not the same around the world 
	Therefore, get appropriate information before making a decision 
	China has weak IP for software/media. 
	Some countries have foreign ownership limitations (less so these days) 
o	Currency controls 
	Around the world there are more  foreign corrupt practices. 
Lawyers have: 
	rule of law: a broader depiction of corruption 
	Americas law is 99% reliable 
o Due process is not always the case around the world 
 other countries are more apt to  put company-people in jail 
	In America you might just get a fine/sanction 
	Terminating distributors is more pr oblematic overseas then in the US 
o	US honors contracts 
	Labor issues: harder to change workforce rules overseas. 
II. Intl JVs (joint ventures) 
	non-international reasons to do JVs: 
o	a partnerships of some kind 
o	strategic alliances/contractual 
o	company who change their goals (e x. Millennium Pharmaceuticals) 
o	Millennium developed a drug, and an other party manufactures it, and 
another party markets it (strategic alliance) 
JV 
	takes the strategic alliance one st ep further to pursue a project 
	a shared investment w/economic risk and return 
	everyone gets a return 
	Whether its worth doing this depends on the size, duration, liability issues, 
management issues.  
	There are dichotomies between local and federal government rules. 
	Favored status from being locally owned. 
o	Easier to get govt contract 
o	Easier to get tax breaks 
	In the US we have majority, minority, or 50/50 
	In terms of control over entity 
	each party has its own concerns</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 12: 3/29/04 
Guest: David Walek, Ropes &amp; Gray 
I.	 Why Intl M&amp;A is different? 
II.	 International JVs (joint ventures) 
III.	 Lawyering 
I. Why Intl M&amp;A is different? 
	For the large part domestic and interna tional deals are not that different.  
	There are same issues, covenants about busin ess, IP issues,  and antitrust issues 
	80% the same 
	20% different: 
o	tax and structuring issues 
o	you need an internationa l tax expert (lawyer) 
 youre dealing with multiple tax jurisdictions assuming a US firm 
is acquiring a firm outside of US 
 when you do intl M&amp;A you do it with several foreign subsidiaries 
 John Kerry is trying to eliminat e companies from going off shore 
 High profit in low tax jurisdiction 
	The Netherlands is a popular structure for companies to adopt since it is easier to 
do business there 
	Multinational acquisitions: there is not a separate body of law that governs intl 
corporate law/tax 
	You are always deali ng with local law. 
	In Delaware its easy to  set up a corporation 
	In Germany, its not enough to have a si gned agreement since it only holds when 
you read it to a local magistrate. 
	Many countries dont have corporate law; but some have more  regulations that 
US 
	Holland has a strict corporate law 
	Delaware has a well established corporate system. 
	In a lot of countries you need  to have a local representa tive there that  acts as a 
local executive. 
Antitrust/competition law 
	As a practical matter, foreign countries arent into antitrust 
	In Europe, there is one head that takes care of all the antitrust rulings for all of the 
countries.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Antitrust (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec21/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 21: 5/3/04 
Antitrust/Fair Competition 
Intro-main concerns 
Merger-Varta Bosch 
Airline 
Monopolization  Microsoft 
Mechanics of M&amp;A Joint Venture 
Exemptions 
 Antitrust law = default 
 If government says you have to do it, then thats that 
 i.e. only one hospital 
 Trend in financial services is that govt has be en pulling back 
 US is an outlier in the antitrust re alm but EU is shifting towards us.  
 Dual system between public and private system 
 Who administers the antitrust laws? 
Three evils: 
1.) Collusion: 2 or more economic player s who are supposed to be competing but 
figure they would do better if they didnt; agreement to fix prices. 
 Bright line 
2.) Monopolization: the enti ty that is so big that is can abuse its power. 
 rule of reason analysis 
o almost never sanctioned by criminal charges 
o a.) market power 
o b.) abuse of monopolization 
 most people are big b ecause of super skills 
3.) M&amp;A 
 Before you engage in M&amp;A you have to get approval in advance. 
 More speculative inquiry 
 Forward-looking 
Varta Bosch 
Markets 
 product defn. 
geographic</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>the party goes in to seek approval will define the market very broadly 
	How do you measure market power? 
	Look at market share: 
	Barriers to entry/ wing player 
o	This is more complicated in the international area 
	Microsoft is a world-wide monopoly 
	Collision-Airlines: 
o	Some big airlines are fl oating big prices to see how other companies will 
react in the future. 
o	Signaling behavior: govt has a hard time proving this 
o	You can follow the market in pric es, just not facilitate it.  
o	Trade associations is a big problem 
o	The very 1st company that comes forward in collusion will get more 
lenient offenses. (extends to companies not individuals)  
	Other collision: somebody has a good lawyer  
	In an antitrust case, if the person doing the suing wins, he gets 3 times damages 
and attorneys fees.  
	The law is designed to keep the bad people away and favors the complaining 
party game of chicken 
	Monopolization-Microsoft 
	Why would you say that in this cas e market power = market shower? 
o	Network effect (every time a consum er uses the product it makes it more 
valuable because other people use it.) 
o	Market share + network effect = market power 
	Example 1: Alcoa steel manufacturer 
	Example 2: Studios have bad movies 
o	Studios have a monopoly; b/c independe nt studios cant sell you a really 
good movie. 
	Example 3: IBM gave colleges computers for really cheap, but competitors said 
IBM was not being nice by selling cheap mainframes because putting them in 
college is encouraging people to use computers.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Bankruptcy and Reorganization I (PDF)
Guest: John Whitlock, Partner, Palmer&#160;&amp; Dodge</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>* Example: special statues withholding taxes: if these taxes arent  paid, the withholder 
has to pay them.  
General unsecured creditor = everyone else 
	the landlord (in some cases, the supermarket guy) 
	creditors rights are set out in  statues in bankruptcy code. 
	Cost of administration done by the people who administer bankruptcy 
	For example, you are company that is fairly have lots of debt you want to transfer 
assets, sell something worth $1M for 100,000 
o	Fraudulent convergence: because it br ings about an unfair advantage 
o	But the company who buys it for cheap er price has to worry about the 
creditors among after him. 
	insolvency: debts greater than assets 
	in fraudulent convergence it means you dont have enough cash to run business.  
	To be in bankruptcy: file a volunt ary petition or i nvoluntary petition. 
	Preference: payment on an account of an an tecedent debt that allows the creditor 
to receive more than they would with bankruptcy 
o	90 day 
o	while insolvent 
o	creditors get more money 
the automatic stay: special pros; creditor s cannot take actions on their collateral to 
foreclose. 
	frozen: no transaction can occur 
o	if someone does make a transaction, they violate the automatic stay. 
o	Automatic stay only gua rantees the creditor. 
	company and a lot of subsidiaries 
	substitute consolidation: treat many subsidiaries/parts as one entity. 
	If holding company goes into bankruptcy, operating entities are treated as assets 
	Chapter 7 Consolidation: lists assets, liabilities, creditors, etc. 
o	Laborious process (couple of weeks) 
	bankruptcy trustees: take on responsibility of liquidating assets, then distributes 
them. 
	trustee meets with creditors and bankruptcy person. 
	Collecting assets is easier for equipment 
o	More difficult for IP 
 Trustee figures this out 
	Chapter 11: reorganize business. Yo u are going to salvage the business 
o	How is the business going to act in its salvaged form? 
o	The debtor continues to run business in Chapter 11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 22: 5/5/04 
Guest: John Whitlock, Partner, Palmer &amp; Dodge 
	The rights creditors are the underlying poi nt for which these negotiations take 
place in reorganization. 
	Basic concepts 
	Liquidation transactions 
	Chapter 11 
	bankruptcy law (some rules ap ply only to bankruptcy code. 
o	Title of US laws 
 Title 11 (organized in chapters) 
 Chapter 11 (general corporate reorganization) 
 Chapter 7 (business being liquidated) 
 Chapter 9 (municipal reorganization) 
	A body of states for creditors rights, sales. 
o	Article 9: secured creditors rights in personal property (everything that is 
not real estate) 
o	Each state has a body of law dealing with mortgages.  
	fraudulent convergence law 
o	state component (uniform transfer act) 
o	some states have landlord laws 
o	all of the above needs to  be taken into account fo r the rights of creditors. 
o	The classes of creditors become significant if there are multiple problems 
between entities and creditors. 
Second Creditor: 
	leans on A/R 
	lean on equipment 
	bank has a lean on inventory, put mortgage on property 
perfection: banks have done things that give them 1st claim to collateral rights that a 
secured party has. 
Second party: when you grab a lean some colla teral can only be perf ected if you take it 
into possession.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>o	Where are you going to file bankruptcy? 
	Has to be in the area where you are incorporated or where your 
headquarters are.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Tax Considerations in Structuring a Deal (PDF)
Guest: Martin Allen, Partner, Kirkpatrick&#160;&amp; Lockhart</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 8: 3/1/04 
Guest: Martin Allen, Partner at Kirkpatrick &amp; Lockhart 
	Tax considerations in transaction are important in knowing why a deal is done 
one way or another. 
	To structure a transaction ask what is  the legal form pass through entity? 
-Partnership, S corp., C corp. s ubsidiary of another corp.  
-it has income 
-Income is passed through to the owner (taxed once to the owner). 
-Profit on sale is taxed to partner not partnership 
	1986: There is double taxation 
	C Corps: If there is an income, it is subj ect to operational tax.  Then, if it goes to 
shareholders, they are taxed as well. 
	According to Badge: there is asset acqui sition, stock acquisition, and merger. But, 
Martin thinks there are only 2 kinds: asset acquisition and stock acquisition. 
When smoke clears, target has disappeared, and buyer has all of the assets. 
	discussed forward triangular mergers 
	taxable transactions 
	What are tax objectives of partners 
	Buyers objective: acquire asse ts of a target company with the most beneficial tax 
attributes as possible. 
	If NBV &lt; fair value, then buyer wants to take it with a stepped-up basis so they 
can claim tax on this basis 
	Tax sheltered cash discussion 
	The buyer in the transaction wants a stepped-up basis 
	C-Corp (basic corp.) Example: GM. trea ted as a separate tax payer. 35% of 
dividends are taxed. 
	Its hard to buy NOLs around election-ti me; politicians want to close tax 
loopholes. 
	Sellers (in class he used Gi bson as an example) goals 
-he wants to pay as l ittle tax as possible 
-wants as much money as he can get</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>-may want to defer tax if he wants to pay for it 
-If Gibson set up a C corp. and Allen wants to buy itwhat happens? 
Allen refers to example 1:  
He states, what if Gibson doesnt  want to sell assets, but stocks? 
-Buyers investment is $13,000. Gibson gets $11,000- 10,000 + tax (.15). 
-Gibson wants $9500 
	Stand alone corporation:  not part of a group 
Allen talked about how to value corp orations? What should you consider? 
	one way to value equity , is after tax-value 
	Suppose someone wants to buy a su bsidiary of United Tech. Co. 
-	Introduces possibility of getting a stepped-up tax basis (to get rapid 
depreciation) when you buy assets. 
	Buyer will allocate a lot for depreciation and a little to goodwill 
	It is difficult for subsidiary to sell asset by asset by asset. 
	It would be easier to buy stock of the subsidiary. (assume depreciation bookvalue 
= 0) 
	Section 338: Election: 
-When a corporate buyer buys a C-Corp, the seller and the buyer can elect 
to treat the transaction as an a sset transaction even though the buyer 
bought the stock. 
-Selling Corp. would have generated a prof it on the sale (as if it sold assets) 
-This election would make sense if subsid iary had  way to absorb the gain 
	Section 338  H-10 Election 
-The deemed asset sale is treated as  it happened the moment before the 
sale. 
-Therefore, UT pays tax, not subsidiary. 
-UT is in the same position had it sold stocks (illustrated in Example 2) 
	Forward triangular asse t transaction: no n eed for Section 338. 
	Reverse Triangular merger: has more limitations than a direct merger. 
Non-Taxable reorganizations: 
	entitled to special tax things 
	Allowed to swap tax, without paying current tax... carry-over basis 
	there is no step-up (swap parent  stock for businesss asset) 
	sellers dont get cash  they get stock for the new stock or promissory notes 
called boot</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>ABC (companies)  
-	A: assets for stock subject to liabilities 
-	B: stock for stock sway i.e. tender offer 
-	C: merger forward or direct or triangular 
1.) Limitation to boot in C corp. 
	if you swap targets assets for stoc k + cash then this treated as boot 
	boot makes it hard to qualify a transaction 
2.) substantially all requirements there w ill be buyers that may not want to buy al 
of the target 
	By not taking B, you lost qualificatio n but buyer buys A and B, not C of the 
target. 
	Direct mergers are the most permissive. 
	Target mergers entice buyers. 
	50% needs to be stock and 50% needs to be cash 
	Gain is realized at the extent  of the boot that is received. 
B-reorganization: 
* Share stock of B for T 
* Only voting stock can be used (this is  a tax problem, so no boot can be used) 
* Difficult to do with a widely-held company, because you may not get all of the shares. 
* This is a tender offer (usually foll owed by a squeeze-out merger to get 20%) 
* You need 80% l</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Other Private Equity (PDF)
Guest: John LeClaire and David Watson, Partners, Goodwin Procter</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 17: 4/14/04 
Guests: John LeClaire and David Watson, Partners, Goodwin Procter 
What is private equity? 
Real estate, investing in hi-tech, natural resource funds. 
	A person targets on a specific industry. 
	What is a private equity fund? 
o	Opt to form an entity and get a co mmitment from investors to give you 
money over time so that you can invest in companies.  
	1st step when a client comes to them: Do you look at the market? 
o	Where are your businesspeople? 
o	Put management team together 
o	Do preliminary market track record. 
	2nd step: 
o	structure fund 
o	What kind of structure should you use? 
 What kind of partnership 
 When choosing you dont want to pay taxes at basis level 
 Capital gain vs. ordinary 
 Jurisdiction (Delaware is where you want to form an entity) 
 Put money for 8-10 years 
 NASD just passed a new rule on wh en you can invest in an IPO. 
	3rd rule: after structuring 
o	What are the terms of the offering 
o	Manager gets 80% of profits. 
o	Investment period: 4-5 years (where  you are putting the money to work) 
o	Offsets: as a fund manager you dont wa nt to get a fee from the portfolio 
company.  
o	6-9 months is the time period when you can bring in investors 
o	When you kick off fundraising you bring investors, and negotiate early-on. 
 Sign all the necessary documents to show commitment 
o	Within 10 year time period you need to liquidate assets. 
o	Carried interest: a share of the profits 
 How do you calculate it? 
 Usually calculated on a fund-wide basis. 
o	Look at value of portfolio and see if its above a certain threshold 
o	Clawbacks: if I gave you $ early then you have to give some of it back. 
o	Will the investors get a preferred return? 
 Issues is the priority on the term of payment</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Clients make 1st mistake in raising money 
 A typical private equity fund is about $200,000 in legal fees. 
 April 14, 2000: bubble burst (people were skittish to put $ in)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Forms of Doing Business - An Introduction (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>a.) Constraints must be reasonable 
i.	Time 
ii.	Function 
iii. Geography 
b.) blue pencil states: those narrow down a contract 
c.) Scenario: you are a programmer, and you emailed home your code, so you 
have proprietary. You leave the job then. What do you do? 
i.	Your new boss will fire you b/c you took something tangible, b/c 
he doesnt want to face a lawsuit.  
3.) One issue in Duty of Loyalty is whats yours and whats your bosses? 
a.) When your boss is paying you, you cant have a 2nd job. 
b.) Duty of loyalty gets thrown into  high relief when you are leaving. 
c.) Usually a serial monogamy model 
d.) When someone is quitting this is what should happen:  
i.	You notify your boss 
ii.	Your boss notifies client and says we will provide you coverage 
for the employees that are leaving. We would like you to stay with 
us. We will both act responsibly.  
	Forms of doing business: 
o	Partnership 
 General 
 Limited partnership (b/c of tax aspect, this is preferred) 
	Corporation (S or C) 
o	Corporate has 2 layers of tax</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 13: 3/31/04 
1.	Looking ahead 
2.	Exercise 
3.	The manager and M&amp;A 
4.	Forms of doing business 
What is it like to be a manager? 
	Will there be jobs 
	Conflict of Board of Directors 
	Position of acquiring 
We have a system called At will employment; either party can walk away from a party 
for any reason whatsoever. 
	We downsize in the US, with very few problems and trepidation. 
	If you have a contract, and it was broken, and you were fired, you can sue for 
damages.  
	You need to mitigate (find a new job), if the money is less, you get the difference 
from the court. 
	Employment lawyers will tell you to get a severance package (not limited by 
responsibility to mitigate) 
Compensations timing: 
	the law is pro-employer 
	So you might get that bonus. 
	Violation of an employers obligation of good faith. If you are a salesperson and there is a clear idea of what you need to do to get compensated, you will win in 
court, if your boss calls you afte r a time t before compensation.  
1.	Non-competition agreements 
2.	Trade secrets 
3.	duty of loyalty 
1.) I, the employer agree that after I leave hi s job, I will not join a company that puts 
me in direct contact w ith my former employer. 
a.) Legitimate interest that the employer is trying to protect (training). Law 
says that this is not a legitimate interest.  
i. You are at risk if you teac h someone sensitive skills 
1. legitimate interest: good will 
2. IP 
2.) Protecting trade secrets is very important</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Bankruptcy and Reorganization II (PDF)
Guest: John Whitlock, Partner, Palmer&#160;&amp; Dodge</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec23/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>If they are at least creditors willi ng to serve on the creditors committee 
o	They are authorized to  hire their own council 
 Paid as expense if administration 
 This could be expensive. 
	Key players: Chairman of committee;  committee council; creditors council 
	Negotiation process then proceeds after the committees are formed. 
	Creditors want to pay the sm allest amount for negotiation. 
	A lot of equipment is financed on a lease:  the debtor must m eet the terms of the 
lease. 
	You can have true lease or finance lease of equipment 
	Bankruptcy: you can sell assets in Chapte r 11, before the plan, or you can do it 
after. 
	You can reject stores that are dong badly, and then deal later with the unsecured 
debtors. 
	90 days before bankruptcy is when you can give preferences. 
	The court can appoint a trustee in a Chapter 7. 
	examine: does not have power of trustee 
o	he reports facts, wrong-doings 
	value of companies assets 
o	the creditors can make up with their ow n plan if they want to after the 120 
day period. This is rare. 
 competing plans. 
	Stalking horse bidde r: a bidder who comes in as  the initial bidder who may 
realize that they are not the highest bidder;  the court may help them if he does not 
succeed. 
o	Stalking horse premiums: make it less  economical for others, because now 
they have to pay that premium.  
	When you buy assets in an auct ion, you get them free of leans. 
	A sale for less than fair value is a fraudulent conveyance. 
	Role as a manager when your company is sliding into bankruptcy.  
	If a company is insolent, shareholders have little interest in companynow only 
creditors care. 
o	Duty shifts to the creditors. 
o	Need to minimize loss to creditors.  
	LBO: when management raises money to buy the  company (pay off existing 
shareholders) 
	Before: company has no debt, but lots of equity. 
	After: company with debt and some equity.  
	In order for fraudulent conveyance to succeed, the court needs to be convinced that the reasonable creditors couldn t make it work from the get-go.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 23: 5/10/04 
Guest: John Whitlock, Partner, Palmer &amp; Dodge 
Bankruptcy: 
1.) you decide to go 
2.) or are thrown into bankruptcy by creditors 
	reorganization track or liquidation track 
	basics on how chapter 11 works is crucial 
	lender has mortgage on building, he can push you to bankruptcy 
	how do you reorganize your business? 
o	Building worth greater than loan 
	bankruptcy judges are former lawyers 
o specialized jurisdiction. They us ually handle routine liquidations. 
	cram down a plan 
o	In bankruptcy you must provide an a ffirmative vote from a class creditor 
for the plan. 
 The first 120 days in bankruptcy: when de btor has exclusive right to the plan 
o	This can be extended, never shortened. 
	If one creditor sells loan on a discount, then one party may lose out.  
	Unsecured: usually on 14 cents on the dollar. 
	Unless the manager puts in more money, he wont get a higher equity stock. 
	Usually creditors get lion share of the equity. 
	Most bankruptcy has a lot of debt. They have to convince creditors that in the 
future they will be viable and that they should NOT liquidate. 
	There are facets to this negotiation.  
	A small business with few creditors who see that your success going forward is 
likely if you got 90% of creditors to agr ee then you can weathe r a storm. If not, 
you can do a prepackaged Ch. 11 plan: a good plan in creditors eyes: approved 
by bankruptcy court: takes 2 or 3 months. 
	It must have force of creditors and then  you can give it to the opposing creditors 
(chapter 11 forces t his on the minority). 
	What if the building is worth less than the debt? 
o	Secured creditor is not secured 
o	Dismiss bankruptcy case 
	Now you go into Ch. 11 
	First day orders 
	Who will you deal with? 
o	Representatives of your secured debt.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Publicly-held Corporation I - Insider Trading and Disclosure (PDF)
Guest: Jocelyn Arel, Partner, Testa Hurwitz&#160;&amp; Thibeault</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 14: 4/5/04 
Guest: Jocelyn M. Arel, Partner, Testa Hurwitz &amp; Thibeault 
What is a security? 
	Security Act of 33 
o	Covers any time a company wants to sell securities 
o	Any time you tell the law, you have the ability to sell 
o	Fed govt doesnt tell yo u if its a good investment, it just gives you a 
green light. 
o	State law 
 Pre-empted in certain areas by fed law 
	Sarbanes-Oxley Act of 2002 
o	Strengthens and expands pre July  29, 2002 corporate governance and 
disclosure regime 
o	Most fundamental change since 33 and 34 Acts 
o	Security: investment contract 
 Lots of wiggle room
	Whether you are a public or private company, you need to  see if there is a way 
you can actually sell. 
	Fairness hearings; few states have them. If the jurisdictional state says the deal is 
fair, you dont have to go through the whol e SEC process. It can be done much 
quickly (20-90 days). 
	Safe harbor provides level of certainty 
	Rule 149 is what i nvestors look at.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Venture Capital (PDF)
Guest: Edward Freedman, Corporate Counsel, Flagship Ventures</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 16: 4/12/04 
Guest: Edward Freedman, Corporate Counsel, Flagship Ventures 
	Venture Capital (VC) is a subset of pr ivate equity ( a cla ss of investments) 
	He refers to venture capital as early state venture capital 
	Friends, Family, Fool 
	VC firms invest in C corps 
	How you decide to incorporate depends on your liquidity. 
	VCs prefer preferred st ock to invest in.  
	C: taxed at entry level and when you take it out. 
	You typically pay with stock, usually options. 
	Investors put in about $10 M over a period of time 
	83b 
o	Under tax code when you are taxed ev ery time the repurchase price lapses. 
Every quarter you have to tax liability.  
o	You give 25-30% of stock immediately 
	Structuring the Venture Financing 
o	Charter: sets out ri ghts and preferences 
o	Stock Purchase Agreement: contract between VC and company, so VC 
can buy the stock, Representation and warranties. Check on IP. 
o	Stock holders agreement: voting agreem ent. Right of first refusal and co-
sale. (And if any stockholder wants to  sell shares, she has to see if VC 
wants to buy it, if not, VC can co-sell. 
	Investor Right Agreement 
o	Registration rights ( you have to go public) 
o	S3 form: needed to register SEC 
o	piggy back form 
o	Information Rights: you have the rights to get information 
	Biggest issue is valuation 
	Cumulative dividends: accumulation over time  and at a rate of 8% or 10%. Built-
in return. 
	Anti-dilution: downside protection. 
	Usually more than 1 investor comes to a deal, which is good for the company and 
the investor. 
	Once anti-dilution goes down, it never goes back up.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Relationship with lawyers in house perspective: at the beginning of the deal you 
have to set parameters and budget. Early deal: maybe $20000-$25000 
	Set time constraints 
	Good communication (look at handouts)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Buying a Publicly-held Company I (PDF)
Guests: Stu Cable and Jim Matarese, Partners, Goodwin Procter</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-617-the-law-of-corporate-finance-and-financial-markets-spring-2004/resources/lec10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>If you sell shares, capital ga ins (one level of taxes) 
	Threshold for taxes: 40%. 
	50% if conservative. 
	Then the entire thing is taxed. 
	If 40% is in stock, then its taxable, only to the extent  of cash received. 
	I bankers do the negotiating (economic and social terms) 
	Always maximize value of the shareholders. 
	How do you know if the price is the best? 
	If a 3rd bidder comes in, the I banker shouldnt say anything specific. 
	After 45 days, look at intrinsic value of the company. It doesnt matter if the stock 
value goes up. 
	Is there a legal obligatio n to solicit other bids? 
A. You can take pre-emptive offer. 
B. Check to see if thats good. 
C. Identify the likely bidders. 
D. Conduct a full scale evaluation. 
E. Put out an option, that we are taking Investment Bank A. 
* Market check: looking around for better offers. 
* Ring fence: keep the person out, be cause of conflict of interests.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.617, Spring 2004 
John Akula 
Lecture 10: 3/8/04 
Guests: Stu Cable and Jim Matare se, Partners, Goodwin Procter 
	Public company M&amp;A transactions 
	The process by which a public comp any (pc) transaction gets done. 
	PCs have institutional investors, regular scrutiny, and media attention. (Different 
from private M&amp;A). 
PC: the threat of litigation is very pa lpable. Increased transparency of PC. 
There are many constituents wa iting to be critical of you. 
	Perhaps contact Board of Directors.  
	Counsel should gather more informa tion about a possible acquisition deal.  
	You have two corporations, A and B. 
	Usually there is a mating dance between A and B.  
	B should talk to non-executive Director 
	You dont want to go formal, until you ar e much further along the process. 
	Be low key! 
	Confidentiality agreements (imperfect world) 
	Remember: there is no exclusivity. 
	You are not required to disclose IP, sens itive information, customer lists, etc. 
	Need ways to protect underbidding. 
	Standstill provision: if we  are going to talk to you guys, you wont buy more 
than 1-2% of securities. I will call you  you wont call me. (Usually 12-24 
months). You will not engage in conversations with other bidders. 
	The confidentiality agreem ent does not obligate you. 
	Being Board chairmen requires common se nse. Has the issue advanced enough to 
warrant issue of the entire Board? 
	Board of Directors is concerned about process. The Board of Directors needs to 
show that they fulfilled their duty of care. 
	The best CEOS reach out to their Board. Never hide. 
	Best CEOS have lots of meetings. 
	CEOS cant see their Board as a rubberstamp. 
	A CEO needs to ask lots of questions. 
	Duty of care 
	Duty of law 
	In public company, the dynamic of management and the Board is becoming more 
hands-on.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
