<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-303-the-production-of-space-art-architecture-and-urbanism-in-dialogue-fall-2006/</course_url>
    <course_title>The Production of Space: Art, Architecture and Urbanism in Dialogue</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Architecture </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Visual Arts </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Mary Otis Stevens: Archive</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-303-the-production-of-space-art-architecture-and-urbanism-in-dialogue-fall-2006/resources/vap_mond_stevens/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>November 27, 2006</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>The Mary Otis Stevens Collection 
A New Gift to the MIT Museum 
 
The MIT Museum has recently received the archives of Mary Otis Stevens (SBArch, 56), 
one of the most important female architect s in the Northeast during the 1960s and 1970s. 
 
Initially a protg of Walter Gropius, St evens partnered with her husband Thomas 
McNulty (MArch 49) from 1956 to 1969. One of  their most important projects was the 
1965 Lincoln House, designed for themselves a nd their three small sons, in Lincoln MA. 
 
Perhaps the first house in the US to be built of glass and exposed concrete, it was an instant sensation in the international archit ectural press on the c over of Architectural 
Forum and Deutsche Bauzeitung and widely featured in the large-circulation press, as 
well. But it rocked the little town of Lincol n the same way the Gropius House had in the 
late 1930s. (Neighbors speculated since ther e were no windows f acing the street, the 
occupants must have been nudists.) 
 
For Lincoln House, Stevens and McNulty enlist ed movement and hesitation as their basic 
design concepts. The originality of the house stemmed from the arch itects' rejection of 
preset notions of what a house was, freeing them to transfer th eir own ideas about 
movement and hesitation on the scale of the city to the scale of the house. 
 
To maximize freedom and movement in the hou se, for instance, the architects eliminated 
most interior doors, fostering movement not  only between the different areas of the 
interior, but also betw een the inside and the outside. We wanted to make the house into 
a kind of miniature city, says Stevens. It was very urban. The idea was to bring people 
together, not isolate them in boxes on different floors. You had choices all the time. 
 
Apart from the unique space created by using urban concepts of movement in the setting of a single-family house, the Lincoln House wa s also one of the first with a curvilinear 
geometry, giving the building a sculptural quali ty. (Life called it a scul pture for living in.) 
The Lincoln House also served as a sundial: si ted so that its longitudinal axis was exactly 
N-S, each cloudless day at noon a streak of li ght would shoot down th e stairs and extend 
its length, as the afternoon wore on, along the pathway leading to the children's area. 
 
In the 1960s, Stevens and McNulty founded iPre ss, Inc., which Stevens directed from 
1968-1978, making a major contribution to arch itectural and urban theory with books 
focusing on the social context of architectur e, such as The Ideal Communist City by 
Alexei Gutnov and Towards a Non-Oppre ssive Environment by Alexander Tzonis. 
 
In 1970, she and McNulty published their own cl assic work, World of Variation, looking 
at the city as a social realm, identifyi ng then-current problems and possible design 
solutions. They also collaborated  with Gyorgy Kepes, founder of 
MITs Center for Advanced Studi es, on the design of the City at Night exhib it at the 1968 
Triennale, where they used moving lines of light, each line programmed with a different 
time sequence, to turn a 100-foot corridor  into a place celebrating human movement.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>In 1975, Stevens founded the Design Guild, a co llaborative architectur al practice focused 
on non-profit clients, historic preservation and adaptive re-use; th e Guild disbanded in 
1991. 
 
Last fall, the new museum collection wa s inventoried and catalogued by Katharina 
Maria Tanzberger, a 2006 graduate of the Un iversity of Applied Arts Vienna, who was 
introduced to Stevens work by her professor, Liane Lefaivre. Intrigued by the notion of a 
house with no doors (Tanzberger was raised in just such a place) she was drawn to 
exploring Stevens work further, writing a re search paper and eventually coming to MIT 
to work on the archive. 
 
The collection consists of more than 300 draw ings and diagrams, as well as many texts. 
Of particular interest is the large collection of the sketches over the years, sketches that 
differ from the architectural drawings of the prewar period in that they were not 
renderings of facades or elevations but rath er diagrams charting the flow of movement. 
 
The Stevens collection is a companion to th e McNulty papers held by the MIT Archives. 
McNulty was a member of MIT?s architectur e faculty from 1949 to 1956, when he went 
into private practice with Stevens. For six ye ars he also taught at  the University of 
Petroleum and Minerals in Dhahran, Saudi Arabia, as professor of architecture. 
 
This article is based in part on Living Outs ide the Box: Marty Otis Stevens and Thomas 
McNultys Lincoln House by Professor Liane Lefaivre, Chair of Architectural History 
and Theory at the University of Applied Ar t in Vienna. It appear ed in Harvard Design 
Magazine, Number 24, Spring/Summer 2006.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Regina Maria Moeller: Who is speaking?</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-303-the-production-of-space-art-architecture-and-urbanism-in-dialogue-fall-2006/resources/vap_mond_moeller/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>September 18, 2006</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Regina 
Maria Moeller
Who is speaking?
 The multitude of voices into which Regina 
Maria Moeller splits her artistic work corresponds 
to the various positions she adopts with regard 
to that which she confronts. Similar to the way in 
which overlapping circles form intersections that 
shift previously peripheral material into a (new) 
center, Moeller shifts attention and reshuffles the 
cards, so to speak: secondary characters become 
protagonists, coherencies become contents, 
opposites are robbed of their oppositions. 
Moeller uses the strategies inherent in her 
media, overwriting and adapting them for her 
own purposes, and shows that there are always 
a number of different versions underneath and 
alongside the official interpretation. 
(Matthias Herrmann in: Regina Moeller: 
embodiment  dress plot , exhibition catalogue 
Secession, Vienna 2004)  
Regina Maria Moeller lives in Berlin. She studied 
art education, art history and history of middle 
ages at the Ludwig Maximilians University in 
Munich / Germany. She is the founding editor of 
the magazine regina  and the creator of the label 
embodiment. Regina Moeller is visiting professor 
for the fall term 06 at MITs Visual Arts Program. 
Regina Maria Moeller situates her works in the 
border realm of art, fashion, and comics. She 
takes various formats of contemporary cultural 
communication and reflects on their identity-
forming, economic, and functional connotations.
For example, in her magazine regina , with which 
she has reached a broad readership since the late 
1990s, she adapts the language of womensmagazines. Through subtle shifts she under-
mines the common constructions of female 
identity. Parallel to this, Regina Moeller has 
designed clothing, carpets, furniture, and 
inner decor under her own label embodiment  
since 1993.
Directions
The Visual Arts Program at MIT is located at 265 
Massachusetts Avenue (building N51) adjacent 
to the MIT Museum. Enter through the grey door 
on Front Street and take the elevator to the third 
floor. Exit the elevator to your left and go down 
the ramp.  The Joan Jonas Performance Hall, 
room N51-337, is located through the glass 
doors on the right.
By Public Transportation
Take the Red Line to Central Square. Walk four 
blocks along Massachusetts Avenue towards 
Boston and the Charles River. The Visual Arts 
Program at MIT is located at 265 Massachusetts 
Avenue (Building N51), adjacent to the MIT 
Museum.
Or take the #1 bus to the stop on Massachusetts 
Avenue at Pacific Street, across from the MIT 
Museum.Massachusetts 
Institute of Technology
Visual Arts Program
Joan Jonas 
Performance Hall
265 Massachusetts Avenue
Bldg N51-337
Cambridge, MA 02139
For information call 
617-253-5229
web.mit.edu/vap/Mon 09/18/06
79pm
Visual  Arts Program
Monday Nights @ VAP
This event is presented in 
conjunction with course 4.303 
The Production of Space: 
Dialogues in Art, Architecture 
and Urbanism, taught by 
Professor Ute Meta Bauer.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Gunther Selichar: Who&#8217;s afraid of blue, red, and green?</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-303-the-production-of-space-art-architecture-and-urbanism-in-dialogue-fall-2006/resources/vap_mond_selicha/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>September 11, 2006</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Gnther Selichar 
Whos afraid of Blue, 
Red and Green?
 Speaking about our populistically acting 
mass media environment and its influence on 
aspects of mediation in general the Austrian 
artist will present examples of his documentary
photographic work and his interactive media 
projects within mass media systems.
 The meta-world of public representation 
where basic aspects of democracy or economy 
are transmitted by setting ideological standards 
seems to be irresistibly shifting over to un-
balanced commercial contents or surveillance 
and propaganda, especially in moments of 
crisis, which does challenge the media systems 
(most important for the development of western 
democracies) in a principal way since its 
beginnings.
 Questions of media observation and of the 
public (media) space and its ownership and 
political implications will be linked to artistic 
concepts which try to research the abstract
technological aspects and strategies of a media 
society and which do suggest also that formal 
abstract work is not necessarily a contradiction 
to political aspects in artistic practices.
Current Exhibition
Gnther Selichar: Media Machines 
September 8  November 19, 2006 
Tufts University Art Gallery 
at the Aidekman Arts Center
For more information:
http://ase.tufts.edu/gallery/shows/selichar.htmlDirections
The Visual Arts Program at MIT is located at 265 
Massachusetts Avenue (building N51) adjacent 
to the MIT Museum. Enter through the grey door 
on Front Street and take the elevator to the third 
floor. Exit the elevator to your left and go down 
the ramp.  The Joan Jonas Performance Hall, 
room N51-337, is located through the glass 
doors on the right.
By Public Transportation
Take the Red Line to Central Square. Walk four 
blocks along Massachusetts Avenue towards 
Boston and the Charles River. The Visual Arts 
Program at MIT is located at 265 Massachusetts 
Avenue (Building N51), adjacent to the MIT 
Museum.
Or take the #1 bus to the stop on Massachusetts 
Avenue at Pacific Street, across from the MIT 
Museum.
Special thanks to 
Tufts University Art Gallery and Amy Schlegel.Massachusetts 
Institute of Technology
Visual Arts Program
Joan Jonas 
Performance Hall
265 Massachusetts Avenue
Bldg N51-337
Cambridge, MA 02139
For information call 
617-253-5229
web.mit.edu/vap/Mon 09/11/06
79pm
Visual  Arts Program
Monday Nights @ VAP
This event is presented in 
conjunction with course 4.303 
The Production of Space: 
Dialogues in Art, Architecture 
and Urbanism, taught by 
Professor Ute Meta Bauer.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Krzysztof Wodiczko: Projections and instrumentations</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-303-the-production-of-space-art-architecture-and-urbanism-in-dialogue-fall-2006/resources/vap_mon_wodiczko/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>November 6, 2006</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT Visual Arts Program 
Monday Nights @ V AP 
Krzysztof W odiczko
Projections and 
Instrumentations
Mon  11/06/06 
79pm
Massachusetts 
Institute of T echnology 
Visual Arts Program 
Department of Architecture 
Bldg N51-337, 3rd  oor, 
Joan Jonas 
Performance Hall 
265 Massachusetts A venue 
Cambridge, MA 02139 
For information call 
617-253-5229 
Further information: 
web.mit.edu/vap/ 
Open to the general public. 
This event is presented in con -
junction with course 4.303 
The Production of Space: Dia -
logues in Art, Architecture 
and Urbanism, taught by Profes -
sor Ute Meta Bauer . 
With the aid of especially designed bodily 
equipment, W odiczko s recent projections 
animate, in real time, the facades of public 
edices. Much smaller in their scale, the 
wearable instrumentations share with these 
monumental projections similar psychological 
and political objectives. The aim of both projects 
is to inspire and assist the users-animators in 
developing, perfecting, and projecting their 
voice and gestures in public space. 
Both projections and instrumentations require a 
preparatory video recording (and re-recording) 
process that psychologically and politically 
engages participants and aids in constructing 
their testimonies. Through this process, 
participants gradually recover and develop 
the mastery and artistry of public speaking. 
Step by step they recall, articulate and convey 
overwhelming life experiences. Armed with 
new psycho-cultural prosthetic equipment, and 
empowered with the prestige and monumental 
scale of civic edi ces, they become prominent 
fearless speakers. 
The main objective of the use of media in these 
projections and instrumentations is to create a 
transitional psychological space that encourages 
a gradual passage from participants traumatic 
silence or traumatized speech toward a con dent 
articulate voice. In this way , their psycho-political 
development, to which W odiczko s projects seek 
to contribute, may help participants to become 
not only frank transmitters of truth, but also 
critical and passionate animators of public space. Since 1980, Krzysztof W odiczko, Professor of 
Visual Arts and a Director of the Center for 
Advanced V isual Studies, 2004 recipient of 
MITs Kepes A ward, has throughout his career 
developed a series of tools and devices for urban 
interventions. In addition his work has been 
exhibited in numerous international festivals and 
exhibitions ranging from Biennales in Paris, Sao 
Paulo, Helsinki, Kyoto and V enice, to the Whitney 
Biennial, Documenta and the International Center 
for Photography T riennial. 
Krzysztof W odiczko s next public projections are 
planned to take place in Caracas in 2007 and his 
most recent commission is by the city of Nantes, 
to design a Memorial commemorating the 
Abolition of Slavery in France (opening in 2007). 
Directions 
The V isual Arts Program at MIT is located above 
the MIT Museum. Enter through the grey door 
on Front Street and take the elevator to the third 
oor. Exit to your left and go down the ramp.  
The Joan Jonas Performance Hall is located on 
the right. 
By Public Transportation 
Take the Red Line to Central Square. W alk four 
blocks along Massachusetts A venue towards 
Boston and the Charles River , or take the #1 bus 
to the stop on Massachusetts A venue at Paci c 
Street, across from the MIT Museum.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Chris Csikszentmihalyi: Politechnics</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-303-the-production-of-space-art-architecture-and-urbanism-in-dialogue-fall-2006/resources/vap_mond_csiksze/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>November 20, 2006</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Chris 
Csikszentmihalyi
Politechnics
Massachusetts Politechnics: Political Technologies from Directions
Institute of Technology the Computing Culture Group. The Visual Arts Program at MIT is located above 
Visual Arts Program All technology is politics, but most technologies the MIT Museum. Enter through the grey door 
Department of Architecture (and technologists!) wont admit it. For   ve on Front Street and take the elevator to the third 
years the Computing Culture Group at the MIT   oor. Exit to your left and go down the ramp.  
Bldg N51-337, 3rd   oor, Media Lab has been developing technologies for The Joan Jonas Performance Hall is located on 
Joan Jonas personal and societal politics. Mixing research the right.
Performance Hall from the humanities and social sciences with 
265 Massachusetts Avenuetechniques from engineering, we develop By Public Transportation
Cambridge, MA 02139systems and products for unique applications, Take the Red Line to Central Square. Walk four 
For information call such as how to spy on the govern-ment, how blocks along Massachusetts Avenue towards 
to invert military technologies, or how to Boston and the Charles River, or take the #1 bus 617-253-5229
nuance the gender of kitchen appliances. These to the stop on Massachusetts Avenue at Paci  c 
systems demonstrate the inherent ideologies in Street, across from the MIT Museum.Further information:
existing technologies, but also point to alternate web.mit.edu/vap/directions. The talk will be a review of past 
projects, and a description of future research Open to the general public.topics.
Chris Csikszentmihlyi (MFA UC San Diego, BFA 
Art Institute of Chicago) is the Muriel Cooper Associate Professor of Media Arts and Sciences and directs the Computing Culture Group at the MIT Media Lab. He has worked in the intersection of new technologies, media, and the arts for 15 years. Lecturing, showing new media work, and presenting installations in four continents and one subcontinent, he is interested in cultural narratives, and his work typically aims to create a new technology to embody some kind of particular social agenda.Mon 11/20/06
8:30-10pm
MIT Visual Arts Program
Monday Nights @ VAP
This event is presented in 
conjunction with course 4.303 The Production of Space: Dialogues in Art, Architecture and Urbanism, taught by Professor Ute Meta Bauer.A Double Lecture
with Powers/Sequeira  Pugwash, 7-8:30pm.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Gustavo Artigas: Game, risk, disaster</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/4-303-the-production-of-space-art-architecture-and-urbanism-in-dialogue-fall-2006/resources/vap_mond_artigas/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>November 13, 2006</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>MIT Visual Arts Program 
Monday Nights @ V AP 
Gustavo Artigas
Game, Risk, 
Disaster 
Mon  11/13/06 
5:307pm 
Massachusetts 
Institute of T echnology 
Visual Arts Program 
Department of Architecture 
Bldg N51-337, 3rd  oor, 
Joan Jonas 
Performance Hall 
265 Massachusetts A venue 
Cambridge, MA 02139 
For information call 
617-253-5229 
Further information: 
web.mit.edu/vap/ 
Open to the general public. 
This event is presented in con -
junction with course 4.303 
The Production of Space: Dia -
logues in Art, Architecture 
and Urbanism, taught by Profes -
sor Ute Meta Bauer . Are we here to play or to be serious? And 
in all seriousness what is of playing or games 
for that matter? ...For the past four years, 
Gustavo Artigas who is based in Mexico City , 
but coordinates the majority of his projects 
in other international cities, has developed a 
stunning, complex language surrounding the 
social tensions of group organization and the 
consequences and risks involved in game and 
disaster situations. More speci cally , Artigas 
work engages a universe of limits. As for the 
game, the limit between what is and what is 
not [a game] is more dif cult to specify than it 
seems at  rst glance. ...The disaster on the other 
hand  in Artigas experience  is a limit con ned 
by fear and/or inevitability .  Acting as Master 
of Ceremonies, he has developed a three-ring 
circus scheme juxtaposing games, performative 
gestures, and political critiques into episodical 
chapters.  Jennifer T eets 
Gustavo Artigas was born in 1970. His works 
have been presented at the Faites vos jeux! 
Art and Game since Dada at the Kunstmuseum 
Liechtenstein, V aduz; at the Akademie der 
Knste, Berlin, Germany , at international 
04 at the Liverpool Biennial, England; at 
OUTLOOK 2003 and at Arena - Society for the 
Advancement of Contemporary Art in Athens, 
Greece. In 2001 Artigas has participated in the 
Aperto Section of the 49th V enice Biennial in 
Italy. Directions 
The V isual Arts Program at MIT is located above 
the MIT Museum. Enter through the grey door 
on Front Street and take the elevator to the third 
oor. Exit to your left and go down the ramp.  
The Joan Jonas Performance Hall is located on 
the right. 
By Public Transportation 
Take the Red Line to Central Square. W alk four 
blocks along Massachusetts A venue towards 
Boston and the Charles River , or take the #1 bus 
to the stop on Massachusetts A venue at Paci c 
Street, across from the MIT Museum. 
Thanks 
This lecture is a collaboration with the 
Cultural Agents Initiative and the Latino and 
Latin American Art Forum at Harvard, and is 
supported by the David Rockefeller Center for 
Latin American Studies (DRCLAS) at Harvard 
University .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
