<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/</course_url>
    <course_title>Theory of Solids I</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Physics </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Band Structure (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 6: Band Structure
Continue to explore the consequences of the Bloch theorem. The concept of Nth Brillouin
zone is introduced. The Fermi surface is dened. The breakup of the free electron Fermi
surface is illustrated by a twodimensional divalent metal. The use of group theory to
simplify band calculation is briey discussed. Two theorems concerning the symmetry of
the band structure of nonsymorphic lattices are stated without proof and illustrated by the
hcp example.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Electron-electron Interaction: Hartree-Fock Approximation (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 
Lecture 15: Electronelectron interaction: HartreeFock approximation 
The Slater determinant is introduced as a trial wavefunction and the HartreeFock equa
tion is derived. Koopmans Theorem is stated and explained. The concept of the exchange 
hole is discussed, leading to the estimate of the exchange energy as e2kF . 
Reading : Marder 9.2.1, 9.2.2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Orthogonalized Plane Wave (OPW) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 7: OPW 
The need to truncate the size of the big matrix is discussed. The problem is traced to the
need to orthogonalize with the core state and Herrings solution using orthogonalized plane
wave (OW) is explained. The OPW scheme is recast as a pseudopotential and the nearly
free electron model is justied.
Reading : Mardar 10.2.1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Semiconductors: Donors, Acceptors and Excitons (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 11: Semiconductors: donors, acceptors and excitons
The band structures of Si and Ge are discussed. The valence band is tted by LCAO
while the conduction band is nearly freeelectronlike. The small indirect band gap and the
cigar shaped electron pockets are discussed. The small band gap leads to a large dielectric
constant . Replacing Si by P leads to extra positive charge and extra electron, which form
a hydrogenlike bound state called the donor level. The small mass m and large  lead to
small binding energy d = (m/m)/2 Rydberg and large eective radius r0 = (m/m)a 0 
of the donor level. Similarly, doping by Al forms acceptor level. The large overlaps betweendonors allows them to form bands and an insulatortometal transition may occur. The small
energy scale allows us to control the electrical property of doped semiconductors with small
potentials. The optical absorption edge in semiconductors is dominated by the electronhole
bound state called the exciton.
Reading : Mardar 19.3, 21.4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Point Group for Bravais Lattice (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 4: Point Group for Bravais Lattice 
The concept of point group is introduced, rst for the Bravais lattice. The classication
of the 14 Bravais lattice is described. The notion of nonsymorphic structure for a general
lattice is introduced, illustrated by the screw axis in hcp structures.
Reading : Marder 2.4, 2.5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Bogoliubov Quasiparticles (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec23/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>23</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 23: The Bogoliubov quasiparticles 
The variation problem with the BCS trial wavefunction was solved as a homework prob
lem. Instead we develop a more general solution using the Bogoliubov quasiparticle opera
tors. We show that this can be considered an extension of Hartree Fock theory where the
four fermion terms are replaced by the best fermion bilinear. Once the odiagonal order
parameter is identied, it is natural to consider the third way of decoupling the four fermion
terms using the pairing order parameter
 =V0 &lt; (r)(r)&gt; .  
The equation of motion leads to a 2  2 matrix which is diagonalized to yield the excitation
spectrum
Ek =2 +|2 .k |
The selfconsistent equation is derived and solved for Tc and .
Reading : Marder 27.3.5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Phonons (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 19: Phonons
We discuss the longitudinal sound wave of jellium. We view it as a charged plasma where
the oscillation of the positively charged jellium is screened by the electrons. The plasma
frequency 2 = 4n 0e2/Mwhere M, which is the nuclear mass, is screened by replacing e2 
pl 
bye2/(q,  = 0) and we use the Thomas Fermi screening
1 q2 
=(q)q2 +2 , (1)
where 2 = 4e2(2N(0)), and N(0) is the single spin electronic density of states at the Fermi
level. This gives
2(q) = 2 
pl/(q)
2 2 =c q (2)
where
4n oe2 
2 c=M2 
1m2 = vF . (3)3M
mThen the sound velocity is reduced from the Fermi velocity by a factor3M . This is a
useful small parameter when discussing phonons and electrons.
Next we introduce a local displacement vector d(r, t ) for the jellium. A modulation of
d(r, t ) causes density modulation given by
n(r, t) =n0d(r, t ). (4)  
Then we can write the Lagrangian as</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2
  21 d B= r Mn d  n0 (n)2 
2L 2d3 
dt
  2d=1d3 r Mn d  B(d)2 (5)2 dt 
where Bis the bulk modulus. This gives the usual classical wave equation with sound
velocity c2 =B/Mn 0.
We introduce the canonical momentum density
d(r, t )(r, t) =Mn 0 (6)t
and the Hamiltonian
1 1   
H = d3 r   +B(d)2 . (7)2 Mn 0   
The problem is quantized by demanding the canonical commutation relation between d and
. This is satised by the Fourier expansion
i 1 
bkeikrikt  b r+i ktd(r, t ) = kkeik. (8) Mn 0 
V
2kk 
Then
1 1H = k bbk + (9)2k2k 
and
bk, b=k,k . (10)k 
In real solids there are transverse acoustic modes in addition to the longitudinal mode
discussed above. If there are two or more atoms per unit cell, there are optical modes as
well. All these can be quantized by extending the above procedure.
Reading : Marder 13.2, 13.3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Electron-phonon Coupling and Electron Lifetime (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec20/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2
where q
=
2ksinF 2is the phonon vector which connects two points on the Fermi surface
separated by the angle .
For the jellium model all the constants are known and Eq. (4) is easily evaluated to give

=
1 
2.
In real metals ranges from 0.2 to 0.3 for simple metals to more than unity for
strong coupled metals such as Pb.
Reading : Marder 13.3.1, 13.3.2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 20: Electronphonon coupling and electron lifetime 
The formalism of second quantization is outlined. The phonon contribution to the specic
heat is discussed. A simple argument shows that at low temperatures the specic heat goes
asT3 in the Debye model.
The electronphonon coupling in the jellium model is discussed. It is simply the screened
Coulomb interaction v(r) between the charge modulation of the jellium n(r) with the charge
modulation of the electrons (r). The former is given by combining Eq. (4) and Eq. (8) of
the last lecture while the Fourier transform of the latter is q = c
k,kq,ck. Putting
everything together, we nd
 
Hepl = drdr n(r)v(r  r)(r)
 
= nqvqq 
q 
    
= gqbq+b
qc
k+q,ck, (1)
qk,
where
4e2 n0 qgq=2 2Mq(2)
Note the linear qterm in the numerator of Eq. (2) comes from the gradient term in the
relation between jellium density and displacement. This form of electronphonon coupling is
called the deformation potential and describes the coupling to longitudinal acoustic phonons.
The lifetime of an electron due to emission or absorption of phonons is written down
1using the Fermi golden rule. We show that if kT D, is linear in T, i.e.,
1= 2kT (3)
where the important dimensionless electronphonon coupling parameter is given by
 1 dcosgq2 
= 2N (0) (4)
1 2q</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Experimental Tests of Band Structure and&#160;A Survey of the Periodic Table (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 10: Experimental Tests of Band Structure and a Survey of the Periodic 
Table 
Various tests of band calculations are described, starting from specic heat coecient
and spin susceptibility as measurements of the density of states at the Fermi level. Optical
absorption and van Hove singularities are discussed. Photoemission and angle resolved
photoemission (ARPES) are discussed in some detail. A brief survey of the band structures
of various parts of the periodic table is given, starting from simple and noble metals to
divalent and trivalent metals. Examples of transition metal bandstructures are shown, with
emphasis on the role of the d bands. The rare earth is discussed with emphasis on the strong
correlation nature of the 4f states.
Reading : Mardar 23.6.2, 10.4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>de Haas-van Alphen Effect and Quantum Hall Effect (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 13: Cyclotron resonance and deHaasvan Alphen eect and quantum Hall
eect
The deHaasvanAlphen eect is explained using the quantized orbits and its usefulness in
mapping Fermi surfaces is explained. The phenomenon of magnetic breakdown is discussed.
The phenomenon of integer quantum Hall eect in SiMOSFET is described.
Reading : Mardar 16.5.2, 16.5.3, 19.5.1, 25.5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Density Functional Theory (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec17/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 
Lecture 17: Density functional theory
The KohnSham formulation of the density functional theory is explained. We contrast 
the ThomasFermi approximation and the KohnSham treatment of the kinetic energy. The 
local density functional theory is explained as a practical method to treat exchange and cor
relation in a selfconsistent band calculation. The limitations of the local density functional 
approximation is discussed, starting with the Heitler London approximation for hydrogen 
molecules. The notion of the Mott insulator is introduced. 
Reading : Marder 9.3.1, 9.3.2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Hubbard Model, Screening and Plasmons (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 18: Hubbard model, screening and plasmons
The Hubbard model is introduced. We argue that in the limit of strong repulsion U t,
the system with one electron per site is a Mott insulator with antiferromagnetic exchange
J= 4t2/U. The details will be derived in a homework problem of a 2site Hubbard model.
We next introduce the notion of screening. We derive the Thomas Fermi screening length
and the Yukawa form of the screened Coulomb interaction which is applicable in the static
limit = 0. On the other hand for = 0, k= 0, the dielectric function takes the form
2 
() = 1 pl 
2 
where 2 = 4ne2/mis the square of the plasma frequency. We emphasize that the =pl 
0,k 0 and k= 0,  0 limits of (k,  ) are not the same. The plasma resonance shows  
up as a plasma edge in the reectivity.
Reading : Marder 20.2.2, 23.1.1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Exchange Energy for Jellium (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Pseudopotential and Augmented-Plane-Wave (APW) (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec8/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 8: Pseudopotential and APW
Further discussion of the pseudopotential. The pseudopotential is nonlocal and also not
unique. The idea of model potential is introduced. The relation to logarithmic derivative
and phase shifts in the scattering from a spherical potential is discussed. The idea of an  
dependent optimized pseudopotential is explained and it is shown how these pseudopoten
G, tials are cast in the form of the big matrix, with o diagonal elements which depend on G 
separately rather than G    G. This is the signature of a nonlocal potential. The concept
of muntin potential is explained and APW is briey discussed.
Reading : Mardar 10.2.4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Cooper Instability and the BCS Wavefunction (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 22: The Cooper instability and the BCS wavefunction 
The twobody problem with attractive interaction in the angular momentum channel 
is reviewed. Cooper, in 1956, studied the modication of this problem in the presence of a
lled Fermi sea. The only change in the formulation is to restrict the wavefunction sum to
the linear superposition of electron pairs with k and k, where k is now restricted to be
above the Fermi sea. This leads to the conclusion that a bound state is always formed, nomatter how weak the attraction. The formal similarity of the Cooper problem to the bound
state problem of two electrons in two dimensions is pointed out. The Cooper problem shows
that the Fermi sea is unstable in the presence of attraction. The full manybody problem
is solved by the BCS trial wavefunction. We motivate this wavefunction by considering the
Bose condensation of Cooper pairs. In second quantized notation this simply means that
the states k,and
k, are either both occupied or both empty.  
We emphasize that the BCS wavefunction is characterized by a phase which is the
phase of the complex variable vk
 &gt; = uk+vk|ei
k
 vac&gt; . (1) | ||
 cc
k 
k 
It is in fact possible to write
dN &gt; = e  &gt; (2) |2iN|
as a wavefunction with xed particle number. The energy is degenerate for any , and so is
N &gt;. This is an example of symmetry breaking, in direct analogy with an xyferromagnet. |
Just as in the ferromagnet, the broken symmetry state | &gt;is more physically relevant than
the superposition which does not break symmetry.
Reading : Marder 27.3.3, 27.3.4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Free Electron Model (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 1: Free Electron Model 
Sommerfelds free fermion model for metals. Specic heat is linear in T and spin suscep
tibility is T independent. Conductivity is described by the Drude model. The dimensionless
number rs is introduced as the ratio between Coulomb energy and kinetic energy.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Crystalline Lattice (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 2: Crystalline Lattice
The Bravais lattice is dened and several examples given. The basis vector is introduced
for a general lattice. The theory of diraction is derived, showing that Bragg refraction
occurs when the momentum transfer equals a reciprocal vector. The reciprocal lattice is
dened. The Ewald construction for Xray diraction is explained. Emphasis is on the fact
that the position of the diraction spots depends only on the Bravais lattice. The basis only
aects their intensities.
Reading : Marder 1.2, 2.2, 3.2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Tight Binding, van Hove Singularity (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec9/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 9: Tight Binding and van Hove Singularity 
The tight binding method is formulated and its relation to the chemists notion of molec
ular orbital emphasized, hence the name LCAO, linear combination of atomic orbitals. An
example involving s and p orbitals is given. The density of states is dened and van Hove
singularity identied.
Reading : Mardar 10.2.2, 6.3.1, and 7.2.1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Semiclassical Dynamics of Electrons, Bloch Oscillation and Quantization of Orbits in a Uniform Magnetic Field (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ginzburg Landau Free Energy, Meissner Effect and Flux Quantization (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec24/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 24: Ginzburg Landau free energy, Meissner eect and ux quantization
We continue to discuss the physical implications of the quasiparticles. The way they are
measured in tunnelling is briey discussed. We then write down the Ginzburg Landau free
energy and the expression for the current. For constant | we recover the London equation| 
which explains the Meissner eect. The phenomenon of ux quantization is also predicted.We emphasize that persistent current is a consequence of topological winding of the phase
 around a superconducting ring.
Reading : Marder 27.2.3, 27.2.4, 27.2.5</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Quantum Hall Effect and Edge States (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 14: Quantum Hall eect and edge states
The eect of a ux tube through the center of a ring is described. We show that a gauge
transforming which removes the ux tube is equivalent to a modication of the periodic
boundary condition. The Laughlin argument for the integer quantum Hall eect is given.
The Halperin picture of edge states is explained in some detail, leading to an estimate that
corrections to the quantization of the Hall resistance is exponentially small in the sample
width.
Reading : R. Laughlin, Phys. Rev. B 23, 5632 (1981).
B.Halperin, Phys. Rev. B 25, 2185 (1982).</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Bloch Theorem (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1 
Lecture 5: Bloch Theorem
The Bloch theorem is stated and a formal proof is given. The notion of the Brillouin 
zone is introduced. It is shown that each zone contains N states, where N is the number of 
Bravais lattice unit cells in the sample. 
A second proof of the Bloch theorem is given by casting the Schrodinger equations in 
Fourier space. It is shown that a plane wave with momentum k is coupled only to plane 
waves with momentum k+ G where G is a reciprocal lattice vector. The problem is reduced 
to the diagonalization of a large matrix. The notion of band gaps on the zone faces is 
introduced. 
Reading : Marder 7.2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Debye Waller Factor and Incommensurate Structures (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 3: Debye Waller factor and Incommensurate Structures 
The Debye Waller factor is derived for the Einstein model. The main point is that lattice
vibrations do not broaden the Bragg peaks, only reduce their magnitude. Examples of
incommensurate lattices and the notion of sidebands in diraction are discussed.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Attraction by Exchanging Phonons (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/8-511-theory-of-solids-i-fall-2004/resources/lec21/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>1
Lecture 21: Attraction by exchanging phonons 
Electronphonon interaction also gives rise to a mass enhancement, i.e., a change in
the electron dispersion within D of the Fermi energy. This phenomenon is qualitatively
explained. It enhances the specic linear Tcoecient from the band structure value by a
factor (1+ ). However, it does not aect the Pauli spin susceptibility because the correction
to the dispersion is tied to the spinup and down Fermi surface, respectively. The electron
phonon interaction gives rise to an attractive interaction among low energy electrons (those
within D of the Fermi energy). This is derived using a canonical transformation valid
to second order in gq. This interaction is local in space but retarded in time. One can
imagine the rst electron set up some lattice vibration but is long gone when a second
electron is attracted by the slowly varying lattice distortion. Once we add the screened
Coulomb repulsion, the net interaction between electrons is still repulsive, but the eect
of the attractive piece can dominate due to its retarded nature. This is important for the
phenomenon of superconductivity.
Reading : Marder 27.3.3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
