<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/</course_url>
    <course_title>Thermodynamics for Geoscientists</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Physics </list>
      <list>Earth Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Alkali and plagioclase feldspars solution models (cont.)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/12480handout_4_5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Udansky and others to suggest a pressure sensitivity to feldspar equilibria.  Therefore, 
coexisting feldspars might serve as a barometer and a thermometer.   
 
Stormer and Whitney (1985)   
 
In this paper Stormer and Whitney estimated a pressure for the Fish Canyon tuff of 8 to 9 
kbar (24-27 km depth).  They cite a pressure dependence of 18 oC/kbar on feldspar 
equilibria.  This pressure dependency comes from Brown and Parsons (1981) CMP 
76:369-377.  B&amp;P fit a pressure dependency to the Ab-Or solvus using a variety of experimental data, and derive this pressure dependency. 
 
Fuhrman and Lindsley (1988) 
 
     In response to the G&amp;U and S&amp;W papers, F&amp;L remodeled the Seck 1 kbar experimental data.  Their contribution to evolution of these models was to fit x-ray data for ternary feldspars to derive an expression for Wv.  They also evaluate critically the 
utility of two feldspar thermometry and provide a calculation procedure for estimating two-feldspar temperatures. 
 
Elkins and Grove (1990) 
 
     New experimental data on coexisting ternary feldspars and a model for excess free 
energy that uses the simpler XlnX formulation for -T Smix.   
 
Kroll et al. (1993) 
 
      Critical analysis of everybodys experiments! 
 
 
Wen and Nekvasil (1994) 
 
      Nice program (MTHERM3) for recovering temperatures of coexisting ternary 
feldspars. 
 
 
Holland and Powell (2003) 
 
     Some alternative formulations for asymmetric solutions.  Includes van Laar reformulation of a variety of mineral systems including ternary feldspars, carbonates, silicate melts and solids and H
2O - CO 2. 
 
 
Benisek et al. (2004) 
 
     This is Krolls (1993) next missive on the topic of ternary feldspar equilibria.  The critics use experimental data to improve feldspar thermometry.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.480   Handout #4 and #5 
 
Models of ternary feldspars 
 
Seck (1971a) Neues Jahrb Mineral Abh 115:315-345. 
Seck (1971b) Contrib Mineral Petrol 31:67-86 
 
Johannes (1979) Contrib Mineral Petrol 68:221-230. 
Brown and Parsons (1981) Contrib Mineral Petrol 76:369-377. 
 
Green and Udansky (1986) Amer Mineral 71:1100-1108. 
Stormer and Whitney (1985) Amer Mineral 70:52-64. 
 
 
Ghiorso (1984) Contrib Mineral Petrol 87:282-296. 
Fuhrman and Lindsley (1988) Amer Mineral 73:201-215. 
Elkins and Grove (1990) Amer Mineral 75: 544-559. 
 
Kroll et al. (1993) Contrib Mineral Petrol 114: 510-519. 
Wen and Nekvasil (1994) Comp Geosci 20: 1025-1040. 
 
Holland and Powell (2003) Contrib Mineral Petrol 145: 492  501 
Benisek et al. (2004) Amer Mineral 89: 1496-1504 
 
 
 
Ghiorso (1984) 
 
     In this paper Ghiorso expanded the Al-avoidance configurational entropy model of 
Kerrick and Darken (1975) and Newton et al. (1980) to ternary feldspars.  The Kerrick 
and Darken approach is intended to provide an approximation of the ideal part of the activity when mixing takes place with charge balance constraints.  We know this as coupled substitution.  These moels for the ideal part of the activity give larger negative 
values to the entropy of mixing term (-T Smix).   
 
     Ghiorso used the constraints from all three equilibria to estimate equilibration 
temperature. 
 
     Ghiorso's analysis of Seck's (1971) experimental data resulted in a negative Ws term 
for the Woran excess parameter.   
 
Green and Udansky (1986) 
 
     In this paper Seck's 1, 5 and 10 kbar data were used to derive a Wv term for the An-Or excess free energy term.  The magmitude of this term was large and led Green and</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Thermodynamic properties of multi-site mineral solutions - Homogeneous equilibria</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/lec6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>We could also write an exchange reaction: 
Encpx + Diopx Dicpx + Enopx  
Gexch =GDi  GEn 
cpx opx opx cpx
= Di + En  Di  En
Now we need to develop a realistic and workable solution model. We have at equilibrium: 
Xcpx cpx
o,opx o,cpx = RT ln En + RT ln En
En  En Xopx opx
En En
Xcpx cpx
Go = RT ln En + RT ln En
En Xopx opx
En En
Now we may plug in what we know and solve for T . 
Xcpx
En
Xopx
En
Go Go 
En Di 
cpx cpx asymmet ric Di En  
opx opx symmet ric Di En  
This is what Lindsley et al. do, using experimental data in Di  En. 
Note  This is the right way of doing things  other ways 
Assu mption of Wood &amp; Banno (1973) CMP 42 109-124 was that: 
cpx 
activity coecient ratio = 1 Mg2 Si2O6 =1 opx 
Mg2 Si2O6 
didnt consider constraints from CaMgSi2O6.
Warner &amp; Luth (1973) Am. Min. 58, 998- assume opx-cpx obey single equation of state and used
WGs as tting paramet ers.
Binary system -two phases 
equilibrium conditions: 
Mg2Si2Oopx  Mg2Si2Ocpx
6 6
CaMgSi2O6 opx  CaMgSi2O6 cpx 
opx cpx opx cpx En  En = 0; Di  Di =0 
XDidDi + XEndEn =0 
Gibbs-Duhem relates Di &amp; En comp onents at equilibrium. 
 o 
   Xcpx cpx
cpx opx o,cpx o,opx En En
En  En = En  En +RT ln Xopx + RT ln opx =0
En En
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.480 Handout #6: Therm ometry-Barometry Using Pyrox
enes 
Reading 
Lindsley et al. (1981) Adv. in Physical Geochem., 149-175. 
Davidson and Lindsley (1985) Contrib. Min. Pet., 91:383-404. 
Suppl ementary Reading 
Lindsley and Andersen (1983) J. Geophys. Res. 88 (1983) : A877-A906. 
Prewitt, Charles T. (ed.) Pyroxenes (Reviews in Mineralogy, Vol. 7). Washington, D. C.: Miner
alogical Society of Amer ica, 1980. ISBN: 0939950146 
This endeavor got its start thanks to an elegantly presented paper by Boyd (1973) GCA37 
2533-2546. 
Boyds suggest ion was that two equilibria be used to estimate the T&amp;P of equilibration of garnet 
lherzolites. 
Boyd proposed that coexisting cpx-opx be used to infer temperature, and that exchange equilibria 
involving garnet-opx be used to infer pressure. 
Weve come a long way from Boyds initial proposal to the thermome try calculations of today. 
Today well look at progress and pitfalls encountered in this endeavor. 
opx-cpx  2 phases with 2 associated G curves. Correct formulation treats each phase as a 
distinct solution. 
En Di
XG
Enss Diss En + Di

o cpx
En
o opx
Eno opx
Di
Dio cpx
At equilibrium: 
cpx opx =Grxn =0 En  En En 
cpx opx =Grxn Di  Di Di =0 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Xcpx cpx 
cpx opx o,cpx o,opx Di Di Di  Di = Di  Di + RT ln Xopx + RT ln opx 
Di Di 
Use symmet ric solution model for opx and asymmet ric for cpx. 
Xcpx 
o,opx o,cpx En  W opx (Xopx)2 +2WG1Xcpx (Xcpx )2 + WG2 (1  2Xcpx )(Xcpx )2 En  En = RT ln Xopx G Di En Di En Di 
En 
Xcpx 
o,opx o,cpx = RT ln Di  W opx (Xopx)2 + WG1 (1  2Xcpx )(Xcpx )2 +2WG2Xcpx (Xcpx )2 
Di  Di Xopx G En Di En Di En 
Di 
Lindsley, Grover, Davidson model: 
GXS, opx = W opxXopxXopx = 25XopxXopx 
G En Di En Di 
GXS, cpx = WG1Xcpx (Xcpx )2 + WG2Xcpx (Xcpx )2 
En Di Di En 
	  
(25.484 + .0812P ) (31.216  .0061P ) 
Calculation of temperature from opx-cpx pairs (binary system CaMgSi2O6  Mg2Si2O6). Note: 
these two expressions should give you the same T . 
T K (Mg2Si2Oopx  Mg2Si2Ocpx )= 3.561 + .0355P +2WG1Xcpx (Xcpx )2 
6 6	 En Di 
	 Xcpx  
+WG2 (Xcpx )2 (1  2Xcpx )  W opx (Xopx)2	 En 
Di En G Di /.0091  R ln Xopx 
En 
T K (CaMgSi2Ocpx  CaMgSi2Ocpx )= 21.178  .0908P + WG1 (Xcpx )2 (1  2Xcpx )6 6	 En Di 
	 Xcpx  
+2W G2Xcpx (Xcpx )2  W opx (Xopx)2	 Di /	.00816  R ln Xopx Di En G En 
Di 
So, weve done the pure system Di  En, but the pyroxenes we want to study are almost always 
Fe  Ca  Mg solid solutions (at least!)  also Al, Ti, Cr, Na, Fe3+ etc. 
How do we generalize to these comp lex phases? 
1. We must generalize activity approx.	to multi-stite phase where the species can be ordered on 
sites. 
2. We must generalize such an expression for two comp onent systems to comp lex systems. This 
has been done by Davidson and Lindsley (1985) . There are also several graphical/emp irical 
thermomet ers for pyx solns. that can be used. 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Choosing components - Representations of composition space</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/lecture_15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Non-ideal solutions</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/handout_2a_06/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>then 
Gsoln =  Xi  G i - TSmix + G ex
             i 
 
and we allow   
 
   G ex = E ex - PV ex - TS ex
 
 
Another way of rationalizing Gex is that it is the contribution to free energy left 
over after the ideal and standard state free energy contributions are subtracted out. 
 
 
Representations of G ex
 
There are many ways of representing Gex, and we'll talk about one representation here and about some other examples later. 
 
We will use Margules' power series expansion in terms of the solution components.  The choice of a power series  as the mathematical representation is 
a matter of convenience.  Some of the criteria are: 1) The method be useful in 
prediction.  2)  Should account for variations in data using the minimum number 
of fitting parameters, 3)  The model should be consistent with mineral site symmetry constraints or molecular constraints.  The Margules' expression represents Gex as the third power of composition. 
 
To obtain values for the coefficients of this power series we need to define 
another expression: G niss
 
Gniss = G soln + TSmix =    Xi Gi + G ex = A + BX 2 + CX 22 + D X 23
 
G1* and G 2* are the hypothetical excess free energies implied by Henrys law 
behavior.  G 2* is obtained by extrapolating the behavior of component 2 (the 
solute) in a solvent consisting dominantly of component 1 to a hypothetical state 
of behavior where the concentration is pure component 2.  G 1 and G 2 are the 
standard state free energies for phases consisting of pure component 1 or 2, 
respectively.  We will derive an expression for G ex that expresses the deviation 
from ideal behavior as the difference between these two end member standard states (G
2* - G2). 
 
First, we'll look at the values of these coefficients in the limits as X 2  0 
 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>G ex = W GX1X2
 
 
 
Gsoln =  X 11o + X 22o + nRT (X 1lnX 1 + X 2lnX 2) + X 1X2WG
 
And 
 
1   =   1   + RTlnX 1 +  (1-X) 12(W G) 
 
The G 1* and G 2* in our expressions are related to the Henry's law chemical 
potential.  They are the chemical potential of component 1 in a physically 
unattainable state - that is in pure component 2. 
 
 
We used Margules (1895) power series and we truncated the power series and obtained a 2 parameter fit.  Originally this expression was used in gas-liq systems to describe vapor pressure of a component in a binary solution. 
 
 
 
Other expressions for excess free energy  
 
(l)  Van laar equations 
 
 
      log   1     =           A 12/[1+(A 12X1/A 21X2)]2
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
(2)  Redlich-Kister or Guggenheim equation 
 
 
 
 Gex/RT = X 1(1-X 1)  B + C(2X 1-1) + D(2X 1-1)2 +....... 
 
           an infinite series - again truncated. 
 
 7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>C =  (G 1* - G 1) - 2(G 2* - G 2) 
plug back into G niss and collect terms 
 
Gsi = G 1 + (G 2* - G 1)X2 + [(G 1* - G 1) - 2(G 2* - G 2) ]X 22
 
           + [(G 2* - G 2) - (G 1* - G 1) ]X 23
 
     
 if we define W G1  = (G 1* - G 1)  
 
             W G2 = [(G 2* - G 2)  
 
 
  C = W G1 - 2W G2
 
  D = W G2 - W G1      (error in JBT) 
 
 
 
No we are ready to plug in for G niss and simplify 
 
Gsi = X 1G1 + X 2G2 + W G2 X2 + [W G1 - 2W G2]X22
                   
                     +[ W G2 - W G1]X23
 
 
Gsi =  Xi Gi  + W G2 X2(1-2X 2 + X 22) + W G1X22(1-X 2) 
 
Gsi =  Xi Gi  + W G2 X2(X1)2 + W G1X22(X1) 
 
So,  G ex = W G2 X2(X1)2 + W G1X22(X1) 
 
and the total free energy of the solution can be expressed by plugging G niss in the 
ideal contribution to the free energy from the existence of a solution. This gives 
us G soln. 
 
Since   i  = G i  we can write G soln in the following way 
 
Gsoln = X 11 + X 22 + nRT(X 1 ln X 1 + X 2lnX 2) + (W G1X2 +W G2X1)X1X2
 
recall 1 = G soln + X 2 Gsoln/X2            P,T = constant 
and    2 = G soln + (1-X 2) Gsoln/X2      P,T = constant 
 5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Gex + X 1G1 + X 2G2 = A + BX + CX2 + DX3  
 
       as X 2    0,  G ex  0 
 
 
so G ex + G 1 =   A and  A  = G 1 
 
 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>as X 2    1,   G ex    0 
 
and G 1 + B + C + D = G 2 
 
Now take the derivative of G si
 
Gniss/X2 = B + 2CX 2 + 3DX 22
 
 
So, well evaluate these in the limits of 
infinite dilution 
 
This is the well known Henrys Law behavior exhibited by solutions. 
 
as X 2        0     Gsi/X2 = B = (G 2* - G 1) 
 
 
 
as X 2      1     Gsi/X2 = B + 2C  + 3D  = (G 2 - G 1*) G2*
G1*
G20
G10
X2G
GexGniss
0 1WG2
WG1
 
 
Therefore, 
 
 
   (G 2* - G 1)  +  2C  +3D  =  (G 2 - G 1*)  
 
(expression for Gniss/X2) 
 
G1  +  (G 2* - G 1) + C +D  =  G 2 
 
(Expression for G niss) 
 
multiply second expression by 2 and subtract 
 
-G1 - G 2* + D  = -G 2 - G 1*
 
          D = (G 2* - G 2) - (G 1* - G 1) 
 
plug back and solve for C 
 
        C = G 2 - G 2* - (G 2* - G 2) +(G 1* - G 1) 
 4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Gsoln/X2  = (2 - 1) + RTln X 2/X 1  + W G1X2(3X 1-1) - W G2X1(3X 2-1) 
 
 
then plug in &amp; simplify: 
 
 
1   =   1   + nRTlnX 1 +  X 22(W G1 + 2(W G2-W G1)X1) 
 
The  observed departure of a solution from ideal behavior for component 1 is 
given by the term: 
 
X22(W G1 + 2(W G2-W G1)X1) 
 
This term can be thought of as  1ex  and 
 
1ex  = nRT ln 1  
 
The  term is a way of expressing the deviation of a solution from ideal behavior 
through the activity of a component in a phase. 
 
ai =   i Xi
 
and  
 
1  = 10  + nRT lna 1
 
RT lna 1 = RTln X 1 + RTln 1  
 
Therefore, 
 
nRTln1 = X 22(W G1 + 2(W G2 - W G1)X1) 
 
and 
 
1 = exp[X 22(W G1 + 2(W G2 - W G1)X1)/nRT] 
 
Symmetric solutions 
 
We call solutions obeying this power series relation asymmetric solutions.  There is a special case called a symmetric solution where W
G2 = W G1 and our 
expressions reduce to: 
 
 6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.480 Handout #2  
 
Non-ideal solutions  
 
Reading Thompson (1967) Researches in Geochem, v.2., 340-361. 
 
 
Solutions for which Hmix &gt; 0 
 
Depending on the contribution from  Hmix, we can have one of two general 
cases. 
 
G
XGex
Gsoln
Gideal 
 
I.  Solution is stable over  
     entire composition range. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
II.  Contribution from  H is such 
that solution is stable only near the end members and we have phase separation 
for intermediate compositions. 
 
G
XGex
Gsoln
GidealGniss
 
In general, we will separate out an excess free energy of mixing term.  Gex 
 1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>(3)  Wilson Equation 
 
 
   Gex/RT =    Xiln (Xij ) 
                          i           j 
 
 8</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Liquidus diagrams - Degeneracies and natural examples</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/lecture_12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Alkali and plagioclase feldspars solution models</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/lec3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>First Assumption 
The os are not equal and we require two sets of W s! So 
AF PF 	Ab = Ab
AF o disordAF
Ab = Ab + RT ln AbXAb 
where W s were appropriate to disordered 0. 
PF o ordered plag Ab = AB + RT ln AbXAb 
potentially we also need W s for a dierent solution. 
TT
XAb OrC2/m
C1at T
XGAbo disord . PF
Abo ord . PFC2/m
C1
Second Assumption 
A ternary solution model would be more appropriate. 
RT ln 1 = WG12X12X2 + WG21X22X1 
+WG13X12X3 + WG31X32X1
+WG23X22X3 + WG32X32X2
Margules formulations for ternary and quaternary solutions were developed by Wohl (1946, 1953) . 
Lindsley and Anderson (1981) go through the exercise of deriving an expression for a ternary asym
metric model. These models, like the ones for binary systems, assume that a polynomial of degree 2 
(symmet ric) or degree 3 (asymmet ric) in comp onent 2 and 3 are adequate models of the excess free 
energy of mixing. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.480 Handout #3 
Reading 
Stormer (1975) Am. Mineral 60, 667-674.
Whitney and Stormer (1977) Am. Mineral 62, 687-691.
Andersen and Lindsley (1981) GCA 45, 847-853.
Suppl ementary Reading 
Grien, Dana T. Silicate Crystal Chemistry, Chapter 2. New York, NY: Oxford University Press,
1992. ISBN: 0195044423
Ribbe, P. H. (ed.) Feldspar Mineralogy (Reviews in Mineralogy, Vol. 2, 2nd ed.). Washington, D.
C.: Mineralogical Society of Amer ica, 1983. ISBN: 0939950146
Two feldspar themomet ry-baromet ry
The use of coexisting plagioclase and alkali feldspars to predict temperature and pressure of equi
libration was rst proposed by Barth (1951) who used natural phase assem blages to calibrate a
thermomet er. Stormer and Whitney and Stormer subsequently develop a simple thermodynamic
model for treating feldspar equilibria. The important assumptions for this model were:
1. Use one of the conditions of equilibrium. 
AF PF Ab = Ab 
where AF = alkali feldspar and PF = plagioclase feldspar. 
PF 2. Assu me that Or content in PF has no eect on aAb and that An content in AF has no eect 
AFon aAb .
The equilibrium condition can be written
 AF =  oAF + RT lnAF 
Ab Ab aAb 
PF oPF + RT lnPF Ab = Ab aAb 
3. Assu me that the standard state chemical potential for pure Ab in both phases was the same. 
Then 
AFa0= RT ln Ab 
PF aAb 
AF XAF
= RT ln Ab Ab
PF XPF 
Ab Ab 
4. Assu me PF = 1, so Ab 
XAF
ln Ab = ln AF
XPF Ab
Ab
1ln AF = (2WGOr  WGAb)(XAF )2 +2(WGAb  WGOr)(XAF )3 
Ab Or Or RT 
Several of the simplications of the Whitney and Stormer thermomet er have been dealt with 
in subsequent models of feldspar equilibria, and some have not. 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Heterogeneous reactions - The Gibbs method</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/lecture_16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Heterogeneous equilibria in two - and three-component systems</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/lecture_10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Schreinemaker&#8217;s analysis - Multi-component systems</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/lecture_14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Liquidus diagrams - Thermodynamic controls on boundaries</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/lecture_13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Pyroxene thermometry II, the quad</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/lec7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>using JBTs ordering paramet ers.... 
  G XM2XM 1 
at equilibrium  RT  = 0 = ln Fe Mg + gs + grsr +2gsss s XM2XM 1 
Mg Fe 
P,T,r 
ln Kintra 
D = gs  grsr  2gsss 
g0 =1  
G F eMg 0 G MgF e 0 + G F eF e 0 + G MgMg 0 + WM1 + WM2  
4RT
gs =1  
G0 G0 
2RT F eMgSi2 O6 MgF eSi2O6 
1
grs =2RT (WM1  WM2)
and gss ... contains all of these terms. 
WM1 +WM 2If we plug in and assume GF eF e = GMgMg, GMgF e = GF eMg and WM = 2 . 
ln Kintra G F eMgSi0 
2O6  G MgF eSi0 
2O6 WM = D 2RT  RT 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>12.480 Handout #7: Eect s of Orderi ng Species on Sites in a 
Crystalline Solution 
Equilibrium in a closed crystal mean s one that does not vary in comp osition. 
There are independently variable reactions that result in distributions of species on sites. We 
want to look at how the free energy of crystals varies as these reactions occur. 
At equilibrium the Gibbs function will be a minimum. 
The free energy of the crystal consists of two parts. The rst is the ideal congurational entropy, 
approprialtely readjusted for species and sites. 
Sideal = nK qNsq ln Nsq,
sq
where nK = R, = sum over all species, = sum over all sites, q = multiplicity of site, and s q 
Nsq = atoms of types on site q. 
Remeb er the equivalent derivation we carried out earlier for ways of distributing species over 
sites... 
(nN)!W = (XnN)!((1  X)nN)! 
Now  dene thermodynamic properties like 
S  S soln  S ideal  excess entropy for sites 
G  G soln + TSideal = H soln  TS  free energies for sites 
then 
Gsoln = G  TS i = G + RT qNsq ln Nsq
i sq
This G is dened as a deviation from ideal solution behavior. It arises from: 
1. long-range ordering on sites 
2. internal reactions (oxidation-reduction) amon g species and vacan cies 
3. excess energy and volume terms for sites 
Application to Pyroxene 
(F e, Mg)M2(F e, Mg)M1Si2O6 
Xxtal XM1 + XM 2
Fe Fe Fe
XFs = Xxtal + Xxtal =2  this is a familiar descriptive paramet er
Fe Mg
Well use dierent comp ositional paramet ers rads that reect distribution of species on sites. 
r  XM2 + XM1  1=2XFs  1Fe Fe 
s  XM2  XM 1 
Fe Fe 
Physically accessi ble comp osition space is then dened in terms of r and s and the possibility of 
ordering is included. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Fe   Mg   SiO
FeSiO
Mg   Fe   SiOMgSiOs
rM M
M MNow -comp osition space can be recast into r and s ordering paramet ers and G expanded in a 
power series about a reference state. 
 G 
= g0 + grr + gss + grrr 2 + grsrs + gsss 2 
RT 
Here is the key to the model. We assume that G can be accou nted for by a power series expansion.
Conditions of equilibrium are used to determine G.
In this example we are dealing with a closed system (crystal). The Gibbs function must be minimized
with respect to all variations in independent paramet ers.
G =0 Xs P,T,Xi 
If this is not the case, some variation of Xis could lower the free energy. 
G
G G
s = ordering parameterG     slope = 0 eq
We could also expand our expression in terms of terms which look a bit more familiar.... 
G =2RT [X11 ln X11 + X21 ln X21 + X12 ln X12 + X22 ln X22] ideal entropy of mixing  
+G0 G0 G0 G0 
X11X12 + 10X21X22 + 0X21X22 + 01X11X22  ordering energy 10 1
+WM1X11X21 + WM2X12X22  deviation from ideality
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Ideal solutions</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/lec1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Study Question 
1. From: 
dG SdT + V dP + idxi
i
show that: 
G
x2 = 2  1
2. Using the denition for G soln, an expression for Gsoln , and 2 = G soln + (1  x) Gsoln , show x2 x 
that:
2 = 20 + nRT ln x2
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Free Energ y of a Solution 
We can write the free energy of a solution as follows: 
2 comp onents 1&amp;2 x = mole fraction. 
G soln = x1G 10 + x2G 20 + nRT (x1 ln x1 + x2 ln x2) 
(1) 
Gmechanical mixing T S mix 
The denition of the chemical potential: 
G 
xi = i 
P,T,nj =ni 
1 2
xGGG
GsolnGsoln

x=x
  Gsoln 
x1 =  G0 
1   G0 2 + nRT [ln x1  ln(1  x1)] (2) 
2 =  Gsoln + (1  x2)   Gsoln 
x2 (3) 
1 = Gsoln + x2 Gsoln 
x2 (4) 
then: 
1 = G0 1 + nRT ln x1 
2 = G0 
2 + nRT ln x2 
1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Liquidus diagrams - Liquidus boundaries</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-480-thermodynamics-for-geoscientists-fall-2006/resources/lecture_11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text></text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
