<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/</course_url>
    <course_title>Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Mathematics </list>
      <list>Algebra and Number Theory </list>
      <list>Topology and Geometry </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Tensor product and tensor functors
Unit object
Grothendieck rings
Groupoids
Finite abelian categories
Fiber functors
Coalgebras</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec04/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>37 
Exercise 1.15.3. One has 1i  1j = 0 for i =j. There are canonical 
isomorphisms 1i  1i = 1i. = 1i, and 1i 
Let Cij := 1i C 1j . 
Denition 1.15.4. The subcategories Cij will be called the component 
subcategories of C. 
Prop osition 1.15.5. Let C be a multiring category. 
(1)	C = i,jI Cij . Thus every indecomposable object of C belongs 
to some Cij . 
(2)	The tensor product maps Cij Ckl to Cil, and it is zero unless 
j = k. 
(3)	The categories Cii are ring categories with unit objects 1i (which 
are tensor categories if C is rigid). 
(3)	The functors of left and right duals, if they are dene d, map Cij 
to Cji. 
Exercise 1.15.6. Prove Prop osition 1.15.5. 
Prop osition 1.15.5 motiv ates the terms multiring category and 
multitensor category, as such a category gives us multiple ring cate
gories, respectively tensor categories Cii. 
Remark 1.15.7. Thus, a multiring category may be considered as a 
2-category with objects being elemen ts of I, 1-morphisms from j to i 
forming the category Cij , and 2-morphism s being 1-morphisms in C. 
Theorem 1.15.8. (i) In a ring category with right duals , the unit 
object 1 is simple. 
(ii) In a multiring category with right duals, the unit object 1 is 
semisimple, and is a direct sum of pairwise non-isomorphic simple ob
jects 1i. 
Proof. Clearly , (i) implies (ii) (by applying (i) to the comp onent cate
gories Cii). So it is enough to prove (i). 
Let X be a simple subobject of 1 (it exists, since 1 has nite length). 
Let 
(1.15.1) 0  X  1  Y  0 
be the corresp onding exact sequence. By Prop osition 1.13.5, the right 
dualization functor is exact, so we get an exact sequence 
(1.15.2) 0  Y   1  X  0. 
Tensoring this sequence with X on the left, we obtain 
(1.15.3) 0  X  Y   X  X  X  0,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>36 
Proof. In the rst case by Prop osition 1.10.9 we have Hom(P X, Y )= 
Hom(P, Y X), which is an exact functor of Y , since the functors X 
and Hom(P, ) are exact. So P  X is projectiv e. The second case is 
similar.  
Corollary 1.13.7. If C multiring category with right duals, then 1 C 
is a projective object if and only if C is semisimple. 
Proof. If 1 is projectiv e then for any X C, X = 1  X is projectiv e. 
This implies that C is semisimple. The converse is obvious.  
1.14. Quasi-tensor and tensor functors. 
Denition 1.14.1. Let C, D be multiring categories over k, and F : 
CD be an exact and faithful functor. 
(i) F is said to be a quasi-tensor functor if it is equipp ed with a 
functorial isomorphism J : F ()  F () F (), and F (1)= 1. 
(ii) A quasi-tensor functor (F, J) is said to be a tensor functor if J 
is a monoidal structure (i.e., satis es the monoidal structure axiom). 
Example 1.14.2. The functors of Examples 1.6.1,1.6.2 and Subsection 
1.7 (for the categories Vec 
G) are tensor functors. The identity functor 
Vec1 V ec2 for non-cohomologous 3-cocycles 1,2 is not a tensor G G
functor, but it can be made quasi-tensor by any choice of J. 
1.15. Semisimplicit y of the unit object. 
Theorem 1.15.1. In any multiring category, End(1 ) is a semisimple 
algebr a, so it is isomorphic to a direct sum of nitely many copies of 
k. 
Proof. By Prop osition 1.2.7, End(1 ) is a comm utativ e algebra, so it is 
sucien t to show that for any a  End(1 ) such that a2 = 0 we have 
a = 0. Let J = Im(a). Then by Corollary 1.13.4 J  J = Im(a  a)= 
Im(a2  1) = 0. 
Now let K = Ker(a). Then by Corollary 1.13.4, K  J is the image 
of 1  a on K  1. But since K  1 is a subobject of 1  1, this is the 
same as the image of a  1 on K  1, which is zero. So K  J = 0. 
Now tensoring the exact sequence 0 K 1 J 0 with J,  
and applying Prop osition 1.13.1, we get that J = 0, so a = 0.  
Let {pi}iI be the primitiv e idemp otents of the algebra End(1 ). Let 
1i be the image of pi. Then we have 1 = iI 1i. 
Corollary 1.15.2. In any multiring category C the unit object 1 is 
isomorphic to a direct sum of pairwise non-isomorphic indecomposable 
objects: 1 = i 1i.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>40 
(2) Let X be a set and let G = X  X. Then the product groupoid 
G(X) := (X, G) is a group oid in which s is the rst projection, 
t is the second projection, u is the diagona l map, and i is the 
permutation of factor s. In this group oid for any x, y  X there 
is a unique morphism from x to y. 
(3) A more interesting example is the transformation gr oupoid T (G, X) 
arising from the action of a group G on a set X. The set 
of objects of T (G, X) is X, and arrows corresp ond to triples 
(g, x, y) where y = gx with an obvious comp osition law. In 
other words, the set of morphisms is G  X and s(g, x)= 
x, t(g, x)= gx, u(x) = (1,x),i(g, x)=(g1, gx). 
Let G =(X, G, , s, t, u, i) be a nite group oid (i.e., G is nite) and let 
C(G) be the category of nite dimen sional vector spaces graded by the 
set G of morphisms of G, i.e., vector spaces of the form V = gG Vg. 
Introduce a tensor product on C(G) by the formula 
(1.17.1) (V  W )g = Vg1  Wg2 . 
(g1,g2):g1g2=g 
Then C(G) is a multitensor category . The unit object is 1 = xX 1x, 
where 1x is a 1-dimensional vector space which sits in degree idx in G. 
The left and right duals are dened by (V )g =(V )g = Vg1 . 
We invite the reader to check that the component subcategorie s 
C(G)xy are the categor ies of vector spaces grade d by Mor(y, x). 
We see that C(G) is a tensor category if and only if G is a group, 
which is the case of VecG already considered in Example 1.3.6. Note 
also that if X = {1, ..., n} then C(G(X)) is naturally equiv alent to 
Mn(Vec). 
Exercise 1.17.1. Let Ci be isomorphism classes of objects in a nite 
group oid G, ni = |Ci|, xi  Ci be represen tatives of Ci, and Gi = 
Aut(xi) be the corresp onding automorphism groups. Show that C(G) 
is (non-canonically) monoidally equiv alent to iMni (VecGi ). 
Remark 1.17.2. The nite length condition in Den ition 1.12.3 is 
not superuous: there exists a rigid monoidal k-linear abelian category 
with bilinear tensor product which contains objects of innite length. 
An example of such a category is the category C of Jacobi matrices of 
nite dimensional vector spaces. Namely , the objects of C are semi-
innite matrices V = {Vij }ijZ+ of nite dimensional vector spaces Vij 
with nitely many non-zero diagon als, and morphism s are matrices of 
linear maps. The tensor product in this category is dened by the</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>43 
Exercise 1.19.3. Show that if an abelian monoidal category C admits 
a quasi-b er functor, then it is a ring category, in which the object 1 
is simple. So if in addition C is rigid, then it is a tensor category . 
1.20. Coalgebras. 
Denition 1.20.1. A coalgebr a (with counit) over a eld k is a k-vector 
space C together with a comultiplicaton (or copro duct)  : CC C
and counit  : Ck such that 
(i)  is coasso ciativ e, i.e., 
(  Id) =(Id  )  
as maps CC3;
(ii) one has
(  Id) =(Id  ) =Id
  
as maps CC (the counit axiom).  
Denition 1.20.2. A left comodule over a coalgebra C is a vector 
space M together with a linear map  : MC  M (called the 
coaction map), such that for any m  M, one has 
(  Id)( (m)) = (Id  )((m)), (  Id)( (m)) = m. 
Similarly , a right como dule over C is a vector space M together with 
a linear map  : MM  C, such that for any m  M, one has  
(  Id)( (m)) = (Id  )((m)), (Id  )((m)) = m. 
For example, C is a left and right como dule with  = , and so is 
k, with  = . 
Exercise 1.20.3. (i) Show that if C is a coalgebra then C is an 
algebra, and if A is a nite dimensional algebra then A is a coalgebra. 
(ii) Show that for any coalgebra C, any (left or right) C-como dule 
M is a (resp ectively, right or left) C-module, and the converse is true 
if C is nite dimensional. 
Exercise 1.20.4. (i) Show that any coalgebra C is a sum of nite 
dimensional subcoalgebras. 
Hint. Let c  C, and let 
(  Id)  (c) = (Id  )  (c) = c 1 
i  c 2 
i  c 3 
i . 
i 
Show that span(c2 
i ) is a subcoalgebra of C containing c. 
(ii) Show that any C-como dule is a sum of nite dimensional subco
modules.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>42 
one can take A = End(P )op, where P is a projectiv e generator of C (e.g., 
P = in 
=1Pi, where Pi are projectiv e covers of all the simple objects 
Xi). 
A projectiv e generator P of C represen ts a functor F = FP : C Vec 
from C to the category of nite dimensional k-vector spaces, given by 
the formula F (X)= Hom(P, X). The condition that P is projectiv e 
translates into the exactness property of F , and the condition that 
P is a generator (i.e., covers any simple object) translates into the 
property that F is faithful (does not kill nonzero objects or morphi sms). 
Moreo ver, the algebra A = End(P )op can be alternativ ely dened as 
End(F ), the algebra of functorial endomorphisms of F . Conversely , 
it is well known (and easy to show) that any exact faithful functor 
F : C Vec is represen ted by a unique (up to a unique isomorphism) 
projectiv e generator P . 
Now let C be a nite k-linear abelian category , and F1,F2 : C Vec 
be two exact faithful functors. Dene the functor F1 F2 : CC  Vec 
by (F1  F2)(X, Y ) := F1(X)  F2(Y ). 
Prop osition 1.18.3. Ther e is a canonic al algebr a isomorphism F1,F2 : 
End(F 1)  End(F 2) = End(F 1  F2) given by 
F1,F2 (1  2)|F1(X)F2(Y ) := 1|F1(X)  2|F2(Y ), 
wher e i  End(Fi),i =1, 2. 
Exercise 1.18.4. Prove Prop osition 1.18.3. 
1.19. Fiber functors. Let C be a k-linear abelian monoidal category . 
Denition 1.19.1. A quasi-b er functor on is an exact faithfulC
functor F : C Vec from C to the category of nite dimensional 
k-vector spaces, such that F (1)= k, equipp ed with an isomorphism 
J : F ()  F () F (). If in addition J is a monoidal structure 
(i.e. satises the monoidal structure axiom), one says that F is a ber 
functor . 
Example 1.19.2. The forgetful functors VecG  Vec, Rep(G) Vec 
are naturally ber functor s, while the forgetful functor Vec  
Vec G 
is quasi-b er, for any choice of the isomorphism J (we have seen that 
if  is cohom ologically nontrivial, then Vec does not admit a ber G 
functor). Also, the functo r Loc(X) Vec on the category of local 
systems on a connected topological space X which attac hes to a local 
system E its ber Ex at a point x  X is a ber functor, which justies 
the terminology . (Note that if X is Hausdor, then this functor can be 
identied with the abovemen tioned forgetful functor Rep(1(X, x)) 
Vec).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>34 
1.13. Exactness of the tensor product. 
Prop osition 1.13.1. (see [BaKi, 2.1.8]) Let C be a multitensor cate
gory. Then the bifunctor  : CC C is exact in both factors (i.e., 
biexact ). 
Proof. The proposition follows from the fact that by Prop osition 1.10.9, 
the functors V  and V have left and right adjoin t functors (the 
functors of tensoring with the corresp onding duals), and any functor 
between abelian categories which has a left and a right adjoin t functor 
is exact.  
Remark 1.13.2. The proof of Prop osition 1.13.1 shows that the bi
additivit y of the functor  holds automatically in any rigid monoidal 
abelian category . However, this is not the case for bilinearit y of , 
and thus condition of bilinearit y of tensor product in the denition of 
a multitensor category is not redundan t. 
This may be illustrated by the following examp le. Let C be the 
category of nite dimensional C-bimo dules in which the left and right 
actions of R coincide. This category is C-linear abelian; namely , it is 
semisimple with two simple objects C+ = 1 and C, both equal to 
C as a real vector space, with bimo dule structures (a, b)z = azb and 
(a, b)z = azb, respectively. It is also also rigid monoidal, with  being 
the tensor product of bimo dules. But the tensor product functor is not 
C-bilinear on morphisms (it is only R-bilinear). 
Denition 1.13.3. A multiring category over k is a locally nite k-
linear abelian monoidal category C with biexact tensor product. If in 
addition End(1 )= k, we will call C a ring category. 
Thus, the dierence between this denition and the denition of a 
(multi)tensor category is that we dont require the existence of duals, 
but instead require the biexactness of the tensor product. Note that 
Prop osition 1.13.1 implies that any multitensor categ ory is a multiring 
category , and any tensor category is a ring category . 
Corollary 1.13.4. For any pair of morphisms f1,f2 in a multiring 
category C one has Im(f 1  f2) = Im(f1)  Im(f 2). 
Proof. Let I1,I2 be the image s of f1,f2. Then the morphisms fi : Xi 
Yi, i =1, 2, have decomp ositions Xi  Ii  Yi, where the sequences 
Xi  Ii  0, 0  Ii  Yi 
are exact. Tensoring the sequence X1  I1  0 with I2, by Prop osition 
1.13.1, we get the exact sequence 
X1  I2  I1  I2  0</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>38 
Since X is simple and X X = 0 (because the coevaluation morphism 
is nonze ro) we obtain that X  X = X. So we have a surjectiv e 
comp osition morphism 1  X  X  X. From this and (1.15.1) we 
have a nonzero comp osition morphism 1  X1. Since End(1 )= k, 
this morphism is a nonzero scalar, whence X = 
1.  
Corollary 1.15.9. In a ring category with right duals, the evaluation 
morphisms are surje ctive and the coevaluation morphisms are injective. 
Exercise 1.15.10. Let C be a multiring category with right duals. and 
X Cij and Y Cjk be nonzero. 
(a) Show that X  Y = 0. 
(b) Deduce that length(X  Y )  length(X )length(Y ). 
(c) Show that if C is a ring category with right duals then an in
vertible object in C is simple. 
(d) Let	X be an object in a multiring categ ory with right duals 
such that X  X  Show that X is invertible. = 1. 
Example 1.15.11. An example of a ring category where the unit ob
ject is not simple is the category C of nite dimensional represen tations 
of the quiver of type A2. Such represen tations are triples (V, W, A), 
where V, W are nite dimensional vector spaces, and A : VW is a 
linear operator. The tensor product on such triples is dened by the 
formula 
(V, W, A)  (V ,W ,A)=(V  V ,W  W ,A  A), 
with obvious associativit y isomorphisms, and the unit object (k, k, Id). 
Of course, this category has neither right nor left duals. 
1.16. Grothendiec k rings. Let C be a locally nite abelian category 
over k. If X and Y are objects in C such that Y is simple then we denote 
by [X : Y ] the multiplicit y of Y in the Jordan-H older comp osition series 
of X. 
Recall that the Grothendiec k group Gr(C) is the free abelian group 
generated by isomorphism classes Xi,i  I of simple objects in C, 
and that to every object X in C we can canonically associate its class 
[X]  Gr(C) given by the formula [X]= [X : Xi]Xi. It is obvious i 
that if 
0  X  Y  Z  0 
then [Y ]=[X]+[Z]. When no confu sion is possible, we will write X 
instead of [X].</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>41 
formula 
(1.17.2)	 (V  W )il = Vij  Wjl, 
j 
and the unit object 1 is dened by the condition 1ij = kij . The left 
and right dualit y functors coincide and are given by the formula 
(1.17.3)	 (V )ij =(Vji). 
The evaluation map is the direct sum of the canonical maps Vij  Vij 
1jj , and the coevaluation map is a direct sum of the canonical maps 
1ii  Vij  Vij . 
Note that the category C is a subcategory of the category C of G(Z+)
graded vector spaces with nite dimension al homogeneous comp onents. 
Note also that the category C is not closed under the tensor product 
dened by (1.17.2) but the category C is. 
Exercise 1.17.3. (1) Show that if X is a nite set then the group 
of invertible objects of the category C(G(X)) is isomorphic to 
Aut(X ). 
(2) Let C be the category of Jacobi matrices of vector spaces from 
Example 1.17.2. Show that the statem ent Exercise 1.15.10(d) 
fails for C. Thus the nite length condition is importan t in 
Exercise 1.15.10. 
1.18. Finite abelian categories and exact faithful functors. 
Denition 1.18.1. A k-linear abelian categor y C is said to be nite if 
it is equiv alent to the category A  mod of nite dimensional modules 
over a nite dimensional k-algebra A. 
Of course, the algebra A is not canonically attac hed to the category 
C; rather, C determines the Morita equiv alence class of A. For this 
reason, it is often better to use the following intrinsic denition, 
which is well known to be equivalent to Denition 1.18.1: 
Denition 1.18.2. A k-linear abelian category C is nite if 
(i) C has nite dimensio nal spaces of morphisms; 
(ii) every object of C has nite length; 
(iii) C has enough projectives, i.e., every simple object of C has a 
projectiv e cover; and 
(iv) there are nitely many isomorphism classes of simple objects. 
Note that the rst two conditions are the requiremen t that C be 
locally nite. 
Indeed, it is clear that if A is a nite dimensional algebra then A 
mod clearly satises (i)-(iv), and conversely , if C satises (i)-(iv), then</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>39 
Now let C be a multiring categor y. The tensor product on C induces 
a natural multiplication on Gr(C) dened by the formula 
XiXj := [Xi  Xj ]= [Xi  Xj : Xk]Xk. 
kI 
Lemma 1.16.1. The above multiplic ation on Gr(C) is associative. 
Proof. Since the tensor product functor is exact, 
[(Xi  Xj )  Xp : Xl]= [Xi  Xj : Xk][Xk  Xp : Xl]. 
k 
On the other hand, 
[Xi  (Xj  Xp): Xl]= [Xj  Xp : Xk][Xi  Xk : Xl]. 
k 
Thus the associativit y of the multiplication follows from the isomor
phism (Xi  Xj )  Xp = Xi  (Xj  Xp).  
Thus Gr(C) is an associativ e ring with the unit 1. It is called the 
Grothendie ck ring of C. 
The following proposition is obvious. 
Prop osition 1.16.2. Let C and D be multiring categories and F : C 
D be a quasi-tensor functor. Then F denes a homomorphism of unital 
rings [F ]: Gr(C) Gr(D). 
Thus, we see that (multi)ring categories categorify rings (which jus
ties the terminology), while quasi-tensor (in particular, tensor) func
tors between them categorify unital ring homomorphisms. Note that 
Prop osition 1.15.5 may be regarded as a categorical analog of the Peirce 
decomp osition in classical algebra. 
1.17. Group oids. The most basic examples of multitensor categories 
arise from nite group oids. Recall that a groupoid is a small category 
where all morphisms are isomorphisms. Thus a groupoid G entails a set 
X of objects of G and a set G of morphisms of G, the source and target 
maps s, t : GX, the comp osition map  : G X GG (where the  
bered product is dened using s in the rst factor and using t in the 
second factor), the unit morphism map u : XG, and the inversion  
map i : GG satisfying certain natural axioms, see e.g. [Ren] for 
more details. 
Here are some examples of group oids. 
(1) Any group G is a group oid G with a single object whose set of 
morphisms to itself is G.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>35 
Tenosring X1 with the sequenc e X2 I2 0, we get the exact se  
quence 
X1  X2  X1  I2  0. 
Combining these, we get an exact sequence 
X1  X2  I1  I2  0. 
Arguing similarly , we show that the sequence 
0 I1  I2  Y1  Y2  
is exact. This implies the statemen t.  
Prop osition 1.13.5. If C is a multiring category with right duals, then 
the right dualization functor is exact. The same applies to left duals. 
Proof. Let 0 XY Z 0 be an exact sequen ce. We need to  
show that the sequence 0 Z Y  X 0 is exact. Let T be  
any object of C, and consider the sequence 
0 Hom(T,Z) Hom(T,Y ) Hom(T,X).  
By Prop osition 1.10.9, it can be written as 
0 Hom(T  Z, 1) Hom(T  Y, 1) Hom(T  X, 1),    
which is exact, since the sequence 
T  XT  YT  Z 0  
is exact, by the exactness of the functor T . This implies that the 
sequence 0 Z Y  X is exact. 
Similarly , consider the sequence
0 Hom(X,T ) Hom(Y ,T ) Hom(Z,T ).
  
By Prop osition 1.10.9, it can be written as 
0 Hom(1,X  T ) Hom(1,Y  T ) Hom(1,Z  T ),    
which is exact since the sequence 
0 X  TY  TZ  T  
is exact, by the exactness of the functor T . This implies that the 
sequence Z Y  X 0 is exact.    
Prop osition 1.13.6. Let P be a projective object in a multiring cate
gory C. If X C has a right dual, then the object P  X is projective. 
Similarly, if X C has a left dual, then the object X  P is projective.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Quantum groups
Skew-primitive elements
Pointed tensor categories
Coradical filtration
Chevalley&#8217;s theorem and Chevalley property</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec06/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>60 
1.29. The coradical ltration. Let C be a locally nite abelian cat
egory . 
Any object X C has a canonical ltration 
(1.29.1) 0 = X0  X1  X2    Xn = X 
such that Xi+1/Xi is the socle (i.e., the maximal semisimple subobject) 
of X/Xi (in other words, Xi+1/Xi is the sum of all simple subobjects 
of X/Xi). This ltra tion is called the socle ltration, or the coradical 
ltration of X. It is easy to show by induction that the coradical 
ltration is a ltration of X of the smallest possible length, such that 
the successiv e quotien ts are semisimple. The length of the coradical 
ltration of X is called the Loewy length of X, and denoted Lw(X). 
Then we have a ltration of the category C by Loewy length of objects: 
C0 C1  ..., where Ci denotes the full subcategory of objects of C of 
Loewy length  i + 1. Clearly , the Loewy length of any subquotient of 
an object X does not exceed the Loewy length of X, so the categories 
Ci are closed under taking subquotien ts. 
Denition 1.29.1. The ltration of C by Ci is called the coradical 
ltration of C. 
If C is endowed with an exact faithful functor F : C Vec then we 
can dene the coalgebra C = Coend(F ) and its subcoalgebras Ci = 
Coend(F |Ci ), and we have Ci  Ci+1 and C = iCi (alternativ ely, we 
can say that Ci is spanned by matrix elemen ts of C-como dules F (X), 
X Ci). Thus we have dened an increasing ltration by subcoalgebras 
of any coalgebra C. This ltration is called the coradical ltration , and 
the term C0 is called the coradical of C. 
The linear algebra denition of the coradic al ltration is as fol
lows. One says that a coalgebra is simple if it does not have nontrivial 
subcoalgebras, i.e. if it is nite dimensional, and its dual is a simple 
(i.e., matrix) algebra . Then C0 is the sum of all simple subcoalgebras 
of C. The coalgebras Cn+1 for n  1 are then dened inductiv ely to 
be the spaces of those x  C for which 
(x)  Cn  C + C  C0. 
Exercise 1.29.2. (i) Supp ose that C is a nite dimensional coalgebra, 
and I is the Jacob son radical of C. Show that Cn= In+1 . This 
justies the term coradical ltration. 
(ii) Show that the copro duct respects the coradical ltration, i.e. 
(Cn)  in 
=0 Ci  Cni. 
(iii) Show that C0 is the direct sum of simple subcoalgebras of C. 
In particular, grouplik e elemen ts of any coalgebra C are linearly inde
penden t.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>61 
Hint. Simple subcoalgebras of C corresp ond to nite dimensional 
irrreducible represen tations of C. 
Denote by gr(C) the associated graded coalgebra of a coalgebra C 
with respect to the coradical ltration. Then gr(C) is a Z+-graded 
coalgebra. It is easy to see from Exercise 1.29.2(i) that the coradical 
 ltration of gr(C) is induce d by its grading. A graded coalgebra C 
with this property is said to be coradically graded, and a coalgebra C 
 such that gr(C)= C is called a lifting of C. 
Denition 1.29.3. A coalgebra C is said to be cosemisimple if C is a 
direct sum of simple subcoalgebras. 
Clearly , C is cosemisimple if and only if C  como d is a semisimp le 
category . 
Prop osition 1.29.4. (i) A category C is semisimple if and only if 
C0 = C1. 
(ii) A coalgebr a C is cosemisimple if and only if C0 = C1. 
Proof. (ii) is a special case of (i), and (i) is clear, since the condition 
means that Ext1(X, Y ) = 0 for any simple X, Y , which implies (by 
the long exact sequence of cohomology) that Ext1(X, Y ) = 0 for all 
X, Y C.  
Corollary 1.29.5. (The Taft-Wilson theorem) If C is a pointe d coal
gebra, then C0 is spanne d by (line arly indep endent) grouplike elements 
g, and C1/C0 = h,gPrimh,g(C)/k(h  g). In particular, any non
cosemisimple pointe d coalgebr a contains nontrivial skew-primitive ele
ments. 
Proof. The rst statemen t is clear (the linear indep endence follows from 
Exercise 1.29.2(iii). Also, it is clear that any skew-primitiv e elemen t 
is contained in C1. Now, if x  C1, then x is a matrix elemen t of a 
C-como dule of Loewy length  2, so it is a sum of matrix elemen ts 2
dimensional como dules, i.e. of grouplik e and skew-primitiv e elemen ts. 
It remains to show that the sum Primh,g(C)/k(h  g)  C/C0 h,g 
is direct. For this, it suces to consider the case when C is nite 
dimensional. Passing to the dual algebra A = C, we see that the 
statemen t is equiv alent to the claim that I/I2 (where I is the radical 
of A) is isomorphic (in a natura l way) to g,hExt1(g, h). 
Let pg be a complete system of orthogonal idemp otents in A/I2, such 
that h(pg)= hg. Dene a pairing I/I2  Ext1(g, h)  k which sends 
a   to the upper right entry of the 2-by-2 matrix by which a acts 
in the extension of g by h dened by . It is easy to see that this</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>63 
Now let G be any group, and V, W be two nite dimensional irre
ducible represen tations of G. Let GV ,GW be the Zariski closures of 
the images of G in GL(V ) and GL(W ), respectively. Then by Lemma 
1.30.2 GV ,GW are reductiv e. Let GVW be the Zariski closure of the 
image of G in GV  GW . Let U be the unipotent radical of GVW . Let 
pV : GVW GV , pW : GVW GW be the projections. Since pV is  
surjectiv e, pV (U) is a normal unipotent subgroup of GV , so pV (U) = 1. 
Similarly , pW (U)=1. So U = 1, and GVW is reductiv e. 
Let G
VW be the closure of the image of G in GL(V  W ). Then 
G
VW is a quotien t of GVW , so it is also reductiv e. Since chark = 0, 
this implies that the representation V  W is completely reducible as 
a represen tation of G
VW , hence of G. 
This proves Chev alleys theorem for groups. The proof for Lie alge
bras is similar.  
1.31. Chev alley property. 
Denition 1.31.1. A tensor category C is said to have Cheval ley prop
erty if the category C0 of semisimple objects of C is a tensor subcategory . 
Thus, Chev alley theorem says that the category of nite dimensional 
represen tations of any group or Lie algebr a over a eld of characteristic 
zero has Chev alley property. 
Prop osition 1.31.2. A pointe d tensor category has Cheval ley prop
erty. 
Proof. Obvious.  
Prop osition 1.31.3. In a tensor category with Cheval ley property, 
(1.31.1) Lw(X  Y )  Lw(X) + Lw(Y )  1. 
Thus Ci Cj Ci+j . 
Proof. Let X(i), 0  i  m, Y (j), 0  j  n, be the successiv e 
quotien ts of the coradical ltration s of X, Y . Then Z := X  Y has 
a ltration with successiv e quotien ts Z(r)= i+j=rX(i)  Y (j), 0  
rm + n. Because of the Chev alley property, these quotien ts are 
semisimple. This implies the statemen t.  
Remark 1.31.4. It is clear that the converse to Prop osition 1.31.3 
holds as well: equation (1.31.3) (for simple X and Y ) implies the 
Chev alley property. 
Corollary 1.31.5. In a pointe d Hopf algebr a H, the coradical ltration 
is a Hopf algebr a ltration, i.e. HiHj  Hi+j and S(Hi)= Hi, so gr(H ) 
is a Hopf algebr a.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>62 
pairing descends to a pairing B : ph(I/I2)pg  Ext1(g, h)  k. If the 
extension  is nontrivial, the upper right entry cannot be zero, so B is 
right-nondegenera te. Simil arly, if a belongs to the left kernel of B, then 
a acts by zero in any A-mo dule of Loewy length 2, so a = 0. Thus, B 
is left-nondegenerate. This implies the required isomorphism.  
Prop osition 1.29.6. If C, D are coalgebr as, and f : CD is a
coalgebr a homomorphism such that f|C1 is injective, then f is injective. 
Proof. One may assume that C and D are nite dimensional . Then 
the statemen t can be translated into the following statemen t about 
nite dimensional algebras: if A, B are nite dimensional algebras and 
f : AB is an algebra homomorphism which descends to a surjectiv e 
homomorphism A B/Rad(B )2, then f is surjectiv e. 
To prove this statemen t, let b  B. Let I = Rad(B). We prove by 
induction in n that there exists a  A such that b  f(a)  In . The 
base of induction is clear, so we only need to do the step of induction. 
So assume b  In . We may assum e that b = b1...bn, bi  I, and let 
ai  A be such that f(ai)= bi modulo I2 . Let a = a1...an. Then 
b  f(a)  In+1, as desired.  
Corollary 1.29.7. If H is a Hopf algebr a over a eld of characteristic 
zero, then the natur al map  : U(Prim(H)) H is injective.  
Proof. By Prop osition 1.29.6, it suces to check the injectivit y of  in 
degree 1 of the coradical ltration. Thus, it is enough to check that 
 is injectiv e on primitiv e elemen ts of U(Prim(H)). But by Exercise 
1.24.4, all of them lie in Prim(H ), as desired.  
1.30. Chev alleys theorem. 
Theorem 1.30.1. (Cheval ley) Let k be a eld of characteristic zero. 
Then the tensor product of two simple nite dimensional representa
tions of any group or Lie algebr a over k is semisimple. 
Proof. Let V be a nite dimensional vector space over a eld k (of any 
characteristic), and G  GL(V ) be a Zariski closed subgroup. 
Lemma 1.30.2. If V is a completely reducible representation of G, 
then G is reductive. 
Proof. Let V be a nonzero rational represen tation of an ane algebraic 
group G. Let U be the unipotent radical of G. Let V U  V be the space 
of invarian ts. Since U is unipotent, V U = 0. So if V is irreducible, then 
V U = V , i.e., U acts trivially . Thus, U acts trivially on any completely 
reducible represen tation of G. So if V is completely reducible and 
G  GL(V ), then G is reductiv e.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>57 
Then V has a basis v0,v1 such that
(v0)= v0  h, (v1)= v1  x + v0  g.
The condition that this is a comodule yields that x is a skew-primitiv e 
elemen t of type (h, g). So any extension denes a skew-primitiv e el
emen t and vice versa. Also, we can change the basis by v0 v0, 
v1 v1 + v0, which modies x by adding a trivial skew-primitiv e 
elemen t. This implies the result.  
Example 1.27.2. The category C of nite dimensional como dules over 
uq (sl2) is an example of a nite tensor category in which there are 
objects V such that V  is not isomorphic to V . Namely , in this 
category , the functor V  V  is dened by the squared antipode 
S2 , which is conjugation by K: S2(x)= KxK1 . Now, we have 
Ext1(K, 1) = Y = E, F K, a 2-dimensional space. The set of iso
morphism classes of nontrivial extensions of K by 1 is therefore the 
projectiv e line PY . The operator of conjugation by K acts on Y with 
eigen values q2,q2, hence nontrivially on PY . Thus for a generic ex
tension V , the object V  is not isomorphic to V . 
However, note that some power of the functor  on C is isomorphic 
(in fact, monoidally) to the identity functo r (namely , this power is the 
order of q). We will later show that this property holds in any nite 
tensor category . 
Note also that in the category C, V  = V if V is simple. This clearly 
has to be the case in any tensor category where all simple objects 
are invertible. We will also show (see Prop osition 1.41.1 below) that 
this is the case in any semisimple tensor categor y. An example of a 
tensor category in which V  is not always isomorphic to V even for 
simple V is the category of nite dimen sional represen tations of the 
the Yangian H = Y (g) of a simple complex Lie algebra g, see [CP, 
12.1]. Namely , for any nite dimen sional represen tation V of H and 
any complex number z one can dene the shifted represen tation V (z) 
(such that V (0) = V ). Then V V (2h), where h is the dual = 
Coxeter number of g, see [CP, p.384]. If V is a non-trivial irreducible 
nite dimensional represen tation then V (z)= V for z = 0. Thus, 
= V . Moreo ver, we see that the functor  has innite order even 
when restricted to simple objects of C. 
However, the represen tation category of the Yangian is innite, and 
the answ er to the following question is unkno wn to us. V  
Question 1.27.3. Does there exist a nite tensor category , in which 
there is a simple object V such that V  is not isomorphic to V ? (The 
answ er is unkno wn to the authors).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>56 
	The q-analo g of the factorial is 
n
[n]q !=  
[l]q =(q  q1)  (qn  qn) . (q  q1)n 
l=1 
Denition 1.26.2. The quantum group Uq(g) is generat ed by elemen ts 
Ei, Fi and invertible elemen ts Ki, with dening relations 
KiKj = Kj Ki,KiEj Ki1 = q aij Ej ,KiFj Ki1 = qaij Fj , 
Kdi  Kdi 
[Ei, Fj ]= iji i , and the q-Serre relations: qdi  qdi 
1aij
(1.26.1)  
[l]q![1(

a1)
ijl 
 l]q! Ei 1aij lEj Eil =0,i =j 
l=0 i i 
and 
(1.26.2) 1aij
[l]q![1(

a1)
ijl 
 l]q! Fi 1aij lFj Fl
i =0,i =j. 
l=0 i i 
More generall y, the same denition can be made for any symmetriz
able Kac-Mo ody algebra g. 
Theorem 1.26.3. (see e.g. [CP]) Ther e exists a unique Hopf algebr a 
structur e on Uq (g), given by 
	(Ki)= Ki  Ki; 
	(Ei)= Ei  Ki +1  Ei;
(Fi)= Fi  1+ Ki1  Fi.
  
Remark 1.26.4. Similarly to the case of sl2, in the limit q 1, these 
relations degenerate into the relations for U(g), so Uq(g) should be 
viewed as a Hopf algebra deformation of the enveloping algebra U(g). 
1.27. Categorical meaning of skew-primitiv e elemen ts. We have 
seen that many interesting Hopf algebras contain nontrivial skew-primitiv e 
elemen ts. In fact, the notion of a skew-primitiv e elemen t has a cate
gorical meaning. Namely , we have the following proposition. 
Prop osition 1.27.1. Let g, h be grouplike elements of a coalgebr a 
C, and Primh,g(C) be the space of skew-primitive elements of type 
h, g. Then the space Primh,g(H)/k(h  g) is natur ally isomorphic to 
Ext1(g, h), wher e g, h are regarded as 1-dimensional right C-comodules. 
Proof. Let V be a 2-dim ensional H-como dule, such that we have an 
exact sequence 
0 hV g 0.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>58 
Theorem 1.27.4. Assume that k has characteristic 0. Let C be a nite 
ring category over k with simple object 1. Then Ext1(1, 1)=0. 
Proof. Assume the contrary, and suppose that V is a nontrivial exten
sion of 1 by itself. Let P be the projectiv e cover of 1. Then Hom(P, V ) 
is a 2-dimension al space, with a ltration induced by the ltration on 
V , and both quotien ts naturally isomorphic to E := Hom(P, 1). Let 
v0,v1 be a basis of Hom(P, V ) compatible to the ltrati on, i.e. v0 spans 
the 1-dimensional subspa ce dened by the ltratio n. Let A = End(P ) 
(this is a nite dimensional algebra) . Let  : Ak be the character 
dened by the (right) action of A on E. Then the matrix of a  A in 
the basis v0,v1 has the form 
(a) 1(a)(1.27.1) [a]1 = 0 (a) 
where 1  A is nonzero. Since a  [a]1 is a homomorphism, 1 is a 
deriv ation: 1(xy)= 1(x)(y )+ (x) 1(y). 
Now consider the represen tation V  V . Using the exactness of 
tensor products, we see that the space Hom(P, V V ) is 4-dimension al, 
and has a 3-step ltration, with successiv e quotients E, E  E, E, and 
basis v00; v01,v10; v11, consisten t with this ltration. The matrix of 
a  End(P ) in this basis is 
  
(1.27.2) [a]2 = 
(a) 1(a) 1(a) 2(a) 
0 (a) 0 1(a) 
0 0 (a) 1(a) 
0 0 0 (a) 
Since a [a]2 is a homomorph ism, we nd  
2(ab)= (a) 2(b)+ 2(a)(b) +21(a) 1(b). 
We can now proceed further (i.e. consider V V V etc.) and dene for 
every positiv e n, a linear function n  A which satises the equation 
n
n(ab)= jj (a)nj (b), 
j=0 n
where 0 . by s(a)= m(a)s=
m0 
pairwise distinct homomorph isms. Thus for any s  k, we can dene s : Ak((t))
mtm/m!, and we nd that s is a family of 
nite dimensional algebra. We are done.
This is a contradiction, as A is a 
Corollary 1.27.5. If a nite ring category C over a eld of charac
teristic zero has a unique simple object 1, then C is equivalent to the 
category Vec.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>59 
Corollary 1.27.6. A nite dimensional bialgebr a H over a eld of 
characteristic zero cannot contain nonzer o primitive elements. 
Proof. Apply Theore m 1.27.4 to the category H  como d and use 
Prop osition 1.27.1.  
Remark 1.27.7. Here is a linear algebra proof of this corollary . Let 
x be a nonzero primitiv e elemen t of H. Then we have a family of 
grouplik e elemen ts estx  H((t)), s  k, i.e., an innite collection of 
characters of H((t)), which is impossible, as H is nite dimension al. 
Corollary 1.27.8. If H is a nite dimensional comm utativ e Hopf 
algebr a over an algebr aically close d eld k of characteristic 0, then 
H = Fun(G, k) for a unique nite group G. 
Proof. Let G = Spec(H ) (a nite group scheme), and x  T1G = 
(m/m2) where m is the k ernel of the counit. Then x is a linear function 
on m. Extend it to H by setting x(1) = 0. Then x s a deriv ation: 
x(fg)= x(f)g(1) + f(1)x(g ). 
This implies that x is a primitiv e element in H. So by Corollary 
1.27.6, x = 0. this implies that G is reduced at the point 1. By using 
translations, we see that G is reduced at all other points. So G is a 
nite group, and we are done.  
Remark 1.27.9. Theorem 1.27.4 and all its corollaries fail in char
acteristic p&gt; 0. A counterexample is provided by the Hopf algebra 
k[x]/(xp), where x is a primitiv e elemen t. 
1.28. Pointed tensor categories and pointed Hopf algebras. 
Denition 1.28.1. A coalgebra C is pointe d if its category of right co
modules is pointed, i.e., if any simple right C-como dule is 1-dimensional. 
Remark 1.28.2. A nite dimensional coalgebra C is pointed if and 
only if the algebra C is basic, i.e., the quotien t C/Rad(C) of C by 
its radical is comm utativ e. In this case, simple C-como dules are points 
of Specm(H/Rad(H)), which justies the term pointed. 
Denition 1.28.3. A tensor category C is pointed if every simple 
object of C is invertible. 
Thus, the category of right como dules over a Hopf algebra H is 
pointed if and only if H is pointed. 
Example 1.28.4. The category Vec is a pointed category . If G isG 
a p-group and k has character istic p, then Repk(G) is pointed. Any 
cocomm utativ e Hopf algebra, the Taft and Nichols Hopf algebras, as 
well as the quan tum groups Uq (g) are pointed Hopf algebras.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>64 
In this situation, the Hopf algebra H is said to be a lifting of the 
coradically graded Hopf algebra gr(H ). 
Example 1.31.6. The Taft algebra and the Nichols algebras are corad
ically graded. The associated graded Hopf algebra of Uq (g) is the Hopf 
algebra dened by the same relations as Uq (g), except that the commu
tation relation between Ei and Fj is replaced with the condition that Ei 
and Fj commute (for all i, j). The same applies to the small quantum 
group uq (sl2). 
Exercise 1.31.7. Let k be a eld of characteristic p, and G a nite 
group. Show that the category Repk(G) has Chevalley property if and 
only if G has a normal p-Sylow subgroup.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>55 
1.25. The Quan tum Group Uq (sl2). Let us consider the Lie algebra 
sl2. Recall that there is a basis h, e, f  sl2 such that [h, e]=2e, [h, f]= 
2f, [e, f]= h. This motivates the following denition . 
Denition 1.25.1. Let q  k, q =1. The quantum group U(sl2) is q
generated by eleme nts E, F and an invertible elemen t K with dening 
relations 
KEK1 = q 2E,KFK1 = q2F, [E, F]= K  K1 
. q  q1 
Theorem 1.25.2. Ther e exists a unique Hopf algebr a structur e on 
Uq (sl2), given by 
 (K )= K  K (thus K is a grouplike element); 
 (E) = E  K +1  E; 
 (F) = F  1+ K1  F (thus E, F are skew-primitive ele
ments). 
Exercise 1.25.3. Prove Theorem 1.25.2. 
Remark 1.25.4. Heuristically , K = qh, and thus 
K  K1 
lim = h. 
q1q  q1 
So in the limit q 1, the relations of Uq (sl2) degenerate into the 
relations of U(sl2), and thus Uq (sl2) should be viewed as a Hopf algebra 
deformation of the enveloping algebra U(sl2). In fact, one can make 
this heuristic idea into a precise statemen t, see e.g. [K]. 
If q is a root of unity, one can also dene a nite dimensional version 
of Uq (sl2). Namely , assume that the order of q is an odd number . Let 
uq (sl2) be the quotien t of Uq (sl2) by the additional relations 
E = F = K  1=0. 
Then it is easy to show that uq (sl2) is a Hopf algebra (with the co
product inherited from Uq (sl2)). This Hopf algebra is called the smal l 
quantum group attac hed to sl2. 
1.26. The quan tum group Uq (g). The exam ple of the previous sub
section can be generalized to the case of any simple Lie algebra . Namely , 
let g be a simple Lie algebra of rank r, and let A =(aij ) be its Cartan 
matrix. Recall that there exist unique relativ ely prime positiv e integers 
di,i =1,...r such that diaij = dj aji. Let q  k, q =1. 
Denition 1.26.1.  The q-analo g of n is 
nq qn 
[n]q = . q  q1</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Main Theorem
Categories of module functors
Dual categories</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>124 
Proof. Let us consider C as a module category over itself. Consider an 
object A C as an object of this module category . Then by Example 
2.10.8 Hom(A, A)= A  A = B and the statemen t follows from 
Theorem 2.11.2. The case of right modules is completely parallel.  
It follows from the Lemma that any Bbimo dule is of the form 
A  X  A and it is easy to see that can(X )= A  X  A. The 
Theorem is proved.  
Remark 2.14.8. Theorem 2.14.6 categories the classical doub le cen
tralizer theorem for projectiv e modules, which says that if A is a nite 
dimensional algebra and P is a projectiv e A-mo dule then the central
izer of EndA(P ) in P is A. 
Corollary 2.14.9. Assume that C is a nite tensor (not only multi-
tensor) category. Then an exact module category M over C is inde
composable over C .M
Proof. This is an immedia te consequence of Theorem 2.14.6 and Lemma 
2.14.3.  
Let M be a xed module category over C. For any other module cat
egory M1 over C the category FunC(M1, M) has an obvious structure 
of a module category over C = FunC(M, M).M 
Lemma 2.14.10. The module category FunC (M1, M) over C is ex-M
act. 
Proof. Assume that M = ModC(A) and M1 = ModC (A1). Identify 
C with the category of Abimo dules and FunC(M1, M) with the M
category of (A1 A)bimo dules. Any projectiv e object of Bimo d(A) is 
a direct summand of an object of the form AP A for some projectiv e 
P C. Let M bean (A1  A)bimo dule, then M A A  P  A = 
M  P  A. Now HomA1A(M  P  A, )= HomA1 (M  P, ) (here 
HomA1A is the Hom in the category of (A1 A)bimo dules and HomA1 
is the Hom in the category of left A1modules) and it is enough to 
check that M  P is a projectiv e left A1module. This is equiv alent 
to (M  P ) being injectiv e (since N  N is an equiv alence of the 
category of left Amodules to the category of right Amodules). But 
(M  P ) = P   M and results follows from projectivit y of P  and 
Lemma 2.7.3.  
The proof of the following Theorem is similar to the proof of Theorem 
2.14.6 and is left to the reader.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>121 
It is easy to see that the module functors with module functor mor
phisms introduced above form a category called the category of mod
ule functors. This category is very dicult to manage (consider the 
case = Vec !) and we are going to consider a subcategory . Let C
F unC (M1, M2) denote the full subcategory of the category of module 
functors consisting of right exact module functors (whic h are not nec
essarily left exact). First of all this category can be describ ed in down 
to earth terms: 
Prop osition 2.12.2. Assume that M1  ModC (A) and M2  ModC (B) 
for some algebr as A, B C. The category F unC (M1, M2) is equiva
lent to the category of A  Bbimo dules via the functor which sends a 
bimo dule M to the functor A M. 
Proof. The proof repeats the standard proof from ring theory in the 
categorical setting.  
Thus we have the following 
Corollary 2.12.3. The category F unC(M1, M2) of right exact module 
functors from M1 to M2 is abelian. 
Proof. Exercise.  
In a similar way one can show that the category of left exact module 
functors is abelian (using Hom over A instead of tensor product over 
A). 
We would like now to construct new tensor categories in the fol
lowing way: take a module category M and consider the category 
F unC (M, M) with comp osition of functors as a tensor product. 
Exercise 2.12.4. The category F unC (M, M) has a natural structure 
of monoidal category. 
But in general the category F unC (M, M) is not rigid (consider the 
case C = Vec!). Thus to get a good theory (and examples of new tensor 
categories), we restrict ourselv es to the case of exact module categories. 
We will see that in this case we can say much more about the categories 
F unC (M, M) than in general. 
2.13. Module functors between exact module categories. Let 
M1 and M2 be two exact module categories over C. Note that the 
category F unC(M1, M2) coincides with the category of the additiv e 
module functors from M1 to M2 by Prop osition 2.7.8. 
Exercise 2.13.1. Any object of F unC (M1, M2) is of nite length.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>119 
2.11. Main Theorem. 
Exercise 2.11.1. Show that for any M M the object Hom(M, M) 
with the multiplication dened above is an algebra (in particula r, dene 
the unit morphism! ). 
Theorem 2.11.2. Let M be a module category over C, and assume 
that M M satises two conditions: 
1. The functor Hom(M, ) is right exact (note that it is automatic ally 
left exact). 
2. For any N M there exists X C and a surje ction X MN.
Let A = Hom(M, M). Then the functor F := Hom(M, ): M 
ModC (A) is an equivalenc e of module categories. 
Proof. We will proceed in steps: 
(1) The map F : Hom(N1,N2) HomA(F (N1),F (N2)) is an iso 
morphism for any N2 M and N1 of the form X  M, X C. 
Indeed, F (N1) = Hom(M, X  M)= X  A and the statemen t 
follows from the calculation: 
HomA(F (N1),F (N2)) = HomA(X  A, F (N2)) = Hom(X, F (N2)) = 
= Hom(X, Hom (M, N2)) = Hom(X  M, N2)= Hom(N 1,N2). 
(2) The map F : Hom(N1,N2) HomA(F (N1),F (N2)) is an iso 
morphism for any N1,N2 M. 
By condition 2, there exist objects X, Y C and an exact sequence 
Y  MX  MN1  0.  
Since F is exact, the sequence 
F (Y  M) F (X  M) F (N1)0   
is exact. Since Hom is left exact, the rows in the comm utativ e diagram 
0 
Hom(N 1,N2) 
F 
Hom(X  M, N2) 
F 
Hom(Y  M, N2) 
F 
0 Hom(F (N1),F (N2)) Hom(F (X  M),F (N2)) Hom(F (Y  M),F (N2))    
are exact. Since by step (1) the second and third vertical arrows are 
isomorphisms, so is the rst one. 
(3) The functor F is surjec tive on isomorphism classes of objects of 
ModC (A). 
We know (see Exercise 2.9.15) that for any object L  ModC(A) 
there exists an exact sequence 
f Y  A  X  A  L  0</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>125 
Theorem 2.14.11. Let M be an exact module category over C. The 
 FunC(M1, M) and M2  Fun (M2, M) mutu
ally inverse bijections of the sets of equivalenc e classes of exact module 
Mmaps M1 C are
categories over C and over C .M
Following Muger, [Mu], we will say that the categories C and (C )op 
M
are weakly Morita equivalent. 
Example 2.14.12. Let C be a nite multitensor category. Then C is 
an exact module category over C  Cop. 
Denition 2.14.13. The corresp onding dual category Z(C) := CC
Cop 
is called the Drinfeld center of C. 
This notion categories the notion of the center of a ring, since the 
center of a ring A is the ring of endomorphisms of A as an A-bimo dule. 
Let M be an exact module category over C. For X, Y M we have 
two notions of internal Hom  with values in C and with values in 
respectively. The following simple 
MC , denoted by Hom and HomM C
consequence of calculations in Examples 2.10.8 and 2.14.5 is very useful. C
Prop osition 2.14.14. (Basic identity) Let X, Y, Z M. Ther e is 
a canonic al isomorphism 
HomC (X, Y )  Z  Hom
MC(Z, X)  Y. 
Proof. By Theorem 2.14.6 it is enough to nd a canonical isomorphism
HomC (Z, X)  Y  Hom
MC(X, Y )  Z. 
This isomorphism is constructed as follows. Choose an algebra A such 
that M = ModC (A). By Example 2.10.8 the LHS is (X A Z)  Y = 
(Z A X)  Y =(Z A X)  Y . On the other hand by Example 
2.14.5 the RHS is Z A (X  Y ). Thus the associativit y isomorphism 
gives a canonica l isomorphism of the LHS and RHS. Observ e that the 
isomorphism inverse to the one we constructed is the image of the 
identity under the homomorphism 
Hom(Y, Y ) Hom(Hom

C
M (X, Y )  X, Y )

Hom(Hom
 
MC(X, Y )  HomC (Z, X)  Z, Y )  
Hom(Hom (Z, X)  HomC C
M (X, Y )  Z, Y ) 
Hom(Hom
 (X, Y )  Z, Hom (Z, X)  Y )
C
MC 
and thus does not depend on the choice of A.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>123 
Thus, the category C is a nite multitensor category; in particu lar M
if M is indecomp osable then C is nite tensor category . Note that M
by the denition M is a module category over C .M
Lemma 2.14.4. The module category M over C is exact. M 

M Proof. Let A C be an algebra such that M = ModC(A). Thus the 
category C is identied with the category Bimo d(A)op of Abimo dules M
with opposite tensor product (because Abimo dules act naturally on 
ModC (A) from the right). Any projectiv e object in the category of 
Abimo dules is a direct summand of the object of the form A  P  A 
for some projectiv e P C. Now for any M  ModC (A) one has that 
M A A  P  A =(M  P )  A is projective by exactness of the 
category ModC (A). The Lemma is proved.  
Example 2.14.5. It is instructiv e to consider the internal Hom for 
the category ModC(A) considered as a module category over C = M
Bimo d(A). We leave to the reader to check that Hom (M, N) =
C
MN (therighthandsidehasanobvious structure of Abimo dule).  
(A,A)= AA isanalgebra inthecategory  
M In particular B = HomC
of Abimo dules. Thus B is an algebra in the catego ry C and it is easy 
to see from denitions that the algebra structure on B = A  A 
comes from the evaluation morphism ev : A  A  1. Moreover, 
the coevaluatio n morphism induces an embedding of algebras A 
A  A  A  A  A = B and the Abimo dule structure of B comes 
from the left and right multiplication by A. 
Thus for any exact module category M over C the category (C ) 
MM
is well dened. There is an obvious tensor functor can : C (C ) .MM
Theorem 2.14.6. The functor can : C (C ) is an equivalenc e of MM
categories. 
Proof. Let A be an algebra such that M = ModC(A). The cate
gory C is identied with the category Bimo d(A)op. The categ ory 
(C )M 
MM is identied with the category of Bbimo dules in the category 
of Abimo dules (here B is the same as in Example 2.14.5 and is con
sidered as an algebra in the category of Amodules). But this latter 
category is tautol ogically identied with the category of Bbimo dules 
(here B is an algebra in the categ ory C) since for any Bmodule one 
reconstructs the Amodule structure via the embedding AB from
Example 2.14.5. We are going to use the following 
Lemma 2.14.7. Any left Bmodule is of the form A  X for some 
X C with the obvious structur e of an Amodule. Similarly, any right 
Bmodule is of the form X  A.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>120 
for some X, Y C. Let f  Hom(Y  M, X  M) be the preimage of 
f under the isomor phism 
Hom(Y M, XM) = HomA(Y A, XA) = HomA(F (Y M),F (XM)) 
and let N M be the cokernel of f. It is clear that F (N)= L. 
We proved that F is an equiv alence of categories and proved the 
Theorem. 
Remark 2.11.3. This Theorem is a special case of Barr-Bec k Theorem 
in category theory , see [ML]. We leave it to the interested reader to 
 deduce Theorem 2.11.2 from Barr-Bec k Theorem. 
We have two situations wher e condition 1 of Theorem 2.11.2 is sat
ised: 
1. M is an arbitrary module category over C and M M is projec
tive. 
2. M is an exact module category and M M is arbitrary . 
Exercise 2.11.4. Chec k that in both of these cases Hom (M, ) is exact 
(Hint: in the rst case rst prove that Hom(M, N) is a projectiv e object 
of C for any N M). 
Exercise 2.11.5. Show that in both of these cases condition 2 is equiv
alent to the fact that [M] generates Gr(M) as Z+module over Gr(C). 
Thus we have proved 
Theorem 2.11.6. (i) Let M be a nite module category over C. Then 
there exists an algebra A C and a module equivalenc e M ModC (A). 
(ii) Let M be an exact module category over C and let M M be 
an object such that [M] gener ates Gr(M) as Z+module over Gr(C). 
Then ther e is a mo dule e quivalenc e M ModC (A) wher e A = Hom(M, M). 
2.12. Categories of module functors. Let M1, M2 be two module 
categories over a multitensor category C, and let (F, s), (G, t) be two 
module functors M1 M2. 
Denition 2.12.1. A module functo r morphism from (F, s) to (G, t) 
is a natural transformation a from F to G such that the following 
diagram comm utes for any X C, M M: 
sF (X  M)  X  F (M) 
(2.12.1)
 a ida 
tG(X  M)  X  G(M )</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>126 
Remark 2.14.15 . Following [Mu] one can constru ct from M a 2
category with 2 objects A, B such that End(A) =(C )op= C, End(B)  ,M
Hom(A, B) M, and Hom(B, A) F unC (M, C). In this language = = 
Prop osition 2.14.14 expresses the associativit y of the comp osition of 
Homs. 
References 
[AS] N. Andruskiewitsc h, H.-J. Schneider, Pointed Hopf algebras, in New direc
tions in Hopf algebras, MSRI series Cambridge Univ. Press; 168 (2002). 
[BaKi] B. Bakalov, A. Kirillo v Jr., Lectures on Tensor categories and modular func
tors, AMS, Providence, (2001). 
[Bi] J. Bichon, T he represen tation category of the quan tum group of a non-
degenerate bilinear form, Comm. Algebra 31 (10) (2003). 
[Br] K. S. Brown Cohomolo gy of groups, Graduate Texts in Mathematics, 87. 
Springer-V erlag, New York, (1994). 
[CFS] Carter, J. S.; Flath, D. E.; and Saito, M. The Classical and Quan tum 6j
Symbols. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1995. 
[CP] V. Chari, A. Pressley , A guide to quantum groups, Cambridge University 
Press, Cambridge, 1995. 
[D] P. Deligne, Categories tannakiennes, in : The Grothendie ck Festschrift , Vol. II, 
Progr. Math., 87, Birkhuser, Boston, MA, 1990, 111-195. 
[Dr1] V. Drinfeld, Quasi-Hopf algebras, Leningrad Math J. 1 (1989), 1419-1457. 
[ENO1] P. Etingof, D. Niksh ych, V. Ostrik, On fusion categories , Annals of Math
ematics 162 (2005), 581-642. 
[ENO2] P. Etingof, D. Niksh ych, V. Ostrik, An analo gue of Radfor ds S4 formula
for nite tensor categories , Int. Math. Res. Not., 2004, no. 54, 2915-2933.
[EO] P. Etingof, V. Ostrik, Finite tensor categories, Mosco w Math. Journal 4
(2004), 627-654. 
[F]	P. Freyd Abelian categories. An introduction to the theory of functors , Harp er 
&amp; Row, New York, Evanston, and London, (1964). 
[Ga] F. R. Gantmac her, The theory of matric es, AMS Chelse a Publishing, Provi
dence, (1998). 
[JS] A. Joyal, R. Street, Braided tensor categories, Adv. Math., 102, 20-78 (1993). 
[K] Ch. Kassel, Quantum groups, Graduate Texts in Mathematics, 155, Springer-
Verlag, (1995). 
[Kup2] G. Kuperberg,	 Finite, conne cted semisimple, rigid tensor categories are 
linear, Math. Res. Lett., 10 (2003), no. 4, 411421. 
[L]	M. Lorenz, Representations of nite-dimensional Hopf algebras, J. Algebr a 188 
(1997), no. 2, 476-505. 
[ML] S. MacLane, Cate gories for the working mathematician, Graduate texts in 
mathematics, 5, 2nd edition, Springer-V erlag (1998). 
[Mo] S. Montgomery , Hopf algebras and their action on rings, Conference Series in 
Math.,V ol. 82, Amer. Math . Soc., Providence, RI, 1993. 
[Mu] M. Muger, From subfactors to categories and topology I. Frobenius algebr as in 
and Morita equivalenc e of tensor categories, J. Pure Appl. Algebra 180 (2003), 
81-157. 
[O2] V. Ostrik, Fusion categories of rank 2, Math. Res. Lett. 10 (2003), 177-183.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>122 
Lemma 2.13.2. Let M1, M2, M3 be exact module categories over 
C. The bifunctor of composition F unC(M2, M3)  F unC(M1, M2) 
F unC (M1, M3) is biexact.
Proof. This is an immediate consequence of Prop osition 2.7.8. 
Another immediate consequence of Prop osition 2.7.8 is the following: 
Lemma 2.13.3. Let M1, M2 be exact module categories over C. Any 
functor F  F unC (M1, M2) has both right and left adjoint. 
We also have the following immediate 
Corollary 2.13.4. Let M1, M2 be exact module categories over C. 
Any functor F  F unC (M1, M2) maps projective objects to projectives. 
In view of Example 2.6.6 this Corollary is a generalization of Theo
rem 1.49.3 (but this does not give a new proof of Theorem 1.49.3). 
Prop osition 2.13.5. The category F unC (M1, M2) is nite. 
Proof. We are going to use Theorem 2.11.2. Thus M1 = ModC (A1) 
and M2 = ModC (A2) for some algebras A1,A2 C. It is easy to 
see that the category F unC(M1, M2) is equiv alent to the category of 
(A1,A2)bimo dules. But this category clearly has enough projectiv e 
objects: for any projectiv e P C the bimodule A1P A2 is projectiv e. 
2.14. Dual categories. Observ e that the adjoint to a module func
tor has itself a natural structure of a module functor (we leave it to 
the reader to dene this). In particular, it follows that the category 
F unC (M, M) is a rigid monoidal catego ry. 
Denition 2.14.1. We denote this category as C and call it the dualM
category to C with respect to M. 
By Prop osition 2.13.5, this category is nite. 
Remark 2.14.2. This notion is a categorical version of notion of the 
endomorphism ring of a module (i.e., a centralizer algebra), and gives 
many new examples of tensor categories. 
Lemma 2.14.3. The unit object 1 C is a direct sum of projectors M
to subcategories Mi. Each such projector is a simple object. 
Proof. The rst statemen t is clear. For the second statemen t it is 
enough to consider the case when M is indecomp osable. Let F be a 
nonzero module subfunctor of the identity functo r. Then F (X)=0 
for any X = 0. Hence F (X)= X for any simple X M and thus 
F (X)= X 
for any X M since F is exact.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Basics of monoidal categories</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec01/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>6 
This gives rise to functorial isomorphisms l : L1 IdC and r : R1 
IdC . These isomorp hisms are called the unit constr aints or unit iso
morphisms . They provide the categorical counterpart of the unit ax
iom 1X = X1= X of a monoid in the same sense as the associativit y 
isomorphism provides the categorical counterpart of the associativit y 
equation. 
Prop osition 1.2.1. The triangle diagr am 
aX,1,Y(1.2.1) (X  1)  Y X  (1  Y )  
rX IdY IdX lY 
X  Y 
is commutative for all X, Y C. In particular, one has r1 = l1 = . 
Proof. This follows by applying the pentagon axiom for the quadruple 
of objects X, 1, 1,Y . More specically , we have the following diagram: 
(1.2.2) 
((X  1)  1)  Y aX,1,1Id (X  (1  1))  Y   
rX IdId (Id)Id 
(X  1)  Y 
aX1,1,Y aX,1,Y aX,11,Y 
X  (1  Y ) 
rX Id 
(X  1)  (1  Y ) 
aX,1,1Y Id(Id) 
Idl1Y X  ((1  1)  Y ) 
Ida1,1,Y 
X  (1  (1  Y )) 
To prove the proposition, it suces to establish the comm utativit y 
of the bottom left triangle (as any object of C is isomorphic to one of 
the form 1  Y ). Since the outside pentagon is comm utativ e (by the 
pentagon axiom), it suces to establish the comm utativit y of the other 
parts of the pentagon. Now, the two quadrangles are comm utativ e due 
to the functorialit y of the associativit y isomorphisms, the comm utativ
ity of the upper triangle is the denition of r, and the comm utativit y 
of the lower right triangle is the deniti on of l. 
The last statemen t is obtained by setting X = Y = 1 in (1.2.1).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>13 
(also called local systems) on any topological space X. All of these are 
monoidal categories in a natural way. 
Example 1.3.11. The category of tangles. 
Let Sm,n be the disjoin t union of m circles R/Z and n intervals 
[0, 1]. A tangle is a piecewise smooth embedding f : Sm,n  R2  [0, 1] 
such that the boundary maps to the boundary and the interior to the 
interior. We will abuse the terminology by also using the term tangle 
for the image of f. 
Let x, y, z be the Cartesian coordin ates on R2  [0, 1]. Any tangle 
has inputs (points of the image of f with z = 0) and outputs (points of 
the image of f with z = 1). For any integers p, q  0, let Tp,q be the set 
of all tangles which have p inputs and q outputs, all having a vanishing 
y-coordinate. Let Tp,q be the set of isotop y classes of elemen ts of Tp,q; 
thus, during an isotop y, the inputs and outputs are allowed to move 
(preserving the conditi on y = 0), but cannot meet each other. We can 
dene a canonical comp osition map Tp,q  Tq,r  Tp,r, induced by the 
concatenation of tangles. Namely , if s  Tp,q and t  Tq,r, we pick rep
resen tatives s Tp,q, t  Tq,r such that the inputs of t coincide with the 
outputs of s, concatenate them, perform an appropriate repar ametriza
tion, and rescale z z/2. The obtained tangle represen ts the desired 
comp osition ts. 
We will now dene a monoidal category T called the category of 
tangles (see [K, T, BaKi] for more details). The objects of this cat
egory are nonnegativ e integers, and the morphisms are dened by 
HomT (p, q)= Tp,q, with comp osition as ab ove. The iden tity morphisms 
are the elemen ts idp  Tp,p represen ted by p vertical intervals and no 
circles (in particular, if p = 0, the identity morphism idp is the empt y 
tangle). 
Now let us dene the monoidal structure on the category T . The 
tensor product of objects is dened by mn = m+n. However, we also 
need to dene the tensor product of morphisms. This tensor product 
is induced by union of tangles. Namely , if t1  Tp1,q1 and t2  Tp2,q2 , we 
pick represen tatives t1  Tp1,q1 ,t2  Tp2,q2 in such a way that any point 
of t1 is to the left of any point of t2 (i.e., has a smaller x-coordinate). 
Then t1  t2 is represen ted by the tangle t1  t2. 
We leave it to the reader to check the following: 
1. The product t1  t2 is well dened, and its denition makes  a 
bifunctor. 
2. There is an obvious associativit y isomorphism for , which turns 
T into a monoidal category (with unit object being the empt y tangle).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>9 
This denition is perhaps more traditional than Denition 1.1.1, but 
Denition 1.1.1 is simpler. Beside s, Prop osition 1.2.4 implies that for 
a triple (C, ,a) satisfying a pentagon axiom (whic h should perhaps 
be called a semigroup category, as it categories the notion of a 
semigroup), being a monoidal categor y is a property and not a structure 
(similarly to how it is for semigroups and monoids). 
Furthermore, one can show that the comm utativit y of the triangl es 
implies that in a monoidal category one can safely identify 1  X and 
X  1 with X using the unit isomorphisms, and assume that the unit 
isomorphism are the iden tities (whic h we will usually do from no w on).3 
In a sense, all this means that in constructions with monoidal cat
egories, unit objects and isomorphisms always go for the ride, and 
one need not worry about them especially seriously . For this reason, 
below we will typically take less care dealing with them than we have 
done in this subsection. 
Prop osition 1.2.7. ([SR, 1.3.3.1]) The monoid End(1 ) of endomor
phisms of the unit object of a monoidal category is commutative. 
Proof. The unit isomorphism  : 1  1 1 induces the isomorphism 
 : End(11) End(1 ). It is easy to see that (a1) = (1a)= a 
for any a  End(1 ). Therefore, 
(1.2.9) ab = ((a  1)(1  b)) = ((1  b)(a  1)) = ba, 
for any a, b  End(1 ).  
1.3. First examples of monoidal categories. Monoidal categories 
are ubiquitous. You will see one whichever way you look. Here are 
some examples. 
Example 1.3.1. The category Sets of sets is a monoidal category , 
where the tensor product is the Cartesian product and the unit object 
is a one elemen t set; the structure morphisms a, , l, r are obvious. The 
same holds for the subcategory of nite sets, which will be denoted 
by Sets 4 . This example can be widely generalized: one can take the 
category of sets with some structure, such as groups, topological space s, 
etc. 
Example 1.3.2. Any additiv e category is monoidal, with  being the 
direct sum functor , and 1 being the zero object. 
The remaining examples will be especially importan t below. 
3We will return to this issue later when we discuss MacLanes coherence theorem. 
4Here and below, the absence of a niteness condition condition is indicated by 
the boldface font, while its prese nce is indicated by the Roman font.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>4 
1. Monoid al categories 
1.1. The denition of a monoidal category . A good way of think
ing about category theory (whic h will be especially useful throughout 
these notes) is that category theory is a reneme nt (or categorica
tion) of ordinary algebra. In other words, there exists a dictionary 
between these two subjects, such that usual algebraic structures are 
recovered from the corresp onding categorical structures by passing to 
the set of isomorphism classes of objects. 
For example, the notion of a (small ) category is a categorication of 
the notion of a set. Similarly , abelian categories are a categoric ation 
of abelian groups 1 (whic h justies the termino logy). 
This dictionary goes surprisingly far, and many importan t construc
tions below will come from an attempt to enter into it a categorical 
translation of an algebraic notion. 
In particular, the notion of a monoid al category is the categorication 
of the notion of a monoid. 
Recall that a monoid may be dened as a set C with an associativ e 
multiplication operation (x, y) xy (i.e., a semigroup), with an  
elemen t 1 such that 12 =1andthemaps11: CC are bijections. , 
It is easy to show that in a semigroup, the last condition is equiv alent 
to the usual unit axiom 1 x = x 1= x. 
As usual in category theory , to categorify the denit ion of a monoid, 
we should replace the equalities in the deni tion of a monoid (namely , 
the associativit y equation (xy)z = x(yz) and the equation 12 = 1) 
by isomorphisms satisfying some consistency properties, and the word 
bijection by the word equiv alence (of categories). This leads to 
the following denition. 
Denition 1.1.1. A monoidal category is a quintuple (C, , a, 1,) 
where C is a category ,  : CC C is a bifuncto r called the tensor 
product bifunctor, 
 () is a functorial isomorphism: a :  () 
(1.1.1) aX,Y,Z :(X  Y )  Z X  (Y  Z), X,Y,Z C  
called the associativity constr aint (or associativity isomorphism), 1 C 
is an object of C, and  : 1  11 is an isomorphism, subject to the 
following two axioms. 
1To be more precise, the set of isomorphism classes of objects in a (small) abelian 
category C is a comm utativ e monoid, but one usually extends it to a group by 
considering virtual objects of the form X  Y , X, Y C.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>10 
Example 1.3.3. Let k be any eld. The category k  Vec of all 
kvector spaces is a monoidal category , where  = k, 1 = k, and the 
morphisms a, , l, r are the obvious ones. The same is true about the 
category of nite dime nsional vector spaces over k, denoted by k  Vec. 
We will often drop k from the notation when no confusion is possible. 
More generally , if R is a comm utativ e unital ring, then replac ing k 
by R we can dene monoidal categories R  mod of R-modules and 
R  mod of R-modules of nite type. 
Example 1.3.4. Let G be a group. The category Repk(G) of all 
represen tations of G over k is a monoidal category , with  being the 
tensor product of repre sentations: if for a represen tation V one denotes 
by V the corresp onding map G GL(V ), then  
V W (g) := V (g)  W (g). 
The unit object in this category is the trivial represen tation 1 = k.A 
similar statemen t holds for the category Repk(G) of nite dimensional 
represen tations of G. Again, we will drop the subscript k when no 
confusion is possible. 
Example 1.3.5. Let G be an ane (pro)alge braic group over k. The 
categories Rep(G) of all algebraic represen tations of G over k is a 
monoidal category (similarly to Example 1.3.4). 
Similarly , if g is a Lie algebra over k, then the catego ry of its repre
sentations Rep(g) and the category of its nite dimension al represen
tations Rep(g) are monoidal categories: the tensor product is dened 
by 
V W (a)= V (a)  IdW + IdV  W (a) 
(where Y : g gl(Y ) is the homomorphism associated to a represen 
tation Y of g), and 1 is the 1-dimensional represen tation with the zero 
action of g. 
Example 1.3.6. Let G be a monoid (whic h we will usually take to 
be a group), and let A be an abelian group (with operation written 
multiplicativ ely). Let CG = CG(A) be the category whose objects g 
are labeled by elemen ts of G (so there is only one object in each iso
morphism class), Hom(g1 ,g2 )=  if g1 =g2, and Hom(g,g)= A, 
with the functor  dened by g  h = gh, and the tensor tensor 
product of morphisms dened by a  b = ab. Then CG is a monoidal 
category with the associativit y isomorphism being the identity, and 1 
being the unit elemen t of G. This shows that in a monoidal category , 
X  Y need not be isomorphic to Y  X (indeed, it suces to take a 
non-comm utative mono id G).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>11 
This example has a linear version. Namely , let k be a eld, and 
k  VecG denote the category of G-graded vector spaces over k, i.e. 
vector spaces V with a decomp osition V = gGVg. Morphisms in this 
category are linear operators which preserv e the grading. Dene the 
tensor product on this category by the formula 
(V  W )g = x,yG:xy =gVx  Wy, 
and the unit object 1 by 11 = k and 1g = 0 for g = 1. Then, 
dening a,  in an obvious way, we equip k  VecG with the structure 
of a monoidal category . Similarly one denes the monoidal category 
k  VecG of nite dimen sional G-graded k-vector spaces. 
In the category k  VecG, we have pairwise non-isomorphic objects 
g, g  G, dened by the formula (g)x = k if x = g and (g)x = 
0 otherwise. For these objects, we have g = gh. Thus the  h 
category CG(k) is a (non-full) monoidal subcategory of k VecG. This 
subcategory can be viewed as a basis of VecG (and VecG as the linear 
span of CG), as any object of VecG is isomorphic to a direct sum of 
objects g with nonnegativ e integer multiplicities. 
When no confusion is possible, we will denote the categories kVecG, 
k  VecG simply by VecG, VecG. 
Example 1.3.7. This is really a generalization of Example 1.3.6, whic h 
shows that the associativit y isomorphism is not always the obvious 
one. 
Let G be a group, A an abelian group, and  be a 3-cocycle of G 
with values in A. This means that  : G  G  GA is a function 
satisfying the equatio n 
(1.3.1) 
(g1g2,g3,g4)(g1,g2,g3g4)= (g1,g2,g3)(g1,g2g3,g4)(g2,g3,g4), 
for all g1,g2,g3,g4  G. 
Let us dene the monoidal category C = C (A) as follows. As a GG
category , it is the same as the category CG dened above. The bifunctor 
 and the unit object (1,) in this category is also the same as those 
in CG. The only dierence is in the new associativit y isomorp hism a , 
which is not the obvious one (i.e., the identity) like in CG, but rather 
is dened by the formula 
(1.3.2) a 
g ,h,m = (g, h, m):(g  h)  m g  (h  m), 
where g, h, m  G. 
The fact that C with these structures is indeed a monoidal category G 
follows from the properties of . Namely , the pentagon axiom (1.1.2) 
follows from equation (1.3.1) , and the unit axiom is obvious.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>12 
Similarly , for a eld k, one can dene the category (k)Vec , which G
diers from VecG just by the associativity isomorphism. This is done 
by extending the associativit y isomorphism of C by additivit y to ar-G 
bitrary direct sums of objects g. This category contains a monoidal 
subcategory Vec of nite dimensional G-graded vector spaces with G 
associativit y dened by . 
Remark 1.3.8. It is straigh tforw ard to verify that the unit morphisms 
l, r in Vec are given on 1-dimension al spaces by the formulas G 
lg = (1, 1,g)1Idg,rg = (g, 1, 1)Idg, 
and the triangle axiom says that (g, 1,h)= (g, 1, 1)(1, 1,h). Thus, 
we have lX = rX = Id if and only if 
(1.3.3) (g, 1, 1) = (1, 1,g), 
for any g  G or, equiv alently, 
(1.3.4) (g, 1,h)=1, g,h  G. 
A cocycle satisfying this condition is said to be normalize d. 
Example 1.3.9. Let C be a category . Then the category End(C) of 
all functors from C to itself is a monoidal category , where  is given 
by comp osition of functors. The associativit y isomorphism in this cat
egory is the identity. The unit object is the identity funct or, and the 
structure morphisms are obvious. If C is an abelian category , the same 
is true about the categories of additiv e, left exact, right exact, and 
exact endofunctors of C. 
Example 1.3.10. Let A be an associativ e ring with unit. Then the 
category A  bimo d of bimo dules over A is a monoidal category , with 
tensor product  = A, over A. The unit object in this category is 
the ring A itself (regarded as an A-bimo dule). 
If A is comm utativ e, this category has a full monoidal subcategory 
A  mod, consisting of A-mo dules, regarded as bimo dules in which 
the left and right actions of A coincide. More generally , if X is a 
scheme, one can dene the monoidal category QCoh(X ) of quasico
heren t sheaves on X; if X is ane and A = OX , then QCoh(X )= 
A  mod. 
Similarly , if A is a nite dimensional algebra, we can dene the 
monoidal category Abimo d of nite dimensional A-bimo dules. Other 
similar examples which often arise in geometry are the category Coh(X) 
of coheren t sheaves on a scheme X, its subcategory VB(X ) of vector 
bundles (i.e., locally free coher ent sheaves) on X, and the category 
Loc(X) of locally constan t sheaves of nite dimensional k-vector spaces</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>5 
1. The pentagon axiom. The diagram 
(1.1.2) 
((
W 
  X)  Y )Z 
 aW X,Y,Z aW,X,Y IdZ 
(W  X)  (Y  Z) (W  (X  Y ))  Z 
aW,X,Y Z aW,XY,Z 
W  (X  (Y  Z)) IdW aX,Y,Z W  ((X  Y )  Z) 
is comm utativ e for all objects W, X, Y, Z in C. 
2. The unit axiom. The functors L1 and R1 of left and right 
multiplication by 1 are equiv alences CC.
The pair (1,) is called the unit object of C. 2
We see that the set of isomorphism classes of objects in a small 
monoidal category indeed has a natural structure of a monoid , with 
multiplication  and unit 1. Thus, in the categorical-algebraic dic
tionary , monoidal categories indeed corresp ond to monoids (which ex
plains their name). 
Denition 1.1.2. A monoida l subcategory of a monoidal category 
(C, , a, 1,) is a quintuple (D, , a, 1,), where DC is a subcate
gory closed under the tensor product of objects and morphisms and 
containing 1 and . 
Denition 1.1.3. The opposite monoidal category Cop to C is the cate
gory C with reversed order of tensor product and inverted associativit y 
somorphism. 
Remark 1.1.4. The notion of the opposite monoidal category is not 
to be confused with the usual notion of the opposite category , which is 
the category C obtained from C by reversing arrows (for any category 
C). Note that if C is monoidal, so is C (in a natural way), which makes 
it even easier to confuse the two notio ns. 
1.2. Basic properties of unit objects in monoidal categories . 
Let (C, , a, 1,) be a monoidal category . Dene the isomorph ism lX : 
1  XX by the formula  
lX = L
1 1((  Id)  a
1,1 
1,X ), 
and the isomorp hism rX : X  1 X by the formula  
rX = R11((Id  )  aX,1,1). 
2We note that there is no condition on the isomorphism , so it can be chosen 
arbitrarily .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>8 
Proof. It follows from the functorialit y of l that the following diagram 
comm utes 
(1.2.6) 1  (1  X) IdlX 1  X 
lX l1X 
1  X X lX 
Since lX is an isomorphism, the rst identity follows. The second iden
tity follows similarly from the functorialit y of r.  
Prop osition 1.2.4. The unit object in a monoidal category is unique 
up to a unique isomorphism. 
Proof. Let (1,), (1,) be two unit objects. Let (r, l), (r,l) be the 
corresp onding unit constrain ts. Then we have the isomorphism  := 
l1  (r1)1 : 1  1. 
It is easy to show using comm utativit y of the above triangle diagram s 
that  maps  to . It remains to show that  is the only isomorphism 
with this property. To do so, it suces to show that if b : 11 is an
isomorphism such that the diagram 
(1.2.7) 1  1 bb 1  1 
  
1 1 b 
is comm utativ e, then b = Id. To see this, it suce s to note that for 
any morphism c : 11 the diagram 
(1.2.8) 1  1 cId 1  1 
  
1 1c 
is comm utativ e (as  = r1), so b  b = b  Id and hence b = Id.  
Exercise 1.2.5. Verify the assertion in the proof of Prop osition 1.2.4 
that  maps  to . 
Hint. Use Prop ositions 1.2.1 and 1.2.2. 
The results of this subsec tion show that a monoidal category can be 
alternativ ely dened as follows: 
Denition 1.2.6. A monoidal category is a sextuple (C, , a, 1, l, r) 
satisfying the pentagon axiom (1.1.2) and the triangle axiom (1.2.1).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>7 
Prop osition 1.2.2. The following diagr ams commute for all objects 
X, Y C: 
a1,X,Y(1.2.3) (1  X)  Y 1  (X  Y )  
lX IdY lXY 
X  Y 
aX,Y,1 (1.2.4) (X  Y )  1 X  (Y  1)  
rXY IdX rY 
X  Y 
Proof. Consider the diagram 
(1.2.5) 
((X  1)  Y )  Z aX,1,Y Id (X  (1  Y ))  Z 
(rX Id)Id   
 (IdlY )Id 
(X  Y )  Z 
aX1,Y,Z aX,Y,Z aX,1Y,Z 
X  (Y  Z) 
rX Id 
(X  1)  (Y  Z) 
aX,1,Y Z Id(lY Id) 
IdlY Z X  ((1  Y )  Z) 
Ida1,Y,Z 
X  (1  (Y  Z)) 
where X, Y, Z are objects in C. The outside pentagon comm utes by 
the pentagon axiom (1.1.2). The functorialit y of a implies the com
mutativit y of the two middle quadrangles. The triangle axiom (1.2.1) 
implies the comm utativit y of the upper triangle and the lower left tri
angle. Conseque ntly, the lower right triangle comm utes as well. Setting 
X = 1 and applyin g the functor L
1 1 to the lower right triangle, we 
obtain comm utativit y of the triangle (1.2.3). The comm utativ ity of the 
triangle (1.2.4) is proved similarly .  
Prop osition 1.2.3. For any object X in C one has the equalities 
l1X = Id  lX and rX1 = rX  Id.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>MacLane coherence theorem
Rigid monoidal categories
Invertible objects
Tensor and multitensor categories</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec03/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>32 
Denition 1.12.1. A k-linear abelian category is said to be locally 
nite if it is essen tially small9, and the following two conditions are 
satised: 
(i) for any two objects X, Y in C, the space Hom(X, Y ) is nite 
dimensional; 
(ii) every object in C has nite length . 
Almost all abelain categories we will consider will be locally nite. 
Prop osition 1.12.2. In a lo cally nite ab elian c ategory C, Hom(X, Y )= 
0 if X, Y are simple and non-isomorphic, and Hom(X, X)= k for any 
simple object X. 
Proof. Recall Schurs lemma: if X, Y are simple objects of an abelian 
category , and f  Hom(X, Y ), then f = 0 or f is an isomorph ism. This 
implies that Hom(X, Y ) = 0 if X, Y are simple and non-isomorphic, 
and Hom(X, X) is a division algebra; since k is algebraically closed, 
condition (i) implie s that Hom(X, X)= k for any simple object X  
C.  
Also, the Jordan-H older and Krull-Sc hmidt theor ems hold in any 
locally nite abelian category C. 
Denition 1.12.3. Let C be a locally nite k-linear abelian rigid 
monoidal category . We will call C a multitensor category over k if 
the bifunctor  is bilinear on morphisms. If in addition End(1 ) k= 
then we will call C a tensor category. 
A multifusion category is a semisimple multitensor category with 
nitely many isomorphism simple objects. A fusion c ategory is a semisim
ple tensor category with nitely many isomorphism simple objects. 
Example 1.12.4. The categories Vec of nite dimensional k-vector 
spaces, Rep(G) of nite dimensional k-represen tations of a group G 
(or algebraic represen tations of an ane algebraic group G), Rep(g) 
of nite dimension al represen tations of a Lie algebra g, and Vec ofG 
G-graded nite dimensional k-vector spaces with associativit y dened 
by a 3-cocycle  are tensor categories. If G is a nite group, Rep(G) 
is a fusion category . In particular, Vec is a fusion category . 
Example 1.12.5. Let A be a nite dimen sional semisimple algebra 
over k. Let Abimo d be the category of nite dimensional A-bimo dules 
with bimo dule tensor product over A, i.e., 
(M, N)  M A N. 
9Recall that a category is called essentially small if its isomorphism classes of 
objects form a set.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>30 
It follows from Prop osition 1.10.4 that in a monoidal categ ory C
with right (respectively, left) duals, one can dene the (contravarian t) 
right (resp ectively, left) duality functor CC by X  X,f  f 
(resp ectively, X  X, f  f) for every object X and morphism f in 
C. By Prop osition 1.10.7(ii), these functors are anti-monoidal, in the 
sense that they dene monoidal functors C Cop; hence the functors 
XX, X X are monoida l. Also, it follows from Prop ositio n 
1.10.9 that the functors of right and left dualit y, when they are dened, 
are fully faithful (it suces to use (i) for U = X,V = Y, W = 1). 
Moreo ver, it follows fro m Remark 1.10.3 that in a rigid monoidal cat
egory , the functors of right and left dualit y are mutually quasi-in verse 
monoidal equiv alences of categories C Cop (so for rigid categories, 
the two notions of opposite category are the same up to equiv alence). 
This implies that the functors XX, X X are mutually 
quasi-in verse monoidal autoequiv alences. We will see later in Example 
1.27.2 that these autoequiv alences may be nontrivial; in particular, it 
is possible that objects V  and V are not isomorph ic. 
Exercise 1.10.15. Show that if C, D are rigid monoidal categories, 
F1,F2 : CD are monoidal functors, and  : F1  F2 is a morphism 
of monoidal functors, then  is an isomorphism.8 
Exercise 1.10.16. Let A be an algebra. Show that M  A  bimo d 
has a left (resp ectively, right) dual if and only if it is nitely generated 
projectiv e when considered as a left (resp ectively, right) A-mo dule. 
Sinilarly , if A is comm utativ e, M  A  mod has a left and right dual 
if and only if it is nitely generated projectiv e. 
1.11. Invertible objects. Let C be a rigid monoidal category . 
Denition 1.11.1. An object X in C is invertible if evX : X X  1 
and coevX : 1  X  X are isomorphisms. 
Clearly , this notion categories the notion of an invertible elemen t 
in a monoid. 
Example 1.11.2. The objects g in Vec are invertible. G 
Prop osition 1.11.3. Let X be an invertible object in C. Then 
(i) X = X and X is invertible; 
(ii) if Y is another invertible object then X  Y is invertible. 
Proof. Dualizing coevX and evX we get isomo rphisms X  X = 1
and X  X 1. = = In any rigid = Hence X X  X  X X. 
category the evaluation and coevaluation morp hisms for X can be 
8As we have seen in Remark 1.6.6, this is false for non-rigid categories.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>28 
Exercise 1.10.6. Let C, D be monoidal categories. Supp ose 
(F, J): CD 
is a monoidal functor with the corresp onding isomorphism  : 1 
F (1). Let X be an object in C with a right dual X. Prove that 
F (X) is a right dual of F (X) with the evaluation and coevaluation 
given by 
JX,X F (evX ) evF (X) : F (X)  F (X)  F (X  X)  F (1)= 1, 
J1 F (coevX ) X,X coevF (X) : 1 = F (1)  F (X  X)  F (X)  F (X). 
State and prove a similar result for left duals. 
Prop osition 1.10.7. Let C be a monoidal category. 
(i) Let U, V, W be objects in C admitting right (respectively, left) 
duals, and let f : VW , g : UV be morphisms in C. Then 
(fg) = g f (respectively, (fg)= g f).  
(ii) If U, V have right (respectively, left) duals then the object V  U 
(respectively, V  U) has a natur al structur e of a right (respectively, 
left) dual to U  V . 
Exercise 1.10.8. Prove Prop osition 1.10.7. 
Prop osition 1.10.9. (i) If an object V has a right dual V  then there 
are natur al adjunction isomorphisms 
(1.10.7) Hom(U  V, W ) Hom(U, W  V ),  
(1.10.8) Hom(V   U, W ) Hom(U, V  W ).  
Thus, the functor  V  is right adjoint to  V and V  is right 
adjoint to V  . 
(ii) If an object V has a left dual V then there are natur al adjunction 
isomorphisms 
(1.10.9) Hom(U  V, W )  Hom(U, W  V ), 
(1.10.10) Hom(V  U, W ) Hom(U, V  W ).  
Thus, the functor  V is right adjoint to  V and V  is right 
adjoint to V ). 
Proof. The isomorphism in (1.10.7) is given by 
f  (f  IdV  )  (IdU  coevV ) 
and has the inverse 
g  (IdW  evV )(g  IdV ).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>31 
dened by evX := coevX and coevX := evX , so X is invertible. 
The second statemen t follows from the fact that evXY can be dened 
as a comp osition of evX and evY and similarly coevXY can be dened 
as a comp osition of coevY and coevX .  
Prop osition 1.11.3 implies that invertibl e objects of C form a monoidal 
subcategory Inv(C) of C. 
Example 1.11.4. Gr-categories. Let us classify rigid monoidal cat
egories C where all objects are invertible and all morphisms are iso
morphisms. We may assume that C is skeletal, i.e. there is only one 
object in each isomorphism class, and objects form a group G. Also, 
by Prop osition 1.2.7, End(1 ) is an abelian group; let us denote it by 
A. Then for any g  G we can identify End(g ) with A, by sending 
f  End(g ) to f  Idg1  End(1 )= A. Then we have an action of G 
on A by 
a  End(1 )  g(a) := Idg  a  End(g ). 
Let us now consider the associativity isomorphism. It is dened by a 
function  : G  G  GA. The pentagon relation gives 
(1.11.1)
(g1g2,g3,g4)(g1,g2,g3g4)= (g1,g2,g3)(g1,g2g3,g4)g1((g2,g3,g4)),
for all g1,g2,g3,g4  G, which means that  is a 3-cocycle of G with 
coecien ts in the (generally , nontrivial) G-mo dule A. We see that any 
such 3-cocycle denes a rigid monoidal category , which we will call 
C (A). The analysis of monoidal equiv alenc es between such categories G
is similar to the case when A is a trivial G-mo dule, and yields that 
for a given group G and G-mo dule A, equiv alence classes of C areG 
parametrized by H3(G, A)/Out(G). 
Categories of the form C (A) are called Gr-categories, and were stud-G
ied in [Si]. 
1.12. Tensor and multitensor categories. Now we will start con
sidering monoidal structures on abelian categ ories. For the sake of 
brevit y, we will not recall the basic theory of abelian categories; let us 
just recall the Freyd-Mitc hell theorem stating that abelian categories 
can be characterized as full subcategories of categories of left modules 
over rings, which are closed under taking direct sums, as well as ker
nels, cokernels, and images of morphisms. This allows one to visualize 
the main conce pts of the theory of abelian categorie s in terms of the 
classical theory of modules over rings. 
Recall that an abelian category C is said to be k-linear (or dened 
over k) if for any X, Y in C, Hom(X, Y ) is a k-vector space, and com
position of morphisms is bilinear.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>26 
and ignore bracketings in calculations in a monoidal category . We will 
do so from now on, unless confusion is possible. 
1.10. Rigid monoidal categories. Let (C, , 1, a, ) be a monoidal 
category , and let X be an object of C. In what follows, we suppress 
the unit morphisms l, r. 
Denition 1.10.1. A right dual of an object X in C is an object X 
in C equipp ed with morphisms evX : X  X  1 and coevX : 1 
X  X, called the evaluation and coevaluation morphisms, such that 
the comp ositions 
(1.10.1) 
X coevX IdX aX,X,X X  (X  X) IdX evX  (X  X)  X   X, 
(1.10.2) 
a1 
X IdX coevX X,X,X evX IdX X X  (X  X)  (X  X)  X  
are the identity morphisms. 
Denition 1.10.2. A left dual of an object X in C is an object X in C
equipp ed with morphisms ev
X : X  X  1 and coev
X : 1  X  X 
such that the comp ositions 
(1.10.3) 
IdX coev a1 
X IdX X,X,X ev
XX  X  (X  X)  (X  X)  X  X, 
(1.10.4) 
X IdX IdX evcoevaX,X,X X X  (X  X)  X  X  (X  X)  X 
are the identity morphisms. 
Remark 1.10.3. It is obvious that if X is a right dual of an object 
X then X is a left dual of X with ev
X = evX and coev
X = coevX , 
and vice versa. Also, in any monoidal category , 1 = 1 = 1 with the 
structure morphisms  and 1 . Also note that changing the order of 
tensor product switc hes right duals and left duals, so to any statemen t 
about right duals there corresp onds a symmetric statemen t about left 
duals. 
Prop osition 1.10.4. If X C has a right (respectively, left) dual 
object, then it is unique up to a unique isomorphism. 
Proof. Let X1 ,X2  be two right duals to X. Denote by e1,c1,e2,c2 the 
corresp onding evaluation and coevaluation morp hisms. Then we have</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>25 
1.9. The MacLane coherence theorem. In a monoidal category , 
one can form n-fold tensor products of any ordered sequence of objects 
X1, ..., Xn. Namely , such a product can be attac hed to any paren the
sizing of the expression X1 ...Xn, and such products are, in general, 
distinct objects of C. 
However, for n = 3, the associativity isomorphism gives a canonic al 
identication of the two possible paren thesizing s, (X1  X2)  X3 and 
X1  (X2  X3). An easy combinatorial argumen t then shows that one 
can identify any two paren thesized products of X1, ..., Xn, n  3, using 
a chain of associativit y isomorphisms. 
We would like to say that for this reason we can completely ignore 
paren theses in computat ions in any monoidal category , identifying all 
possible paren thesized products with each other. But this runs into the 
following problem: for n  4 there may be two or more dieren t chains 
of associativit y isomorphisms connecting two dieren t paren thesizings, 
and a priori it is not clear that they provide the same identication. 
Luckily, for n = 4, this is settled by the pentagon axiom, which 
states exactly that the two possible identications are the same. But 
what about n&gt; 4? 
This problem is solved by the following theorem of MacLane, which 
is the rst importan t result in the theory of monoidal categories. 
Theorem 1.9.1. (MacL anes Coher ence The orem) [ML] L et X 1,...,Xn  
C. Let P1, P2 be any two parenthesize d products of X1, ..., Xn (in this 
order) with arbitr ary insertions of unit objects 1. Let f, g : P1 P2
be two isomorphisms, obtaine d by composing associativity and unit 
isomorphisms and their inverses possibly tensor ed with identity mor
phisms. Then f = g. 
Proof. We deriv e this theorem as a corollary of the MacLanes strictness 
Theorem 1.8.5. Let L : CC be a monoidal equiv alence between C
and a strict monoidal category C. Consider a diagram in C represen ting 
f and g and apply L to it. Over each arrow of the resulting diagram 
represen ting an associativit y isomorphism, let us build a rectangle as 
in (1.4.1), and do similarly for the unit morphisms. This way we obtain 
a prism one of whose faces consists of identity maps (asso ciativ ity and 
unit isomorphisms in C) and whose sides are comm utativ e. Hence, the 
other face is comm utativ e as well, i.e., f = g.  
As we mentioned, this implies that any two paren thesized products 
of X1, ..., Xn with insertions of unit objects are indeed canonically iso
morphic, and thus one can safely identify all of them with each other</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>33 
Then C is a multitensor category with the unit object 1 = A, the left 
dual dened by M  Hom(AM, AA), and the right dual dened by 
M  Hom(MA,AA).10 The category C is tensor if and only if A is 
simple, in which case it is equiv alent to k  Vec. More generally , if 
A has n matrix blocks, the category C can be alternativ ely describ ed 
as the category whose objects are n-by-n matrices of vector spaces, 
V =(Vij ), and the tensor product is matrix multiplication: 
(V  W )il = jn 
=1Vij  Wjl. 
This category will be denoted by Mn(Vec). It is a multifusion category. 
In a similar way, one can dene the multitensor category Mn(C) of 
n-by-n matrices of objects of a given multitensor category C. If C is a 
multifusion category, so is Mn(C). 
10Note that if A is a nite dimensional non-semisimple algebra then the category 
of nite dimensional A-bimo dules is not rigid, since the dualit y functors dened as 
above do not satisfy rigidit y axioms (cf. Exercise 1.10.16).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>27 
a morphism  : X1  X2  dened as the comp osition  
IdX a1 
,X,X e1IdX 
1 c2 X1  
2 2X1   X1   (X  X2 )  (X1   X)  X2   X2 .
Similarly one denes a morphism  : X2  X1 . We claim that 
  
and  are the identity morp hisms, so  is an isomorphism. Indeed 
consider the following diagram : 
X1  Id c1 X1   X  X1  
Id Id c2 Id c2Id 
X1   X  X2  
Id c1 X1   X  X2   X  X1 
Id e2Id X1   X  X1  
e1Id e1Id e1Id 
X2  
Id c1 X2   X  X1  
e2Id X1 . 
Here we suppr ess the associativit y constrain ts. It is clear that the three 
small squares comm ute. The triangle in the upper right corner com
mutes by axiom (1.10.1) applied to X2 . Hence, the perimeter of the 
diagram comm utes. The comp osition through the top row is the iden
tity by (1.10.2) applied to X1 . The comp osition through the bottom 
row is  and so  = Id. The proof of  = Id is completely  
similar. 
Moreo ver, it is easy to check that  : X1  X2  is the only iso 
morphism which preserv es the evaluation and coevaluation morphisms. 
This proves the proposition for right duals. The proof for left duals is 
similar.  
Exercise 1.10.5. Fill in the details in the proof of Prop osition 1.10.4. 
If X, Y are objects in C which have right duals X,Y  and f : X  Y 
is a morphism, one denes the right dual f : Y  X of f as the 
comp osition 
a1 
Y  IdY  coevX Y ,X,X 
(1.10.5)  Y   (X  X)  (Y   X)  X 
(IdY  f)IdX evY IdX  (Y   Y )  X  X. 
Similarly , if X, Y are objects in C which have left duals X, Y and 
f : XY is a morphism, one denes the left dual f : Y X of f   
as the comp osition 
X IdY coevaX,X,Y 
(1.10.6) Y  (X  X)  Y  X  (X  Y ) 
IdX (fIdY ) IdX ev
Y  X  (Y  Y )  X.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>29 
The other isomorphisms are similar, and are left to the reader as an 
exercise. 7  
Remark 1.10.10. Prop osition 1.10.9 provides another proof of Prop o
sition 1.10.4. Namely , setting U = 1 and V = X in (1.10.8), we obtain 
a natur al isomorphism Hom(X,W ) Hom(1,X  W ) for any right = 
dual X of X. Hence, if Y1,Y2 are two such duals then there is a 
natural isomorphism Hom(Y 1,W ) Hom(Y 2,W ), whence there is a = 
canonical isomorphism Y1 = Y2 by Yonedas Lemma. The proof for left 
duals is similar. 
Denition 1.10.11. A monoidal category C is called rigid if every 
object X C has a right dual object and a left dual object. 
Example 1.10.12. The category Vec of nite dimensional k-vector 
spaces is rigid: the right and left dual to a nite dimensional vector 
space V are its dual space V , with the evaluation map evV : V  V 
k being the contraction, and the coevaluation map coevV : k  V V  
being the usual embedding. On the other hand, the category Vec of 
all k-vector spaces is not rigid, since for innite dimensional spaces 
there is no coevaluation maps (indeed, supp ose that c : kV  Y
is a coevaluation map, and consider the subspace V  of V spanned by 
the rst comp onent of c(1); this subspace nite dimensional, and yet 
the comp osition V  V  Y  V  V , which is supp osed to be the 
identity map, lands in V  -a contradiction). 
Example 1.10.13. The category Rep(G) of nite dimensional 
k-represen tations of a group G is rigid: for a nite dimensional rep
resen tation V , the (left or right) dual represen tation V  is the usual 
dual space (with the evaluation and coevaluation maps as in Example 
1.10.12), and with the G-action given by V  (g)=(V (g)1). Simi
larly, the category Rep(g) of nite dimensional represen tations of a Lie 
algebra g is rigid, with V  (a)= V (a). 
Example 1.10.14. The category VecG is rigid if and only if the monoid 
G is a group; namely , g  = g = g1 (with the obvious structure 
maps). More generally , for any group G and 3-cocycle   Z3(G, k), 
the category Vec
G is rigid. Namely , assume for simplicit y that the 
cocycle  is normalized (as we know, we can do so without loss of 
generalit y). Then we can dene dualit y as above, and normalize the 
coevaluation morphisms of g to be the identities. The evaluation mor
phisms will then be dened by the formula evg = (g, g1,g). 
7A convenien t way to do computations in this and previous Prop ositions is using 
the graphical calculus (see [K, Chapter XIV]).</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Quantum traces
Pivotal categories and dimensions
Spherical categories
Multitensor cateogries
Multifusion rings
Frobenius-Perron theorem</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec08/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>77 
(2) Let	C = Rep(H), where H is a nite dimensional Hopf alge
bra. Show that pivotal structures on C bijectiv ely correspond 
to group-lik e elemen ts of H such that gxg1 = S2(x) for all 
x  H. 
Let a be a pivotal structure on a rigid monoidal category C. 
Denition 1.38.4. The dimension of an object X with respect to a 
is dima(X) := Tr(aX )  End(1 ). 
Thus, in a tensor category over k, dimensions are elemen ts of k. Also, 
it follows from Exercise 1.38.3 that dima(V ) = dima(V ). 
Prop osition 1.38.5. If C is a tensor category, then the function X 
dima(X) is a character of the Grothendie ck ring Gr(C). 
Proof. Prop osition 1.37.3 implies that dima is additiv e on exact se
quences, which means that it gives rise to a well-dened linear map 
from Gr(C) to k. The fact that this map is a character follows from the 
obvious fact that dima(1) = 1 and Prop osition 1.37.1 (3).  
Corollary 1.38.6. Dimensions of objects in a pivotal nite tensor cat
egory are algebr aic integers in k. 12 
Proof. This follows from the fact that a character of any ring that is 
nitely generated as a Z-mo dule takes values in algebraic integers.  
1.39. Spherical categories. 
Denition 1.39.1. A pivotal structure a on a tensor category C is 
spheric al if dima(V ) = dima(V ) for any object V in C. A tensor 
category is spheric al if it is equipp ed with a spherical structure. 
Since dima is additiv e on exact sequences, it suces to require the 
property dima(V ) = dima(V ) only for simple objects V . 
Theorem 1.39.2. Let C be a spheric al category and V be an object of 
Then for any x  Hom(V, V ) one has TrL (aV x)= TrR (xa1). C.	V VV 
Proof. We rst note that TrR (a1) = dima(X) for any object X by X	X 
Prop osition 1.37.1(1) and Exercise 1.38.3(1). Now let us prove the 
proposition in the special case when V is semisimple. Thus V = i Yi 
Vi, where Vi are vector spaces and Yi are simple objects. Then x = 
12If k has positiv e characteristic, by an algebraic integer in k we mean an element 
of a nite subeld of k.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>80 
(3) A multifusion ring is a based ring of nite rank. A fusion ring 
is a unital based ring of nite rank. 
Remark 1.42.3. (1) It follows easily from denition that i, j 
I0,i =j implies that b2 
i = bi,bibj =0,i = i. 
(2) It is easy to see that for a given Z+ring A, being a (unital) 
based ring is a property, not an additional structure. 
(3) Note that any Z+-ring is assumed to have a unit, and is not 
necessarily a unital Z+-ring. 
Prop osition 1.42.4. If C is a semisimple multitensor category then 
Gr(C) is a based ring. If C is semisimple tensor category then Gr(C) is 
a unital based ring. If C is a (multi)fusion category, then Gr(C) is a 
(multi)fusion ring. 
Proof. The Z+-basis in Gr(C) consists of isomorp hism classes of simple 
objects of C. The set I0 consists of the classes of simple subobjects of 
1. The involution  is the dualit y map (by Prop osition 1.41.1 it does 
not matter whether to use left or right dualit y). This implies the rst 
two statemen ts. The last statemen t is clear.  
Example 1.42.5. Let C be the category of nite dimensional repre
sentations of the Lie algebra sl2(C). Then the simple objects of this 
category are irreducible represen tations Vm of dimension m + 1 for 
m =0, 1, 2,... ; V0 = 1. The Grothendiec k ring of C is determined by 
the well-kno wn Clebsc h-Gordon rule 
i+j
(1.42.3) Vi  Vj = Vl. 
l=|ij|,i+jl2Z 
The dualit y map on this ring is the identity. The same is true if C = 
Rep(Uq (sl2)) when q is not a root of unity, see [K]. 
Let C be a semisimple multitensor category with simple objects 
{Xi}iI . Let I0 be the subset of I such that 1 = iI0 Xi. Let 
Hijl := Hom(Xl,Xi  Xj ) (if Xp Cij with p  I and i, j  I0, we 
will identify spaces Hp and Hp with k using the left and right unit pi ip 
morphisms).  We have Xi  Xj = l Hijl  Xl. Hence, 
(Xi1 = Hj  Hi4 Xi2 )  Xi3 
i1i2 ji3  Xi4 
i4 j 
Xi1  (Xi2 )= Hii
14 
l  Hl .  Xi3 i2i3  Xi4 
i4 l</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>82 
It is clear from the above explanations that this problem is equiv a
lent to ndin g all solutions of the system of algebraic equations coming 
from the axioms of the rigid monoidal category modulo the group of au
tomorphisms of the spaces Hijk (gauge transformations). In general, 
this problem is very dicult because the system of equations involved 
is nonlinear, contains many unkno wns and is usually over-determined . 
In particular, it is not clear a priori whether for a given R this sys
tem has at least one solution, and if it does, whether the set of these 
solutions is nite. It is therefore amazing that the theory of tensor 
categories allows one to solve the categorication problem in a number 
of nontrivial cases. This will be done in later parts of these notes; now 
we will only mention the simplest result in this direction, which follows 
from the results of Subsection 1.7. 
Let Z[G] be the group ring of a group G, with basis {g  G} and 
involution g = g1 . Clearly , Z[G] is a unital based ring. 
Prop osition 1.42.9. The categoric ations of Z[G] are Vec 
G, and they 
are parametrize d by H3(G, k)/Out(G). 
Remark 1.42.10. It is tempting to say that any Z+-ring R has a 
canonical categoricatio n over any eld k: one can take the skeletal 
semisimple category C = CR over k whose Grothendiec k group is R, 
dene the tensor product functor on C according to the multiplic ation 
in R, and then dene the associativit y isomorphism to be the identity 
(whic h appears to make sense because the category is skeletal, and 
therefore by the associativit y of R one has (X Y )Z = X (Y Z)). 
However, a more careful consideration shows that this approac h does 
not actually work. Namely , such asso ciativit y isomorphism fails to 
be functorial with respect to morphism s; in other words, if g : YY is
a morphism, then (IdX g)IdZ is not always equal to IdX (g IdZ ). 
To demonstrate this explicitly , denote the simple objects of the cat
egory C by Xi, i =1, ..., r, and let Xi  Xj = kNijl Xl. Take X = Xi, 
Y = mXj , and Z = Xl; then g is an m by m matrix over k. The alge
bra End((X  Y )  Z)= End(X  (Y  Z)) is equal to sMatmns (k), 
where  
ns = Nijp Npls = Niqs Njlq , 
p q 
and in this algebra we have 
(IdX  g)  IdZ = pr 
=1IdN p  g  IdNs ,
ij pl 
IdX  (g  IdZ )= r IdNs ,q=1iq  g  IdN q 
jl 
We see that these two matrices are, in general, dieren t, which shows 
that the identity asso ciativ ity isomorp hism is not functorial.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>78 
i xi IdVi with xi  Endk(Yi) and a =  IdYi aVi (by the functorialit y 
of a). Hence 
TrL
V (ax) = Tr(xi) dim(Vi), 
TrR
V (xa1) = Tr(xi) dim(Vi ). 
This implies the result for a semisimple V . 
Consider now the general case. Then V has the coradical ltration 
(1.39.1) 0 = V0  V1  V2    Vn = V 
(such that Vi+1/Vi is a maximal semisimple subobject in V/Vi). This 
ltration is preserv ed by x and by a (i.e., a : Vi Vi ). Since traces 
are additiv e on exact sequences by Prop osition 1.37.3, this implies that 
the general case of the required statemen t follows from the semisimple 
case.  
Exercise 1.39.3. (i) Let Aut(IdC) be the group of isomorphism classes 
of monoidal automorphisms of a monoidal category C. Show that the 
set of isomorphism classes of pivotal structures on C is a torsor over 
Aut(IdC), and the set of isomorphism classes of spheric al structures 
on C is a torsor over the subgroup Aut(IdC)2 in Aut(IdC ) of elemen ts 
which act by 1 on simple objects. 
1.40. Semisimple multitensor categories. In this section we will 
more closely consider semisimple multitensor categories which have 
some importan t additional properties compared to the general case. 
1.41. Isomorphism between V  and V . 
Prop osition 1.41.1. Let C be a semisimple multitensor category and 
let V be an object in C. = V . = V . Then V  Henc e, V 
Proof. We may assume that V is simple. 
We claim that the unique simple object X such that Hom(1,V X)=
0 is V . Indeed, Hom(1,V  X) Hom(X, V ) which is non-zero if = 
and only if X = V . = V , i.e., X  Similarly , the unique simple object 
X such that Hom(V  X, 1)=0 is V . But since C is semisimple, 
dimk Hom(1,V  X) = dimk Hom(V  X, 1), which implies the result. 
Remark 1.41.2. As noted in Remark 1.27.2, the result of Proposi
tion 1.41.1 is false for non-semisimp le categories. 
Remark 1.41.3. Prop osition 1.41.1 gives rise to the following ques
tion.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>84 
be the minimal polynomial of X (ai are distinct). Assume that a0 =0 
(we can do so since X is not nilpotent). Let 
r
g(t)= (x  ai)mi xh(x), 
i=1 
where h is a polynomial chosen in such a way that g(a0) = 1, g(j)(a0)= 
0 for j =1, ..., m0  1 (this is clearly possible). Then g(X) is an 
idemp otent, so by Corollary 1.43.3, (g(X)) &gt; 0. Hence there exists 
n&gt; 0 such that (Xn) = 0, as desired.   
1.44. The Frobenius-P erron theorem. The following classical the
orem from linear algebra [Ga, XIII.2] plays a crucial role in the theory 
of tensor categories. 
Theorem 1.44.1. Let B be a squar e matrix with nonne gative entries. 
(1)	B has a nonne gative real eigenvalue. The largest nonne gative 
real eigenvalue (B) of B dominates the absolute values of all 
other eigenva lues  of B: || (B) (in other words, the spec
tral radius of B is an eigenvalue). Moreover, there is an eigen
vector of B with nonne gative entries and eigenvalue (B). 
(2)	If B has strictly positive entries then (B) is a simple positive 
eigenvalue, and the corresponding eigenve ctor can be normalize d 
to have strictly positive entries. Moreover, || &lt;(B) for any 
other eigenvalue  of B. 
(3)	If B has an eigenve ctor v with strictly positive entries, then the 
corresponding eigenvalue is (B). 
Proof. Let B be an n by n matrix with nonnegativ e entries. Let us rst 
show that B has a nonnegativ e eigen value. If B has an eigen vector v 
with nonnegativ e entries and eigen value 0, then there is nothing to 
prove. Otherwise, let  be the set of column vectors x  Rn with 
with nonnegativ e entries xi and s(x) := xi equal to 1 (this is a 
simplex). Den e a continuous map fB :   by fB(x)= s(B
Bx
x) . By 
the Brou wer xed point theorem, this map has a xed point f. Then 
Bf = f, where &gt; 0. Thus the eigen value (B) is well dened, and 
B always has a nonn egativ e eigenvector f with eigen value  = (B). 
Now assume that B has strictly positiv e entries. Then f must have 
strictly positiv e entries fi. If d is another real eigen vector of B with 
eigen value , let z be the small est of the numbers of di/fi. Then the 
vector v = d  zf satises Bv = v, has nonnegativ e entries and has 
one entry equal to zero. Hence v = 0 and  is a simple eigen value.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>79 
Question 1.41.4. Does any semisimple tensor category admit a piv
otal structure? A spherical structure? 
This is the case for all known examples. The general answ er is un
known to us at the momen t of writing (even for ground elds of char
acteristic zero). 
Prop osition 1.41.5. If C is a semisimple tensor category and a : V 
V  for a simple object V then Tr(a)=0. 
Proof. Tr(a) is the comp osition morphism of the diagram 1 V 
V  1 where both morph isms are non-zero. If the comp osition mor 
phism is zero then there is a non-z ero morphism (V V )/1  1 which 
means that the [V  V  : 1]  2. Since C is semisimple, this implies 
that dimk Hom(1,V  V ) is at least 2. Hence, dimk Hom(V, V )  2 
which contradicts the simplicit y of V .  
Remark 1.41.6. The above result is false for non-semisimple cate
gories. For exam ple, let C = Repk(GLp(Fp)), the represen tation cat
egory of the group GLp(Fp) over a eld k of characteristic p. Let 
V be the p dimensional vector represen tation of GLp(Fp) (whic h is 
clearly irreducible). Let a : VV  be the identity map. Then 
Tr(a) = dimk(V )= p =0 in k. 
1.42. Grothendiec k rings of semisimple tensor categories. 
Denition 1.42.1. (i) A Z+basis of an algebra free as a module over 
Z is a basis B = {bi} such that bibj = k cijk bk,cijk  Z+. 
(ii) A Z+ring is an algebra over Z with unit equipp ed with a xed 
Z+basis. 
Denition 1.42.2. (1) A Z+ring A with basis {bi}iI is called a 
based ring if the following conditions hold  [a] There exists a subset I0  I such that 1 = iI0 bi. 
[b] Let  : A Z be the group homomorphism dened by  
 
(1.42.1) (bi)= 1if i  I0 
0 if i  I0 
There exists an involution i  i of I such that induced map 
a = iI aibi  a = iI aibi ,ai  Z is an anti-involution 
of ring A and such that 
1 if i = j 
(1.42.2) (bibj )= 0if i = j. 
(2) A unital Z+-ring is a Z+-ring A such that 1 belongs to the basis.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>81 
Thus the associativit y constrain t reduces to a collection of linear iso
morphisms 
(1.42.4) i4 : Hj  Hi4 = Hi4 .i1i2i3 i1i2 ji3 
i1l  Hil 
2i3 
j l 
The matrix blocks of these isomorphisms, 
(1.42.5) (i4 )jl : Hj  Hi4 Hii
14 
l  Hl 
i1i2i3 i1i2 ji3  i2i3 
are called 6j-symb ols because they depend on six indices. 
Example 1.42.6. Let C be the category of nite dimensional repre
sentations of the Lie algebra sl2(C). Then the spaces Hijl are 0-or 
1-dimensional. In fact, it is obvious from the Clebsc h-Gordan rule that 
the map (i
i4
1i2i3 )jl is a map between nonzero (i.e., 1-dimensional) spaces 
if and only if the numbers i1,i2,i3,i4, j, l are edge lengths of a tetrahe
dron with faces corresp onding to the four H-spaces (i1i2j, ji3i4,i1li4, 
i2i3l, such that the perimeter of every face is even (this tetrahedron 
is allowed to be in the Euclidean 3-space, Euclidean plane, or hyper
bolic 3-space, so the only conditions are the triangle inequalities on 
the faces). In this case, the 6j-symbol can be regarded as a number, 
provided we choose a basis vector in every non-zero Hijl . Under an ap
propriate normalizat ion of basis vectors these numbers are the Racah 
coecients or classic al 6j-symb ols. More generally , if C = Uq (sl2), 
where q is not a root of unity, then the numbers (i
i4
1i2i3 )jl are called 
q-Racah coecients or quantum 6j-symb ols [CFS]. 
Further, the evaluation and coevaluation maps dene elements 
(1.42.6) ij  (Hiij 
 ) and ij  Hiij 
 ,j  I0. 
Now the axioms of a rigid monoidal category , i.e., the triangle and 
pentagon identities and the rigidit y axioms translate into non-linear al
gebraic equations with respect to the 6j-symbols (i
i4
1i2i3 )jl and vectors 
ij ,ij . 
Exercise 1.42.7. Write down explicitly the relation on 6j symbols 
coming from the pentagon identity. If C = Rep(sl2(C)) this relation is 
called the Elliott-Bie denharn relation ([CFS]). 
Prop osition 1.42.4 gives rise to the following general proble m of cat
egoric ation of based rings which is one of the main problems in the 
structure theory of tensor categories. 
Problem 1.42.8. Given a based ring R, describ e (up to equiv alence) 
all multitensor categories over k whose Grothendiec k ring is isomorphic 
to R.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>85 
Now let y =(y1, ..., yn)  Cn be a row vector. Dene the norm 
|y| := |yj|fj . Then 
|yB| = | yibij |fj |yi|bij fj = |y|, 
j i i,j 
and the equalit y holds if and only if all the complex numbers yibij 
which are nonzero have the same argumen t. So if yB = y, then 
|| , and if || =  then all yi which are nonzero have the same 
argumen t, so we can renormalize y to have nonnegativ e entries. This 
implies that  = . Thus, part (2) is proved. 
Now consider the gener al case (B has nonnegativ e entries). Assume 
that B has a row eigenev ector y with strictly positiv e entries and eigen
value . Then 
yf = yBf = yf, 
which implies  = , as yf = 0. This implies (3). 
It remains to nish the proof of part (1) (i.e. to prove that (B) 
dominates all other eigen values of B). LetB be the orien ted graph 
whose vertices are labeled by 1, ..., n, and there is an edge from j to 
i if and only if bij &gt; 0. Let us say that i is accessible from j if there 
is a path in B leading from j to i. Let us call B irreducible if any 
vertex is accessible from any other. By conjugating B by a permutation 
matrix if necessary , we can get to a situation when i  j implies that 
i is accessible from j. This means that B is a block upper triangular 
matrix, whose diagonal blocks are irreducible. So it suces to prove 
the statemen t in question for irreducible B. 
But if B is irreducible, then for some N the matrix 1 + B + + BN  
has strictly positiv e entries. So the nonnegativ e eigen vector f of B 
with eigen value (B) is actually strictly positiv e, and one can run the 
argumen t in the proof of part (2) with a norm bound (all that is used 
in this argumen t is the positivit y of f). Hence, the result follows from 
(2).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>83 
1.43. Semisimplicit y of multifusion rings. 
Denition 1.43.1. A -algebra is an associativ e algebra B over C 
with an antilinear anti-involution  : BB and a linear functional 
 : B C such that (ab)= (ba), and the Hermitian form (ab) is 
positiv e denite. 
Obviously , any semisimple algebra B = r Mati(C) is a -algebra.i=1
Namely , if pi &gt; 0 are any positiv e numbers for i =1, ..., r then one 
can dene  to be the usual hermitian adjoin t of matrices, and set 
(a1, ..., ar)= i piTr(ai). Conversely , it is easy to see that any 8
algebra structure on a nite dimensional semisimple algebra has this 
form up to an isomorphism (and the numbers pi are uniquely deter
mined, as traces of central idemp otents of B). 
It turns out that this is the most general example of a nite dimen 
sional -algebra. Namely , we have 
Prop osition 1.43.2. Any nite dimensional -algebr a B is semisim
ple. 
Proof. If M  B is a subbimo dule, and M is the orthogonal comple
ment of M under the form (ab), then M is a subbimo dule of B, 
and M  M = 0 because of the positivit y of the form. So we have 
B = M  M. Thus B is a semisimple B-bimo dule, which implies the 
proposition.  
Corollary 1.43.3. If e is a nonzer o idemp otent in a nite dimensional 
-algebr a B then (e) &gt; 0. 
The following proposition is obvious. 
Prop osition 1.43.4. Let A be a based ring. Then the algebr a A ZC 
is canonic ally a -algebr a. 
Corollary 1.43.5. Let A be a multifusion ring. Then the algebr a 
A ZC is semsimiple. 
Corollary 1.43.6. Let X be a basis element of a fusion ring A. Then 
there exists n&gt; 0 such that (Xn) &gt; 0. 
Proof. Since (Xn(X)n) &gt; 0 for all n&gt; 0, X is not nilpotent. Let 
r
q(x):= (x  ai)mi 
i=0</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>76 
1.37. Quan tum traces. Let C be a rigid mono idal category , V be an 
object in C, and a  Hom(V, V ). Dene the left quan tum trace 
(1.37.1) TrL (a) := evV   (a  IdV  )  coevV  End(1 ).V 
Similarly , if a  Hom(V, V ) then we can dene the right quan tum 
trace 
(1.37.2) TrR (a) := evV  (IdV  a)  coevV  End(1 ).V 
In a tensor category over k, TrL(a) and TrR(a) can be regarde d as 
elemen ts of k. 
When no confusion is possible, we will denote TrL
V by TrV . 
The following proposition shows that usual linear algebra formulas 
hold for the quan tum trace. 
Prop osition 1.37.1. If a  Hom(V, V ),b  Hom(W, W ) then 
(1) TrVL (a)= TrVR 
 (a); 
(2) TrVL 
W (a  b)= TrL
W (b) (in additive categories); V (a)+ TrL 
(3) TrVL 
W (a  b)= TrL (a)T rL (b);VW 
(4) If c  Hom(V, V ) then T rL (ac)= TrL (ca), TrR (ac)= TrR(ca).V V V V 
Similar equalities to (2),(3) also hold for right quantum traces. 
Exercise 1.37.2. Prove Prop osition 1.37.1. 
If C is a multitensor category , it is useful to generalize Prop osi
tion 1.37.1(2) as follows. 
Prop osition 1.37.3. If a Hom(V, V ) and WV such that   
a(W )  W  then TrL = TrL 
V/W (a). That is, Tr is addi-V (a) W (a)+ TrL 
tive on exact sequenc es. The same statement holds for right quantum 
traces. 
Exercise 1.37.4. Prove Prop osition 1.37.3. 
1.38. Pivotal categories and dimensions. 
Denition 1.38.1. Let C be a rigid monoidal category . A pivotal 
structur e on C is an isomorphism of monoidal functors a : Id ?.
That is, a pivotal structure is a collection of morphisms aX : X 
X natural in X and satisfying aXY = aX  aY for all objects X, Y 
in C. 
Denition 1.38.2. A rigid monoidal category C equipp ed with a piv
otal structure is said to be pivotal. 
Exercise 1.38.3. (1) If a is a pivotal structure then aV  =(aV )1 . 
Hence, aV  = a 
V .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Bialgebras and Hopf algebras</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec05/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>46 
For a bialgebra H, the monoidal category of right H-como dules will 
be denoted by H  como d, and the subcategory of nite dimensional 
como dules by H  como d. 
1.22. Hopf algebras. Let us now consider the additional structure 
on the bialgebra H = End(F ) from the previous subsection in the case 
when the category C has right duals. In this case, one can dene a 
linear map S : HH by the formula 
S(a)X = a 
X , 
where we use the natural identication of F (X) with F (X). 
Prop osition 1.22.1. (the antip ode axiom) Let  : H  HH and
i : kH be the multiplic ation and the unit maps of H. Then 
 (Id  S) = i =  (S  Id) 
    
as maps HH. 
Proof. For any b  End(F F ) the linear map (IdS)(1 (b))X ,X F,F 
C is given by 
(1.22.1) 
coevF (X) bX,X evF (X)F (X)  F (X)F (X)F (X)  F (X)F (X)F (X)  F (X), 
where we suppress the identity isomorphisms, the associativit y con
strain t, and the isomorphism F (X) = F (X). Indeed, it suces to 
check (1.22.1) for b =   , where ,   H, which is straigh tforw ard. 
Now the rst equalit y of the proposition follows from the comm uta
tivity of the diagram 
coevF (X)(1.22.2) F (X) F (X)  F (X)  F (X) 
Id JX,X 
F (coevX )F (X) F (X  X)  F (X) 
1 XX 
F (coevX )F (X) F (X  X)  F (X) 
J1 Id X,X 
evF (X)F (X) F (X)  F (X)  F (X), 
for any   End(F ). 
Namely , the comm utativit y of the upper and the lower square fol
lows from the fact that upon identication of F (X) with F (X), the 
morphisms evF (X) and coevF (X) are given by the diagrams of Exer
cise 1.10.6. The middle square comm utes by the naturalit y of . The</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>47 
comp osition of left vertical arrows gives ()IdF (X), while the compo
sition of the top, right, and bottom arrows gives  (Id  S) (). 
The second equality is proved similarly .  
 
Denition 1.22.2. An antip ode on a bialgebra H is a linear map 
S : HH which satises the equalities of Prop osition 1.22.1.  
Exercise 1.22.3. Show that the antipode axiom is self-dual in the 
following sense: if H is a nite dimensional bialgebra with antipode 
SH , then the bialgebra H also admits an antipode SH = S 
H . 
The following is a linear algebra analog of the fact that the right 
dual, when it exists, is unique up to a unique isomorphism. 
Prop osition 1.22.4. An antip ode on a bialgebr a H is unique if exists. 
Proof. The proof essen tially repeats the proof of uniqueness of right 
dual. Let S, S be two antipodes for H. Then using the antipode 
properties of S, S, associativity of , and coasso ciativit y of , we get 
S =   (S  [  (Id  S)  ])  = 
  (Id  )  (S  Id  S)  (Id  )  = 
  (  Id)  (S  Id  S)  (  Id)  = 
  ([  (S  Id)  ]  S)  = S. 
Prop osition 1.22.5. If S is an antip ode on a bialgebr a H then S is an 
antihomomorphism of algebr as with unit and of coalgebr as with counit. 
Proof. Let 
1 2 3(  Id) (a) = (Id  ) (a) =   a
 a
 a
i ,i i 
i 
(  Id) (b) = (Id  ) (b) = b   2 1 
j  bj  b
j 
Then using the denition of the antipode, we have 3 
j . 
3 3 2211 3 2 1 
i b)ai S(ai )= i bj )ai bj S(bj )S(ai )= S(b)S(a). 
i i,j 
Thus S is an antihomomorphism of algebras (which is obviously unital). 
The fact that it is an antihomomorphism of coalgebras then follows 
using the self-dualit y of the axioms (see Exercises 1.21.4,1.22.3), or can 
be shown indep enden tly by a similar argumen t.  S(ab)= S(a
 S(a</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>45 
Thus we see that one has the following theorem. 
Theorem 1.21.3. The assignments (C,F )  H = End(F ), H 
(Rep(H ), Forget) are mutual ly inverse bijections between 
1) nite abelian k-linear monoidal categories C with a ber functor 
F , up to monoidal equivalenc e and isomorphism of monoidal functors; 
2) nite dimensional bialgebr as H over k up to isomorphism. 
Proof. Straigh tforw ard from the above.  
Theorem 1.21.3 is called the reconstruction theorem for nite dimen
sional bialgebr as (as it reconstructs the bialgebra H from the category 
of its modules using a ber functor). 
Exercise 1.21.4. Show that the axioms of a bialgebra are self-dual 
in the following sense: if H is a nite dime nsional bialgebra with 
multiplication  : H  HH, unit i : kH, comultipli cation  
: H  H  H and counit  : H  k, then H is also a bialgebra, 
with the multiplication , unit , comultiplication , and counit i. 
Exercise 1.21.5. (i) Let G be a nite monoid, and C = VecG. Let 
F : C Vec be the forgetful functor. Show that H = End(F ) is the 
bialgebra Fun(G, k) of k-valued functions on G, with comultiplication 
(f)(x, y)= f(xy) (where we identify H  H with Fun(G  G, k)), 
and counit (f)= f(1). 
(ii) Show that Fun(G, k) = k[G], the monoid algebra of G (with 
basis x  G and product xy = xy), with copro duct (x) = x x, and  
counit (x) = 1, x  G. Note that the bialgebra k[G] may be dened 
for any G (not necessarily nite ). 
Exercise 1.21.6. Let H be a k-algebra, C = H mod be the category 
of H-modules, and F : C Vec be the forgetful funct or (we dont 
assume nite dimensionalit y). Assume that C is monoidal, and F is 
given a monoidal structure J. Show that this endows H with the 
structure of a bialgebra, such that (F, J) denes a monoidal equiv alenc e 
C Rep(H ). 
Note that not only modules, but also comodules over a bialgebra H 
form a monoidal category . Indee d, for a nite dimensional bialgebra, 
this is clear, as right (resp ectively, left) modules over H is the same 
thing as left (resp ectively, right) como dules over H. In general, if 
X, Y are, say, right H-como dules, then the right como dule X  Y is 
the usual tensor product of X, Y with the coaction map dened as 
follows: if x  X, y  Y , (x)= xi  ai, (y)= yj  bj , then 
XY (x  y)= xi  yj  aibj .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>49 
2) nite dimensional Hopf algebr as over k up to isomorphism. 
Proof. Straigh tforw ard from the above.  
Exercise 1.22.12. The algebra of functio ns Fun(G, k) on a nite 
monoid G is a Hopf algebra if and only if G is a group. In this case, 
the antipode is given by the formula S(f)(x)= f(x1), x  G. 
More generally , if G is an ane algebraic group over k, then the 
algebra O(G) of regular functions on G is a Hopf algebra, with the 
comultiplication, counit, and antipode dened as in the nite case. 
Similarly , k[G] is a Hopf algebra if and only if G is a group, with 
S(x)= x1 , x  G. 
Exercises 1.21.5 and 1.22.12 motiv ate the following denition: 
Denition 1.22.13. In any coalgebra C, a nonzero elemen t g  C 
such that (g)= g  g is called a grouplike element. 
Exercise 1.22.14. Show that if g is a grouplik e of a Hopf algebra H, 
then g is invertible, with g1 = S(g). Also, show that the product of 
two grouplik e elemen ts is grouplik e. In particular, grouplik e elemen ts 
of any Hopf algebra H form a group, denoted G(H ). Show that this 
group can also be dened as the group of isomorphism classes of 1
dimensional H-como dules under tensor multiplication . 
Prop osition 1.22.15. If H is a nite dimensional bialgebr a with an 
antip ode S, then S is invertible, so H is a Hopf algebr a. 
Proof. Let Hn be the image of Sn . Since S is an antihomomorphism 
of algebras and coalgebras, Hn is a Hopf subalgebra of H. Let m be 
the smallest n such that Hn = Hn+1 (it exists because H is nite 
dimensional). We need to show that m = 0. If not, we can assume 
that m = 1 by replacing H with Hm1. 
We have a map S : H1  H1 inverse to S. For a  H, let the triple 
copro duct of a be  
1 2 3 ai  ai  ai . 
i 
Consider the eleme nt 
b = S(S(ai 1))S(ai 2)ai 3 . 
i 
On the one hand, collapsing the last two factors using the antipode 
axiom, we have b = S(S(a)). On the other hand, writing b as 
b = S(S(ai 1))S(S(S(ai 2)))ai 3 
i</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>52 
2) k-linear abelian monoidal categories C with right duals with a ber 
functor F , up to monoidal equivalenc e and isomorphism of monoidal 
functors, and bialgebr as over k with an antip ode, up to isomorphism; 
3) tensor categories C over k with a ber functor F , up to monoidal 
equivalenc e and isomorphism of monoidal functors, and Hopf algebr as 
over k, up to isomorphism. 
Remark 1.23.3. This theore m allows one to give a categorical proof 
of Prop osition 1.22.4, deducing it from the fact that the right dual, 
when it exists, is unique up to a unique isomorphism. 
Remark 1.23.4. Corollary 1.22.15 is not true, in general, in the in
nite dimensional case: there exist bialgebras H with a non-in vertible 
antipode S, see [Ta1]. Therefore, there exist ring categories with sim
ple object 1 and right duals that do not have left duals, i.e., are not 
tensor categories (namely, H  como d). 
In the next few subsections, we will review some of the most im
portan t basic results about Hopf algebras. For a much more detailed 
treatmen t, see the book [Mo]. 
1.24. More examples of Hopf algebra s. Let us give a few more 
examples of Hopf algebras. As we have seen, to dene a Hopf algebra, it 
suces to give an associativ e unital algebra H, and dene a copro duct 
on generators of H (this determines a Hopf algebra struct ure on H 
uniquely if it exists). This is what well do in the examples below. 
Example 1.24.1. (Enveloping algebras) Let g be a Lie algebra, and 
let H = U(g) be the universal enveloping algebra of g. Dene the 
copro duct on H by setting (x)= x  1+1  x for all x  g. It is easy 
to show that this extends to the whole H, and that H equipp ed with 
this  is a Hopf algebra. Moreo ver, it is easy to see that the tensor 
category Rep(H) is equiv alent to the tensor category Rep(g). 
This example motiv ates the following denition. 
Denition 1.24.2. An element x of a bialgebra H is called primitive 
if (x)= x1+1x. The space of primitiv e elemen ts of H is denoted 
Prim(H ). 
Exercise 1.24.3. (i) Show that Prim(H ) is a Lie algebra under the 
comm utator. 
(ii) Show that if x is a primitiv e elemen t then (x) = 0, and in 
presence of an antipode S(x)= x. 
Exercise 1.24.4. (i) Let V be a vector space, and SV be the symmet
ric algebra V . Then SV is a Hopf algebra (namely , it is the universal</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>51 
Proof. (sketch) Consider the ind-ob ject Q := XCF (X)  X. For 
X, Y C and f  Hom(X, Y ), let 
jf : F (Y )  X  F (X)  X  F (Y )  Y  Q 
be the morphism dened by the formula 
jf = Id  f  F (f)  Id. 
Let I be the quotien t of Q by the image of the direct sum of all jf . In 
other words, I = lim (F (X)  X).The following statemen ts are easy to verify: 
(i) I represen ts the functor F (), i.e. Hom(X, I) is naturally iso 
morphic to F (X); in particular , I is injectiv e. 
(ii) F (I)= C, and I is naturally a left C-como dule (the como d
ule structure is induced by the coevaluation morphism F (X)  X 
F (X)  F (X)  F (X)  X). 
(iii) Let us regard F as a functor C C  como d. For M  C 
como d, let M : M IM C I be the morphism M IdIdI , 
and let KM be the kernel of M . Then the functor G : C  como d C 
given by the formula G(M ) = KerM , is a quasi-in verse to F . 
This completes the proof.  
Now assume that the abelian category C is also monoidal. Then the 
coalgebra Coend(F ) also carries a multiplication and unit, dual to the 
comultiplication and counit of End(F ). More precisely , since End(F ) 
may now be innite dimensional, the algebra End(F  F ) is in general 
isomorphic not to the usual tensor product End(F )End(F ), but rather 
to its completion End(F )End(F ) with respect to the inverse limit 
topology . Thus the comultiplication of End(F ) is a continuous linear 
map  : End(F )  End(F )End(F ). The dual  of this map denes 
a multiplication on Coend(F ). 
If C has right duals, the bialgebra Coend(F ) acquires an antipode, 
dened in the same way as in the nite dimensional case. This antipode 
is invertible if there are also left duals (i.e. if C is rigid). Thus Theorem 
1.23.1 implies the following innite extensions of the reconstruction 
theorems. 
Theorem 1.23.2. The assignments (C,F )  H = Coend(F ), H 
(H  Como d, Forget) are mutual ly inverse bijections between 
1) k-linear abelian monoidal categories C with a ber functor F , up 
to monoidal equivalenc e and isomorphism of monoidal functors, and 
bialgebr as over k, up to isomorphism;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>53 
enveloping algebra of the abelian Lie algebra V ). Show that if k has 
characteristic zero, then Prim(SV )= V . 
(ii) What happ ens in characteristic p? 
Hint. One can restrict to a situation when V is nite dimensional. 
In this case, regarding elemen ts f  SV as polynomials on V , one can 
show that f is primitiv e if and only if it is additiv e, i.e., f(x + y)= 
f(x)+ f(y). 
(iii) Let g be a Lie algebra over a eld of characteristic zero. Show 
that Prim(U (g)) = g. 
Hint. Identify U(g) with Sg as coalgebras by using the symmetriza
tion map. 
Example 1.24.5. (Taft algebras) Let q be a primitiv e n-th root of 
unity. Let H be the algebra (of dimension n2) generated over k by g 
nnand x satisfying the following relations: g= 1, x= 0 and gxg1 = qx. 
Dene the coproduct on H by (g)= g  g, (x) = x  g +1  x. It is 
easy to show that this extends to a Hopf algebra structure on H. This 
Hopf algebra H is called the Taft algebr a. For n = 2, one obtains the 
Sweedler Hopf algebra of dimension 4. Note that H is not comm utativ e 
or cocomm utativ e, and S2 =1 on H (as S2(x)= qx). 
This example motiv ates the following generalization of Denition 
1.24.2. 
Denition 1.24.6. Let g, h be grouplik e elemen ts of a coalgebra H. 
A skew-primitiv e elemen t of type (h, g) is an elemen t x  H such that 
(x) = h  x + x  g. 
Remark 1.24.7. A multiple of hg is always a skew-primitiv e elemen t 
of type (h, g). Such a skew-primitiv e elemen t is called trivial . Note that 
the elemen t x in Example 1.24.5 is nontrivial. 
Exercise 1.24.8. Let x be a skew-primitiv e elemen t of type h, g in a 
Hopf algebra H. 
(i) Show that (x) = 0, S(x)= h1xg1 . 
(ii) Show that if a, b  H are grouplik e elemen ts, then axb is a skew-
primitiv e elemen t of type (ahb, agb). 
Example 1.24.9. (Nichols Hopf algebras) Let H = C[Z/2Z](x1, ..., xn), 
where the generator g of Z/2Z acts on xi by gxig1 = xi. De
ne the copro duct on H by making g grouplik e, and setting (xi) := 
xi  g +1  xi (so xi are skew-primitiv e elemen ts). Then H is a Hopf 
algebra of dimension 2n+1 . For n = 1, H is the Sweedler Hopf algebra 
from the previ ous example.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>54 
Exercise 1.24.10. Show that the Hopf algebras of Examples 1.24.1,1.24.5,1.24.9 
are well dened. 
Exercise 1.24.11. (Semidirect product Hopf algebras) Let H be a 
Hopf algebra, and G a group of automorphisms of H. Let A be the 
semidirect product k[G]  H. Show that A admits a unique structure 
of a Hopf algebra in which k[G] and H are Hopf subalgebras.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>50 
and collapsing the rst two factors using the antipode axiom, we get b = 
a. Thus a = S(S(a)) and thus a  H1, so H = H1, a contradiction.  
Exercise 1.22.16. Let op and op be obtained from ,  by permu
tation of comp onents. 
(i) Show that if (H, , i, , , S) is a Hopf algebra, then Hop := 
(H, op, i, , , S1), Hcop := (H, , i, op, , S1), Hcop := (H, op, i, op, , S)op 
are Hopf algebras. Show that H is isomorphic to Hcop, and Hop to Hcop.op 
(ii) Supp ose that a bialgebra H is a comm utativ e ( = op) or co
comm utativ e ( = op). Let S be an antipode on H. Show that 
S2 = 1. 
(iii) Assume that bialgebras H and Hcop have antipodes S and S. 
Show that S = S1, so H is a Hopf algebra. 
Exercise 1.22.17. Show that if A, B are bialg ebras, bialgebras with 
antipode, or Hopf algebras, then so is the tensor product A  B. 
Exercise 1.22.18. A nite dimensional module or como dule over a 
Hopf algebra is invertible if and only if it is 1-dimensional. 
1.23. Reconstruction theory in the innite setting. In this sub
section we would like to generalize the reconstruction theory to the 
situation when the category C is not assumed to be nite. 
Let C be any essen tially small k-linear abelian category , and F : C 
Vec an exact, faithful funct or. In this case one can dene the space 
Coend(F ) as follows: 
Coend(F ) := (XCF (X)  F (X))/E 
where E is spanned by elemen ts of the form y  F (f)x  F (f)y  x, 
x  F (X), y  F (Y ), f  Hom(X, Y ); in other words, Coend(F )= 
lim End(F (X)). Thus we have End(F ) = lim End(F (X)) = Coend(F ), 
which yields a coalgebra structure on Coend(F ). So the algebra End(F ) 
(whic h may be innite dimensiona l) carries the inverse limit topology , 
in which a basis of neigh borhoods of zero is formed by the kernels KX 
of the maps End(F )  End(F (X)), X C, and Coend(F )= End(F ), 
the space of continuous linear functionals on End(F ). 
The following theorem is standard (see [Ta2]). 
Theorem 1.23.1. Let C be a k-linear abelian category with an ex
act faithful functor F : Vec. Then F denes an equivalenc e C 
between C and the category of nite dimensional right comodules over 
C := Coend(F ) (or, equivalently, with the category of continuous nite 
dimensional left End(F )-mo dules).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>( 44 
1.21. Bialgebras. Let C be a nite monoidal category , and (F, J): 
C Vec be a ber functor. Consider the algebra H := End(F ). This 
algebra has two additional structures: the comultiplication  : H 
H  H and the counit  : Hk. Namely , the comultiplication is 
dened by the formula 
(a) = 1 (a)),F,F 
where (a)  End(F  F ) is given by 
X,Y aXY JX,Y , (a)X,Y = J1 
and the counit is dened by the formula 
(a)= a1  k. 
Theorem 1.21.1. (i) The algebr a H is a coalgebr a with comultiplic a
tion  and counit . 
(ii) The maps  and  are unital algebr a homomorphisms. 
Proof. The coasso ciativit y of  follows form axiom (1.4.1) of a monoidal 
functor. The counit axiom follows from (1.4.3) and (1.4.4). Finally , ob
serve that for all ,   End(F ) the images under F,F of both ()() 
and () have comp onents J1 ()XY JX,Y ; hence,  is an algebra X,Y 
homomorphism (whic h is obviously unital). The fact that  is a unital 
algebra homomorphism is clear.  
Denition 1.21.2. An algebra H equipp ed with a comultiplication  
and a counit  satisfying properties (i),(ii) of Theorem 1.21.1 is called 
a bialgebr a. 
Thus, Theorem 1.21.1 claims that the algebra H = End(F ) has a 
natural structure of a bialgebra. 
Now let H be any bialgebra (not necessarily nite dimensional). 
Then the category Rep(H ) of represen tations (i.e., left modules) of 
H and its subcategory Rep(H) of nite dimensional represen tations 
of H are naturally monoidal categories (and the same applies to right 
modules). Indeed, one can dene the tensor product of two H-modules 
X, Y to be the usual tensor product of vector spaces X  Y , with the 
action of H dened by the formula 
XY (a)=(X  Y )((a)),a  H 
(where X : H End(X ),Y : H End(Y )), the associativit y iso  
morphism to be the obvious one, and the unit object to be the 1
dimensional space k with the action of H given by the couni t, a(a).
Moreo ver, the forgetful functor Forget : Rep(H) Vec is a ber func 
tor.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>48 
Corollary 1.22.6. (i) If H is a bialgebr a with an antip ode S, then 
the abelian monoidal category C = Rep(H) has right duals. Namely, 
for any object X, the right dual X is the usual dual space of X, with 
action of H given by 
X (a)= X (S(a)), 
and the usual evaluation and coevaluation morphisms of the category 
Vec. 
(ii) If in addition S is invertible, then C also admits left duals, i.e. 
is rigid (in other words, C is tensor category). Namely, for any object 
X, the left dual X is the usual dual space of X, with action of H given 
by 
X (a)= X (S1(a)), 
and the usual evaluation and coevaluation morphisms of the category 
Vec. 
Proof. Part (i) follo ws from the an tipode ax iom and Prop ositio n 1.22.5. 
Part (ii) follows from part (i) and the fact that the operation of taking 
the left dual is inverse to the operation of taking the right dual.  
Remark 1.22.7. A similar statemen t holds for nite dimensional co
modules. Namely , if X is a nite dimensional right como dule over a 
bialgebra H with an antipode, then the right dual is the usual dual X 
with 
(X (f),x  ) := ((Id  S)(X (x)),f  ), 
x  X, f  X,  H. If S is invertible, then the left dual X is 
dened by the same formula with S replaced by S1 . 
Remark 1.22.8. The fact that S is an antihomomorphism of coalge
bras is the linear algebra version of the categorical fact that dualiza
tion changes the order of tensor product (Prop osition 1.10.7(ii)). 
Denition 1.22.9. A bialgebra equipp ed with an invertible antipode 
S is called a Hopf algebr a. 
Remark 1.22.10. We note that many authors use the term Hopf 
algebra for any bialgebra with an antipode. 
Thus, Corollary 1.22.6 states that if H is a Hopf algebra then Rep(H) 
is a tensor category . So, we get the following reconstruction theorem 
for nite dimensional Hopf algebr as. 
Theorem 1.22.11. The assignments (C,F )  H = End(F ), H 
(Rep(H ), Forget) are mutual ly inverse bijections between 
1) nite tensor categories C with a ber functor F , up to monoidal 
equivalenc e and isomorphism of monoidal functors;</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Exact module categories
Algebras in categories
Internal Hom</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec11/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>112 
Of course, in the case when C = Vec, we get denition of an asso
ciativ e algebra with unit, and in the case C = Vec we get the den ition 
of a nite dimensional associativ e algebra with unit. 
Remark 2.9.2. If C is not closed under direct limits (e.g., C is a 
multitensor category), one can generalize the above denition, allowing 
A to be an ind-o bject (i.e., innite dimensional). However, we will 
mostly deal with algebras honestly in C (i.e., nite dimensional), and 
will make this assumption unless otherwise specied. 
Example 2.9.3. 1. 1 is an algebra. 
2. The algebra of functions Fun(G) on a nite group G (with values 
in the ground eld k) is an algebra in Rep(G) (where G acts on itself 
by left multiplication). 
3. Algebras in VecG is the same thing as G-graded algebras. In 
particular, if H is a subgroup of G then the group algebra C[H] is an 
algebra in VecG. 
4. More generally , let  be a 3-cocycle on G with values in k, and  
be a 2-cochain of G such that  = d. Then one can dene the twiste d 
group algebr a C[H] in Vec , which is hH h as an object of Vec 
G G, 
and the multiplication h  h  hh is the operation of multiplication 
by (h, h). If  = 1 (i.e.,  is a 2-cocycle), the twisted group algebra 
is associativ e in the usual sense, and is a familiar object from group 
theory . However, if  is nontrivial, this algebra is not associativ e in the 
usual sense, but is only associativ e in the tensor category Vec , which, G
as we know, does not admit ber functors. 
Example 2.9.4. Let C be a multitensor categor y and X C. Then the 
object A = X  X has a natural structure of an algebra with unit in 
C given by the coevaluation morphism and multiplication Id evX  Id. 
In particular for X = 1 we get a (trivial) structure of an algebra on 
A = 1. 
We leave it to the reader to dene subalgebras, homomorphisms, 
ideals etc in the categorical setting. 
Now we dene modules over algebras: 
Denition 2.9.5. A (right) module over an algebra (A, m, u) (or just 
an Amodule) is a pair (M, p), where M C and p is a morphi sm 
M  AM such that the following axioms are satised: 
1. The following diagram comm utes:</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>108 
2.7. First properties of exact module categories. 
Lemma 2.7.1. Let M be an exact module category over nite multi-
tensor category C. Then the category M has enough projective objects. 
Proof. Let P0 denote the projectiv e cover of the unit object in C. Then 
the natura l map P0  X 1  X  X is surjectiv e for any X M 
since  is exact. Also P0  X is projectiv e by denition of an exact 
module category .  
Corollary 2.7.2. Assume that an exact module category M over C
has nitely many isomorphism classes of simple objects. Then M is 
nite. 
Lemma 2.7.3. Let M be an exact module category over C. Let P C 
be projective and X M. Then P  X is injective. 
Proof. The functor Hom(,P  X) is isomorphic to the functor 
Hom(P  ,X). The object P  is projectiv e by Prop osition 1.47.3. 
Thus for any exact sequence 
0 Y1  Y2  Y3  0  
the sequence 
0  P   Y1  P   Y2  P   Y3  0 
splits, and hence the functor Hom(P  ,X) is exact. The Lemma is 
proved.  
Corollary 2.7.4. In the category M any projective object is injective 
and vice versa. 
Proof. Any projectiv e object X of M is a direct summand of the object 
of the form P0  X and thus is injectiv e.  
Remark 2.7.5. A nite abelian category A is called a quasi-F robenius 
category if any projectiv e object of A is injectiv e and vice versa. Thus 
any exact module category over a nite multitensor category (in par
ticular, any nite multitensor category itself ) is a quasi-F robenius cat
egory . It is well known that any object of a quasi-F robenius category 
admitting a nite projectiv e resolution is projectiv e (indeed, the last 
nonzero arrow of this resolu tion is an embedding of projectiv e (= injec
tive) modules and therefore is an inclusion of a direct summand. Hence 
the resolution can be replaced by a shorter one and by induction we 
are done). Thus any quasi-F robenius category is either semisimple or 
of innite homological dimension.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>116 
with ind-ob jects, one can extend the theory below to this more general 
case. We leave this for an interested reader. 
Denition 2.10.2. The internal Hom Hom(M 1,M2) is an object of C
represen ting the functor Hom( M1,M2). 
Note that by Yonedas Lemma (M1,M2)  Hom(M1,M2) is a bi
functor. 
Exercise 2.10.3. Show that the functor Hom(, ) is left exact in both 
variable s. 
Lemma 2.10.4. Ther e are canonic al isomorphims 
(1) Hom(X  M1,M2) = Hom(X, Hom(M1,M2)), 
(2) Hom(M 1,X  M2) = Hom(1,X  Hom(M 1,M2)), 
(3) Hom(X  M1,M2) = Hom(M 1,M2)  X, 
(4) Hom(M 1,X  M2) = X  Hom(M 1,M2). 
Proof. Formula (1) is just the denition of Hom(M1,M2), and isomor
phism (2) is the comp osition 
Hom(M 1,X  M2) = Hom(X  M1,M2)=
= Hom(X, Hom(M1,M2)) 
= Hom(1,X  Hom(M1,M2)). 
We get isomorphism (3) from the calculation 
Hom(Y, Hom (XM1,M2)) = Hom(Y (XM1),M2)= Hom((Y X)M1,M2)= 
= Hom(Y  X, Hom(M 1,M2)) = Hom(Y, Hom(M1,M2)  X), 
and isomorphism (4) from the calculation 
Hom(Y, Hom (M1,X  M2)) = Hom(Y  M1,X  M2)=
= Hom(X  (Y  M1),M2)= Hom((X  Y )  M1,M2)=
= Hom(X  Y, Hom(M 1,M2)) = Hom(Y, X  Hom(M1,M2)).
Corollary 2.10.5. (1) F or a xe d M 1, the assignment M 2  Hom(M 1,M2) 
is a module functor MC; 
(2) For a xed M2, the assignment M1  Hom(M 1,M2) is a module 
functor MCop. 
Proof. This follows from the isomor phisms (4) and (3) of Lemma 2.10.4. 
Corollary 2.10.5 and Prop osition 2.7.8 imply 
Corollary 2.10.6. Assume that M is an exact module category. Then 
the functor Hom(, ) is exact in each variable.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>111 
 as (b2)ml0 and as b(bml0 ), and computing the sum of the coecien ts, 
we have:
Nd  cl  d2 
l 
and conseque ntly d  N. So there are only nitely many possibilities 
for |L|, values of ci and consequen tly for expansions biml (since each 
ml appears in bml0 ). The Prop osition is proved. 
In particular, for a given nite multitensor category C there are only 
 nitely many Z+modules over Gr(C) which are of the form Gr(M) 
where M is an indecomp osable exact module category over C. 
Exercise 2.8.8. (a) Classify irreducible Z+modules over ZG (An
swer: such modules are in bijection with subgroups of G up to conju
gacy). 
(b) Classify irreducible Z+modules over Gr(Rep(S 3)) (consider all 
the cases: chark =2, 3, chark = 2, chark = 3). 
(c) Classify irreducible Z+modules over the Yang-Lee and Ising 
based rings. 
Now we can suggest an approa ch to the classication of exact mod
ule categ ories over C: rst classify irredu cible Z+modules over Gr(C) 
(this is a combinatorial part), and then try to nd all possible cate
gorications of a given Z+module (this is a categorical part). Both 
these problems are quite nontrivial and interesting. We will see later 
some nontrivial solutions to this. 
2.9. Algebras in categories. 
Denition 2.9.1. An algebra in a multitensor category C is a triple 
(A, m, u) where A is an object of C, and m, u are morphi sms (called 
multiplication and unit morphisms) m : A  AA, u : 1 A such 
that the following axiom s are satised: 
1. Associativit y: the following diagram comm utes: 
A  A  A mid  A  A 
(2.9.1) idm m 
A  A A 
m 
2. Unit: The morphisms A  1  A  A  A  A and A 
A  1  A  A  A are both equal to IdA.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>118 
Exercise 2.10.9. Chec k that this multiplication is associativ e and 
compatible with the isomorphisms of Lemma 2.10.4.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>113 
pid  M  A  M  A  A 
(2.9.2) idm 
p 
M  A M 
p 
2. The comp osition MM  1 M  AM is the identity.   
The denition of a left module is entirely analogous. 
Denition 2.9.6. The homomorphism between two Amodules (M1,p1) 
 and (M2,p2) is a morphism l  HomC(M1,M2) such that the following 
diagram comm utes: 
M1  A lid  M2  A 
(2.9.3) p1 p2 
l M1 M2 
Obviously , homomorphisms form a subspace of the the vector space 
Hom(M 1,M2). We will denote this subspace by HomA(M1,M2). Itis 
easy to see that a comp osition of homomorphisms is a homomorphism. 
Thus Amodules form a category ModC (A). 
Exercise 2.9.7. Chec k that ModC(A) is an abelian category . 
The following observ ations relate the categories ModC (A) and mod
ule categories: 
Exercise 2.9.8. For any Amodule (M, p) and any X C the pair 
(X  M, id  p) is again an Amodule. 
Thus we have a functor : C ModC(A)  ModC (A). 
Exercise 2.9.9. For any Amodule (M, p) and any X, Y C the 
associativit y morphism aX,Y,M :(X  Y )  MX  (Y  M) is an 
isomorphism of Amodules. Similarly the unit morphism 1  MM
is an isomorphism of Amodules. 
This exercise denes associativit y and unit constrain ts a, l for the 
category ModC (A). 
Prop osition 2.9.10. The category ModC (A) together with functor 
and associativi ty and unit constr aints a, lis a left module category over 
C.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>110 
Remark 2.7.9. We will see later that this Prop osition actually char
acterizes exact module categories. 
2.8. Z+modules. Recall that for any multiten sor category C its Grothe ndiec k 
ring Gr(C) is naturally a Z+ring. 
Denition 2.8.1. Let K be a Z+ring with basis {bi}.A Z+module 
over K is a Kmodule M with xed Zbasis {ml} such that all the 
structure constan ts ailk (dened by the equalit y biml = k ailk mk) are 
nonnegativ e integers. 
The direct sum of Z+modules is also a Z+module whose basis is 
a union of bases of summands. We say that Z+module is indecom
posable if it is not isomorphic to a nontrivial direct sum. 
Let M be a nite module category over C. By denition, the Grothendiec k 
group Gr(M) with the basis given by the isomorp hism classes of sim
ple objects is a Z+module over Gr(C). Obviously, the direct sum of 
module categories corresp onds to the direct sum of Z+modules. 
Exercise 2.8.2. Construct an example of an indecomp osable module 
category M over C such that Gr(M) is not indecomp osabl e over Gr(C). 
Note, however, that, as follows immediately from Prop osition 2.7.7, 
for an indecomp osable exact module category M the Z+module Gr(M) 
is indecomp osable over Gr(C). In fact, even more is true. 
Denition 2.8.3. A Z+module M over a Z+ring K is called irre
ducible if it has no proper Z+submo dules (in other words, the Zspan 
of any proper subset of the basis of M is not a Ksubmo dule). 
Exercise 2.8.4. Give an example of Z+module which is not irre
ducible but is indecomp osable. 
Lemma 2.8.5. Let M be an indecomposable exact module category 
over C. Then Gr(M) is an irreducible Z+module over Gr(C). 
Exercise 2.8.6. Prove this Lemma. 
Prop osition 2.8.7. Let K be a based ring of nite rank over Z. Then 
there exists only nitely many irreducible Z+modules over K. 
Proof. First of all, it is clear that an irredu cible Z+module M over 
K is of nite rank over Z. Let {ml}lL be the basis of M. Let us 
consider an elemen t b := biB bi of K. Let b2 = i nibi and let 
N = maxbiB ni (N exists since B is nite). For any l  L let bml = 
kL dk
l mk and let dl := kL dk
l &gt; 0. Let l0  I be such that d := dl0 
equals minlL dl. Let b2ml0 = lL clml. Calculating b2ml0 in two ways</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>117 
The mere denition of the internal Hom allows us to prove the con
verse to Proposition 2.7.8: 
Prop osition 2.10.7. (1) Supp ose that for a module category M over 
C, the bifunctor Hom is exact in the second variable, i.e., for any object 
N M the functor Hom(N, ): MC is exact. Then M is exact. 
(2) Let M1, M2 be two nonzer o module categories over C. Assume 
that any module functor from M1 to M2 is exact. Then the module 
category M1 is exact. 
Proof. (1) Let P C be any projectiv e object. Then for any N M 
one has Hom(P  N, )= Hom(P, Hom(N, )), and thus the functor 
Hom(P  N, ) is exact . By the denition of an exact module category , 
we are done. 
(2) First we claim that under our assumptions any module functor 
F  FunC(M1, C) is exact. Indeed, let 0 =M M2. The functor 
F ()M  FunC(M1, M2) is exact. Since M is exact, and XM = 
0 implies X = 0, we see that F is exact. 
In particular, we see that for any object N the functor M1, 
Hom(N, ): M1 C is exact, since it is a module functor. Now 
(2) follows from (1).  
Example 2.10.8. It is instruct ive to calculate Hom for the category 
ModC (A). Let M, N  ModC(A). We leave it to the reader as an 
exercise to check that Hom (M, N)=(M A N) (note that N has 
a natural structure of a left Amodule). One deduces from this de
scription of Hom that exactness of A is equiv alent to biexactness of the 
functor A. 
For two objects M1,M2 of a module category M we have the canon
ical morphism 
evM1,M2 : Hom(M1,M2)  M1  M2 
obtained as the image of Id under the isomorph ism 
Hom( Hom(M1,M2), Hom(M1,M2)) = Hom(Hom(M 1,M2)  M1,M2). 
Let M1,M2,M3 be three objects of M. Then there is a canonical 
comp osition morphism 
(Hom(M 2,M3)Hom (M1,M2))M1 = Hom(M2,M3)(Hom(M 1,M2)M1) 
Id evM1,M2 evM2,M3  Hom (M2,M3)  M2  M3 
which produces the multipic ation morphism 
Hom(M 2,M3)  Hom(M 1,M2) Hom(M1,M3).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>114 
Exercise 2.9.11. Prove this Prop osition. 
The following statemen t is very useful: 
Lemma 2.9.12. For any X we have a canonic al isomorphism C 
HomA(X  A, M)= Hom(X, M). 
Exercise 2.9.13. Prove this Lemma. 
Exercise 2.9.14. Is it true that any object of ModC (A) is of the form 
X  A for some X C? 
Exercise 2.9.15. Show that for any M  ModC (A) there exists X C 
and a surjection X  AM (namely , X = M regarded as an object 
of C). 
Exercise 2.9.16. Assume that the category C has enough projectiv e 
objects. Then the category ModC(A) has enough projectiv e objects. 
Exercise 2.9.17. Assume that the category C is nite. Then the 
category ModC (A) is nite. 
Thus we get a general construction of module categ ories from al
gebras in the category C. Not any module category over C is of the 
form ModC (A): for C = Vec the module categ ory of all (possibly in
nite dimensional) vector spaces (see Example 2.5.11) is not of this 
form. But note that for C = Vec any nite module category is of the 
form ModC (A) (just because every nite abelian category is equiv alent 
to Mod(A) for some nite dimensio nal algebra A). We will show later 
that all nite module categories over a nite C are of the form ModC(A) 
for a suitable A. But of course dieren t algebras A can give rise to the 
same module categories. 
Denition 2.9.18. We say that two algebras A and B in C are Morita 
equivalent if the module categories ModC (A) and ModC (B) are module 
equiv alent. 
Note that in the case C = Vec this denition specializes to the usual 
notion of Morita equiv alence of nite dimensional algebras. 
Example 2.9.19. We will see later that all the algebras from Exam
ple 2.9.4 are Morita equiv alent; moreo ver any algebra which is Morita 
equiv alent to A = 1 is of the form X  X for a suitable X C. 
Not any module category of the form ModC (A) is exact: 
Exercise 2.9.20. Give an exam ple of module category of the form 
ModC (A) which is not exact.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>115 
Thus we are going to use the following 
Denition 2.9.21. An algebra A in the category C is called exact if 
the module category ModC (A) is exact. 
It is obvious from the denition that the exactness is invarian t under 
Morita equiv alence. 
We will need the notion of a tensor product over an algebr a A C. 
Denition 2.9.22. Let A be an algebra in C and let (M, pM ) be a right 
Amodule, and (N, pN ) be a left Amodule. A tensor product over 
A, M A N C, is the quotien t of M  N by the image of morphism 
pM  id  id  pN : M  A  N  M  N. 
Exercise 2.9.23. Show that the functor A is right exact in each 
variable (that is, for xed M, N, the functors M A  and A N are 
right exact). 
Denition 2.9.24. Let A, B be two algebras in C. An ABbimo dule 
is a triple (M, p, q) where M C, p  Hom(A  M, M), q  Hom(M 
B, M) such that 
1. The pair (M, p) is a left Amodule. 
2. The pair (M, q) is a right Bmodule. 
3. The morphisms q(pid) and p(idq) from Hom(AM B, M) 
coincide. 
Remark 2.9.25. Note that in the categorical setting, we cannot dene 
(A, B)-bimo dules as modules over A  Bop, since the algebra A  Bop 
is, in general, not dened. 
We will usually say Abimo dule instead of A  Abimo dule. 
Exercise 2.9.26. Let M be a right Amodule, N be an ABbimo dule 
and P be a left Bmodule. Construct the associativit y morphism 
(M A N) A PM A (N A P ). State and prove the pentagon 
relation for this morphism. 
2.10. Internal Hom. In this section we assume that the category C
is nite. This is not strictly necessary but simplies the exposition. 
An importan t technical tool in the study of module categories is 
the notion of internal Hom. Let M be a module category over C and 
M1,M2 M. Consider the functor Hom(M1,M2) from the category 
C to the category of vector spaces. This functor is left exact and thus 
is represen table 
Remark 2.10.1. If we do not assume that the category C is nite, the 
functor above is still represen table, but by an ind-ob ject of C. Working</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Distinguished invertible object
Integrals in quasi-Hopf algebras
Cartan matrix
Basics of Module categories</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec10/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>100 
1.53. Dimensions of projectiv e objects and degeneracy of the 
Cartan matrix. The following result in the Hopf algebra case was 
proved by M.Lorenz [L]; our proof in the categorical setting is analogous 
to his. 
Let Cij =[Pi : Lj ] be the entries of the Carta n matrix of a nite 
tensor category C. 
Theorem 1.53.1. Supp ose that C is not semisimple, and admits an 
isomorphism of additive functors u : Id  . Then the Cartan matrix 
C is degener ate over the ground eld k. 
Proof. Let dim(V )= Tr|V (u) be the dimension function dened by 
the (left) categorical trace of u. This function is additiv e on exact 
sequences, so it is a linear functional on Gr(C). 
On the other hand, the dimension of every projectiv e object P with 
respect to this function is zero. Indeed, the dimension of P is the 
comp osition of maps 1  P  P   P   P   1, where the maps 
are the coevaluation , u  Id, and the evaluation. If this map is nonzero 
then 1 is a direct summand in P  P , which is projectiv e. Thus 1 is 
projectiv e, So C is semisimple by Corollary 1.13.7. Contradiction. 
Since the dimension of the unit object 1 is not zero, 1 is not a linear 
combination of projectiv e objects in the Grothendiec k group tensored 
with k. We are done.  
2. Module categories 
We have seen that the notion of a tensor categor y categ ories the 
notion of a ring. In a similar way, the notion of a module category 
categories the notion of a module over a ring. In this section we will 
develop a systematic theory of module categories over tensor categories. 
This theory is interesting by itself, but is also crucial for under standing 
the structure of tensor categories, similarly to how the study of modules 
is improtan t in understanding the structure of rings. 
We will begin with a discussion of module categories over general 
monoidal categories, and then pass to the k-linear case. 
2.1. The denition of a module category. Let C be a monoidal 
category . 
Denition 2.1.1. A left module category over C is a category M
equipp ed with an action (or tensor product) bifunctor M : CM 
M and a functorial associativity isomorphism (or constr aint) aM : 
() M  (M ), such that the funct or 1M : MM</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>101 
is an autoequiv alence, and aM satises the pentagon relation: 
(2.1.1) 
((X  Y )  Z) M M 
aMaX,Y,Z IdM XY,Z,M 
  
(X  Y )  (Z M M) (X  (Y  Z))  M 
aMaM
X,Y Z,M X,Y,ZMM  IdX aM 
Y,Z,MX  (Y  (Z  M))  X  ((Y  Z) M M) 
is comm utativ e for all objects X, Y, Z in C and M in M. 
Clearly , this denition categories the notion of a module over a 
monoid. 
In a similar way one denes a right C-module category . Namely , a 
right C-module category is the same thing as a left Cop-module category . 
By a module category we will always mean a left module category unless 
otherwise specied. 
Similarly to the case of monoidal categories, for any C-module cate
gory M, one has a canoni cal functorial unit isomorphism lM : 1M 
Id (also called the unit constr aint), and one can give the following 
equiv alent denition of a module category , making this isomorphism a 
part of the data. 
Denition 2.1.2. A left module category over C is a category M
equipp ed with a bifunctor M : CM  M, a functorial isomor
phism aM :() M    (M ), and a functo rial isomorphism 
lM : 1M  Id such that aM satises the pentagon relation (2.1.1), 
and lM satises the triangle relation : 
aM
X,1,M(2.1.2) (X  1) M M X M (1 M M) , 
rX MId IdMlM
M   
X M M 
X C, M M. 
We leave it to the reader to establish the equiv alence of the two 
denitions; this is entirely parallel to the case of monoidal categories. 
Similarly to the case of monoidal categories, one can assume without 
loss of generali ty that 1M = IdM, lM = Id, and we will often do so 
from now on. We will also often suppress the superscript M and write 
 instead of M.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>98 
projectiv e module has the same dimension as its cosocle (i.e., the simple 
quotien t). As follows from the above, these conditions are satised for 
nite dimensional quasi-Hop f algebras (namely , the second condition 
follows from the fact that L is 1-dimensional).  
1.52. Integrals in quasi-Hopf algebras. 
Denition 1.52.1. A left integral in an algebra H with a counit  : 
Hk is an element I  H such that xI = (x)I for all x  H. 
Similarly , a right integral in H is an elemen t I  H such that Ix = (x)I 
for all x  H. 
Remark 1.52.2. Let H be the convolution algebra of distributions 
on a compact Lie group G. This algebra has a counit  dened by 
()= (1). Let dg be  a left-in varian t Haar measure on G. Then 
the distribution I(f)= G f(g)dg is a left integral in H (unique up to 
scaling). This motiv ates the terminology . 
Note that this example makes sense for a nite group G over any 
eld k. In this case, H = k[G], and I = gG g is both a left and a 
right integral. 
Prop osition 1.52.3. Any nite dimensional quasi-Hopf algebr a ad
mits a unique nonzer o left integral up to scaling and a unique nonzer o 
right integral up to scaling. 
Proof. It suces to prove the statemen t for left integrals (for right 
integrals the statemen t is obtained by applying the antipode). A left 
integral is the same thing as a homomorphism of left modules kH.
Since H is Frobenius, this is the same as a homom orphism kH, i.e. 
a homomorphism Hk. But such homomorphisms are just multiples 
of the counit.  
 
Note that the space of left integrals of an algebra H with a counit 
is a right H-module (indeed, if I is a left integral, then so is Iy for all 
y  H). Thus, for nite dimensio nal quasi-Hopf algebras, we obtain 
a character  : Hk, such that Ix = (x)I for all x  H. This 
character is called the distinguishe d character of H (if H is a Hopf 
algebra, it is commonly called the distinguished grouplik e elemen t of 
H, see [Mo]). 
Prop osition 1.52.4. Let H be a nite dimensional quasi-Hopf algebr a, 
and C = Rep(H ). Then L coincides with the distin guishe d character 
. 
Proof. Let I be a nonzero left integral in H. We have xI = (x)I and 
Ix = (x)I . This means that for any V C, I denes a morphism 
from V  1 to V .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>97 
1.51. The distinguished invertible object. Let C be a nite tensor 
category with classes of simple objects labeled by a set I. Since duals 
to projectiv e objects are projectiv e, we can dene a map D : II 
such that Pi  = PD(i). It is clear that D2(i)= i.  
Let 0 be the label for the unit object. Let  = D(0). (In other words, 
L is the socle of P0 = P (1)). We have 
Hom(Pi ,Lj )= Hom(1,Pi  Lj )= Hom(1, kNi 
kj Pk). 
This space has dimension Ni Thus we get j . 
Ni 
j = D(i),j. 
Let now L be the corresp onding simple object. By Prop osition 1.47.2, 
we have 
= kNk = PD(m) . L 
  Pm mPk 
Lemma 1.51.1. L is an invertible object. 
Proof. The last equation implies that the matrix of action of L on 
projectiv es is a permutation matrix. Hence, the Frobenius-P erron di
mension of L is 1, and we are done.  
Lemma 1.51.2. One has: PD(i) = Pi  L; LD(i) = Li  L. 
Proof. It suces to prove the rst statemen t. Therefore, our job is to 
show that dim Hom(Pi ,Lj ) = dim Hom(Pi,Lj  L ). The left hand 
side was computed before, it is Ni On the other hand, the right hand j . 
side is Ni (we use that  =  for an invertible object ). Thesej, 
numbers are equal by the properies of dualit y, so we are done.  
Corollary 1.51.3. One has: Pi = L 
PiL; Li = L 
LiL. 
Proof. Again, it suces to prove the rst statemen t. We have 
Pi = Pi  =(Pi  L) = L   P 
i = L 
  Pi  L 
Denition 1.51.4. L is called the distinguishe d invertible object of C. 
We see that for any i, the socle of Pi is Li := L 
  Li = L 
i  L. 
This implies the following result. 
Corollary 1.51.5. Any nite dimen sional quasi-Hopf algebr a H is a 
Frobenius algebr a, i.e. H is isomorphic to H as a left H-module. 
Proof. It is easy to see that that a Frobenius algebra is a quasi-F robenius 
algebra (i.e. a nite dimensional algebra for which projectiv e and in
jectiv e modules coincide), in which the socle of every indecomp osable</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>102 
The following proposition gives an alternativ e denition of a module 
category . Let M be a category . Consider the category End(M) of 
endofunctors of M. As we know, End(M) is a monoidal category . 
Exercise 2.1.4. Fillthedetails intheproofofProp osition 2.1.3. 
Prop osition 2.1.3. Structur es of a C-module category on M are in a 
natur al 1-1 correspondenc e with monoidal functors F : C End(M). 
Proof. Let F : C End(M) be a monoidal functor. We set 
X  M := F (X)(M), and dene the associativ ity constrain t aM us
ing the monoidal structure on F , as a comp osition (X  Y )  M = 
F (X  Y )(M)  F (X)(F (Y )(M)) = X  (Y  M). 
Conversely , let M be a module category over C. Then for any 
X C we have a functor M  X  M; thus we have a functor 
F : C End(M). Using the associativit y isomorphism aM, one de
nes a monoidal structure on F .  
Clearly , Prop osition 2.1.3 categories the fact in elemen tary algebra 
that a module over a ring is the same thing as a represen tation. 
Remark 2.1.5. Note that under the corresp ondence of Prop osition 
2.1.3, the hexagon diagram for the monoidal structure on F corresp onds 
to the pentagon diagram (2.1.1). One of the sides of the hexagon 
disapp ears due to the fact that the catego ry End(M) is strict, so its 
associativit y isomorphism (whic h is the identity) is suppressed. 
Denition 2.1.6. A module subcategory of a C-module category M is 
a full subcategory M M which is closed under the action of C. 
Exercise 2.1.7. Let M be a C-module category . Show that for any 
X C which has a left dual and any M, N M there a natural 
isomorphism Hom(X  M, N)  Hom(M, X  N). Thus, if C is rigid, 
the functor X is left adjoin t to X, and X is right adjoin t to 
X. 
2.2. Module functors. 
Denition 2.2.1. Let M1 and M2 be two module categories over C.A 
module functor from M1 to M2 is a pair (F, s) where F : M1 M2 
is a functor, and s is a natural isomorphism sX,M : F (X  M) 
X  F (M) such that the following diagrams comm ute: 
(2.2.1) 
F ((X  Y )  M) sXY,M F (X  (Y  M))   (X  Y )  F (M) 
F (aX,Y,M ) 
X  F (Y  M)
sX,Y M Id  sY,M  aX,Y,F (M) 
X  (Y  F (M))</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>105 
Example 2.5.5. Let C be a multitensor category and let C = i,j Cij 
be its decomp osition into comp onents (see Prop osition 1.15.5). Then 
obviously Cij is a (Cii, Cjj )-bimo dule category . 
Example 2.5.6. Let us study when the simplest category M = Vec is 
a module category over a multitensor category C. Obviously Fun(M, M)= 
Vec as a tensor category . Hence by Proposition 2.1.3 the structures of 
the module categor y over C on M are in a natural bijection with tensor 
functors F : C Vec, that is, with ber functors. Thus the theory of 
module categories can be considered as an extension of the theory of 
ber functors. 
Example 2.5.7. Let F : CD be a tensor functor. Then M = D
has a structure of module category over C with X M Y := F (X)  Y . 
Exercise 2.5.8. Dene the associativit y and unit constrain ts for this 
example using the tensor structure of the functor F and verify the 
axioms. 
Example 2.5.9. Let G be a nite group and let H  G be a subgroup. 
Since the restriction functor Res : Rep(G) Rep(H ) is tensor functor, 
we conclude that Rep(H ) is a module category over C = Rep(G). A lit
tle bit more generally , assume that we have a central extension of groups 
1  k  H H  1 represen ting an elemen t   H2(H, k). 
Consider the catego ry Rep(H) of represen tations of Hsuch that any 
  k acts by multiplication by  (thus any object of Rep(H) is a 
projective represen tation of H). Then usual tensor product and usual 
associativit y and unit constrain ts determine the structure of module 
category over C on M = Rep(H). One can show that all semisimple 
indecomp osable module categories over C = Rep(G) are of this form. 
Example 2.5.10. Let C = VecG, where G is a group. In this case, a 
module category M over C is an abelian category M with a collection 
of exact funct ors Fg : MM, Fg(M) := g  M, together with a 
collection of functorial isomorphisms g,h : Fg  Fh  Fgh satisfying the 
2-cocycle relation: 
gh,k  gh = g,hk  hk 
as morphisms Fg  Fh  Fk  Fghk. 
Such data is called an action of G on M. So, module categories over 
VecG is the same thing as abelian categories with an action of G. 
Example 2.5.11. Here is an example which we consider as somewhat 
pathological with respect to niteness properties: let C = Vec and let 
M = Vec be the catego ry of all (possibly innite dimensional) vector</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>103 
and 
(2.2.2) F (1  M) 
F (lM ) 
 s1,M 1  F (M) 
lF (M ) 
 
F (M) 
A module equivalenc e F : M1 M2 of C-module categories is a 
module functor (F, s) from M1 to M2 such that F is an equiv alence 
of categories. 
Clearly , this denition categories the notion of a homomorphism 
(resp ectively, isomorphism) of modules. 
Remark 2.2.2. Note that if lMi = Id then the second diagram reduces 
to the conditi on that s1,M = IdF (M). 
Remark 2.2.3. One can prove a version of Maclanes coherence theo
rem for module categorie s and module functors, stating that positio ns 
of brackets are, essen tially , imma terial (we leave it to the reader to 
state and prove this theorem). For this reason, when working with 
module categories, we will suppress brackets from now on. 
2.3. Module categories over multitensor categories. Our main 
interest will be module categories over multitensor categories (dened 
over a eld k). In this case, we would like to consider module categories 
with an addit ional structure of an abelian category . 
Let C be a multitensor category over k. 
Denition 2.3.1. A (left or right) abelian module category over C is 
a locally nite abelian category M over k which is equipp ed with a 
structure of a (left or right) C-module category , such that the functor 
M is bilinear on morphisms and exact in the rst variable. 
Remark 2.3.2. Note that M is always exact in the second variable 
due to Exercise 2.1.7. 
All module categories over multiten sor categories that we will con
sider will be abelian, so we will usually suppress the word abelian 
from now on. 
Let EndL(M) be the category of left exact functors from M to M. 
This is an abelian category . (Namely , if M is the category of nite 
dimensional como dules over a coalgebra C then EndL(M) is equiv alent 
to a full subcategory of the category of C-bicomo dules, via F  F (C); 
note that F (C) is well dened, since F , being left exact, comm utes 
with direct limits, and thus extends to the ind-completion of M).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>104 
Prop osition 2.3.3. Structur es of a C-module category on M are in 
a natur al 1-1 correspondenc e with exact monoidal functors F : C 
End(M). 
Proof. The proof is the same as that of Prop osition 2.1.3.  
We will also need to consider module functors between abelian mod
ule categories. Unless otherwise specied, we will consider only left 
exact module functors, referring to them just as module functors. 
2.4. Direct sums. There is a very simple construc tion of the direct 
sum of module categories. 
Prop osition 2.4.1. Let M1, M2 be two module categories over C. 
Then the category M = M1 M2 with M = M1 M2 , aM = 
aM1  aM2 , lM = lM1  lM2 is a module category over C. 
Proof. Obvious.  
Denition 2.4.2. The module category M is called the direct sum of 
module categories M1 and M2. 
Denition 2.4.3. We will say that a module category M over C is in-
decomposable if it is not equiv alent to a nontrivial direct sum of module 
categories (that is, with M1, M2 nonzero). 
2.5. Examples of module categories. The following are some basic 
examples of module categories. 
Example 2.5.1. Any multitensor category C is a module category 
over itself; in this case we set M = , aM = a, lM = l. This 
module category can be considered as a categoricati on of the regular 
represen tation of an algebra. 
Example 2.5.2. Let C be a multitensor category . Then one considers 
M = C as a module category over CCop via (XY )MZ = XZY . 
(This can be extended to the entire category CCop by resolving objects 
of this category by injectiv e -decomp osable objects). 
Exercise 2.5.3. Dene the associativit y and unit constrain ts for this 
example using the associativit y and unit constrain ts in C. 
This module category corresp onds to the algebra considered as a 
bimo dule over itself. 
Denition 2.5.4. Let C, D be multitensor categories. A (C, D)-bimo dule 
category is a module category over C  Dop.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>107 
category C considered as a module over C  Cop (see Example 2.5.2) is 
exact. 
Example 2.6.6. Let C and D be a nite multitensor categories and 
let F : CD be a surjective tensor functor. Then the category D
considered as a module category over C (see Example 2.5.7) is exact by 
Theorem 1.49.3. 
Exercise 2.6.7. Show that the assumption that F is surjective is es
sential for this example.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>99 
The elemen t I belongs to the submo dule Pi of H, whose socle is 
the trivial H-module. Thus, Pi  = P (1), and hence by Lemma 1.51.2, 
i = . Thus, I denes a nonzero (but rank 1) morphism P 1  P. 
The image of this morphism, because of rank 1, must be L0 = 1, so 
1 is a quotien t of P  1, and hence  is a quotien t of P. Thus, 
 = L, and we are done.  
Prop osition 1.52.5. The following conditions on a nite dimensional 
quasi-Hopf algebr a H are equivalent: 
(i) H is semisimple; 
(ii) (I)=0 (wher e I is a left integral in H); 
(iii) I2 =0; 
(iv) I can be normalize d to be an idemp otent. 
Proof. (ii) implies (i): If (I) = 0 then k = 1 is a direct summand in 
H as a left H-module. This implies that 1 is projectiv e, hence Rep(H ) 
is semisimple (Corollar y 1.13.7). 
(i) implies (iv): If H is semisimp le, the integral is a multiple of the 
projector to the trivial representation, so the statemen t is obvious. 
(iv) implies (iii): obvious. 
(iii) implies (ii): clear, since I2 = (I)I.  
Denition 1.52.6. A nite tensor category C is unimo dular if L = 1. 
A nite dimensional quasi-Hopf algebra H is unimo dular if Rep(H ) is 
a unimo dular category , i.e. if left and right integrals in H coincide. 
Remark 1.52.7. This terminology is motiv ated by the notion of a 
unimo dular Lie group, which is a Lie group on which a left invarian t 
Haar measure is also right invarian t, and vice versa. 
Remark 1.52.8. Obviously , every semisimple category is automati
cally unimo dular. 
Exercise 1.52.9. (i) Let H be the Nichols Hopf algebra of dimension 
2n+1 (Example 1.24.9). Find the projectiv e covers of simple objects, 
the distinguished invertible object, and show that H is not unimo d
ular. In particular, Sweedlers nite dimensional Hopf algebra is not 
unimo dular. 
(ii) Do the same if H is the Taft Hopf algebra (Example 1.24.5). 
(iii) Let H = uq (sl2) be the small quan tum group at a root of unity q 
of odd order (see Subsection 1.25). Show that H is unimo dular, but H 
is not. Find the distinguishe d character of H (i.e., the distinguished 
grouplik e elemen t of H). What happ ens for the corresp onding graded 
Hopf algebra gr(H)?</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>106 
spaces. Then the usual tensor product and the usual associativ ity and 
unit constra ints determine the structure of module category over C on 
M. 
2.6. Exact module categories for nite tensor categories. Con
sider the simplest tensor category C = Vec. Let M be any abelian 
category over k. Then M has a unique (up to equivalence) structure 
of module category over C. Thus in this case the understanding of 
all module categories over C is equiv alent to the understanding of all 
klinear abelian categories. This seems to be too comp licated even if 
restrict ourselv es only to categories satisfying some niteness conditions 
(for example, to nite categories). Thus in this section we introduce a 
much smaller class of module categories which is quite manageable (for 
example, this class admits an explicit classication for many interesting 
tensor categories C) but on the other hand contains many interesting 
examples. Here is the main denition: 
Denition 2.6.1. Let C be a multitensor category with enough pro
jectiv e objects. A module category M over C is called exact if for any 
projectiv e object P C and any object M M the object P  M is 
projectiv e in M. 
Exercise 2.6.2. Let M be an arbitrary module category over C. Show 
that for any object X C and any projectiv e object Q M the object 
X  Q is projectiv e in M. 
It is immediate from the denition that any semisimple module cat
egory is exact (since any object in a semisimple category is projectiv e). 
Remark 2.6.3. We will see that the notion of an exact module cat
egory may be regarded as the categorical analog of the notion of a 
projectiv e module in ring theory . 
Example 2.6.4. Notice that in the category C = Vec the object 1 
is projectiv e. Therefore for an exact module category M over C any 
object M = 1  M is projectiv e. Hence an abelian category M consid
ered as a module category over C is exact if and only if it is semisimple. 
Thus the exact module categories over Vec are classied by the cardi
nality of the set of the isomorphism classes of simple objects. More 
generally , the same argumen t shows that if C is semisimple (and hence 
1 is projectiv e) then any exact module category over C is semisimple. 
But the classication of exact module categories over non-semisimple 
categories C can be quite nontrivial. 
Example 2.6.5. Any nite multitensor category C considered as a 
module category over itself (see Example 2.5.1) is exact. Also the</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Monoidal functors
MacLane&#8217;s strictness theorem</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec02/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>23 
group with a surjectiv e homomorphism f : GG such that the 3
cocycle f is cohomo logically trivial. Such G
always exists, e.g., a 
free group (recall that the cohomology of a free group in degree s higher 
than 1 is trivial, see [Br]). Let C be the category whose objects g 
are labeled by elemen ts of G, Hom(g,h)= A if g, h have the same 
image in G, and Hom(g,h)=  otherwise. This category has an 
obvious tensor product, and a monoidal structure dened by the 3
cocycle f. We have an obvious monoidal functor F : C C dened 
by the homomorphism GG, and it is an equiv alence, even though 
not an isomorphism. However, since the cocycle f is cohomo logically 
trivial, the category C is isomorphic to the same category with the 
trivial associativit y isomorphism, which is strict. 
Remark 1.8.7. 6 A category is called skeletal if it has only one object 
in each isomorphism class. The axiom of choice implies that any cate
gory is equiv alent to a skeletal one. Also, by MacLanes theorem, any 
monoidal category is monoidally equiv alent to a strict one. However, 
Remark 1.8.6 shows that a monoidal category need not be monoidally 
equiv alent to a catego ry which is skeletal and strict at the same time. 
Indeed, as we have seen, to make a monoidal category strict, it may 
be necessary to add new objects to it (whic h are isomorphic, but not 
equal to already existing ones). In fact, the desire to avoid adding 
such objects is the reason why we sometimes use nontrivial associa
tivity isomo rphisms, even though MacLanes strictn ess theorem tells 
us we dont have to. This also makes precise the sense in which the 
categories Sets, Vec, VecG, are more strict than the category Vec 
G 
for cohomologically nontrivial . Namely , the rst three categories 
are monoidally equiv alent to strict skeletal categories Sets, Vec, VecG, 
while the category Vec is not monoidally equiv alent to a strict skeletal G 
category . 
Exercise 1.8.8. Show that any monoidal category C is monoidally 
equiv alent to a skeletal monoidal category C. Moreo ver, C can be chosen 
in such a way that lX ,rX = IdX for all objects X C. 
Hint. Without loss of generalit y one can assume that 1  X = 
X  1 = X and lX ,rX = IdX for all objects X C. Now in every 
isomorphism class i of objects of C x a represen tative Xi, so that X1 = 
1, and for any two classes i, j x an isomorphism ij : Xi  Xj  Xij ,
so that i1 = 1i = IdXi . Let C be the full subcategory of C consisting 
of the objects Xi, with tensor product dened by XiXj = Xij , and 
6This remark is borrowed from the paper [Kup2].</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>18 
Conversely , given a group homo morphism f : G1 G2, a function  
 : G1  G1 A satisfying (1.7.2) gives rise to a monoidal functor 
F : C1 C2 dened by F (g)= f(g) with the monoidal structure 
given by formula (1.7.1). This functor is an equiv alence if and only if 
f is an isomorphism. 
To summarize, monoidal functors C1 C2 corresp ond to pairs G1 G2 
(f, ), where f : G1 G2 is a group homomorphism such that 1 
and f2 are cohomologous, and  is a function satisfyin g (1.7.2) (such 
functions are in a (non-cano nical) bijecti on with A-valued 2-cocycles 
on G1). Let Ff, denote the corresp onding functor. 
Let us determine natural monoida l transformations between Ff, and 
Ff, . Clearly , such a transform ation exists if and only if f = f, is 
always an isomorphism, and is determined by a collection of morphisms 
g : f (g)  f(g) (i.e., g  A), satisfying the equation 
(1.7.3) (g, h)(g  h)= gh(g, h) 
for all g, h  G1, i.e., 
(1.7.4)  = 1(). 
Conversely, every function  : G1 A satisfying (1.7.4) gives rise to 
a morphism of monoidal functors  : Ff,  Ff, dened as above. 
Thus, functors Ff, and Ff, are isomorphic as monoidal functors if 
and only if f = f and  is cohomologous to . 
Thus, we have obtained the following proposition. 
Prop osition 1.7.1. (i) The monoidal isomorphisms Ff,  Ff, of 
1 2monoidal functors Ff,i : CG1 CG2 form a torsor over the group 
H1(G1,k) = Hom(G1,k) of characters of G1; 
(ii) Given f, the set of  parametrizing isomorphism classes of Ff, 
is a torsor over H2(G1,k); 
(iii) The structur es of a monoidal c ategory on (CG, ) are parametrize d 
by H3(G, k)/Out(G), wher e Out(G) is the group of outer automor
phisms of G. 5 
Remark 1.7.2. The same results, including Prop osition 1.7.1, are 
valid if we replace the categories C by their linear spans Vec , and G G
require that the monoidal functors we consider are additiv e. To see 
this, it is enough to note that by denition, for any morphism  of 
monoidal functors, 1 = 0, so equation (1.7.3) (with h = g1) implies 
5Recall that the group Inn(G) of inner automorphi sms of a group G acts trivially 
on H(G, A) (for any coecien t group A), and thus the action of the group Aut(G) 
on H(G, A) factors through Out(G).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>15 
Prop osition 1.4.3. For any monoidal functor (F, J): CC, the 
diagr ams 
l
1  F (X) F (X) F (X) 
(1.4.3) IdF (X) 
F (1)  F (X) F (lX ) 
J1,X  F (1  X) 
and 
r
F (X)  1 F (X) 

(1.4.4) IdF (X)  F (X) 
F (rX ) 
JX,1  F (X  1) F (X)  F (1) 
are commutative for all X C. 
Exercise 1.4.4. Prove Prop osition 1.4.3. 
Prop osition 1.4.3 implies that a monoidal functor can be equiv alently 
dened as follows. 
Denition 1.4.5. A monoidal functor CC is a triple (F, J, ) which 
satises the monoid al structure axiom and Prop osition 1.4.3. 
This is a more traditional denition of a monoidal functor . 
Remark 1.4.6. It can be seen from the above that for any monoidal 
functor (F, J) one can safely identify 1 with F (1) using the isomor
phism , and assume that F (1)= 1 and  = Id (similarly to how we 
have identied 1  X and X  1 with X and assumed that lX = rX = 
IdX ). We will usually do so from now on. Prop osition 1.4.3 implies 
that with these conventions, one has 
(1.4.5) J1,X = JX,1 = IdX . 
Remark 1.4.7. It is clear that the comp osition of monoidal functors is 
a monoidal functor. Also, the identity functor has a natural structure 
of a monoidal functor. 
1.5. Morphisms of monoidal functors. Monoidal funct ors between 
two monoidal categories themselv es form a category . Namely , one has 
the following notion of a morphism (or natural transformation) between 
two monoidal functors.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>16 
Denition 1.5.1. Let (C, , 1, a, ) and (C, , 1,a,) be two monoidal 
categories, and (F 1,J1), (F 2,J2) two mono idal functors from C to 
C. A morphism (or a natur al transformation ) of monoidal functors 
 :(F 1,J1) (F 2,J2) is a natural transformation  : F 1 F 2 such  
that 1 is an isomorphism, and the diagram 
J1 
X,Y F 1(X)  F 1(Y )  F 1(X  Y ) (1.5.1)
 X Y XY 
J2 
X,Y F 2(X)  F 2(Y )  F 2(X  Y ) 
is comm utativ e for all X, Y C. 
Remark 1.5.2. It is easy to show that 1  1 = 2 , so if one makes 
the convention that i = Id, one has 1 = Id. 
Remark 1.5.3. It is easy to show that if F : CC is an equiv alence 
of monoidal categories, then there exists a monoidal equiv alence F 1 : 
C C such that the functors F  F 1 and F 1  F are isomorphic 
to the identity functor as monoidal functors. Thus, for any monoidal 
category C, the monoidal auto-equiv alences of C up to isomorphism 
form a group with respect to comp osition. 
1.6. Examples of monoidal functors. Let us now give some exam
ples of monoidal functors and natural transformation s. 
Example 1.6.1. An importan t class of examples of monoidal functors 
is forgetful functors (e.g. functors of forgettin g the structure, from 
the categories of groups, topological spaces, etc., to the category of 
sets). Such functors have an obvious monoidal struct ure. An example 
importan t in these notes is the forgetf ul functor RepG Vec from
the represen tation category of a group to the category of vector spaces. 
More generally , if H  G is a subgroup, then we have a forgetful 
(or restriction) functor RepG RepH . Still more generally , if f : 
HG is a group homomorphism, then we have the pullback functor 
f : RepG  RepH . All these functors are monoidal. 
Example 1.6.2. Let f : HG be a homomorp hism of groups. Then  
any H-graded vector space is natural ly G-graded (by pushforw ard of 
grading). Thus we have a natural monoidal functor f : VecH VecG.
If G is the trivial group, then fis just the forgetful functor VecH  
Vec. 
Example 1.6.3. Let A be a k-algebra with unit, and C = A  mod 
be the category of left A-mo dules. Then we have a functor F : A</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>22 
First of all, L essen tially surjectiv e: it is easy to check that for any 
(F, c) C,(F, c) is isomorphic to L(F (1)). 
Letusnowshowthat L isfully faithful. Let L(X) L(Y )bea : 
(1.8.4) XX 1 Y 1 Y.    
Weclaim that forall Z inonehas f Id(sothat L(f)and C= = Z Z 
L isfull). Indeed, thisfollowsfrom thecomm utativit yofthediagram 
1Id Idl r a Z  X,1,Z XZXZ (X 1) Z XZ     
morphism in C. Dene f : XY to be the comp osite  
r1 
X 1 rY 
(1.8.5) 
X 
   X  (1  Z) 
1IdZfIdZ 1Z Z 
Y  Z (Y  1)  Z 
aY,1,Z IdY lZ Y  Z, 
r1 IdZ Y  (1  Z) 
Y 
where the rows are the identity morphisms by the triangle axiom (1.2.1) , 
the left square comm utes by the denition of f, the right square com
mutes by naturalit y of , and the central square comm utes since  is a 
morphism in C. 
Next, if L(f)= L(g) for some morphisms f, g in C then, in particular 
f  Id1 = g  Id1 so that f = g. Thus L is faithful. 
Finally , we dene a monoidal functor structur e JX,Y : L(X)L(Y ) 
L(X  Y ) on L by 
JX,Y = a1 
 : X  (Y ), ((IdX  aY,)  aX,Y ,)X,Y, ,
).  ((X  Y ) ,aXY,,
The diagram (1.8.2) for the latter natural isomorp hism is just the pen
tagon diagram in C. For the functor L the hexagon diagram (1.4.1) 
in the den ition of a monoidal funct or also reduces to the pentagon 
diagram in C. The theorem is proved.  
Remark 1.8.6. The nontrivial nature of MacLa nes strictness theo
rem is demonstrated by the following instructiv e example, which shows 
that even though a monoidal category is always equiv alent to a strict 
category , it need not be isomorphic to one. (By denition, an iso
morphism of monoida l categories is a monoidal equiv alence which is an 
isomorphism of categories). 
Namely , let C be the category CG. If  is cohomologically nontrivial, 
this category is clearly not isomorphic to a strict one. However, by 
Maclanes strictness theorem, it is equivalent to a strict category C. 
In fact, in this example a strict category C monoidally equiv alent 
to C can be construc ted quite explicitly , as follows. Let Gbe another</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>19 
that all g must be nonzero. Thus, if a morphism  : Ff, Ff,
exists, then it is an isomorphism, and we must have f = f. 
Remark 1.7.3. The above discussion implies that in the denition 
of the categories C and Vec it may be assumed without loss of G G, 
generalit y that the cocycle  is norma lized, i.e., (g, 1,h) = 1, and 
thus lg = rg = Id (whic h is convenien t in computations). Indeed, we 
claim that any 3-cocycle  is cohomologous to a norm alized one. To 
see this, it is enough to alter  by dividing it by 2, where  is any 
2-cochain such that (g, 1) = (g, 1, 1), and (1,h)= (1, 1,h)1 . 
Example 1.7.4. Let G = Z/nZ where n&gt; 1 is an integer, and k = C. 
Consider the cohom ology of Z/nZ. 
Since Hi(Z/nZ, C) = 0 for all i&gt; 0, writing the long exact sequence 
of cohomology for the short exact sequence of coecient groups 
0  Z  C  C = C/Z  0, 
we obtain a natural isomorphism Hi(Z/nZ, C) = Hi+1(Z/nZ, Z). 
It is well known [Br] that the graded ring H(Z/nZ, Z) is (Z/nZ)[x] 
where x is a generator in degree 2. Moreo ver, as a module over Aut(Z/nZ) = 
(Z/nZ), we have H2(Z/nZ, Z)  There = H1(Z/nZ, C)=(Z/nZ). 
fore, using the graded ring structure, we nd that H2m(Z/nZ, Z) = 
H2m1(Z/nZ, C) = ((Z/nZ))m as an Aut(Z/nZ)-mo dule. In par
ticular, H3(Z/nZ, C) = ((Z/nZ))2 . 
This consideration shows that if n = 2 then the categorication 
problem has 2 solutions (the cases of trivial and non-trivi al cocycle), 
while if n is a prime greater than 2 then there are 3 solutions: the trivial 
cocycle, and two non-tr ivial cocycles corresp onding (non-canonically) 
to quadratic residu es and non-residues mod n. 
Let us give an explicit formula for the 3-cocycles on Z/nZ. Modulo 
coboundaries, these cocycles are given by 
si(j+k(j+k)) (1.7.5) (i, j, k)=  n , 
where  is a primitiv e nth root of unity, s  Z/nZ, and for an integer 
m we denote by m the remainder of division of m by n. 
Exercise 1.7.5. Show that when s runs over Z/nZ this formula denes 
cocycles represen ting all cohomology classes in H3(Z/nZ, C). 
1.8. MacLanes strictness theorem. As we have seen above, it is 
much simpler to work with monoidal categories in which the associa
tivity and unit constrains are the identity maps. 
Denition 1.8.1. A monoidal category C is strict if for all objects 
X, Y, Z in C one has equalities (X  Y )  Z = X  (Y  Z) and</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>17 
bimo d End(C) given by F (M)= MA. This functor is naturally 
monoidal. A similar functor F : A  bimo d End(C). can be dened 
if A is a nite dime nsional k-algebra, and C = A  mod is the category 
of nite dimensiona l left A-mo dules. 
Prop osition 1.6.4. The functor F : Abimo d End(C) takes values 
in the full monoidal subcategory Endre(C) of right exact endofunctors of 
C, and denes an equivalenc e between monoidal categories A  bimo d 
and Endre(C) 
Proof. The rst statemen t is clear, since the tensor product functor 
is right exact. To prove the second statemen t, let us construct the 
quasi-in verse functor F 1 . Let G  Endre(C). Dene F 1(G) by the 
formula F 1(G)= G(A); this is clearly an A-bimo dule, since it is a 
left A-mo dule with a comm uting action EndA(A)= Aop (the opposite 
algebra). We leave it to the reader to check that the functor F 1 is 
indeed quasi-in verse to F .  
Remark 1.6.5. A similar statemen t is valid without the nite dimen
sionalit y assumption, if one adds the condition that the right exact 
functors must comm ute with inductiv e limits. 
Example 1.6.6. Let S be a monoid, and C = VecS , and IdC the identity 
functor of C. It is easy to see that morphisms  : IdC  IdC corresp ond 
to homomorphisms of monoids:  : Sk (where k is equipp ed with 
the multiplication operation). In particular, (s) may be 0 for some s, 
so  does not have to be an isomorphism. 
1.7. Monoidal functors between categories CG. Let G1,G2 be 
groups, A an abelian group, and i  Z3(Gi,A),i =1, 2 be 3-cocycles. 
iLet Ci = CGi ,i =1, 2 (see Example 1.3.7). 
Any monoidal functor F : C1 C2 denes, by restriction to simple 
objects, a group homomorphism f : G1  G2. Using the axiom (1.4.1) 
of a monoidal functor we see that a monoidal structure on F is given 
by 
(1.7.1) Jg,h = (g, h)Idf (gh) : F (g)  F (h) F (gh), g,h  G1,  
where  : G1  G1  A is a function such that 
1(g, h, l)(gh, l)(g, h)= (g, hl)(h, l)2(f(g),f(h),f(l)), 
for all g, h, l  G1. That is, 
(1.7.2) f2 = 12(), 
i.e., 1 and f2 are cohomologous in Z3(G1,A).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>24 
with all the structure transp orted using the isomorphisms ij . Then C
is the required skeletal category , monoida lly equiv alent to C.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>21 
every monoid M is isomorphic to the monoid consisting of maps from 
M to itself comm uting with the right multiplication. 
For a monoidal category C, let C be the monoidal category dened 
as follows. The objects of C are pairs (F, c) where F : CC is a 
functor and 
cX,Y : F (X)  Y F (X  Y ) 
is a functorial isomorphism, such that the following diagram is com
mutativ e for all objects X, Y, Z in C: 
(1.8.1) 
(
F 
 (X)  Y ) Z 
 cX,Y IdZ aF (X),Y,Z 
F (X  Y )  Z F (X)  (Y  Z) 
cXY ,Z cX,Y Z 
F ((X  Y )  Z) F (X  (Y  Z)). 
F (aX,Y,Z ) 
A morphism  :(F 1,c1)  (F 2,c2) in C is a natural transformation 
 : F 1 F 2 such that the following square comm utes for all objects 
X, Y in C: 
1c
(1.8.2) F 1(X)  Y X,Y F 1(X  Y ) 
X IdY XY 
F2(X)  YF 2(X  Y )2cX,Y 
Comp osition of morphisms is the vertical composition of natural trans
formations. The tensor product of objects is given by (F 1,c1) 
(F 2,c2)=(F 1F 2,c) where c is given by a comp osition 
1 2 cF2(X),Y F1(cX,Y ) 
(1.8.3) F 1F 2(X)  Y  F 1(F 2(X)  Y )  F 1F 2(X  Y ) 
for all X, Y C, and the tensor product of morphisms is the horizon tal 
comp osition of natural transformation s. Thus C is a strict monoidal 
category (the unit object is the identity functor). 
Consider now the functor of left multiplication L : CC given by 
L(X)=(X ,aX,,),L(f)= f . 
Note that the diagram (1.8.1) for L(X) is nothing but the pentagon 
diagram (1.1.2). 
We claim that this functor L is a monoidal equiv alence.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>20 
X  1 = X = 1  X, and the associativity and unit constrain ts are the 
identity maps. 
Example 1.8.2. The category End(C) endofunctors of a category C is 
strict. 
Example 1.8.3. Let Sets be the category whose objects are nonnega
tive integers, and Hom(m, n) is the set of maps from {0, ..., m  1} to 
{0, ..., n  1}. Dene the tensor product functor on objects by mn = 
mn, and for f1 : m1  n1,f2 : m2  n2, dene f1  f2 : m1m2  n1n2 
by 
(f1  f2)(m2x + y)= n2f1(x)+ f2(y), 0  x  m1  1, 0  y  m2  1. 
Then Sets is a strict monoidal category . Moreo ver, we have a natural 
inclusion Sets Sets, which is obviously a monoidal equiv alence.  
Exam ple 1.8.4. This is really a linear version of the previous example. 
Let kVec be the category whose objects are nonnegativ e integers, and 
Hom(m, n) is the set of matrices with m columns and n rows over some 
eld k (and the comp osition of morphisms is the product of matrices). 
Dene the tensor product functor on objects by m  n = mn, and for 
f1 : m1 n1,f2 : m2 n2, dene f1  f2 : m1m2 n1n2 to be the  
Kronec ker product of f1 and f2. Then k  Vec is a strict monoidal 
category . Moreo ver, we have a natural inclusion k  Vec k  Vec, 
which is obviously a monoidal equiv alenc e. 
Similarly, for any group G one can dene a strict monoidal category 
k  VecG, whose objects are Z+-valued functions on G with nitely 
many nonzero values, and which is monoid ally equiv alent to k  VecG. 
We leave this denition to the reader. 
On the other hand, some of the most importan t mono idal categories, 
such as Sets, Vec, VecG, Sets, Vec, VecG, should be regarded as non-
strict (at least if one denes them in the usual way). It is even more 
indisputable that the categories Vec , Vec for cohomologically non-GG 
trivial  are not strict. 
However, the following remark able theorem of MacLane implies that 
in practice, one may always assume that a monoidal category is strict. 
Theorem 1.8.5. Any monoidal category is monoidal ly equivalent to a 
strict monoidal category. 
Proof. The proof presen ted below was given in [JS]. We will establish 
an equiv alence between C and the monoidal category of right C-module 
endofunctors of C, which we will discuss in more detail later. The non-
categorical algebraic counterpart of this result is of course the fact that</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>14 
1.4. Monoidal functors , equiv alence of monoidal categories. 
As we have explained, monoidal categ ories are a categorication of 
monoids. Now we pass to categor ication of morphisms between monoids, 
namely monoidal functors . 
Denition 1.4.1. Let (C, , 1, a, ) and (C, , 1,a,) be two monoidal 
categories. A monoidal functor from isapair (F,J)where toCC
 F : CC is a functor, and J = {JX,Y : F (X)  F (Y ) F (X 
Y )|X, Y  C} is a natural isomorphism, such that F (1) is isomorphic 
to 1. and the diagram 
(1.4.1) 
a
F (X),F (Y ),F (Z)(F (X)  F (Y ))  F (Z)  F (X)  (F (Y )  F (Z))
JX,Y IdF (Z) IdF (X)JY,Z 
F (X  Y )  F (Z) 
JXY,Z  F (X)  F (Y  Z) 
JX,Y Z 
F (aX,Y,Z ) 
F ((X  Y )  Z)

F (X  (Y  Z))
  
is comm utativ e for all X, Y, Z C (the monoidal structure axiom). 
A monoidal functor F is said to be an equivalenc e of monoidal cate
gories if it is an equiv alence of ordinary categories. 
Remark 1.4.2. It is importan t to stress that, as seen from this deni
tion, a monoidal functor is not just a functor between monoidal cate
gories, but a functor with an additional structure (the isomorph ism J) 
satisfying a certain equation (the monoidal structure axiom) . As we 
will see later, this equation may have more than one solution, so the 
same functor can be equipp ed with dieren t monoidal structures. 
It turns out that if F is a monoidal functor, then there is a canon
ical isomorphism  : 1 F (1). This isomorphism is dened by the 
comm utativ e diagram 
l
1  F (1) F (1) F (1)
(1.4.2) IdF (X) F (l1 ) 
J1,1  F (1  1) F (1)  F (1) 
where l, r, l,r are the unit isomorphisms for C, C dened in Subsection 
1.2.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Andruskeiwitsch-Schneider conjecture
Cartier-Kostant theorem
Quasi-bialgebras and quasi-Hopf algebras</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec07/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>68 
The Cartier-Kostan t theorem implies that any ane pro-algebraic 
group scheme over a eld of characteristic zero is in fact a pro-algebraic 
group. Namely , we have 
Corollary 1.33.4. Let H be a commutative Hopf algebr a over a eld 
k of characteristic zero. Then H has no nonzer o nilpotent elements. 
Proof. It is clear that H is a union of nitely generated Hopf subalge
bras (generated by nite dimensional subcoalgebra s of H), so we may 
assume that H is nitely generated. Let m be the kernel of the counit 
of H, and B = 
n=1(H/mn) (i.e., B is the continuous dual of the 
formal completion of H near the ideal m). It is easy to see that B is 
a cocomm utativ e Hopf algebra, and its only grouplik e elemen t is 1. So 
by the Cartier-Kostan t theorem B = U(g), where g =(m/m2). This 
implies that G = Spec(H ) is smooth at 1  G, i.e. it is an algebraic 
group, as desired.  
Remark 1.33.5. Note that Coro llary 1.33.4 is a generaliz ation of 
Corollary 1.27.6. 
1.34. Quasi-bialgebras. Let us now discuss recon struction theory for 
quasi-b er functors. This leads to the notion of quasi-bialgebras and 
quasi-Hopf algebr as, which were introduced by Drinfeld in [Dr1] as 
linear algebraic counterparts of abelian monoidal categorie s with quasi-
ber functors. 
Denition 1.34.1. Let C be an abelian monoidal category over k, 
and (F, J): C Vec be a quasi-b er functor. (F, J) is said to be 
normalize d if J1X = JX1 = IdF (X) for all X C. 
Denition 1.34.2. Two quasi-b er functors (F, J1) and (F, J2) are 
said to be twist equivalent (by the twist J11J2). 
Since for a quasi-b er functor (unlik e a ber functor), the isomor
phism J is not required to satisfy any equations, it typically does not 
carry any valuable structural information, and thus it is more reason
able to classify quasi-b er functors not up to isomorphism, but rather 
up to twist equiv alence combined with isomorphism. 
Remark 1.34.3. It is easy to show that any quasi-b er functor is 
equiv alent to a normalized one. 
Now let C be a nite abelian monoidal category over k, and let 
(F, J) be a normalized quasi-b er functor. Let H = End F be the 
corresp onding nite dimensional algebra. Then H has a copro duct  
and a counit  dened exactly as in the case of a ber functor, which 
are algebra homomorphisms. The only dierence is that, in general,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>65 
1.32. The Andruskiewitsc h-Schneider conjecture. It is easy to 
see that any Hopf algebra generated by grouplik e and skew-primitiv e 
elemen ts is automatically pointed. 
On the other hand, there exist pointed Hopf algebras which are not 
generated by grouplik e and skew-prim itive eleme nts. Perhaps the sim
plest example of such a Hopf algebra is the algebra of regular functions 
on the Heisen berg group (i.e. the group of upper triangular 3 by 3 
matrices with ones on the diagonal). It is easy to see that the comm u
tative Hopf algebra H is the polynomial algebra in generators x, y, z 
(entries of the matrix), so that x, y are primitiv e, and 
(z)= z  1+1  z + x  y. 
Since the only grouplik e elemen t in H is 1, and the only skew-primitiv e 
elemen ts are x, y, H is not generat ed by grouplik e and skew-primitiv e 
elemen ts. 
However, one has the following conjecture, due to Andruskiewitsc h 
and Schneider. 
Conjecture 1.32.1. Any nite dimensional pointed Hopf algebra over 
a eld of characteristic zero is generated in degree 1 of its coradical 
ltration, i.e., by grouplik e and skew-primitiv e elemen ts. 
It is easy to see that it is enough to prove this conjecture for corad
ically graded Hopf algebras; this has been done in many special cases 
(see [AS]). 
The reason we discuss this conjecture here is that it is essen tially a 
categorical statemen t. Let us make the following denition. 
Denition 1.32.2. We say that a tensor category C is tensor-gener ated 
by a collection of objects X if every object of C is a subquotien t of a 
nite direct sum of tensor products of X. 
Prop osition 1.32.3. A pointe d Hopf algebr a H is gener ated by grou
plike and skew-primitive elements if and only if the tensor category 
H  como d is tensor-gener ated by objects of length 2. 
Proof. This follows from the fact that matrix elemen ts of the tensor 
product of como dules V, W for H are products of matrix elements of 
V, W .  
Thus, one may generalize Conjecture 1.32.1 to the following conjec
ture about tensor categories. 
Conjecture 1.32.4. Any nite pointed tensor category over a eld of 
characteristic zero is tensor generated by objects of length 2.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>66 
As we have seen, this property fails for innite categories, e.g., for 
the category of rational represen tations of the Heisen berg group. In 
fact, this is very easy to see categorically: the center of the Heisen berg 
group acts trivially on 2-dimensional represen tations, but it is not true 
for a general rational represen tation. 
1.33. The Cartier-Kostan t theorem. 
Theorem 1.33.1. Any cocommutative Hopf algebr a H over an alge
braically close d eld of characteristic zero is of the form k[G]  U(g), 
wher e g is a Lie algebr a, and G is a group acting on g. 
Proof. Let G be the group of grouplik e elemen ts of H. Since H is 
cocomm utativ e, it is pointed, and Ext1(g, h) = 0 if g, h  G, g = h. 
Hence the category C = Hcomo d splits into a direct sum of blocks C = 
gGCg, where Cg is the category of objects of C which have a ltration 
with successiv e quotien ts isomorphic to g. So H = gGHg, where 
Cg = Hg como d, and Hg = gH1. Moreo ver, A = H1 is a Hopf algebra, 
and we have an action of G on A by Hopf algebra automorph isms. 
Now let g = Prim(A) = Prim(H). This is a Lie algebra, and the 
group G acts on it (by conjugation) by Lie algebra automorphisms. So 
we need just to show that the natural homomorphism  : U(g) A is
actually an isomor phism. 
It is clear that any morphism of coalgebras preserv es the coradical 
ltration, so we can pass to the associated graded morphism 0 : Sg 
A0, where A0 = gr(A). It is enough to check that 0 is an isomorphism. 
The morphism 0 is an isomorphism in degrees 0 and 1, and by 
Corollary 1.29.7, it is injectiv e. So we only need to show surje ctivit y. 
We prove the surjectivit y in each degree n by induction. To simplify 
notation, let us identify Sg with its imag e under 0. Supp ose that the 
surjectivit y is known in all degrees below n. Let z be a homogeneous 
elemen t in A0 of degree n. Then it is easy to see from the counit axiom 
that 
(1.33.1) (z)  z  1  1  z = u 
where u  Sg  Sg is a symmetric elemen t (as  is cocomm utativ e). 
Equation 1.33.1 implies that the elemen t u satises the equation 
(1.33.2) (  Id)(u) + u  1 = (Id  )(u)+1  u. 
Lemma 1.33.2. Let V be a vector space over a eld k of characteristic 
zero. Let u  SV  SV be a symmetric element satisfying equation 
(1.33.2). Then u = (w)  w  1  1  w for some w  SV .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>67 
Proof. Clearly , we may assume that V is nite dimensional. Regard u 
as a polynomial function on V   V ; our job is to show that 
u(x, y)= w(x + y)  w(x)  w(y) 
for some polynomial w. 
If we regard u as a polynomial, equation (1.33.2) takes the form of 
the 2-cocycle condition 
u(x + y, t)+ u(x, y)= u(x, y + t)+ u(y, t). 
Thus u denes a group law on U := V   k, given by 
(x, a)+(y, b)=(x + y, a + b + u(x, y)). 
Clearly , we may assume that u is homogeneous, of some degree d = 1. 
Since u is symmetric, the group U is abelian. So in U we have 
((x, 0) + (x, 0)) + ((y, 0) + (y, 0)) = ((x, 0) + (y, 0)) + ((x, 0) + (y, 0)) 
Computing the second comp onent of both sides, we get 
u(x, x)+ u(y, y)+2d u(x, y)=2u(x, y)+ u(x + y, x + y). 
So one can take w(x) = (2d  2)1u(x, x), as desired.  
Now, applying Lemma 1.33.2, we get that there exists w  A0 such 
that z  w is a primitiv e elemen t, which implies that z  w  A0, so 
z  A0.  
Remark 1.33.3. The Cartier-Kostan t theorem implies that any co
comm utativ e Hopf algebra over an algebraically closed eld of char
acteristic zero in which the only grouplik e elemen t is 1 is of the form 
U(g), where g is a Lie algebra (a version of the Milnor-Mo ore theorem), 
in particular is genera ted by primitiv e elemen ts. The latter statemen t 
is false in positiv e charactersitic. Namely , consider the commutativ e 
Hopf algebra Q[x, z] where x, z are primitiv e, and set y = z + xp/p, 
where p is a prime. Then 
p11  p  
(1.33.3) (y)= y  1+1  y + p ix i  xpi . 
i=1 
Since the numbers 1 
p p
i are integers, this formula (together with (x)= 
x  1+1  x, S(x)= x, S(y)= y) denes a Hopf algebra structure 
on H = k[x, y] for any eld k, in particular, one of characteristic p. But 
if k has characteristic p, then it is easy to see that H is not generated 
by primitiv e elemen ts (namely , the elemen t y is not in the subalgebra 
generated by them).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>72 
Proof. This follows directly from the dualit y axioms.  
Denition 1.35.2. An antip ode on a quasi-bialgebra H is a triple 
(S, , ), where S : HH is a unital antihomom orphism and ,   
H, satisfying identities (1.35.1) and (1.35.2). 
A quasi-Hopf algebr a is a quasi-bi algebra (H, , , ) for which there 
exists an antipode (S, , ) such that S is bijectiv e. 
Thus, the notion of a quasi-Hopf algebra is a generalization of the 
notion of a Hopf algebra; namel y, a Hopf algebra is a quasi-Hopf algebra 
with =1,  =  = 1. 
We see that if in the above setting C has right duals, then H = 
End(F ) is a nite dimensional bialgebra admitting antipode, and if C
is rigid (i.e., a tensor category) , then H is a quasi-Hopf algebra. 
Conversely , if H is a quasi-bialgebra with an antipode, then the 
category C = Rep(H) admits right duals. Indeed, the right dual module 
of an H-module V is dened as in the Hopf algebra case: it is the dual 
vector space V  with the action of H given by 
 h, v  =  , S(h)v ,v  V,   V ,h  H. 
Let vi  fi be the image of IdV under the canonical isomorphism 
End(V ) Then the evaluation and coevaluation maps are  V  V . 
dened using the elemen ts  and : 
evV (f  v)= f(v), coevV (1) = vi  fi. 
Axiom (1.35.1) is then equivalent to evV and coevV being H-module 
maps. Equations (1.35.2) are equiv alent, respectively, to axioms (1.10.1) 
and (1.10.2) of a right dual. 
If S is invertible, then the right dualization functor is an equiv alence 
of categories, so the represen tation category Rep(H) of a quasi-Hopf 
algebra H is rigid, i.e., a tensor categor y. 
Exercise 1.35.3. Let H := (H, , , , S, , ) be a quasi-bialgeb ra 
with an antipode, and u  H be an invertible elemen t. 
(i) Show that if one sets 
(1.35.3) S(h)= uS(h)u1 , = u, and  = u1 
then the triple (S, , ) is an antipode. 
(ii) Conversely , show that any S, , and  satisfying conditions 
(1.35.1) and (1.35.2) are given by formulas (1.35.3) for a uniquely de
ned u. 
Hint. If H is nite dimensional, (ii) can be formally deduced from 
the uniqueness of the right dual in a tensor category up to a unique</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>74 
1.36. Twists for bialgebras and Hopf algebras. Let H be a bial
gebra. We can regard it as a quasi-bialgebra with  = 1. Let J be a 
twist for H. 
Denition 1.36.1. J is called a bialgeb ra twist if HJ is a bialgebra, 
i.e. J = 1. 
Thus, a bialgebra twist for H is an invertible elemen t J  H H such 
that (  Id)(J ) = (Id  )(J) = 1, and J satises the twist equation 
(1.36.1) (Id  )(J )(Id  J) = (  Id)(J )(J  Id). 
Exercise 1.36.2. Show that if a bialgebra H has an antipode S, and J 
is a bialgebra twist for H, then the bialgebra HJ also has an antipode. 
Namely , let J = ai  bi, J1 = a
i  b
i, and set QJ = S(ai)bi. i 
Then QJ is invertible with Q
J 1 = i a
iS(b
i), and the antipode of HJ 
is dened by SJ (x)= QJ1S(x)QJ . In particular, a bialgebra twist of 
a Hopf algebra is again a Hopf algebra. 
Remark 1.36.3. Twisting does not change the category of H-modules 
as a monoidal category , and the existence of an antipode (for nite 
dimensional H) is a categorical property (existence of right duals). 
This yields the above formulas, and then one easily checks that they 
work for any H. 
Any twist on a bialgebra H denes a ber functor (Id,J) on the 
category Rep(H). However, two dieren t twists J1,J2 may dene iso
morphic ber functor s. It is easy to see that this happ ens if there is an 
invertible elemen t v  H such that 
J2 = (v)J1(v1  v1). 
In this case the twists J1 and J2 are called gauge equivalent by the 
gauge transformation v, and the bialg ebras HJ1 ,HJ2 are isomorphic 
(by conjugation by v). So, we have the following result. 
Prop osition 1.36.4. Let H be a nite dimensional bialgebr a. Then 
J  (Id,J) is a bijection between: 
1) gauge equivalenc e classes of bialgebr a twists for H, and 
2) ber functors on C = Rep(H), up to isomorphism. 
Proof. By Prop osition 1.34.7, any ber functor on C is isomorphic to 
the forgetful functor F as an additiv e functor. So any ber functor, up 
to an isomorphism, has the form (F, J), where J is a bialgebra twist. 
Now it remains to determine when (F, J1) and (F, J2) are isomorphic. 
Let v :(F, J1)  (F, J2) be an isomorphism. Then v  H is an 
invertible elemen t, and it denes a gauge transformation mapping J1 
to J2.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>70 
is an H-module isomorphism . The axiom (1.34.4) implies that the 
natural maps lV = Id : 1  V V and rV = Id : V  1 V are also  
H-module isomorphisms. Finally , equations (1.34.3) and (1.34.5) say, 
respectively, that the pentagon axiom (1.1.2) and the triangle axiom 
(1.2.1) are satised for Rep(H ). In other words, Rep(H ) is a monoidal 
category . 
Denition 1.34.6. A twist for a quasi-bialgebra H is an invertible 
elemen t J  H  H such that (  Id)(J ) = (Id  )(J) = 1. Given a 
twist, we can dene a new quasi-bialgebra HJ which is H as an algebra, 
with the same counit, the copro duct given by 
J (x)= J1(x)J, 
and the associator given by 
J = (Id  J)1(Id  )(J)1(  Id)(J )(J  Id) 
The algebra HJ is called twist equivalent to H, by the twist J. 
It is easy to see that twist equiv alent quasi-b er functors produce 
twist-equiv alent quasi-bialge bras, and vice versa. Also, we have the 
following proposition. 
Prop osition 1.34.7. If a nite k-linear abelian monoidal category C
admits a quasi-b er functor, then this functor is unique up to twisting. 
Proof. Let Xi, i =1, ..., n be the simple objects of C. The functor 
F is exact, so it is determined up to isomorphism by the numbers 
di = dim F (Xi). So our job is to show that these numbers are uniquely 
determined by C. 
Let Ni =(Nijk ) be the matrix of left multiplication by Xi in the 
Grothendiec k ring of C in the basis {Xj }, i.e. 
XiXj = Nijk Xk 
(so, k labels the rows and j labels the columns of Ni). 
We claim that di is the spectral radius of Ni. Indeed, on the one 
hand, we have  
Nijmdm = didj , 
so di is an eigen value of NiT , hence of Ni. On the other hand, if ej is the 
standard basis of Zn then for any r  0 the sum of the coordinates of 
the vector Nirej is the length of the object Xr Xj , so it is dominated i 
by dr
i dj. This implies that the spectral radius of Ni is at most di. This 
means that the spectral radius is exactly di, as desired.  
Therefore, we have the following reconstruction theorem.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>71 
Theorem 1.34.8. The assignments (C,F )  H = End(F ), H 
(Rep(H ), Forget) are mutual ly inverse bijections between 
1) nite k-linear abelian monoidal categories C admitting a quasi-
ber functor, up to monoidal equivalenc e of categories. 
2) nite dimensional quasi-bialgebr as H over k up to twist equiva
lence and isomorphism. 
Proof. Straigh tforw ard from the above.	  
Exercise 1.34.9. Supp ose that in the situation of Exercise 1.21.6, the 
functor F is equipp ed with a quasi-monoidal structure J, i.e. an iso
morphism J : F ()  F () F (), such that J1X = JX1 = IdF (X). 
Show that this endows H with the structure of a quasi-bialgebra, such 
that (F, J) denes a monoidal equiv alence C Rep(H ). 
Remark 1.34.10. Prop osition 1.34.7 is false for innite categories. 
For example, it is known that if C = Rep(SL2(C)), and V C is a 2
dimensional repesentation, then there exists a for any positiv e integer 
n  2 there exists a ber functor on C with dim F (V )= n (see [Bi]). 
1.35. Quasi-bialgebras with an antipode and quasi-Hopf alge
bras. Now consider the situation of the previous subsection, and as
sume that the category C has right duals. In this case, by Prop osition 
1.13.5, the right dualization functor is exact; it is also faithful by Prop o
sition 1.10.9. Therefore, the functor F (V ) is another quasi-b er func
tor on C. So by Prop osition 1.34.7, this functor is isomorphic to F . Let 
us x such an isomorphism  =(V ), V : F (V ) F (V ). Then we 
have natural linear maps k  F (V )  F (V ), F (V )  F (V )  k con
structed as in Exercise 1.10.6, which can be regarded as linear maps 
: F (V ) F (V ) and : F (V ) F (V ). Thus, the quasi 	 
bialgebra H = End(F ) has the following additional structures. 
1. The elemen ts ,   H such that for any V C, V = 1 V ,V 
V = V  V . Note that  and  are not necessarily invertible.  
2. The antipode S : HH, which is a unital algebra antihomo   morphism such that if (a) = i ai 1  ai 2 , a  H, then 
(1.35.1)	 S(a 1 
i )a2 
i = (a), a 1 
i S(a 2 
i )= (a). 
i i 
Namely , for a  HS(a) acts on F (V ) by 1  a . F (V )  
Let us write the associator as  = i 1 
i  i 2  3 
i and its inverse 
as 1 
i  2 
i  3 
i . 
Prop osition 1.35.1. One has 
(1.35.2)	 1 
i S(i 2)3 
i =1,S(1 
i )2 
i S(3 
i )=1.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>75 
Prop osition 1.36.5. Let G be a group. Then ber functors on VecG 
up to an isomorphism bijectively correspond to H2(G, k). 
Proof. A monoidal structure on the forgetful functor F is given by a 
function J(g, h) : g  h  g  h, J(g, h)  k. It is easy to see that 
the monoidal structure condition is the condition that J is a 2-cocycle, 
and two 2-cocycles dene isomorphic monoidal structures if and only 
if they dier by a coboundary. Thus, equivalence classes of monoidal 
structures on F are parametrized by H2(G, k), as desired.  
Remark 1.36.6. Proposition 1.36.5 shows that there may exist non-
isomorphic ber functors on a given nite tensor category C dening 
isomorphic Hopf algebras. Indeed, all ber functors on VecG yield the 
same Hopf algebra Fun(G, k). These ber functors are, however, all 
equivalent to each other by monoidal autoequivalences of C. 
Remark 1.36.7. Since Vec does not admit ber functors for cohomo-G 
logically nontrivial , Proposition 1.36.5 in fact classies ber functors 
on all categories Vec 
G.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>69 
 is not coassociativ e, since J does not satisfy the monoidal structure 
axiom. Rather, there is an invertible elemen t   H3, dened by the 
comm utativ e diagram 
(1.34.1) 
 F (X),F (Y ),F (Z)(F (X)  F (Y ))  F (Z)  F (X)  (F (Y )  F (Z)) JX,Y IdF (Z) IdF (X)JY,Z 
F (X  Y )  F (Z) 
JXY,Z   F (X)  F (Y  Z) 
JX,Y Z 
F (aX,Y,Z ) 
F ((X  Y )  Z)

F (X  (Y  Z))
for all X, Y, Z C, and we have the following proposition. 
Prop osition 1.34.4. The following identities hold: 
(1.34.2) (Id  )((h)) = (  Id)((h))1 ,h  H, 
(1.34.3)
(Id  Id  )()(  Id  Id)() = (1  )(Id    Id)()(  1),
(1.34.4) (  Id)((h)) = h = (Id  )((h)),
(1.34.5) (Id    Id)() = 1  1.
Proof. The rst identity follows from the denition of , the second 
one from the pentagon axiom for C, the third one from the condition 
that (F, J) is normalized, and the fourth one from the triangl e axiom 
and the condit ion that (F, J) is normalized.  
Denition 1.34.5. An associativ e unital k-algebra H equipp ed with 
unital algebra homomorphisms  : HH  H (the copro duct) and 
 : H  k (the counit) and an invertible elemen t   H3 satisfying 
the identities of Prop osition 1.34.4 is called a quasi-bialgebr a. The 
elemen t  is called the associator of H. 
Thus, the notion of a quasi-bialgebra is a generalization of the notion 
of a bialgebra; namely , a bialgebra is a quasi-bialgebra with  = 1.11 
For a quasi-bialgebra H, the tensor product of (left) H-modules V 
and W is an H-module via , i.e., in the same way as for bialgebras. 
Also, it follows from (1.34.2) that for any H-modules U, V, W the map
ping 
(1.34.6) = U (V W ): uvw  (uvw) aU,V,W :(U V )W 
11However, note that  can be coasso ciativ e even if  = 1.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>73 
isomorphism. Use this appro ach to obtain the uniqu e possible formula 
for u, and check that it does the job for any H. 
Remark 1.35.4. The non-uniqueness of S, , and  observ ed in Ex
ercise 1.35.3 reect s the freedom in choosing the isomorphism . 
Example 1.35.5. (cf. Example 1.10.14) Let G be a nite group and 
let   Z3(G, k) be a normalized 3-cocycle, see (1.3.1). Consider 
the algebra H = Fun(G, k) of k-valued functions on G with the usual 
copro duct and counit. Set 
= (f, g, h)pf  pg  ph, = (g, g1 ,g)pg, =1, 
where pg is the primitiv e idemp otent of H corresp onding to g  G. 
It is straigh tforw ard to check that these data dene a comm utativ e 
quasi-Hopf algebra, which we denote Fun(G, k). The tensor category 
Rep(F un(G, k)) is obviously equiv alent to Vec 
G. 
It is easy to show that a twist of a quasi-bialgebra H with an antipode 
is again a quasi-bialgebra with an antipode (this reects the fact that 
in the nite dimensional case, the existence of an antipode for H is the 
property of the category of nite dimensional represen tations of H). 
Indeed, if the twist J and its inverse have the form 
  
J = ai  bi, J1 = a
i  bi 
i i 
 then HJ has an antipode (SJ ,J ,J ) with SJ = S and J 
 = i S(ai)bi, 
J = i a
iS(b
i). Thus, we have the following reconstruction theorem. 
Theorem 1.35.6. The assignments (C,F )  H = End(F ), H 
(Rep(H ), Forget) are mutual ly inverse bijections between 
(i) nite abelian k-linear monoidal categories C with right duals ad
mitting a quasi-b er functor, up to monoidal equivalenc e of categories, 
and nite dimensional quasi-bialgebr as H over k with an antip ode, up 
to twist equivalenc e and isomorphism; 
(ii) nite tensor categories C admitting a quasi-b er functor, up to 
monoidal equivalenc e of categories, and nite dimensional quasi-Hopf 
algebr as H over k, up to twist equivalenc e and isomorphism. 
Remark 1.35.7. One can dene the dual notions of a coquasi-bialgebra 
and coquasi-Hopf algebra, and prove the corresp onding reconstruction 
theorems for tensor categories which are not necessarily nite. This is 
straigh tforw ard, but fairly tedious, and we will not do it here.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Tensor categories
Deligne&#8217;s tensor product
Finite (multi)tensor categories
Categorical freeness</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-769-topics-in-lie-theory-tensor-categories-spring-2009/resources/mit18_769s09_lec09/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>93 
Proof. We have FPdim(X i) dim Hom(Pi,Z)= FPdim(Z ) for any obi 
ject Z of C.  Hence,  
FPdim(X i) dim Hom(Pi  Z, Y ) = FPdim(X i) dim Hom(Pi, Y  Z) 
i i 
= FPdim(Y  Z) 
= FPdim(Y ) FPdim(Z) 
= FPdim(Y ) FPdim(Z ) 
= FPdim(Z ) FPdim(X i) dim Hom(Pi, Y ). 
i 
Now, P (X)Z are projectiv e objects by Prop osition 1.13.6. Hence, the 
formal sums FPdim(X i)PiZ = RCZ and FPdim(Z ) FPdim(X i)Pi = i i 
FPdim(Z )RC are linear combination s of Pj ,j  I with the same coe
cients.  
Remark 1.47.8. We note the following useful inequalit y: 
(1.47.4) FPdim(C)  N FPdim(P ), 
where N is the number of simple objects in C, and P is the projectiv e 
cover of the neutral object 1. Indeed, for any simple object V the 
projectiv e object P (V )  V has a nontrivial homomorphism to 1, and 
hence contains P . So FPdim(P (V )) FPdim(V )  FPdim(P ). Adding 
these inequalities over all simple V , we get the result. 
1.48. Integral tensor categories. 
Denition 1.48.1. A transitiv e unital Z+-ring A of nite rank is said 
to be integral if FPdim : A Z (i.e. the Frobenius-P erron dimnensions 
of elemen ts of C are integers). A tensor catego ry C is integral if Gr(C) 
is integral. 
Prop osition 1.48.2. A nite tensor category C is integral if and only 
if C is equivalent to the representation category of a nite dimensional 
quasi-Hopf algebr a. 
Proof. The if part is clear from Example 1.45.6. To prove the only 
if part, it is enoug h to construct a quasi-b er functo r on C. Dene 
P = i FPdim(X i)Pi, where Xi are the simple objects of C, and Pi 
are their projective covers. Dene F = Hom(P, ). Obviously , F is 
exact and faithful, F (1) = 1, and dim F (X)= FPdim(X ) for all X  
C. Using Prop osition 1.46.2, we continue the functors F () and 
F ()  F () to the functors C  C Vec. Both of these functors are 
exact and take the same values on the simple objects of C  C. Thus 
these functors are isomorphic and we are done.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>90 
eigen values of the matrix BBT , which is symmetric and nonnegativ e 
denite), so all conjugates of (B) are real. Thus, if q is a conjugate of 
q then q +q1 is real with absolute value &lt; 2 (by the Frobenius-P erron  
theorem), so |q| = 1. By a well known result in elementary algebraic 
number theory , this implies that q is a root of unity: q = e2ik/m, where 
k and m are coprime . By the Frobenius-P erron theorem, so k = 1, 
and m is even (indeed, if m =2p + 1 is odd then |qp + qp| &gt; |q + q1|). 
So q = ei/n for some integer n  2, and we are done.  
Corollary 1.45.16. Let A be a fusion ring, and X  A a basis ele
ment. Then if F P dim(X ) &lt; 2 then F P dim(X ) = 2cos(/n), for some 
integer n  3. 
Proof. This follows from Prop osition 1.45.15, since F P dim(XX)= 
F P dim(X )2 .  
1.46. Delignes tensor product of nite abelian categories. Let 
C, D be two nite abelian categories over a eld k. 
Denition 1.46.1. Delignes tensor product C  D is an abelian cat
egory which is universal for the functor assigning to every k-linear 
abelian category A the category of right exact in both variables bilin
ear bifunctors CD A. That is, there is a bifunctor  : CD  
C  D :(X, Y )  X  Y which is right exact in both variables and is 
such that for any right exact in both variables bifunctor F : CD  A 
there exists a unique right exact functor F: C  DA satisfying 
F = F . 
Prop osition 1.46.2. (cf. [D, Prop osition 5.13] ) (i) The tensor product 
C  D exists and is a nite abelian category. 
(ii) It is unique up to a unique equivalenc e. 
(iii) Let C, D be nite dimensional algebr as and let C = C  mod 
and D = D  mod. Then C  D = C  D  mod. 
(iv) The bifunctor  is exact in both variables and satises 
HomC(X1,Y1)  HomD(X2,Y2) = HomCD(X1  X2,Y1  Y2). 
(v) any biline ar bifunctor F : CD A exact in each variable 
denes an exact functor F: C  DA. 
Proof. (sketch). (ii) follows from the universal property in the usual 
way. 
(i) As we know, a nite abelian category is equiv alent to the category 
of nite dimensional modules over an algebra. So there exist nite 
dimensional algebras C, D such that C = C  mod, D = D  mod. 
Then one can dene C  D = C  D  mod, and it is easy to show that</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>94 
Corollary 1.48.3. The assignment H  Rep(H ) denes a bijection 
between integral nite tensor categories C over k up to monoidal equiva
lence, and nite dimensional quasi-Hopf algebr as H over k, up to twist 
equivalenc e and isomorphism. 
1.49. Surjectiv e quasi-tensor functors. Let C, D be abelian cate
gories. Let F : CD be an additiv e functor. 
Denition 1.49.1. We will say that F is surje ctive if any object of D
is a subquotien t in F (X) for some X C. 13 
Exercise 1.49.2. Let A, B be coalgebras, and f : AB a homomor
phism. Let F = f : A  como d  B  como d be the corresp onding 
pushforw ard functor. Then F is surjectiv e if and only if f is surjectiv e. 
Now let C, D be nite tensor categories. 
Theorem 1.49.3. ([EO]) Let F : CD be a surje ctive quasi-tensor 
functor. Then F maps projective objects to projective ones. 
Proof. Let C be a nite tensor category , and X C. Let us write 
X as a direct sum of indecomp osable objects (such a represen tation 
is unique ). Dene the projectivity defect p(X) of X to be the sum 
of Frobenius-P erron dimensions of all the non-pr ojectiv e summands in 
this sum (this is well dened by the Krull-S chmidt theorem). It is clear 
that p(X  Y )= p(X)+ p(Y ). Also, it follows from Prop osition 1.13.6 
that p(X  Y )  p(X)p(Y ). 
Let Pi be the indecomp osable projectiv e objects in C. Let Pi  Pj = 
kBk Pk, and let Bi be the matrix with entries Bk Also, let B = Bi.ij ij . 
Obviously , B has strictly positiv e entries, and the Frobenius-P erron 
eigen value of B is i FPdim(P i). 
On the other hand, let F : CD be a surjecti ve quasi-tensor functor 
between nite tensor categories. Let pj = p(F (Pj )), and p be the vector 
with entries pj . Then we get pipj Bk so ( pi)p  Bp.  k ij pk, i 
So, either pi are all zero, or they are all positiv e, and the norm of 
B with respect to the norm |x| = pi|xi| is at most pi. Since 
pi  FPdim(P i), this implies pi = FPdim(P i) for all i (as the largest 
eigen value of B is i FPdim(P i)). 
Assume the second option is the case. Then F (Pi) do not contain 
nonzero projectiv e objects as direct summands, and hence for any pro
jectiv e P C, F (P ) cannot contain a nonzero projectiv e object as a 
direct summand. However, let Q be a projectiv e object of D. Then, 
13This denition does not coincide with a usual categorical denition of surjec
tivity of functors which requires that every object of D be isomorphic to some F (X) 
for an object X in C.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>88 
where H is the regular represen tation of H. Thus X  H = dim(X)H, 
so FPdim(X ) = dim(X) for all X, and R = H up to scaling. 
This example motivates the following denition . 
Denition 1.45.7. The elemen t R will be called a regular element of 
A. 
Prop osition 1.45.8. Let A be as above and  : II be a bijection 
which extends to an anti-automorphism of A. Then FPdim is invariant 
under . 
Proof. Let X  I. Then the matrix of right multiplication by X is 
the transp ose of the matrix of left multiplication by X modied by 
the permutation . Thus the required statemen t follows from Prop osi
tion 1.45.5(2).  
Corollary 1.45.9. Let C be a ring category with right duals and nitely 
many simple objects, and let X be an object in C. If FPdim(X )=1 
then X is invertible. 
Proof. By Exercise 1.15.10(d) it is sucien t to show that X  X = 
1. This follows from the facts that 1 is contained in X  X and 
FPdim(X  X)= FPdim(X ) FPdim(X) = 1.  
Prop osition 1.45.10. Let f : A1  A2 be a unital homomorphism of 
transitive unital Z+-rings of nite rank, whose matrix in their Z+-bases 
has non-ne gative entries. Then 
(1) f preserves Frobenius-Perr on dimensions. 
(2) Let I1,I2 be the Z+-bases of A1,A2, and suppose that for any 
Y in I2 there exists X  I1 such that the coecient of Y in 
f(X) is non-zer o. If R is a regular element of A1 then f(R) is 
a regular element of A2. 
Proof. (1) The function X  FPdim(f (X)) is a nonzero character of 
A1 with nonnegativ e values on the basis. By Prop osition 1.45.5(3), 
FPdim(f (X)) = FPdim(X ) for all X in I. (2) By part (1) we have 
(1.45.1) f( X)f(R1)= FPdim(f ( X))f(R1). 
 XI1 XI1 
But f( XI1 X) has strictly positiv e coecien ts in I2, hence f(R1)= 
R2 for some &gt; 0. Applying FPdim to both sides, we get the result. 
Corollary 1.45.11. Let C and D be tensor categories with nitely 
many classes of simple objects. If F : CD be a quasi-tensor functor, 
then FPdimD(F (X)) = FPdimC (X) for any X in C.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>86 
1.45. Tensor categories with nitely man y simple ob jects. Frobenius-
Perron dimensions. Let A be a Z+-ring with Z+-basis I. 
Denition 1.45.1. We will say that A is transitive if for any X, Z  I 
there exist Y1,Y2  I such that XY1 and Y2X involve Z with a nonzero 
coecien t. 
Prop osition 1.45.2. If C is a ring category with right duals then Gr(C) 
is a transitive unital Z+-ring. 
Proof. Recall from Theorem 1.15.8 that the unit object 1 in C is simple. 
So Gr(C) is unital. This implies that for any simple objects X, Z of C, 
the object X  X  Z contains Z as a comp osition factor (as X  X 
contains 1 as a comp osition factor), so one can nd a simple object 
Y1 occurring in X  Z such that Z occurs in X  Y1. Similarly , the 
object Z  X  X contains Z as a comp osition factor, so one can nd 
a simple object Y2 occurring in Z  X such that Z occurs in Y2  X. 
Thus Gr(C) is transitiv e.  
Let A be a transitiv e unital Z+-ring of nite rank. Dene the group 
homomorphism FPdim : A  C as follows. For X  I, let FPdim(X ) be 
the maximal nonnegativ e eigen value of the matrix of left multiplication 
by X. It exists by the Frobenius-P erron theorem, since this matrix has 
nonnegativ e entries. Let us extend FPdim from the basis I to A by 
additivit y. 
Denition 1.45.3. The function FPdim is called the Frobenius-Perr on 
dimension. 
In particular, if C is a ring categ ory with right duals and nitely many 
simple objects, then we can talk about Frobenius-P erron dimensions of 
objects of C. 
Prop osition 1.45.4. Let X  I. 
(1)	The numb er  = FPdim(X ) is an algebr aic integer, and for any
algebr aic conjugate  of  we have  ||.
(2)	FPdim(X )  1. 
Proof. (1) Note that  is an eigen value of the integer matrix NX of left 
multiplication by X, hence  is an algebraic integer. The number  is 
a root of the characteristic polynomial of NX , so it is also an eigenvalue 
of NX . Thus by the Frobenius-P erron theorem  ||. 
(2) Let r be the number of algebraic conjugates of . Then r 
N() where N() is the norm of . This implies the statemen t since 
N()  1.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>89 
Example 1.45.12. (Tambara-Y amagami fusion rings) Let G be a 
nite group, and TYG be an extension of the unital based ring Z[G]: 
TYG := Z[G]  ZX, 
where X is a new basis vector with gX = Xg = X, X2 = gG g. This 
is a fusion ring, with X = X. It is easy to see that FPdim(g ) = 1, 
FPdim(X )= |G|1/2 . We will see later that these rings are categori able 
if and only if G is abelian. 
Example 1.45.13. (Verlinde rings for sl2). Let k be a nonnegativ e 
integer. Dene a unital Z+-ring Verk = Verk(sl2) with basis Vi, i = 
0, ..., k (V0 = 1), with dualit y given by Vi  = Vi and multiplication 
given by the truncated Clebsc h-Gordan rule: 
min(i+j,2k(i+j)) 
(1.45.2) Vi  Vj = Vl. 
l=|ij|,i+jl2Z 
It other words, one computes the product by the usual Clebsc h-Go rdan 
rule, and then deletes the terms that are not dened (Vi with i&gt;k) and 
also their mirror images with respect to point k +1. We will show later 
that this ring admits categorications coming from quan tum groups at 
roots of unity. 
Note that Ver0 = Z, Ver1 = Z[Z 2], Ver2 = TYZ2 . The latter is 
called the Ising fusion ring, as it arises in the Ising model of statistical 
mechanics. 
Exercise 1.45.14. Show that FPdim(V j )=[j+1]q := qj+1qj1 , where qq1 
i q = ek+2 . 
Note that the Verlinde ring has a subring Ver0 
k spanned by Vj with 
even j. If k = 3, this ring has basis 1,X = V2 with X2 = X +1,X = 
X. This ring is called the Yang-L ee fusion ring. In the Yang-Lee ring, 
FPdim(X ) is the golden ratio 1+
2 
5 . 
Note that one can dene the generalized Yang-Lee fusion rings YLn 
n  Z+, with basis 1,X, multipli cation X2 = 1+nX and dualit y X = 
X. It is, however, shown in [O2] that these rings are not categoriable 
when n&gt; 1. 
Prop osition 1.45.15. (Kronecker) Let B be a matrix with nonne gative 
integer entries, such that (BBT )= (B)2 . If (B) &lt; 2 then (B)= 
2 cos(/n) for some integer n  2. 
Proof. Let (B)= q + q1 . Then q is an algebraic integer, and |q| = 
1. Moreo ver, all conjugates of (B)2 are nonnegativ e (since they are</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>92 
Prop osition 1.47.1. Let C be a nite multitensor category. Then 
K0(C) is a Gr(C)-bimo dule. 
Proof. This follows from the fact that the tensor product of a projectiv e 
object with any object is projectiv e, Proposition 1.13.6.  
Let us describ e this bimodule explicitly . 
Prop osition 1.47.2. For any object Z of C, 
= j,kNi = j,kNiPi  Z kj [Z : Xj ]Pk,Z  Pi jk[Z : Xj ]Pk. 
Proof. Hom(Pi  Z, Xk)= Hom(Pi,Xk  Z), and the rst formula 
follows from Prop ositio n 1.13.6. The second formula is analogous.  
Prop osition 1.47.3. Let P be a projective object in a multitensor 
category C. Then P  is also projective. Henc e, any projective object in 
a multitensor category is also injective. 
Proof. We need to show that the functor Hom(P , ) is exact. This
functor is isomo rphic to Hom(1,P ). The functor P  is exact 
and moreo ver, by Prop osition 1.13.6, any exact sequence splits after 
tensoring with P , as an exact sequenc e consisting of projectiv e objects. 
The Prop osition is proved.  
Prop osition 1.47.3 implies that an indecomp osable projectiv e object 
P has a unique simple subobject, i.e. that the socle of P is simple. 
For any nite tensor category C dene an elemen t RC  K0(C) ZC 
by 
(1.47.2) R= FPdim (Xi)Pi. C 
iI 
Denition 1.47.4. The virtual projectiv e object RC is called the reg
ular object of C. 
Denition 1.47.5. Let C be a nite tensor category . Then the Frobenius-
Perr on dimension of C is dened by 
(1.47.3) FPdim(C) := FPdim(RC)= FPdim(X i) FPdim(P i). 
iI 
Example 1.47.6. Let H be a nite dimensional quasi-Hopf algebra. 
Then FPdim(Rep(H )) = dim(H). 
Prop osition 1.47.7. (1) Z  RC = RC  Z = FPdim(Z )RC for all 
Z  Gr(C). 
(2) The image of RC in Gr(C) ZC is a regular element.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCou rseWare 
http://ocw.mit.edu 
18.769 Topics in Lie Theory: Tensor Categories 
Spring 2009 
For information about citing these materials or our T erms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>95 
since F is surjectiv e, there exists an object X C such that Q is a 
subquotien t of F (X). Since any X is a quotient of a projectiv e object, 
and F is exact, we may assume that X = P is projectiv e. So Q occurs 
as a subquotien t in F (P ). As Q is both projectiv e and injectiv e, it is 
actually a direct summand in F (P ). Contradiction. 
Thus, pi = 0 and F (Pi) are projectiv e. The theorem is proved.  
1.50. Categorical freeness. Let C, D be nite tensor categories, and 
F : CD be a quasi-tensor functor. 
Theorem 1.50.1. One has 
FPdim(C)(1.50.1) F (RC )= FPdim(D) RD. 
Proof. By Theorem 1.49.3, F (RC) is a virtually projective object. Thus, 
F (RC ) must be proportional to RD, since both (whe n written in the ba
sis Pi) are eigen vectors of a matrix with strict ly positiv e entries with its 
Frobenius-Perron eigen value. (For this matrix we may take the matrix 
of multiplication by F (X), where X is such that F (X) contains as com
position factors all simple objects of D; such exists by the surjectivit y 
of F ). The coecien t is obtained by computing the Frobenius-P erron 
dimensions of both sides.  
Corollary 1.50.2. In the ab ove situation, one has FPdim(C)  FPdim(D), 
and FPdim(D) divides FPdim(C) in the ring of algebr aic integers. In 
fact, 
FPdim(C)  
(1.50.2) FPdim(D)= FPdim(X i) dim Hom(F (Pi), 1D), 
wher e Xi runs over simple objects of C. 
Proof. The statemen t is obtained by computing the dimension of Hom(, 1D) 
for both sides of (1.50.1).  
Supp ose now that C is integral, i.e., by Prop osition 1.48.2, it is the 
represen tation category of a quasi-Hopf algebra H. In this case, RC
is an honest (not only virtual) projectiv e object of C, namely the free 
rank 1 module over H. Theorefore, multiples of RC are free H-modules 
of nite rank, and vice versa. 
Then Theorem 1.49.3 and the fact that F (RC ) is proportional to RD
implies the following categori cal freeness result. 
Corollary 1.50.3. If C is integral, and F : CD is a surje ctive 
quasi-tensor functor then D is also integral, and the object F (RC) is 
free of rank FPdim(C)/ FPdim(D) (which is an integer).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>96 
Proof. The Frobenius-P erron dimensions of simple objects of D are 
coordinates of the unique eigen vector of the positiv e integer matrix of 
multiplication by F (RC ) with integer eigen value FPdim(C), normalized 
so that the comp onent of 1 is 1. Thus, all coordinates of this vector are 
rational numbers, hence integers (because they are algebraic integers). 
This implies that the category D is integral. The second statemen t is 
clear from the above.  
Corollary 1.50.4. ([Scha]; for the semisimple case see [ENO1]) A 
nite dimensional quasi-Hopf algebra is a free module over its quasi-
Hopf subalgebra. 
Remark 1.50.5. In the Hopf case Corollary 1.50.3 is well known and 
much used; it is due to Nichols and Zoeller [NZ].</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>91 
it satises the required conditions. This togeth er with (ii) also implies 
(iii). 
(iv),(v) are routine.  
A similar result is valid for locally nite categories.
Delignes tensor product can also be applied to functors. Namel y, if
F : CC and G : DD are additiv e right exact functors between 
nite abelian categorie s then one can dene the functor F G : CD  
C  D.
Prop osition 1.46.3. If C, D are multitensor categories then the cate
gory C  D has a natur al structur e of a multitensor category.
Proof. Let X1  Y1,X2  Y2 C  D. Then we can set 
(X1  Y1)  (X2  Y2) := (X1  X2)  (Y1  Y2). 
and dene the associativit y isomorphism in the obvious way. This 
denes a structure of a monoidal category on the subcatego ry of C  
D consisting of -decomp osable objects of the form X  Y . But 
any object of C  D admits a resolut ion by -decomp osable injectiv e 
objects. This allows us to use a standard argumen t with resolution s to 
extend the tensor product to the entire category C D. It is easy to see 
that if C, D are rigid, then so is C D, which implies the statemen t.  
1.47. Finite (multi)tensor categories. In this subsection we will 
study general properties of nite multitensor and tensor categories. 
Recall that in a nite abelian categor y, every simple object X has a 
projectiv e cover P (X). The object P (X) is unique up to a non-uniqu e 
isomorphism. For any Y in C one has 
(1.47.1) dim Hom(P (X),Y )=[Y : X]. 
Let K0(C) denote the free abelian group generated by isomorphism 
classes of indeco mposable projectiv e objects of a nite abelian category 
C. Elemen ts of K0(C) ZC will be called virtual projectiv e objects. We 
have an obvious homomorphism  : K0(C) Gr(C). Although groups 
K0(C) and Gr(C) have the same rank, in general  is neither surjectiv e 
nor injectiv e even after tensoring with C. The matrix C of  in the 
natural basis is called the Cartan matrix of C; its entries are [P (X): Y ], 
where X, Y are simple objects of C. 
Now let C be a nite multitensor category , let I be the set of isomor
phism classes of simple objects of C, and let i, i denote the right and 
left duals to i, respectively. Let Gr(C) be the Grothendiec k ring of C, 
spanned by isomorph ism classes of the simple objects Xi,i  I. In this 
ring, we have XiXj = k Nijk Xk, where Nijk are nonnegativ e integers. 
Also, let Pi denote the projectiv e covers of Xi.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>87 
Prop osition 1.45.5. (1) The function FPdim : A C is a ring 
homomorphism. 
(2) Ther e exists a unique, up to scaling, element R  AC := AZC 
such that XR = FPdim(X )R, for all X  A. After an appro
priate normalization this element has positive coecients, and 
satises FPdim(R ) &gt; 0 and RY = FPdim(Y )R, Y  A. 
(3)	FPdim is a unique nonzer o character of A which takes non
negative values on I. 
(4)	If X  A has nonne gative coecients with respect to the basis of 
A, then FPdim(X ) is the largest nonne gative eigenvalue (NX ) 
of the matrix NX of multiplic ation by X. 
Proof. Consider the matrix M of right multiplic ation by XI X in A 
in the basis I. By transitivit y, this matrix has strictly positiv e entries, 
so by the Frobenius-P erron theorem , part (2), it has a unique , up to 
scaling, eigen vector R  AC with eigen value (M) (the maximal posi
tive eigen value of M). Furthermore , this eigenvector can be normalized 
to have strictly positiv e entries. 
Since R is unique, it satises the equation XR = d(X)R for some 
function d : A C. Indeed, XR is also an eigen vector of M with 
eigen value (M), so it must be proportional to R. Furthermore, it 
is clear that d is a charac ter of A. Since R has positiv e entries, 
d(X)= FPdim(X ) for X  I. This implies (1). We also see that 
FPdim(X ) &gt; 0 for X  I (as R has strictly positiv e coecien ts), and 
hence FPdim(R ) &gt; 0. 
Now, by transitivit y, R is the unique, up to scaling, solution of the 
system of linear equations XR = FPdim(X )R (as the matrix N of left 
multiplication by XI X also has positiv e entries). Hence, RY = 
d(Y )R for some character d. Applying FPdim to both sides and using 
that FPdim(R ) &gt; 0, we nd d = FPdim, proving (2). 
If  is another character of A taking positiv e values on I, then the 
vector with entries (Y ),Y  I is an eigen vector of the matrix N of the 
left multiplicat ion by the elemen t XI X. Because of transitivit y of 
A the matrix N has positiv e entries. By the Frobenius-P erron theorem 
there exists a positiv e number  such that (Y )=  FPdim(Y ). Since 
 is a character,  = 1, which completes the proof. 
Finally , part (4) follows from part (2) and the Frobenius-P erron the
orem (part (3)).  
Example 1.45.6. Let C be the category of nite dimensional repre
sentations of a quasi-Hopf algebra H, and A be its Grothendiec k ring. 
Then by Prop osition 1.10.9, for any X, Y C 
dim Hom(X  H, Y ) = dim Hom(H, X  Y ) = dim(X ) dim(Y ),</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
