<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/</course_url>
    <course_title>Turbulence in the Ocean and Atmosphere</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Mechanical Engineering </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>3D Turbulence (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch5/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7-8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>or
E + [u(p + E)+  u]= 2Z, (5.5)t 
,with E  1/2(u u) being the energy and Z  1/2( ) being the enstroph y. 
Turbulence in the presence of boundaries can ux energy through the walls, but for 
homogeneous turbulence the ux term must on the average vanish and the dissipation 
is just 2Z. Dissipat ion and energy cascades are closely tied to the rotational 
nature of a turbulen t ow. 
Taking an ensem ble average, denoted with angle brackets, the energy budget for an 
isotropic homogeneous ow becomes, 
/angbracketleftE/angbracketright = /epsilon1, (5.6)t 
,where /epsilon1 2/angbracketleftZ/angbracketright. This equation state that the rate of change of turbulen t kinetic 
energy E is balanced by viscous dissipation /epsilon1. Such a balance cannot be sustained 
for long times -a source of kinetic energy is needed. However sources of TKE are 
typically not homogeneous: think of a stirrer or an oscillating boundary . We sidestep 
this contradic tion by assuming that for large Reynolds numbers, although isotropy 
and homogeneit y are violated by the mechanism producing the turbulence, they still 
hold at small scales and away from boundaries. In this classic picture, we force the 
energy at a certain rate, which is then balanced o by dissipation. But the energy 
injection does not depend upon viscosit y. For the balance (5.6) to hold, the enstroph y 
must grow as the viscosity decreases. The enstroph y equation indeed has suitable 
source terms, 
/angbracketleftZ/angbracketright + /angbracketleftuZ Z/angbracketright= /angbracketleftiSijj /angbracketright/angbracketleft(ij)2/angbracketright (5.7)t 
where Sij =1/2[iuj + j ui] is the rate of strain tensor. Therefore, if the vorticity 
vector is on average aligne d with the directions where the strain is causing exten
sion rather than contraction, the enstrophy will increa se. In other words, we expect 
constant-vorticity lines to get longer on average. In a 3-D turbule nt ow, the vortic
ity is indeed on average undergoing stretching since this term ends up balancing the 
sign-denite dissipation terms. 
Dhar (Phyisics of Fluis, 19, 1976) gave a simple proof of why we might expect that the 
average length of constan t-voticity lines increases in a statistically isotropic velocity 
eld. Consider two neighboring uid particles with position vectors r1(t)and r2(t). 
Let r = r2(t) r1(t) be the innitesimal displacemen t between the two moving 
particles. Then, 
Dr Dr2 Dr1 =  . (5.8)Dt Dt Dt 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 5 
Isotropic homogeneous 3D 
turbulence 
Turbulence was recognized as a distinct uid behavior by Leonardo da Vinci more 
than 500 years ago. It is Leonardo who termed such motions turbolenze, and hence 
the origin of our modern word for this type of uid ow. But it wasnt until the be
ginning of last century that researchers were able to develop a rigorous mathematical 
treatment of turbulence. The rst major step was taken by G. I. Taylor during the 
1930s. Taylor introduced formal statistical methods involving correlations , Fourier 
transforms and power spectra into the turbulence literature. In a paper published in 
1935 in the Proceedings of the Royal Society of London, he very explicitly presen ts 
the assumptio n that turbulence is a random pheno menon and then proceeds to intro
duce statistical tools for the analysis of homogeneous, isotropic turbule nce. In 1941 
the Russian statistician A. N. Kolmogoro v published three papers (in Russian) 
that provide some of the most important and most-often quoted results of turbulence 
theory. These results, which will be discussed in some detail later, comprise what is 
now referred to as the K41 theory, and represen t a major success of the statistical 
theories of turbulence. This theory provides a prediction for the energy spectrum of a 
3D isotropic homogeneous turbule nt ow. Kolmogorov proved that even though the 
velocity of an isotropic homogeneous turbulent ow uctuates in an unpredictable 
fashion, the energy spectrum (how much kinetic energy is presen t on average at a 
particula r scale) is predicta ble. 
The spectral theory of Kolmogorov had a profound impact on the eld and it still 
represen ts the foundation of many theories of turbulence. It it thus imperative for 
any course on turbule nce to introduce the concepts of 3D isotropic homogeneous 
turbule nce and K41. It should however be kept in mind that 3D isotropic homo
geneous turbulence is an idealization never encountered in nature. The challenge is 
then to understand what aspects of these theories apply to natural ows and what 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>If pressure and advection were not presen t, the energy equation would reduce to, 
 +2k2 i,i(k,t)=0, (5.29)t 
in which the wavenumbers are uncoupled. The solution to this equation is, 
i,i(k,t)= i,i(k, 0)e k2t . (5.30) 
According to (5.30), the energy in wavenumber k decays exponentially, at a rate 
that increases with increasing wavenumber magnitude k. Thus viscosit y damps the 
smallest spatial scale fastest. 
We now restrict our analysis to isotropic velocity elds, so that we can use (5.19) and 
simplify (5.28), 
 E(k,t)= T(k,t)  2k2E(k,t), (5.31)t 
where T(k,t) compris es all triad interaction terms. If we examine the integral of this 
equation over all k, 
    
E(k)dk = T(k,t)dk  2k2E(k)dk, (5.32)t 0 0 0 
and note that 2k2E(k) is the Fourier transform of the dissipation term, then we 
see that the equation for the total energy budget in (5.6), is recovered only if, 
  
T(k,t)dk =0. (5.33) 
0 
Hence the nonlinear interactions transfe r energy between dieren t wave numbers, but 
do not change the total energy. 
Now, adding a forcing term to the energy equation in k-space we have the following 
equation for energy at a particular wavenumber k, 
 E(k,t)= T(k,t)+ F(k,t)  2k2E(k,t), (5.34)t 
where F(k,t)isthe forcing term, and T(k,t)isthe kinetic energy transfer , due to 
nonlinea r interactions. The kinetic energy ux through wave number k is (k,t), 
dened as,   
(k,t)= T(k/prime,t)dk/prime , (5.35) 
k 
or 
(k,t)T(k,t)=  . (5.36)k 
For stationary turbulence, 
2k2E(k)= T(k)+ F(k). (5.37) 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>/epsilon1 Characteristic scales of turbulence 
Kolmogoro v scale 
We have shown that viscous dissipation acts most ecien tly at small scales. Thus 
above a certain wavenumber kd, viscosit y will become important, and E(k) will decay 
more rapidly than in the inertial range. The regime k&gt;kd is known as the dissip ation 
range. A simple scaling argumen t for kd can be made by assuming that the spectrum 
follows the inertial scaling until kd and then drops suddenly to zero because of viscous 
dissipation. In reality the transition between the two regimes is more gradual, but 
this simple model predicts kd quite accurately . First we assume, 
E(k)= CK /epsilon12/3k5/3 ,ki &lt;k&lt;kd, 
E(k)=0, k&gt;kd. (5.49) 
Substituting (5.38), and integrating between ki and kd we nd, 
/epsilon11/4 
kd  3/4 . (5.50) 
The inverse ld =1/kd is known as the Kolmo gorov scale, the scale at which dissipation 
becomes important. 
3/4 
ld  (5.51)/epsilon11/4 
Integral scale 
At the small wavenumber end of the spectrum, the important lengths cale is li,the 
integral scale, the scale of the energy-containing eddies. li =1/ki. We can evaluate 
li in terms of /epsilon1. Let us write, 
  
U2 =2 E(k)dk (5.52) 
0 
and substituting for E(k) from ( 5.45), 
  
U2  2 CK /epsilon12/3k5/3dk  3CK /epsilon12/3ki 2/3 . (5.53) 
0 
Then, 
ki  (5.54)U3 
so that li  U3//epsilon1. Then the ratio of maximum and minimum dynamically active 
scales, 
li = kd  U3 
  Uli 3/4 
 Re3
li /4 . (5.55)ld ki /epsilon13/43/4  
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>where Reli is the integral Reynolds numb er. Hence in K41 the inertial range spans 
a range of scales growing as the (3/4)th power of the integral Reynolds number. It 
follows that if we want to describ e such a ow accurately in a numerical simulation 
on a uniform grid, the minimum number of points per integral scale is N  Rel9
i /4 . 
One consequence is that the storage requiremen ts of numerical simulations scale as 
Rel9
i /4 . Since the time step has usually to be taken proportional to the spatial mesh, 
the total computational work needed to integrate the equations for a xed number of 
large eddy turnover times grows as Re3 
li . This shows that progress in achieving high 
Reli simulations is very slow. 
5.2.1 Kolmogoro v in physical space 
Kolmogorov formulated his theory in physical space, making predictions for Sp,the 
longitudinal velocity structure function of order p, 
r vr =[u(x + r,t)  u(x,t)] . (5.56) r 
Sp = /angbracketleft|vr|p/angbracketright. (5.57) 
For homogeneous isotropic turbulence the structure function depends only on the 
magnitude of r, i.e. Sp = Sp(r). Under the assumptio ns describ ed above, i.e. that at 
ascale r, Sp depends only on the energy ux /epsilon1,and thescale r, dimensional analysis 
can be sued to predict that, 
Sp(r,t)= Cp(/epsilon1r)p/3 (5.58) 
where Cp is a constant. In particular S2  (/epsilon1r)2/3 . The second order structure 
function is related to the energy spectrum for an isotropic homogeneous eld, 
S2 = /angbracketleft(vr)2/angbracketright = /angbracketleft(u//(x + r,t)  u//(x,t))2/angbracketright 
=2/angbracketleftu//(x + r,t)u//(x,t)/angbracketright +2/angbracketleft|u//(x,t)|2/angbracketright 
=2 (1  e ikr)(k,t)dk 
  sin(kr)=4 E(k,t)1  dk. (5.59) 
0 kr 
If we substitute for E(k) from the Kolmogorov spectrum, and assume this applie s 
from k /greatermuch r1 then, 
/angbracketleft(vr)2/angbracketright CK (/epsilon1r)2/3 . (5.60) 
Hence the Kolmogorov k5/3 spectrum is consistent with the second order structure 
function of the form r2/3 . (Note that S2 is only nite if E(k,t) has the form kn 
where 1 &lt;n&lt; 3.) 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>If r is small, this gives, 
Dr = u(r2,t)  u(r1,t)=(j u)rj. (5.9)Dt 
This equation is identical to the vorticity equation in the absence of dissipa tion, 
D =(j u)j. (5.10)Dt 
We can therefore think that the vorticity is frozen into the uid. The eld  
can be stretched and bent, but never thorn apart. Its topology is preserv ed despite 
distortion. We can now proceed to analyze the evolution of r and wewill usethe 
results to understand the evolution of . 
Let ri(t)= ri(0) + ri(t). The initial partic le positions are given and non-random 
(i.e. statistically sharp), but the subsequent locations acquire a statistical distribu
tion that depends on the statistics of the velocity eld. the mean square separation 
between the uid particles at time t is thus, 
/angbracketleft|r|2/angbracketright = |r(0)|2 +2r(0) /angbracketleftr(t)/angbracketright + /angbracketleft|r(t)|2/angbracketright. (5.11) 
For a statistically homogeneous and isotropic ow, 
/angbracketleftr(t)/angbracketright = 0 (5.12) 
and therefore, 
/angbracketleft|r(t)|2/angbracketright|r(0)|2 . (5.13) 
The distance between uid particles increa ses on average! Unfortunately, however, 
this proof does not, strictly speaking, apply to the case of constant-vorticity lines, 
because (5.12) holds only for uid particles whose relative initial locations are initially 
uncorrelated with the ow (and therefore does not apply to pairs of uid particles 
that always lie on a vorticit y line). Thus (5.12) contributes plausibilit y, but not rigor, 
to the idea that in a turbulen t ows constant vorticit y lines are stretched on average. 
5.2 Kinetic Energy Spectra for 3D turbulence 
Denition of KE in spectral space 
For a ow which is homogeneous in space (i.e. statistical properties are independent of 
position), a spectral description is very appropriate, allowing us to examine properties 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>where lB is known as the Ozmidov scale. 
In stratied geophysical ows, we have a scenario in which a regime transition occurs 
at lB . 
	l&lt;lB : Fully 3D, isotropic turbulence. In this regime stratication can be 
neglected, and an inertia l range may exist, if ld &lt;&lt; lB , i.e. /epsilon1/(N2) &gt;&gt; 1. 
	l&gt;lB : Stratication inuenced regime. In this regime /epsilon1 is no longer constan t 
with wave number, since some kinetic energy is lost through conversion to po
tential energy. 3D turbulence is replaced by motion controlled by the buoyancy 
stratication: either internal waves, or a quasi-2-dimensio nal turbulence, often 
describ ed as pancak e turbulence, characterized by strong vortical motions in 
decoupled horizontal layers. 
(For more on stratie d turbule nce, see Lesieur Ch XIII, Metais and Herring, 1989: 
Numerical simulations of freely evolving turbulence in stably stratied uids. J. 
Fluid Mech., 239. Fincham, Maxworthy and Spedding, 1996: Energy dissipation and 
vortex structure in freely-decaying stratied grid turbulence. Dyn. Atmos. Oceans, 
23, 155-169.) 
Further reading: Lesieur, Ch V, VI; Tennekes and Lumley, Ch 8; Frisch, Ch 5, 6, 7, 
8. 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>ux is independent of wavenumber k, and equal to /epsilon1 for k&gt;ki. Kolmogorovs theory 
assumes the injection wavenumber is much less than the dissipation wavenumber 
(ki &lt;&lt; kd, or large Re). In the intermediate range of scales ki &lt;k&lt;kd neither the 
forcing nor the viscosit y are explicitly important, but instead the energy ux /epsilon1 and 
the local wavenumber k are the only controlling parameters. Then we can express 
the energy density as 
E(k)= f(/epsilon1,k) (5.43) 
Now using dimensional analysis: 
Quantity Dimens ion 
Wavenumber k 1/L 
Energy per unit mass E U2  L2/T 2 
Energ y spectrum E(k) EL  L3/T 2 
Energy ux /epsilon1 E/T  L2/T 3 
In eq. (5.43) the lhs has dimensionality L3/T 2; the dimension T 2 can only be bal
anced by /epsilon12/3 because k has no time dependence. Thus, 
E(k)= /epsilon12/3 g(k). (5.44) 
Now g(k)must have dimensions L5/3 and the functional dependence we must have, 
if the assumptions hold, is, 
E(k)= CK /epsilon12/3k5/3 (5.45) 
This is the famous Kolmo gorov spectrum, one of the corners tone of turbulence theory . 
CK is a universal constan t, the Kolmo gorov constant , experimen tally found to be 
approximately 1.5. The region of parameter space in k where the energy spectrum 
follows this k5/3 form is known as the inertial range . In this range, energy cascades 
from the larger scales where it was injected ultimately to the dissipation scale. The 
theory assumes that the spectrum at any particular k depends only on spectrally 
local quantities -i.e. has no dependence on ki for example. Hence the possibilit y for 
long-range interactions is ignored. 
We can also derive the Kolmogorov spectrum in a perhaps more physical way (after 
Obukho v). Dene an eddy turnover time (k)at wavenumber k as thetimetaken 
for a parcel with energy E(k)to move a distance 1/k.If (k) depends only on E(k) 
and k then, from dimensional analysis, 
(k)   
k3E(k) 1/2 (5.46) 
The energy ux can be dened as the available energy divided by the characteris tic 
time . The available energy at a wavenumber k is of the order of kE(k). Then we 
have, 
/epsilon1  kE(k) 
(k)  k5/2E(k)3/2 , (5.47) 
and hence, 
E(k)  /epsilon12/3k5/3 . (5.48) 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>are pathologic al. 
A turbulen t ow is said to be isotropic if, 
 rotation and buoyancy are not important and can be neglected, 
 there is no mean ow. 
Rotation and buoyancy forces tend to suppres s vertical motions, as we discuss later 
in the course, and create an anisotropy between the vertical and the horizon tal direc
tions. The presence of a mean ow with a particular orientation can also introduce 
anisotropies in the turbulen t velocity and pressure elds. 
A ow is said to be homo geneous if, 
 there are no spatial gradien ts in any averaged quantity. 
This is equivalent to assume that the statistics of the turbulen t ow is not a function 
of space. An example of 3D isotropic homogeneous ow is shown in Fig. 5.1. 
5.1	Kinetic energy and vorticit y budgets in 3D 
turbulence 
The mean zonal velocity is zero by denition of homogeneity and isotropy. The 
theory of 3D isotropic homogeneous turbule nce is therefore a theory of the second 
order statistics of the velocity eld, i.e. the kinetic energy E  1/2/angbracketleftu2 
i /angbracketright. The angle 
brackets represen t an ensemble average. 
In order to understand the energy balance of 3D ows, it is useful to derive the 
vorticity equation. From the Navier-Sto kes equations for a homogeneous uid, 
u	 1 +  u =  p + u u ,	 (5.1)t	 2 
u =0,  = u, (5.2) 
we can derive the vorticity equation, 
 + ( u)= 2.	 (5.3)t 
The energy equation can be written as, 
E + [u(p + E)] = u ,	 (5.4)t 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Figure 5.1: Isosurfaces of the the velocity gradient tensor used to visualize structures 
in computation of isotropic homogeneou s 3D turbulence. The yellow surfaces rep
resent ow regions with stable focus/stretching topology while the blue outlines of 
the isosurfaces show regions with unstable focus/contracting topology. 1283 simula
tion with Taylor Reynolds number = 70.9. (Andrew Ooi, University of Melbourne, 
Australia, 2004, http://www.mame.mu.oz.au/uids/). 
3
Image courtesy of Andrew Ooi. Used with permission.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>5.2.2	 3D homogeneous isotropic turbulence in geoph ysical 
ows 
The assumptions of homogeneity, stationarit y and isotropy as employed by Taylor and 
Kolmogoro v have permitted tremendous advances in our understanding of turbulence. 
In partic ular the theory of Kolmogorov remains an outstanding example of what we 
mean by emergence of statistical predicta bility in a chaotic system. However this a a 
course on geophysical turbule nce and we must ultimately confron t the fact that real 
world physical ows rarely conform to our simplifying assumptions. In geophysical 
turbulence, statistical symmetries are upset by a complex interpla y of eects. Here 
we focus on three important class of phenomena that modify small- scale turbulence in 
the atmosphere and ocean: large-scale shear, stratication, and boundary proximity. 
In a few weeks we will consider the role of rotation. 
A very nice description of the eect of shear, stratication, and boundary proximity on 
small-scale geophysical turbulence is given in the review article on 3D Turbulence 
by Smyth and Moum included as part of the reading material. The student should 
read that paper before proceeding with this chapter. Here we only provide some 
additional comments on the denition of the Ozimdov scale. 
Ozmido v scale 
In geophysical ows 3D turbule nce can be a reasonable approximation at scales small 
enough that buoyancy and rotation eects can be neglected. Stratication becomes 
important at scales smaller than rotation and it is therefore more important in setting 
the upper scales at which 3D arguments hold. Stratication aects turbulence when 
the Froude number Fr = U/(NH) &lt; 1, where U is a typical velocity scale, and H 
a typical vertical length scale of the motion. For large Fr, the kinetic energy of the 
motion is much larger than the potential energy changes involved in making vertical 
excursio ns of order H. For small Fr, the stratication suppresses the vertical motion 
because a substa ntial fraction of kinetic energy must be converted to potential energy 
when a parcel moves in the vertical. 
We can dene a characteristic scale lB at which overturning is suppressed by the 
buoyancy stratication as follows. The velocity associated with a particula r length 
scale l in high Reynolds number isotropic 3D turbulence scales like, 
u 2  /epsilon12/3k2/3  u  (l/epsilon1)1/3 .	 (5.61) 
Vertical motion at length scale l will be suppressed by the stratication when the 
local Froude number Frl = 1. If we dene the length scale at which this suppression 
occurs as lB then, 
uB (lB /epsilon1)1/3	  /epsilon1 1/2 
= =1 = lB =	 (5.62)NlB	 NlB N3 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Remem bering that the total dissipation rate is given by, 
  
/epsilon1 = 2k2E(k)dk (5.38) 
0 
and that the integral of the triad interactions over the whole k-space vanishes, we 
have,   
/epsilon1 = F(k)dk. (5.39) 
0 
The rate of dissipation of energy is equal to the rate of injection of energy . 
If the forcing F(k) is concentrated on a narrow spectral band centered around a wave 
number ki,then for k /negationslash= ki, 
2k2E(k)= T(k). (5.40) 
In the limit of  0, the energy dissipation become s negligible at large scales. Thus 
there must be an intermediate range of scales between the forcing scale and the scale 
where viscous dissipation becomes important, where, 
2k2E(k)= T(k) 0. (5.41) 
Notice that /epsilon1 must remain nonzero, for nonzero F(k), in order to balance the energy 
injection. This is achieved by  
0  k2E(k)dk , i.e. the velocity uctuations at 
small scales increase. 
Then we nd the energy ux in the limit  0, 
(k)=0, : k&lt;ki 
(k)= /epsilon1 : k&gt;ki (5.42) 
Hence at vanishing viscosit y, the kinetic energy ux is constan t and equal to the in
jection rate, for wavenumbers greater than the injection wavenumber ki. The scenario 
is as follows. (a) Energy is input at a rate /epsilon1 at a wavenumber ki. (b) Energy is uxed 
to higher wavenumbers at a rate /epsilon1 trough triad interactions . (c) Energy is eventually 
dissipated at very high wavenumbers at a rate /epsilon1, even in the limit of  0. 
The statemen t that triad interactions produce a nite energy ux /epsilon1 toward small 
scales does not mean that all triad interactions transfer energy exclusively toward 
small scales. Triad interactions transfer large amounts of energy toward both large 
and small scales. On average, however, there is an excess of energy transfer toward 
small scales given by /epsilon1. 
Kolmogoro v spectrum 
Kolmogorovs 1941 theory for the energy spectrum makes use of the result that /epsilon1,the 
energy injection rate, and dissipation rate also controls the ux of energy. Energy 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>as a function of wavelength. The total kinetic energy can be written replacing the 
ensem ble average with a space average, 
1 2 11 E = /angbracketleftu /angbracketright = ui(x)ui(x)dx, (5.14)2 i 2 V 
where V is the volume domain. The spectrum i,j(k) is then dened by, 
  1 E = i,i(k)dk = E(k)dk (5.15)2 
where i,j(k) is the Fourier transform of the velocity correlation tensor Ri,j(r), 
  
i,j(k)= (21 
)3 Ri,j (r)e ik.rdr,Ri,j (r)= V 1 uj(x)ui(x + r)dx. (5.16) 
Ri,j(r) tells us how velocities at points separated by a vector r are related. If we 
know these two point velocity correlations , we can deduce E(k). Hence the energy 
spectrum has the information content of the two-point correlation. 
E(k) contains directional inform ation. More usually, we want to know the energy at 
a particula r scale k = |k| without any interest in separating it by direction. To nd 
E(k), we integrate over the spherical shell of radius k (in 3-dimensio ns), 
      
E = E(k)dk = k2E(k)d dk = E(k)dk, (5.17) 
0 0 
where  is the solid angle in wavenumber space, i.e. d =sin 1 d1 d2.We now 
dene the isotropic spectrum as, 
1 E(k)= k2E(k)d = k2i,i(k)d. (5.18)2 
For isotropic velocity elds the spectrum does not depend on directions, i.e. i,i(k)= 
i,i(k), and we have, 
E(k)=2k2i,i(k). (5.19) 
Energy budge t equation in spectral space 
We have an equation for the evolution of the total kinetic energy E. Equally interest
ing is the evolution of E(k), the isotropic energy at a particular wavenumber k.This 
will include terms which describe the transfer of energy from one scale to another, 
via nonline ar interactions. 
To obtain such an equation we must take the Fourier transform of the non-rotating, 
unstratied Boussinesq equations, 
ui 2ui ui 1 p 
t   x2 
j = uj xj  0 xi . (5.20) 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>The two terms on the lhs are linear and are easily transformed into Fourier space, 
  ui(x,t)  ui(k,t), (5.21)t t 
2 
x2 
j ui(x,t)   kj 2 ui(k,t). (5.22) 
In order to convert the pressure gradien t term, we rst notice that taking the diver
gence of the Navier-Stokes equation we obtain, 
2p ui uj 
x2 =  0 xj xi . (5.23) 
i 
Thus both terms on the rhs of eq. (5.20) involve the product of velocities. The 
convolution theorem states that the Fourier transform of a product of two functions 
is given by the convolution of their Fourier transforms, 
  1 1 ui(x,t)uj(x,t)e ikxdx = ui(p,t)uj (q,t)(p + q  k)dpdq. (5.24)V (2)3 
Apply ing the convolution terms to the terms on the rhs we get, The two terms on 
the lhs are linear and are easily transformed in Fourier space, 
ui uj  i qj uj(p,t)ui(q,t)(p + q  k)dpdq, (5.25)xj 
p  0 piqj uj(p,t)ui(q,t)(p + q  k)dpdq. (5.26)k2 
Plugging all these expressions in eq. (5.20) we obtain the Navier-Stok es equation in 
Fourier space, 
 kipm + k2 ui(k,t)=  i qj i,m  uj(p,t)um(q,t)(p + q  k)dpdqt k2 
(5.27) 
The term on the right hand side shows that the nonlinear terms involve triad inter
actions between wave vectors such that k = p + q. 
Now to obtain the energy equation we multiply e. (5.27) by ui (k,t) and we integrate 
over k, 
 +2k2 i,i(k,t)=t 
 Re Aijm(k,p,q)ui (k,t)uj(p,t)um(q,t)(p + q  k)dpdqdk .(5.28) 
The terms on the rhs represen t the triad interactions that exchange energy between 
ui(k,t), uj(p,t),and um(q,t). The coecien t Aijm are the coupling coecien t of 
each triad and depends only on the wavenumbers. 
7</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Convection (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4-6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>,!? 
so that 
- ~ ~ A~~RUP~ w + RU'~ ~al+O 
h2 
giving 2w = + 1. Finally, assurrle that the buoyar~t forces in the bountlary layer 
balance dissipation 
. . glvlrlg = 1, -iw, . Corrlbining these three gives 
This agrees well wit11 experiments in the higher Rayleigh nurr~ber range. 
For a good general reference, see Kadanoff, L. (Ph,ysics Toda,y, Aug. 2001) and 
Errlanuel, K. (1994) Atmospheric Convection. 
Mixed layer 
In the atrnosphere and oceans, one cornrnon cause of convection is heat fluxes at the 
surface which warrn (atrr~os~here) The rest or cool (ocean) the fluid near the boundary. 
of the fluid is stably-stratified. Conceptually, the unstable region diffuses into the stable 
region, with both the buoyancy jurnp and the thickness increasing (practically, of course, 
the boundary layer always lvas sorne level of turbulence, so the transport of heat is likely to 
he related to that rather tllar~ to molecular processes). In a very short time: the Rayleigh 
rlurrlber exceetls the critical value and convection begins. We'll consider the oceanic case; 
just turn upside down (and tl~ink of b as proportional to the potential terr~~erature) for 
the atrnosphere. The diffusive layer will grow as h N a.If the 1)uoyancy flux out the 
surface is Q,the effective buoyancy difference across layer is order Qtlh (ignoring the deep 
stratification); therefore the Rayleigl~ rlurrlber grows as t2. 
Demos, Page 13: Finite amp &lt;convection into stratification&gt; &lt;means&gt; 
&lt;waterfall&gt; &lt;shallowerlayer&gt; &lt;means&gt; &lt;waterfall&gt; &lt;rotating&gt; 
&lt;means&gt; &lt;waterfall&gt; &lt;equilibrated&gt; &lt;means&gt; 
When corlvection is vigorous, the unstably-stratified part of the water colurnn rnixes to 
hecorne essentially uniforrn. For fixed ternperature boundary contlitions, you then tlevelop 
thin layers near the boundary with thickness such that the local Rayleigl~ number is nearly 
critical. If the heat flux is fixed, these layers do not occur ant1 the ternperature gradient 
decreases to srrlall values. 
The first exarnples illustrate the developrrlent when we start with an unstable layer 
over a stable layer, with no heat flux at the surface. Then we can figure out the depth of 
convection by finldir~g the depth h such tlvat</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Convection 
Corivection is the first exarnple we shall study of turbulence which is not homogeneous 
or isotropic, It draws on the potential energy which is available when the fluid is negatively 
stratified or has horizorital buoyancy variations. For the Boussinesq equations 
the kinetic energy satisfies 
Tlie last terrn represerits the conlversion of available poteritial erlergy to kinetic energy. We 
car1 see the connection to poteritial energy hy noting that 
so that wb is a sink for PE: raising lighter (I)uoyan~t) fluid and lowering heavier fluid de- 
creases the potential energy. Tlie definition zb corresponds to the starltlard rrlass xgravityx 
heiglit for a unit volurrie, once we rerrierr11)er 
Note that we really have to corripare the poteritial energy of tlie entire systenr~ to the energy 
it would have in some other obtainable state to decide if the transition is possible. In the 
figure on the following page, the various states have potential energies as follows: 
state PE trar~sitior~ SPE 
a 27bc -21bh --t b 18(bh-be) 
b 45bL 3bh 
c 24bc -24bh --t d 12(bh-be) 
d 36bc -12bh 
(1' 12bc-24bh --t d 12(bh-be) 
e ?be 3 h +d 20 56b -T(bh-bc) 
f 24(bh +be) td 12(bh be) 
wliere d' is an inverted version of d. From this, we see that either horizorital gratlierits or 
irlvertetl density profiles release potential energy when the heavy fluid settles to the l&gt;ottom 
(no surprises here!). However, we also see that the potential energy of a rnixed state is 
actually higher tlian that of a stably-stratified state. In the potential energy equation: this 
shows up as the 2 a ~ terrri~ -diffusion acting on a stable state increases the ceriter of rriass b 
heiglit and the potential energy. (The energy to (lo this rriust come frorri the molecular 
kinetic energy; the Boussinesq equations sweep this under the rug a bit in tliat internal 
erlergy is not well-represented.)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Various states wit11 lighter fluid be, heavier fluid bh &lt; be and a mixture. 
When dense fluid overlies less dense fluid, the layer will tend to overturn. To get 
any idea of when this rnigl~t occur, consider a blob of fluid of size h rising with speed W 
through a fluid where the temperature decreases with height 3T/32 &lt; 0. The terr~perature 
of the blob, T, will reflect the environrner~t with sorr~e tirr~e lag for the outside terr~perature 
to diffuse in. On the rising particle, we can think of the heat budget as 
The parcel feels a buoyancy force cwg(T T)with n being the tl~errrral expansion coefficier~t 
p = po -cx(T-To); this force rrlust balance or overcorrle the viscous drag 1/W/h2where 
u is the viscositv. 
We car1 look for exp(at) solutions to these in which case 
and unstable solutions (a &gt; 0) will exist for 
The neutral solutions Ru = 1are simple: the fluid rises steadily</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Details of growth rate eqn. 
For corlvenience, we replace o = (scaling time tjy the viscous rather than diffusive PT~ 
scale). Then we have 
Near the critical poir~t A3-Ru k2 +Tr2=0 we have 
- Ru k2 -Tr2-A3 u = A2(2+PT)-(Ru k2 -Tr2Pr)/A2 
-Ru k2 -Tx2-A3 -Pr A2+(Pr-1)Tr2/A2 
Demos, Page 7: growth rate surfaces &lt;T=O&gt; &lt;T=l00&gt; &lt;T=l000&gt; 
The growth rate u will pass through zero on the real axis when 
Demos, Page 7: Stability bndry &lt;various Ra T&gt; &lt;closeup&gt; &lt;closer&gt; 
The srr~allest critical Rayleigl~ r1urrlt)er occurs at T =0. k2 =ir2and is 
corresponding to a temperature change over 1rneter of 4xlo-' OC using (1=2.5~~o-~/'C, 
u =10V2 crn2/s, v/~ =7. (The Taylor rurrltxr with f =10-~/sis about 1.) 
There can he an ir~stability in which Re(o) passes through zero at a poir~t where 
Irn(o) # 0. For Prandtl rlurrlt&gt;er v/n = 7) however) this happens at a Rayleigh rurrltxr 
larger than the value above. 
Nonlinear dynamics</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>aF .For the profile used in the r~urnerical experirnents (z111 the upper ho/h of the tlorrlain -
given by -2x the value in the lower we fir~dthat the ~r~ixin~gdepth is ,/:/Lo. This 
corresponds to IL = 0.G and 0.3 in the two cases; these estimates are consister~t wit11 the 
experirnents. This assurrles that the convective elernents near the end of the experiment 
do not penetrate significar~tly l&gt;elowthe depth 
The effect of surface cooling will be to mix the fluid until the 1)uoyancy gradient 
hecornes zero again. We can find the new profile hy figuring out the depth la such that the 
heat cor~ter~tchange balances the surface cooling: 
If we hegin wit11 a linearly increasing temperature towards the surface T = To+yt,we find 
the arnour~tof heat removed by the tirne the rr~ixedlayer reaches tlepth IL is poc,yh2/2. 
If the cooling rate is constar~t~ it takes a tirne Qt to rernove the heat pocPyIi2/2 above 
,z = ti,, irnplying that the tlepth of the rrlixetl layer increases as &amp;. 
Demos, Page 14: Surface convection &lt;mfa&gt; &lt;means&gt; &lt;2D&gt; &lt;means&gt; 
&lt;final&gt; &lt;mfa,f=O.l&gt; &lt;mfa,f=l&gt; &lt;mfa,f=5&gt; &lt;mfa,f=5&gt; &lt;2D&gt; &lt;means&gt; 
&lt;final&gt; 
Convective Plumes and Thermals 
Thermals 
Suppose we release a blob of buoyant fluid at the surface in the atmosphere or we have 
a cor~tir~uous source such as a therrr~alvent or smokestack: what happens? Let's corlsider 
the blob case first. 
If the blob were a 1)uoyant ol&gt;ject, it would accelerate upwartls until it reaches its 
terminal velocity where drag matches the buoyancy force. If its 1)uoyancy initially is b, its 
volurr~eV ; ant1 its velocity W; we could use Stokes law to descrihe the rnotion by 
where b is the buoyancy of the fluid outside the blob. In reality. the blob entrains fluid 
frorn outsitle: tllis alters its volurne, its I)uoyancy, and its rnorner~turn. Let us tlenote the</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Note tlvat there is no real requirement that the systerr~ be two-D; planforms like those 
shown previously are perfectly acceptable. 
The rrleasure of the effects of the fluctuating/ tur1)ulent velocities is the Nusselt num-
ber, which is the ratio of the heat (or 1)uoyancy) transport to that carried by contluction 
(w'b') -K&amp; (h)Nu = -~cAh/h 
In general, we need to average over long tirr~es as well. 
Demos, Page 11: mfa &lt;2*crit&gt; &lt;10*crit&gt; &lt;50*crit&gt; &lt;50*crit, 1,2,3&gt; 
&lt;Nu&gt; 
Full Solutions 20 
Demos, Page 11: 2d &lt;2*crit&gt; &lt;Nu&gt; &lt;lO*crit&gt; &lt;Nu&gt; &lt;50*crit&gt; 
&lt;Nu&gt; &lt;50*crit wide&gt; &lt;75*crit&gt; &lt;Nu&gt; &lt;Nu 95&gt; &lt;100*crit&gt; &lt;Nu&gt; 
&lt;200*crit&gt; &lt;Nu&gt; &lt;bbar&gt; &lt;500*crit&gt; &lt;Nu&gt; &lt;bbar&gt; &lt;brange&gt; 
&lt;w'bJ&gt; &lt;Nu-Ra&gt; 
Measurements at high Rayleigh nurr~ber are difficult and fraught wit11 prohlerns frorn 
side walls, urleven terrlperature on the boundaries, non-Boussinesq effects, etc. But they 
tend to show Nu N Ru0.29-0.3. 
Takeshita, T., T.Segawa. J.A.Glazier, ant1 M.Sano (1996) Tllerrrlal turbulence in rnercury. 
Ph,ys. R,Pv. Let.: 76, 1465-68. 
Ahlers, G. and X.Xu Prandlt-r1urn1)er dependence of heat transport in turbulent Rayleigh- 
Bervartl convection. 
Nikolaenko, A. and G.Ahlers (2003) Nusselt nurr11)er rneasurernen~ts in turbulent Rayleigh- 
Bhnartl convection. Ph,ys. R,ev. Let., 91 
Demos, Page 11: 3d &lt;variance in T&gt; &lt;Nu&gt; &lt;Nu&gt; &lt;Nu&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Bifiirca tions 
The steady solution X = Y = 2= 0 for T = 0 becornes unstable for p &gt; 1;leatling to 
a second steady solution X = p -1; Y = 2= dm. This solution l&gt;econnes unstable 
at p = ,!? +Pr(Pr + 3)/(Pr -p -1)= 24.737. This is a subcritical Hopf bifurcation. For 
larger p, the 3D system has neither stable 1D equilibria nor stable 2D lirnit cycles. 
11tt~://www.atnr1.ox.ac.uk/user/read/chaos/lect6.~~df 
Attractor 
If we consitler the probability of being in a particular volurne in (X; Y, 2:U) space, 
it evolves by 
Note that the "velocity" in phase space is convergent 
so that the volurne contir~ually corltracts. Tllus the solutions reside on an attractor wit11 
dinr~ension~ 2.062 (Sprott, J. 1997). He also estirr~ates less tllan~ 3; calculations suggest D -
the Lyapunov exponerlts to be 0.906, -14.572. 
11tt~://s~rott.~~h~sics.wisc.edu/chaos/lorenzle.11tnn 
Mean Field Approx. 
The rrlearl field approximation (Herring, 1963, J.Atmos. Sci.) works wit11 the equation 
for the mean buoyancy 
and the fluctuation flow 
The rnean-field approx. irlvolves tlropping the nonlinear terrns in the fluctuation equations, 
so that they revert to the linear stability problern -except that the rrlearl (b)is changing 
wit11 time and is rnore complicated tl~an~ in the vertical. The vertical structures of the z 
perturbations will also change with tirne. However, the perturbation equations can still be 
separated with horizontal structures V2b1= k2b1,and we choose one or rnore k values.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>so that the atlvective heat fluxes arltl velocities also becorne srr~all as I/ arltl n becorne small. 
These versions of Sandstrorn's theorern confirrn Wunsch's view that the thermohaline 
circulation is tlriver~ not by the surface buoyancy gradients but hy rr~ixing in the tleep ocean 
associatetl with winds and tides. 
Other problems 
Another irrlportar~t forrn corlvection takes in the atmosphere and ocean is gravity 
currents, where dense fluid is running down a slope. Using plurne theory gives 
a-hU2 = h(b -be)sin 0ax 
hut the entrainment velocity now depends on Kelvin-Helmholtz instability of the top edge. 
Price and Baringer (1994, Prog. Oceanogr., 33. 161-200) use a form 
0.08 -O.1Ri (b-be)la cos 0 
'ue = U Ri= &lt; 0.81 +5Ri U2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>so that the terrlperature lags its surroundings hy a fixed arnour~t~ and thebuoyancy force 
is corlstar~t and car1 balance the drag 
Rayleigh-Benard 
The classic Rayleigh-Benard problem hegins wit11 the dynarnical equatior~s for conser- 
vation of rrlass arld mornenturn arld buoyancy. We shall add rotation 
Note: There's no prognostic equation for P;how can we step the equatior~s forward? 
The original equations car1 be written in terrr~s of a prognostic systerr~ for u, p; and p. 111 
principle, it car1 he stepped forward, although; as L.F. Richardson found out, sountl waves 
rrvake any sucl~ attempt problernatical at best. For the Boussinesq equations: you have to 
find P diagnostically: if you take the tlivergence of the rnornenturn equations, the 8 terrn 
disappears ant1 you're left wit11 
from which you can cornpute P. If we use u = V4 -V x .II, with V . .II, = 0, the first 
terrn is just fV2g3and relates the strearnfunction to the pressure -they halarlce under 
geostrophic conditions. 
Vector invariant fm 
The (u. V)u is well-defined in Cartesian coordinates, but not in other systerrls; there- 
fore, it is usefully to write the rr~orrlerlturr~ equatior~ in a forrr~ which can be converted 
to polar, spherical, ellipsoidal ... coordinates by using starltlard forrns (e.g., Morse arld 
Feshbachl 
where 5 is the vorticity V x u. Note again the reserrlblance of the vorticity to twice 
the rotation rate. You car1 think of the parcel as accelerating because of gratlier~ts in 
the Bernoulli function P + ?ju. u arltl Coriolis forces associated with plar~etary arid local 
rotation.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>surface area of the blob by S arid the rate at which fluid crossed that surface by we;then 
our volume: buoyancy; arltl rnorr~er~turn equations becorne 
(assuming molecular exchanges are negligible) or 
wit11 the last terrr~ giving the height of the therrnal. In this sense, er~trainrner~t acts like 
viscous drag arld conduction in that it darrlps the velocity or buoyancy hack to the external 
values. However; we cannot expect the darnping rate to be constant. 
If we rnake the er~trainrr~en~t hypothesis that the turbuler~t veloocities are proportional 
to relative velocity W and look at the case wit11 a uniforrr~ exterior b = 0 
and apply a slyape sirnilarity assumption 
we find 
v = [vf3+ UPZ]~z3 t3I2 , b = bn-vn 2-3 t-312 v 
Demos, Page 15: Thermals &lt;Z vs t&gt; &lt;b vs t&gt; &lt;W vs. t&gt; Demos, 
Page 15: Thermals in stratification &lt;Z vs t&gt; &lt;b vs t&gt; &lt;W vs. t&gt; 
&lt;W vs. t linear&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Lorenz eqns. and chaos 
To derive the Lorenz equations, we note tlmt rnean l&gt;uoyancy satisfies 
suggesting a correction to the rnean profile proportior~al to sin(27rz). On the other hantl, 
the rrlearl vertical rr~ornen~turn flux is zero. So we try representing the fields as 
b = X(t) sin(27rz) -Z(t) cos(ky) sin(7rt) 
&lt; = Y(t) sin(kY) sin(7rz) 
71. = U(t) sin(ky)cos(7rz) 
We substitute these into the equations arid project by the various coefficier~ts to get a 
dynarnical systern: 
3 k7r-X = -YZ -47r2x at A 
i a --Y=kRaZ-AY-TTU 
at 
If we rescale D --t A&amp; and choose suitaide scales for the variables, we can get the classical 
Lorenz systerr~ (with an extra equation for rotation) 
The growth rate is given by 
u u(5+ I)~(U+ 1)+ (u + 1)T -(-Pr + l)p = 0 
which is a rescaled version of the previous result. The neutral cnrve is just 
p=Tf 1 
Demos, Page 9: Lorenz eqns tau=O &lt;rho=0.9&gt; &lt;rho=2&gt; &lt;rho=20&gt; 
&lt;same&gt; &lt;rho=24.1&gt; &lt;same&gt; &lt;rho=24.2&gt; &lt;same&gt; &lt;closeup&gt; &lt;rho=25&gt; 
&lt;same&gt; &lt;sensitivity&gt; &lt;closeup&gt; Demos, Page 9: Lorenz eqns tau=lO 
&lt;rho=iO&gt; &lt;rho=20&gt; &lt;rho=40&gt; &lt;same&gt; &lt;rh0=8O&gt; &lt;same&gt; &lt;closeup&gt; 
&lt;medium rho&gt; Crho=350&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Large Ra,yleigh number scalings 
The 2D calculations and 3D experiments suggest Nu -Raa. There are various 
argurnerlts for wlvat the power law should be: 
1) The buoyancy (heat) flux sl~ould become independent of the values of I/ and n. In 
3D turi)ulence; the flux of energy down the spectrurn is given by the rate of injection; 
viscosity only (leterrnines the scale at which it is finally tlissipatetl. If the sarrle idea 
were to hold in corlvection then 
Fb 1Nu = I, --[Ra PT.]~J~ (nAb/h) n 
This value of cr: = 0.5 is rruch higher tllar~ observed. But see Rachel Castaing, 
Chabautl, ar~tl H6i)ral (2001, Ph,ys. Rev. E, 63: 45303). Demos, Page 12: Rough 
surfaces &lt;Apparatus&gt; &lt;Nu&gt; &lt;Nu&gt; 
2) Suppose that the final state looks like a broken line profile and that the sharp temper- 
ature gradients at the boundaries are nearly neutrally stable. If the bountlary layer 
has thickness h,,, then 
Therefore 
so that the i)ountlary layer thickness tlecreases as Ru-lI3. If the flux tllrougl~ the 
boundary layer is contluctive (marginally staide) 
This works up to Ru = 4 x lo7 (result frorn Lii)chaher; see Kklurana, A. (1988) Phys. 
Toda,y,41. 17-20). Herring fount1 this with the mean-field approach as well. 
3) Frorn Kadanoff, et al. we assurrle that 
Since the heat is carried by convection in the interior, this suggests 
so that cw = + w. In the interior, we assurne that the balance is between vertical 
advection of w and i)uoyar~t forces</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>2-D convection 
When we consider corlvective rnotions which are intlepender~t of x, the zonal cornpo- 
ner~t of the vorticity equation gives us 
where 4 is the strearnfunction (w = 3,,u = -2 arld 6 the x-componen~t of Z (= '20-2= OY' a~ 
V24). The other two equations are 
wit11 71. = T'/'c. 
The stability 1)rol)lern has constar~t (coefficier~ts so tlvat 
( = co sin(ky) sin(.rrz)eot 
b = bo cos(ky) sin(xz)eut (tlropping prirnes) 
71 = 7ro sin(ky) cos(.rrz)eot (dropping tildes) 
(A = k2 + .rr2) and the equations l&gt;ecorne 
giving the dispersion relation 
discussed previously. 
Fluxes 
Note that linear theory predicts a buoyancy flux 
U+KA
wb = bi cos2 (ky) sin2 (mz)eZot 
IS1 
which has a non-zero arltl positive average 
o+lcA ,.(wb) = bo SI~I (rr~z)e~"~ 
21s 
irnplying that the instability will draw energy frorr~ the poter~tial energy field arld corlvert 
it to kir~etic energy (motion).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>For this rnodel, we idealize the cross-section as a circle arld compute the steady state 
balances. We have 
3 2-nr Wy = cwW27rrye +nr2y,3z 
wit11 q, the external value arld y, the source/sink. Applying to rnass (y =ye = 1, (I, = 0): 
huoyancy (Y = b; q, = N2z;ys = 0) , and rrlornerlturn (y = W:ye =0, y, =h NZZ)gives 
wit11 bb'= h -N2z the local 1)uoyancy anornaly. 
1r1 the case of an unstratified environment, we can again solve the eqnations; however, 
let's corlsider how the sirnilarity solutior~ works. We assurne 
arld use the conservation of l&gt;uoyancy flux to find 
From the rnass arld rnorner~turn equations, we firltl the exponerlts satisfy 
Demos, Page 16: Plumes &lt;r vs z&gt; &lt;b vs z&gt; &lt;W vs. z&gt; Demos, 
Page 16: Plumes in stratification &lt;r vs z&gt; &lt;b vs z&gt; &lt;W vs z&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Inhomogeneous forcing 
When the fluxes at the surface vary with latitude, the fluid rnust be in motion (there is 
a vorticity generatior1 rnechanisrn frorn V x hi). This car1 occur on srnall scales (convective 
chimneys) or on large scales (the Hatlley cell or therrnohaline circulation). Generally, you 
get weak corlvection on the cooling side, filling the tlorr~air~with colt1 fluid which upwells 
into a atlvective-tliffusive thermocline on the warrrlir~g side. 
To illustrate orle of the connections between the large arld srrlall scales, consider the 
"ar~ti-turbulence" theorern of Paparella arld Young. Suppose we represent the surface 
hountlary conditions on b as exhange of heat with the atmosphere 
Multiplying the buoyancy equation by z antl averaging over the ocean antl over a long tirne 
gives 
The vertical heat fluxis lirrlitetl by the tliffusivity 
The kinetic energy satisfies 
so that the dissipation is 
In the absence of wind forcing the dissipation is not insensitive to the srrlall scale 
dissipation coefficients. Thus, thermally tlriver~circulation is not turbuler~t in the 
Kolrnogorov sense of energy cascading to the tlissipatior~ scales and rrlairltair~ir~g the 
sarrle tlissipatior~ rate even as the viscosity/ contluctivity gets srnaller. 
Wit11 winds, the required dissipation is rrlore or less indepentler~t of the viscosity and the 
flow will hecorne turbulerlt. 
The circulation strength is also limited: Siggers (2002) shows that a rneasure of the 
horizontal flux of heat is bounded by</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>to get a single equation for w 
-
ahFor positive S = z,Ra &lt; 0)this gives darnped ir~ternal waves; however, we're interested 
in the development for S &lt; 0. 
Demos, Page 5: planforms &lt;theta=O&gt; &lt;theta=45,135&gt; &lt;theta=O,60,120&gt; 
&lt;p greater than -0.33&gt; &lt;theta=O, 55,118&gt; &lt;theta=O, 99,162,274&gt; &lt;theta=O, 72,144,216, 
At this point we make a horizor~tal planform staterrler~t 
and a vertical structure forrr~ w = sin(~z) 
This is where bourldary conditions corne in: we have originally a sixth order equation for 
w so that we need three conditions on w, the obvious one being w = 0. The sinusoidal 
solution has the perturbation b zero, consister~t wit11 fixed temperatures on the plates. It 
also has = = 0corresponding to free slip. 
Growth rates 
We cor~tinue separating variables, now in time: 
so that D, = u +A wit11 A = k2 + K'. The flow will be unstable when Re(u) &gt; 0;the 
growth/ propagation rates are the eiger~values of the matrix arltl satisfy the characteristic 
equation 
1 a/Pr +A u+A(%a +A)'(U +A) -Ra k2 +Tr2 = 0A A 
In the ir~viscid case. I/ = n = 0; the growth rates (dimensional) are 
and instability requires 
k2S+m2f2 &lt;O 
which will occur for sufficier~tly srr~all scale rnotions whenever S &lt; 0.The resting state is 
unstable when the density increases with height (or the buoyancy decreases).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Vorticity equation 
Taking the curl gives the equation for the tirne rate of change of the absolute vorticity 
Z=C+fi 
3-Z+Vx(Zxu)=-2xVbvVx(VxZ)3t 
or (back in Cartesian forrn, using the nor-tlivergence of u arltl Z) 
Vorticity is generatetl tjy stretching arld twisting or hy 1)uoyancy forces. 
We scale x by ti,; t by l?/n, u by h/[t]= n/h, and l&gt;uoyancy hy [w]S[t]= hIS1 
where S is the background stratification gb (and is negative) set by the top and l&gt;ottom 
hountlary conditions. Fir~ally~the scaling for the pressure is chosen to balance viscosity 
u[w]//i,= vn/h2. 
1D x u=-vP+R~~~+v~u --U+T~/~~
PT Dt 
wit11 b = z + bl(x,t). 
The parameters are</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Linear s tabi1it.y 
The classical problerr~ consitlers a fluitl with an ur~stable stratification confinetl between 
horizontal plates at ,z = 0, IL. The temperatures on the plates are held fixed, arltl the 
hourltlaries are assurned to be stress-free (this car1 he fixed, but rnakes the rnath rr~essier -
see Chandrasekhar). The linearized equations becorne 
We define two operators 
and start with the vertical vorticity equation 
and the Laplacian of the vertical rnorner~turn equatior~ 
Using the diagr~ostic equation for the pressure 
3bV2P= TI/'(+ Ra-32 
gives 
3(D,V'W = TI/^-+ ~avib3z 
wit11 Vi being the borizorltal Laplacian. Elirr~inatir~g the vertical vorticity yields 
wl~ich will be corrlt&gt;ined with the buoyancy eyuatior~</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Effective Diffusivity (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>In a statistically steady state we have, 
2Q i,yviqi= q
i 2  0, (13.5) 
i.e. the QGPV ux in each layer is down its mean gradient. We can therefore write, 
viq= KQi,y, (13.6) i 
where K is a positive denite quantity generally referred to as the eddy diusivity. 
If we can specify the eddy diusivit y in terms of zonally averaged quantities, we can 
use (13.6) to solve the mean eld equatio ns. 
The goal of this lecture is to introduce in a formal way the concept of eddy diusivit y. 
In the next lecture we will come back to the zonal mean problem for QG turbulence . 
But in this lecture we will study the relatio nship between mean tracer concen tration 
and tracer uxes in general. The tracer will be any concen tration c that satises the 
advection-dius ion equation. The QGPV budg et is an example of such a tracer. 
13.1 Tracer transp ort 
We want to study the tracer uxes generat ed by a turbulen t ow. Our goal is to 
deriv e an expression for the eddy uxes in terms of mean quantities. Consider a 
generic passiv e tracer of concentration c, 
ct + u  c = 2 c, (13.7) 
where  is the molecular diusivit y and u is an incompress ible ( u = 0) velocity 
eld. The velocity eld is given in this problem, i.e. we do not write a momen tum 
equat ion to solve for the velocity eld. The equat ion for the mean tracer concen tration 
is, 
ct + uc+  uc = 2c. (13.8) 
The funda mental problem of tracer turbulence is to determine the eect of the 
Reyno lds uxes uc on the mean tracer concen tration. 
In order to determine the Reynolds uxes, we must solve the equat ion for the tracer 
uctuat ions, 
c
t + uc +  uc  uc  2 c = u c. (13.9) 
Inspection of eq. (13.9) further suggests that if c = 0 at t = 0 then, c and care 
linearly related at all times. The equat ion for the tracer uctua tions is linear in c for a 
prescrib ed velocity eld and it is forced by c: doubling the forcing doubles the tracer 
uctuat ions. In other words we are stating that tracer uctuat ions c are generat ed 
by advective distor tion of the mean gradient, c. It follows that the eddy ux uc is 
linearly related to the mean gradient c. The coecient of proportiona lity between 
the tracer ux and the mean tracer gradien t turns out to be the eddy diusivit y 
introduced in the previous lectur e. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Using the equation for , 
u
ij =(i,t + u
ki,k + Uki,k  i,kk) j , (13.33) 
we obtain useful expressions for the diusive and skew components of the diusivit y, 
1 1   
Ds 
ij = t(ij )+ xk (u
k + Uk)(ij)  xk (ij )+ i,kj,k 2 2 
1 1   
Da = j i,t  ij,t + j (u
k + Uk) i,k  i (u
k + Uk) j,k  xk (i,kj  j,ki)ij 2 2 
(13.34) 
The rst line is symmetric and represe nts the dius ive comp onent. The second line 
is asymmetric and is the skew component. Molecular dius ion contribut es a positiv e 
denite term to the diusiv e comp onent. 
13.2.5 Antisymmetric componen t of the eddy diusi vity 
The role of the antisymmetric comp onent of the dius ivity tensor is best interpr eted 
if we write Da in the form, 
Da 
ij = ijkk. (13.35) 
This is the generic form of an antisymmetric tensor in three dimensions, i.e. any 
antisymmetric tensor can be written in the form (13.35). The tracer ux associated 
to the antisymmetric component of the diusivit y is the so called skew ux, 
uca = Da xj c= ijkkxj c=  c.ij (13.36) 
The skew ux can also be written as, 
a  uc=  (c)  ( ) c=  c+ uS c, (13.37) 
where, 
uS =   . (13.38) 
The skew ux is therefore equal to the sum of a rotationa l ux and an advective ux. 
The rotational ux does not aect the tracer evolution, since it has no divergence . 
The advective comp onent represen t the transp ort of tracer by the Stokes drift uS . 
13.2.6 Symmetric component of the eddy diusi vity 
Consider the evolutio n of the variance of the mean tracer concentration, 
tc2 +  u2 +c 2 + Dsc 2 = Ds   (13.39) c uS  ijxi cxj c. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Consider a tracer patch with concentration dieren t from zero only in a small area 
around xi = 0. Then we can approximat e the momen t evolution as, 
dM =0,	 (13.46) dt 
dM i   
dt  ui +uSi + j Ds M, (13.47) ij 
dM ii 
dt  2Diis M.	 (13.48) 
13.2.8 Summ ary about eddy diusiv ity 
In summa ry then, 
	The symmetric part of the diusivit y tensor corresponds to something like dif
fusive transp ort. 
	The antisymmet ric part, which is almost never zero, and it is in fact usually 
domina nt for rotationally dominat ed waves, corresponds to an advective trans
port. As a result, the mean advecting velocity that appears in eq. (13.28) is not 
u, but the velocity u+ uS. This seems to be telling us that the Eulerian mean 
velocity uis not the most natural choice of mean . 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Chang es in tracer variance can be induced by the terms inside the divergence or 
the term in the rhs. The terms inside the divergence depends both on the antisym
metric and the symmetric components of the eddy dius ivity. The term on the rhs 
instead depends on the symmetr ic comp onent only. The terms inside the divergence 
represen t processes that move tracer variance around the uid without changing the 
total integra l of the tracer variance. The rhs term, instead, represe nt a net source of 
tracer variance. hence only the symmetric comp onent of the eddy diusivit y represent 
processe s that enhance/reduc e tracer uctua tions. 
Lets compute the term on the rhs of equation (13.39), 
1   
Dijs xi cxj c =   xk (uk + Uk)(ixi  xk  (i,kxi c)2   t(ixi c)2 c)2 (ixi c)2 . 2 
Integrating over the uid volume, we obtain, 
   1  cxj c =  2 c)2 + (i,kxi c)2 dxdy dzDijs xi   dxdy dz t(ixi   0. 
The molecular processes and transience terms that appear in the symme tric com
ponent of the eddy dius ivity tend to reduce the tracer variance, i.e. they tend to 
homo genize the mean tracer concen tration. 
13.2.7 Eddy diusiv ity and moments of tracer concentration 
An alternativ e appro ach to understa nd the eect of the eddy diusivit y on the mean 
tracer concen tration is to compute the evolution of the tracer momen ts. The rst 
three tracer momen ts are dened as, 
M = dxdy dz c, (13.40) 
Mi = dxdy dzxic, (13.41) 
Mij = dxdy dzxixj c. (13.42) 
The evolution of the tracer momen ts is given by, 
dM =0, (13.43) dt 
dM i    
= dxdy dz ui +uSi + j Ds c, (13.44) dt ij 
dM ii     
=2 dxdy dz ui +uSi + j Dijs xic+2 dxdy dzDiis c.dt 
(13.45) 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>By taking the large scale and long time average of this equation, we obtain the 
solvabilit y condition, 
C0T2 = 2 (13.24) + U X2 C0 + C1T + U X C1 X C0 +(u X )  X C0.
The rhs represen ts the diusion of tracer concen tration by molecular and turbulen t 
processe s. This is best seen if we write, 
  
2 
X C0 + (u  X )   X C0 = X  X C0 + u  X C0 (13.25) 
= X  [DX C0], (13.26) 
where the tensor D, 
Dij = ij + u
ij , (13.27) 
is the eective diusivit y tensor. 
Summing the solvability conditio ns at O() and O(2) we obtain the evolution equa
tion for the mean tracer concen tration, 
ct + uc= xi [Dij xj c]. (13.28) 
The mean tracer concen tration is given by c= C0 + C1 and derivatives include 
variations on the slow space and time of rst seond order. The eectiv e diusivit y D 
is obtained by solving eq. (13.20) and compu ting the correlations between  and the 
velocity uctuatio ns u. 
13.2.4 Eddy diusi vity 
The main result of the multiple scale analysis is that there is a relationship between 
the eddy ux uc and the mean tracer gradien t c, 
u
ic = Dij xj c. (13.29) 
We want to understa nd what is the meaning of this diusivit y. Let us decompose 
diusivit y tensor into its symmetric and antisymmetric components, 
D = Ds + Da , (13.30) 
where the symmetric component is, 
1 Ds 
ij  (Dij + Dji) , (13.31) 2 
and the antisymme tric comp onent is, 
1 Da 
ij  (Dij  Dji) . (13.32) 2 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>13.2.1 Zerot h order solution 
Lets write the series of equatio ns order by order in . At st order we have, 
O(0) : C0t +(U + u) xC0  2 C0 =0. (13.15) x
The solutio n to this equatio n, satisfying the assumption that the initial tracer con
centration is smooth, has the genera l form, 
C0 = C0(X,T, X2,T2). (13.16) 
13.2.2 First order solution 
O() : C1t +(u + U ) xC1  x2 C1 = C0T  (u + U) X C0. 
(13.17) 
Averaging over the small and fast scales scales, we have, 
C0T + U X C0 =0, (13.18) 
from which it follows that, 
C1t +(u + U) xC1  x2 C1 = u X C0. (13.19) 
Solut ions to this problem can be written in the form C1 = ( )C0 + C1(X,T ), 
with (x,t) satisfying the equatio n, 
t +(U + u) x  x2  = u. (13.20) 
This equation resembles the equatio n for a particle displa cemen t, except for the pres
ence of the molecular diusiv e term. This dierenc e is extremely important, because 
molecula r dius ion is ultima tely the only process that can mix the tracer. Any theory 
of dius ion which neglects molecular processes must be taken with suspicion. The 
terms C1(X,T ) represe nts a small correction to the initial tracer concen tration. 
13.2.3 Second order solution 
O(2) : C2t +(u + U ) xC2  2 
xC2 = (13.21) 
C1T  (u + U) X C1 +2x X C1 + (13.22) 
X 2 C0  C0T2  (U + u) X2 C1. (13.23) 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 13 
Eddy Diusi vity 
Glenn introduced the mean eld appr oximation of turbulence in two-layer quasi
gesot rophic turbulence. In that approximation one must solve the zonally averaged 
equat ions for the zonal mean ow and temp erature and in addition the equat ions for 
the pertrur batio n potential vorticit y. This approach is comp utatio nally very expen
sive, because the pertur batio n potential vorticit y must be solved at full resolution 
and requir e short time steps. In this lecture we discuss under what approximatio ns 
we can step forward the zonal mean equations witho ut solving for the perturba tion 
equat ions. 
The zonal mean QG momentum equatio ns are, 
Ui = viqi+ F U i +(1)i+1F (13.1) t 
where F = f02/gH, F is any external stress,  is Raleigh damping of momentum, 
and i refers to the layer number (1 or 2). The residual streamfunction  is given by 
the the zonally averaged omega equatio n, 
2 g 
y2  F1  F2  = f0 Hy + v1q1 v2q2(13.2) 
and H is the diabatic forcing of the interface (temp erature) equat ion. The mean eld 
approxima tion consists in linear izing the uctua ting qiequat ion as, 
qiqi
+ Ui + Qi,yvi= qi. (13.3) t x 
Let us now multiply the perturb ation equatio ns by qiand take once again a zonal 
average, 
qi2 
+2Qi,yviqi= qi2 . (13.4) t 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>13.2 Eddy uxes and the multi-scal e metho d 
Using an assumptio n of scale separa tion between the turbulen t eddie s and the mean, 
we will show how the concept of a tracer diusivit y arises in a Elueria n context. 
The scale separ ation appro ach is based on the assumption that the advected tracer 
is weakly inhomogeneous on a scale L much greater than the scale l0 of the turbulen t 
uctuat ions. The goal is then to deriv e equatio ns for the evolution of the coarse-
grained averaged tracer on the length scale L, and on a time scale T large compar ed 
with the time scale t0  l0/u0, characteristic of the energy containing eddies of the 
turbulence. We may then choose an intermedia te scale , e.g.  =(l0L)1/2, and an 
intermedia te time , e.g.  =(t0T )1/2, satisfying, 
l0    L, t0    T, (13.10) 
and think of the overbar average as a local average over a cube of side , and a 
time of order . Averaged quantities will vary only on larger scales of order L and 
longer times of order T . The repla cemen t of ensem ble and volume/time averages is 
possible only if the turbulence is homo geneous and stationa ry on the small spatial 
and temp oral scales, so that an ergodic assumptio ns can be made. 
The multi-scale metho d that we use here was rst introduced by Papanicolao u and 
Pirro neau (1981). The scale separation assumptio n suggests that a perturba tion 
expansio n can be done in terms of the small parameter   l0/L. Supp ose now that 
c(x, 0) is slowly varying so that, 
c(x, 0) = C0(x). (13.11) 
Eq. (13.7), together with the initial conditio n in eq. (13.11) suggests a multiple scale 
analysis with the slow variables, 
X = x, X2 = 2 x, T = t,T2 = 2t. (13.12) 
The solut ion of eq. (13.7) then takes the form, 
c(x,t; )= C0(X,T )+ C1(x,t; X,T )+ 2C2(x,t; X,T )+ .... (13.13) 
The quan tity of interest is the large-scale, long-time, averaged eld c = C0(X,T )+ 
O(). Its evolutio n is obtained by usual asympt otic methods. Substituting the ex
pansio n (13.13) into the advection diusion equatio n (13.7), one obtains a series of 
equat ions order by order in . 
The advecting velocity eld must be expanded as well. We will assume that the 
velocity eld is composed of a mean ow varying on the slow variables only U(X,T ) 
and a turbulent pertur batio ns u, 
u  U(X,T )+ u(x,t; X,T ). (13.14) 
We do not assume that the mean ow is of small amplitude comp ared to the turbulen t 
ow as it is often done in the litera ture of eddy mean ow interactions 
3</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Baroclinic Turbulence (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch18/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Resitlual circulation 
We can compare the residiial circ~ilation, represented by 4, to the Elilerian mean 
meridional flow, which we can represent by 
These are for F = 100: P = 0.1. 
Demos, Page 3: Diagnostics &lt;Eddy enstrophy&gt; &lt;Zonal flow&gt; &lt;mean: 
&lt;PV gradients&gt; &lt;mean PV gradients&gt; &lt;phi&gt; &lt;phia&gt; &lt;mean&gt; 
In this case the divergence of the eddy fl~ixes vanishes, so there is no feedback on the 
mean. The linearly growing wave is an exact sohition to the fully nonlinear eq~iations: if 
then the inversion implies 41' =g(&lt;) with 
But the nonlinear term is now 
Pedlosky (1975) and Pedlosky and Polvani (1987) suggest that the growing wave can 
itself becorne iinstable to other waves which then remove the energy. We can illlistrate this 
by using a wave triad in which the middle wavm~irnber is the baroclinically iinstable one 
while the smaller and larger ones are stable. 
The indices are triad minlber: these need to be solved in each layer so that there are 12 
degrees of freedom (6 cornplex q's). 
Demos, Page 3: triad &lt;no nonlinearity&gt; &lt;nonlinear&gt; &lt;full calculation: 
&lt;full enstrophies&gt; &lt;full enstrophies&gt; &lt;full energy&gt; &lt;zonal flow&gt; 
The fill1 sollition shows this breakdown and the development of tiirb~ilence. With 
these parameters, there are zonal means with amplitlides (at the end) of about 113 the 
rnaxinnirn zonal velocity.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>So that the Arnol'd invariant simply decays with time. 
We thus obt,ain the two theorems: 
Unstable flows imply t,hat t,heenergy and enstrophy are growing in time; this can only 
happen if the second term can offset the first. Thus, if Qq &gt; 0 everywhere, the flow 
is stable. 
If Qg is everywhere negat,ive, the flow can still be nnstable if t,he available waveniim-
hers are so large that A is negative definite. 
For nonlinear stability, we define the Hamiltonian fimctional 
and a so-called Casirnir 
Cbl = //q~(s)ds 
under the asslimption that P is rnonotonically increasing (and ignoring the boundary terms 
-see Shepherd, Adv. in Geopllys; 32, 287-338 for a more fornlal derivation). Then 
&amp;[nl = H[ql -H[Q1+ C[ql -C[121 
is conserved, is equal to zero when q' = 0 and its first variation also vanishes (it's q~iadrat~ic 
in q'). E is called the "pse~idoenergy." If, therefore, 
0 &lt; Cmin &lt; Pg &lt; Cma:c 
and 
$'2 =E+CminZ 
then ma:,;ll*'(t)l12 5 -lld~'([))l12Cmin 
-t,he flow is nonlinearly stable. 
For flows witahtranslational invariance, the pse~idornoment,~im 
is also conserved. Y(Q) is the inverse of Q(y). The stability theorern now states that 
For small amplitude, the psiiedornornent~im becomes the negative of the wave activity</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>(Shepherd uses U &gt; 0 but that doesn't, seem necessary). 
We have either 
PU = 2--U (weak s~i~ercriticality) 
Fz 
For the first case 11 @Hz -2H -H~Y':+H~Y':5 -8) 
and for strong shear 
For the run shown (U = 1;F1 = Fz= 100, P = lo), this works out to about 250(?). 
Demos, Page 7: example &lt;Eddy enstrophy&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Baroclinic Turbulence 
Two layer model 
We have the two PV eqliations 
q' = v2~,' -f F($; $4) 
Here F = f;lg1H and (I),, = P -Uy, &amp; F(U~-u2). 
The zonal average eqliations are 
The omega eqliation becomes 
-with R = v'q' + F-TU, 
We shall arrange the forcing to produce a linifornl vertical shear so that Uj + Uj +Uj. 
The backgrolind PV gradients are 
The Rayleighl Charney-Stern theorem gives a necessary condition for instability: the 
gradient Qg nnist change sign either in the horizontal or in the vertical; this will occur 
when 
Ui -U2 &lt; -PIIFI OT Ul -U2 &gt; P2IF2 
Note the asynlnletry between eastward vs. westward shear in the ocean where we typically 
take F2 N $F1:we require ~nlich more eastward shear to destabilize the flow. 
To solve; we take q' = qexp(zk . x + ot)with $I defined similarly. from the PV 
specification, we have 
,ji = L~~*~ *i,,T = ~7.16. 
Z? 3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Bounds 
Shepherd considers the flow to be a stable zonal shear plus a deviation which inchides 
a zonal shear which shifts the total into the instable range phis the wave distlirbance 
This derivation follows Shepherd (and Held's suggestion) dirctly except the layer depths 
are not presiimed to be eqiial. For the Phillip's problem, we take U to be mif form. Then 
and the conservation follows directly 
For Q; &gt; &amp;', &gt; 0,we have 
The PV gradients of the background flow are 
and the PV's of the renlainer are 
The right-hand side of the inequality (assliming the waves start off at infinitesimal 
anlplitlide) becomes 
1-(u -u)' [H~F:+ 24 P -F2U 
since HIFl = H2F2. We want t,o minimize this siibject t,o</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Upper bounds 
Shepherd (1988, JAS) develops an lipper boimd for the wave enstrophy based on the 
nonlinear stability theory of Arnol'd. It's worthwhile starting from that point since it can 
give insight into nonzonal systenls as well. 
Essentially we want to derive a fiinctional which has vanishing derivative at the basic 
stat,e and then determine if it has a mininliim, maximiim, or saddle point there. In ther 
first two cases, the basic state will be stable. For the linearized problem siich a fiinctional 
can be derived directly and is proportional to the square of t,he perturbation amplitiide (in 
the instable case having indeterminate sign for the coefficients at varioiis wavemimnbers). 
We start witah the PV equation and split it into basic stat,e and fliictiiation 
We presiin1e we can take Q = Qf and that the corresponding satisfies 
For the channel with Qf depending on y, this is straightforward. This relationship implies 
Then we can write the linearized stability problem as 
The pertiirbation enstrophy satisfies 
while the total energy obeys 
The first eqiiation implies</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The dynamical eqiiation becomes 
(a+p)Gi = -zkUiGi -tk&amp;yiqi +rk2&amp; 
This is a standard eigenvahie problem 
zk~~t-l+ q [-zkU - k2~t-l] = (a+p)q 
except the rnatrix is complex. The U, Qy, and R matrices are diagonal (with the latter 
having Rll = 0, R22 = T). For the two-layer model, 
and 
Demos, Page 2: Growth rates &lt;r=O,ul pos F2=4&gt; &lt;r=O,ul neg F1=20&gt; 
&lt;r=O. 01 ,ul pos&gt; &lt;r=O. 01, ul neg&gt; &lt;r=O. 1, ul pos&gt; &lt;r=O. 1,ul neg&gt; 
Other 1)roblrrns 
The Eady model jiist has a different L: if slibscript 1is the top and 2 is the bottom, 
then 
sinh Kz sinh K (H-z)* = *'sinh KH + *' sinh KH 
awith K = -N/ f. The active scalars are ql = z$H and 42 = $go and 
L= (	K cothKH -KcschKH 
KcschKH -K coth KH 
Demos, Page 2: eady &lt;sigma vs r&gt; 
Cessation of growth 
The linear problenl predicts exponential growth even with frict,ion; to stop this, the 
nonlinearity nnist enter at some point. This co~ild occiir in the form of divergent eddy PV 
fliixes . . 
which alter the mean PV and therefore the mean U fields. In tlirn, the linear part of the 
fliictiiation eqn. changes and the growth rate can drop. 
The mean field approximation disclissed previolisly relies on this mechanism. Becaiise 
of channel walls, the growing modes have 
qi = &amp;(t)cos(kx -Bi) sin(!y) 
and the phases differ between the two q's and therefore between the dl's and q's. In that 
case: the u' will not be in qiiadratnre with the q'. The linear soliit,ion predicts a PV flux 
proportional to sin(2ey) which tries to eliminate the negative Qy gradient in the center of 
the channel. 
Demos, Page 2: Examples &lt;F=100, beta=O. 1&gt; &lt;full&gt; &lt;mean&gt;</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Transformed Eulerian Mean in 3D (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch15/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>In conclusion, if we wish to parameterize the eddy forcing, it is only the divergence of
the QGPV flux that we need to parameterize in order to calculate the response of the
mean geostrophic flow.  Notice, however, that a parameterization of the divergentQGPV eddy flux might be elusive, because the QGPV variance budget in 3D is not as
useful as in the zonal problem.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>where
=zu/primeb/prime
N2. (15.7)
This denitio nleavesthebuo yancybudg etinthe simple form,
bt+(u)b+wN2=B. (15.8)
15.2 Transfo rmedmomentum budget
The momen tumbudget mustnowbewritt enreplacing theageo strophic velocitywith
the residua lvelocity,
ut+(u)u+f0zu= G(u/prime)u/prime+fz() (15.9 )
= G(u/prime)u/prime+fz
z/parenleftBiggu/primeb/prime
N2/parenrightBigg
f
= GjMji
where the genera lizedEP uxes are givenby,
M =
Mxx Mxy
MyxMyy
MzxMzy
=
u/prime2+f u/primev/prime
u/primev/prime v/prime2+f
fN2v/primeb/primefN2u/primeb/prime
. (15.10 )
The functio nisyettobedetermined (itisarbitra rybecauseofagauge invaria nce
inthe denitio nof).
The QGPV ux in3Dis,
u/prime
iq/prime=u/prime
i/bracketleftBigg
v/prime
xu/prime
y+f
z/parenleftBiggb/prime
N2/parenrightBigg/bracketrightBigg
=jQji (15.11 )
where,
Q =
Qxx Qxy
QyxQyy
QzxQzy
=
u/primev/prime v/prime2/epsilon1
/epsilon1u/prime2 u/primev/prime
fN2u/primeb/primefN2v/primeb/prime
. (15.12 )
Weintroduced the energydens ity,
/epsilon1=1
2/parenleftBig
u/prime2+v/prime2+N2b/prime2/parenrightBig
=/epsilon1K+/epsilon1P (15.13 )
givenbythesum ofthe kinetic and potentialenerg ydensities.
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>By choosing,
=1
f/parenleftBig
/epsilon1u/prime2v/prime2/parenrightBig
=1
f(/epsilon1P/epsilon1K), (15.14 )
wehavethat jMji=zjQji=zu/primeq/prime.And the transformed equatio nsbecome,
ut+(u)u+f0zu=Gzu/primeq/prime (15.15 )
bt+(u)b+wN2=B, (15.16 )
u=0. (15.17 )
This system appearstobeanalo goustothe TEM zonal meanproblem: there areno
explicit eddy terms inthebuo yancybudget, andthe eddies app ear inthe momen tum
budget inthe form ofaQGPV ux. Tobeexactasaforce peruntilmass equa lin
mag nitude, and norma l,tothe QGPV ux.
15.3 Transfo rmedQGP Vbudg et
The transformed QGPV budget isstraigh tforw ard,because QGPV isadv ected only by
the horizon talgeostrophic owandnot bythe ageostrophic velocities(whic hchang e
uponintroduction ofthe residua lvelocity),
qt+uq=u/primeq/prime+zG+f
z/parenleftbiggB
N2/parenrightbigg
. (15.18 )
Not ethattheQGPV budget isonly aected bythe diver gent part ofthe QGPVux,
while the full QGPV ux appearsinthe residua lmomen tum budget. This ispuzzling,
because weknowthat the mean geostr ophic circula tion can bereconstr uctedfrom
kno wledgeofthe mea npotentialvorticit y,and hence formakno wledge oftheQGPV
ux divergence alone. Following Plum b(JAs, 1986)wecan showthat itisindee d
only the divergen tpartofthe QGPV ux thatappearsinthe momentum equa tion.
Lets lookattheconsequence ofsubtra cting apurely rotatio nal comp onenttothe
QGPV ux,
(u/primeq/prime)D=u/primeq/primez. (15.19 )
The forcingofthemomen tum equa tion becomes,
zu/primeq/prime=z(u/primeq/prime)D+. (15.20 )
the term can thenbeabsorb edintoarede nition ofthe ageostro phic circulation
dening,
=1
f(/epsilon1P/epsilon1K+). (15.21 )
Using this technique, wecanremo veanyrotational componen tofthe QGPV ux
from the momen tum equa tion.
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Cha pter 15
Transfo rmedEulerianMean in3D
Inthislecture weshowthat the Transfor medEulerian Meantheo rycanbeextende d
tothreedimens ions. Wewillrestrict the analysis tothequa si-geo strophic equatio ns,
but progress can bemade forprimitiv eequat ions aswell.Most ofthe workreported
here canbefound inPlum b(JAS, 1990)and Wardle and Marshall (JPO, 2000).
Consider the averag e(x,y,z,t)ofa3D,QG system.The averagecanbeatemporal
averag e,alow-passspatial lteroratemp orallter. The averag edQG equatio nsat
O(1)are,
fuz=zb, u=0, (15.1)
(15.2)
where uisthehorizontalgeostro phic velocity.AtO(Ro),
ut+(u)u+f0zua=G(u/prime)u/prime, (15.3)
bt+(u)b+waN2=Bu/primeb/prime, (15.4)
ua=0. (15.5)
15.1 Theresidual circulat ion
Asforthe zonal mean case, webegin bydening the residua lcirculation with the aim
ofremo ving anyskewbuo yancy ux from thebuo yancy budget. Since N2doesnot
dep endonxand y,the whole ux isskewand can beeliminated withthe follo wing
denition ofresidual circulatio n,
u=ua+, (15.6)
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Turbulence intheAtmospher eand
Oceans
Instructors: Raaele Ferrariand Glenn Flierl
Coursedescript ion
The cour sewillpresen tthephenomena ,theor y,and modeling ofturbulence inthe
Eart hs oceans andatmosphere. The scop ewill range from centime tertoplanetary
scale motions. The regime softurbule nce will includehomo geneous isot ropic three
dimensional turbulenc e,convection, bounda rylayerturbulence, internal waves,two
dimensional turbulence, quasi-geo strophic turbule nce, andplaneta ryscale motion sin
the ocean andatmosphere. Prerequisites: themathemat icsandphysics required for
admission tothe gradua tecurriculum inthe EAPS depa rtmen t,orconsentofthe
instructo r.
Courserequire ments
Class attendance and disc ussion, bi-w eeklyhomew ork assignm ents.
Refe rence texts
Frisch,Turbulence: the lega cyofKolmogo rov
Lesieur, Turbu lence inFluids, 3rdrevisededition
McC omb,The physic softurbulence
Sama n,Vortex dynamics
Salmo n,Lectures ongeoph ysical uid dynamics
Stro gatz,Nonlinear Dyna mic sandChao s:With Applic ationsinPhysic s,Biology,
Chemis try,andEng ineering 
Tennek esand Lumley ,Arst course inTurbulence</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Nonlinear Internal Waves, Solitary Waves (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch21/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>- - We note that .J(gl, C1) = 0 and .J(?l,l, bl) = 0. The solvability condition comes from 
looking at the part of the second order solution which is proportional to 4; taking the 
second equation minus co tiines the first gives 
Therefore we require 
and 
A(X, T; r) = A(X -cYT, r) 
I11 addition to the forced solution, we can add a free solution at order eZ so that 
g2 = P(X -cyT, T, r) fW)(z) 
N aZbz = B(X -cyT, T, r) f (2)---K 3x3~" 
At order e3 (sigh!) we find 
3 3 3 3 3 
-C3+ -CZ+ -C1 --b3 --bz +.J(?1,1, CZ) + .J(?~,Z, Cl) + 3($1, (1) = 03t 3T 3r 3x 3X 3(X, Y) 
3 3 a 3 3 a($1; bl) 
-b3 + -bz + -bl +NZ-$3 + N'-$JZ + .J(?l,l; bz) + bl) + = 03t 3T 3r dx 3X 3(X; Y)
a2 32 
V2?1,3+ 2=?1,z + 7@$1 = C3 
We can collect the terms which are independent of x -cot 
3P 3P 32fC*) 3B a2 
(--c -)-322- + 2.J(q51, - $1) = 03T ydX 3~ f 
3B 3B (1) 3P N a2 (--c -) f +N2- f C*) --.J(q!ll, 7 $1) = 0dT Y3X 3X K 
We use a2 3AI2 . 
$1) = k2m- 3X sin 2mzeJ($l, 
to find f C~J)= f ('1 = sin2mz and 
These deternine the corrections to the mean stratification and flow in the region of the 
wave packet. 
Collecting the terms which are proportional to 4gives 
which determines the packet amplitude.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>SOLITARY WAVES: For these, we look at the steady solutions for the mean correctioils 
and 
the nonlinear Schriidinger equation, with 
Letting 
A = A exp(-zkclr) 
gives 
which has solutions 
Again, the nonlinear group travels faster with a speed depeildeilt on the amplitude and a 
width decreasing as A. increases. 
MODULATIONAL If we begin with an infinite regular wave A = INSTABILITY: 1+ 6A, 
we can look at the perturbation by envelope variability. The P and B equations will show 
rapid oscillations around 
and we'll ignore the high frequency variations. Then 
This gives 
6A e"' . r2= k2(2wp-k2) 
This call be positive near k &lt; 0.766m where P becomes large.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Nonlinear waves 
Theories of nonlinear waves have been developed for inany systems; we shall treat 
two-dimensional internal gravity wave dynamics here. 
We assume that there is no variation in y and write the horizontal and vertical velocities 
in terms of a streamfunction 
Forming a horizontal vorticity equation (C = -C. 9 = ik! 2 = ~211,)gives the set a%-
We shall use B(z) = JZ N2 for the basic stratification. 
Steadily propagating waves 
We begin by looking for steadily propagating nonlinear solutions. If we replace 6by 
-cz,a we have 
.7($ +cz; &lt;) = -3b 
ax 
.7($ + cz, b + B(z)) = 0 
The last equation implies 
b+ B(z) = B(z+ -)$ 
C 
which has a (by no means unique) solution 
For this solution, 11, and b go to zero smoothly and are related in the linear limit by</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>have &lt;Q 3( -QJ ill the center; this will occur when Q is positive. Solitary waves are a?single-signed; for S' &gt; 0, we find only waves with the isotherms depressed. 
We call write an explicit solution to 
with 
in the form of the hyperbolic secant squared solitary wave 
Kortweg-deVries equation 
We can examine the time-dependent behavior of nonlinear disturbances in the liinit 
where dispersion and nonlinearity are weak, but comparable, effects. We again use multiple 
scale expailsions with t as a "marker" 
To think of these as nondimensional, scale x -L, z -H, ?i, UH; &lt; -U/H, c 
NOH,t -L/NUH; and b -NoU. Then S is the nondimeilsional function N'/N; and 
E = U/NoH = HZ/L2. The last equality expresses the relationship between U and L so 
that iloilliilearity and dispersion are similar in strength. 
The expailsion gives 
and</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Thus we see asynlmetries in the shape of the wave. If we multiply the Fzz equation above 
by F and integrate, we see that 
Thus for S' &gt; 0,FZ2will be negative and the cos(2kx) term will have a positive coefficient: 
streamfunction highs will be sharper and lows flatter. Also, the isotherms will have flat 
crests and sharp troughs. In addition, the $I2 field has a net nleail flow contribution. We 
can get rid of this term if we choose by going back to the equation for the vorticity and 
writing it as 
with the last term order E. The sequence of equations now has 
This kind of ambiguity is characteristic of nonlinear waves -there can be many different 
solutions depending on the choice of functionals. Without some further specification, 
there will be aspects which are undetermined. One such consideration is elimination of the 
mean zonal flow at second order; another might be requiring that the volume between two 
isotherins be the same as in the case when the buoyancy is just B(z). Since the streamlines 
are isotherms; this coines back to the same requirement: we want dx$ = 0. Therefore 
we choose 1z1= -A;S'F~2 
and $2 is just 1 
$12 = --A3/' cos(2Xx)F22(~)2 O 
For the third equation, we have 
Substitutiilg for the last term, doing the averages of the cosines, and integrating by parts 
a few tiines gives 
3 I 4~11X2(F2S)+ Z~~12(~2fi2~1) ) = 0 + -A;(F8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Stokes' expansion 
For small, but finite, amplitude waves, we can Taylor-expand the equation to get 
This is like the oscillator equation with a iloilliilear restoring force. 
We expand 
$ = t$l + t2?JI2+ t3$3... 
2 c = Xo +Al+t2X2 
and use the ilotatioil S = N2 to get a sequence of problenls 
The first equation gives 
We apply solvability coilditioils to the second and third equations: if 
then 
dx F (z) cos(kx)R,, (x, z) = 0H 
For the second equation, this implies X1 = O and therefore 
1 1 
$2 = 2 -2 (z) --A~'~FZO(Z) -Xi/' co~(2kx)F~~ 
with 
32[s-n2k2+ XoS]F2T,,= S!F2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>At lowest order, we have disturbances moving at the long wave speed el, with vertical 
structure Fl,: 
(we'll drop the lw subscript henceforth). At the next order, we have 
We multiply both equations by F and average to find 
Multiplying the first equation by -co and adding gives 
The solvability condition gives the KdV equation: 
with A and B defined as before. 
CHARACTERISTICS The KdV eqn. has solitary wave solutions 
 OF THE KDV EQN: 
as we found before. Note that if A = 6A/BL2; the speed is proportional to the amplitude 
cl = 2BA/3 and the width varies inversely L = (~A/B)~/~A~~/~. 
We can set up two waves to "collide" and find that they pass through (with a phase 
shift). Demos, Page 7: Collision &lt;two waves&gt; &lt;summary&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>which is exactly what one gets for linear waves. 
The vorticity equation now gives 
1a$ .J($ +cz, vZ$)=B'(z+$1~)--c ax 
Therefore we have z $v" --N~(Z +$/c) =Z(z +-)
C C 
or (taking the same kind of extension of the linear solution) 
Our final equation is 
When NZ(z) is constant -unifornz stratification -the wave equation is linear with 
solutions like 
$ =Acos(kx) sin(mz) , c2 =NZ/(kZ+mZ) 
with m = n/H for a domain height H bounded by horizontal surfaces. This is the standard 
internal gravity wave dispersion relationship. For this case, the linear waves are a solution 
to the nonlinear equations. 
For a non-uniform stratification, if the wave amplitude is small enough; we can sepa- 
rate variables 
$ = d~(x)F(z) 
with 
The vertical structure equation gives a relationship between c and yZ while the horizontal 
equation just gives sinusoidal disturbances with wavenumber k = y. Note that there will 
be a gravest long wave nzode corresponding to the value c = el, where yZ goes through 
zero.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>SOLITONS: An initial disturbance breaks up into a train of solitary waves ranked 
in amplitude plus a weak dispersive field. This is not a ilunlerical artifact or accident 
associated with a particular shape of initial conditions; "inverse scattering theory" gives 
an exact solution to the KdV problem treating the initial coildition as a potential. The 
solitoils correspoild to the bound states of the potential and the dispersive waves nlap to 
the scattering modes. 
Demos, Page 7: kdv solns &lt;dispersive amp=0.1&gt; &lt;one soliton mp=l&gt; 
&lt;two mp=3&gt; &lt;three mp=7&gt; 
INTERNAL WAVES: AS a warning, though, we cannot be sure that similar "particle- 
like" properties apply when the waves have different vertical modes or propagate in different 
directions. 
Group solitary waves 
Noilliilearity can also act on wave groups,where it can create solitary wave packets 
and lead to modulational instability -the breakdown of a regular wave into groups. The 
inath here is more complicated, unfortunately. We again expand the wave into 
etc., with X = ex; T = d,T = e2t.The sequence of problems becomes 
with N2= const for simplicity and to avoid the Stokes' wave kind of nonlinearity. These 
give the basic wave solution 
with = exp(zkx -scukt) sin(mz), K = dm, and co = N/K. 
At order e2, we have</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>This determines the corrections to the phase speed: 
For the case S' &gt; 0, S" = 0 (buoyancy increasing quadratically with height), we have 
The wave moves more slowly, which makes sense since it extends downward more into the 
weakly stratified zone. 
Solitary wa,ves 
We can also find long wave solutions limit which are spatially isolated. Since such 
solutions decay to zero, the original choices for B(Z) = B(Z) and Z(Z) = -ZN2(Z)/c are 
necessary; the values are set along a streamline by the fields flowing in from +awhere 
the streanllines correspond to the background state. We now analyze 
a"under the assumption that u/c t and L -~c'/~H -t compared to -. We SO that &amp; 
then have the sinlpler sequence 
The lowest order equation now constrains oilly the vertical structure to be the long wave 
structure fuilctioil $1 = Q(x)Fl, and the eigenvalue to be Xo = el,2 . The solvability 
condition for the next order problem is 
To have decaying solutions at infinity, we must have A1 &lt; 0; since c = el, -iXlcf,',, this 
implies that solitary waves move faster than the longest linear wave. This makes sense 
from the linear dispersioil relation: if 
and lc2 &lt; O representing exponential decay (at the front) or growth (at the back); the 
phase speed will be increased rather than decreased from the long wave value N/m. In 
addition, to turn the rising wave on the left to a decaying wave on the right, we must</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Transition to Turbulence (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 2 
From laminar to turbulent ows 
Turbulent ows can often be observ ed to arise from lamina r ows as the Reyno lds 
number is increased1 . The transitio n to tubule nce happens because small distur bances 
to the ow are no longer da mped by the o w, but b egin to grow by taking energy from 
the original lamina r ow. This natur al process is easily visualized by watching the 
simple strea m of water from a faucet (or even a pitcher). Turn the ow on very slow 
(or pour) so the stream is very smooth initially, at least near the outlet. Now slowly 
open the faucet (or pour faster) and observ e what happ ens, rst far away, then closer 
to the spout. The surface begins to exhibit waves or ripples which appear to grow 
downstream. In fact, they are growing by extra cting energy from the primary ow. 
Eventually they grow enoug h that the ow breaks into drops. These are capillary 
instabilit ies arising from surface tension, but regardless of the type of instabilit y, the 
idea is the same innit esimal disturbances have grown to disrupt the simplicit y of 
the laminar ow. In this lecture we investiga te how this transitio n from laminar to 
turbulen t dynamics occurs. 
Laminar ows are soluti ons of the Navier-Stok es equat ions in the limit when nonlin
earities can be neglected. This situa tion corresponds to the Stokes approxima tion; 
the ow is given by a balance between exter nal forcing (mechanical or thermo dyna m
ical) and dissipatio n. The corresp onding velocity eld is entirely predicta ble and has 
the same regularit y properties as the applied externa l forces. 
As the Reyno lds number is increased, nonline arities are no longer negligible. There 
is a critical Reyno lds number, above which the system bifurcates toward completely 
new solut ions. These solutio ns correspond to break ing of symmetr ies of the origi
nal ow. For example a steady ow submitted to time independen t forcing becomes 
time periodic. Usually the state resulting from a rst bifurcatio n is still very regular. 
1In this lecture Reynol ds number is used to iden tify whatever nondimensional number is appro
priate to characterize the onset of turbulence in the prob lem at hand. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>When the Reyno lds number is increased even further, the ow that emerged after the 
prima ry bifurcat ion can itself become unstable to new modes breaking new symme
tries. The set of bifurca tion continues until the global dynamics of the ow becomes 
very comp licated, i.e. turbulent. 
The transition from simple to complex behavior is observed in models as simple as 
deterministic maps. Thus in the next sectio n we derive a map based on a loose anal
ogy to the Navier-Sto kes equat ion. A study of solut ions of the map will provide an 
introduction to the problem of the onset of complexit y and chaos in simple deter
ministic systems . These results will provide an introductio n to the problem of onset 
of turbulence. How can irregular and apparen tly stochastic solutio ns appear in uid 
ows that are governed by deterministic equat ions? 
2.1	The lo gistic map as a poor man s Navier-Stokes 
equat ion 
Following Frisch we introduce a discrete map that mimics some of the properties of 
the Navier-Stokes equatio ns. A sort of a poor mans Navier-Stokes equatio n. We 
begin with the incompressible form of the NavierStokes equat ions, 
u + F ,	 (2.1) ut + u u = p + Re12 
 u =0.	 (2.2) 
We now express the sloutio ns in terms of the Fourier represe ntation of u, 
u(x, t)= ai(t)e ikx .	 (2.3) 
i 
This resulting innite system of ordinary dierential equations (ODEs) for the Fourier 
coecie nts is known as a Galerkin projection of the Navier-Stok es equat ions; e.g., 
ai =  Aijkaj ak  Re1|k|2 ai + Fi. (2.4) 
jk 
Equat ion (2.4) is simple to understand. Every mode ai represen ts a comp onent of 
the velocity eld with a lengthscale |k|. The velocity eld at each lengt hscale can 
be changed through nonlinea r interactio n with other modes, throug h linea r damping 
or through forcing Fi. The nonlinear interaction are quadr atic and their streng th is 
controlled by the coecients Aijk. Damping is inversely proportiona l to the length-
scale and thus it is more ecien t for small-scale modes. A detailed derivation of 
equat ion (2.4) is given in chapter 3 of Salm ons book. 
In order to keep the problem simple let us remo ve all but a single arbitra ry wave 
mode. This procedure is called a Galerkin trunca tion. This results in an equatio n of 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Figur e 2.1: The complete orbit diagram, which is the plot of the maps attracto r as 
a functio n of r. This amazing diagram is as beautiful as it is myster ious. If you look 
at it more closely, you will nd that lying just above the periodic windo ws in the 
chaotic regio n are small copies of the whole orbit diagram. Thus this pictur e has ne 
structures at arbitrar ily small scales. 
7
Figure removed due to copyright restrictions.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>and |xn| will increase on succe ssive iterations for F (xf ) &gt; 1. Thus the xed point 
is stable for F (xf ) &lt; 1 and is unstable for F (xf ) &gt; 1. This procedure is the map 
equiv alent of the linear stabilit y analysis of solutio ns of the Navier-Stok es equatio ns. 
In 12.803 we considered the linear stabilit y analysis of shear ows. In that case we 
considered the stabilit y as a functio n of external parameters like the shear and its 
curvature. Here we will study the stability of xed points for dierent Reyno lds 
numbers. 
2.1.2 Bifurcat ions and the onset of chaos in the logistic map 
In the logistic map for small values of r there is only one stable xed point xf and 
almo st all initia l conditio ns lead to an orbit that converges to the xed point (x =0 
and x = 1 being exceptiona l initia l conditio ns). Thes e solut ions correspond to the 
lamina r ows at small Reyno lds numbers. Nonline arities are subdominan t. However 
thing s chang e as we increase r. Wha t happens when xf becomes unstable (whic h 
happ ens at r = 3)? 
The rst bifurcati on 
As the map parameter r is changed, the character of the long time solution drama t
ically chang es, from a xed point to a time dependen t solutio n. These changes are 
called bifurca tions. For values of r slightly larger then 3, the solut ion converges to an 
orbit which alterna tely visits two values x1 and x2: this is the discrete time version of 
a limit cycle or periodic orbit (here period two). The second iterate function y = F 2 
yields three intersection s with the line y = x. It is easy to check that at two of 
these the magnitude of the slope |dF 2/dx| is less than unity, i.e. there are two stable 
xed points of F 2, and these corresp ond to x1 and x2. The third xed point of F 2 is 
unstable: xf is of course an unsta ble xed point of F . These issues are illustrated by 
the matla b functio ns cobweb.m and logistic fp.m. Try to run them using r =3.2. 
The second bifurcati on 
Set r to r =3.5 and look at the iteratio ns of F . The period two orbit has gone 
unstable, and the trajectory converges to a period four orbit. We have seen that the 
period two orbit is simple (a xed point!) in F 2 . We can understand the second 
bifurcatio n by studying the xed points of F 4 . The instabilit y of the period two orbit 
is seen to be associated with the slope of F 4 becoming greater than unity, and again 
two new xed points of F 4 develop. 
Further bifurcat ions 
The analysis of bifurcatio ns gets more and more awkward as r increases. Hence we 
switc h to numberical explo ration. But keep in mind that numerics can nd attractor s 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>the form,
a= Aa2  Re1|k|2 a, (2.5) 
i.e. an evolution equation for one mode forced by a quadr atic nonline arity and damp
ing. This deriv ation is not formally correct. A careful expansion of the Navier-Stok es 
equat ion would show that a mode cannot interact nonlinea rly with itself. In other 
words Aiii = 0. We ignore the issue for the moment. The only justicatio n for 
equat ion (2.5) is that it has a quadra tic nonline arity and dissipatio n, much alike 
the Navier-Stokes equatio n and it migh t be a useful paradigm to study the onset of 
complex behavior in a simple determinis tic system. 
It is straightforward to solve (2.5) numerically . Here we will emplo y a simple forward 
Euler single-step, explicit time integratio n procedure. This leads to, 
an+1 
  an = Aa2 
n  Re1|k|2 an, (2.6) 
where  is an arbitrary discrete time step parameter. We now rearr ange the equation 
as, 
an+1 = Aan 1  Re1|k|2 
 an . (2.7) A 
This map can be reduced to a well studied example, if we require, 
1  Re1|k|2 
=1, (2.8) A 
which implies that, 
A =1  Re1|k|2 . (2.9) 
This in turn permits us to write (2.6) as, 
an+1 =4 1  Re1 |k|2 an(1  an)= ran(1  an), (2.10) 
which is the well known logistic map. 
It is easily seen that as Re , r 1 from below. Since a(1  a) has a maximum 
at 1/4 for a  [0.1] we see that we should rescale r by a facto r of 4 to obtain that the 
range of values for r is is between zero and four, just as in the logistic map. It is also 
worth observing that r depends on the wavevector magnitude, and on the numerical 
time step parameter. In particular, we see that the product of these factors must be 
less than Re in order for r&gt; 0 to hold. This implies that as the wavevector magnitude 
increases, the time step size must decrease, just as would certainly be the case in order 
to maintain stability of an explicit time-stepping metho d such as forward Euler. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>2040608010000.20.40.60.81xn
n00.20.40.60.8 1010002000300040005000Histogram
xFigur e 2.4: A trajectory and the histogram for the logistic map with r = 4.
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>We will show that the logistic map displa ys broadba nd spectrum in time, nonlinearit y, 
unpredicta ble behavior, and time reversibility. However it is deriv ed assuming a single 
lengthscale and it canno t displa y any spatial structure. Thus the logistic map is poor 
mans Navier-Stokes equatio n and cannot displa y turbulen t behavior. However it is a 
useful tool to study how a deter minis tic system can produce chaos and unpredicta ble 
behavior. 
2.1.1 Linear solutions of the logistic map 
We start by studying linear solutions of the logistic map. The variable an represen ts 
the amplitude of the velocity at time n. For convenience we will now switch from 
an to xn to indica te the mode amplitude. The logistic map is a one dimens ional map 
of the form xn+1 = F (xn), 
xn+1 = rxn(1  xn). (2.11) 
The iteration of one dime nsional maps is easy to see graphically : if we plot y = F (x) 
and y = x, the iterations are given by succes sive steps between these two curves, 
y = F (xn), xn=1 = y. (2.12) 
Succe ssive iterat ions from a given initia l values are given by succe ssive operations of 
the map F , an operation known as functional comp ositio n, 
x1 = F (x0), (2.13) 
x2 = F (x1)= F (F (x0)), (2.14) 
. . . (2.15) 
xn = F (xn1)= F (F ...F (x0)). (2.16) 
We use the matlab functio n cobweb.m to study the properties of the map. The 
intersection xf of y = F (x) with y = x is a xed point of the iteration, if, 
F (xf )= xf . (2.17) 
We can easily answ er the question of whether an initial condit ion close to xf ap
proaches the xed point under iterat ion (when we call the xed point stable) or 
moves away from it (unsta ble xed point) by linear izing the evolution about xf : 
write x = xf + x and then using a Taylor expansion with F (x) the deriv ative of the 
function, 
xn+1 = xf + xn+1 = F (xf + xn)  F (xf )+ xnF (xf ) (2.18) 
so that 
xn+1 = F (xf )xn (2.19) 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Period doubl ing route (Feigenbaum , 1978) 
The system loses stabilit y throug h period-doubling, pitchfork bifurcations. The sys
tem undergo es a cascade of such period-doubling s until at the accum ulation point 
one observ es aperiodic behaviour, but no broad-band spectrum. Note also, that if 
one has seen three bifur cations, a fourth bifurca tion becomes more probable than a 
third after only two, etc. This route to chaotic behavior has been observ ed in heat 
transport by convection. 
Intermittency route (Pomeau &amp; Manevil le, 1980) 
The system loses stabilit y through intermit tency , i.e. chaos appears intermitten tly 
within an otherwise regular trajector y. There are no clear cut precursors for this route 
although it is characterized by long periods of periodic motion with bursts of chaos. 
The logistic map shows transitio n to chaos through intermittency for r =3.8282 just 
below the period three window. Intermitt ent behavior generally happ ens close to a 
saddle-no de bifurca tion. 
Quasi -periodic route (Ruelle &amp; Takens, 1971) 
In this route to chaos, there are a number of periodic orbits with irrationally related 
frequencies that lead to chaos. The system loses stabilty throug h Hopf bifurcatio ns. 
Assume that a system with a steady state solution loses its stabilit y, as some control 
parameter is varied, through a Hopf bifurca tion (ie. a pair of comple x eigenvalues 
crosses the imaginar y axis). The steady state becomes oscillat ory. Assume that 
this happ ens three times in succe ssion and that the three newly creat ed modes are 
essentially indep enden t -then chaos may occur. The precursor is the existence of 
quasi-periodic motio ns. 
The power spectrum will exhibit one, then two, and possibly three indep enden t ba
sic frequencies. When the third frequency is about to appear simultaneo usly some 
broad-band noise will appear  this is then regarded as chaotic. Evidence is from 
Taylor-Couette vortices in uid ow between rotating cylinders and in Rayleigh-Bnard 
convection. 
2.4 A statistical descr iption of chaos 
The previous examples suggest that trajectories of maps and dyna mical systems are 
predictab le when orbits are xed points or periodic oscillations. After the onset of 
chaos, instead, there seem to be little hope to predict the details of the trajecto
ries. This situatio n is similar to what happ ens in the study of uid ows. When the 
Reyno lds number is small, solutions are linear and predictable. At large Reyno lds 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>(Landau and Lifshitz, 1971). According to this model, as the Reynolds number is 
increased, the system underg oes a innit e series of Hopf bifurcations. Each bifurcation 
causes the velocity eld to oscillate with a new frequenc y fi, until for sucien tly large 
i the motion appears chaotic. In this picture the unpredicta bility of turbulence arises 
because each new frequency fi is associated with a new phase i and, for large i, it 
becomes progressiv ely dicult to keep track of all oscillat ions. 
The Landa u transitio n scenario is, however, untenable because a few incommensu
rate frequencies do not generate positive Lyapuno v exponents. And the sensitiv e 
dependence on initial condi tions is a trademar k of turbulen t ows. This character
istic feature is now known as the buttery eect. Thus the transition to turbulence 
is proba bly best understood in terms of the routes to chaos observ ed in maps and 
simple dyna mical systems . 
Shortco mings of the dynami cal system approach 
Should we then conclude that the onset of turbulence is analogous to the onset of 
chaos? Unfor tunately the story is more complicated. Dynamical systems arise from 
the projections of the full Navier-Sto kes dynamics on a very limited number of spatial 
scales. The onset of chaos in those system is then forced to remain conned to few 
spatia l scales. Experimen ts suggest that the onset of turbulence in real ows is 
associated with broadband spectra both in time and in space. It is very dicult to 
set up experimen ts where there is transitio n to chaos with the appearance broadband 
spectrum in time, witho ut an increa se in the number of the spatial degrees of freedom. 
Only by carefully designing experimen ts in closed environmen ts, can one observ e the 
routes to chaos describ ed above in real ows. For the momen t, we must conclude that 
the theor y of dyna mical systems and chaos provides useful insights in the world of 
turbulence, but it is not the whole story. We will return to this issue in the discussion 
of turbulen t convection. 
2.5.2 Statistical descr iption of turbulence 
The logistic map is a useful tool to illustrate some important characteristics of tur
bulen t ows. However it is patho logical in at least two ways, 
	The logistic map explor es the full available space [0, 1]. Typica lly turbulen t sys
tems are dissipative and collapse on an attractor with fracta l structure (at least 
for nite-dime nsional systems). This limitat ion can be overcome considering 
two dimensio nal maps. 
	Natural systems tend to have more than one attractor. Thus the equilibrium 
statistical properties are not fully predicta ble. 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>50100 150 20000.51xn
nFigur e 2.3: Intermitt ency route to chaos in the logistic map for r =3.8282. Part of 
the orbit looks like a stable period three cycle, as indic ated by the blue circles. But 
this is spooky since the period three orbit no longer exists! We are seeing the ghost 
of the three cycle. 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Figur e 2.2: The bifurcat ion diagr am together with the corresp onding Lyapuno v ex
ponents for the logistic map. 
10
Figure removed due to copyright restrictions.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>the equilibrium distribut ion. The uniform distribution is indee d the nal state that 
one obtains by running numerica l integratio ns of the tent map. Thus the statistical 
description predicts a result that cannot be deriv ed from simple inspectio n of the 
deterministic equatio n. 
How do we know that the equilibr ium distributio n is obtained for any set of initial 
conditio ns? In order to solve arbit rary initial value problems , we need the full set of 
eigenfunctions and eigenvalues of the Perron-F robenius operator. These eigenfunc
tions can be used to repres ent any arbitrar y initia l conditio n. The eigenfunc tions for 
the tent map belong to a family of polynom ials called the Bernoul li polynomials. The 
eigenfunctions are found by solving the problem, 
P (v)=  UP (v). (2.32) 
In the example of the tent map, we nd that the all eigenfunctio ns but the uniform 
distributio n have   1. For exam ple an eigenfunction is given by, 
2 P (v)= v 2  2v + . (2.33) 3 
This eigenfunction has an eigenvalues  =1/4. The unifor m distributi on P =1 is 
the only eigenfunction with eigen value  = 1. Thus all eigenfunctions other than 
the unifor m distributio n decay in time. And the unifo rm distributio n emerges as the 
asympt otic state. 
It is left as an exercis e to relate the probabilit y distributio n of the tent map to that 
of the poor mans Navier-Stokes map, and show that it correctly predicts what we 
found by numerical integrations of the map. 
2.5 Turbul ence and chaos 
It is nally time to go back to uid dynamics and try to relate the lessons of chaotic 
maps to the descript ion of turbulence . 
2.5.1 Transition to turbulence 
Lesso ns from the dynam ical system approac h 
Up to the discovery of chaos in simple deterministic systems, studies on the onset 
of turbulence dealt with linear and, very rarely , with weakly non-linear evolution of 
externa l disturba nces. The rst physical model of laminar-turbulen t transition is due 
to Landau and it is reported in the fourth volume of the course on Theoretical Physics 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>but miss the unstable structures. With r slightly bigger than 3.54, the popula tion 
will oscillate between 8 values, then 16, 32, etc. The lengths of the parameter inter
vals which yield the same number of oscillations decrease rapidly; the ratio between 
the lengths of two succes sive such bifurcatio n intervals approaches the Feigen baum 
consta nt, 
 = lim rn  rn1 =4.669 ... (2.20) n rn+1  rn 
All of these behaviors do not depend on the initial popula tion. This is the so-called 
period-doubling bifurcat ion. 
The bifurcatio ns that occur, and the dieren t types of orbit s, are well shown by 
the bifurcatio n map. This is constr ucted with the parameter r along the abscissa, 
and all values of x visited (after some numbers of iterat ions to eliminat e transients) 
plotted as points along the ordina te. A xed point orbit over a range of r appears 
as a single curve, which splits into two curves at the bifurca tion to the period two 
orbit etc. Chaotic dynamics, where the orbit visits an innite number of points 
(otherwis e the orbit would repeat, and therefor e be periodic) appears as bands of 
continua of points (subject to limita tions of how many points are actua lly plotted in 
the impleme ntatio n). 
The bifurcatio n diagram of the logistic map shows that simple systems can have an 
amazingly rich bifurcation structure. This complexit y in the logistic map was rst 
studied by May in the context of popula tion dyna mics. You can creat e a bifurcation 
map with the matlab function logistic bif.m. 
The onset of chaos 
At r =3.569946 ... the orbits become very irregula r and we can no longer see any 
oscillat ions. Slight variations in the initial populat ion yield dramatica lly dieren t 
results over time. These are signat ures that the orbits have become cahotic. Notice, 
however, that periodic windo ws mysteriously appear here and there as we further 
increase r. These are sometimes called islands of stability. The largest window is 
near (3.8284, 3.8415) where there is a period three orbit. For slightly higher values of 
r oscillat ions icker between 6 values, then 12 etc. There are other ranges which yield 
oscillat ion between 5 values etc.; all oscillat ion periods do occur. These behaviour s 
are again indep enden t of the initial value. 
At r = 4, the large admissible value for r, the map is fully chaotic. The iterations 
appear comple tely random, and the values eventually ll up the whole interval [0, 1]. 
This chaotic motion can be completely understo od by making a transforma tion of 
variables. Dene, 
xn = sin2(zn/2). (2.21) 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>unstable periodic orbits), and will be denoted  and called the Lyapuno v exponent 
of the map. The deriv ative can be evaluated by the chain rule in terms of deriv atives 
of F at the intermedia te iterations, 
dF n(x0) = F (xn1)F (xn2) ...F (x1)F (x0). (2.26) dx0 
Thus we can compactly write, 
 = log |F |, (2.27) 
where the average  is over the iterations of the map. A positiv e value of  corre
sponds to the dierenc e between closely spaced initial conditions growing (on average 
exponentially) with iterat ion i.e. to sensitiv e dependence on initial conditions. Thus 
a positive Lyapuno v exponent is a signat ure of chaos, and may be used as a dening 
criterio n. The Lyapuno v exponents of the logistic map are shown as a function of r in 
gure 2.2. Positiv e values of  appear forlarger values of r. The occasional negative 
dips corresp ond to the islands of stabilit y. 
r  Commen ts 
1 0  0.005112 . . . start stable xed point 
3 0.00 3518... start stable 2-cycle 
3.449489743... 0.00 3150... start stable 4-cycle 
3.56994571869 +0.001934... start of chaos (Dewdne y, 1988) 
3.828427125... 0.00 3860... start stable 3-cycle 
3.9 +0.7095... back into chaos 
4 +0.6931... end of chaos (2.28)
2.3 Routes to chaos 
The logistic map is a useful example to study the onset of chaos in a determinis tic 
system as a functio n of an external parameter like the Reynolds number r. The 
question arises as to whether the bifurca tion patterns that leads to the onset of chaos 
is typical of other systems, or whether it is an oddity of the logistic map. For the 
momen t we restrict the discussion to maps and low order dyna mical systems (i.e. 
systems describ ed by a small number of ordina ry dierential equatio ns). We will 
extend the discuss ion to turbulen t ows at the end of the lecture. 
Despite the richness and complexit y in the orbit s genera ted by maps and dynamical 
systems, it turns out that the routes to chaos are quite universal and can be broadly 
grouped in three classes : the period doubling route, the intermitt ency route, and the 
quasi-perido c route. The logistic map is an example of a map that follows the rst 
route. 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>The iteration of z for r = 4 is then just,
zn+1 =2zn, 0  zn  1/2 (2.22) 2  2zn, 1/2  zn  1 
This is known as the tent map. Success ive values of zn from a random initial value are 
as rando m as a coin toss (and in fact in binary repres entation answering the question of 
whether the n-th value is to the right or left of 0.5 just gives the binar y represe ntatio n 
of the initia l value, which is rando m for a rando m initial value). Beyond r = 4, the 
values eventually leave the interval [0, 1] and diverge for almost all initia l values. 
It is interesting to consider the temp oral spectrum of orbits of the logistic map for 
dieren t values of r. At the appearance of the period two orbit, the spectrum has a 
single peak at f =1/2. As r increases, period doubling bifurca tions generate new 
peaks at sub-harmonics f/2, f/4 and so on. Notice that the appearance of sub-
harmonics is quite dieren t from the appearance of super-harmonics (2f,4f, ...) 
as a result of quadr atic nonline arities. Finally , at the onset of chaos the number of 
excited harmonics becomes large and the spectrum appears to be broadband. 
2.2 Chaos and sensit ivity to initial condi tions 
The orbits of the logistic map become very erratic when r = 4. But what do we mean 
by the orbits being chaotic? The onset of chaos is dened by a sensitiv e dependence 
on initial conditio ns, i.e. orbits with simila r initia l condit ions diverge exponentially 
fast. The sensitiv e dependence on initia l conditio ns can be made quantitative by 
genera lizing the idea of instabilit y of a xed point. Equa tion (2.19) can in fact be 
used for the expansio n of a small separation at any xn, 
xn+1 = F (xn)xn, (2.23) 
so that the product of the deriv atives at succe ssive iterat ions gives us the expansion 
(or contraction) of the separ ation between the iterates of nearby points. 
More precisely we start with initial conditions x0 and x0 +x and ask for the distance 
between the n-th iterates, which we expect to grow as, 
|xn| =xe n(x0) , (2.24) 
where (x 0) is the so-called Lyapunov exponent for the initial condit ion x0, i.e. 
F n(x0 +x)  F n(x0) 
x
=
dF n(x0) 
dx0 .
(2.25)
1
 1
(x 0) = lim lim logn lim log
x 0 n n n
 
For systems like the logistic map for r = 4 the limit exists and is independen t of the 
initia l conditio n x0 for almost all initial condit ions (e.g. not those points exactly on 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>numbers, the ow becomes erratic and exact solutions canno t be found neither an
alytically , nor numerically . Does it mean that a theory of turbulence is beyond our 
reach? 
Let us consider the logistic map with r = 4, in the strong ly chaotic regime. The 
map displa ys broadband spectrum in time, nonline arity, unpredicta ble behavior, and 
time irreversibilit y (Fig. 2.4). However the histog ram of the positions x assumed by 
the orbit is quite predicta ble (Fig. 2.4). In the chaotic regime the histog rams show a 
predictab ility that does not emerge in indiv idual trajectori es. The histo gram always 
converge toward the same distributio n, regardless of initia l conditions. Why does 
the histogram of the logistic map converge to a limit solution? Why a determinis tic 
system such as a map has a regular statistical behavior? We do not have comple te 
answ ers to these equat ions, but progress is being made. The curren t unde rstanding 
is that maps in the chaotic regime collapse on a strang e attracto r which is a gener
alization of the xed points and periodic orbit s in the linear regime. The structur e 
of strang e attractors is very complex. That is why trajector ies are so errat ic and 
dicult to predict. However ensem ble of trajectories reec ts the mean structur e of 
the attractor and can be predic ted. 
In this sectio n we deriv e a statistica l descriptio n of the logistic map. The goal is to un
derstand the dierence between the trajector y-based descript ion and the histo gram-
based description. First we need to determine the evolution equation for the histog ram 
P (v), also known as the proba bility distribution function, so that we can observ e the 
recurrence relatio n Pn+1(v)= UPn(v). The distributio n function Pn+1(v) after n +1 
iterations is obtained by the action of the operator U on Pn(v), which is the distri
butio n function after n iteration of the map. The operator U acts on functio ns and 
it is known as the Perron-Frobenius operato r. 
We can deriv e the Perron-Frobenius operator for the logistic map. We have already 
shown that by making the chang e of variables, 
xn = sin2(zn/2), (2.29) 
the logistic map with r = 4 becomes, 
zn+1 =2zn, 0  zn  1/2 (2.30) 2  2zn, 1/2  zn  1 
which is known as the tent map, because of the shape of its graph. We can easily 
write the Perron-Frobenius operator for the tent map, 
 1 v v Pn+1(v)= Pn + Pn 1  . (2.31) 2 2 2 
As a consequence of the form of the Perron-Frobenius operator, if Pn is constant 
equal to P0, then Pn+1 is also equal to P0. The unifor m distributio n P = P0 is 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Furthermor e there are technica l issues that have not been solved for the Navier-
Stokes equat ions. We do not know if solutio ns exist for all times for arbitr ary initial 
conditio n. We do not know how to write the equivalent of the Perron-F robenius 
operator. 
Further reading :
Frisch, chapter 1-3
Strogatz, chapter 10
Tritton, chapter 24
17</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction (PDF - 1.0 MB)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Courtesy of American Meteorological Society. Used with permission. 
Figure 1.6: Evolution of a simulated tracer deployed in the Arctic vortex in April 
1993. The circles on plots for 30 April, 1, 6, and 7 May are the location where 
tracer values repres entative of vortex air where measured aboard the ER-2 aircraft. 
There is good agreemen t between the location of the laments of ex-vortex air in the 
simulation and the locations where vortex air was observed (See Waugh et al., 1997 
for details). The tracer tends to spread out from the location where it was released. 
	Materially conned versus dispersive. 
Parcels initially close to each other, tend to spread in time. Turbulence mixes 
tracers, it doesnt unmix them. 
	Conserv ative versus non-conserv ative. 
If we neglect  and , then the equations are conservative (of energy, tracer 
variance, etc.), but the outcome of turbulence is dissipa tive (the second law of 
thermo dynamics applies). If dissipati on continues to occur in a regime with only 
large-scale forcing or initial conditions  as is true for the Earths climate system 
 then there must be a continuing transfer of uid properties from larger spatial 
scales to smaller ones, and eventually small enough so that diusiv e terms can 
be comparable to the advective ones. This process is called the forward (i.e. 
toward smaller scales) turbulent cascade. 
	Quasi-periodic and spatially smooth versus broad-band. 
Turbulence develops a broad spectrum in (, k) space even when given smooth 
or periodic initial conditions or forcing. The spectra of atmospheric and oceanic 
ows can show some indication of preferred time and spatial scales, but have 
broad-band shape (examples: atmospheric near-surface wind frequency spec
trum and oceanic internal wave frequency spectrum). Spectra often have power-
law forms over wide frequency and wavenumber ranges (e.g. the famous k5/3 
form of the Kolmogorov cascade in three-dimensional turbule nce and the 5 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft /bracehtipupleft /bracehtipupright Boussinesq system is,
  
u 1 +(u )u = p + 2 u +  bzfzu  , (1.4)t /bracehtipupleft /bracehtipupright 0 /bracehtipupleft 
/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft 
/bracehtipupright /bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright /bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft 
inertia friction buoyancy Coriolis   
 b   +(u )b = 2b  , (1.5)t /bracehtipupleft /bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft /bracehtipupright /bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright 
advection diffusion 
  
 c 2   +(u )c = c  , (1.6)t /bracehtipupleft /bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft /bracehtipupright /bracehtipupleft/bracehtipdownright/bracehtipdownleft/bracehtipupright 
advection diffusion 
u =0, (1.7) 
where p is the pressure, f is the Coriolis frequency associated with planetary rotation, 
and the vertical versor zis assumed to be parallel to both gravity and the axis of 
rotation. The buoyancy b is dened in terms of densit y as  = 0(1 g1b). Notice 
that b has the dimensio n of an accelera tion. These equations must be complemen ted 
by forcing, boundary and initial conditions to obtain a well posed problem. We can 
also consider the evolution of a passive tracer c: it satises the same equation as b, 
but it has no inuence on the evolution of u. [The Boussinesq equations follow from 
the full Navier-Stokes equations if one neglects all densit y uctuations except those 
due to heat, salt, and humidit y]. 
These equations have conservative integral invariants for energy, and all powers and 
other functionals of buoyancy, in the absence of friction and diusion. For non-
conservative dynamics, the energy and scalar variance satisfy the equations, 
E B = /epsilon1, = /epsilon1B , (1.8)t t 
where, 
/integraldisplay/integraldisplay /integraldisplay /bracketleftbigg /bracketrightbigg1 [E, B, /epsilon1, /epsilon1B]= dx 
u u bz, b2, u : u + z2b,  b b, (1.9)2 
In deriving (1.8), it is assumed that there are no boundary uxes of energy or scalar 
variance. These integrals measures of the ow can only decrease with time through 
the action of molecular viscosit y and diusiv ity. The only exception is the compressiv e 
work, z2b, which can act as a source of mechanical energy. We will return to this 
issue inthe chapteronconvection. 
Every problem we will consider lies within the set of solutions of the PDE system in 
(1.4) through (1.7). No general solution is known, nor is any in prospect, because 
we do not know a mathematical metho dology that seems powerful enough. However 
computers are giving us access to progressively better particula r solutions, i.e. with 
progressiv ely larger Re. 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>The brackets in (1.4) through (1.5) contain the eects of buoyancy and rotation, and 
these terms are ignored in the classical literature on turbulence, which deals with 
uniform densit y uids in inertial referenc e frames. In these simpler circumsta nces, 
the Boussinesq system is called the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations, or with 
the further elimination of the frictional term, the incompressible Euler equations. 
Because of the lack of general solutions to the Boussinesq equations, it is useful to 
identify which terms might be neglected in specic situations in order to simplify the 
proble m and make analytical progre ss. The relative size of the various terms that 
appear in (1.4) through (1.7) can be estimated in terms of nondimensional numbers. 
The ones that will be most useful in this class are as follows. 
	Inertia and friction
The Reynolds number is dened as
UL Re 	 (1.10) 
Here U and L are characteristic velocity and length scales of the ow and  is 
the kinematic viscosit y of the uid. The Reynolds number measures the ratio 
of inertia and friction, 
|(u )u| U/L U 
|2u|U/L2 = Re.	 (1.11) 
Equiv alently, the Reynolds number is the ratio of the characteristic scale of the 
ow L and the scale at which momen tum is dissipated l = /U. In turbulen t 
ows Re /greatermuch1, advective dominance nonlinear dynamics chaotic evolution 
and broadband spectrum. 
The focus of this course is on turbulence in the Earths ocean and atmosphere. 
Typical values for  near the Earths surface are 1.5 105 m2 s1 for air 
and 1.0 106 m2 s1 for water. These values are small enough, given typical 
velocities U,that Re /greatermuch1 on all spatial scales L from the nescale of about 
1 m to the planetary scale of about 104 km. For example, U =1ms1 and 
L =103 mgive Re =109 1010 respectively for the atmosphere and the ocean. 
For Re /greatermuch1, the frictional term is small, at least at the scale L. Paradoxically, 
however, the dissipation terms in (1.8) control the energetics of the system. 
Thus, there must be a profound dierence in solutions between the asymptotic 
tendency as Re , and the Euler limit, Re = or  = 0. The dierence 
is that as long as Re , there are small scales at which friction becomes 
important and Re is small. 
It is instructiv e to check how Re controls the behavior of solutions in a real ow. 
Let us consider a uid of uniform density in an inertial reference system, i.e. let 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Figure removed due to copyright restrictions.
Citation: Van Dyke, Milton. An album of fluid motion . Stanford,
 
CA: Parabolic Press, 1982, p. 176. ISBN: 978 0915760039.
Figure 1.8: Flow past a cylinder at R =0.16 and R =1.54 (Van Dyke 1982). 
l /l. The Prandtl number is a property of the uid, not of the particular ow. 
Hence there is a restriction on the transfer of information from experiments 
with one uid to those with another. For Pr &gt; 1 the scales at which friction 
becomes important are larger than those for diusion and, at some small scale, 
we expect to nd smooth velocity elds together with convoluted tracer elds. 
For Pr &lt; 1 we expect the opposite. The Prandtl numbers for air and water are 
0.7and 12.2 respectively. The paper by Paparella and Young (Journal of Fluid 
Mechanics, 2002) shows examples of ows with low and high Pr. 
 Inertia and Coriolis U Ro  (1.14)fL 
The Rossby number Ro measures the relative importance of the real inertial 
forces and the ctitious Coriolis force, that appear because of the rotating ref
erence system. Thus Ro measures the importanc e of rotation in the proble m at 
hand. Ro /greatermuch 1 characterizes essentially non-rotating turbulence, while Ro  1 
ows are strongly aected by rotation (Fig. 1.12). 
 Buoyancy and diusion 
bL3 
Ra  (1.15) 
In convective problems , motions are generated by imposing an unstable den
sity stratication on the uid (b/z &lt; 0). In these problems, it is useful to 
characterize turbulence in terms of the Rayleigh number, i.e. the ratio of 
the diusiv e timescale t = L2/ and the buoyancy timescale tb =(L/b)1/2 . 
The buoyancy scale b is the buoyancy dierence maintained across the layer 
depth L through external forcing. If the forcing is imposed by maintaining a 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Figure removed due to copyright restrictions. 
Figure 1.4: These internal wave photographs were taken by astronauts on board the 
space shuttle on Jan. 14, 1986. The picture shows the sea surface of the Eastern 
Pacic, around the Galapagos Islands, 600 miles o the coast of Ecuador. The sea 
surface coverage of a photograph is about of 75 km by 75 km. There is a clear 
dierence between the wavy patterns of internal waves and the turbulen t patterns of 
clouds. 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Figure 1.7: Uniform ow with velocity U, inciden t on a cylinder of diameter L. 
us neglect rotation and variations in buoyancy in (1.4) and (1.5) (b = f =0). A 
classical example is a uniform ow incident on a cylinder (gure 1.7). Figures 
1.8 through 1.10 show how the ow past the cylinder changes for dieren t 
Reynolds numbers. And the movie by Wim de Leeuw at Re = 22000 gives you 
the feeling of how complex is the ow that develops behind the obstacle (run 
dns-midi.mpg). 
 Advection and diusion UL Pe  (1.12) 
The Peclet number is the direct analog of Re for a conserved tracer c with a 
diusivit y  and measures the relativ e importance of advection and diusion. 
At large Pe, the tracer evolution is dominated by advection. Once more, the 
limit Pe  is very dieren t from Pe = , because dissipation, no matter 
how small, eventually is responsible for removing structure from the tracer eld 
(Fig. 1.11). 
 Friction and diusion  Pr  (1.13) 
The frictional length scale is l = /U and the diusiv e length scale l = /U. 
The Prandtl number is dened as the ratio of these two length scales, Pr  
14 Uniform flow with velocity U,  incident on a cylinder of diameter L
U L +
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Figure removed due to copyright restrictions.
Citation: Van Dyke, Milton. An album of fluid motion. Stanford,
CA: Parabolic Press, 1982, p. 176. ISBN: 9780915760039.
Figure 1.9: Flow past a cylinder at R =9.6, R =1 3.1, and R = 26 (Van Dyke 1982) 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>Figure removed due to copyright restrictions. 
Figure 1.14: Kelvin Helmholt z instabilit y in the atmosphere. Picture taken near 
Washington, D.C.. Darker areas are clouds. 
Since there are no time derivatives in (1.17), pressure is a purely diagnostic eld, 
which is wholly slaved to u. It can be calculated from (1.17) and then substituted 
for the pressure gradie nt force in the momentum equations . Its role is to maintain 
incompressibilit y under the action of all other forces. It would be redundan t to in
troduce nondimensional parameters involving pressure, because any such parameters 
can be expressed as combinations of the parameters already discussed. 
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Figure removed due to copyright restrictions.
Citation: Van Dyke, Milton. An album of fluid motion. Stanford, CA:
Parabolic Press, 1982, p. 176. ISBN: 978 0915760039.
Figure 1.2: High Re jet exiting from a nozzle. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>y [km] y [km] 50 
540 
30 
0 
20 
10 5 
0 
0 10 20 30 40 50
x [km]
50 
540 
30 
0 
20 
10 5 
0 
0 10 20 30 40 50
x [km]
Buoyancy [km h2] Spice [km h2] 
Figure 1.11: Contours of two tracers advected by a two dimensional ow eld. The 
two tracers have Pe = 100 (upper panel) and Pe =10 (lower panel). 
18</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>frequency spectrum for surface waves in the open ocean). 
	Predictable versus unpredictable. A turbulen t ow is predictable for only a 
limited period of time, usually of the order of several eddy turnover times, 
L/U. On the other hand statistical properties of the ow can be quite stable, 
hence in principle predictable. This situation is reminiscen t of thermo dynamics: 
if we put two bodies of dieren t temperatures in contact we can predict their 
nal temperature, but not the trajectory of every single molecule. 
	Smooth versus sensitiv e dependence. 
The evolution of the partial dieren tial equations of uid dynamics is ill-posed 
in the classical sense, in that small changes in any aspect of the problem for
mulation (initial conditions, boundary conditions, model parameters, etc.)lead 
to large macroscopic changes in the solution after a nite time, the so-called 
predictabilit y time. 
	Statistically regular versus statistically irregular. 
Some statistical measures of turbulence have nearly Gaussian probabilit y distri
butions, but the overall structure of turbulen t elds is highly non-Gaussian with 
rare and intense events relativ ely more probable (i.e. turbulence has bursts). 
	Globally ordered versus locally ordered. 
Global ordering is rare for large Re, unless it is established through ordered 
forcing or domain geometry . But local ordering, particularly of the vorticity 
eld, is nearly universal. This local ordering is the coher ent structures. 
	Persistent versus transient, evanescent, chaotically recurren t patterns . 
The evident ordering in the ow patterns is usually transient. Coheren t struc
tures appear and disapp ear in an unpredictable sequence. 
In real turbulen t ows neither pair of the antonyms is entirely false. However much 
of our understanding of turbulence lies in comprehending how ows transitions from 
one member of the antonym to the other. 
1.2 Governing equations 
We will take a simplied form of the governing equations for use in this course, 
viz., the Boussinesq equations. The ocean and the atmosphere have a more complex 
thermo dynamics than these equations do, but this is largely extraneous to the fun
damen tal behaviors of turbulence and thus will be ignored. The three dimensional 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 1 
Introduction 
Richard Feynman (1964) in his Lecture on Physics observed that, 
Often, people, in some unjustied fear of physics, say you cant write an 
equation for life. Well, perhaps we can. As a matter of fact, we very 
possibly already have the equation to a sucien t approximation, when we 
write the equation for quantum mechanics: 
 H =  . (1.1)i t 
However, we are unable to reconstruct the eld of biology from this equa
tion, and we depend on detailed observation of biologic al phenomena. 
Uriel Frisch (1995) in his book Turbulence points out that an analogous situation 
prevails in the study of turbulen t ows. The equation, generally referred to as the 
Navier-Stokes equation, has been know since Navier (1827) and Stokes (1845), 
Du 1 = p + 2 u, (1.2)Dt 0 
u =0, (1.3) 
The Navier-Stokes equations probably contain all of turbulence. Yet it would be 
foolish to try to guess from these equations all the variety of regimes of turbulen t 
ows without looking at experimental facts. The phenomena are almost as varied as 
in the realm of life. The ows shown in Fig. 1 are example of solutions of the Navier-
Stokes equations , with modications to account for rotation and density variations . 
But nobody knows how to derive these solutions from the equations themselv es. 
A good way to make contact with the world of turbulence phenomena is through 
observations of natural ows. Examples are ubiquitous in the ocean, atmosphere, h 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>that describ e the slow time and large scale evolution of nearly monochromatic 
waves. Turbulence is dieren t, because it is always complex both in space and 
time. 
	Time irreversible 
Turbulen t motions are not time reversible. As time goes on, turbulen t motions 
tend to forget their initial conditions and reach some equilibrated state. Turbu
lence mixes stu up, it does not unmix it (Fig. 1.6). A challenge of this course 
will be to explain how irreversibilit y can arise in uids that are governed by 
classical mechanics, i.e. Newtons dynamics, which is time reversible. 
The classication of properties that a ow must displa y to be considered turbulen t 
is a subject of continuous debate in the scientic comm unity. Many authors make 
narrower denitions of turbulence, limiting the scope to 
	ows exhibiting explosiv e three dimensional vortex stretching 
	ows obeying Kolmogorovs cascade law (to be described later) 
	ows with a nite cascade of energy toward smaller scales. 
These denitions are arbitrarily exclusive, since there are many geophysical ows 
which share the fundamen tal properties of broadband spectrum, advective nonlinear
ity, unpredictabilit y, and time irreversibilit y, yet, due to the eects of rotation and 
stratic ation, are not fully three dimensional, do not satisfy Kolmogorovs law, and 
have no energy transfer toward smaller scales. 
The properties of turbulen t ows are better described in terms of dualities between 
regular and turbulen t ows. Here we follow a list proposed by Jim McWilliams, a 
very inuen tial oceanographer from UCLA. 
	Determinis tic vs random. 
The equation of motions are deterministic, but their solutions have many at
tributes of random processes. 
	Orderly versus chaotic. 
Many of the spatial and temporal patterns are orderly , but the overall behavior 
is clearly chaotic. 
	Time reversible versus time irreversible. 
If we neglect  and  (because Re is large), then the equations are time re
versible, i.e. any solutions for (t, u,p,b) is also a solution for (t, u,p,b), but 
the outcome is evidently irreversible, even after a short period of time of the 
order of the eddy turnover time, L/U. The breaking of symmetries is a salient 
feature of turbulen t motions. 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Figure removed due to copyright restrictions.
Citation: Van Dyke, Milton. An album of fluid motion. Stanford,
 
CA: Parabolic Press, 1982, p. 176. ISBN: 978 0915760039.
Figure 1.3: Uniform ow incident on a cylinder at low Re. Uniform ow inciden t on 
two cylinders at high Re. 
If L is the length scale of the largest motions and l is the length scale of the 
smallest motions in a ow, then a large range of spatial scales implies L /greatermuch l.The 
scale l is typically the scale at which dissipa tion becomes important and removes 
energy from the ow. The scale L, instead, is set by the forcing mechanisms 
that set the large-s cale ow. The ratio L/l is the Reynolds number Re,and 
L /greatermuch l implies that the Reynolds number be large. Turbulen t ows have large 
Reynolds numbers (Fig. 1.2 and 1.3). 
 Dominat ed by advective nonlinearit y 
A eld of non-interacting linear internal waves with many dieren t frequencies 
and wavenumbers can also have a large range of length scales, but it is not 
turbulen t. Why not? In a turbulen t ow the dieren t scales interact, through 
the nonline ar terms in the equations of motion. And these nonline ar interactions 
are responsible for the presence of structure on many dieren t scales. Thus the 
broad band spectrum appears as a result of the internal dynamics. In a eld of 
linear internal waves, instead, the broad band spectrum is generated by externa l 
controls like forcing, initial or boundary conditions (Fig. 1.4). 
 Unpredict able in space and time 
Turbulen t ows are predictable for only short times and short distances. Even 
though we know the equations that govern the evolution of the uid, we cannot 
make predictions about the details of the ow due to its sensitiv e dependence 
on initial and boundary conditions. This sensitiv e dependence is once more 
a result of the strong nonlinearit y of the ow. Predictabilit y, however, can be 
recovered in a statistical sense, as we will see in lecture 2 (Fig. 1.5). The sensitiv e 
dependence on initial and boundary conditions is a fundamen tal property of 
chaot ic systems. Are thus turbulence and chaos synonyms? No. Turbulen t 
motions are indeed chaotic, but chaotic motions need not be turbule nt. Chaos 
may involve only a small number of degrees of freedom, i.e. it can be narrow 
band in space and/or time. There are numerous examples of chaotic systems 
characterized by temporal complexity, but spatial simplicit y, like the Lorenzs 
system. Another class of chaotic ows is represen ted by amplitude equations 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Figure removed due to copyright restrictions.
Citation: Uriel, Frisch . Turbulence.  New York , NY: Cambridge University Press, 1995.
ISBN: 978 0521451031 (hardback), 9780521457132 (pbk).
Figure 1.5: Two sections of one second of a signal recorded by a hot-wire (sampled 
at 5 kHz) in a wind tunnel. The two sections dier in some small details of the ow 
upstream, i.e. initial conditions . The statistical properties of the two signals are 
simila r, but the details of the ow are completely dieren t. 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>/bracketleftBig /bracketrightBig Figure removed due to copyright restrictions.
Citation: Van Dyke, Milton. An album of fluid motion . Stanford,
 
CA: Parabolic Press, 1982, p. 176. ISBN: 978 0915760039.
Figure 1.10: Wake behind two cylinders at R = 1800, and homogeneous turbule nce 
behind a grid at R = 1500 (Van Dyke 1982). 
temperature dierence T , then one has b = gT ,where  is the coecien t 
of thermal expansion of the uid, and g the accelera tion of gravity. Convec
tion starts if t /greatermuch tb, i.e. if RaP r /greatermuch 1, when diusion is too slow to change 
substantially the buoyancy of water/air parcels as they rise (Fig. 1.13). 
 Buoyancy and inertia 
b/z Ri  (1.16)|u/z|2 
In the presence of stable buoyancy stratication, vertical motions tend to be 
suppressed, but turbulence can still emerge, if there is enough energy in the 
horizon tal velocity eld. A useful parameter to characterize the ow in these 
problems is the ratio of the buoyancy timescale tb =(L/b)1/2 =1/(b/z)1/2 
and the inertial timescale due to horizon tal shears in the ow ti = L/U = 
1/(u/z). This ratio is called the gradie nt Richardson number Ri.If Ri /lessmuch 
1, buoyancy can be neglected in the momentum equations, and it becomes a 
passiv e scalar with no feedbac ks on the dynamics (Fig. 1.14). 
A nal remark about the only term that never appeared explicitly in the nondimen
sional numbers presen ted: the pressure force. Pressure can be formally elimina ted 
from the equations. This is a consequenc e of the Boussinesq approximation. We 
simply need to take the divergence of the momen tum equation in (1.4) and note that 
ut = 0 because of incompressibilit y. This yields the relation, 
2 p = 0 (u )u + 2 u + bzfzu . (1.17) 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Figure 1.1: Examples of turbulen t ows at the surface of the Sun, in the Earths 
atmosphere, in the Gulf Stream at the ocean surface, and in a volcanic eruption. 
lakes, and rivers of our Earth, in the atmos pheres of other planes , in stars, galaxies, 
and space gases (neutra l and ionized). A few examples are shown in Fig. 1. These 
ows are very irregular and do not display the regularit y of the solutions of the Navier-
Stokes equations that you studied in introductory courses in uid dynamics. The eld 
of turbulence can be dened as the attemp t to bring together our understanding of 
the laws that govern uid dynamics (the Navier-Stok es equations ) with the irregular 
nature of real ows. 
But how can we tell which natural ows are turbulen t and which are not? As for the 
problem of dening life, there is no simple answer. A useful approac h is to list what 
properties must be presen t to consider a ow turbulen t. 
1.1 Properties of turbulen t ows 
 Broadband spectrum in space and time 
Turbulen t ows are characterized by structures on a broad range of spatial and 
temporal scales, even given smooth or periodic initial conditions and forcing. 
That is turbulen t ows have a broadband spectrum both in frequency and 
wavenumber domains. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>Figure removed due to copyright restrictions. 
Citation: http://www.the-planet-jupiter.com. 
Figure 1.12: Rotational eects produce the well-known jets in the atmosphere of 
Jupiter. The Ro can be estimated to be of order 0.1using U = 300 m/s, f =2.5104 
s1,and L =10, 000km). 
Figure removed due to copyright restrictions.
Citation: Vincent, Alain , and David A. Yuen, "Statistical Physics, Plasmas, Fluids, and
Related Interdisciplinary Topics."  Physical review E,  2000.
Figure 1.13: Convection in air at a Ra =1012 and Ra =1014 (Alain Vincen t and 
David A. Yuen, Phys. Review E, 2000). 
19</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Particle Motions, Stokes&#8217; Drift (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch16/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Note that we can split Dij as usual: 
%" with the first term giving the up-diffusive-gradient transport associated with the symmetric 
part of j' Rij and the second, llondivergent part: arising from the antisymmetric term; gives 
the Stokes drift. For the primary wave, 
K.. -	-c2 (~i~7rt r2 lrv 
2lr sin lrt sin2 lr?rl/ 
and has no time average, while 
produces the nondivergeilt Stokes drift (and does have a mean). Demos, Page 7: 
drift &lt;amp=O. 2&gt; &lt;amp=O. 2 comoving&gt; &lt;amp=l. O&gt; &lt;amp=l. 0 comoving&gt; 
&lt;stokes drift&gt; &lt;mean&gt; 
FINITE AMPLITUDE 
In the frame of reference of the wave (Xi = X -ct) 
Thus particles simply move along the streamlines. At some Lagrailgian period TL,the 
particle will have moved one period to the left so that 
Stokes drifts occur when the Lagrallgian period differs from the Eulerian period. Trapped 
particles have</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Stokes' drift 
Consider first the steady wave case. 
$=-t.sin(~[x-t]) sin(~y) 
7r 
We look at the particle trajectories by solving the Lagrangian equations as above 
For small t (which is the ratio of the flow speed to the phase speed, we can find an 
approximate solution (as before) by iterating 
The mean Lagrangian drift is therefore -
Rij (x,T)d~ 
Treating the mean as a phase average gives 
cos TT cos2 TY sin 7rrsin TYcos TY 
2 Rij (T) =22 (-sin TT sin TY cos 7rv cos TT sin TY 
the integral gives 
t sin ~y cos 7rv sin ~t cos2 TY (1-cos ~t) Qj(t) =1R-(T)~T=--(1 -cos xt) sin xy cos x?ry sin TT sin2 xy 0 
so that the drift is -a 2 u, =-El =-cos(27q)[l-cos(TIt)]at 2 -3 t2 
UL =-[2 =-sin(2xv) sin7rt 3t 2 
Note that there is a time-averaged drift 
prograde on the walls and retrograde in the center. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>assume the mean flows are small E iiNU' and the coefficients in the reaction terms vary 
rapidly in the vertical but slowly horizontally and in time. 
Vertical Strnctlire 
1) We assume the case with no flow has a stable solution: 
Demos, Page 10: bio dynamics &lt;growth rates&gt; 
2) The eddy-induced perturbations satisfy 
with W = (3/3X, 3/3Y, 3/82). 
3) The equation for the mean is 
Summary: 
Eddies generate fluctuations by horizoiltal and vertical advection of large-scale gra- 
dients; but the strength and structure depends on the biologically-induced perturbation 
decay rates. 
Perturbatioils generate eddy fluxes and alter the average values of the nonlinear bio- 
logical terms.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Not so simple example 
"Mixing length;' models 
Flux(b)= -K,V~ 
even if appropriate for passive tracers are not suitable for biological properties whose time 
scales may be comparable to those in the physics. Instead, we find 
where R,, is the equivalent of Taylor's Lagrangian covariance (but including K). 
We divide the coefficient into symmetric (K)and antisymmetric terms related to the 
Stokes drift (V) 
Note that 
Eddy diffusivities and wave drifts mix different components (flux of P depends on 
gradient of 2). 
If R has a negative lobe, the biological diffusivities can be larger than that of a passive 
scalar 
The quasi-equilibrium approximation 
works reasonably well in the upper water column. In particular 
so that 
I 1 P I= -ul . V7 unlike C = -5. 
Demos, Page 14: complex diffusion &lt;transport coeff: display -geometry 
+0+0 -bordercolor white -border 20x20 -rotate 90 -glenn/l2.822t/graphics/tO.p~&gt; 
up Z grad flux of Ptl.ps &lt;quasiequilibrium fluxes: display -geometry +0+0 -
bordercolor white -border 20x20 -rotate 90 "glenn/l2.822t/graphics/tla.ps&gt; down-
gradient Kpp,KZZt2.ps</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Taylor dispersion 
In 1922, Taylor described the dispersion under the assumption that the Lagrangian 
velocity had a known covariance structure. He considered just 
We find that 3-X,Xj = KXj + x,y3t 
and, in the ensemble average, 
If we substitute t 
X = Xo + 6V(tl)dt' 
and look at the case where (V)= 0 and the flow is statioilary, we have 
where R&amp; is the covariance of the Lagrangian velocities 
For isotropic motions RL.(t)= U2RL(t)bij with RL(t)being the autocorrelation function; 
the change in x-variance %J.is given by 
From this formulal we see that 
For short times, (x2)= U2t2 
For long times, if the integral Tint= JrRL(t)dtis finite and non-zero,</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Particle Dispersion 
Random Flight -Lagrangian dispersion 
As an exanlple, we examine the randoin flight model. which assumes that the accel-
erations have a stochastic component and use Newton's equations 
dX = Vdt 
dV = Adt +PdR 
where A is the acceleration produced by deterministic (or large-scale) forces. We include 
randoin accelerations with the random increment dR satisfying (dRi dRj) = Gijdt. 
As examples, consider a drag law for the acceleration 
with u being the water velocity. The dispersion is determined by P and T; from the 
equations: we can show that 
The latter corresponds to a diffusivity of r; = p2/2r2. 
Area grows like 4~t(6r;t in 3-D) 
Velocity variance is TK 
Demos, Page 1: Random flight &lt;dispersion&gt; &lt;mean sq displacement&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Relation to diffiisivity 
Consider the diffusion of a passive scalar 
and define moments of the distribution 
Integrating the diffusion equation gives conservation of the total scalar, under the assump- 
tion that the initial distribution is compact and the values decay rapidly at infinity 
The first inoment gives 
In the absence of flow and with a constant r;, &amp;(x) = 0. Otherwise, the center of mass 
migrates according to a weighted version of u+VK: it inoves with the flow and upgradient 
in diffusivity. 
The second inonlent a a-(x2) = =(xu)+ 2(-(xr;))at 3x 
implies that 
3 ar; -at [(x2)-(x)~]= 2 [(xu) -(x)(u)+ (xz) -(x)(%) + 2(s)"I 
For uniform flow and constant diffusivity, the blob spreads in x at a rate 2~.Thus we can 
identify the effective diffusivity 
K = U2~int 
Strain in the flow and curvature in K will alter the rate of spread.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Chaotic advection 
We start with the basic wave 
$=-t.sin(~[x-t]) sin(~y) 
IT 
and add a small amount of a second wave 
Demos, Page 8: psi &lt;alpha=O&gt; &lt;alpha=O. 01&gt; &lt;alpha=O. I&gt; 
When we have a non-zero, the trajectories become less regular in the vicinity of the 
stagnation points. A line of particles approachiilg the point begins to fold, with some fluid 
crossing into the interior and some being ejected. Which way a parcel goes depends on the 
phase of the perturbing wave as it nears the stagnation point. 
Demos, Page 9: lobe dynamics &lt;alpha 0.008&gt; 
We can look at Poincark sections (snapshots at the period of the perturbing wave) 
at various amplitudes to see the mixing regions Demos, Page 9: poincare sections 
&lt;alpha=O&gt; &lt;alpha=O. 002&gt; &lt;alpha=O. 004&gt; &lt;alpha=O. 008&gt; &lt;alpha=O. 016&gt; 
&lt;alpha=O. 032&gt; &lt;alpha=O. 064&gt; &lt;alpha=O. 128&gt; 
The inixing across the channel is still blocked for a small enough &lt; 0.05 so the inixing 
is still diffusion-limited: although some gain is realized by enhanced flux out of the wall 
and a decrease in the width of the blocked region. 
Demos, Page 9 : Continuum &lt;steady&gt; &lt;weak&gt; &lt;strong&gt; 
References 
Flierl, G.R.. (1981) Particle motions in large amplitude wave fields. Geoph,ys. Astrophys. 
Fluid D,yn., 18,39-74. 
Pierrehuinbert. R..T. (1991) Chaotic mixing of tracer and vorticity by modulated travelling 
R.ossby waves. Geoj,h,ys. Astrophys. Fluid D,yn., 58, 285-319. 
Active Tracers 
We review mixing length theory applied to a set of active scalars (think in terms of 
biological properties): 
Split the field into an eddy part which varies rapidly in space and time and a mean part 
which changes over larger (order l/t) horizontal distances and longer (order l/t2)times: 
We must allow for short vertical scales in both means and fluctuations. Counterbalancing 
this difficulty is the fact that vertical velocities tend to be weak (order x F).We</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Simple Example 
If we ignore vertical diffusion and advectioil and consider only one component with 
all= -A, we have 
4m:i= e-X7Vm&amp; 
so that 
Ia, = -[Jdxf J itlc*(t-t~c(~, tl).h(xI, Itlx~, 
The eddy flux takes the form 
If we split the right-hand side into symmetric and ailtisymmetric parts, we find 
The last term has no divergence and can be dropped. Thus the eddy flux is a mix of 
diffusion and Stokes' drift: a= -K:,V&amp; + vA~, 
Both coefficients depend on the biological time scale Apl. 
For the random R.ossby wave case: the Stokes drift term is 
while the diffusivity tensor is 
Demos, Page 13: effective coeff &lt;effective k,v&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Eulerian-Lagrangian 
If K = 0: we can relate the relevant form of the Eulerian covariance 
to Taylor's form. The Greens' function equation 
has a solution 
G(x, tx', t') = 6 (x -X(txl, t')) 
where 
3-X(tx',tl)=u(X,t) , X(tlx',t')=x I at 
gives the Lagrangian position of the particle initially at x' at time t'. But it is more 
convenient to back up along the trajectory and let 
where the particle at c at time t' passes x at time t (and takes a time T for this tranistion). 
Thus the c's give the starting position: which, for stochastic flows varies from realization 
to realization. We can solve 
for T = 0 to T = t -t' to find c. 
We can now define the generalization of the Lagrangian correlation function used by 
Taylor 
R,,(t -t', x) = dx'ul(x, t)G(x, t x', t1)u'(x', t') 
= &amp;(x; t)u:,([(t -t'x, t); t -(t -t')) 
For homogeneous, stationary turbulence (on the scales intermediate between the eddies 
and the mean), this will be equivalent to Taylor's 
R,,(T) = uk(X(tl +TX', t'), t' +T)u&amp;(x', t') 
but we include inhomogeileity and (forl general G, diffusion).</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Note that the antisymmetric part of the contribution to the Lagrangian velocity is nondi- 
vergent: 
Thus the Lagrangian mean velocity has contributions from the mean Eulerian flowl from 
the Stokes' drift, and a term which tends to move into regions of higher diffusivity 
We will discuss the meanings of these terms in more detail next. 
Random Rossby Waves 
Consider a randomly-forced R.ossby wave in a channel: 
where is randomly distributed on a disk of radius ro. This gives a streamfuilction 
with 
and w = -flk/(k2 +e2). 
dTe-(~-$"~T(t -T)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>NPZ 
A simple biological model (mixed layer): 
Mean-field approach 
We call get a very similar picture using the mean-field approximation: take 
-u' . Vb, + +b',X,t) -&amp;((b +bb',X,t) 
or (dropping the quadratic and higher terms) 
The differences are subtle: the MFA does not presume that the scale of Zi is large but 
linearizes in a way which may not be consisteilt.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Back to random wave 
with 
dTe-(~-+"~r(t -T) 
we find 
~(x,Y, t)*(x1, Y', tlj = 
2-Uo -y(t-tl)cos[k(x-x') -w(t -t')] sin(@) sin(!yl) 2e2 
cos 1 wT COS~2 -7, ey $ sin ,wr sill&amp; cos!v R,, (7)= -UOe2 -$ sill wr siillg cos e~ k2cos WT sin2!v 
This gives 
y cos2 w$ sin!V cos!yDm, = -
-w $ sin Vg cos Vg y k2sin28~ 
The diffusivities and Stokes' drift are given by 
1 k w 
Q3 = -Al2 = AZ1= --U - sin codel/2 Oey2+d 
L '71 w u =U = -u2k cos 2ey2 O y2+w2 
L 1 2k2 a =-U- sin 2tg2 Oey2+w2 
Demos, Page 8: structure &lt;K,u,v&gt; Demos, Page 8: stokes drift &lt;lin 
vs act sd&gt; &lt;mean drift&gt; 
Conclusions: 
R.ossby waves cause mean westward drifts at the edges and eastward drifts in the 
center. 
Eddy diffusivities are spatially variable and anisotropic.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Separable Problems 
The inesoscale eddy field has horizontal velocities in the near-surface layer which 
are nearly independent of z; and the vertical velocity increases linearly with depth w' = 
s(x; t)z. The stretching satisfies 
For linear (or linearized perturbation) problems in the near-surface layers, we can separate 
the physics and the biology using Greens' functions. 
We define the Greens function for the horizontal flow problem: 
(4+ u(x, t) V -V 1G(x,x'; t -t') = 6(x -x1)6(t-t') 
The perturbation equations can now be solved: 
-1dx' 1dt1G(x; tlx', t')s'(xl, tl)pi(z, t -tl) 
The two functions representing the biological dynamics both satisfy 
with Bij = 3Bi/3bj. These give the diffusive/ biological decay of standardized initial 
perturbations a -@m,i(z,0) = v,&amp; , pi(z, 0) = z-bi3%</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Small amplitude motions 
If we assume that the scale of a typical particle excursion over time Tint is small 
compared to the scale over which the flow variesl we can relate the Lagrangian and Eulerian 
statistics. The displacement ti= Xi(t)-Xi(0)satisfies 
and we can substitute the lowest order solution 
into the second term above to write 
and average, recognizing that the mean Lagrangian velocity is just (;ti): 
For simplicity, we assuine that the turbulent velocities are large coinpared to the inean; 
then this becomes 
3 "1~ij(x&gt; f -ti)= (ui)+ "[d~Rij(x,T) (u:) = + 3xj.o(~i) 
Let us assuine that the integrals with respect to T exist and split the covariance into 
its syininetric and antisyminetric parts 
with 
We can write an arbitrary ailtisymmetric tensor in terins of the unit ailtisymmetric tensor 
so that the contribution to the Lagrangian velocity is</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Gyres (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch19/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Bifiircations and stability 
The bifurcation sequence can be inferred by looking at where the roots coalesce; 
stability can be foiind by discretizing the linearize equations and looking for eigenvaliies 
with posit,ive real parts. Alternatively one can integrate the linearized equations start,ing 
with random perturbations and look for exp~nent~ially growing modes to appear. 
Demos, Page 2: bifurcations &lt;df=0.075&gt; &lt;df=0.0478&gt; Demos, Page 
2: stability &lt;regions&gt; 
Baroclinic case 
The two-layer problem allows for baroclinic instability as well, with significant changes 
in the dynamics. In principle the two-layer system allows an upper-layer only sohition: 
like the Miink soliit,ion biit with the addition of a deformation radius to the PV. If the 
diffiision acts only on the relative vorticity, the RCiterm woiild drop out in steady state; in 
our model, the diffiisivity acts on the PV, so it woiild still appear, But the spin-lip to this 
stat,e is complicat,ed. We tend to think of each mode independently in the linear problem: 
so that the barotropic wave crosses the basin, followed rnlich more slowly by the baroclinic 
wave which wipes oiit the deep signal; leaving the Sverdr~ip flow in the upper layer only. 
But, this picture does not acco~intfor the boiindary conditions. Cane and Sarachik (1976: 
JMR,, 34, 629-665) showed that the spin-lip involves Kelvin waves crossing to the east along 
the eqliator or souther boiindary, moving lip the eastern wall, and generating Rossby waves 
which then cross the basin to the west. 
The QG model has a representation of this process in the baroclinic bo~indary condi-
tion. If we take the transformed geostrophic mon~mt,~im, interface, and mass eqiiations 
and not,e that the transformed variables still satisfy ut . n = 0 on the walls, we find 
The mass of each layer rnnst be conserved. In addition, this implies that the circ~ilation 
aroiind the basin is altered only by direct forcing and dissipation. From these statements, 
we can alignlent the ?i,3---r:3 -(t)condit,ions with a forc~ilafor cl -cz (the barotropic part 
does not matt,er). Alternat~vely, when we invert the PV, we add snfficient free soliltion</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>so that the int,egrals of 
are zero. 
Demos, Page 2: bc spinup &lt;correction field&gt; &lt;no corr&gt; &lt;corr&gt; 
We can avoid this problem by iising the double-gyre. 
Berloff and Meacharn (JPO, 28, 361-388) have explored the two-layer; single-gyre 
version of the same problem. 
Demos, Page 3: Berloff and Meacham &lt;bifurcation&gt; &lt;limit cycle&gt; 
&lt;more complex&gt; &lt;chaos&gt; 
We can see the transit,ions in the two-layer doiible gyre model. By comparison, the 
case with infinitely deep lower layer has steady sohitions 
Demos, Page 3: Transition &lt;tau 0.003&gt; &lt;tau 0.004&gt; &lt;tau 0.005&gt; 
&lt;tau 0.004 del=O&gt; &lt;q&gt; &lt;q tot&gt; 
Demos, Page 3: Example &lt;single layer&gt; &lt;two layer&gt; &lt;ql&gt; &lt;qtl&gt; 
&lt;qt2&gt; &lt;psil&gt; &lt;psi2&gt; &lt;h&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Ocean Basins 
We now want to consider instability, transition to t~irb~ilence: in an and t~irb~ilence 
ocean basin. There are lots of systems t,o choose frorn. The Stornrnel rnodel appears to be 
stable even at strong forcing. 
q = v2g 
For these, hf = 0.032. Demos, Page 1: Stommel 1 gyre &lt;linear model&gt; 
&lt;zeta&gt; &lt;Stomme1 di=O. 023&gt; &lt;zeta&gt; &lt;di=O. 071&gt; &lt;zeta&gt; &lt;di=O. 23&gt; 
&lt;zeta&gt; 
Demos, Page 1 : Two gyre &lt;di=O. 0093&gt; &lt;q&gt; &lt;di=O. 030&gt; &lt;q&gt; 
&lt;di=O. 093&gt; &lt;q&gt; 
The Mlink model 
is livelier. 
Demos, Page 1 : Munk &lt;di=O. 0037&gt; &lt;di=O. 0053&gt; &lt;di=O. 0064&gt; &lt;di=O. 0074&gt; 
&lt;di=O. 0083&gt; &lt;di=O. 010&gt; &lt;di=O. 012&gt; &lt;summary&gt; 
Demos, Page 1 : Munk two gyre &lt;di=O. 0037&gt; &lt;di=O. 0053&gt; &lt;di=O. 0064&gt; 
&lt;di=O. 0074&gt; &lt;di=O. 0083&gt; &lt;di=O. 010&gt; &lt;di=O. 012&gt; &lt;summary&gt; 
Stability and Bifurcations 
Steady states 
Cessi and Ierley (.JPO, 25, 1196-1205) fo~ind steady states by discretizing (nsing 
Chebyshev polynomials) and iising Newton's method t,o find conditions where $q = 0. 
Some soliltions can be fo~ind by starting with the visco~is sohition and gradiially shifting 
the paramet,ers; ohters require initial guesses. Once fo~ind, t,hese can then be continlied. 
Markings indicate mirnber of steady states fo~ind; 
(1)one antisymmetric 
(3) one anti + 2 non 
(5a) one anti + 4 non 
(5b) three anti + 1non 
Demos, Page 1: Regimes Cessi and Ierley &lt;overall: xv -geometry -0+0 
-glenn/12.822t/graphics/cil. jpg&gt; closnipci2.jpg &lt;df=4e-2, di=2e-2&gt; &lt;di=3e-
2&gt; &lt;di=4e-2&gt; &lt;di=5e-2&gt; &lt;di=6e-2&gt; &lt;summary&gt; &lt;A1 and N1&gt; &lt;N2&gt; 
&lt;A2 and A3&gt; 
The experiments shown have hf = 4 x 10V2 and 6,i = 1...6 x lop2 so that they cross the 
regimes shown.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Statistics and Turbulence (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>the probabilit y of the variable vtaking a value between vand v+ dv,and 
 + 
P(v)dv=1. (3.1) 
 
The PDF can be estimated by constructing a histogram of an ensemble of measure
ments of v at the specied location, repeating the experiment time and time again. 
The larger the ensemble (i.e. the more times the experiment is repeated), the more 
closely the histogram will approximate the PDF. 
The momen ts of the variable vare derived from the PDF. The n-th moment &lt;vm &gt; 
is dened as  + 
&lt;vn &gt;= v nP(v)dv (3.2) 
 
The rst moment &lt;v&gt;is the mean : 
 + 
&lt;v&gt;= vP(v)dv (3.3) 
 
The variance is the second momen t of the perturbation quantity v/prime = v &lt;v&gt;, 
and describ es the level of variabilit y about this mean. 
 + 
&lt;v/prime2 &gt;= (v&lt;v&gt;)2P(v)dv (3.4) 
 
The skewness is the third momen t of v/prime, normalized by the variance: 
&lt;v/prime3 &gt; skewness = &lt;v/prime2 &gt;3/2 (3.5) 
A PDF which is symmetric about the mean &lt;v&gt;will have zero skewness. All higher 
odd moments of such a symmetric PDF will also be identically zero. The skewness 
reveals inform ation about the asymmetry of the PDF. Positive skewness indicates 
that the PDF has a longer tail for v/angbracketleftv/angbracketright&gt;0thanfor v/angbracketleftv/angbracketright&lt;0. Hence a positive 
skewness means that variable v/prime is more likely to take on large positive values than 
large negativ e values. A time series with long stretches of small negativ e values and 
a few instances of large positive values, with zero time mean, has positive skewness 
(Fig. 3.1). 
The kurtosis (or atness) is the fourth momen t of v/prime, normalized by the variance: 
&lt;v/prime4 &gt; kurtosis = &lt;v/prime2 &gt;2 (3.6) 
A PDF with longer tails will have a larger kurtosis than a PDF with narrower tails. 
A time series with most measuremen ts clustered around the mean has low kurtosis, 
a time series dominated by intermitten t extreme events has high kurtosis (Fig. 3.2). 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Axisymmet ry 
Turbulence is axisymmet ric if all the mean quantities are invariant under a 
rotation about one particular axis only (e.g. the z axis for stratied turbulence). 
Stationary , isotropic, homogeneous statistics are frequen tly assumed in theories of 
turbulence, but are in fact rare in geophysical contexts where stratication and Cori
olis break the symmetry with respect to rotation, boundaries break the symmetry 
with respect to translation, and seasonal and diurnal forcing break the symmetry 
with respect to time-s hifts. However less restrictiv e assumptions , to be described in 
the rest of this class, allow progress to be made. 
3.4 Central Limit Theorem 
Many quantities in turbulence can be thought of as a sum of random variable s. For 
example a net particle displacemen t in a turbulen t ow may be though t as the sum 
of N random displacemen ts by small eddies; a net velocity may be though t as the 
sum of N random velocity incremen ts. If we assume the incremen tal changes xn all 
have the same unkno wn PDF and zero mean value, then the net change in variable 
is given by, 
N 
z = xn. (3.18) 
n=1 
If all the individual incremen tal changes are independent and uncorrelated with PDF 
P(x), the variance of z is given by, 
NN 
&lt;z2 &gt;= &lt;xnxm &gt;= N2 , (3.19) 
n=1 m=1 
where 2 is the variance of all the xn. (Notice that we are assuming that 2 is nite. 
This is not always the case as for example for power-law PDFs). 
Thevarianceof z increa ses with the size of the ensemble N. As it turns out, it is 
more convenient to work in terms of the variable u = N1/2z, which has variance 2 
for all N. We can now determine the PDF of u. 
The characteris tic function of P(u)is given by 
n=1 Pu(k)=&lt;eiku &gt;= /angbracketlefte ik/N1/2 N xn /angbracketright =(P(kN1/2))N . (3.20) 
We can expand P(kN1/2) as shown in (3.9), 
k22 
P(kN1/2)=1  + O(k3N3/2). (3.21)2N 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Figure 3.2: Signal with a large kurtosis.
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>For large N we obtain the characteristic function of the sum: 
Pu(k) = lim (1  k22/2N)N = e k22/2 . (3.22)
N
The corresp onding PDF is 
1 u2/22 P(u)= e , (3.23)(22)1/2 
i.e. a Gaussian PDF. Therefore the sum of a large number of identically distributed 
independent variables has a Gaussian PDF, regardless of the shape of the PDF of the 
variables themselv es. This result is known as the central limit theorem . 
 
The sum, normalize d by 1/N,of N random, indep endent and ident ically 
distribut ed variables of zero mean and nit e varianc e, 2 , is a random 
variable with a PDF conver ging to a Gaussian distribut ion with varianc e 
2 . 
It is important to remem ber the conditions under which this statemen t holds: the 
individual variables must be independent; N must be large; the variance 2 of the 
PDFs of the individual variables must be nite. 
The central limit theorem is most useful as a starting point, because deviations from 
Gaussian PDFs indica te that some of the assumpt ions discussed above are broken. 
This happens often in turbulen t ows. 
3.5 Intermittency 
A signal is said to be intermittent if rare events of large magnitude are separated by 
long periods with events of low magnitude. Spatial intermittency implies that the 
signal displays localized regions with events of large magnitude , and wide areas with 
events of low magnitude . PDFs of intermittent ows are not Gaussian. If turbule nce 
is dominated by coherent structures localized in space and time, then PDFs are not 
Gaussian. Flows characterized by intermittency are not self-similar. 
(Further reading: Tennekes and Lumley , Ch 6; Lesieur, Ch 5; Frisch, Ch 3, Ch 4, and 
Ch 8 for more on intermittency ). 
3.6 The Closure Problem 
Although it is impossible to predict the detailed motion of each eddy in a turbulen t 
ow, the mean state may not be changing. For example, consider the weather sys
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>The eddy term u/primeb/prime represen t the Reynolds eddy ux of buoyancy. 
The problem of turbulence is often that of nding a represen tation of such Reynolds 
stress and ux terms in terms of mean ow quantities. However, it is not at all clear 
that a general solution (or parameterization) exists, short of computing the terms 
explicitly . 
3.8 Eddy viscosit y and eddy diusivit y 
The simples t closure for the Reynolds stress terms is one which relates u/primeu/prime to the 
mean ow, by assuming a relation of the form, 
u/primeu/prime = T u, (3.33) 
where T is the eddy viscosit y. With such a closure the Reynolds stress term 
takes the same form as the mean viscosity term, but with a dieren t viscosity. In 
essence, this closures states that turbulen t eddies are similar to molecular motions 
that constan tly act to redistribute and homogenize momen tum. Similarly , for the 
tracer ux term we can dene an eddy diusivit y 
u/primeb/prime = T b. (3.34) 
This eddy viscosit y/diusivit y closure is the most commonly used in modeling and 
interpretation of geoph ysical observations. At the crudest level T and T are assumed 
to be constants; in more sophisticated models they are functions of the large scale 
ow. However, an eddy viscosit y/diusivit y closure is rarely appropriate. 
(Further reading: Chapter 1 of McComb) 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>These concepts can be extended to three or more variables , but it is rarely the case 
that one has enough inform ation about the statistics of a ow to measure quantities 
like PJ (u,v,w). 
While PDFs and JPDFs are fundamen tal to theories of turbulence, one seldom mea
sures or use such quantities. Most often, only the rst and the second momen ts are 
used to characterize the turbulen t ow. Particular importance is given to covariances , 
which appear in the problem of Reynolds averaging and will be discussed at the end 
of this lecture. 
3.3 Ergodicity and statistical symmetries 
Computing ensemble means is a daunting task when dealing with laboratory experi
ments or numerica l simulations, because it requires to repeat experimen ts or numerica l 
runs over and over. In the case of geophysical ows, the situations is even worse; we 
cannot ask nature to repeat weather patterns in order to compute our means . Does 
it mean that a statistical description of turbulence is a nice theoretical idea with 
no practical relevance? Fortunately not, because we can estima te ensem ble means 
through time and spatial means, under certain assumptions. 
	Stationarit y 
Turbulence is stationary if all mean quantities (e.g. &lt;v&gt;, &lt;vn &gt;etc) are 
invariant under a translation in time. A stationary variable vis ergodic if the 
time average of vconverges to the mean &lt;v&gt;as the time interval extends to 
innit y, 
1 T 
v(t)dt=&lt;v&gt; as T .	 (3.16)T 0 
(See Frisch, 4.4 for a detailed discussion of ergodicity). In this case a time 
average is equivalent to an ensem ble average. 
	Homogeneit y 
Turbulence is homogeneous if all the mean quantities are invariant under any 
spatial translation. Then an ergodic hypothesis allows an ensem ble average to 
be calculated as a spatial average, 
1 L 
v(x)dx=&lt;v&gt; as L.	 (3.17)L 0 
	Isotrop y 
Turbulence is isotropic if all the mean quantities are invariant under any ar
bitrary rotation of coordinates . 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 3 
A statistical description of 
turbulence 
The evolution of turbulen t ows is very complex. Turbulen t ows appear highly dis
organized with structure at all scales. Signals appear unpredictable in their detailed 
behavior. However some statistical properties of the ow can be quite reproducible. 
This suggests that it can be useful to seek a statistical description of turbulen t ows. 
A statistical measure is an average of some kind: over the symmetry coordinates , 
if any are available (e.g, a time average for stationary ows); over multiple realiza
tions (e.g, an ensemble); or over the phase space of solutions if the dynamics are 
homogeneous. 
In lecture 2 we have shown that a similar behavior is observed in simple deterministic 
maps. These maps are chaotic and not predictable in their detailed properties, but 
their statistical properties are reproducible, just like for turbulen t ows. 
Thus it seems quite appropriate to introduce a probabilistic description of turbulence. 
However we know that the basic Boussinesq equations are deterministic. How can 
chance and chaos arise in a purely deterministic context? A nice discussio n of this 
issue can be found, in chapter 3 of Frischs book. 
In this lecture we rst introduce the statistical tools used in the analysis of turbulen t 
ows. Then we show how to apply these tools to the study of turbulence. 
3.1 Probabilit y density functions and momen ts 
A complete description of a turbulen t variable v at a given location and instant in 
time is given by the probabilit y density function (PDF), P (v), where P (v)dv is 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Figure 3.1: Signal with a positive skewness. 
The characteristic function P(k) is the Fourier transform of the PDF, 
 + 
P(k)= e ikvP(v)dv=&lt;eikv &gt;. (3.7) 
 
The characteristic function of the sum of two independent variables is the product of 
their individual characteristic functions. 
If we take the derivative of the above equation with respect to k and evaluate it at 
the origin (k = 0) we see that the n-th moment is related to the derivatives of the 
characteris tic function by, 
dnP(k) 
n  =in &lt;v&gt;, (3.8)dkn  
k=0 
 where i = 1. Then the characteris tic function can be written as a Taylor series of 
the moments, 
 n   
P(k)=  1 dP(k) kn =  (ik)n 
&lt;vn &gt;. (3.9) n! dkn  n! n=0 k=0 n=0 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>metho ds of closing the hierarchy make assumptions about the relations hip of (n+1)-th 
order terms to n-th order terms, for example by supposing that, 
uuuu = uu uu uuu, (3.28) 
where  is some parameter. Such assumptions require additional, and sometimes 
dubious, reasoning. Nobody has been able to close the system without introducing 
physical assumptions not directly deducible from the equations of motion. 
3.7 The Reynolds equations 
Let us repeat the averaging procedure for the full Boussinesq equations. We start 
with the momentum equations , 
u 1 +(u)u+ fzu=bzp+ 2 u(u/prime )u/prime , (3.29)t 0 
The extra term on the right hand side represen t the eect of eddy motions on the 
mean ow. If the average operator is a time average over some time T , then eddy 
motions are those motions with time scales shorter than T . If the average operator is 
a spatial average over some scale L, then eddy motions are those motions with spatial 
scales shorter than L. If the average operator is an ensemble mean, then the eddy 
motions are those motions that change in every realizations , regardle ss of their scale, 
i.e. they represen t the unpredictable or turbulen t part of the ow. 
Using the continuity equation, 
u =0   u=0 and u /prime =0, (3.30) 
we can rewrite the averaged momentum equation as, 
u 1 +(u)u+ fzu=bz  pI 0u+ 0u/primeu/prime . (3.31)t 0 
I is th unit matrix. These are the so-called Reynolds momen tum equation and 
the eddy ux 0u/primeu/prime represen t the Reynolds stress tensor due to uctuations in 
velocity led. 
We can similarly decomp ose the buoyancy equation into a mean and a uctuating 
component, b =b +b/prime, and write an equation for the mean component by substituting 
back into the buoyancy equation, 
b   
+(u)b =  b + u/primeb/prime . (3.32)t 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>3.2 Joint probabilit y density functions 
Turbulence, of course, involves not one, but several random variables dependent on 
each other. Theref ore, it is necessa ry to dene joint probabilit y density functions 
(JPDF ). For example the JPDF PJ (u,v)ofvariables u and v is the probabilit y of 
nding the rst random variable between u and u + du, and the second one between 
v and v + dv. The integral of PJ over the u,v two-dimensional space is unity by 
denition,   
PJ (u,v)du dv =1, (3.10) 
0  
and PJ (u,v) is positive denite. We recover the PDF of u by integrating PJ over all 
values of v,and thePDF of v by integrating over all values of u, 
    
P (u)= PJ (u,v)dv, P (v)= PJ (u,v)du. (3.11) 
  
The moments of u and v can therefore be obtained from PJ as well. The joint rst 
moment of u and v, /angbracketleftuv/angbracketright, is dened as, 
  
/angbracketleftuv/angbracketright = uvPJ (u,v)du dv. (3.12) 
  
The covariance of u and v is dened as, 
C(u,v)= /angbracketleftuv/angbracketright/angbracketleftu/angbracketright/angbracketleftv/angbracketright = /angbracketleftu /prime v /prime/angbracketright. (3.13) 
Thecovarianceof u and v normalized by the rms values of u and v (the square roots 
of their variances) is called the correlation function r(u,v) and is used to quantify 
the degree of correlation between u and v, 
/angbracketleftu/primev/prime/angbracketright r(u,v)=   . (3.14) 
/angbracketleftu/prime2/angbracketright/angbracketleftv/prime2/angbracketright 
For perfectly correlated variables, the correlation function is 1. The covarianc e is a 
measure of the asymmetry of the JPDF. 
Two variable s whose covarianc e is zero, or equivalently whose correlation is zero, 
are said to be uncorrelated. Notice that two uncorrelated variables need not to be 
independent. Statistical independence of two variables requires that the JPDF can 
be expressed as the product of the individual PDFs, 
PJ (u,v)= P (u)P (v). (3.15) 
Thus independent variables are uncorrelated, but the reverse is not true. 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>tem, in which the storms, anti-cyclones, hurrica nes, fronts etc. constitute the eddies. 
Although we cannot predict these very well, we certainly have some skill at predict
ing their mean state, the climate. For example, we know that next summer will be 
warmer than next winter, and that in California summer will be drier than winter. 
We know that next year it will be colder in Canada than in Mexico, although there 
might be an occasional day when this is not so. We would obviously like to be able 
to predict the mean climate without necessarily trying to predict or even simulate 
all the eddies. We might like to know what the climate will be like one hundred 
years from now, without trying to know what the weather will be like on February 
9, 2056, plainly an impossible task. Even though we know what equations determine 
the system, this task proves to be very dicult because the equations are nonlinear. 
This is the same problem we discussed at the beginning of the lecture. We seek a 
statistical descriptio n of the turbulen t ow, because a detailed descriptio n is beyond 
our grasp. The simplest statistical quantity we might try to predict is the mean 
ow. However, because of the nonline arities in the equations , we come up agains t the 
closure problem. 
The program is to rst decompose the velocity eld into mean and uctuating com
ponents, 
u = u+ u /prime . (3.24) 
Here u is the mean velocity eld, and u/prime is the deviation from that mean. The mean 
may be a time average, in which case uis a function only of space and not time. 
It might be a time mean over a nite period (e.g a season if we are dealing with 
the weather). Most generally it is an ensemble mean. Note that the average of the 
deviation is, by denition, zero; that is u/prime = 0. We then substitute into the momentum 
equation and try to obtain a closed equation for u. To visualize the problem most 
simply, we carry out this program for a model nonline ar system proposed by Geo 
Vallis   which  obeys, 
du 
dt + uu + u =0. (3.25) 
The average of this equation is, 
du 
dt + uu +  u =0. (3.26) 
The value of the term uu is not deducible simply by knowing u, since it involves 
correlations between eddy quantities u/primeu/prime.That is, uu =uu+ u/primeu/prime =/negationslashuu. Wecango 
to next order to try to obtain a value for uu. First multiply (3.25) by u to obtain an 
equation for u2 , and then average it to yield, 
1 duu + uuu + uu =0. (3.27)dt 
This equation contains the undetermined cubic term uuu. An equation determining 
this would contain a quartic term, and so on in an unclos ed hierarchy. Most current 
2 
9
(http://www.princeton.edu/~gkv/aofd.pdf)</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>QG Turbulence (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>QG Turbulence and Waves 
The quasigeostrophic equation contains a num
geophysical flows, while retaining some of the simplber of essential features of large scale 
icity of 2D flow. We assume that the 
system is rapidly rotating and hydrostatic, so that the vertical vorticity equation becomes 
with C = (-v,,ll.,,() and the P-plane approxin~ation f = f,,+By. We assume that C is 
sinall compared to f (Ro= C/ f &lt;&lt; 1)though it nYay be similar in size to 6f / f = PL/ f. 
In that case the term C . Vw is order (1f compared to f gui. Thus the vortex stretching 
is dominantly associated with fluid columns suffering extension along the rotation axis. 
We can in general represent a nondivergent flow as 
a a aand we choose a gauge such that z$l+ -g2 = 0 so that = gd and g2= --$a?] ax . Then 
For near-geostrophic balance, 
1* u=-ZXV?,f 
am .the divergence 1s order DL/ f times the vorticity. Thus the vorticity equation becomes 
-C3 + J($, C + by) = f -lri a + disa3t 32 
aAaB aA aBwith J(A, B) = zF -qz and C = V2+ 
The buoyancy equation can also be simplified by neglecting the divergent part of the 
horizontal flow and noting that &amp;b/N2 is order ((1f)(f 2L2/N2H2; for synoptic/ mesoscale 
flows the last factor is order one. Thus 
a aUsing b = ~p = f z$ and combining gives the QG equation 
-q 3 + .J($, q) = di.s.s/heat3t 
with 
3 f2 3 q=V2$+---$+BY Dz N2Dz</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Let us look at one set of wavenumbers kl, k2, k3 and choose the labelling such that 
K: &lt;K: &lt;K;. The dynamics of this triad is given by 
This triad conserves energy and enstrophy iilterilally 
From the triad equations, we also have 
Energy leaving component 2 will transfer into both 1and 3; when it does so, the average 
scale (CKjEj/ CE,)-' increases; however, oilly the triads with K: -Kg &gt; Kg -K; 
will actually put inore energy into the larger scale mode than the smaller scale one. 
Demos, Page 6: Example &lt;(0,0,0) triads&gt; &lt;sigma&gt; 
STABILITY: If we start with energy in the second component, we can calculate the 
rate at which it goes to other components by looking at the growth rate. We assume 
and 
so that the perturbation problem becomes</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Beta effects 
Demos, Page 3: beta runs &lt;beta=O&gt; &lt;beta=O&gt; &lt;beta=l&gt; &lt;beta=l&gt; 
&lt;beta=5&gt; &lt;beta=5&gt; 
Note that these arguments make no mention of the variation of the Coriolis parameter 
with latitude, P. While it is true that the P-effect does not make the QG equations 
inhomogeneous (the full equations or the shallow water equations are a different matter)) 
it does make the dynamics anisotropic. R.otation by 90 degrees alters the form of q. R.hines 
showed that turbulence on the P-plane has a profoundly different charater, developing 
zonal bands of flow. He used the barotropic vorticity equation (the &amp; = 0 case of the 
QG equation, though the BTVE is actually an exact representation of 2-D motion on a 
P-plane) 
The dyilainics now iilcludes both turbulence and waves riding on the large-scale poten- 
tial vorticity gradient p. The evolution of the flow beconles at some point a problem of 
interacting waves rather than nlultiple-scale energy transfers. 
We can see that this will happen at some scale by considering the parameter measuring 
iloillinear versus wave effects -the wave steepness S = U/c. Since the phase speed for 
R.ossby waves is -,!3/k2: S = Uk2/p. For a k:-3 energy spectrum, we have the velocities 
proportional to kpl and the steepness behaves like k. Therefore: we expect the P-effect 
will have little influence on the short waves, but that the long waves will have restoring 
forxes which are as significant as the turbulent transfers. The scale at which this transition 
occurs should be when the steepness is order one, or L N = E~/~,!Y~/~. 
Alternatively, we could view the effects of the turbulence as mixing the PV and at- 
tempting to homogenize it. But this can only be done over narrow latitude bands. Suppose 
we start with an initial eddy energy density E. If we hoinogenize the PV over width W, 
the zonal mean flow looks like 
-U	3 +Py = const. = 0 for -W/2 &lt; y &lt; W/23~ 
so that U = ,!3y2/2-PW2/24. The energy density for this flow is 
If we used all the initial energy and put it into zonal flow, we'd have 
Two things prevent this froin happening; not all of the energy goes into the waves and the 
interactions become very slow as wave processes dominate. 
Demos, Page 4: Means &lt;psi&gt; &lt;q&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>The growth rates are determined by 
when the amplitude is small, the growth rate will be nonzero only in the regions where 
Demos, Page 6: Resonance &lt;phi=O; beta=O&gt; &lt;beta=O. 5&gt; &lt;beta=l&gt; &lt;beta=2: 
&lt;beta=5&gt; 
Demos, Page 7: Resonance-angle &lt;phi=30;beta=O&gt; &lt;phi=45;beta=O&gt; 
&lt;phi=60; beta=O&gt; &lt;phi=30; beta=2&gt; &lt;phi=45; beta=2&gt; &lt;phi=60; beta=2&gt; 
Demos, Page 7: Resonance-modes &lt;(0,0,0)&gt; &lt;(1,1,0)&gt; &lt;(0,1, I)&gt; 
&lt;(1,1,0)&gt; &lt;(0,1,1)&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The QG equations determine the evolutioil of a scalar property, the approximate 
potential vorticity q, under advection by the horizontal flow u = i x V$. Although the 
movement of PV is treated two-dimensionally at a given depth, the flow is related to the 
PV structure at nearby depths. 
Conserved properties 
The QG equations preserve energy 
and potential enstrophy 
Indeed, they conserve the average of any function of the PV, not just the square, so that 
we have to worry about whether or not the energy and entrophy tell the whole story. 
The /3 term also can have importailt consequences, depending on the boundaries. If 
we represent 
rl=Lli,+Py 
In the doubly-periodic case with uniform buoyancy on the top and bottom bouildaries 
(&amp;$ = 0) the only surviving term is 
the one which can be thought of as Jd3x K2E. We'll talk about other cases later. 
Charney (1971) argues that for small enough scales in the interior of the atmosphere, 
we call treat N2 as constant: rescale z* =Nz/f, and transform the L operator into V:$. 
All of the arguments for upscale energy transfer and downscale enstrophy transfer apply. 
so that the spectrum should be 
just as in the 2-D case. In addition, the theory predicts equipartition of energy among the 
Ir: 11; and bf /N fields. Demos, Page 2: Data &lt;Gage and Nastrom, 1986&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Baroclinicity 
The transfer to large scale occurs in both horizoiltal and vertical directions. Therefore, 
we expect the energy in the gravest vertical mode (F= 1; A,) = 0) to dominate after a 
while. We can expand q' = L?i,and ?i, in the vertical eigenfunctions 
with 
r = v,,-A2?i, ,,, 
The F, functions are the eigenfunctions of the vertical operator 
Then the energy is 
E = -[/%,!,$,,, = EO+ El + Ez... 
Demos, Page 5: Two vertical mode case &lt;pv&gt; &lt;psi&gt; &lt;energies&gt; 
Spectral space transfers 
Let us transform the streanlfunction to wavenumber space 
li, = $(k, t,na, t) exp(zk.r + dy)F,,,, (z) 
q' = i(k,t,7n,,t) exp(zk.r + zty)F,,, (2) 
We introduce a shorthand ?i,? = $(k:, t,A,!,, t) so that each different subscript j corresponds 
to a different set of {k:, !; na) values. The streainfunction is related to the poteiltial vorticity 
by 
q? = (k; + t; + -K;g1 
Now we can project out the equation for the amplitude of one mode by multiplying 
the equation by F,,,, (2) exp(-zk2 . x) and volunle averaging 
with the definition k3 = kl -kz.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>FjijrtijR1s argurrlent; 
Fjiirtiift's (1953) argument can also be applied to the 3D QG flow problem. Suppose 
we have unit energy at a net waveilumber K such that 
and we wish to transfer it elsewhere through illviscid iilteractions. Let a fraction al go to 
larger scales (K/2)and a2to smaller scales 2K. Then our energy and enstrophy pictures 
look like 
Wavenuinber K/2 
Init. energy 0 1 0 
Init. enstrophy 0 K2 0 
Final energy a1 1-alp a2 *z 
Final enstrophy K2a1/4 K2(1 -a1 -a2) K24a2 
If we conserve both energy and enstropl~y by this interaction (i.e., we're in an inertial 
range), we find a1 =4az so that 
Init. energy 0 1 0 
Init. enstrophy 0 K 0 
Final energy 4a2 1 -5a2 az 
Final enstropl~y K2az K2(1 -5a2) K24a2 
More energy is transferred to large scales and more enstrophy to sinall scales. Indeed the 
center of the energy is now at wavenumber K(1 az) and the center of the enstropl~y is at 
K(1 f3.5~~). R.emember that in the cascade to larger scale) the vertical scale can increase 
-the flow can become inore barotropic.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Topographic Waves (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch22/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Initial Value Problem: Finally , we can look at what happens 
if we suddenly turn the ow or the topograph y on. Using 
 2    2 
+ kU  k2  = k2N2 t z2 
with the initial and boundary conditions 
(z, 0) = 0 ,(0,t)= Uh0 ,(,t)=0 
The Laplace transformed problem gives the same z structure equation 
as in the damped system 
2 N2 
 k2 T =  T 
z2 (U2  2sU/k  s2/k2) 
with 
T (0,s)= Uh0/s, T (,s)=0 
Again the positive root is the proper one 
1 N2 
T = Uh0 exp( [  k2]1/2 z) s (U2  2sU/k  s2/k2)
The inverse transform
  1 N2 
 = Uh0 exp( [  k2]1/2 z)e st 
 s (U2  2sU/k  s2/k2) 
is dominated by the singularit y at s = 0; for large time, we recover the 
standing wave solution.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>PSI 
LeBlond and Mysak, Waves in the Ocean, 377-379.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>Critical levels 
Critical levels appear when the phase speed of the waves matches 
the mean ow speed. For stationary non-rotating lee waves this hap
pens when U = 0. The vertical wavenumber m N/U ,The 
positive sign is the correct one, so that 
 = Uh0 cos(kx + N2/U2 k2 z). 
Group Velocity: 
  
cg  
m Uk  
kNk 
2 + mNkm 
2 = (k2 + m2)3/2 0 
Ener gy Flux: The energy ux vanishes at the critical level. 
1 wP =  U3h02km. 2 
Nappo, Atmospheric gravity waves, 114-123.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Boundary conditions 
The boundary condition over a bumpy lower boundary in terms 
of a streamfunction is given by, 
(x, 0,t)= Uh(x, y). 
For a bumpy lower boundary with elevation given by 
h = h0 cos(kx) 
we have 
(x, 0) = Uh0e kx ,(0) = Uh0. 
We will imagine that the upper boundary condition is very far 
and idealize that by considering that z runs between 0 at the lower 
boundary and innity for large positive z.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Group Velocity: Since the topograph y is the source of the 
waves, we would expect the vertical component of cg to be positive. 
This means that if we suddenly add or eliminate the topograph y, the 
disturbance in the wave eld would propagate upwards. Therefore 
 Nk Nkm Uk  = &gt; 0 m k2 + m2 (k2 + m2)3/2 
The positive sign is the correct one, so that 
 = Uh0 cos(kx + N2/U2  k2 z) 
Ener gy Flux: For these 2-D motions, we can write the average 
(as in zonal average) vertical energy ux as 
 P wP = P =  x x 
and we expect it to be positive. Using the zonal momentum equation 
gives 
2 2 2   wP =   U =  + U tz xz tz x z 
Forsteadyow with  = Uh0 cos(kx  mz), we have 
1 wP =  U3h02km2 
again showing the plus sign to be the desired one.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Linearized equations 
One mechanism for creating internal gravity wave is ow over 
topograph y. Well consider the simple case with zonal ow U at a si
nusoidal topograph y at z = h0 cos(kx). The basic state is composed 
of a mean zonal ow u = U(z), a vertical stratication  b = N2(z)z 
in hydrostatic balance, P = z b. All deviations are negligible com
pared with the basic state. For simplicit y we consider two dimensional 
problems only (  = 0 for all perturbations). y
The perturbation equations are, 
   u + Uu + wUz  fv =  P t x x 
  v + fu =  P t y 
   w + Uw =  P + b t x z 
  u + w =0 x z 
  b + Ub + wN2 =0 t x</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Long scales 
If k2 &lt;N2/U2 then m is real and our solution looks like 
 = Uh0 /Rfractur(e kxmz) 
and we must decide which sign to use (or have some contribution from 
each). We shall discuss a number of ways of resolving the issue.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>The Nonlinear Problem 
We can also look at the nonlinear problem in simple 2-D cases. 
The steady equations 
 u q =  b x 
u (b + N2 z)=0 
can be solved by noting that u  = 0 implies  =()the 
advected property is constan t along streamlines, since the parcels of 
uid move along the streamlines in steady ows. The streamfunction 
here includes both the mean ow and the uctuations  = Uz+ /prime(x). 
Therefore 
N2 
N2 z + b/prime(x)= B(Uz + /prime(x))= (Uz + /prime)U 
Uniqueness could be a problem, of course. In any case, well take 
N2 
b/prime /prime= U</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Short scales 
For a mean ow with zero shear, we have 
 N N2 
k2 + m2 = or m 2 =  k2 
U U2 
If the topographic scale is short compared to U/N,the m2 will be 
negativ e so that if m = k2  N2/U2 then 
kx  = Uh0 /Rfractur(e mz ) 
We must choose the negativ e sign so that the disturbance decays with 
height 
 = Uh0 cos(kx)exp( k2  N2/U2 z)</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Bottom boundary conditions 
The condition at the bottom is of no normal ow. 
z h(Ux+ u)  n=(Ux+ u)   =0 
1+ |h|2 
or (U + u) h = wat z = h(x, y)x 
(We can nd the normal by thinking about a function F (x, y, z)= z  
h(x, y); its three-dimensional gradien t is perpendicular to the surfaces 
of constan t F , in particular the one at F = 0 which represen ts the 
boundary .) This linearizes to 
 w = U hat z =0 x 
when the slope and the net height change is small.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>The vorticit y equation then tells us that 
N2 N2 
u q = w  u (q  z)=0U U 
so that 
N2 N2 
2/prime  z = Q(Uz + /prime)=  (Uz + /prime)U U2 
or 
N2 
2/prime =  /prime 
U2 
with the boundary conditions 
/prime(x,h)= Uh , radiation conditionatinnit y 
Solutions can be found in the form, 
(x,h)= Uh(x) cos(N(z h)/U)+ Uf(x)sin(N(z h)/U). 
the function f(x) is determined imposing the radiation condition.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Generation of internal gravity waves by ow over topograph y
Boussinesq equations 
From  = 0(1  b/g), p = 0gz + 0P ,and b&lt;&lt;g (and cs &gt;&gt; gH) 
D u + fz  u = P + zb Dt 
 u =0 
D b =0 Dt</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Generation of lee waves with no rotation 
The motions is two-dimensional and non-div ergent and we can 
therefore write the linear problem in terms of the wave streamfunction, 
  u =  , w = . z x 
The streamfunction satised the linear problem, 
2 N2 UzzU2 2 +   =0. x2 U2 U 
For motion that is periodic in x, we can integrate the above equation 
twice to obtain, 
N2 Uzz2 +   =0. U2 U 
For solutions that are periodic in x with wavenumber k, we can write 
the streamfunction as, 
 = (z)e kx 
where it is understo od that we take the real part of the solution. 
Thus  satises, 
2   2 N2 Uzz + m 2(z)  k2  =0,m   . z2 U2 U</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>Convective instability 
The buoyancy eld is given by, 
N2 
b = N2 z  . U 
The condition for convective instabilit y is, 
 N2  b = N2  &lt; 0,z Uz 
or  &gt;U. z 
For solutions of the form 
N2 N2 
 = Uh0 /Rfractur(e kxmz ),m 2 = U2  k2  U2 
this implies 
Nh0 &gt; 1. U</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Damping: Another approac h is to add damping to the equations 
so that even the vertically wavy mode decays and reject any growing 
solution. We take 
  u + U u = P + bz  /epsilon1u t x 
 u =0 
  b + Ub + wN2 = /epsilon1b t x 
We now have 
N 2k2 N2 
(kU + /epsilon1)2 =  k2 + m2  m 2 = U 2(1  /epsilon1/kU)2  k2 
The imaginary part of m is 
/Ifractur(m) /similarequal 1 /epsilon1N2 
/Rfractur(m) kU3 
so that vertically decaying solutions /Ifractur(m) &gt; 0require /Rfractur(m) &gt; 0as 
before.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>Shear instabilit y 
The condition for shear instabilities is
N2 + bz 1
Ri  &lt;(Uz + uz)2 
Nappo, Atmospheric gravity waves, 141-144.
4 .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Transformed Eulerian Mean (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Eulerian Mean equatio ns indeed give us a clear er pictur e on what is going on when 
eddies interact with a mean ow. 
14.4.1 The QGPV ux and the residual Ertel PV ux 
The major advantage of the transformed Eulerian Mean formulation is that the only 
eddy forcing is the QGPV ux. We will now show that the QGPV ux is the residual 
comp onent of the full Ertel PV ux and can thus be expected to be dius ive. 
The full Ertel potential vorticity in the quasi-geo strophic approximatio n is given by 
P = fN2 + fbz + N2 . The eddy PV ux can be comput ed easily , 
uP  = fubz+ u, (14.35) 
= fvb
z + v j + O(Ro2). (14.36) 
Thus to leading order the eddy PV ux has only an horizon tal component. It is 
instructiv e to write the meridona l ux in the form, 
vP  = fz(vb)+ v (14.37) 
= f vb 
N2 + v (14.38) z N2 
= fvb 
z(N2)+ fN2 vb 
. (14.39) N2 z N2 
Using the fact that Pz = z(fN2)+ O(Ro) and that vz= f1b
x + O(Ro) we can 
simplify the expression as, 
vP  = v
Nb
2  
Pz + N2 vq + O(Ro2). (14.40) 
Using this relation we can write the full Ertel PV ux as the sum of skew and sym
metric components, 
     
vP  
=0 c 0+  vP   v
Nb
2  Pz  . (14.41) wP  c 0 Pz wP  + v
Nb
2  Py 
To leading order this relatio n is, 
        
vP  
wP  = 0 
c c 
0 0 
Pz + N2 vq 
0 (14.42) 
In this form we see that the Ertel PV ux is comp osed of an advective skew comp onent
and a residual component, which happ ens to be proportional to the QGPV. In the
lecture on passiv e tracer transport we emphasized that the residual ux tends to mix
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>across tracer contours, while the skew comp onent does not mix. Furthermor e the 
skew comp onent is typically much larger than the residua l comp onent. Simila rly in 
this problem, the skew component advects PV around and domina tes the full PV 
ux, but it is the residual ux that achieves mixing. This can be demonstra ted by 
considering the QGPV variance budg et, 
tq2 + yvq2 = 2vqqy +2D.	 (14.43) 
this suggests that in steady state for homogeneous turbulence, the eddy QGPV ux 
must be down its mean gradient, 
vq = Kqy.	 (14.44) 
14.5	Param eterizing mesoscale motions in numer 
ical models 
So far we avoided getting our hands dirty to nd closures that relate the eddy uxes to 
the mean ow. The TEM formalism is however often invoked to deriv e parameteriza
tions of the interaction between large-sc ale mean ows and small-scale transient eddy 
motions. In this sectio n, we will use the results of TEM together with some physical 
insigh t to deriv e sets of equatio ns where the eddy terms do not appear explicitly . Two 
approaches are used in the literature, one based on an energ etic argumen t, and the 
other on potential vorticit y mixing theory . 
14.5.1	The energetic argum ent 
The energetic argument has been used to deriv e eddy parameterizatio ns in the ocean 
only. Thus we will restrict our scope to ocean dyna mics in this section. 
Altho ugh mesoscale eddy motions can be directly genera ted by external forcing , like 
the wind eld, most of the mesoscale eddy energy is believed to be the result of 
instabilit ies in many forms (Pedlosky, 1987). The common belief is that eddies are 
genera ted by extracting kinetic and potential energy from the mean ow. This migh t 
not be the whole story thoug h: in two dime nsional and quasi- geostro phic turbulence , 
eddy motions can create an inverse energy cascade and return some of the energy 
back to the mean ow. The point here is that an analy sis of the exchang e of energy 
between mean and eddy motions might be fruitful to deriv e parameterizat ions. 
The total mechanica l energy is given by the sum of the kinetic K and potential 
energies P , which in the geostro phic approximatio n are, 
K = 1(u 2 + v 2),P =1 b2 
.	 (14.45) 2	 2 N2 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>Baro clinic insta bility tends to extra ct potential energy from the mean state. The 
simples t closure that would ensure that energy is always released from the mean 
state and lost into the eddy led is, 
 vb = Kyb. (14.53) 
This closure scheme was rst proposed by Gent and McWilliams in 1990, and it is 
now in use in most coarse-res olution ocean models. 
In terms of the TEM, this closure provide an estimate of the eddy induced circulation, 
yb c = KN2 (14.54) 
The parameterizatio n of Gent and McWillia ms is thus equivalent to assuming that 
the eddy induced circulatio n is proportional to the isopycnal slope. As long as mean 
isopycnals are tilted, there is available potential energy to drive an eddy-induce d 
circulatio n. 
In terms of the Transformed eulerian mean forma lism the parameterizat ion of Gent 
and McWilliams is as a closure for the eddy forcing of the residual circula tion, i.e., 
yb  F f0z KN2 . (14.55) 
In this closure the eddy stress is proportional to the isopycnal slope. In order to 
satisfy conserv ation of mean momen tum, it is customa ry to impose K = 0 at the 
ocean surface and ocean bottom. 
Further reading 
Bryan K, Dukowicz JK, Smith RD, 1999: On the mixing coecien t in the parame
terizat ion of bolus velocity J. Phys. Oceanogr.29, 2442-2456. 
Danabaso glu, G., J. McWilliams, and P. Gent, 1994: The role of mesoscale tracer 
transports in the global ocean circulatio n. Scienc e, 264, 1123-1126. 
Gent, PR, McWillia ms JC, 1990: Isopycnal mixing in ocean circulation models. J. 
Phys. Oceanogr., 20, 150-155. 
Green, JSA, 1970: Transfer properties of large scale eddies and the genera l circulation 
of the atmosphere. QJR MS, 96, 157-185. 
Gries SM, 1998: The Gent-Mc Willia ms skew ux, J. Phys. Oceanogr., 28, 831-841. 
Held IM, Larichev VD, 1996: A scaling theory for horizon tally homogeneous, baro
clinically unstable ow on a beta plane. J. Atmos. Sci, 53, 946-952. 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>Conserv ation of total energy takes the form, 
 1 
t + u  [K + P ]+ 0  (pu a)= u  G + NbB 
2 . (14.46) 
Exchang e of energy between eddies and a zonal ow may be dened following the 
separa tion of the zonally averaged kinetic and potential energies into comp onents 
associated with the eddy and mean motions. In the quasi- geostro phic approxima tion, 
this is straightforward, 
1b2 
KM = 1
2 (u2 +v2),PM = , (14.47) 2 N2 
KE = 21  
u2 + v2  
,PE =1 b2 
. (14.48) 2 N2 
Let us assume once again that the basic state is a zonal ow, i.e. u= u(y,z,t), 
 b = b(y,z,t), but v= w= 0. The equat ions for the mean kinetic and potential 
energies are, 
KM 1 + uap) = b uy(uv)+u  (14.49) t 0  (wa   G, 
PM +bwa =  by vb 
+bB  
. (14.50) t N2 N2 
The eddy terms on the rhs represen t conversion of mean energ y into turbulent energy 
and are often associated with instabilities of the mean ow. 
Equat ions (15.49) and (15.50) can be combined together in the form, 
 1 
t(KM + PM )+ 0  (uap) = 
b  
= y uuv +bv
Nb
2  
+ uvyu+ v
Nb
2  
y b +uG + NB 
2 . (14.51) 
The ocean is a strongly strat ied uid and most of the energy in the basic state 
is stored as potential energy due to tilted isopycnal surfaces . This energy is con
verted into mesoscale eddy motions mainly through baroclinic instabilit ies. Thus 
in equat ion (15.51) the buoyancy eddy ux terms typically dominate over the eddy 
momen tum ux terms. 
The divergent terms represen t transp ort of eddy activity from one region to another. 
In a statistica lly steady state, we can assume that there is no net transport of mean 
mechanica l energy out of the doma in considered. Neglecting the kinetic energy loss 
terms and the divergen t terms, we have that on average, 
 vb 
t(KM + PM ) N2 yb + externa l forcing. (14.52) 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 14 
Transfo rmed Eulerian Mean 
In the last lectur e we showed under what approximat ions we can relate the tracer 
uxes genera ted by a turbulen t ow to the large scale tracer gradien t. In this lecture 
we show how to apply those ideas to study the eect of macro turbulence on the a 
large scale circula tion of the ocean and atmo sphere. As a rst step we will consider 
eddies generat ed through insta bilities of a zonal mean jet in the quasi- geostro phic 
approxima tion. This is a very special example, but it is a useful and simple testb ed 
to develop our intuitio n about these problems. 
The litera ture on eddy mean-s lows interactions is so vast that it is impossible to give 
a compr ehensiv e review. Thus we will focus on a few aspects of particular relevance 
in the atmospheric and oceanic context. Our goal is to show how these theor ies can 
be used to derive closure schemes to repres ent the eect of eddy motions on mean 
ows. More informa tion on these problems can be found in the references given at 
the end of the chapter. 
14.1 The quasi -geostrophic equat ions on a -plane 
Consider a ow in a Boussines q uid with characteristic horizo ntal length scale L, 
velocity U, time scale T  L/U, on a -plane for which the Coriolis parameter is 
f = f0 + y. We make the assumption that, 
1. the Rossb y number Ro = U/f0L is small, 
2. the -eect is small, L/f 0  Ro, 
3. the isopycnal slopes |xb|/|zb| and |yb|/|zb| are  Ro (otherwis e vertical mo
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>that, under non-accelera tion condit ions, tuand tb must be zero. What must, and 
thus happ en, under such circumsta nces, is that eddie s induce an ageostro phic mean 
motion, which exactly balance the eddy ux terms in (15.21) and (15.24), i.e. eddy 
uxes induce a mean circula tion. This is reminiscen t to the result that eddy uxes of 
quasi-conserv ed tracers can have an advectiv e comp onent: in this problem the mean 
advective eect of the eddy uxes is repres ented by the ageostrophi c circulatio n. 
14.4 The Transformed Eulerian Mean Theory 
The diculty in interpreting the balance of eddy terms and ageostro phic motio ns can 
be overcome by what may seem a mathematica l trick, but is in fact linked to the de
comp ositio n of eddy uxes in skew (advectiv e) and symmetr ic (dius ive) comp onents. 
The trick is to redene the mean meridiona l, ageostrophic, circulatio n. 
Consider the mean buoyancy budget (15.24). This is (apart for the loss of some terms 
through the quasi-geo strophic assumptio n) the same as the Eulerian mean budget of a 
tracer equat ion. We saw that the eddy ux term can include an advectiv e comp onent. 
Under quasi-geostro phic assumpt ions, we can guess what that component is. 
We begin by noting that, from eq. (15.23), we may dene an ageostroph ic mean 
streamfunctio n a, such that, 
(va,wa)=(za,ya). (14.25) 
We can then rewrite the mean buoyancy budget in (15.24) as, 
t b + y a + v
Nb
2  
N2 = B . (14.26) 
where we used the fact that N2 = N2(z), i.e. the vertica l stratica tion does not 
chang e with latitude. In this form, it is quite clear that the eddy ux term can be 
represen ted as a mean advection, by dening an eddy induced mean streamfunction 
c as, 
vb
c = . (14.27) N2 
We now dene the residua l circula tion as, 
(v,w)=(z,y), (14.28) 
where the new strea mfunctio n is, 
 = a + c. (14.29) 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>14.2	Potential vorticity uxe s and the Eliassen-
Palm Theorem 
The next three sections, up to the denitio n of Transformed Euleria n Mean, follow 
very closely the notes of Alan Plum b on eddy-mean ows interactio ns. If you are 
interested in learning more on this topic, I encourage you to contact Alan and ask for 
a copy of his notes. 
Consider the small amplitude motions on a steady , zonally-uniform basic state, 
u = u(y, t), b = b(y, t),  = (y, t), (14.13) 
where 
u = y , y b = f0z u. (14.14) 
The mean PV is,   
q = f0 + y + 2 
y  + z f2 
0 
N2 z  . (14.15) 
The pertur batio n strea mfunction and PV are given by, 
f2 	 0 =   , q = q  q= x2 + y 2 + z z (14.16) N2 
Using v = x, we can also show that, 
vq =  F =  FFy
z =  
N
2 u
v
v
b
 .	 (14.17) f0 
F is known as the Eliassen-Palm ux. Note that the northward comp onent of F is 
minus the northward ux of zonal momen tum by the eddies, uv, while the vertica l 
comp onent is proportiona l to the northward ux of buoyancy, vb. 
Linear izing the quasi-geostrophic potential vorticity equat ion (15.10), we get, 
tq +uxq + vyq= .	 (14.18) 
If we multiply by q and average, we obtain the eddy potential enstrophy equat ion, 
q2 
t + vqyq= q.	 (14.19) 2 
This equation is the basic ingredien t for the Eliassen-Palm theorem: For waves which 
are steady (tq2 =0), of smal l amplitude, and conservative (v =0), the northwar d 
eddy PV ux vanishes (vq =0) and the ux F is nondiver gent. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Adco ck, S.T. and D.P. Marsha ll, 2000: Interactio ns between geostro phic eddies and
the mean circulatio n over large-scale bottom topography. J. Phys. Oceanogr., 10,
1010-1031.
Holla nd W., and P. Rhines, 1980: An exam ple of eddy-induce d ocean circulat ion, J.
Phys. Oceanogr., 10, 1010-1031.
Rhines P., and W.R. Young , 1982: Homog enization of potential vorticit y in ocean
gyres, J. Fluid Mech., 122, 347-367.
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>We can now consider the problem of how eddies impa ct the zonal mean circulation. 
The mean quasi-geostrophic PV budg et reads, 
tq+ y. (vq) = 	 (14.20) 
Because of the quasi-geostrophic approximat ion, eq. (15.20) contains no mean advec
tion term and no vertical comp onent of eddy uxes . 
The inuence of the eddies on the mean QGPV, therefore, is entirely describ ed by the 
northward ux vq. Now we know from the Eliassen- Palm theorem that if the waves 
are 1) steady , 2) conserv ative, and 3) of small amplitude, then F is nondiv ergent and 
vq = 0. Under these condit ions, theref ore, the equation for the zonally-averaged 
QGPV is indep enden t of the eddies. An therefor e the full evolution of the mean ow 
is indep enden t of the eddies. This is known as the non-ac celeration theorem. 
14.3	Mean mom entum and buo yancy budg ets: con
ventional approach 
In order to fully appreciate the meaning of the Eliassen- Palm theorem, it is useful to 
consider t he zona l mean of the qua si-geo strophic momen tum and buoyancy equatio ns, 
 tu f0va = Gx  y(uv), (14.21) 
 f0zu= yb,	 (14.22) 
yva + zwa =0,	 (14.23) 
b +N2 = 	 (14.24) t wa B y(vb). 
The evolution of the zonal mean state in the presence of eddie s is therefore manifes ted 
in two terms  the convergence of the eddy ux of momentum, uv, and buoyancy, 
vb. Both these terms force the mean ow equations and it is important to note that 
the whole system is coupled, i.e., the buoyancy uxes can impa ct on the mean ow, 
just as much as the mom entum uxes. Therma l wind balance (15.22) links the two. 
Consider, for example, a wave with vb = 0, but uv = 0 (as it is largely true in 
the ocean) . The mean state canno t respond with a changin g mean buoyancy only; 
therma l wind balance dema nds a corresponding change in u. From eq. (15.21), this 
can only be achieved throug h an ageostr ophic meridio nal circulat ion, which would 
impact on both the momen tum and buoyancy budgets. Thus, the eddies will not 
 only drive tuand tb, but also va and wa (except in the unlik ely case where the eddy 
forcing terms conspire not to disturb the thermal wind balance). 
Note that the central role of the potential vorticity ux, obvious in the QGPV budget, 
is not at all obvious here. Indeed, we have seen from the potential enstro phy budget, 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>Lee MM, Marshall DP, Willia ms RG, 1997: On the eddy transfe r of tracers: Advectiv e 
or diusiv e? J. Mar. Res., 55 (3) 483-505. 
Spall MA, Chapma n DC, 1998: On the eciency of baroclinic eddy heat transport 
across narrow fronts J. Phys. Oceanogr., 28, 2275-2287. 
Stone, PH, 1972: A simplied radiativ e-dyna mical model for the static stability of 
rotating atmospheres. J. Atmos. Sci., 29, 405-418. 
Stamme r D, 1998: On eddy characteristics , eddy transports, and mean ow properties 
J. Phys. Oceanogr., 28, 727-739. 
Treguier AM, Held IM, Larichev VD, 1997: Parameteriza tion of quasigeostro phic 
eddies in primitiv e equat ion ocean models J. Phys. Oceanogr.27, 567-580. 
Visbeck, M., J. Marshall, T. Haines, and M. Spall, 1997: On the specicatio n of eddy 
transfer coecien ts in coarse-resolut ion ocean circula tion models. J. Phys. Oceanogr., 
27, 381-402. 
14.5.2 The potential vorticity mixing argumen t 
We have shown that in steady state for homo geneous turbulence, the eddy QGPV 
ux must be down its mean gradient, 
vq = Kqy. (14.56) 
Plugg ing this closure in the expression for the Eliassen-Palm uxes gives, 

 F = vq = K  yy u+ f0z 
Ny 
2 b. (14.57) 
This express ion for the eddy forcing of the residual circula tion diers from that 
in (15.55). The two expressions are equiv alent if 1) K is consta nt, 2) there is no 
planeta ry PV gradient ( = 0), and 3) PV is dominated by the baroclinic term. 
In the ocean condition 3 is often satised. Condition 2 is harder to assess , because 
it depends on whether eddie s mix on dista nces large enoug h to feel the eect of . 
Conditio n 1 instead cannot be satised, because one needs to impose K = 0 at the 
bounda ries in the Gent-McWillia ms parameterizat ion and theref ore K canno t be con
stant. Thus the two closure schemes are dierent. It is open to deba te which approach 
is more appropri ate. A good discussion can be found in the paper by Treguier et al. 
(1997). 
Further reading : 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>The streamfunctio n  is the so-called residual streamfunction and it represen ts the 
new denitio n of mean circulation. It is called a residual circulat ion, because in many 
situat ions a and c tend to oppose each other, and  is the residual between two 
strong circulat ions. If we substit ute the denitio n in (15.27) into the mean buoyancy 
budget, we obtain, 
t b + wN2 = B .	 (14.30) 
. 
We thus succee ded in deriving a mean buoyancy equatio n in which there is no explicit 
eddy term; buoyancy is transported solely throu gh the mean vertica l residua l motion. 
It might be thoug ht, of course, that the eddy terms are still there, implicit in w. But 
this was also true of wa which, as noted earlier, is in genera l inue nced by the eddies . 
What we have done, is to redene this inue nce, so as to put the mean buoyancy 
budget into its simplest possible form. 
We can complete the transformed system of equat ions, 
tu f0v = G x +  F , (14.31) 
 f0zu= yb,	 (14.32) 
yv + zw =0,	 (14.33) 
t b + w N2 = B ,	 (14.34) 
where F is the Eliassen- Palm ux. 
This transfor matio n makes the role of eddies look quite dieren teven thoug h the 
physics described by equatio ns (15.31) through (15.34) is the same describ ed by 
(15.21) through (15.24).	The main advantage is that in terms of v, w, tu, and 
tb, the only term representing the eddy forcing is  F = vq. This eddy forcing ap
pears as an eective body force in the mean momentum equatio n. It is clear therefor e 
that, under non-accele ration conditio ns (when F = 0 and the boundary condit ions 
are indep enden t of eddy dependent terms), v, w, tu, and t b, are indep enden t of 
the eddies. 
When non-acceleratio n conditio ns are not satise d, the transfor med equations oer 
a more transpa rent approach to the eddy-mean ow interactio n problem, simply be
cause the single term represented by the eectiv e force  F entirely describes the 
eddy forcing of the mean state. In fact, this formulation gives us another interpreta 
tion of F , as an eddy ux of transformed negative (easterly) momen tum, which is a 
more reliable measure of eddy transport of momen tum than uv itself. 
The interpreta tion of F as a momen tum ux may seem to be a result of mathemat ical 
tinkering. However, it should be reme mbered that the process of taking a mean is an 
arbitrar y onet here is no unique way of doing it. Thus, it is legiti mate to choose the 
denition of mean that simplies the most the problem at hand. The Transfor med 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>tions would not be small), 
4. the static stabilit y N2 = b/z is a functio n of z only. 
Under these assumptions, the leading order equations in Ro give geostr ophic balance.
Thus we can write the leading order geostro phic velocities in the Ro expan sion, as,
  u =  y , v = x , w = 0, (14.1) 
where  is the geostrophic streamfunctio n, 
 = p  p0(z) 
0f0 . (14.2) 
Hydro static balance gives us, 
 b 
z = f0 . (14.3) 
At the next order in Ro, we obtain the progno stic quasi- geostro phic equations, 
Dgu  yv  f0va = Gx, (14.4) 
Dgv + yu + f0ua = Gy, (14.5) 
xua + yva + zwa =0, (14.6) 
Dgb + N2 wa = B, (14.7) 
(14.8) 
where Dg is the time deriv ative following the geostroph ic motions, 
Dg = t + ux + vy, (14.9) 
(ua,va,wa) is the ageostrophic velocity, i.e the dierence between the actual velocity 
and the geostr ophic one, (Gx, Gy) is the external forcing on momen tum (e.g. wind 
stress, friction, ...), and B are the nonco nservative buoyancy forces (e.g. small scale 
mixing , sea-surface heat uxes, ...). 
Using (15.4) throug h (15.7), we can derive the equatio n for the quasi- geostro phic 
potential vorticit y (QGPV), q, 
Dgq = , (14.10) 
where, 
q = f0 + y + xv  yu + f0z(b/N2), (14.11) 
 = xGy  yGx + f0z(B/N2). (14.12) 
Eq. (15.10) tells us that for conserv ative ows (G = 0, B = 0) q is conserved following 
the geostrophic ow. When the ow is not conservative,  represen ts the local sources 
and sinks of q, arising from viscous and diaba tic eects. As you can see, the QGPV 
satisfy the advection-diusion equatio n of a generic tracer. Thus we might be able to 
use the results on tracer transp ort in turbulent ows to study the dyna mics of q. 
2</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>SQG Turbulence (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch12/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 12 
Surface Quasi Geostroph y 
The quasi-geostro phic (QG) theory introduced by Glenn describ es the ow depart ures 
from solid body rotation in a rapidly rotating, stably str atied uid. In its Boussine sq 
version, the ow evolves according to the coupled vorticit y () and buoyancy (b) 
equat ions, 
t = J(,)+ fzw, (12.1) 
tb = J(,b)  N2 w, (12.2) 
 2, b  fz. (12.3) 
Here  is the strea mfunc tion for the horizo ntal geostrophic ow, (u,v)=(y,x), 
w is the vertica l velocity, f is the constan t vorticity due to the background rotation, 
while N(z) is the buoyancy frequency of a reference state. The vorticit y  is dened 
as in two-dimensional ows. Eliminat ing the vertical velocity, one obtains the pseudo-
potential vorticit y equat ion, 
tq = J(,q),q  xx + yy + zS2z , S2  (N/f)2 . (12.4) 
If we specialize to the case of constant N, the Prandtl ratio S can be subsumed into 
a rescaled vertical coordina te, Nz/f (in which case we retain the notation z for the 
rescaled coordina te), and the potential vorticit y is now simply the three-dimensional 
Laplacian of the streamfunction. At at lower bounda ries, the conditio n of no normal 
ow is, 
tb = J(,b), at z = 0. (12.5) 
(12.6) 
If a at upper bounda ry is imposed, then (12.5) also holds at z = H. 
The familiar special case of two-dimens ional ow is obtaining by assuming that the 
streamfunctio n is indep enden t of z. Char ney suggested that a more geophysically 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Following Kraichnan, the strain rate due to eddies with scale 1/K is K2U(K)dK = 
K(K)dK. Substitutin g (12.15) for the spectrum , we nd that the enstroph y 
cascade is domina ted by local strain in SQG. In the direct enstrophy cascade range 
of QG, the K1 local scaling spectrum is the same as the passive scalar spectrum 
predicted for the strongly nonlocal case in which straining is domina ted by large 
eddies with a xed timesc ale. Thus, the spectra l behavior shades continuously over to 
the nonlo cal scaling. This is because in QG the conserv ed quan tity q is coincidentally 
the straining rate. 
It is important to notice that the energ y spectrum E refers to the 3D volume integral 
of potential plus kinetic energies. However the kinetic and potential energies at the 
lower bounda ries both scale like the buoyancy variance spectrum . In SQG the 
energy spectrum in the interior diers from that at the surface, because each normal 
mode of the system decays at a dieren t rate away from the bounda ry so that the 
surface and interior spectra can be quite dierent. 
12.3.1 Fjortofts argumen t 
Fjort ofts (1953) argumen t for the directio n of the energy ux in 2D turbulen t ows 
can also be applied to the SQG ow problem with minor modica tions. Supp ose we 
have unit energ y at a wavenumber K such that, 
(K)= KE(K), 
and we wish to transfer it elsewhe re throug h inviscid interactio ns. Let a fractio n 1 
go to larger scales (K/2) and 2 to smaller scales (2K). Then our energy and variance 
pictures look like, 
Wavenumber K/2 K 2K 
Init. energy 0 1 0 
Init. variance 0 K 0 
Final energy 1 1  1  2 2 
Final variance K1/2 K(1  1  2) K22 
If we conserv e both energy and variance by this interaction (i.e., were in an inertial 
range), we nd 1 =22 so that, 
Wavenumber K/2 K 2K 
Init. energy 0 1 0 
Init. enstrophy 0 K 0 
Final energy 22 1  32 2 
Final enstrop hy K2 K(1  32) K22 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Turbulence in the Atmospher e and
Oceans
Instructors: Raaele Ferrari and Glenn Flierl 
Course descript ion 
The course will presen t the phenomena , theor y, and modeling of turbulence in the 
Earths oceans and atmosphere. The scope will range from centimeter to planetary 
scale motions. The regimes of turbulence will include homo geneous isotropic three 
dimensional turbulenc e, convection, bounda ry layer turbulence, internal waves, two 
dimensional turbulence, quasi-geo strophic turbulence, and planeta ry scale motions in 
the ocean and atmosphere. Prerequisites: the mathemat ics and physics required for 
admission to the gradua te curriculum in the EAPS departmen t, or consent of the 
instructo r. 
Course require ments 
Class attendance and discussion, bi-weekly homework assignm ents. 
Refe rence texts 
Frisch, Turbulence: the legacy of Kolmogo rov
Lesieur, Turbulence in Fluids, 3rd revised edition
McC omb, The physics of turbulence
Sama n, Vortex dynamics
Salmo n, Lectures on geophysical uid dynamics
Strogatz, Nonlinear Dyna mics and Chao s: With Applic ations in Physics, Biology,
Chemis try, and Engineering 
Tennek es and Lumley , A rst course in Turbulence</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>t Kj 2|j |2 = Kj Ej =0 
From the triad equat ions, we also have, 
tE1 = K3  K2 tE2 (12.21) K3  K1 
tE3 = K2  K1 tE2. (12.22) K3  K1 
Energy leaving component 2 will transfer into both 1 and 3; when it does so, the 
triads with K3  K2 &gt;K2  K1 put more energy into the larger scale mode than the 
smaller scale one, and put more buoyancy variance into the smaller scale mode than 
the larger scale one. 
Following Merilees and Warn (JAS, 1975), who studied triads interactio ns in the QG 
problem, the relativ e magnitude of the energy ows from or to the middle wave, 
represen ted by K2, will be considered for the SQG problem. We can write, 
tE1 K3  K2 1+ r2 +2r cos   1 = = , (12.23) tE3 K2  K1 1  r 
t1 = K1 K3  K2 =1  rtE1 , (12.24) t3 K3 K2  K1 1+ r2 +2r cos tE3 
where  denot es the angle between the wavenumbers k1 and k2, and r = K1/K2. 
The region in (,r) space where the vector k1 may terminat e is shown in Fig.1. The 
conditio ns K1 &lt;K2 and tE1/tE3  0 provide the respective boundaries of this 
regio n, i.e. r = 1 and cos  = r/2. The energ y and enstrophy exchange diagram for 
QG is very simila r to Fig.1, although the relativ e magnit udes of the regions where 
tE1/tE3  1 and tZ1/tZ3  1 are slightly dierent. In the present case about 
61% of the interactions lead to a larger exchang e of depth-in tegra ted energ y with low 
wavenumbers, tE1/tE3  1. More available potential energ y on the bounda ries, i.e. 
bounda ry buoyancy variance, is sent to high wavenumbers in 57% of the interactio ns, 
t1/t3 &lt; 1. 
12.5 The eect of a rigid upper lid 
A rigid upper lid changes the properties of SQG turbulenc e, because it introduces a 
vertical scale in the problem, 
tb = J(,b), at z =0,H, (12.25) 
b  fz, (12.26) 
q  (xx + yy + zz) , for 0 &lt;z &lt;H. (12.27) 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>Blume n, W., Unifor m potential vorticit y ow: Part I. Theory of wave interactio ns
and twodimens ional turbulence, J. Atmos. Sci., 35, 1978, 774-783.
Blume n, W., Unifor m potential vorticit y ow: Part II. A model of wave interactio ns, 
J. Atmos. Sci., 35, 1978, 784-789.
Held, I., R. Pierrehumbert, S. Garner, K. Swanson, J. Fluid Mech., 282, 1-20, 1995.
Pierreh umbert, R. I. Held, K. Swanson, Chaos, Solitons and Fractals, 4, 1111-1116,
1994.
Tulloch, R. and K. S. Smith, A New Theory for the Atmospheric Energ y Spectrum:
Depth-Limited Temperatur e Anoma lies at the Tropopause, Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci.,
103, 14690-14694, 2006.
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>A remarkable property of the nite- depth SQG problem is that it transitio ns between 
quasi-two-dimensional barotropic ow at large scales and baroclinic three-dimensional 
ow at small scales. 
The solution to the SQG problem with a bottom rigid lid shows that as the horizo ntal 
scales get larger (or K gets smaller), the penetrat ion depth of the buoyancy anoma lies 
increases, with aspect ratio given by the Prandt l ratio, S = N/f. At large enough 
scale, the penetra tion will reach deep into the interior ow all the way to the upper 
lid. The eect of an upper limit in the penetration of buoyancy anomalies is best 
described in terms of the solutions of the SQG problem, 
(k, z) = cosh[S (z + H)K] 
SK sinh(SHK) b(k, 0), (12.28) 
which at the upper surface becomes, 
(k, 0) = (SK)1 tanh(SHK)b(k, 0). (12.29) 
The remark able property of this nite-depth SQG model results from the properties 
of the hyperbolic tangent in the inversion. At large scales, or K  (SH)1, the 
buoyancy is related to the streamfunctio n like b(k, 0)  S2HK2(k, 0), while at 
small scales, or K  (SH)1, the inversion is approxima tely b(k, 0)  SK (k, 0). 
Thus the relation at the surface of streamfunction to advected quan tity (buoyancy) 
transitions from a 2D-like inversion at large scales, to an SQG- like inversion at small 
scales, with the transitio n occurring at the wavenumber 
f Kt  (SH)1 = . (12.30) NH 
The transitio n scale is the deformat ion radius. 
Tulloch and Smith (2006) have recently suggested that the transition between 2D 
and SQG spectral slopes in nite depth uids can be seen in measurements of at
mospheric spectra . The horizon tal spectra of atmospheric wind and temp erature at 
the tropopause have a steep 3 slope at synoptic scales, but transitio n to 5/3 at 
wavelengths of order 5001000 km. The basic idea is that temp erature perturbatio ns 
genera ted at the planeta ry scale excite a direct cascade of energy with a slope of 3 
at large scales, 5/3 at small scales and a transition near horizon tal wavenumber 
Kt = f/NH, where f is the Corio lis parameter. Ballpa rk atmospheric estimates 
for N, f and H give a transitio n wavenumber near the one observ ed. Numerical 
simulations also support the expected behavior. 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>More energy is transferred to large scales and more variance to small scales. In SQG 
the baricen ter of the energy remains at wavenumber K while the baricen ter of the 
buoyancy variance shifts to K(1 + 1.52). In the energy cascade to larger scale, the 
vertical scale can increase  the ow becomes more barotropic. 
12.4 Spectral transfer s 
A study of triad interactio ns illustr ates the dynamics behind the direct and inverse 
cascades of SQG turbulence. Let us transform the streamfunction to wavenumber 
space, 
 = (k,,t)exp(kx + y  Kz), (12.16) 
b =b(k,,t)exp(kx + y  Kz). (12.17) 
We introduce a shorthand j = (k,,t) so that each dieren t subscript j corresponds 
to a dierent set of {k,} values. The streamfunc tion is related to the buoyancy 
variance by, 
bj =(kj 2 + 2 
j )1/2j = Kj j . 
Now we can project out the equatio n for the amplitude of one mode by multiplying 
the equatio n by exp(ik2  x) and surface averaging, 
  
1 
 
3 . K2t2 = (k13  k31)K3
k1+k2+k3=0 
 Thes e equatio ns are identical to those obtained for the QG problem except for the 
replacemen t of K22 and K32 with K2 and K3 as a result of the dierent relatio nship 
between the two conserved quantities: energ y and enstro phy in QG, energy and 
buoyancy variance in SQG. Following the approa ch describ ed for the QG problem, 
the equatio ns can be rewritt en in the form, 
1  
1 K2t2 = (k12  k21)(K 1  K3)2 3 
with the denitio n k3 = k1  k2. 
Let us look at one triad of wavenumbers k1, k2, k3 and choose the labelling such that 
K1 &lt;K2 &lt;K3. The dyna mics of this triad is given by, 
K1t1 = (k12  k21)(K3  K2)
K2t2 = (k12  k21)(K1  K3)
K3t3 = (k12  k21)(K2  K1)
 (12.18)
3 

 1 
2 2 
 
3 (12.19)
 
1 (12.20)
This triad conserv es energ y and buoyancy variance internally , 
t Kj |j |2 = Ej =0 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>relevant limit is to retain vertica l dependenc e in  and q assuming that the top and 
bottom boundaries are homog eneous, i.e. b = 0. Char neys model has become the 
de-facto standard tool for QG studies of oceans and atmospheres. A less familiar 
special case is that of surface quasi-gesot rophic (SQG) ow, in which it is assume d 
that q = 0, so that the interior equatio n is identically satised, and the ow is driven 
entirely by the surfa ce b-distributio n. If the surfa ce is at, if N2 is a constan t, and if 
there is no upper boundary , then the resulting equations are, 
tb = J(,b), at z =0, (12.7) 
b  fz, (12.8) 
q  (xx + yy + zz)  = const, for z&gt; 0, (12.9) 
 0, (12.10)  as z . 
One can easily generalize to the case of q = q0 a non-zero constan t. For example, 
in the presence of a unifo rm horizontal shear, with the total ow describ ed by the 
streamfunctio n 1/2q0y2 + , one need only incorp orate advection by the mean ow, 
u = q0y, into the buoyancy equat ion. 
The QG and SQG equations are complemen tary descriptio n of stratied rotating 
ows. One can always divide the total ow at any instan t into a part induced by 
the surface b-distributio n and a part induced by the interior q-distribution . The 
QG appro xima tion has attracted more atten tion after the seminal work of Charney. 
However there are meteor ological and oceanographic problems for which the SQG 
approxima tion is thoug ht to be more appro priate. Examples are the evolution of 
temp eratu re anomalies at the tropopause (Juckes, JAS, 1994) and density anoma lies 
at the ocean surface (LaCasce and Mahadev an, JMR , 2006). 
12.1 2D turbul ence versus QG turbulence 
Some of the distinctions between SQG and 2D ows are immedia tely eviden t from 
the form of the equat ions. In two-dimensiona l ow, the streamfunctio n induced by 
a point vortex,  = (x), in an unbounded domain is (x)= (2)1In(|x  x|). 
In SQG, b = (x) results in the ow (x)= (2|x  x|)1 . The circumferen tial 
velocities around the vortex are proportional to r1 for 2D ow and r2 for SQG ow, 
r being the dista nce from the vortex centre. 
The more singula r SQG Greens functio n has several important consequences. Nearby 
point vortices rotate about each other more rapidly than in the twodimensiona l case; 
in consequence, a greater ambient strain is required to pull them apart, since the 
rapid rotation averages out the eects of the strain. Conversely , distan t eddie s are 
less tightly bound to each other than in two-dime nsional ow. Taken together, a 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>12.6 The Eady problem 
Introducing an environmen tal horizon tal buoyancy gradient in SQG, analogous to the 
-eect in two-dimens ional ow, results in, 
tb = J(,b +y), at z =0,H. (12.31) 
The constan t  can equiv alently be thoug ht of as due to a background vertical shear 
in the x-component of the ow, fuz = . As this contributes nothing to the interior 
potential vorticity, the interior equat ion is unaltered. This system now supports linear 
waves with the dispersion relation, 
 = k/K, (12.32) 
ei(kx+y t)where  =   . (This should be contrasted with the famil iar Rossby 
wave dispersion relation,  = k/K2.) These are edge waves that decay away from 
the surface as eKz . The interaction between two such waves, one at the surface and 
another at the tropopause, gives rise to baroclinic instabilit y in Eadys (1949) classic 
model of that process. 
In the Eady problem perturbatio ns develop as a result of a baroclinic insta bility 
of the basic state. the most unstable wavenumber (k,) = (2.4f/NH, 0) can be 
considered as the injection scale. One might therefore expect a 2D inverse cas
cade of energ y toward larger scales and an SQG direc t cascade of buoyancy vari
ance toward smaller scales. The corresp onding spectral slopes are expected to be, 
Variable Inverse cascade range Direct cascade range 
Buoyancy K5/3 K5/3 
Energy K5/3 K8/3 
The direct numerica l simulations shown in the webpag e do not seem to repro duce the 
transition between the direct and inverse cascade regimes. however more needs to be 
done to properly explo re the parameter space of the problem. 
Held et al. (1994) discuss in detail the properties of the direct and inverse cascades 
in Eady turbulence. In the direct cascade of buoyancy variance to small scales they 
show that strains genera tes lamen ts of high vorticit y. This vorticit y eld is of interest 
when one considers the geostr ophic momen tum (GM) equati ons (Hoskins 1975). In 
this extension of quasigeostro phic theor y, one approximat es the momentum by the 
momen tum of the geostr ophic ow, but advects it with the full, geostrophic plus 
ageostro phic, ow. It turns out that the GM equatio ns can be solved by transforming 
to geostrophic coordinates in which coordinate system the equations simply reduce to 
quasigeostro phy. Therefore, one can take a quasi-geostro phic solution, such as those 
shown in the webapge, and transform it into a solutio n of the GM equatio ns. The 
Jacobian of the transformat ion is essen tially 1/f, where  is the vorticity. When the 
Rossby number /f reaches unity, GM predicts the forma tion of a frontal singular ity. 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>greater tende ncy to form localized vortex assemblages is implie d. Since the ow dies 
away from a point vortex as r2 rather than r1 in SQG, the aggregat e eect of dista nt 
eddies on the local velocity eld is more limited. SQG is qualitativ ely characterize d 
by the preponderance of spatially local rather than long range interactions. 
In terms of spectral amplit udes, if  = keikx in two-dimensiona l ow, then 
 =  keikx with, 
(k,t)= |k|2(k,t). (12.11) 
Since the vertical structure of a sinusoida l disturbance in SQG theor y is e|k|z, the 
analogous relatio n is, 
b(k,t)= |k|(k,t). (12.12) 
In both models, the ow can be though t of as determ ined by a smoothing operator 
acting on the conserv ed scalar, but in SQG there is less smoothing . This implies that 
large-scale strain will play a relativ ely smaller role in the advection of small-s cale 
features in SQG, resulting in a cascade of variance to small scales that is more local 
in wavenumber. Held et al. (JFM, 1994) discuss the implicat ions of the locality of 
interactions for atmo spheric and oceanic ows. 
12.2 Conserv ed properties 
In the rst part of the lecture we conside r SQG ows with a rigid lower boundary 
and no upper boundary . These SQG equatio ns preserv e energy , 
1 1 z=0 1 E  2||2 + z 2 = 2 b  2q. 
where  denotes an average over the full 3D domain and the overbar a 2D average 
along the lower bounda ry. For zero potential vorticit y ows, the conserv ation of 
energy becomes, 
1 z=0 E =  b . 2 
Furthermor e the SQG equatio ns conserv e the buoyancy variance along the lower 
bounda ry, 
1 z=0 = b2
2 
Indee d, they conserv e the average of any function of buoyancy, not just the squar e, 
so that we have to worry about whether or not the energy and buoyancy variance tell 
the whole story. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>The implicatio n is that one can anticipate a ligree of microfrontal singularit ies in 
homo geneous turbulen t simulations of the geostro phic momen tum equat ions. The 
possibilit y that the quasi-geostrophic equations themselv es would also form such a 
pattern of discon tinuities has been raised by Constantin et al. (1994). But GM 
predicts that the ow will develop a singularit y well before the SQG equatio ns do. 
The main point is that SQG can be expected to reproduce well the eddy stirring of 
buoyancy at the bounda ries, but not neces sarily the nal frontal collapse. 
The inverse energ y cascade in SQG appears to have much in common with that in 
the two-dimensional case. held et al. (1994) show snapshots from the free evolution 
of an SQG ow with an initia l white noise temp erature eld. In the movie of Eady 
turbulence there is a transfer of energy toward larger scales during the spinup phase. 
Vortices form as the cascade proceeds, more or less as in two dimens ional ow (e.g. 
McWilliams 1984), and the evolution can be thoug ht of as the movemen t of the 
vortices in the ow eld induced by other vortices, with occasiona l intense encoun ters. 
There is considerable pairing of vortices and the sporadic format ion of larger groups, 
but we have not yet attempted to determine whether there is a greater tendency for 
the formatio n of assemblages than in two-dimensions, as suggested by the discussion 
at the beginning of this chapter. A qualita tive dierence hinted at by the movie is 
that vortex encoun ters are more violent than in two-dimensiona l ow: rather than 
merger accompanied by the format ion of relativ ely passiv e laments, encounters such 
as that seen on the left edge of the doma in are almost invariably accompanied by the 
forma tion of small satellite vortices, through the lamentary instabilit ies describ ed 
above. The forma tion of these satellite vortices should modify the evolution of the 
vortex size probabilit y distribut ion in important ways. 
Rhines (1975) has discusse d the way in which the inverse energ y cascade in two-
dimensional ow is halted by the presenc e of an environmen tal vorticity gradien t, the 
beta-e ect (see also Vallis and Malt rud 1992). In the two-dimens ional case, within the 
K5/3 inverse energy cascade range the characteristic inverse times cale, or advective 
frequency , of an eddy with wavenumber is, 
ad = K2E(K)dK  K2/3 
Compa ring with the Rossby wave dispersion relation, R = k/K2, one sees that 
wave dispersion will eventually domina te, except along the k = 0 axis. The transition 
is a fairly sharp one: R/ad  K5/3 for l = 0. In the SQG case, the surfa ce 
ow and buoyancy are predicted to have a K5/3 spectral shape as well. The edge 
wave frequency is E = k/K, giving the ratio E /ad  K2/3 . Thus, we still 
expect a transitio n between turbulen t and wavelike behaviour, but a more gradual 
one, with increa sing scale. Nume rical experimen ts in which the inverse energy cascade 
is arrested with an environmen tal temperature gradient have yet to be performed. 
Further reading 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>There is a remark able confusion in the literat ure on the appro priate denitio n of en
ergy for SQG ows. The discus sion hinges on a misunderstand ing about the dierence 
between surfa ce averaged energy , 
1 Es =2||2 + b2 
and volume averaged energy, 
E = 1
2||2 + b2. 
For a ow with a rigid lower lid, it is straightforward to prove, 
1 E(K)dKdz = Es(K)e2KzdKdz = K1Es(K)dK. 2 
the two spectra have dieren t units and, more importantly, dierent slopes. 
12.3 SQG turbulence 
Blume n (1978) has presented the Kolmo gorov-Kraichnan scaling argumen ts for the 
spectral shapes expected in the SQG turbulent inertia l ranges, and these have been 
compa red with numerica l simulations by Pierrehumbert, Held and Swanson (1994). 
The power spectra E(K) and (K) are dened so that, 
 
E = E(K)dK, = (K)dK (12.13) 
0 0 
with (K )= KE(K)= U(K), where U(K) is the power spectrum of the velocity 
eld. The spectra l uxes are dened by tE = K FE and t= K F. In 
equilibrium, both FE and F must be consta nt. 
The dimensions of FE /F are L. The fundamen tal tenet of the Kolmo gorov-Kraichnan 
scale analysis is that the only available length scale is the local eddy scale K1 . Since 
the uxes must be indep enden t of K, only one of FE and F can be nonzero. Nonzero 
FE yields the energ y cascading spectrum; since the dimensions of E are L2T 2 and 
the dime nsions of F are L3T 3, dime nsional analysis implies, 
E(K)= CE (FE )2/3K3 , (K)= C(FE )2/3K1 . (12.14) 
Following simila r reasoning , the spectrum in the variance cascading range is, 
E(K)= CE (F)2/3K8/3 , (K)= C(F)2/3K5/3 . (12.15) 
4</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Turbulent Boundary Layers (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch20/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>20.1.4 Inertial subla yer: logarithmic layer 
Thus far we have two dieren t laws for u+ . One applies close to the wall in the viscous 
subla yer and satises the no-slip condition u= 0. The other applie s further away 
from the wall and is not guaranteed to satisfy the no-slip bounda ry condition at the 
wall; actua lly it turns out that away from the wall u  u0 and thus u  u0 u0. 
This indic ates that a viscous subla yer with very steep gradien ts is required in order to 
satisfy the boundar y condit ions. Of course the velocity doesnt sudde nly jump from 
one scaling behavior to another -there is a transition region. In this transition region 
we expect both the law of the wall and the velocity defect law to apply . 
From eq. (20.10) we expect that, 
du+ df = . (20.15) dz+ dz+ 
From eq. (20.14) instead we have, 
du+ ddF dF = = , (20.16) dz+ dz+ d z+ d 
where we used the fact that  = z/ and z+ = zu/. In this overlap region these 
two expression must be equal so, 
df dF = , (20.17) dz+ z+ d 
and rearranging terms, 
df dF z + =  . (20.18) dz+ d 
The right hand side of eq. (20.18) depends only on  and the left hand side can 
depends only on z+ . This can only be true only if both sides are equal to a constant, 
df dF 1 z + =  = , (20.19) dz+ d 
where  is the Von Karman constan t. This implies that 
du u=  (20.20) dz z 
so that in this region the only important quantities are uand z. Then in this  
transition region, the inertial sublayer, the ow is unaware both of viscosit y and of 
the size of the boundary layer  -just as in the inertia l range isotropic homogeneo us 
3D turbulence is unaware of viscosity or of the integral scale of the forcing. 
Integrating eq.(20.19) we have, 
u 1 u= log z + C1, (20.21) u    
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>One can think of this as the mixed layer rubbing against the water underneath 
it. This largely has the eect of blurring the transitio n between the mixed layer and 
the seasona l thermo cline below, which would normally be rather sharp. Laboratory 
experimen ts indicate that there is a critica l gradient Richardson number, below which 
stirring occurs, 
zb Rg = zu2  0.25. (20.27) ||
This turns out to be a not very vigorous process, but becomes a little more important 
in the absence of any explicit turbulen t vertica l diusion. Notice that the gradien t 
Richardson number introduced by Price, Weller, and Pinkel diers from the one used 
in KPP in that it does not include any parameterizat ion for unresolved turbulen t 
shear. 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>In the viscous subla yer z&lt;zf , the velocity must depend on z, the distance from the 
wall, u, the frictio n velocity and , the viscosit y. We can write this relationship as, 
u zu= f  (20.9) u   
Note that u has been nondimens ionalized by u, and the dista nce z has been nondi
mensionalized by the frictio nal lengthscale /u. We can rewrite the relatio n in 
nondimensio nal form, 
u+ = f(z +) (20.10) 
where u+ = and z+ = zu/. u/u
Near a rough wall, the characteristic scale instead of being controlled by a frictional 
scale, it may be controlled by roughness length z0, if z0 &gt;zf , and the self-similar 
solutio n in eq. (20.10) must be interpreted with z+ = z/z0. 
20.1.3 Turbulen t boundary layer: velocity defect law 
Outside the viscou s subla yer, we can neglect viscosit y. Thus the only dimensional 
parameters that enter in the problem are the turbulen t velocity scale u, the total 
depth of the bounda ry layer , and the heigh t z away from the wall. We can express 
this dependence as, 
du u z =  g . (20.11) dz   
This relationship states that the mean velocity gradien t, du/dz , which is the recipro cal 
of a transv erse time scale for the mean ow, has to be of order u/ and varies on 
spatia l scales of order . Notice that we cannot make a simila r scaling argumen t for 
the mean velocity u and say that u= ug(z/), because the mean velocity depends 
on an addit ional externa l parameter, the velocity outside the bounda ry layer u0. We 
know that for z/ , we have u u0. 
We can now integrate from z =  in toward the boundary to obtain u, 
 du u z 
dz =  g dz, (20.12) 
z dz  z  
and hence,  z u(z)  u0 = uF , (20.13)  
or in nondimensiona l form, 
+ + u u0 = F (), (20.14) 
where  = z/. This is a similar ity solutio n for u+ , which assumes that as the 
bounda ry layer changes size, or for dieren t boundary layers u+ has the same form. 
This simila rity solutio n is only valid outside of the viscous bounda ry layer, and cannot 
satisfy the boundary condit ion u = 0 at the wall. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>20.1.1 Equations of motion 
We will assume a constant background ow u0, which is indep enden t of dista nce 
along the plate x and dista nce normal to the plate z. We assume 2-dimensiona l ow 
(/y = 0), and also assume that downstream evolution is slow. If L is a streamwise 
lengthscale, we are assuming /L &lt;&lt; 1, so that we can neglect variations in the 
stream wise direc tion compar ed to those in the vertical for averaged variables (i.e. 
/x = 0). Given these assumptio ns, the Reynold s averaged equations become, 
  du d du d w w dz = dz  dz  wu , dz = 0. (20.3) 
Because of the no normal ow throug h the boundary , we have w= w =0 at z = 0, 
the bottom boundar y. Then from eq. (20.3b) w=0forall z. Then eq. (20.3a) 
becomes,   d du
dz dz  wu =0. (20.4) 
Hence if we have a stress  given by, 
du du =  dz  wu = dz , (20.5) 
z=0 
this stress is constan t througho ut the bounda ry layer. Near the bounda ry the stress 
is dominated by the viscous term. Away from the boundary we will have, 
 = wu. (20.6) 
We can dene a velocity scale from this surface stress 
u 2 = , (20.7)  
where uis the friction velocity. Away from the boundary eq. (20.6) implies that  
u is the turbu lent velocity uctuat ion magn itude. 
20.1.2 Viscous sublayer: law of the wall 
The frictiona l length scale zf is the scale at which Re = 1, i.e. the scale at which 
the viscous and turbulen t stresses are of compa rable magnitude. Thus the frictional 
length scale can be dened as,  zf = . (20.8) u 
This lengthscale determines the transitio n between the inertial and viscous subla yers. 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>20.4	Convection 
Convection is the process by which vertical motio ns modify the buoyancy distribution 
in a uid. In the example considered above, the mixing of the upper ocean layer is 
caused by the mechanica l actio n of the wind stress , and convection is said to be 
forced. Free convection arises when the only source of energy is of thermo dyna mic 
origin, such as an imposed heat ux. A commo n occurrence of free convection in 
geophysical uids is the developmen t of an unsta ble atmospheric boundar y layer. 
Glenn showed that free convection occurs when the Rayleigh number Ra, 
bh3 
Ra =	 , (20.24) T 
excee ds a critical value, which depends on the nature of the boundar y conditio ns. For 
a uid conne d between two rigid plates and maintained at dieren t tempertures at 
the two plates, the critical Rayleigh number is Ra = 1708. At values slightly over the 
threshold, convection organizes itself in parallel two dime nsional rolls or in packed 
hexag onal cells. At higher values of the Rayleigh number, erratic time dependen t 
motions develop, and convection appears much less organized. 
Geoph ysical ows almost always fall in this last category, because of the large depths 
involved and the small values of molecular viscosit y and diusivit y of air and water. 
In the atmo spheric and oceanic boundar y layer, where the Rayleigh number easily ex
ceeds 1015, convection is manifes tly turbulen t and viscosit y/diusivit y play secondary 
roles. In this limit, the usntably-stratied part of the water column mixes to become 
essentially uniform. For xed buoyancy bounda ry conditio ns, thin layers develop near 
the bounda ries with thickness such that the local Rayleigh number is nearly critical. 
if the ux of buoyancy is xed, these layers do not occur and the buoyancy gradien t 
decreases to small values. 
20.5	Ocean Mixed Layer Models 
20.5.1	Bulk Mixed Layer Models: Price Weller and Pinkel 
Model 
Price, Weller, and Pinkel (PWP) proposed a simplied boundar y layer model for the 
upper ocean. The model is based on simple heuristic argumen ts and has proved quite 
accura te. The model adjusts the distributio ns of momen tum and tracer properties, 
and in doing that it sets the mixed layer depth. The interna l working s are rather 
simple. After adding the surface forcing, one applies three criteria for vertical sta
bility (i.e. whether water should mix vertica lly, and whether the mixed layer should 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>a viscous stress and a turbulent stress in a turbulen t bounda ry layer experimen t 
(Schubauer, J. Appl. Physics, 1954). The total stress parallel to the wall does not 
chang e with dista nce from the wall, but there is an exchange of balance between the 
viscous and turbulen t contributio ns. 
Further reading : Tritton, chapter 21, 336344 
To simplify the algebra let us consider a parallel irrotational ow over a at boundar y. 
Turbulence is generated because the no-slip condit ion u = 0 at the bounda ry means 
that a shear layer results, and vorticit y is introduced into the ow. Boundar y-layer 
ows are more complica ted than free shear ows, because the importance of viscosit y 
at the boundaries (whic h enf orces the no-slip conditio n) introduces a new spatia l scale 
in the problem. As a result there is a viscous sublayer next to the wall, whose width 
is set by viscou s forces, and a high Re bounda ry layer, whose thickness is controlled 
by the turbulen t Reyno lds stresses . These two layers are separ ated by an inertial sub-
layer. The three dieren t regio ns of the boundary layer are somewhat analogous to the 
viscous range, inertial range, and forcing ranges of isotropic, homog eneous turbulence . 
1. The viscous sublayer 
For distances close to the wall, i.e. z&lt;zf where zf is the dista nce at which Re = 1, 
friction is important. This can be compar ed to length scales l  1/k d in homo geneous 
turbulence, where viscosit y is important. 
2. The inertial sublayer 
At dista nces further away from the wall than zf , we can neglect viscosit y. Simila rly, 
if we are not close to the edge of the bounda ry layer at z = , we can assume that 
the ow will not depend directly on the size of the bounda ry layer. Therefore we 
have an inertia l subla yer for zf &lt;&lt; z &lt;&lt; . This region is similar to the inertia l 
range in homogeneo us turbulence , where the ow is not aected by  or by k0, the 
wavenumber of the energ y input . 
3. The turbulent boundary layer 
The full turbulen t boundar y layer is determined by the maximum size of the eddies , 
the so-called the integral scale . This region corresp onds to the forcing range of 3D 
turbulence. 
4. The ambient ow 
Finally at some dista nce z&gt;, the ow is no longer turbulen t and we are in the 
irrotational ambient ow. 
Further reading : Tennekes and Lumley , chapter 5, 147163. 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Chapter 20 
Boundar y layer turbulence 
Turbulence in the ocean and atmosphere is strongly aected by the presence of bound
aries. Boundar ies impose severe modications to the momen tum and buoyancy bud
gets. At solid bounda ries, the bounda ry conditio n that the uid velocity is zero 
applies to both the mean velocity and to the uctuatio ns. Thus the turbulen t uxes 
of momen tum must vanish. At the ocean free surface winds apply a stress that drives 
strongly turbulen t motions. Surface uxes of heat, salt and moistur e can generat e 
turbulen t convection as we have seen at the beginning of this class. Finally the combi
nation of surface stress es and uxes determines the full spectrum of turbulen t motio ns 
that can develop at the ocean and atmo sphere bounda ries. Before discus sing in detail 
the physics of planetary bounda ry layers in the ocean and atmosphere, it is useful to 
review some fundamen tal results that apply to bounda ry turbulence in genera l. 
20.1 Shear boundar y layers 
Let us consider shear-driv en turbulence at solid boundaries. At luid bounda ries, 
the condit ion that the uid velocity is zero applies at every insta nt in time. Thus it 
applies to the mean velocity and the uctuatio ns separa tely, 
u=0, u =0. (20.1) 
The fact that the uctuatio ns drop to zero at the wall has the particular implic ation 
that the Reynolds stress vanish, 
uiuj =0. (20.2) 
The only stress exerted directly on the wall is the viscous one. Away from the wall, 
instead, turbulence generates a Reynol ds stress typically large compa red to the viscous 
stress. Tritton (chapter 5, page 337) shows in Figur e 21.12 the transition between 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>and ,  u u0 = 1 log z + C2. (20.22) u    
The region where this applies (  1, z+  1) is known as the logarithmic layer. 
Near a rough boundar y, the equiv alent of 20.21 would be, 
u 1 z = log + C1,	 (20.23) u  z0  
with z0, the roughness length, taking the place of zf = /u, the frictio nal lengt hscale. 
Hinze (chapter 7, pag. 477) in gure 1.6.1 show the mean velocity distribution adi
ajent to a smooth wall, showing the logarithmic distribut ion away from the viscous 
regio n next to the wall and the linear regio n in the viscous sublayer from a comp osite 
of dierent laboratory experimen ts. 
The value of the Von Karman constan t has been measured in a variety of labora
tory ows that indicat e a universal value of 0.41. Some early measuremen ts in the 
atmosphere (Businger et al., 1971) suggested a much smaller value of 0.35, and this 
led to speculations for a while that the consta nt migh t not be universal, but instead 
a functio n of salient nondimensiona l numbers in the ow (for example the Rossb y 
number). Careful reexamina tion of the errors involved (Hogstro m, 1996) and more 
recen t observations (Zhang, 1988) indicate that the constant is indeed a consta nt with 
a value around 0.40  0.01. 
20.2	Shear turbul ence in stratied bounda ry lay
ers 
See Benoit Cushman-Roisin, section 11-1. 
20.3	Planetar y Boundary Layers 
The boundary layers in geophysical ows are also aected by rotation through the 
Corio lis force. This is discussed by Tennekes and Lumley , chapter 5.3. 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>deepen). After that, it applies advection and diusion (vertical advection and vertical 
diusion) to the water column. 
Static Stabi lity Criterion 
The rst stability criterion, and the one that proves the most important in the model, 
is static stability. In fact, it accounts for about 80% of the action . Quite simply 
put, one cannot have denser water overlying lighter water. This means that one must 
 have zb  0. Thus one goes through the model domain (let i be the positio n 
index, with i increasing downward), one tests to make sure that, 
bi  bi+1, (20.25) 
and where this is not the case, one then mixes all the cells above this depth (that is 
average them among themselv es). In general, what one should really do is to just mix 
the two cells together, then start from the top of the model and do it again. What 
happ ens in practice, however, is since all the heat exchange (in particular cooling, 
which decreases buoyancy) takes place at the top of the model, one always nds that 
the eect of this insta bility is to mix all the way back to the top. So one may as 
well do it the rst time. This scheme is equiv alent to the convective overturning 
scheme describ ed above, if one sets the diusivit y to inni ty whenev er there is static 
instabilit y. 
Bulk Richardson Num ber Stabi lity Criterion 
The second stabilit y criterion is the bulk Richardson Num ber stabilit y. This arises 
due to the fact that if the mixed layer gets going too fast (i.e. the wind stress is 
allowed to accele rate it to too great a speed), it tends to stumble over itself. What 
actua lly happ ens is that if there is too much velocity shear at the base of the mixed 
layer, it will tend to mix downward. This eect, determined by eld and laboratory 
experimen ts is such that the mixed layer deepens if the bulk Richardson number goes 
below a critical value, 
h b Rb = |u|2  0.65, (20.26) 
where h is the height (thickness) of the mixed layer, b is the buoyancy contrast 
between the mixed layer and the water below, and  uis the dierence in horizon tal 
velocity between the mixed layer and the underlying water. This eect tends to 
be important when the mixed layer becomes very thin, because a thin mixed layer 
becomes easily accelerated by wind stress , and the inverse quadra tic natur e of the 
dependence makes for a strong damping. The relativ e activit y of this process is about 
20% of the static instabilit y. 
Gradient Richardson Number Stability Criterion 
The third stability criterio n is based on the gradient Richardson number, and has 
the eect of stirring together layers where the velocity gradient becomes too great. 
8</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>2D Turbulence (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/12-820-turbulence-in-the-ocean-and-atmosphere-spring-2007/resources/ch6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>FR.EEMODES: 111terrr~s of the Green's fur~ctiorl 
we have -v=-An.gl(r,n) , li,~,,=Ao..~,,,g~,,(r,n) 
where ,rlT,, is the 7~~~ Fourier ~orr~por~er~t in angle 8. The kinerrlatic equation then gives 
This has solutions rlTl, -exp(ws(B -fit))with 
Using 
gives high rnodes being advected arltl low rnodes rr~ovir~g more slowly propagating against 
the flow because of the vorticity gradient 
Demos, Page 7: Vortex waves &lt;circular&gt; &lt;go&gt; &lt;n=2&gt; &lt;go&gt; &lt;n=3&gt; 
&lt;go&gt; &lt;n=4&gt; &lt;go&gt; &lt;n=8&gt; &lt;go&gt; 
SHEAR. FLOW: A background shear ir~troduces a forcing of the 71, = 2 rnode. If we 
therefore limit ourselves to this rr~ode; we have 
This has a steatly solution with the vortex elongated along the shear when the sense of 
rotation of the shear is the sarrle as the vortex or perpendicular when they have opposite 
rl2 = -rloa cos 28 = qoan, cos 284n 2A(n -1) 
In general '12 will oscillate around this value: depending on the initial condition. Kitla 
(1981) tlernonstrated tlvat an exact nonlinear solutior~ to the problerr~ is elliptical wit11 
the aspect ratio ant1 orientation cllarlgir~g with tirne. Demos, Page 7: Vortices in 
shear &lt;elliptical&gt; &lt;go&gt; &lt;strong shear&gt; &lt;go&gt; &lt;weak shear&gt; &lt;go&gt; 
&lt;balanced&gt; &lt;go&gt; &lt;adverse&gt; &lt;go&gt; &lt;adverse weak&gt; &lt;go&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Multiple power laws 
We now have two possil&gt;le power laws: the K41 law 
and the enstropl~y cascade law 
E N ,,/2/3k-3 
In the first case) the enstrophy transfer rate rrlust be zero since then r/ k2t which will .I 
not 1x3 independent of k un~less the coefficier~t is zero. Similarly: the energy cascade rate 
will be zero in the second case. 
Calculations of the transfer rates (c.f. Kraichnanl 1967) show that K41 gives upscale 
energy transfer while kp3 gives tlownscale enstropl~y transfer. We rnigl~t (consider using 
the forrr~er in the range k &lt; ki,j,,ti ,,,
and the latter for srr~aller scales k &gt; ki,,,j,,ti,,. 
Problems with the power law spectra 
The assumption in the sirr~ilarity rnodels is that the turn-over tirne at scale k depentls 
on the net shear/ strain at that scale 
For K41; this gives 
,qz N k4/3 -k4/30 
which is dominated by the cor~trihution near k -the transfers are local. The estirnate of 
strain corlverges as ko t0 and 60% is generated frorn k/2 to k. For the K3case: however, 
which diverges; intleed. the corltribution frorn k/8 to k/4 is the sarne as frorn k/4 to k/2 
and as that frorn k/2 to k. Thus the transfers are not local and the argunr~er~t is not 
consistent.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>TWOVORTICES: 
If two vortices are separated widely enough, we can ignore all but the monopole field 
of the secontl vortex in the vicinity of the first. In atldition, we look at the first vortex in 
a co-rotating frarne. In that case the 1)ackground strearnfur~ction field looks like 
The first terrn in the Taylor series assurrling R &gt;&gt; a is 
4 Aa4 go----"sin20 = --cos 20 2R2 4R2 
Thus the vortex is err~betlded in an opposing shear and car1 be elongated until it meets the 
other vortex. In linear theory, the l&gt;oundary tlisplacerr~en~t is Aa3/4R2C12 and crosses the 
centerline when r/ = R/2 -a; this gives a critical separation of 2.4 radii. In fact, rrlerger 
occurs for separations less tllar~ 3.3 radii. Demos, Page 8: Vortices in neighbor 
field &lt;R=4&gt; &lt;go&gt; &lt;R=3&gt; &lt;go&gt; &lt;R=3.5&gt; &lt;go&gt; &lt;R=4full&gt; &lt;R=3.5 
full&gt; &lt;R=3.45 full&gt; &lt;R=3.4 full&gt; &lt;R=3.3 full&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Vortex dynamics 
Onsager (19xx) realized that vortex dynarnics rr~igl~t indeed be a significar~t part of 
2-D turbulence. For the inviscitl problern, a poir~t vortex 
is a basic solution in the sense that the irlversion forrrlula from vorticity to strearnfunction 
irlvolves the Green's fur~ction G(x) = log(Ix)/2,rr 
To tlerive the forrrlula for G, we locate the origin at the vortex, use syrnrnetry to replace 
i aV2$ wit11 Tzr$$ and use the free solution away from r = 0. Irltegrating over a srrrall 
disk centered at r = 0 gives the constant in front. 
A single vortex tloes not atlvect itself: we can1 think of the nnotion of the poir~t as 
associatetl with the average velocity in a srnall tlisk centered at xo. This flow is protlucetl 
hy all the other vortices in the flow. Thus, if we have a set of vortices at positions xi,we 
have 
Kirchhoff (1876) realized that this could be written as a Harniltonian systerr~ 
3-F = {F,H}3t 
For a srrlall nurr11)er of vortices, this systerr~ is integrable: it has 4 conserved properties 
(energy, x arltl y cerlters of rnass, angular morner~tunn) vs. 2 ur~kr~owr~s per vortex. Wit11 
rnore than three vortices: however, the nnotions can becorne chaotic. 
Demos, Page 5: Point vortex simulations &lt;n=3&gt; &lt;delta solutions&gt; 
&lt;n=4&gt; &lt;delta&gt; &lt;single vortex trajectory&gt; &lt;long example&gt; 
Onsager(l941) considered the statistical properties of a rrlarly vortex systerr~ and pre- 
dicted clunrlpir~g of like-signet1 vortices would result, corresponding to a cascatle to larger 
scales.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The two-tlirnensional systern differs significarltly in its vorticity dynamics. Since u.i = 
0 and &amp;U = 0, the vorticity is purely vertical &lt; = Cz. The enstrophy production terrn 
hecornes 
C,iS,i,C, = c2s33= (Z -~ = W 0az 
In a 2D system, the energy and enstrophy will decay monotonically 
Since the enstroplly is bounded by its initial value, the energy dissipation rate will decrease 
in proportion to the viscosity; an energy cascade in the Kolnnogorov sense will not occur. 
However the terrr~ giving dissipation of enstropl~y will have a non-trivial generation 
term; this follows frorn the vorticity equation 
and examination of the tlissipation~ tern11 -vV(I2 If we let g = VC and G = ;VC2 the11 
If the corltours of vorticity are aligned with the axis of extension, the gradients will be 
aligned with the axis of cornpression and the vorticity lines will be pushed closer together, 
increasing the rrlean square gradient. Thus enstrophy (can cascade, since there is a source 
terrn for vorticity gratlierlts. 
These results suggest that we could derive a spectrurn frorn an enstrophy (cascade 
argurner~t: E(k) (ctlirnensio~~s L3/T2) sholild depend on k (Lpl) arid the rate of enstroplly 
dissipation TI = v(V,igi)' (which has tlirr~ensions Tp3). The result is 
with the enstropl~y spectrurn also decreasing at srnall scales Z(k)N kpl.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>2-D Turbulence 
One rnight think the two-tlirnensional problem rrligllt be a sirnpler, more tractable 
version of 3-D turbulence. However) the dynarnics turn out to be quite different. To see 
why this is the case, let's consider the vorticity dynarnics of each kirld of flow. Frorn the 
Navier-Stokes equations for a homogeneous fluid 
we can derive the vorticity equation 
and the energy equatiorl 
wit11 E = iu. u 1)eing the energy and Z = +&lt;.&lt; being the enstrophy. Tur1)ulence in the 
presence of boundaries can flux energy through the walls. hut for homogeneous turbulence 
the flux terrn rrlust on the average vanish and the dissipation is just 2vZ. Dissipation 
and energy cascades are closely tied to the rotational nature of a turbulent 
flow. 
In the classic picture, we force the energy at a certain rate; which is then balanced 
off by dissipation. But the spectrurn depends only on the forcing rate and k: not upon 
viscosity. For this to hold, the enstropl~y rrrlust grow as the viscosity decreases. This is 
consistent wit11 the Kolrnogorov s1)ectrurn: if E(k) N kp5/3: Z(k) -k2E(k) N k1l3. As 
the viscosity decreases ant1 we excite smaller and srrlaller scales) the enstropl~y will becorne 
larger and larger to cornpensate. 
The enstropl~y equation intleed has suitable source terrns: 
1
where SiJ= ?[Viuj+Vjui]is the rate of strain tensor. Therefore, if the vorticity vector 
is on average aligned wit11 the directions where the strain is causing extension rather 
than corltraction; the enstrophy will increase. In a 3-D turbulent flow, the vorticity is 
irltleed on average undergoing stretching since this term entls up balancing the sign-definite 
dissipation terrns.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>2D simulations 
What does 2-D turbulence look like? We show results frorn a 512x512 2-D pseu- 
dospectral code solvir~g the vorticity equatior~ and the inversion of vorticity to fir~tl the 
strearnfunction. 
3-C + J($, C) = filter at 
Demos, Page 2: 2D &lt;psi&gt; &lt;zeta&gt; Demos, Page 2: Statistics &lt;spectra&gt; 
&lt;pdf of zeta&gt; Demos, Page 2: Averages &lt;E and Z&gt; &lt;variance and 
kurtosis&gt; The strearnfunction shows a marked increase in scale -the so-called "irlverse 
cascade" while the vorticity collects ir~tto strong isolated vortices with filamentary structure 
in between. The PDF and the kurtosis of the vorticity field shows the non-Gaussian nature 
of the flow quite clearly. 
Inverse cascade 
We car1 quan~tify the irlverse cascade using an argurner~t of Peter Rhines: consider the 
average scale, defined as 
We note tlvat E = JE(k) ant1 Z = Jk2E(k) are conservetl in irlviscid rnotion. If we 
presume the energy is initially near ko and is spreading then 
Therefore 
As the energy spreatls in the spectrurn its rnean scale increases. Demos, Page 3: mean 
k &lt;kbar vs time&gt;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Vortex dynamics 
To urlderstarld the rnerger process, let us consitler the irlviscid tlynarrlics of a single 
vortex ernbedded in a shear or strain field. We car1 represent the vorticity as 
qo else (={qO+A 
and the flow as 1 
?i, = -qoy2 + li,' 2 
The points on the 1)oundary of D are material poirlts since they separate fluid with tlifferer~t 
vorticities. Furthermore, the velocities can be written as a line integral around the patch 
hountlary 
Thus the evolution of the vorticity contours can be posetl as a tlyrlarr~ical systern (in fact 
a Harniltonian one). We'll analyze linearizetl versior~s but show fully r~onlirlear examples. 
Perturbed circular vortex 
We slvall consider a vortex patch 
( = t) - qo + A.tl(o, + ~(0, r) 
(where 'U is the step function) and define the circular state 
13 3 1v2$= qo + A.tl(o. -r) + --r-v- -?i = A6(a -r)r 3r 3r r2 
wit11 li, = iqoy2+ + $I. The perturbation strearr~functio~~ satisfies 
02?i,li,'A [%(a+ rl -r) -'U(a -r)] -. A$(a -r) = 
and the condition tlvat the edge be a material surface is</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
