<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-177-universal-random-structures-in-2d-fall-2015/</course_url>
    <course_title>Universal Random Structures in 2D</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Mathematics </list>
      <list>Probability and Statistics </list>
      <list>Topology and Geometry </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>courses/18-177-universal-random-structures-in-2d-fall-2015/resources/mit18_177f15_lecnotes</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-177-universal-random-structures-in-2d-fall-2015/resources/mit18_177f15_lecnotes/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>0</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>13</slideno>
          <text>7.2 Interior ow lines
 
It is similarly possible to make sense of ow lines of eih(z)/ starting from interior points 
of a planar domain. 
7.3 Counterow lines and space-lling SLE 
The tree and dual tree of ow lines have an interface that can be described as a 
space-lling curve. 
7.4 Time reversal symmetries 
Imaginary geometry can be used to prove several basic facts about SLE, including time 
reversal symmetry for several forms of SLE with &lt; 4 and SLE! with ' &gt; 4. 
8 Conformal welding and the quantum zipper 
8.1 Welding simple quantum wedges 
One can conformally weld two quantum wedges to each other to obtain a new thicker 
quantum wedge. The rst version of this story (which applies to two wedges of a 
particular thickness) was described in [She10] 
8.2 Welding more general quantum wedges 
Additional welding constructions are described in [DMS14 ]. These allow one to weld 
together two wedges of weights W1 and W2 to produce a new wedge of weight W1 + W2. 
One can also weld the left and right sides of a single quantum wedge to each other, to 
produce a quantum cone. 
9 Mating trees and the peanosphere 
9.1 Moores theorem and topological tree mating 
There is a simple way to see that gluing two continuum random trees produces a 
topological sphere decorated by a space-lling path [DMS14]. 
14</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>where Bt is standard Brownian motion and  is a xed real constant. The interesting 
question is how to extend this denition beyond times at which Xt reaches zero. One 
approach is to have the process jump up by f each time it hits 0, and take a limit as 
f  0. Another is to dene the square of the process Bessel process (which turns out to 
t more neatly into the framework of some general theorems in SDE theory, and allows 
us to show that the process is adapted to the Brownian motion). A simple application 
of It os formula allows us to check which power of Xt (depending on ) is a martingale, 
and also to prove that summing independnet 1 and 2 Bessel processes produces a 
1 + 2 Bessel process. 
1.3 Brownian excursions, meanders, and bridges 
One may dene a Brownian excursion indexed by [0, 1] by conditioning a Brownian 
motion, started at f, to end in [0,f], and then taking the f  0 limit. Brownian motion 
conditioned to stay in a cone (starting from the apex) is explained in [Shi85 ] along with 
the relationship to Bessel processes. 
1.4 Stable L evy processes 
We recall Lampertis classic work on continuous state branching processes [Lam67 ] and 
textbooks on L evy processes by Sato, by Bertoin and by Barndo-Nielson, Mikosch, 
and Resnick [Sat99, Ber96, BNMR01] 
1.5 Ranges of stable subordinators 
The range of a stable subordinator is a random closed subset of R+. it can be understood 
as the zero set of a Bessel process. If we condition the endpoints of the Bessel process to 
be zero at 1, we can also dene a random closed subset of [0, 1]. These random sets can 
be characterized by renewal and scale invariance properties, which are similar to the 
properties we will later use to characterize conformal loop ensembles (the complement 
of the union of the interiors of these loops will turn out to be a random subset of R2). 
2 Random trees 
2.1 Galton-Watson trees 
Galton-Watson trees and their scaling limits are described by Duquesne and Le Gall 
in [DLG05 ]. See also [LGLJ98 , DLG06 , DLG09 ]. One of the interesting features of 
6</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>16</slideno>
          <text>[BN11] N Berestycki and JR Norris. Lectures on schrammloewner evolution. 2011. 
[BNMR01] Ole E. Barndor-Nielsen, Thomas Mikosch, and Sidney I. Resnick, editors. 
L evy processes. Birkh auser Boston Inc., Boston, MA, 2001. Theory and 
applications. 
[Car06] J. Cardy. Lectures on Stochastic Loewner Evolution and other growth 
processes in two dimensions, March 2006. 
[CK13] N. Curien and I. Kortchemski. Random stable looptrees. ArXiv e-prints, 
April 2013. 
[CL12] N. Curien and J.-F. Le Gall. The Brownian plane. ArXiv e-prints, April 
2012. 
[Cor12] Ivan Corwin. The Kardar-Parisi-Zhang equation and universality class. 
Random Matrices Theory Appl., 1(1):1130001, 76, 2012. 1106.1596. 
[CQ11] I. Corwin and J. Quastel. Renormalization xed point of the KPZ univer
sality class. ArXiv e-prints, March 2011. 
[CS] D. Chelkak and S. Smirnov. Universality in the 2D Ising model and 
conformal invariance of fermionic observables. Invent. Math. 
[CV81] Robert Cori and Bernard Vauquelin. Planar maps are well labeled trees. 
Canad. J. Math., 33(5):10231042, 1981. 
[DFMS97] Philippe Di Francesco, Pierre Mathieu, and David S en echal. Conformal 
eld theory . Graduate Texts in Contemporary Physics. Springer-Verlag, 
New York, 1997. 
[DLG05] Thomas Duquesne and Jean-Fran cois Le Gall. Probabilistic and fractal 
aspects of L evy trees. Probab. Theory Related Fields, 131(4):553603, 2005. 
[DLG06] Thomas Duquesne and Jean-Fran cois Le Gall. The Hausdor measure of 
stable trees. ALEA Lat. Am. J. Probab. Math. Stat., 1:393415, 2006. 
[DLG09] Thomas Duquesne and Jean-Fran cois Le Gall. On the re-rooting invariance 
property of L evy trees. Electron. Commun. Probab., 14:317326, 2009. 
[DMS14] B. Duplantier, J. Miller, and S. Sheeld. Liouville quantum gravity as a 
mating of trees. ArXiv e-prints, September 2014. 
[DRSV14a]	 Bertrand Duplantier, R emi Rhodes, Scott Sheeld, and Vincent Vargas. 
Critical gaussian multiplicative chaos: Convergence of the derivative mar
tingale. The Annals of Probability, 42(5):17691808, 09 2014. 
17</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>21</slideno>
          <text>[Pol81] A. M. Polyakov. Quantum geometry of bosonic strings. Phys. Lett. B, 
103(3):207210, 1981. 
[Pol08] A. M. Polyakov. From Quarks to Strings. ArXiv e-prints , November 2008. 
[PW98] James Gary Propp and David Bruce Wilson. How to get a perfectly random 
sample from a generic markov chain and generate a random spanning tree 
of a directed graph. Journal of Algorithms , 27(2):170217, 1998. 
[RV08] R. Rhodes and V. Vargas. KPZ formula for log-innitely divisible multi-
fractal random measures. ArXiv e-prints:0807.1036, 2008. To appear in 
ESAIM P&amp;S. 
[RV14] R emi Rhodes and Vincent Vargas. Gaussian multiplicative chaos and 
applications: a review. Probab. Surv., 11:315392, 2014. 1305.6221. 
[RY99] Daniel Revuz and Marc Yor. Continuous martingales and Brownian motion, 
volume 293 of Grundlehren der Mathematischen Wissenschaften [Funda
mental Principles of Mathematical Sciences]. Springer-Verlag, Berlin, third 
edition, 1999. 
[Sat99] Ken-iti Sato. L evy processes and innitely divisible distributions, volume 68 
of Cambridge Studies in Advanced Mathematics. Cambridge University 
Press, Cambridge, 1999. Translated from the 1990 Japanese original, 
Revised by the author. 
[Sch99] Gilles Schaeer. Random sampling of large planar maps and convex 
polyhedra. In Annual ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (Atlanta, 
GA, 1999), pages 760769 (electronic). ACM, New York, 1999. 
[Sch00] Oded Schramm. Scaling limits of loop-erased random walks and uniform 
spanning trees. Israel J. Math. , 118:221288, 2000. math/9904022. 
[She07] Scott Sheeld. Gaussian free elds for mathematicians. Probab. Theory 
Related Fields , 139(3-4):521541, 2007. math/0312099. 
[She09] Scott Sheeld. Exploration trees and conformal loop ensembles. 
Math. J., 147(1):79129, 2009. math/0609167. Duke 
[She10] S. Sheeld. Conformal weldings of random surfaces: SLE and the quantum 
gravity zipper. ArXiv e-prints, December 2010. 
[She11] S. Sheeld. Quantum gravity and inventory accumulation. ArXiv e-prints, 
August 2011. 
[Shi85] Michio Shimura. Excursions in a cone for two-dimensional Brownian motion. 
J. Math. Kyoto Univ., 25(3):433443, 1985. 
22</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>induce a topology on the Schwartz space; continuous linear functionals on the Schwartz 
space are called tempered distributions. The space of tempered distributions is the 
smallest space which includes the bounded continuous functions and is closed under 
both dierentiation and the Fourier transform. 
In the exposition on Gaussian free elds, we will often nd it convenient to limit attention 
to compactly supported test functions (instead of test functions in the Schwartz space) 
as this will allow us to more easily isolate the eects of boundary conditions. 
3.2 Gaussian free elds 
Gaussian Hilbert spaces are introduced in [Jan97 ]. Surveys of the Gaussian free eld 
can be found in [She07, Ber]. 
3.3 Fractional Gaussian elds and log correlated free elds 
The GFF can be generalized in several ways. See the survey articles [DRSV14b , 
LSSW14 ] for more on fractional Gaussian elds and log correlated Gaussian elds in 
general d-dimensional spaces. These are obtained by applying powers of the Laplacian 
to white noise. The Gaussian free eld can be understood as the restriction to two 
dimensions of log correlated elds dened in higher dimensions. 
3.4 Dimer models and uniform spanning trees 
The UST height function is arguably the simplest discrete analog of the GFF. See 
Kenyons scaling limit proof [Ken00b , Ken01 ], which makes use of the equivalent 
formulation of the model in terms of dimers. 
4 Random curves and loop ensembles 
4.1 Schramm-Loewner evolution: basic denitions and phases 
Much of the work on Schramm-Loewner evolution is pregured in the physics literature 
on conformal eld theory [DFMS97 ]. Schramms original paper [Sch00 ] has been followed 
by many excellent survey articles and textbooks [Wer03 , KN04 , Car06 , Law09 , BN11 ]. 
The so-called natural parameterization is described in [LS11, LR12, LZ13]. 
8</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>11</slideno>
          <text>5.9	 KPZ (Knizhnik-Polyakov-Zamolodchikov) scaling relations 
A relationship between scaling dimensions was discovered by Knizhnik, Polyakov, and 
Zamolodchikov in [KPZ88 ]. In a recent memoir [Pol08 ] Polyakov explains how the 
discover of this relationship cemented the belief that the discrete planar map models 
were (in some sense) equivalent to Liouville quantum gravity. See [DS11 ] and the 
references therein. See the Hausdor variant in [RV08]. 
See the derivation of the d = 26 value for the bosonic string by Lovelace in 1971 in 
[Lov71]. 
5.10 Quantum wedges, cones, spheres and disks 
There are natural ways to dene quantum surfaces using Bessel process excursions. 
There are some natural probability measures on the space of innite volume surfaces. 
There are also some natural innite measures on the space of nite volume surfaces. 
See the introduction to [DMS14]. 
6 Random growth trajectories 
6.1	 Eden model and rst passage percolation 
There are a number of natural growth trajectories. The Eden model, introduced by 
Edein in 1961 [Ede61 ], is the simplest to describe. Here, every edge has an exponential 
clock, and when it rings the edge is added to the growing edge cluster (if it is incident 
to the existing cluster). A generalization of this story known as rst-passage percolation 
was introduced by Hammersley and Welsh in 1965 [HW65]. 
6.2	 Diusion limited aggregation and the dieelectric break
down model 
Diusion limited aggregation, as introduced by Witten and Sander in 1981 [WJS81 , 
WS83 ], is a model for growth in which new particle locations on the boundary are 
chosen from harmonic measure instead of uniform measure. See early conjectures in 
[Mea86] and the theorem of Kesten [Kes87]. 
12</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>14</slideno>
          <text>9.2 Matings from complex dynamics
 
The idea of topologically mating Julia sets is given an overview in [Mil04 , Mil06 ] and 
the references therein. 
9.3 Matings of correlated continuum random trees 
The peanosphere theorem is proved in [DMS14]. 
9.4 Matings of trees of disks 
The tree of disk analog of the peanosphere theorem is also proved in [DMS14]. 
9.5 Relation to discrete bijections 
The tree mating construction has discrete analogs in the planar maps decorated by FK 
models, uniform spanning trees, and bipolar orientations, as detailed in the various 
bijections described in Section 5. 
10 Quantum Loewner evolution 
10.1 Reshuing in discrete examples 
Discrete and continuum analogs of the quantum Loewner evolution are introduced in 
[MS13b]. We begin with an account of the discrete models. 
The recurrence of random walk on the innite tree decorated map is a special case of 
the result in [GGN13]. 
DLA and the Eden model (and more generally DBM) can be dened on random planar 
maps. They are related, respectively, to loop erased random walk and a Bernoulli 
percolation interface via a certain reshuing construction. 
In the case of the Eden model, some relevant work on exploring triangulations by Angel 
and Schramm appears in [Ang03, AS03] 
10.2 Dening QLE 
This reshuing has a continuum analog that can be shown to converge (at least 
subsequentially) [MS13b]. 
15</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Preface 
The goals of this book are very simple. We will 
1. introduce a few fundamental random objects, and 
2. explain how they are related to one another. 
The fundamental random objects include processes, trees, distributions (a.k.a. general
ized functions), curves, loop ensembles, surfaces, and growth trajectories. 
All of these objects are in some sense universal. That is, they arise as macrosopic limits 
of many dierent kinds of random systems, which may have very dierent microscopic 
behavior. This usage of the term universal comes from statistical physics. Physicists 
tell us that many phenomena (such as phase transitions) are surprisingly similar from 
one material to another. Physical systems  and mathematical models  that look 
very dierent on the microscopic level (dierent atoms, molecules, etc.) are declared to 
belong the same universality class if they behave the same way in some macroscopic 
limit. The convergence of general random walks to Brownian motion (under only a 
mild second moment condition) is an example of mathematical universality. We will 
encounter many other examples during the course of this book, some proven and some 
conjectural. 
The random objects introduced in this book are also all in some sense canonical. 
Many fundamental objects in mathematics are singled out by special symmetries. For 
example, in a universe full of roughly round-ish shapes, the sphere stands out; it is 
uniquely determined by rotational invariance, equidistance of points from a center, 
etc. Similarly, among all random variables taking values in the space of continuous 
paths, Brownian motion is (up to multiplicative constant) the only one with reection 
invariance, stationarity, and independence of increments. It has a strong claim to be 
the canonical continuous random path. This book will survey objects that can claim 
with equal justication to be the canonical random planar tree, the canonical random 
non-self-crossing curve, the canonical random surface, and so forth. 
Among the various symmetries that make these objects special, many involve some 
sort of conformal invariance . Recall that the Riemann uniformization theorem implies 
the existence of a conformal map between any two sphere-homeomorphic surfaces; 
when the sphere is replaced by a multi-handled torus or a disk with holes, the space 
of conformal equivalence classes (a.k.a. the moduli space) remains nite dimensional. 
This remarkable fact is a peculiar feature of two dimensions and seems to be a large 
part of what makes the two dimensional theory interesting. In the 1980s and 1990s a 
branch of physics called conformal eld theory , motivated by both string theory and 
two dimensional statistical mechanics, began to discover and explore some surprisingly 
far reaching consequences of conformal symmetry assumptions in physical models. 
4</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>20</slideno>
          <text>[Mil04] John Milnor. Pasting together Julia sets: a worked out example of mating. 
Experiment. Math., 13(1):5592, 2004. 
[Mil06] John Milnor. Dynamics in one complex variable, volume 160 of Annals 
of Mathematics Studies. Princeton University Press, Princeton, NJ, third 
edition, 2006. 
[Mil10] J. Miller. Universality for SLE(4). ArXiv e-prints, October 2010. 
[MM06] Jean-Fran cois Marckert and Abdelkader Mokkadem. Limit of normalized 
quadrangulations: the Brownian map. Ann. Probab., 34(6):21442202, 
2006. 
[MP10] Peter M orters and Yuval Peres. Brownian motion. Cambridge Series in 
Statistical and Probabilistic Mathematics. Cambridge University Press, 
Cambridge, 2010. With an appendix by Oded Schramm and Wendelin 
Werner. 
[MS12a] J. Miller and S. Sheeld. Imaginary Geometry I: Interacting SLEs. ArXiv 
e-prints, January 2012. 
[MS12b] J. Miller and S. Sheeld. Imaginary geometry II: reversibility 
SLE(1; 2) for   (0, 4). ArXiv e-prints, January 2012. of 
[MS12c] J. Miller and S. Sheeld. Imaginary geometry III: reversibility of SLE for 
  (4, 8). ArXiv e-prints, January 2012. 
[MS13a] J. Miller and S. Sheeld. Imaginary geometry IV: interior rays, whole-plane 
reversibility, and space-lling trees. ArXiv e-prints, February 2013. 
[MS13b] J. Miller and S. Sheeld. Quantum Loewner Evolution. ArXiv e-prints, 
December 2013. 
[MS15a] J. Miller and S. Sheeld. An axiomatic characterization of the Brownian 
map. ArXiv e-prints, June 2015. 
[MS15b] J. Miller and S. Sheeld. Liouville quantum gravity and the Brownian 
map I: The QLE(8/3,0) metric. ArXiv e-prints, July 2015. 
[MS15c] Jason Miller and Scott Sheeld. Liouville quantum gravity and the Brown
ian map II: geodesics and continuity of the embedding. 2015. In preparation. 
[MS15d] Jason Miller and Scott Sheeld. Liouville quantum gravity and the Brow
nian map III: the conformal structure is determined. 2015. In preparation. 
[Mul67] R. C. Mullin. On the enumeration of tree-rooted maps. Canad. J. Math., 
19:174183, 1967. 
21</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>12</slideno>
          <text>6.3 KPZ (Kardar-Parisi-Zhang) growth
 
The KPZ growth model is the logarithm of the stochastic heat equation with geometric 
noise. It was introduced in a slightly dierent form, and without a rigorous construction, 
Karder, Parisi, and Zhang in [KPZ86 ]. It does not itself describe the conjectural scaling 
limit of Eden model uctuations; rather, it describes what amounts to a sort of o 
critical variant, which is believed to converge to a xed point as a certain parameter 
tends to zero. These models can be viewed as interesting in their right, or interesting 
as approximations to the (still conjectural) KPZ xed point, which is in turn the 
conjectural scaling limit of Eden model uctuations. The xed point conjecture is 
described by Corwin and Quastel in [CQ11]. See also Corwins survey article [Cor12]. 
6.4 Hastings-Levitov 
The Hastings-Levitov model was designed as an approximation of what should be 
a continuum DLA theory. The hope was that one could prove the existence of an 
isotropic scaling limits of this model, and that would be easier than establishing the 
analogous result for (an isotropic form of) ordinary DLA. While this goal has not yet 
been achieved, there has been some recent progress in understanding Hastings-Levitov; 
see, e.g., [JVST12]. 
6.5 Internal DLA 
Internal DLA is a growth model introduced by Meakin and Deuthch in 1986 [MD86 ]. 
Internal DLA growth seems to be much smoother than Eden model, with logarithmic 
uctuations [LBG92 , JLS12 , JLS13 , AG13b , AG13a ]. Unlike ordinary (external) DLA 
and most of the other growth models presented in this section, uctuations of internal 
DLA on the grid have a well understood scaling limit, which can be described by a 
variant of the Gaussian free eld [JLS+14]. 
7 Imaginary geometry 
7.1 Flow lines starting from the boundary 
The results in this section are detailed in a series of imaginary geometry papers by the 
current authors [MS12a , MS12b , MS12c , MS13a ]. The idea is to try to dene ow lines 
of eih(z)/ where &gt; 0 is a xed parameter and h is an instance of the Gaussian free 
eld. We begin by discussing paths that originate at the boundary, and are related to 
forms of chordal SLE. 
13</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>19</slideno>
          <text>[LG14] J.-F. Le Gall. The Brownian map: a universal limit for random planar 
maps. In XVIIth International Congress on Mathematical Physics, pages 
420428. World Sci. Publ., Hackensack, NJ, 2014. 
[LGLJ98] Jean-Francois Le Gall and Yves Le Jan. Branching processes in L evy 
processes: the exploration process. Ann. Probab., 26(1):213252, 1998. 
[LGM+12] Jean-Fran cois Le Gall, Gr egory Miermont, et al. Scaling limits of random 
trees and planar maps. Probability and statistical physics in two and more 
dimensions, 15:155211, 2012. 
[Lov71] C Lovelace. Pomeron form factors and dual regge cuts. Physics Letters B, 
34(6):500506, 1971. 
[LR12] G. F. Lawler and M. A. Rezaei. Minkowski content and natural parame
terization for the Schramm-Loewner evolution. ArXiv e-prints, November 
2012. 
[LS11] Gregory F. Lawler and Scott Sheeld. A natural parametrization for 
the Schramm-Loewner evolution. Ann. Probab., 39(5):18961937, 2011. 
0906.3804. 
[LSSW14] Asad Lodhia, Scott Sheeld, Xin Sun, and Samuel S Watson. Fractional 
gaussian elds: a survey. arXiv preprint arXiv:1407.5598, 2014. 
[LSW03] Gregory Lawler, Oded Schramm, and Wendelin Werner. Conformal restric
tion: the chordal case. J. Amer. Math. Soc., 16(4):917955 (electronic), 
2003. math/0209343. 
[LSW04] Gregory F. Lawler, Oded Schramm, and Wendelin Werner. Conformal 
invariance of planar loop-erased random walks and uniform spanning trees. 
Ann. Probab., 32(1B):939995, 2004. math/0112234. 
[LZ13] Gregory F. Lawler and Wang Zhou. SLE curves and natural parametrization. 
Ann. Probab., 41(3A):15561584, 2013. 1006.4936. 
[MD86] Paul Meakin and JM Deutch. The formation of surfaces by diusion limited 
annihilation. The Journal of chemical physics, 85:2320, 1986. 
[Mea86] Paul Meakin. Universality, nonuniversality, and the eects of anisotropy 
on diusion-limited aggregation. Physical Review A, 33(5):3371, 1986. 
[Mer94] Russell Merris. Laplacian matrices of graphs: a survey. Linear algebra and 
its applications, 197:143176, 1994. 
[Mie13] Gr egory Miermont. The Brownian map is the scaling limit of uniform 
random plane quadrangulations. Acta Math., 210(2):319401, 2013. 
20</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>23</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
18.177 Universal Random Structures in 2D
Fall 2015
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>9</slideno>
          <text>5 Random surfaces 
5.1 Planar maps 
A planar map is a planar map together with an embedding in the plane (dened 
up to topological equivalence). Enumeration work was done by Tutte in the 1960s 
[Tut62, Tut68]. 
5.2 Decorated surfaces and Laplacian determinants 
The Laplacian determinant and its inverse are related to partition functions for the 
GFF and UST models in surprisingly simple ways. See Kenyons work on scaling limits 
of determinant Laplacians on grids [Ken00a ] and the broad survey by Merris [Mer94 ] 
which describes Kirchhos matrix tree theorem, among other things. 
Given any nite connected graph (V, E) the Laplacian on the graph can be dened as 
a linear operator  from RV itself. Its matrix is given by 
Mi,j =
  
 

 1 i= j, (vi,vj )  E 
0 i= j, (vi,vj )  E .
 
deg(vi) i = j. 
Let R  RV be the set of functions with mean zero. Then  : R  R is invertible, 
and Kirchhos matrix tree theorem states that if  is the determinant of this invertible 
operator on R then  is the number of spanning trees of V . The quantity  is also the 
product of all of the non-zero eigenvalues of the matrix M. 
 
 The DGFF partition function can be be written
tx2/2dt = t1/2, we nd that quantity is R(2)|V 1|/2e(f,f )/2df. Expanding
 
1over eigenbases, and using the fact the e2
1/2 . 
5.3 Mullin-Bernardi bijection 
There is a very simple bijection between discrete lattice walks in Z2 starting and ending + 
at zero and rooted planar maps with distinguished spanning trees. See [Mul67 , Ber07 ] 
as well as the exposition in [She11]. 
5.4 Cori-Vaquelin-Schaeer bijection 
The Cori-Vaquelin-Schaeer bijection gives a way to bijectively count undecorated planar 
maps [CV81 , JS98, Sch99 ]. Every quadrangulation with a root can be decorated by a 
10</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Mathematicians have more recently expanded these ideas further, building in particular 
on the introduction of the so-called Schramm-Loewner evolution in 1999. 
The focus of this text is on the mathematics, and in particular on a few of the most 
fundamental discrete and continuum mathematical objects in one and two dimensions. 
However we will provide some cursory discussion of the motivating problems that link 
them to physics and to other elds. 
The rst half of this book introduces both discrete and continuum analogs of several uni
versal random objects: processes, trees, distributions, curves, loop ensembles, surfaces, 
and growth trajectories. The second half explores the intricate and often surprising 
relationships between these objects. To put this another way, the rst half of the book 
introduces a certain cast of characters, and the second half explores the drama that 
takes place when these characters interact. 
This book is intended as a broad introductory overview of this eld and as such it 
covers a good deal of material. With additional detail, each individual chapter could be 
(and in many cases already has been) expanded into an entire book of its own. We do 
not provide fully detailed proofs of every result cited in this text. However, we aim to 
provide enough rigor and detail to enable the reader to appreciate the overall narrative 
and to begin further research in this eld. 
Acknowledgments. J.M.s work was partially supported by DMS-1204894 and S.S.s 
work was partially supported by DMS-1209044, a fellowship from the Simons Foundation, 
and EPSRC grants EP/L018896/1 and EP/I03372X/1. S.S. presented this material 
as a graduate topics course at MIT in Fall 2015 and would like to thank the students 
there for feedback and support. 
1 Random processes 
1.1 Brownian motion 
We recall the basic construction, It os formula, martingale representation theorem, local 
martingales, and quadratic variation. More detailed accounts of this material can be 
found in basic probability texts like [Dur10 ], the book on Brownian motion by Morters 
and Peres [MP10], and the stochastic calculus texts [KS91, RY99]. 
1.2 Bessel processes 
An introduction to Bessel process can be founded for example in [RY99 , Chapter 11]. 
The idea is to construct a solution to the stochastic dierential equation 
  1 X1dXt = dBt + t dt,2 
5</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Universal randomness in 2D
 
Jason Miller and Scott Sheeld 
Abstract 
We begin by reviewing one-dimensional random objects that are universal in 
the sense that they arise in many contexts  in particular as scaling limits of large 
families of discrete models  and canonical in the sense that they are uniquely 
characterized by scale invariance and other natural symmetries. Examples include 
Brownian motion, Bessel processes, stable L evy processes and ranges of stable 
subordinators. 
We then introduce several universal and canonical random objects that are 
(at least in some sense) two dimensional or planar, along with discrete analogs of 
these objects. These include trees, distributions, curves, loop ensembles, surfaces, 
and growth trajectories. Keywords include continuum random tree, stable L evy 
tree, stable looptree, Gaussian free eld, Schramm-Loewner evolution, percolation, 
uniform spanning tree, loop-erased random walk, Ising model, FK cluster model, 
conformal loop ensemble, Brownian loop soup, random planar map, Liouville 
quantum gravity, Brownian map, Brownian snake, diusion limited aggregation, 
rst passage percolation, and dielectric breakdown model. 
Finally, we discuss the intricate and surprising relationships between these 
universal objects. We explain how to use generalized functions to construct 
curves and vice versa; conformally weld a pair of surfaces to produce a surface 
decorated by a simple curve; topologically and conformally mate pairs of trees to 
obtain surfaces decorated by non-simple curves; and reshue these constructions 
to describe random growth trajectories on random surfaces. We present both 
discrete and continuum analogs of these relationships. Keywords include imaginary 
geometry, quantum zipper, peanosphere, and quantum Loewner evolution. 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Contents
 
1 Random processes 5
 
1.1 Brownian motion . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5
 
1.2 Bessel processes .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5
 
1.3 Brownian excursions, meanders, and bridges . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6
 
1.4 Stable L evy processes . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6
 
1.5 Ranges of stable sub ordinators . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6
 
2 Random trees 6
 
2.1 Galton-Watson trees . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6
 
2.2 Aldouss continuum random tree . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7
 
2.3 L evy trees and stable looptrees . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7
 
2.4 Brownian snakes . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7
 
3 Random generalized functions 7
 
3.1 Tempered distributions and Fourier transforms . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7
 
3.2 Gaussian free elds . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8
 
3.3 Fractional Gaussian elds and log correlated free elds . . . . . . . . . 8
 
3.4 Dimer models and uniform spanning trees . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8
 
4 Random curves and loop ensembles 8
 
4.1 Schramm-Loewner evolution: basic denitions and phases . . . . . . . . 8
 
4.2 Loop erased random walk and uniform spanning tree . . . . . . . . . . 9
 
4.3 Critical percolation interfaces . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9
 
4.4 Gaussian free eld level lines . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9
 
4.5 Ising, Potts, and FK-cluster models . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9
 
4.6 Bipolar orientations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9
 
4.7 Restriction measures, self-avoiding walk, and loop soups . . . . . . . . . 9
 
4.8 Conformal loop ensembles . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9
 
5 Random surfaces 10
 
5.1 Planar maps . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 10
 
5.2 Decorated surfaces and Laplacian determinants . . . . . . . . . . . . . 10
 
5.3 Mullin-Bernardi bijection . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 10
 
5.4 Cori-Vaquelin-Schaeer bijection . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 10
 
5.5 Hamburger-cheeseburger bijection . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11
 
5.6 Bipolar bijection . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11
 
5.7 Brownian map . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11
 
5.8 Liouville quantum gravity . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11
 
5.9 KPZ (Knizhnik-Polyakov-Zamolodchikov)scaling relations . . . . . . . 12
 
5.10 Quantum wedges, cones, spheresand disks . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 12
 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>15</slideno>
          <text>i 10.3 QLE and the Brownian map
 
This continuum exploration introduced in [MS13b ] can be used to prove the equivalence 
of 8/3-Liouville quantum gravity and the Brownian map. This is accomplished in a 
series of papers [MS15b, MS15c, MS15d]. 
It remains an open problem to endow -LQG with a metric space structure for general 
. A famous calculation of Watabiki describes what can be conjectured to be the 
Hausdor dimension of general -LQG surfaces [Wat93]. 
References 
[AG13a]	 Amine Asselah and Alexandre Gaudilli` ere. From logarithmic to subdiusive 
polynomial uctuations for internal DLA and related growth models. Ann. 
Probab., 41(3A):11151159, 2013. 1009.2838. 
[AG13b]	 Amine Asselah and Alexandre Gaudilli` ere. Sublogarithmic uctuations for 
internal DLA. Ann. Probab., 41(3A):11601179, 2013. 1011.4592. 
[Ald91a]	 David Aldous. The continuum random tree. I. Ann. Probab., 19(1):128, 
1991. 
[Ald91b]	 David Aldous. The continuum random tree. II. An overview. In Stochastic 
analysis (Durham, 1990), volume 167 of London Math. Soc. Lecture Note 
Ser., pages 2370. Cambridge Univ. Press, Cambridge, 1991. 
[Ald93]	 David Aldous. The continuum random tree. III. Ann. Probab., 21(1):248 
289, 1993. 
[Ang03]	 O. Angel. Growth and percolation on the uniform innite planar triangula
tion. Geom. Funct. Anal., 13(5):935974, 2003. math/0208123. 
[AS03]	 Omer Angel and Oded Schramm. Uniform innite planar triangulations. 
Comm. Math. Phys., 241(2-3):191213, 2003. math/0207153. 
[Ber]	 Nathana el Berestycki. Introduction to the gaussian free eld and liouville 
quantum gravity. 
[Ber96]	 Jean Bertoin. L evy processes, volume 121 of Cambridge Tracts in Mathe
matics. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 1996. 
[Ber07]	 Olivier Bernardi. Bijective counting of tree-rooted maps and shues of 
parenthesis systems. Electron. J. Combin. , 14(1):Research Paper 9, 36 pp. 
(electronic), 2007. math/0601684. 
16</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>18</slideno>
          <text>[JVST12] Fredrik Johansson Viklund, Alan Sola, and Amanda Turner. Scaling limits 
of anisotropic Hastings-Levitov clusters. volume 48, pages 235257, 2012. 
0908.0086. 
[Kah85] J-P Kahane. Le chaos multiplicatif. Comptes rendus de lAcad emie des 
sciences. S erie 1, Math ematique, 301(6):329332, 1985. 
[Ken00a] Richard Kenyon. The asymptotic determinant of the discrete laplacian. 
Acta Mathematica, 185(2):239286, 2000. 
[Ken00b] Richard Kenyon. Conformal invariance of domino tiling. 
28(2):759795, 2000. Ann. Probab. , 
[Ken01] R. Kenyon. Dominos and the Gaussian free eld. Annals of Probability, 
29:11281137, 2001. 
[Kes87] Harry Kesten. Hitting probabilities of random walks on Zd . 
Process. Appl., 25(2):165184, 1987. Stochastic 
[KN04] Wouter Kager and Bernard Nienhuis. A guide to stochastic l owner evolution 
and its applications. Journal of statistical physics, 115(5-6):11491229, 
2004. 
[KPZ86] Mehran Kardar, Giorgio Parisi, and Yi-Cheng Zhang. Dynamic scaling of 
growing interfaces. Phys. Rev. Lett., 56:889892, Mar 1986. 
[KPZ88] V. G. Knizhnik, A. M. Polyakov, and A. B. Zamolodchikov. Fractal 
structure of 2D-quantum gravity. Modern Phys. Lett. A, 3(8):819826, 
1988. 
[KS91] Ioannis Karatzas and Steven E. Shreve. Brownian motion and stochastic 
calculus, volume 113 of Graduate Texts in Mathematics. Springer-Verlag, 
New York, second edition, 1991. 
[Lam67] John Lamperti. Continuous state branching processes. Bull. Amer. Math. 
Soc., 73:382386, 1967. 
[Law09] G. Lawler. Conformal invariance and 2D statistical physics. Bull. AMS, 
46:2554, 2009. 
[LBG92] Gregory F. Lawler, Maury Bramson, and David Grieath. Internal diusion 
limited aggregation. Ann. Probab., 20(4):21172140, 1992. 
[Le 14] J.-F. Le Gall. Random geometry on the sphere. ArXiv e-prints, March 
2014. 
[LG13] Jean-Fran cois Le Gall. Uniqueness and universality of the Brownian map. 
Ann. Probab., 41(4):28802960, 2013. 1105.4842. 
19</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>6 Random growth trajectories 12
 
6.1 Eden model and rst passage percolation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 12
 
6.2 Diusion limited aggregation and the dieelectric breakdown model . . . 12
 
6.3 KPZ (Kardar-Parisi-Zhang) growth . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13
 
6.4 Hastings-Levitov . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13
 
6.5 Internal DLA . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13
 
7 Imaginary geometry 13
 
7.1 Flow lines starting from the boundary . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13
 
7.2 Interior ow lines . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 14
 
7.3 Counterow lines and space-lling SLE . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 14
 
7.4 Time reversal symmetries . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 14
 
8 Conformal welding and the quantum zipper 14
 
8.1 Welding simple quantum wedges . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 14
 
8.2 Welding more general quantum wedges . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 14
 
9 Mating trees and the peanosphere 14
 
9.1 Moores theorem and topological tree mating . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 14
 
9.2 Matings from complex dynamics . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 15
 
9.3 Matings of correlated continuum random trees . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 15
 
9.4 Matings of trees of disks . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 15
 
9.5 Relation to discrete bijections . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 15
 
10 Quantum Loewner evolution 15
 
10.1 Reshuing in discrete examples . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 15
 
10.2 Dening QLE . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 15
 
10.3 QLE and the Brownian map . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 16
 
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>8</slideno>
          <text>4.2 Loop erased random walk and uniform spanning tree
 
See Wilsons algorithm [Wil96 , PW98 ] and the original UST/LERW convergence paper 
[LSW04]. 
4.3 Critical percolation interfaces 
Percolation interface scaling limits are tractable thanks to a fundamental discovery by 
Stanislav Smirnov [Smi01]. 
4.4 Gaussian free eld level lines 
See [SS05, SS09, SS13] and the universality theorem in [Mil10]. 
4.5 Ising, Potts, and FK-cluster models 
Some of these next simplest after percolation models are also tractable [CS] 
4.6 Bipolar orientations 
This is another simple model conjectured to scale to SLE 12. The conjecture is easy to 
state, but the motivation behind the conjecture will not be explained until the sections 
on imaginary geometry and the peanosphere. 
4.7 Restriction measures, self-avoiding walk, and loop soups 
The relationship between SLE 8/3 and Brownian motion is especially beautiful and has 
an especially beautiful history. See the account in the early work by Lawler, Schramm, 
and Werner [LSW03]. 
4.8 Conformal loop ensembles 
Given that the discrete interfaces that scale to SLE have loop ensemble variants, 
one would expect there to be a natural loop ensemble variant of SLE itself. See the 
introduction in [She09, SW12]. 
9</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>10</slideno>
          <text>directed breadth rst spanning tree spannign all of the edges. When multiple incoming 
edges come into the same vertex, each outgoing edge is connected to only one of them 
in this tree namely, the next one over in clockwise ordering. 
5.5 Hamburger-cheeseburger bijection 
There is a generalization of the Mullin-Bernardi bijection in which the rooted planar 
map comes with an arbitrary distinguished edge subset, instead of a distinguished 
spanning tree [She11]. 
5.6 Bipolar bijection 
The scaling limit of the pair of trees can be easily described in this case, as it can in 
each of the other cases described above. 
5.7 Brownian map 
The idea behind the Cori-Vaquelin-Schaeer bijection can be used to dene a continuum 
random metric space [MM06 , LG13 , Mie13 , LG14 ], which has a natural innite volume 
analog [CL12 ]. See Le Galls ICM notes [Le 14] or the survey by Miermont and Le 
Gall [LGM+12]. An axiomatic characterization of the Brownian map in terms of it 
symmetries appears in [MS15a]. 
5.8 Liouville quantum gravity 
Polaykov conceived of a random surface model based on an action closely related to the 
Gaussian free eld [Pol81]. If h is an instance of the Gaussian free eld, one attempts 
to dene a meausre of the form eh(z)dz, which in turn encodes the volume form of a 
random surface after a conformal map back to a xed parameter space (say, a disk in the 
plane). The rigorous construction of this random measure was given by Hegh-Krohn in  
1971 [HK71 ], for the range   [0, 2), and the full range [0, 2) was treated by Kahane 
(who used the term multiplicative chaos) in 1985 [Kah85 ], see also the survey [RV14 ]. 
The construction of the measure as a measure-valued function on the space of instances 
h of the GFF was done in [DS11 ]. The case  = 2 is dierent but one can make sense 
of the measure by dierent means [DRSV14a, DRSV14c]. 
11</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>22</slideno>
          <text>[Smi01] Stanislav Smirnov. Critical percolation in the plane: conformal invariance, 
Cardys formula, scaling limits. C. R. Acad. Sci. Paris S er. I Math., 
333(3):239244, 2001. 
[SS05] Oded Schramm and Scott Sheeld. Harmonic explorer and its convergence 
to SLE 4. Ann. Probab., 33(6):21272148, 2005. 
[SS09] Oded Schramm and Scott Sheeld. Contour lines of the two-dimensional 
discrete Gaussian free eld. Acta Math., 202(1):21137, 2009. 
[SS13] Oded Schramm and Scott Sheeld. A contour line of the continuum 
Gaussian free eld. Probab. Theory Related Fields, 157(1-2):4780, 2013. 
1008.2447. 
[SW12] Scott Sheeld and Wendelin Werner. Conformal loop ensembles: the 
Markovian characterization and the loop-soup construction. Ann. of Math. 
(2), 176(3):18271917, 2012. 1006.2374. 
[Tut62] W. T. Tutte. A census of planar triangulations. Canad. J. Math., 14:2138, 
1962. 
[Tut68] W. T. Tutte. On the enumeration of planar maps. Bull. Amer. Math. Soc., 
74:6474, 1968. 
[Wat93] Yoshiyuki Watabiki. Analytic study of fractal structure of quantized 
surface in two-dimensional quantum gravity. Progr. Theoret. Phys. Suppl. , 
(114):117, 1993. Quantum gravity (Kyoto, 1992). 
[Wer03] Wendelin Werner. Random planar curves and schramm-loewner evolutions. 
arXiv preprint math/0303354, 2003. 
[Wil96] David Bruce Wilson. Generating random spanning trees fmore quickly 
than the cover time. In Proceedings of the twenty-eighth annual ACM 
symposium on Theory of computing, pages 296303. ACM, 1996. 
[WJS81] TA Witten Jr and Leonard M Sander. Diusion-limited aggregation, a 
kinetic critical phenomenon. Physical review letters, 47(19):1400, 1981. 
[WS83] T. A. Witten and L. M. Sander. Diusion-limited aggregation. Phys. Rev. 
B (3), 27(9):56865697, 1983. 
Department of Mathematics 
Massachusetts Institute of Technology 
Cambridge, MA, USA 
23</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Galton-Watson trees is the phase transition: when the expected number of children is 
less than one, the tree is easily seen to be nite almost surely. (The expected number of 
children at level k decays exponentially in k.) When the expected number of children 
is greater than one, the tree has a positive probability of being innite. 
When the expected number of children is equal to 1, one may observe ospring sets of 
vertices one at a time, exploring tree boundary in a clockwise way, so that the number 
of live vertices is a martingale. This martingale is closely related to the contour function 
of the tree (but not exactly the same; see L evy tree story below). 
2.2 Aldouss continuum random tree 
The continuum random tree was introduced in a series of papers by Aldous in 1991 
[Ald91a , Ald91b , Ald93 ]. It can be understood as a scaling limit of Galton-Watson 
trees. 
2.3 L evy trees and stable looptrees 
There are some very simple analogs of the CRT in which stable L evy excursions play 
the role of the Brownian excursion [DLG05 ]. These can also be understood as scaling 
limits of Galton-Watson trees, when the number of children has a power law tail (nite 
mean but innite variance). 
There is a closely related construction in which each of the countably many big branch 
points is replaced with a loop; the resulting tree of loops called a looptree. See the 
work by Curien and Korchemski on stable looptrees [CK13 ], as well as the exposition in 
[DMS14]. 
2.4 Brownian snakes 
A Brownian snake is essentially a Brownian motion indexed by a CRT. It will play a role 
later in the construction of a certain canonical random surface called the Brownian map, 
but it was actually studied independently before its relationship to random surfaces 
was discovered [DLG05]. 
3 Random generalized functions 
3.1 Tempered distributions and Fourier transforms 
The Schwartz space on Rd is the space of C functions  such that for any multi-indices 
 and  in which each of the seminorms sup D(x)x is bounded. These seminorms 
7</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>17</slideno>
          <text>[DRSV14b]	 Bertrand Duplantier, R emi Rhodes, Scott Sheeld, and Vincent Vargas. 
Log-correlated gaussian elds: an overview. arXiv preprint arXiv:1407.5605, 
2014. 
[DRSV14c]	 Bertrand Duplantier, R emi Rhodes, Scott Sheeld, and Vincent Vargas. 
Renormalization of Critical Gaussian Multiplicative Chaos and KPZ Rela
tion. Comm. Math. Phys., 330(1):283330, 2014. 
[DS11] Bertrand Duplantier and Scott Sheeld. Liouville quantum gravity and 
KPZ. Invent. Math., 185(2):333393, 2011. 0808.1560. 
[Dur10] Rick Durrett. Probability: theory and examples. Cambridge Series in 
Statistical and Probabilistic Mathematics. Cambridge University Press, 
Cambridge, fourth edition, 2010. 
[Ede61] Murray Eden. A two-dimensional growth process. In Proc. 4th Berkeley 
Sympos. Math. Statist. and Prob., Vol. IV, pages 223239. Univ. California 
Press, Berkeley, Calif., 1961. 
[GGN13] Ori Gurel-Gurevich and Asaf Nachmias. Recurrence of planar graph limits. 
Ann. of Math. (2), 177(2):761781, 2013. 1206.0707. 
[HK71] Raphael Hegh-Krohn. A general class of quantum elds without cut-os 
in two space-time dimensions. Communications in Mathematical Physics, 
21(3):244255, 1971. 
[HW65] J. M. Hammersley and D. J. A. Welsh. First-passage percolation, sub-
additive processes, stochastic networks, and generalized renewal theory. 
In Proc. Internat. Res. Semin., Statist. Lab., Univ. California, Berkeley, 
Calif, pages 61110. Springer-Verlag, New York, 1965. 
[Jan97] Svante Janson. Gaussian Hilbert spaces , volume 129 of Cambridge Tracts 
in Mathematics. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 1997. 
[JLS12] David Jerison, Lionel Levine, and Scott Sheeld. Logarithmic uctuations 
for internal DLA. J. Amer. Math. Soc., 25(1):271301, 2012. 1010.2483. 
[JLS13] David Jerison, Lionel Levine, and Scott Sheeld. Internal dla in higher 
dimensions. Electron. J. Probab, 18(98):114, 2013. 
[JLS+14] David Jerison, Lionel Levine, Scott Sheeld, et al. Internal dla and the 
gaussian free eld. Duke Mathematical Journal, 163(2):267308, 2014. 
[JS98] Benjamin Jacquard and Gilles Schaeer. A bijective census of nonseparable 
planar maps. J. Combin. Theory Ser. A, 83(1):120, 1998. 
18</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
      <videos/>
    </lecture>
  </lectures>
</doc>
