<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-15-electrical-optical-magnetic-materials-and-devices-fall-2006/</course_url>
    <course_title>Electrical, Optical &amp; Magnetic Materials and Devices</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Science </list>
      <list>Physics </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Displays (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-15-electrical-optical-magnetic-materials-and-devices-fall-2006/resources/lecture14/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.15 
Displays 
C.A.  Ross, DMSE, MIT
References: Braithwaite and Weaver chapter 6.4 
Displays can work by
-emitting light, eg.
Incandescence (light from heating a filament)
Cathodoluminescence (light from electron bombardment)
ZnS +Ag (blue), (Zn,Cd)S +Cu (green), Y2O2S +Eu,Tb (red) &#8211;excited by three 
20kV electron guns in a TV screen 
Photoluminescence (light from UV irradiation), eg anti-theft printing on banknotes, black 
lights, etc. Use phosphors, TiO2 
Electroluminescence (light from electrical excitation) 
LED or semiconductor laser 
Plasma emission (light from electrically excited plasma). Sodium light, Hg lamp, neon tube. In a plasma screen, a small UV plasma excites a phosphor, similar to a fluorescent light. 
-or modulating light , e.g. liquid crystal display, electrooptic modulator, micromirror 
array, etc. 
Liquid crystal displays 
Stiff, rod-shaped organic molecules such as cyanobiphenyls which can order in different
ways:
Nematic (lined up parallel)
Cholesteric (helical, also called a chiral nematic) &#8211;pitch of helix is a fraction of a micron
Smectic (layered arrangements, 8 different types)
Optical properties are different parallel vs perpendicular to the molecule. Polarizability is
higher parallel to the molecule. The complex refractive index, dominated by electronic
polarizability, is higher parallel to the molecule, so light with electric field parallel to the
molecule is transmitted better.
Twisted nematic display consists of
Polarizer/ front plate with electrode pattern /grooved polymer / ~10 mm nematic +
cholesteric / grooved polymer / back plate /polarizer / mirror
The grooved polymer sheets are oriented perpendicular to each other and guide the
nematic into a slow 90&#730; twist; light is transmitted. Appling a vertical electric field (eg 3V)
between the front and back plates aligns the nematic and light can no longer pass, so the
display is dark. Colors come from dyes or filters. Response time limited by viscosity.
Electrode patterns are made from thin film transistors (TFTs) made on glass &#8211; these use
a-Si to make the channel region, with p-type source and drain doped with Al, and a Cr
gate. The drain is connected to a pixel made from ITO (indium tin oxide, a transparent
conductor).
Handout 7 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Magnetic Fundamentals (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-15-electrical-optical-magnetic-materials-and-devices-fall-2006/resources/ho9_magnetic_fundamentals/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>e.g. Fe3+ 
has 3d5
: expect 5 &#181;B per atom (neglecting orbital contributions) 
Fe has 4s23d6
: in the metal, because of the way the s and d hybridize,
the structure is actually 4s0.95 3d7.05 with 4.62 spin-up and 2.42 spin-
down electrons, giving a net 2.2&#181;B
Ferromagnets have spontaneous ordering of the spins in neighbor ing atoms due to
exchange coupling. If spins make angle &#952;,
exchange energy = A (1 &#8211; cos &#952;) 
where A is the exchange constant, e.g. 1.4 10 -20 
J for Fe 
Negative A gives antiparallel alignment: material is antiferromagnetic or ferrimagnetic.
Above the Curie temperature Tc, the spins are disordered, so kTc ~ A. (770&#730;C for Fe) 
In ferro/ferrimagnets, aligned spins form domains which usually point in different
directions, giving no net moment to the sample. However, the domains can be oriented (i.e.
the domain walls can be moved) by a relatively small field giving a large net moment, so 
the permeability is very high. The shape of the M-H curve is hysteretic; important loop 
parameters include
area within the curve (the energy expended as the field is cycled back and forth)
saturation magnetization (the magnetization in a large field)
remanence (the magnetization remaining at zero field)
coercivity (field needed to bring the magnetization to zero).
Anisotropy and Domains
Magnetic energy consists of the following terms:
exchange energy (minimise by having all spins parallel) 
magne tostatic energy (minimise by having domains pointing in different directions so 
there is no external field)
Zeeman energy (potential energy due to an external magnetic field, E = M.H)
magne tocrystalline energy (lower if the magnetization is pointing in certain 
crystallographic directions, eg the c-axis in Co)
Domain structures form to minimise energy. D omains are typically microns or larger;
domain wall widths ~ 100 nm.
Magne tocrystalline anisotropy represents the energy needed to &#8216;pull&#8217; the magnetization 
away from the preferred (easy) axis.
e.g. Co K = 4.1 105 
J/m3 
uniaxial, [0001 ] is easy u 
Fe K1 = 4.8 104 
J/m3 
cubic, &lt;100&gt; is easy 
Ni K1 = -4.5 103 
J/m3 
cubic, &lt;111&gt; is easy 
Uniaxial: energy E = Ksin2 
&#966; &#966; = angle between M and easy axis u 
Cubic: E = K1 (cos2 
&#966;1 cos 2 
&#966;2+ cos 2 
&#966;2 cos 2 
&#966;3 + cos 2 
&#966;3cos 2 
&#966;1) + higher order terms 
&#966;i = angle between M and the i axis
Domain wall width is determined by a balance between exchange (favors wide walls) and
magnetocrystalline anisotropy (favors narrow walls). (a = lattice parameter) 
Handout 9 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>d =&#960;
 wall width 
wall energy E w 
For small enough particles it is not worth establishing a wall because the savings in 
magnetostatic energy are less than the wall energy. T hese are &#8216;single domain&#8217; particles.
Very small particles are thermally unstable because the net magnetic energy
KtotV &lt; 25kT . (here V is the volume of the particle)
Magne tostatic energy (a.k.a. self-energy or demagne tizing energy)
The energy in the field surround ing the magnetized object depends on the way the object is
magnetized. For instance, a long thin object has less magnetostatic energy if it is magnetized 
along its length, compared to across its length. This can be expressed in the same way as a
uniaxial anisotropy: if the long axis is z and the short axis is x then 
E = Kshape sin2 
&#966; &#966; = angle between M and z axis 
2
where Kshape = 0.5(Nx &#8211; Nz)Ms
The Ns are called demagnetizing factors and depend on the shape of the object. For instance
for an infinite cylinder with length in the z direction, N= 0 and N = N = 0.5. z x y 
The field inside the object along the i axis due to its own magnetization is
Hd = -Ni M M = saturation magnetization. s s 
Hard and soft materials 
In a soft material, walls are easy to nucleate (low energy, i.e. low A and magnetocrystalline
anisotropy) and move (few pinning sites), magnetization is easy to rotate (low
magnetocrystalline anisotropy). Hard materials have oppos ite properties: high energy walls,
pinning sites, high anisotropy, often made of single-domain particles. 
Handout 9 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.15 Magnetic Fundamentals
C.A. Ross, DMSE, MIT 
References: 
Jiles, Introduc tion to Magnetism and Magnetic Materials 
Magnetic quantities and units
H = magnetic field, A/m &#8211;represents energy gradient, or torque on a dipole 
B = magnetic flux density, T or Wb/m2 
&#8211;number of magnetic field lines per unit area
M = magnetization, A/m &#8211;the magnetic moment, the respons e of a material to a field.
H comes from a current: current i produc es tangential field H = i/2 &#960; r at radius r
or from a magnetic material.
B depends on H: in free space B = &#181;oH &#181;o = 4&#960; 10-7 Henry/m
but inside a material B = &#181;o(H + M)
or B = &#181;o &#181;rH &#181;r = relative permeability 
or M=H(&#181;r-1) 
or M= &#967;H &#967; = (&#181;r -1) = susceptibility 
M and B both indicate how a material responds to a field H. Lines of B are continuous . 
Note the same relation expressed in cgs units:
B (Gauss) = H (Oersted) + 4&#960;M (emu/cc) 
where 1 Oe = (1000 /4&#960;) A/m = 79.6 A/m 
1 G = 10 -4 
T 
1 emu/cc = 1 kA/m 
Different types of materials
Diamagnet: atom has no net magnetic moment, but a field induc es a small moment oppos ite
to the field. Susceptibility is negative (&#181;r &lt;1)
Paramagnet: atoms have a net moment but the spin directions are random ly arranged. An
applied field can give weak alignment, hence a small susceptibility that varies with 1/T.
(&#181;r&gt;1)
Ferromagnets have spontaneous magnetization, a large permeability which depends
on the history of the sample, and nonlinear, hys teretic behavior.
Origin of magnetic behavior
Angular momentum of electrons produc es magnetization due to moving charges.
Magnetization comes from 1) electron spin, 2) electron orbital motion.
Contributions from paired electrons cancel out, so strong magnetic effects are found in
materials with unpa ired electrons.
One electron has a moment of 1 &#181;BB (Bohr magneton) = 9.27 10 -24 
Am2
Stern-Gerlach and Zeeman experiments indicate the quantization of the magnetization in
atoms.
We expect large magnetic effects in transition metals (unfilled 3d) and rare earths (unfilled
4f) because these can have a large net spin.
Handout 9 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Drift and Diffusion of Carriers (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-15-electrical-optical-magnetic-materials-and-devices-fall-2006/resources/lecture2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.15
Carrier Drift, Diffusion and R&amp;G
C.A. Ross, Department of Materials Science and Engineering
Reference: Pierret, chapter 3.
Electron and holes can drift, diffuse, and unde rgo generation and 
recombination (R&amp;G).
Drift:
thermal velocity 1/2 mv2
thermal = 3/2 kT
drift velocity, vd = &#181;E (&#181; = mobility, E = field)
Current density (electrons) J = n e vd
Current density (electrons &amp; holes) J = e (n &#181;n+ p &#181;h)E 
Conduc tivity &#963; = J/E = e(n &#181;n+ p &#181;h) 
Magnitude of mobility (cm
&#181;n &#181;h
Si 1500 450
Ge 3900 1900
Ag 50 -
GaAs 8500 4002/Vs) 
Time between collisions is &#964; &#181; =e&#964;/m* 
Distance between collisions is l l = &#964;vthermal 
Diffusion 
J = eDn &#8711;n + eDp &#8711;p
Derivation of the Einstein relation: Dn/&#181;n = kT/e 
typical Dn in Si is 40 cm2/s 
Carrier R&amp;G 
Mechanisms: band-to-band (direct)
RG centers or traps (indirect) 
Thermal R and G at equilibrium: R = G
expect R = G = rnp = r ni2 r = rate constant 
Handout 2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Shining light, etc. on the semiconduc tor causes additional R. These excess
carriers nl and pl (nl = pl )decay once the light is turned off. 
Illuminated: n-type material
n =ND+nl ~ND
p =ni2/ND+pl ~pl
net rate of change of carriers = R &#8211; G = rnp &#8211; r ni2 
the rate of recombination of the minority carriers is 
-dp/dt = r(NDp -ni2) but ni2 = ND(p -pl ) 
-dp/dt = rND(p &#8211; p + pl) = rNDpl 
This has a solution pl = pl, t=0 exp (-t/&#964;p), where &#964;p = 1/rND = minority carrier 
lifetime. 
Example of Carrier Action &#8211; Formal solution 
A piece of p-type Si is illuminated at one end; how does the carrier
concentration vary with depth x? 
dn/dt = dn/dtdrift + dn/dtdiffn + dn/dtthermal RG + dn/dtother RG
= 0 at steady state
n = np + nl where np = ni2/NA
Inside the material there is only thermal R&amp;G:
Gthermal = rni2 = r np NA
Rthermal = rnp ~ r nl NA
R&#8211;G=rNA(nl-np)~rNAnl =nl/&#964;n 
In the steady state,
dn/dt = dn/dtdiffn &#8211; (R &#8211; G) = 0 
dn/dt = 1/e &#8711;Jdiffn &#8211; (R &#8211; G) = 0 
d2nl /dx2 = nl /&#964;nDn 
(since dn/dtdiffn = 1/e &#8711;Jdiffn = Dnd2n/dx2 from Fick&#8217;s law) 
solution: nl = nl, x=0 exp (-x/&#8730;&#964;nDn ) 
Generally, if excess carrier concentrations are written as nl or pl, then 
dn/dtthermal = -nl/&#964;n or dp/dtthermal = -pl/&#964;p
Minority carrier lifetimes are &#964;n = 1/rNA, or &#964;p = 1/rND,
Minority carrier diffusion lengths are &#955;n= &#8730;&#964;nDn, or &#955;p= &#8730;&#964;pDp. 
If traps dominate the recombination, then &#964; = 1/r2NT where r2 &gt;&gt; r 
Handout 2 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Photodetectors and Photovoltaics (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-15-electrical-optical-magnetic-materials-and-devices-fall-2006/resources/lecture9/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Handout 5 4 Darkened l-V Behavior
Fully Illuminated
00
12.023.0 32.941.643.837.028.519.8
Power (Watts)
-5-4-224
00
-0.04-0.020.020.04
0.00
5 10 15 20 25
V oltage -- 36 Cells in Series (V olts)0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6ASE Americas, Inc. Solar Panel, Model BC-16-DG
V oltage per Cell (V olts)
Current Density (Amps/cm2)Current (Amps)
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Handout 5 2 Scanned article removed due to copyright restrictions. 
Please See "This Month in Physics History, October 22, 1938: Invention of Xerography." APS News 12 (2003): 2.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>&#8224; 
&#8224; 3.15
Photoconductors, Photovoltaics and Photodetectors
C.A. Ross, Department of Materials Science and Engineering
Reference: Pierret, chapter 9.2 and 9.3
Photoconductors &#8211; conductivity a function of light
Photovoltaics &#8211; generate power from light
Photodetectors &#8211; use a pn junction to detect light
Photoconducting materials:
CdS, ZnS for camera lightmeters, amorphous As,Se,Te for photocopiers
Photodiode and Photovoltaic (PV):
Carriers created within Ln or Lp of junction contribute to reverse current:
I = Io + IG 
Photodiode operates in reverse bias. A PIN diode has a wide depletion region; operates much faster than a pn junction photodetector because it doesn not rely on diffusion. 
A PV operates in the fourth quadrant (positive V, negative I). When 
connected to a load (e.g. a battery charger or a lightbulb) with resistance RL, 
V = I (RPV + RL) 
also I = Io (exp(eV/kT) - 1) + IG 
these two relations define the voltage and current that the PV produces. 
Power = IV 
Solar Cells: the PV must respond to the visible spectrum (400 &#8211; 700 nm,
or 2 &#8211; 3 eV; note that l (mm) = 1.24/E (eV))
Ideally we would use a bandgap of about 1.2 eV, but Si does not absorb light
well because it has an indirect band gap.
Direct and indirect gap
On an E-k plot: m* = h2(&#8706;2 E /&#8706;k2)-1
Momentum of an electron typically p/a ~ 1010 m-1
Momentum of a photon = 2p/l ~ 107 m-1
If the band gap is indirect, a phonon plus a photon are eeded to make an e-h 
pair, so light absorption (and emission) is less efficient.
Amorphous Si: uncertainly principle DxDp &#8805; h
 -the localization of carriers gives them an uncertain momentum, so direct 
absorption of light can occur. Use PIN design because mobility is low. 
Handout 5 1 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>PDF 1</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-15-electrical-optical-magnetic-materials-and-devices-fall-2006/resources/lecture7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Handout 4 4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.15
Transistors
C.A. Ross, Department of Materials Science and Engineering
Reference: Pierret, chapter 10, 15.1-2, 16.1-2 and 17.1.
Transistors are three-terminal devices that use a small voltage (or current)
applied to one contact to modulate (i.e. control) a large voltage (or current)
between the other two contacts.
An analogy is the vacuum tube from the 1900s. A small voltage applied to 
the &#8216;grid&#8217;</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>at pinchoff, VSD, sat = (eNDt2/8&#949;o&#949;r) -(Vo + VG) 
MOS devices (metal &#8211; oxide &#8211; semiconductor)
Ideal MOS bandstructure: where &#966; = &#967; s + (Ec -Ef), the Fermi level is flat 
without any band bending 
vacuum level Eo 
&#966; &#967;s 
Ec
Ef
Ev 
M O S (p-type)
Negative voltage to the gate (i.e. to the metal) causes charge to accumulate 
(acts as a capacitor)
Small positive voltage to the gate causes charge to be depleted
Large positive voltage to the gate causes inversion: once all the mobile
carriers are depleted, carriers of the oppos ite sign are attracted to the region 
of the semiconduc tor next to the oxide. This creates a channel of oppos ite
type. 
MOSFET G 
S D oxide 
n+ 
n-channel 
p-type substrate n+ 
depletion region 
Source and substrate are grounde d. Applying a large positive VG creates an 
n-channel which conduc ts current between S and D.
If VD = 0, channel has uniform width.
If VD &gt; 0, channel is thinner towards the D and may pinch-off; also the
depletion width is larger.
At pinch-off, the current ISD cannot increase any more.
Example application: a DRAM (dyna mic random access memory) stores one
bit in a cell consisting of a MOSFET plus a MOS-capacitor. Opening the
channel of the MOSFET (by applying VG) allows the capacitor to be charged 
to represent &#8216;1&#8217; or uncharged for &#8216;0&#8217;.
Handout 4 3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Forward current IE
At the edge of the depletion region at the left of the base,
p = (ni2/ND,B) exp(eVEB/kT) 
At the right of the base, p = 0
Current across base IE = (eDp/w) (ni2/ND,B) exp(eVEB/kT) 
Base current IB
The base current &lt;&lt; collector current, so most current goes straight through 
from E to C. 
Current gain &#945; =IC/IE ~1, &#946; = IC /IB ~ 100 -1000 
IB = In (electrons going from B to E in forward bias)
+ InC (electrons going from C to B in reverse bias -small) 
+ eRB (recombination in base -small) 
The gain &#946; = IC /IB ~ IE /IB = NA,E / ND,B is determined by doping. 
&#8216;Common base&#8217; circuit: by setting VEB and IE we control VCB and IC
&#8216;Common emitter&#8217; circuit: by setting VEB and IB we control VEC and IC
Digital logic: make the transistor act like a switch by running between 
saturation and cutoff. 
Junction Field Effect Transistor 
Apply a reverse voltage to gate G. This makes the depletion regions grow,
alters the n-channel width and therefore alters its resistance, which changes 
the source-drain voltage (for constant current). This is a voltage amplifier 
and also a majority carrier device. 
p+
S n D G 
p+ 
For VG = 0 it is a linear resistor. However, applying VSD causes pinch-off 
(i.e. the depletion regions touch) and no more current ISD can flow.
Applying a negative VG makes pinchoff occur earlier.
Beyond pinchoff, a small change in VG causes a large change in VSD.
For depletion width d, channel length t, and initial channel width t, 
Handout 4 2 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>LEDs, Lasers (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-15-electrical-optical-magnetic-materials-and-devices-fall-2006/resources/lecture11_12_13/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11-13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.15 
LEDs and Lasers 
C.A.  Ross, Department of Materials Science and Engineering
References: Pierret Chapter 9.4, article on LEDs from MRS BulletinOct. 
2001 p764, and Solymar and Walsh chapter 12 for lasers 
Luminescence mechanisms 
Cathodoluminescence (light from electron bombardment) 
ZnS +Ag (blue), (Zn,Cd)S +Cu (green), Y2O2S +Eu,Tb (red) 
Photoluminescence (light from UV irradiation) 
phosphors, TiO2 
Electroluminescence (light from electrical excitation) 
LED or semiconductor laser 
LEDs : recombine e+h at a pn junction in forward bias: direct or indirect 
band-to-band recombination, at a trap or impurity center, or at an exciton. 
Color is determined by the band gap. Changing the composition of III-V or 
II-VI materials controls the band gap. Lattice parameter is important because 
it determines how well the material grows on a substrate, i.e. how many 
defects may be present. 
Red: direct gap (AlxGa1-x)As; for 670 nm (1.85 eV) use x = 0.5 
Green: N-doped indirect gap GaP, where the N introduces a trap level, 
or direct gap (AlInGa)P 
Blue: indirect SiC, 
or direct InGaN or AlGaN, 450 nm (2.75 eV) 
IR: InGaAsP for 1.1 &#8211; 1.7 eV 
Use heterojunctions to minimize reabsorption of light. 
Lasers (light amplification by stimulated emission of radiation), an optical 
amplifier: 
probability of absorption = B13 
probability of stimulated emission (makes coherent light) = B31 
probability of spontaneous emission = A31 
Light can be amplified if stimulated emission exceeds spontaneous emission 
If N1 atoms are at energy level 1, N3 are at energy level 3, E31 = h&#957; 31 is the 
energy difference between levels 1 and 3, and &#961; (&#957; 31)d&#957; represents the 
Handout 6 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>number of photons present with frequency &#957; in a spectral band of width d &#957;31 
(i.e. &#961;(&#957;) is the photon energy density) then 
rate of photon absorption in range d &#957; R13 = N1 B13 &#961; (&#957; 31)d&#957; 
rate of photon emission in range d&#957; R31 = N3 B31 &#961; (&#957; 31)d&#957; +  N3A31d&#957; 
at equilibrium, R13 = R31
also N3 = N1 exp (-h&#957; 31 /kT)
therefore &#961; (&#957; 31)d&#957; = A31/{ B13 exp (h &#957; 31 /kT) &#8211; B31 } d&#957;
Planck&#8217;s expression for black body radiation gives the photon energy
distribution, for all &#957;
&#961; (&#957; )d&#957; = {8&#960; h&#957; 3/c3 }/{exp (h &#957; /kT) - 1} d &#957; 
Comparing the two expressions implies 
B13 = B31
3/c3
and A31/B31 = 8&#960; h&#957;  (Einstein relations) 
Usually N3 &lt; N1 so absorption occurs more often than spontaneous emission. 
To make an amplifier, we need a population inversion, i.e. N3 &gt; N1, to 
produce a gain &gt; 1. N3 &gt; N1 ensures that stimulated emission exceeds 
absorption. 
gain = number of photons produced per incident photon 
&#8733; (N3 &#8211; N1) B31 &#961; (&#957; 31)d&#957; 
Gain exceeds 1 over a small range of wavelengths around &#957; 31. 
A population inversion can be produced in a three or four level system by pumping atoms up to a high energy level, from which they slowly decay into 
a lower level. Pumping requires a higher energy than h &#957; 
31. 
Energy states in a Nd3+ atom in Nd:YAG laser make a 4-level system, 
which lases at 1.064 &#181; m (IR) 
Energy states in a Cr3+ atom in ruby laser make a 3-level system, 
which lases at 693nm (red) 
To raise gain we also need to increase &#961; (&#957; 31)d&#957; which is done by confining 
the light inside a cavity, length d; this ensures that stimulated emission 
exceeds spontaneous emission. 
cavity modes exist when &#957;  = c/2Nd, N an integer. 
Handout 6 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Semiconductor lasers 
A p+n+ degenerate junction can give a population inversion (need more 
electrons in conduction band than in valence band for population inversion). 
At low forward bias it acts as a LED, but when the applied voltage &gt; bandgap it can act as a laser. 
More efficient to use a heterostructure to trap carriers in a small region. Note 
in heterostructures when bands join, there is a band offset ( &#916; E or &#916; Ev).c
example: n-AlGaAs &#8211; GaAs &#8211; p-AlGaAs laser. 
e&amp;h are injected into the GaAs region and cannot escape. Light is also 
confined due to the difference in refractive index. Cavity is defined by 
cleaving the crystal. Cladding and active region need a good lattice match to 
avoid defects. 
Blue lasers: ZnSSe cladding, CdZnSe active, or 
AlGaN cladding, GaInN active. 
Handout 6 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Transformers and DC Motors (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-15-electrical-optical-magnetic-materials-and-devices-fall-2006/resources/lecture19_21/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19, 21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>&#8224; 3.15 
Transformers and DC motors 
C.A.  Ross, DMSE, MIT
References: 
Braithwaite and Weaver, Electronic Materials, sections 3.2 and 3.3 
(Jiles, Introduction to Magnetism and Magnetic Materials 4.3.3 &amp; 12.1.7) 
How do transformers work? 
Two coils wrap around a soft magnetic core. The input side has a varying current im 
through n turns of wire.
&#218; Ampere: H.dl = nim 
Within the core, B = mo mrH 
(Soft magnet: large, nearly constant mr) 
Put a secondary coil around the core: n&#8217; turns Faraday V = -n&#8217; d f/dt 
where f = B.A (A = coil area) 
Now we draw a current from the secondary: current is induces a current i  back in thep
primary. Now primary current is im + ip.
Power transferred Vs is = Vp ip, where Vs/Vp = n&#8217;/n
Properties of the core:
-easy to magnetize to have a high B
-high Bs 
-low hysteresis
-resistive to avoid eddy currents.
Soft magnetic materials 
Tc/ K Bs /T Hc / A/m  mr W, J/m3 
Fe 1043 2.2 ~4 200,000 30 
Fe-3%Si 1030 2.1 ~12 40,000 30 
a-FeBSi 630 1.6 ~0 &gt;100,000 15 
How do DC motors work? 
We characterize hard magnets by the (BH)max product in the hysteresis loop.
For the magnet to be able to do some useful work, it needs to produce some external flux,
e.g. at the gap of a ring-shaped magnet with a cut made in it. Field Hg exists in the gap. 
Ampere: 	 lmHm + lgH  = 0 around dotted lineg
also 	 Bm = Bg
Bm = mo mrHm (negative since in second quadrant) 
B  = moHg g
hence Hm = -lg Bm/lm mo 
This linear relation intersects the hysteresis loop and defines uniquely the operating point. 
Handout 10 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>The amount of work that can be done by the magnet is proportional to lH B  so scalesg g g
with the (BH)max product. 
In a permanent magnet motor: a current i runs through a wire length l in a B field.
Force F = Bi l (use Fleming&#8217;s left hand rule)
This gives a force perpendicular to the wire and to B.
-A radial B is produced by two permanent magnets called the stator.
-The wire is wrapped round a vertical piece made of a soft magnet (the rotor). The
purpose of the soft magnet is to concentrate the flux lines through the coil, giving 
maximum B. 
-Current is supplied by a commutator (sliding contact).
Desirable properties of the permanent magnets: must stay magnetized despite their shape,
and the fields produced by the wire, hence a high coercivity. Must produce large B, hence
a high Bs i.e. high (BH)max.
Efficiency of motor is maximized if we can reduce the resistive losses in the wire. So
minimize ri/ABv, where r is resistivity, A is wire x-section and v is rotation velocity.
Hard magnetic materials
Tc/ K Br /T Hc / kA/m (BH)max, kJ/m3 
Alnico-5 1160 1.4 64 44 
BaO.(Fe2O3)6 720 0.4 264 28 
SmCo5 1000 0.85 600 140 
Nd2Fe14B 620 1.1 890 216 
remanence 
Handout 10 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>PN Junctions (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-15-electrical-optical-magnetic-materials-and-devices-fall-2006/resources/lecture4_5_6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4-6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Therefore diffusion flux Jdiff = Jo exp eVA/kT 
To evaluate Jo, we know that Jo = -Jdrift = Jdiff at VA = 0. 
Consider an asymmetric junction with NA &gt;&gt; ND, then the current is mainly 
holes, and their concentration decays in the n-type material (outside the 
depletion region) over a distance &#955;p= &#8730;(&#964;pDp). The diffusion current 
Jdiff = eDp &#8711;p = eDp (pn(x=0) &#8211; pno)/ &#955;p (where pno = ni2 /ND)
~ eDp (pn(x=0))/ &#955;p
pn = pp exp &#8211;eVo/kT (unbiased)
and pn = pp exp &#8211;e(Vo-VA)/kT (forward biased)
so pn = pno exp &#8211;eVA/kT
Hence Jdiff = {eDp ni2 /ND&#955;p} exp &#8211;eVA/kT = Jo exp eVA/kT 
Include both electron and hole terms: Jo = eni2 {Dp/ND&#955;p + Dn/NA&#955;n}
Also, Jdrift = Jo gives an expression for Jdrift 
The ideal diode equation is then 
J = Jdiff + Jdrift = Jo {exp eVA/kT &#8211; 1} 
What happens in reverse bias? The current reaches a reverse saturation value 
of Jo (~10-12 A cm-2 in Si)
All minority carriers reaching the depletion region are sucked across (i.e. the
junction &#8216;collects&#8217; minority carriers). There is no diffusion flux across the
depletion region. There is a diffusion flux outside the depletion region that
supplies minority carriers to the junction: its value is just -eni2 { pnoDp/&#955;p+ 
npo Dn/&#955;n}= -Jo. 
Reverse bias pn junction collects minority carriers
Forward bias pn junction injects minority carriers
Non-idealities: 
a) Reverse bias Zener breakdow n, where carriers tunne l through a narrow
depletion width
b) Avalanche diode, where impact ionization generates more carriers in the
depletion region. 
Handout 3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>p = ni exp (Ei -Ef)/kT
The Fermi level is flat across the junction:
eVo = (Ef -Ei)n-type -(Ef -Ei)p-type
= kT/e ln (nn/np) or kT/e ln (NAND/ni2)
Using the depletion approximation &#961; = -NAe in the p-type and NDe in the n-
type: 
E = NAe dp/&#949;o&#949;r = NDe dp/&#949;o&#949;r atx =0 
Vo = (e /2&#949;o&#949;r ) (NDdn2 + NAdp2)
dn = &#8730;{(2&#949;o&#949;rVo/e) (NA/(ND(ND + NA))} 
d = dp + dn = &#8730;{(2&#949;o&#949;rVo/e) (ND + NA)/ NAND} 
Biased pn junction (apply voltage VA)
Forward bias raises the n-side energy levels (or lowers the p-side)
by applying -ve to the n-side (or +ve to p-side)
This reduces the voltage barrier. The quasi-Fermi level is higher on the n-
side.
The diffusion term changes because the number of carriers eligible to diffuse
increases expone ntially.
The drift term does not change.
Outside the depletion region there is a net diffusion current.
Reverse bias lowers the n-side energy levels.
Diffusion is reduced; drift is unchanged. Only a small reverse current flows. 
Reverse bias increases the depletion width 
d = &#8730;{(2&#949;o&#949;r(Vo + VA)/e) (ND + NA)/ NAND} 
The ideal diode equation
In forward bias the diffusion flux increases because more carriers are able to 
diffuse. This comes from the Fermi function. When Ef is away from the band 
edge, 
f(E) = 1/ {1 + exp (E &#8211; Ef)/kT } ~ exp -(E &#8211; Ef)/kT 
If we shift the energy levels by VA, we change the available number of 
carriers by a factor
{exp -(e(Vo -VA) &#8211; Ef)/kT} / {exp -(eVo &#8211; Ef)/kT}
= exp eVA/kT
Handout 3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.15
pn Junctions
C.A. Ross, Department of Materials Science and Engineering
Reference: Pierret, chapter 5-6. 
Unbiased (equilibrium) pn junction
Imagine an abrupt pn junction. The p side has a high hole concentration and 
the n side has a high electron concentration. 
There is immediate diffusion of the carriers down the concentration 
gradient.
This leaves a space charge due to the ionized dopa nts. The resulting electric
field leads to drift of carriers in the oppos ite direction compared to the 
diffusion flux. 
At equilibrium the drift and diffusion currents are balanced. 
p type n type
electron drift
electron diffusion
Ec
Ef
Ei 
hole drift
hole diffusion Ev 
+ve 
dp
-vecharge density &#961;
p type ND n type
dn distance x 
NA 
Gauss&#8217; law E = 1/&#949;o&#949;r &#8747;&#961;(x) dx where &#961; = e(p &#8211; n + ND -NA) 
Energy (i.e. position of energy bands) = eV; can be found from voltage vs
distance; calculate from E = -dV/dx 
Depletion region width d = dp + dn (some books use d = xp + xn) 
Built-in voltage Vo: from earlier, 
n = ni exp (Ef -Ei)/kT 
Handout 3 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Overview, Carrier Fundamentals (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-15-electrical-optical-magnetic-materials-and-devices-fall-2006/resources/lecture1/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Carrier distributions (intrinsic)
g(E) dE = density of electron states cm-3 in the interval (E, E+dE), 
units #/eV.cm-3 
gc(E)dE =mn*&#8730;(2mn*(E &#8211; Ec)) / (&#960;2 3
! h
! h) dE
gv(E)dE =mp*&#8730;(2mp*(Ev &#8211; E)) / (&#960;2 3) dE
In these states, the electrons distribute according to Fermi function
f(E) = 1/ {1 + exp (E &#8211; Ef)/kT } 
Number of electrons in the interval (E, E+dE) is therefore f(E)g(E)dE.
In a dope d semiconduc tor, the position of Ef with respect to the band gap 
determines whether there are more electrons or holes.
Total number of electrons: by integrating f(E)g(E)dE 
n = ni exp (Ef -Ei)/kT
p = ni exp (Ei -Ef)/kT
where 
ni = Nc exp (Ei -Ec)/kT 
Nc = 2{2&#960;mn*kT/h2}3/2 = &#8216;effective density of conduc tion band states&#8217; 
Ei is the position of the Fermi level in the intrinsic case.
Similarly for Nv. 
Hence 
np = ni2 at equilibrium 
ni2 = Nc Nv exp (Ev -Ec)/kT = Nc Nv exp (-Eg)/kT 
Intrinsic case: 
Ei = (Ev + Ec)/2 + 3/4 kT ln (mp*/ mn*) 
In a dope d material, where n ~ ND or p ~ NA
Ef-Ei=kTln (n/ni) = -kTln (p/ni)
~kTln (ND/ni) or -kTln (NA/ni)
n-type p-type
Handout 1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.15 
Carrier Fundamentals 
C.A. Ross, Department of Materials Science and Engineering 
Reference: Pierret, chapters 1-2. 
Electron and hole charge: e = 1.6 10-19 C 
Effective mass: m*, rest mass mo
F = -eE = mo dv/dt in vacuum 
F = -eE = m* dv/dt in solid 
in Si, mn*/mo = 1.18, mh*/mo = 0.81 at 300K. 
Intrinsic properties
in Si, n = p = 1010 cm -3at 300K 
N = 5 1022 atoms cm-3 
Extrinsic properties
Donors &#8211; group V
Acceptors &#8211; group III 
B C N O 
Al Si P S 
Ga Ge As Se 
In Sn Sb Te 
Tl Pb Bi Po 
Band diagrams: Ec = conduc tion band edge, Ev = valence band edge 
band gaps: Si 1.12 eV 
diamond 5.4 eV 
silica 5 eV 
energies of dopa nt levels, in meV, in silicon (kT = 26 meV @ 300K ) 
P 45 B 45 
As 54 Al 67 
Ga 72 
Handout 1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Mayer and 
Lau,
Electronic 
Materials
Science 
Handout 1
AlAsGaP
AlSb
GaAs (D)
InP(D)
GaSb (D)
InAs (D)Si
Ge
0.65 0.64 0.63 0.62 0.61 0.60 0.59 0.58 0.57 0.56 0.55 0.5400.20.40.8
0.61.01.21.41.61.82.02.22.42.6
6.2003.1002.0671.5501.2401.0330.8850.7750.6890.6200.5630.5170.477
InSb (D)
Wavelength (microns)
Lattice constant (nm)Energy gap (eV)AlP
Indirect band gap
Direct band gap (D)Energy Gap and Lattice ConstantsProperties Si GaAs SiO 2
Atoms/cm3, molecules/cm3 x 1022
Structure
Lattice constant (nm)
Density (g/cm3)
Relative dielectric constant, er
Permittivity, e = ereo (farad/cm) x 10-12
Expansion coefficient (dL/LdT) x (10-6 K)
Specific Heat (joule/g K)
Thermal conductivity (watt/cm K)
Thermal diffusivity (cm 2/sec)
Drift mobility (cm 2/volt-sec)
(cm-3) x 1019Energy Gap (eV)
Electrons
Holes
Effective density of states
Conduction band
Valence band
Intrinsic carrier concentration (cm -3)5.0
diamond
0.543
2.33
11.9
1.05
2.6
0.7
1.48
0.9
1.12
1500
450
2.8
1.04
1.45 x 10104.42
zincblende
0.565
5.32
13.1
1.16
6.86
0.35
0.46
0.44
1.424
8500
400
0.047
0.7
1.79 x 1062.27a
amorphous
2.27a
3.9
0.34
0.5
1.0
0.014
0.006
~9Ge
0.67 
Properties of Si, GaAs, Si O2, and Ge at 300 K
Figure by MIT OCW.
Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>Physical Constants, Conversions, 
and Useful Combinations 
Physical Constants 
Avogadro constant 
Boltzmann constant 
Elementary charge 
Planck constant 
Speed of light 
Permittivity (free space) 
Electron mass 
Coulomb constant 
Atomic mass unit N, = 6.022 x particles/mole 
k = 8.617 x 10-'eV/K = 1.38 x J/K 
e = 1.602 X 10-l9 coulomb 
h = 4.136 x 10-IS eV . s 
= 6.626 x lo-" joule . s 
c = 2.998 x 10" cm/s 
co = 8.85 X 10-l4 farad/cm 
rn = 9.1095 x lo-" kg 
kc = 8.988 x lo9 ne~ton-m~/(coulomb)~ 
u = 1.6606 x kg 
Useful Combinations 
Thermal energy (300 K) kT = 0.0258 eV = 1 eV/40 
Photon energy E = 1.24eVatX = 1 pm 
Coulomb constant kce2 = 1.44 eV . nm 
Permittivity (Si) E = e,e, = 1.05 x 10-l2 faradlcm 
Permittivity (free space) q, = 55.3e/V . pm 
Prefixes 
k = kilo = I@; M = mega = Id; G = giga = 10'; T = tera = 1012 
m = milli = p = micm = n = nano = IW9; 
p = pica = lo-'' 
Symbols for Units 
Ampere (A), Coulomb (C), Farad (F) 
Gram (g), Joule (J), Kelvin (K) 
Meter (m), Newton (N), Ohm (a) 
Second (s), Siemen (S), Tesla (T) 
Volt (V), Watt (W), Weber (Wb) 
Conversions 
1 nm = m = 10 A = cm 
1 eV = 1.602 x 10-l9 joule = 1.602 X 10-l2 erg 
1 eV/particle = 23.06 kcal/mol 
1 newton = 0.102 kg,,, 
lo6 newton/m2 = 146 psi = lo7 dyn/crn2 
1 Fm = cm 
0.001 inch = 1 mil = 25.4 pm 
1 bar = lo6 dyn/cm2 = Id ~/m~ PHYSICAL CONSTANTS, CONVERSIONS, AND USEFUL COMBINATIONS
Physical Constants
Useful Combinations
Prefixes
Symbols for Units
ConversionsAvogadro constant
Boltzmann constantElementary chargePlanck constant
Speed of light
Permittivity (free space)Electron massCoulomb constantAtomic mass unit
Thermal energy (300 K)
Photon energyCoulomb constant
Permittivity (Si)
Permittivity (free space)
Ampere (A), Coulomb (C), Farad (F), Gram (g), Joule (J), Kelvin (K)
Meter (m), Newton (N), Ohm (W), Second (s), Siemen (S), Tesla (T)
V olt (V), Watt (W), Weber (Wb)
1 nm = 10
-9 m = 10 A = 10-7 cm; 1 eV = 1.602 x 10-9 Joule = 1.602 x 10-12 erg; 
1 eV/particle = 23.06 kcal/mol; 1 newton = 0.102 kgforce; 
106 newton/m2 = 146 psi = 107 dyn/cm2 ; 1 mm = 10-4 cm  0.001 inch = 1 mil = 25.4 mm; 
1 bar = 106 dyn/cm2 = 105 N/m2; 1 weber/m2 = 104 gauss = 1 tesla; 
1 pascal = 1 N/m2 = 7.5 x 10-3 torr; 1 erg = 10-7 joule = 1 dyn-cmk = kilo = 103; M = mega = 106; G = giga = 109; T = tera = 1012 
m = milli = 10-3; m = micro = 10-6; n = nano = 10-9; p = pica = 10-12NA = 6.022 x 1023 particles/mole
k = 8.617 x 10-5 eV/K = 1.38 x 10-23 J/K
e = 1.602 x 10-19 coulomb
h = 4.136 x 10-15 eV .s
= 6.626 x 10-34 joule .s
c = 2.998 x 1010 cm/s
e0 = 8.85 x 10-14 farad/cm
m = 9.1095 x 10-31 kg
kc = 8.988 x 109 newton-m2/(coulomb)2
u = 1.6606 x 10-27 kg
E = 1.24 eV at l = mm
kce2 1.44 eV . nm
e = ere0 = 1.05 x 10-12 farad/cm
e0 = 55.3e/V . mmkT = 0.0258 eV _ 1 eV/40~
1 weber/m2 = lo4 gauss = 1 tesla 
1 pascal = 1 N/m2 = 7.5 X torr 
1 erg = 10-'joule = 1 dyn-cm Figure by MIT OCW.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Data Storage (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/3-15-electrical-optical-magnetic-materials-and-devices-fall-2006/resources/lecture22_23_24/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22-24</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>3.15 
Data Storage 
C.A.  Ross, DMSE, MIT
References: 
Braithwaite and Weaver, Electronic Materials, sections 3.8-10, 3.12 and 3.3 
Jiles, Introduction to Magnetism and Magnetic Materials Chap. 14 
Magnetic Recording - Tape or hard disk recording system 
Writing by induction: 
a field is produced in the gap of the core, when a current flows through a wire 
wrapped round the core. The field writes data on the disk. 
Reading by induction: 
as the head passes over the fringing fields from the bits in the medium, the 
changing flux in the gap induces changing magnetization in the core which induces a voltage in the coil. 
The medium is usually magnetized in plane. A change in magnetization direction (and the 
associated fringing field) represents a 1. No change in magnetization represents a 0. 
Head materials: soft, high permeability, high saturation magnetization. 
Permalloy, NiFe Hc ~4 A/m Bs = 0.9T mr = 20,000 (1000 @ 10 MHz) 
Sendust, FeAlSi Hc ~5 A/m Bs = 1.0T mr = 10,000 
FeN Hc ~100 A/m Bs = 2.8T mr = 1,000 
Media: Hard disk 
Al /NiP or glass substrate.
Cr underlayer with (200) texture.
CoCrPtTa&#8230; alloy with (1120) texture; grown at high temperature to obtain Cr
segregation at grain boundaries so each grain is decoupled and acts as a single domain 
particle. Pt raises K1. 
Carbon-nitrogen-hydrogen overcoat with perfluoroether lubricant. 
Track pitch &lt;1 mm, bit length ~0.1 mm. 
Tape: PET substrate (polyethylene teraphthalate) 
g-Fe2O3 (maghemite) particles in a polymer binder. Single domain; elongated for 
high coercivity, which is also raised by adding Co. This is a defect spinel structure 
(spinel is AB2O4, e.g. Fe3O4; A in the tetrahedral, B in the octahedral sites, fcc oxygen. 
Other particles have been used &#8211; CrO2, Fe, BaO-6Fe2O3 
Magnetoresistive readback 
Magnetoresistance of a magnetic material comes from the difference in scattering of spin-
polarized electrons as they pass through the material. For example Fe has &#8230;3d64s2 
electrons. In the solid there are 2.2 more spin-up than spin-down electrons, oriented 
parallel to M. If M is parallel to the current, there is more chance of scattering so 
resistance is higher: DR is small, e.g. 2% for permalloy (NiFe). 
Anisotropic magnetoresistance (AMR) R = Ro + DR cos2 q 
In a multilayer structure such as Co/Cu/Co/Cu&#8230;, Fe/Cr/Fe/Cr&#8230; or Co/Cu/NiFe, there is 
a larger effect called giant magnetoresistance (GMR). Scattering depends on the relative 
magnetization of adjacent magnetic layers: if parallel, the resistance is lower. This effect can be ~ 10%. It does not depend on the current direction, only on the relative 
magnetization of the layers. 
Handout 11 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>GMR is used to make readback heads. A stack called a spin-valve is used: 
Antiferromagnet-Ferromagnet-Nonmagnet-Ferromagnet. 
The AF pins the adjacent FM (the pinned layer). The other FM layer can rotate its 
magnetization in response to the fringing fields from the bits on the disk. The resistance of the stack depends on the angle between magnetization directions in the two magnetic layers, so is sensitive to the field from the disk. 
The AF can be FeMn, IrMn, NiO, etc; the FMs are Co or NiFe, and the 
nonmagnetic spacer is Cu (a spin valve) or Al2O3 (a tunnel junction). In the tunnel 
junction, resistance changes of ~50% can be achieved. 
Magnetoresistance is an example of a coupling between magnetism and electronic properties. There are many devices being developed to use these &#8216;magnetoelectronic&#8217; or &#8216;spintronic&#8217; phenomena, e.g. MRAM (magnetic random access memories). 
Magnetooptical Media 
Magnetooptical properties such as Faraday rotation are examples of a coupling between
magnetism and optical properties.
Kerr effect: polarized light is rotated on reflection from a magnetic material.
Faraday effect: polarized light is rotated on transmission through a magnetic material.
Kerr effects occur in all magnetic materials (Faraday effects also, if the material is
transparent). Amorphous RE-TM alloys (rare earth &#8211; transition metals), e.g. a-
(Tb,Gd)x(Fe,Co) 1-x where x ~ 0.2, have large Kerr rotations and are used in MO disks.
Other materials are Co/Pt multilayers.
The RE and the TM elements magnetize antiparallel so the materials are ferrimagnets.
The magnetization of each group varies differently with temperature, so at some
temperature the material is an AF because they exactly cancel.This is called the
compensation temperature, and it is designed to be ~ 300K. At this point, the
magnetization cannot be affected by an external field.
To write, a laser spot heats the disk locally and a global magnetic field reverses its
magnetization (which is perpendicular to the substrate, due to deposition of the film in a
field during manufacture). To read, a weaker laser is used and the Kerr rotation shows
which way the spot is magnetized (up = 1, down = 0). The Kerr effect comes mostly
from the TM atoms so is high even at the compensation temperature.
The disk is made of glass or plastic with dielectric/MO material/ dielectric/Al heatsink
layer/protective coat.
Optical media - CDs and DVDs Track pitch 1.5 mm, bit length 1- 2 mm.
They look superficially similar to MO disks, but these rely on the reflectivity of a surface.
In CDs and DVDs bits are encoded as small pits which lower the reflectivity
Write-once media (WORM) uses Al films, Te alloys, organic dyes or semiconductors
such as a-GaSb, where a laser permanently burns or melts the film to write a bit.
Phase change media is a rewritable version, where the reflectivity depends on the cooling
rate of the spot. Use Te alloys (fast cool &#8211; amorphous &#8211; reflective; slow cool &#8211; crystalline
&#8211; less reflective). This can be rewritten many times.
Handout 11 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <videos>
      <video>
        <video_url/>
        <video_title/>
        <transcript>
          <slice>
            <text_slice/>
            <time_slice/>
          </slice>
        </transcript>
      </video>
    </videos>
  </lectures>
</doc>
