<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/</course_url>
    <course_title>Gender, Sexuality, and Society</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Society </list>
      <list>Anthropology </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Social Reproduction: Reproducing Formal and Informal Class Relations (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_social/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text> 
&#8220;It is women who bridge the gap between what a household&#8217;s resources really are 
and what a family&#8217;s positi on is supposed to be&#8221; (175) 
 
contemporary examples? still gendered?  
 SO, both authors suggest, because families are dominant means of recruiting household members, and household economies are part of market economies, family
 relationships 
can and do involve economic exploitation  &#8212;  Q: What do you think? was Engels right? 
 most famously, women&#8217;s &#8220;double day&#8221; or &#8220;double burden&#8221;   doing shopping, housework, childcare, cooking on top of full day of paid work  most heterosexual 2-parent households, men doing more of this, but NOT 50%  
(especially not in households where there&#8217;s no hired help) 
 it&#8217;s not just doing the dishes or doing  the shopping, but making the shopping list; 
mental inventory of what&#8217;s in the pant ry, anticipating running  out of TP or  
Tylenol 
 not just driving kids around but knowing wh en they&#8217;re due for doctors or dental  
  apts, making the play dates, researching day care centers, etc. 
 in theoretical terms, feminist scholars have underst ood this labor in terms of: 
social reproduction &#8212; both Rapp and Nakano Glenn 
 
recognizing the economic contri bution of domestic labor 
 
1) includes physical reproduction &amp; daily main tenance of individua ls (keeping labor  
force strong) 
2) but also reproduce class divisions generationally  
 
family is also mechanism for social  reproduction in so far as we learn class dispositions 
as part of our socialization &#8212; including class-based gender acquisition 
 these dispositions are called  cultural capital  (Pierre Bourdieu)&#8212;  language/accent, 
aesthetic tastes, values, knowledge  of Culture,  exposure to cl ass-inflected lifestyle that 
we inherit, alongside economic capital, that facilitates some pe ople&#8217;s &#8220;success&#8221; in 
capitalist economy. it&#8217;s the kind of thing th at can make or break a job interview  
 so here&#8217;s another spike in the  myth of strict meritocracy  &#8212; we don&#8217;t all start as blank 
slates, with nothing but our G od-given ability and own industr y; not just economic assets, 
but also cultural assets  Q: What do you envision for yourselves, your families/careers? What do you expect? 
[we haven&#8217;t even begun to take into a ccount two-mommy or two-daddy families]  
 
&#8220;The Family Question&#8221; &#8212; recent NY Times  article on ivy league women dreaming of 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>common identity of womanhood. By not rec ognizing the different relationships 
women have had to such supposedly unive rsal female experiences as motherhood 
and domesticity, they risk essentializing  gender&#8212;treating it as static, fixed, 
eternal, and natural. They fail to take  seriously a basic premise of feminist 
through, that gender is a social construct&#8221;  &#8212; interlocks with other systems of 
inequality (Collier) 
 
Do you really get what she means when sh e says: &#8220;to represent race and gender as 
relationally constructed is to assert that the experiences of white women and women of 
color are not just different but connected  in systematic ways&#8221; (457)?? example? 
 
race makes a difference to white wome n, too, their experience of gender 
 
 
 
5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>social reproduction 
 Rayna Rapp is clearly in dialogue with Jane Collier, Ehrenreich &amp; English 
 but while Collier and E&amp;E concerned with how gender ideology  changes with economic 
transformation, Rapp is doing something different: she&#8217;s looking at gaps  between the 
ideologies  of capitalism and the more or less objective realities  of how capitalism works 
on the ground  Q: what are the ideologies of capitalism that she goes after? 
 success is NOT all about achievement &#8212; ascribed  status, inheritance, is still relevant  
 
brings up Q of the roll of FAMILY in MODERN SOCIETY 
 Rapp addresses this questi on by first distinguishing &#8220; family &#8221; from &#8220; household &#8221;: 
 households  = &#8220;entities in which people actually  live&#8221;, but also &#8220;the empirically 
measurable units within which people pool resources and perform certain tasks&#8221; &#8212; 
related to the distribu tion of resources.  
 households  (as Rapp puts it) pool resources and &#8220;are  the basic units in which labor power 
is reproduced and maintained&#8221;, and therefore fundamental  to wage labor economy 
 and family? relatives (by birth or marriage)  
&#8220;the family  is the normative, correct way in  which people get recruited into households &#8221; 
(170)  [nuclear family] 
 
Family , particularly marriage, thus provides opportunities for reproducing and also 
crossing  class lines &#8212;&gt; household with higher or lower status, more or less resources &#8212; 
esp. for women:  marrying &#8220;up&#8221; or &#8220;down&#8221; 
 
Q: why especially important for women?  
 Fredrick Engels , noting these things in 19th C, ar gued that for modern middle class 
women, MARRIAGE is a relationship of SLAV ERY, &#8220;the crassest prostitution&#8221;  
 in Engels&#8217; view, in marital ideal under capitalism: women service men (sexually as well 
as domestically), in return for having material needs satisfied (he br ings home the bacon) 
marriage is relationship of economic e xploitation; husband = bourgoisie; wife = 
proletariat  BUT people themselves don&#8217;t see this as exploitation.   Q: Why did/do women say they do what they do in the home?  
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>becoming stay at home moms&#8230; 
 Do you see it as an either/or choice &#8212; career or family?   
putting it that way only makes sense given public/private split! 
 
Why aren&#8217;t we talking about men? Or are we? 
 Is fatherhood  today equivalent to motherhood? should  it be? 
 
why is it when m-c women want fulfilling career and kids, we&#8217;re &#8220;wanting it all&#8221; when for m-c men &#8212; at least straight  men &#8212; it&#8217;s totally the norm, assumed, 
unremarkable?  
 from Nakano Glenn (456): &#8220;In the traditiona l middle-class household, the availability of 
cheap female domestic labor buttressed white male privilege by perpetuating the concept of reproductive labor as women&#8217;s work, sust aining the illusion of a protected private 
sphere for women, and displacing conflict aw ay from husband and wife to struggles 
between housewife and domestic.&#8221;  i.e., &#8220;Rather than challenge the inequity in  the relationship with their husbands, white 
women pushed the burden onto women with even less power.&#8221;(446)  As Nakano Glenn importantly notes: When we ask the government/employers for th ings like childcare provisions, we have to 
ask &#8212; who&#8217;s going to be working in thes e childcare facilities? and what will their  lives 
be like? 
 
And this is what Romero  addresses &#8212; &#8220;Who Takes Care of the Maid&#8217;s Children?&#8221; 
 Q: what social/psychologi cal repercussions from th is piece did you find most 
interesting/surprising? unfamiliar? Or what struck a cord?   ambivalence &#8212; damned if do/damned if  don&#8217;t &#8212; all decisions about having/not  
having kids, pursuing/ not pursuing career 
 problem of ideology of choice and achieved status  &#8212; assume people have lives 
they have b/c of choices they&#8217;ve made &#8212; hold people accountable for life paths 
&#8212; motherhood, analogous to career, as achieved status; also fear others will judge us 
 What can we learn from this, analytically?  from Nakano Glenn (455):  
When feminists perceive reproductive labor only as gendered, they imply that domestic labor is identical for all women and that it therefore can be the basis of a 
4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>E&amp;E and Rapp make this argument &#8212; 
 
Because they LOVE their husbands/kids.  Because they take pride in th eir home (role well performed) 
Even because it&#8217;s their &#8220;destiny.&#8221;   (God or nature) 
 
They don&#8217;t  say it&#8217;s because their labor is exploited and they&#8217;re living under 
conditions of oppression. (until 1970s) 
 that&#8217;s because of ideological separation of public / private  spheres 
     work / household      for money / for love  Engels: economic and sexual exploitation of women hidden  by the ideology of romantic 
love (marriage  for love as achieved  status) and by the descri ption of women&#8217;s domestic 
and sexual labor as wifely and maternal duties, not &#8220;work&#8221;  After all, what does &#8220;home&#8221; signify, symbolize in the modern world? (E&amp;E)  It&#8217;s a space where LOVE rules. Under modern ideology of gender and family, domestic labor is one way in which wome n have expressed their love. 
 This ideology is what E&amp;E call &#8220;the romantic solution &#8221; &#8212; buttressed by scientific 
&#8220;experts&#8221; finding in women&#8217;s psyches and biology source of innate nurturing, fragility, 
etc. &#8212; keep them (if ideally possible) out of  mean, cruel market and in protective cocoon 
of home. 
  
Like all ideologies, this story masks a very different reality: 
 A) class difference  &#8212; working class women didn&#8217;t have  luxury of staying home; their 
bodies and psyches were differe nt, but this evidence wasn&#8217;t brought into calculation of 
women&#8217;s &#8220;nature&#8221; (theorized  from middle class norm) 
 B) constructed nature of domestic/public  &#8212; what people do for love and for money &#8212; 
not so separate as we like to think  as RAPP shows, this division is an ILLUSION: Domestic/work is false distinction   
 domestic labor is absolutely crucial  to capitalist economy; HOW? 
 PLUS beyond  unpaid domestic labor, household site of informal economy :  
 
money lending, coupon-cutting, leaving ki d with neighbor during emergency  
 NOT incidental, or outside, of capitalist production; fully integral  to capitalism.  
It is crucial to the reproduction of the labor power of employees. 
2 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Arranged Marriage and Inheritance in Agricultural and Pastoral Societies (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_gndr_agra/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>this week and next we&#8217;ll study historical shifts in gender ideology  -- and ways that people 
have maneuvered within those ideologies to make status claims, in European/American 
societies 
 reference HANDOUT (factors affecting gender roles) &#8212; use it to assess not so much 
degree of gender inequality &#8212; more/less patriarchal &#8212; but pr imary ideological reasoning 
for gender inequality in differe nt cultures and societies 
 beginning with subsistence base
 &#8212; economic system (h/f; agrarian; chattel slavery; 
market capitalism) points to labor and resource allocation as  basis of social inequality
 next couple classes we&#8217;ll look at rise of capitalism and how  that affected gender and 
sexual relations  today we&#8217;ll talk about early modern agrari an Europe (Greece, Asia Minor; Spain) 
 pairing Jane Collier and beginning of Middlesex, which is historically  and culturally well-
researched  
 
looking at handout, we should be able, on basis of readings, to say something of agrarian 
Mediterranean about #s 1-5 &#8212; and more, about how these are related to one another 
 1) subsistence base &#8212; contributi ons to material needs of group 
 productive labor; division of labor 2) distribution &amp; exchange of goods &amp; services 3) child-rearing 4) sexuality 5) symbolism &amp; ritual 6) extraordinary events (who deals, and how, with unexpect ed crises, illness, etc.) 
 &#8230;  one key site where these factors intersect is FEMALE CHASTITY   (premarital virginity + marital fidelity) 
 WHY, according to Collier, do we often find a preoccupation with female chastity, sexual 
modesty, in agrarian societie s? (also pastoral ones &#8212; wher e subsistence based on herding 
cattle, camels, etc. &#8212; middle east, east Africa)  Collier: &#8220;To question the chastity of a man&#8217;s mo ther is to question his right to the status 
he claims as his. In such a world, women&#8217;s bodies appear as gatewa ys to all privileges&#8230; 
The status and reputation of a family thus rest on the degree to which its women are protected from penetration&#8212;by women&#8217;s own sense of sexual shame, by being locked away, and/or by the courage of family  men in repelling seducers&#8221; (101) 
 this exemplifies one way in which gender is a vector of social  status, and therefore, of 
inequality/hierarchy &#8212; this is Collier&#8217;s thesis 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text> 
definition of  status  of an individual = ri ghts due to and duties expected of one; person&#8217;s 
position relative to others (usu ally hierarchical in some  way) in same society  
 2 basic types of statuses, having to do with recruitment  ascribed : assigned to individual,  often (not nec.) from birth (e.g., lineage) 
 achieved : gained through special effort or ch oice; requiring special knowledge, skill,  
qualities (e.g., occupation) and that are re garded as responsibility of individual 
 do you think gender is better viewed as  an ascribed or achieved status? 
 some statuses can be either ascribed or achieved &#8212; marriage  (arranged or chosen) 
 agrarian  societies tend to emphasize ascribed statuses  (clan, age, ar ranged marriage) 
how does Collier explain this? 
 
capitalist  societies clearly based on ideal of achieved statuses  (educational degree, 
occupation, chosen marriage)  
how are differences and in equalities e xplained?  
  statuses, whether ascribed or achieved, imply roles -- refers to the dynamic  aspect of 
status; what people do and how they do it, what relationships with others they engage in, 
as person of particular status position  
all statuses must be maintained through proper performance of roles 
 
Collier is describing a shift in RO LES attached to PROPER WOMANHOOD 
 we&#8217;ll continue discussion of this historical shift tomorrow 
 
 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>gender and status  in agrarian societies 
 
last time we talked about modes of gender acq uisition: socialization, ritual &#8212; ways that 
kids learn there&#8217;s a si gnificant distinction between girls and boys &#8212; put in different 
clothing (especially for important occasions ), ritualized differentiation (counting off 
boy/girl for dodgeball). And they learn that to be a good girl/boy often means not acting 
like the other &#8212; &#8220;big boys don&#8217;t cry&#8221; (meaning that girls do); girls should sit with their 
legs closed (meaning boys don&#8217;t have to).  if gendered rituals make meanings explic it, the power of gender socialization  (as 
opposed to formal ritual) lies in its implic itness, often glossed as &#8220;common sense&#8221; &#8212; 
&#8220;just the way things are&#8221; wit hout explicit reason given:   share a sense of what is meant 
by &#8220;boys will be boys&#8221;, &#8220;be a good girl&#8221;  while powerful, kids internalize gender lessons only to an extent  there&#8217;s often a gap b/w soci al reality and ideology 
 
definition of ideology : official story told, retol d, to articulate and, perhaps, 
explain status quo, often ine quality; dominant norms, values sedimented in our 
institutions, ritualized in public  events, elicited by others 
 in patriarchal societies, gender ideology buttresses male prestige  i.e., masculinity often more valued than  femininity; gender-neutral = masculine 
rather than feminine, like &#8220;tomboy&#8221;  and, as we&#8217;ll start to see in our readings , gender ideology can also reinforce other 
forms of social inequality : racism, class hierarchy 
 
BUT ideology is never totalizing, never co mplete story &#8212; again, masks fissures, 
tensions, contradictions, exceptions  much about gender ideology &#8216;evidenced&#8217; in  childhood has to do with adults seeing 
what we expect to see, not noticing &#8212; or att aching social significance to &#8212; 
behavior that challenges norms &#8212; AS we&#8217;ll see in Middlesex  
 SO, to understand gender, cannot merely ask &#8220;how men/women act or behave&#8221; (assuming that there is a meaningful differen ce) but rather at how individuals use gender ideologies 
creatively, strategically &#8212; or, perhaps, self-destructively  
 this is an argument Jane Collier makes   p. 101; &#8220;To understand conceptions of gender,  we cannot look [merely] at what  
men and women are or do, but rather must  ask what people want and fear, what 
privileges they seek to clai m, rationalize, and defend.&#8221;  
and how they use gender to do so 
 
1 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Other Genders/Sexualities (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_gndr_sexua/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>indeed, sex-segregated initiation rites a nd male homosocial/homosexual events are 
infused with feminine elements &#8212; gender is n&#8217;t absolute difference in ideology here  
 
 semen = mother&#8217;s milk (&#8220;when the semen falls into my mouth, I think it&#8217;s the  
milk of women&#8221; &#8212; easily identified as homo sexual experience?) 
 penis = flute; breast = flute  flute is animated by female spirit [male body is vessel; again, seeming inversion]   
and the ritualized insemination necessary to make &#8220;real&#8221; men prepared to  
survive heterosexual encounters  with women for procreation!  
 
ritual embodies contradiction (ideology is never seamless) 
 ultimately, what&#8217;s ritualized here is male prestige , rather than sexua l orientation or 
essential gender differentiation      Annick Prieur&#8217;s Mema&#8217;s House  
 let&#8217;s get a handle on the terminology: joto =  (passive) homosexual, prefers men exclusively and usually passive role 
jota = feminine passive homosexuals (&#8220;queens&#8221;) vestida = jota who consistently dresses as woman 
 
core of these definition is preferring pa ssive role, in keeping with feminine 
presentation &#8212; ideological link b/w position  and appearance  
 femininity in man suggests wants to be penetrated 
masculinity suggests wants to penetrate  
mayate = masculine men who penetrate jotas + also have sex with women  
(external label &#8212; they would simply call themselves &#8216;men&#8217;; acts &#8800; identity) 
 tortilla = mayate sometimes takes pa ssive position with men, sometimes active 
 bisexual = tortilla = internacional = alternating active/passive roles   [implicit &#8212; if take active role with men, then will also have sex with women]  buga = term used by homosexuals who designa te men they think only have sex with  
 women; only penetrating role; also used to describe manly men, macho   
 2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>other ways of c onceiving gender/sexualities 
 
first, I want to underscore the point that not  only are identity cat egories oversimplified, 
individual identities are not necessarily st able &#8212; may not plot on graph as single dot 
 this is why anthropologists  like Weston talk about the uses of gender, gender-typed 
qualities: men and women make use of  both femininity and masculinity 
 does it make sense to speak in similar way about sexuality? uses of sexuality, sexuality-typed qualities?    readings for today: different articulations between categ ories of gender and of sexuality 
 
Gilbert Herdt 
well-known anthropologist, stud ied Sambia in Highlands of Papua New Guinea in 1970s, 
with return trips throughout  the 1980s; now heads Human Sexuality Program, San 
Francisco State U. 
 his work addresses 1) the role of ritual  in gender/sexuality 
2) the multiple ways gender/se xuality can be interrelated 
3) distinction b/w sexual acts and &#8220;orientations&#8221; (as identity)  according to Herdt, the Sambia can be said to have a sex/gender system &#8212; strong binary 
oppositions between male and female, accompanied by a strict gender division of labor 
&#8212; but they do not not have an equivalent sexuality/gender system 
 instead, male sexuality and female sexu ality not equivalent categories 
female = natural and heterosexual (orientation, acts) male = cultural and sequentially bisexual (first homosexual, then heterosexual)  first, notable that they regard females as more naturally &#8220;complete&#8221; &#8212; less in need of ritual elaboration (seemingly differe nt from European traditions)  
 why?  &#8220;ritualized male homosexuality&#8221; &#8212; secret rites, hidden from women (they don&#8217;t know) 
 if blood makes femaleness, semen make s maleness and must be ingested,  
culturally acquired through initiation rituals 
 FILM CLIP  for all he narrates rituals as &#8220;men making men&#8221;  or &#8220;masculinizing men&#8221; there&#8217;s quite a bit 
of feminine imagery!  
 1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Making Modern Mothers (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_make_mod/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>22</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text> Making Modern Mothers: Ethics and Family Planning in Urban Greece  
 
based on fieldwork I conducted in Athens 1993-95  how I set out, and w ith what questions&#8230; 
 can you explain the title?  what cultural changes do I track?   women evaluated on basis of sexuality &#8212;&gt; mothering  motherhood as purpose &#8212;&gt; achievement  (consumerism)  controlling nature of sensuality &#8212;&gt; controlling natu re of f
 ertility 
 questions, points of clarification?  discussion questions:  How do I use "ethics" to unde rstand how gender operates, and has changed, in urban 
Greece? Ho
w does "nature" enter into gender constructions? Do you think this model is 
specific to Greece, or might it be usefully applied to and/or adapted for another cultural setting, like the US?  How would you characterize the moral disc ourse of abortion in Greece? H
 ow does it 
contrast with how abortion is debated in the US? Under what circumstances are Greek 
women seemingly able to reconcile use of  abortion and proper motherhood? In what 
ways might this be both "good" and "bad" for women? 
 How does family planning advocacy in Greece (a nd elsewhere) "rationalize sex"? W
 hat 
repercussions does this have? Given that fam ily planning is something that Greeks want 
to be able to do, how might condoms and other contraceptive methods be better 
advertised and presented to poten tial users? Or sex ed promoted? 
 How is it that the Greek government, which professes nationalist concern over Greece's 
declining birthrate (pronatalism
), offers legal, potentially state-s ubsidized abortion and 
other liberal family planni ng policies? How do intersecting ideologies of gender and 
nationalism (i.e., maternal citizenship) inform  these apparently paradoxical governmental 
positions, and with what repercussions for Greek families?  
In so far as motherhood is a &#8220;choice,&#8221; then, pol iticians see it as an either/or choice 
&#8212; you are a mother or you are not; if you are, m 
ight as well have many children. 
 Meanwhile, urban Greek women want the &#8220;choice&#8221; to have children and a caree
 r 
or employment.   </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>not surprisingly, legalized  abortion has not had the demographic effect the 
politicians hoped for.  
 The state politicians&#8217; naive belief in the power of &#8220;rational choice&#8221; neg
 lects the 
economic and infrastructural cons traints on reproductive &#8220;choice.&#8221;  
 Rather than see the maternal pensions and legalized abortion in conflict with one another, viewed together we can see them contribu
te to a modern  construction of women&#8217;s civic 
duty that is based on the liber al, western ideology of &#8220;choi ce&#8221; but which is nonetheless 
circumscribed by the notion that women&#8217;s ultimate civic duty, patriotic duty, is a maternal duty to produce new citizens.  </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Science, Republicanism and The Woman Question (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_woman/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>5</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>(note that activities that move from domestic to public sphe re acquire an exchange-value 
and can shift from women&#8217;s to men&#8217;s work: cooking &#8212;&gt; chefs) 
 HOWEVER, these separations, dualisms ar e NOT &#8220;natural&#8221;, old or inevitable.  
 the apparent separation of public/private s pheres when it comes to  qualitative difference 
in kinds of labor is very recent.  this is the fr
amework in which &#8220;The Wo man Question&#8221; emerged in the 19th C  
 imm
igrant stories like Desdemona&#8217;s in Middlesex also enacted the woman question &#8211; 
sym
bolized by her having to dump her silkwo rms, the basis of her livelihood, at Ellis 
Island  now, let&#8217;s return to Collier&#8217;s thesis &#8212; which E&amp;E are in agreement with&#8230;   &#8220;To understand conceptions of gender, we cannot look at what men and women are or do, but rather must ask what people want and far, what privileges they seek to claim, 
rationalize, and defend. To understand, gender,  we m
ust understand social inequality. 
And, if gender conceptions are idioms for interpreting and ma nipulating social inequality, 
then we should expect notions of femininity and masculinity to change when one organization of inequality  gives way to another.&#8221; 
 in GROUPS: evaluate hypothesis: that ideas about g/s are related to  ideas about labor  
 using Collier, Middlesex, E&amp;E and handout as guide: correlations b/w mode of 
subsistence (agrarianism v. industrial capitalis m
) and the rest &#8211; making generalizations &#8212; 
and discuss  &#8230;   
3</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text> 
2) wage labor introduced division between paid and unpaid work  &#8212; qualitative 
difference between work done in household  and work done in market  (unlike agraria
n) 
this is significant &#8212; work that doesn&#8217;t earn wages suddenly &#8220;worth&#8221; less  today, tendency to see &amp; accept symbolic and st ructural separation b/w different kinds of 
labor &#8212; in ma
rket society: 
 1) productive labor
  
  in market economy, labor that generates wages, income = purchasing power to meet 
basic needs &#8211; commercial transa ctions in market society 
 and other  kinds of labor that people do, but are not seen as &#8220;productive&#8221; in sam
e way 
 2) reproductive labor
 &#8212; making and raising babies; phys ical and emotional labor of 
feeding and nurturing; social izing good citizens and future workers and members of 
ethnic/religious communities 
 
sustaining people on a daily basis: cooki ng, cleaning, feeding, se xing (conjugal right 
of sexual servicing), taking care of sick and elderly  
3) work of status enhancement
 (middle classes) &#8212; promote so cial worth and prestige of 
families and husbands. Raising well-adjusted children and be smart consumers. Stay at home mom has become symbol  of middle-upper class status. 
 
4) &#8220;kinwork&#8221; and &#8220;community work&#8221;
 &#8212; maintaining kin networks through sharing work 
and resources; also writing letters, arranging family even ts and parties, emotional 
support. Narrator in Middlesex : &#8220;Didn&#8217;t my mother quiz me on uncles and aunts and 
cousins, too? She never quizzed my brother, because he was in charge of snow 
shovels and tractors, whereas I was supposed to provide the feminine glue that keeps 
families together, writing thank-you notes and remembering everybody&#8217;s birthdays and name days.&#8221; (72) 
  Often extends into community: church and community activism (from PTA to party 
politics). 
 Easy to think of separation b/w 1 a nd 2-4 as &#8220;natural&#8221; or &#8220;logical&#8221;: 
  Dom estic
  capitalist market 
 Private   public 
Unpaid   paid 
 Love   money  Family   co-workers/bosses/employees  Reproduction  production 
Women  men 
2</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>&#8220;The Woman Question&#8221; 
 Collier writes:  &#8220;To understand, gender, we must unde rstand social inequality. And , if gender 
conceptions are idioms fo r interpreting and manipul ating so
cial inequality, then we 
should expect notions of femininity and masculinity to change when one organization of inequality gives way to another.&#8221; (101)  Collier is writing about 20th C rural Spain, but similar dynamics took place in England, US, in 19th C &#8212; transition from agrarian so ciety (what Ehrenreich and English call the 
&#8220;Old Order&#8221;) to modern, industrial society  Ehrenreich and English ALSO write that sh ift in subsistence base was accompanied by 
shift in the idiom
 in whic
h people unders tood inequality &#8212; haves and have-nots &#8212; AND 
thus also understand gender, sexuality, marriage, etc.   E&amp;E frame discussion of the shift in gender id eologies with a shift from agrarianism
  to 
market capitalism in 19th C England and America as &#8220;The Woman Question&#8221;   how would you phrase &#8220;The Woman Question&#8221;? 
 what are women to do/what are women good for, when wage labor  reorganized 
how people thought about work 
 wage labor  is different fr
om all previous labor re lations (products of labor could be sold; 
laborers could be sold (slaves, indent ured servants); but not labor itself) 
 w
age labor  = idea that E can buy W&#8217;s labor for X  amount of time, and by extension all 
products of that labor for duration  of that time. 
 Requires the idea that a worker is &#8220;free&#8221; to SELL his own labor; that is, need sense that a person OWNS his own labor power (productive capacity) (as if  property) and thus can 
sell this belonging for $ wages.  
as opposed to the vision of a person as a &#8220;dependent&#8221;; who is not free to dispose 
of his/her labor because dependent o
n the support of another person (indentured 
servant, appr
entice, tenant farmer, sl ave &#8212; AND in 19th C, woman; legally 
&#8220;belonged&#8221; to father and then husband [classic patriarchy]) 
 what did wage labor system do that was so  significant for how we think about social 
relations?  1) notion that get paid what labor is &#8220;worth&#8221; &#8212; different ki
nds of labor are &#8220;worth&#8221; more 
than others &#8212; we&#8217;re deserving of what we have b
ecause we&#8217;ve earned it &#8212; achieved 
status &#8212; if we aren&#8217;t successful, it&#8217;s our fault; don&#8217;t have what it takes (ideology) 
1</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .
</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Introduction to the Study of Gender and Sexuality: The Sex/Gender System (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_opening/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>1</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>6) resistance: gender bending: sex cha nge surgery, cross-dressing, hermaphrodism 
challenge gender binary m/f? or reinforce it in new ways? 
malleability and infinite variety of human behavior &#8212; and different ways this behavior is 
bundled into a sense of identity, attached to m
orality, used to legitimate social inequality 
this class is cross-listed with anthropology &#8212; I&#8217;m an anthropologist &#8212; and we&#8217;ll focus 
(though not exclusively) on an anthropological  approach to study of gender and 
sexuality. 
what is this? 
starting point is CULTURE encompasses both the things people make, do, believe 
and is a fram
e of reference &#8212; the conceptual vocabulary through which we perceive 
things, 
that gives meaning to what we make, do, believe 
we don&#8217;t just HAVE culture (traditions like Mexican quinci&#241;era or male circumcision), we THINK and DO culture &#8212; it&#8217;s the W
AY we give meaning to things 
EX: it&#8217;s not only the Barbie&#8482; Doll that&#8217;s cultural, but what we do with the Barbie&#8482; Doll &#8212; 
dutifully dress it up for a Malibu beach party? or hack off its hair and stick pins in its eyebrow? 
Culture dictates and reproduces social norms. But it also provides opportunities for subverting, resisting, m
essing with social norms &#8212; especially important to recognize 
how this works in terms of gender: dominant cultural norms, expectations are important, but even more important is how individuals interpret those norms, bend the rules of those norms, in their everyday life 
gender and sexuality, like culture more generally, are both codified by tradition, 
and also improvised in daily life 
SYLLABUS 
This is a CI course &#8212; communications intensive 
expected to com
e to class, having done the reading, ready to discuss 
classes will integrate lecture and discussion, with occasional group activities 
3 papers, at least 2 will be re-written with my comments in mind; only second will be 
graded 
3 
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>GENDER, SEXUALITY &amp; SOCIETY 
What is GENDER ? 
&#8226; the characteristics, traits that differentiate men and women &#8212; behavioral, 
aesthetic 
&#8226; what it takes to be good at being  a m an/woman  
&#8226; it&#8217;s a relational category &#8212; gender is not a euphemism for &#8220;women&#8221; 
&#8226; includes value judgments, positive and negative, associated with masculinity 
and 
fem
ininity  
&#8226; things other than people can be &#8216;gendered&#8217; &#8212; an outfit, a color (blue/pink), a sport 
the analytical concept of gender was introduced in the 1970s to indicate the social roles, characteristics, and values assigned  to m
ales and females in a given society; gender 
understood as historically and cross-culturally particular 
gender is social, not natural, not fixed  in nature &#8212; biological or cosm ological 
important implication: gender hierarchy, patriarchy, is thus social, not natural &#8212; not inevitable 
sex/gender system  of difference (sex = biology + gender = social norm
 s) 
nature/culture 
this meaning of gender has entered public, commonplace understanding 
in this class, we will use &#8216;gender&#8217; to mean social, cultural expectations and actions;  
and &#8216;sex&#8217; to refer to 
physiological characteristics 
HOWEVER, it&#8217;s important to note that the sex/gender system  has been challenged 
theoretically 
we won&#8217;t  be talking about gender as simply  the cultural elaboration  of fundam ental 
differences, given in nature, between women, as a whole, and men, as a whole 
and we&#8217;ll begin on Monday with a discussion of why  the sex/gender system , while useful,  
is inadequate for the task of understanding what it means to be a man/woman  
readings for Monday, by biologists, will explain why &#8212; come to class with a few 
sentences, drawing from
 the articles, with at least 2 arguments about the analytical limits 
of the sex/gender system
NOW let me ask &#8212; 
W
hat is, or what do we mean by, SEXUALITY ? (as opposed to sex difference) 
1 
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text> sexual desire, as an aspect of human nature  
(hormones, bodies as well as feelings, thoughts) 
sexual acts, practices, behavior &#8212; what people do sexually &#8212; within social 
relations, relations that may be characterized by hierarchy, inequality 
sexual orientation  &#8212; personal identity (gay, straight, bi) based on the gender of 
one&#8217;s generalized object of desire 
&#8220;sexuality&#8221; has to do with all of these, how desire, practice  and identity  are 
bundled together, in various ways 
SO, in this course we&#8217;ll seek to make sense of: 
1) variety in what it means to be, to live as, man/woman, historically and cross 
culturally 
readings will focus largely on the U.S., but will take us around the world 
masculinity and femininity &#8212; traits, characteristics, objects associated 
with m
en/women &#8212; do not mean the same thing everywhere, and are not 
valued  in the same way everywhere 
moreover, what it means to be woman/man differs not just based on social, cultural context, but on one&#8217;s relative position within society 
in U.S., how people experience gender, sexuality is very much informed by 
socioeconom
ic class, race or ethnicity, religion, age 
SO, we&#8217;ll talk about differences w/in as well as b/w cultures, societies 
2) variety in sexual desires, practices &#8212; and how and why they are socially 
accepted 
or stigm
atized 
again, incredibly varied around the world &#8212; from sexual modesty of  Muslim women in Middle East to ritualized male homosexuality as part of initiation ceremony in PNG 
3) reproduction of symbolic and structural inequalities between men and women 
what is patriarchy? how does it work? is the US still a patriarchal society? 
gender is an economic, as well as a social, emotional relationship 
4) homophobia and heterosexism &#8212; social pressure to conform within binary  
system
s of identity 
5) sexual violence, misogyny (including internalization of psychological 
violence) 
2 
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>choice of possible paper topics, or some flexibility in answering prompts 
writing tutor  &#8212; handout &#8212; m eeting required before 1st draft due 
the more you work with her, the better your writing will get &#8212; may or may not affect 
grade (which will also be on your critical and creative thinking) 
books and other readings on MIT server 
includes a novel ( Middlesex  &#8212; start reading early) and two ethnographies (anthro 
research) 
READINGS 
the class isn&#8217;t just about wom
en, but, admittedly, most readings attend more to  
women&#8217;s experiences 
start with general conceptual tools 1) talk about relationship b/w gender and labor &#8212; economic relationship 
2) sexuality and dif
ferent configurations of sex/gender 
3) reproductive politics &#8212; religion, race and nationalism 
QUESTIONS? ATTENDANCE and INTRODUCTIONS (what do you anticipate from class?) for MONDAY &#8212; first readings are on MIT server bring in 1-2 paragraphs (typed or legibly hand-written) with arguments about the 
analytical lim
itations of theorizing gender as  the social elaboration of biological sex 
difference 
4 
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Intersexuality (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_intersex/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Q: is this rational modern science? or patr iarchal culture? or can we separate the two? 
 
Cheryl Chase  and the ISNA  
 from the website (isna.org):   
&#8220;The Intersex Society of North America (I SNA) is devoted to systemic change to 
end shame, secrecy, and unwanted genita l surgeries for people born with an 
anatomy that someone decided is not  standard for male or female.  
 
We have learned from listening to individuals  and families dealing with intersex that: 
     * Intersexuality is primarily a problem of stigma and trauma, not gender.      * Parents' distress must not be treated by surgery on the child.      * Professional mental health care is essential. 
     * Honest, complete disclosure is good medicine. 
     * All children should be assigned as boy or girl, wit hout early surgery.&#8221; 
 
1) what do you think about routine sex assignment surgery on infants? pro/con 
2) what do you think about current tran ssexual &#8220;treatment&#8221; of &#8220;gender dysphoria&#8221;? 
  NOW: are your arguments concerning intersex  and transsexualism  philosophically, 
logically consistent? 
 
transgender/transexual  support based on essentializing gender identity &#8212; body  
is malleable but sex/gender should match up 
 
sex-assignment surgery on infants  ALSO based on sex/gender matching &#8212;  
in this sense conceptually cons istent w/ transsexualism 
 
but what about intersexual activism  (Chase)?  
based on essentializing biological sex  gender should be malleable &#8212; and sex/gender system itself challenged at least in long term; in short term, advocating &#8216;choosing&#8217; a gender identity  
 
support of transsexualism is consistent with a major criticism  of sex assignment 
surgery of intersex infants &#8212; informed consent &#8212; ascription, not achievement, of 
embodiment  
begging question of usefulness and limitations of  appealing to &#8220;nature,&#8221; natural &#8220;fact&#8221; to 
legitimate social formations &#8212; it&#8217;s a political and cultural, not strictly logical, argument   MIDDLESEX: what did you make of Eugenide s&#8217; fictional account? helpfully &#8211; through 
fiction &#8211; get at experience? 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text> 
not only modern US: ancient Sparta ns practiced infant abandonment 
 
 
WHY today insistence on 2-sex model of ge nder difference? clearly  defined binaries? 
as Fausto-Sterling noted, our institutions, laws presume 2 genders  did you read Bill Beeman&#8217;s Baltimore Sun  op-ed piece, &#8220;Who are you?&#8221; 
marriage law is one thing at stake  Q of marriage defined constitutionally as &#8220;between a man and a woman&#8221; &#8212; is that such an obvious statement? what about inters exuals? transsexuals? how WOULD the law 
define man/woman today, with ISNA and other groups to raise the question of definition? 
 
begs Q of how, as a society, we should  approach intersexuality 
 protocols established in 1950s that doctors would do sex determinations without seeking 
permission or even really knowledge of parents &#8212; idea being that gender acquisition 
would go more smoothly if no ambiguity 
 Cheryl Chase speaks of sex &#8220;determina tion&#8221; in both senses of the word&#8230; 
but this &#8220;determination&#8221; based not only on &#8220;facts&#8221; but on technological ability &#8212; 90% 
&#8220;determined&#8221; female b/c easier to &#8220;make a hole than a pole&#8221;! 
 
gender identity is a complex INTERACTION of biology and culture  (Hubbard) &#8212; not 
just one informing the other  
John/Joan case, overseen by Dr. John Money (the inspiration for Eugenides&#8217; Dr. 
Luce) 
 &#8216;Joan&#8217; grew up to identify as &#8216;John&#8217;, transitioned to masculine persona  had phalloplasty, married a woman [R olling Stone story on MIT server] 
 for the general medical community, what would count as a &#8220;successful" sex assignment 
or reassignment?  
 
often adoption by the intersexed person of the gender role corresponding to the 
sex assigned by the health care workers + "heterosexual" se xual orientation 
 
not only is equivalence b/w sex/gender at  issue, but heterosexuality as normative 
 
note that the identification of hetero sexuality is contingent upon what gender 
the person was assigned by the me dical professionals during infancy 
 
what are the cultural/ideological underpinnings of this scientific protocol? 
 
 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>intersex 
 handout: http://www.marchofdimes.com/professionals/681_1215.asp 
 
recall Anne Fausto-Sterling: about 1 in 2000 infants born wi th &#8216;ambiguous genetalia&#8217; and 
1 in 400, 5 sex-related characteristics do not correspond neatly according to binary model 
of difference  more variety than even &#8220;5 sexes&#8221; &#8212; hor monal as well as anatomical patterns 
 our Q: what are various ways in which culture-bearing humans have interpreted and lived 
with this natural ambiguity? and why? 
 a) cultures have accommodated the ambiguity   hermaphrodite (hermes + Aphrodite) 
 
1) hijra in India&#8212; not so much a &#8216;natural cat egory&#8217; of person, but a role that can  
subsume a range of sex/gender nonconformists 
including intersexuals but also what in  west would call eunuchs (castrati),  
homosexuals, transsexuals, transgendered persons 
  
anthropologist Serena Nanda interprets h ijras in the conceptu al, cultural context 
of Hinduism 
 
the hijra is marginalized, but recognized &#8212; there&#8217;s a conceptual space for intersex 
 
2) guevedoche  (&#8216;penis at 12&#8217;) Dominican Republic  
= the hereditary genetic mutation that Cal has in Middlesex, which in US 
has no popular  name and is treated as a medical condition &#8212; 5 alpha-
reductase &#8212; &#8220;treatable&#8221; 
 in US, are there ways of accepting ambiguity? &#8220;queer&#8221; identity &#8212; not based on sh ared essential identity but on shared nonconformism  
&#8212; &#8220;queer nation&#8221; or &#8220;transgende r nation&#8221;&#8212; not in thrall to bi nary sex/gender distinction 
in which biology and cultural identi ty and behavior viewed as both categorically different  
and ideally congruent   more commonly (mainstream US),  b) rejecting the ambiguity of intersex  
 
we have no social category to accomm odate ambiguously sexed individuals 
(except pornographic freak shows, like in Middlesex  &#8212; commoditization!) 
 "hermaphrodite" is not one of the opt ions available on a birth certificate 
1 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Fetal Images and Abortion Debates (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_visual/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>20</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>if self-sacrifice is expected of  mothers, then shouldn&#8217;t it be expected of pregnant women? 
nurturance now begins at conception &#8212; producin g the &#8220;perfect baby&#8221;  (blaming self for 
&#8216;defect&#8217; in fetus/baby, as we saw in Landsman&#8217;s article) 
 
in pro-life rhetoric, fetus portrayed as bot h helpless victim and autonomous, heroic 
individual  fetal images are the perfect symbol for this duality &#8212; HOW? what meanings are read from this? what analogy does Petchesky make?   fetus as free-floating &#8212; no pregnant woman in sight, just hanging on cord 
 abstract individualism (homunculus)  spaceman fetus &#8212; floating in space, daring, brave, but fragile  it&#8217;s powerful in pro-life rhetoric &#8212; making fetal personhood, after al l, is requisite for 
fetal rights &#8212; more, makes it seem self-evi dent &#8212; but only because we read visual 
images literally , as reality &#8212; objective representations, as if the camera extended our 
own subject position, access to object &#8212; brings viewers and object into same reality 
 BUT, pro-life use of fetal imagery is selective, somewhat misleading 
 
90% of abortions happen w /in first trimester (up to 12-14 weeks), only 1% after 
20 weeks (Massachusetts has a 23 week limit) 
  but the most common &#8220;public fetuses&#8221; are late term 
at 12 weeks (limit for &#8220;on demand&#8221; abortion), the fetus is just over 2 inches long 
&#8212; the head is the same size as rest of the body 
 
 also, picturing an intact fetus is misleading 
  even when late-term abortions are performed they&#8217;re generally therapeutic, when  
fetus had, say, a skull that wasn&#8217;t fully fo rmed or other massive defect OR when 
there&#8217;s some medical emergency regardi ng the woman &#8212; it&#8217;s NOT elective; very 
late abortions are nearly al ways performed on women who want  that child 
 amniocentisis can only be done between 18-20 weeks, some as early as 16 weeks (though with increased risk of miscarriage)  level-2 diagnostic ultrasound (to screen fo r ancephaly, spina bi fida) at 20 weeks 
 we can think about how this context of cu ltural representations of fetuses and their 
relationship to pregnant wome n might help us understand Linda Layne&#8217;s ethnography of 
pregnancy loss (which she prefers to &#8216;miscarriag e&#8217;, which suggests women mis-carried, 
did something wrong &#8212; like in Landsman&#8217;s article)  Layne&#8217;s article puts ultrasound in context  of social  aspect of pregnancy, other things 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>done, consumed, made to &#8220;make real&#8221; not  the pregnancy, but the coming of a child  &#8212; 
buying stuff, choosing a name , having a shower, etc. 
 
when childbirth is a rite of passage , pregnancy is a liminal stage when 
preparations are made for new statuses; ritual is important 
 
ultrasound is becoming a ritual of pregnancy  &#8220;being prepared&#8221; is a mark of &#8220;good mothering&#8221; &#8212; cont rast w/ N S-H 
 the technology is experienced by women as part  of other practices, not a thing in itself 
 
&#8220;personhood is actively constructed during the course of a pregnancy&#8221; (199) 
 parts of body  that are used indexically &#8212; hair, ha ndprints/footprints &#8212; indicating babies, 
not fetuses  
different/similar to citation of fingerprints in pro-life poster? 
symbols of humanness, uniqueness &#8212; INDIVIDUALISM 
 physical tangibility of ultrasound images &#8212; not  necessarily of own fetus, even from book 
to mark something measurable &#8212; measurab ility and realness (i f easily misleading) 
  Q: What do you make of comm odification of ultrasound imaging? (Fetal Fotos, Inc.) 
 
Fetal Fotos was founded almost a decade ago by a board-certified obstetrician. 
Our exclusive, unsurpassed prenatal imaging techniques help you bond  with your 
baby using the best systems technology has  to offer. The limited medical study 
we conduct offers extra reassurance. It is truly an experience to treasure for a lifetime. 
 
BUT people are using it differently, too &#8212; facilitating the bonding not of mother 
and child, but older kids and child, deployed father, etc. 
 
 
Q: does routine ultrasound challenge cultural support for th e legal status of abortion, 
other reproduc tive politics? 
 Q: does legal status of abortion based on wo man&#8217;s right to privacy/choice complicate the 
experience of pregnancy loss?  next week, different cultural context in whic h abortion is not black /white issue either 
politically or personally; where abortion is consistent with &#8220;real&#8221; motherhood  
4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text> 
 this is not to say that women shouldn&#8217;t do ultrasounds &#8212; or enjoy them! 
 but it&#8217;s important to recognize unintended conceptual implications of what we do 
 
it&#8217;s not evil that people buy all pink for gi rls/all blue for boys, but it can 
contribute to enduring belief in fundament al differences &#8212; including capacities 
&#8212; between boys/girls 
 next Monday we&#8217;ll discuss a counter exam ple for thinking about abortion &#8212; what it is 
and what it means &#8212; from my research in Greece 
 FIRST, let&#8217;s talk about what Rosalind Pe tchesky has to say about the power of fetal 
images  and their relevance to abortion in the US. This important article was published 20 
years ago, before the technology was so routinized  she&#8217;s not  arguing that ultrasound, or other repro technologies, absolutely &#8216;bad&#8217; &#8212; rather, 
she&#8217;s interested in the cultural assumptions that make them thinkable, and the social 
factors that inform their use, interpretation, meaning  e.g., fetal images have become ubiquitous in  pro-life campaigns. So ubiquitous that it 
might seem obvious to you, but it&#8217;s not [again, contrast with Greece next week] 
 how did this campaign begin? where did the idea come from? 
 NE Journal of Medicine  article in early 80s suggesti ng that early fetal ultrasounds 
resulted in &#8220;maternal bonding&#8221; and possibly &#8220;fewer abortions&#8221; &#8212; based on 2 isolated 
cases, not scientifically controlled for &#8212; basically, the article simply forwarded the 
hypothesis  but the National Right to Life Committee jumped on this, made The Silent Scream  
featuring a 12 week-old fetus being aborted &#8220;from the victim&#8217;s point  of view&#8221; &#8212; but is 
it?  what does Petchetsky say in her analysis of the film?  it&#8217;s the view from the camera, from an outside observer &#8212; neither from the perspective of a fetus or pregnant woman  
fetuses can&#8217;t speak or scream. 
 this is obvious what&#8217;s less obvious is the more subtle transfer of  meaning &#8212; of what it means to be a 
person who can scream or speak or has a name or has rights &#8212; a social person &#8212; to a fetus, a potential person. Anticipating personhood
. 
 anticipated personhood seems to go hand and hand with anticipated motherhood:  
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text> visualizing the fetus 
 today&#8217;s articles address the relationship be tween a pregnant woman and her fetus.  
how that relationship is e xperienced by pregnant women and represented by others is 
obviously fraught in this country b ecause it&#8217;s become so tied up in abortion politics 
 HANDOUT  (encyclopedia entry)  today I don&#8217;t want to hash out the abortion deba te itself; rather, want  to see if we can 
ferret out some of the a ssumptions that underlie how abortion is debate d in this country 
&#8212; as a debate over relative rights  with Roe, legal status of abortion is framed in te rms of individual right s: legally, right to 
privacy b/w woman and her docto r. more popularly, &#8220;right to choose&#8221; whether to carry a 
pregnancy to term &#8212; but this is misleading, b/c in legal terms it&#8217;s a &#8220;negative&#8221; right &#8212; 
free of government interference, not a &#8220;positive&#8221; right of access  3 states have only 1 aborti on provider (including S.D.) 
 criminalizing abortion has NEVER ended its  practice &#8211; legal a bortion doesn&#8217;t mean 
abortion v. no abortion, it means safe, medica lly regulated abortion v. unsafe, unregulated 
abortion  but to argue against the &#8220;right  to choose&#8221;, anti-abortioni sts have championed &#8220;right-to-
life&#8221;: pitting one set of rights against the other and reframing issue of &#8220;life&#8221; 
 
more, the language of individual rights pits mother against  fetus &#8212; makes abortion seem 
obviously antithetical to motherhood, a sign of  the rejection of maternal values and 
nurturance [see Faye Ginsburg&#8217;s Contested Lives] 
 
abortion is far more common than many Americans might believe roughly 20% of all pregnanc ies in US end in aborti on (13% in miscarriage) 
abortion rate dropped in the 1990s (under Clinton) &#8212; reasons? ( not stronger maternal 
values)  better contraceptives available  morning-after pill available  stronger economy (21% women having a bortion give reason of insufficient  
resources) 
abortion rate has gone up under Bush for inverse reasons [stats from Guttmacher Institute]  framing abortion question as  matter of rights of woman against  rights of fetus is not 
inevitable; this is makes sense only within a particular cultural logic 
 right to life movement and commercialized ultrasound emerge from (and reinforce)  
same shift: referring to fetus as se parate and distinct from woman 
1 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Gender and Agency (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_agncy_resi/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>9</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text> 
 
transformations in local power relations w ill upset patriarchal bargains &#8212; may lead 
women, depending on patriarchal bargains, to adopt seemingly conservative attitudes 
about change 
 
ex: returning to th e veil &#8212; Egypt, Turkey (secular states) 
 
new opportunities for women to work outside the home, but need to demonstrate  
adherence to virtue of feminine modest y &#8212; veil allows for modesty in public 
spaces, allows new social actions to be incorporated into older values &#8212; signals 
that women are still worthy of  respect, protection (expres sion of old values in new 
social reality &#8212; social change isn&#8217;t all or nothing) 
the veil itself isn&#8217;t a symbol of women&#8217;s oppression &#8212; in fact, many women experience  
it as just the opposite!  they pity the western woman objectif ied as sex symbol by strange men 
 
GROUPS: brainstorm patriarchal bargains in ot her readings, in the US historically or  
today 
 
strategic use of gender-typed qualities th at might give women short-term gains 
but long-term, could reinforce subordination? 
  Abu-Lughod  &#8212; &#8220;the romance of resistance&#8221; &#8212; picks up where Kandiyoti leaves off  
 
inverting Foucault: &#8220;where there is resistance, there is power&#8221; 
resistance against social power (incl uding male dominance) can tell us about how power 
works 
  Bedouin of Egypt? what &#8220;traditional&#8221; everyda y women&#8217;s resistances does she describe? 
 women cover for other women (secrets, silences) 
resistance to arranged marriages 
 &#8220;sexually irreverent discourse&#8221; &#8211; poking fun at male prestige through belittling  
manhood, sexual basis of male dominance 
 oral poetry that conveys the sentiments that violate sexual codes of modesty &#8212;  
romantic love 
 but, again, times are changing &#8212; poetry is bein g recorded almost exclusively by men;  
as the Bedouin are more sedentary, they&#8217;re more dependent on cash income and  consumer goods 
how are women accommodating male dominance w ithin a new consumer society, when  
they are losing occasions for reciting poetry?  
generational resistances: ne gligees, nail polish &#8211; to please husbands sexually  
 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text> 
context for these articles: schol ars in the 60s and 70s began to look for examples of how 
subordinated groups resist dominant power structures, not necessarily through overt 
rebellion &#8212; civil rights move ment in US, peasant uprisings in colonial states &#8212; but 
through everyday acts of subordination or a re-interpretation of dominant symbols 
 
ex: &#8220;queer&#8221; as appropriated by groups w ho had been stigmatized by this as a 
derogatory label; same with &#8220;black power&#8221;  
 
inspired by Michel Foucault: &#8220;w here there is power, there is  resistance&#8221; &#8212; people aren&#8217;t 
completely bonked over the head by ideology, aren&#8217;t completely passive in their own lives even if  politically and economically subordinated 
 
corrective to some socialist feminist analys es that reduce love to ideology (Rapp?) 
&#8220;false consciousness&#8221; 
 not coincidentally, perhaps, both authors writing about women in Muslim Middle East why do you think this might be? why perhaps especially important to rethink women&#8217;s 
&#8220;resistance&#8221; &#8212; and how to identify resistance &#8212; here? 
  Let&#8217;s start with Kandiyoti&#8217;s &#8220; patriarchal bargain &#8221;  
what does she mean by this?  Foucault: &#8220;every form of power and domina tion engenders its own forms of resistance&#8221; 
  
patriarchy (or better, male dominance) wo rks differently in different places 
women&#8217;s accommodation to male dominance has thus meant different patriarchal 
bargains  women&#8217;s agency will look different in different  contexts &#8212; isn&#8217;t necessarily going to be 
about &#8220;choice&#8221; (chosen marriage, right to choose abortion, etc.) 
 &#8220;classic patriarchy&#8221; (see Ehrenreich &amp; English) = law of fathers for women, what was the classic patriarchal bargain?   exercising power as mothers of sons, rulers of daughters-in-law 
 generational, kin-based power   Ernestine Friedl (1967) (anthropol ogist who worked in rural Greece): 
&#8220;the appearances of [male] prestige can obs cure the realities of  [female] power&#8221; 
  
precisely because women have been de nied public prestige, they are free 
to maneouver behind the scenes to  affect outcomes, often through 
manipulating men &#8212; what Abu-Lughod calls &#8220;kin-based power&#8221; &#8212; characterized here as the quintessen tially feminine trait of &#8220;cunning&#8221; 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>how is this interpreted by older Bedouin women?  
how is this interpreted by Abu-Lughod?  
 parallels with other readings? 
with Collier &#8212; shift in how gender is used to claim status positions: from  
modesty to attractiveness 
and Weston &#8212; strategic use of  gender-typed characteristics 
   
4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>gender, power and agency 
 last time, Weston importantly argued:  
&#8220;Persons do not possess  gender-typed qualities so much as they use symbols to 
fashion presentations of self  that incorporate gender.&#8221; 
 And yet, in everyday practice, many jobs ar e strongly associated with either men or 
women  &#8220;The conceptual links between gendered traits and job requirements are so powerful that 
they can influence what men on the job s ee when they watch a woman work&#8221; (142) 
 
what women conceive as calculated troubleshooting pro cedure can be otherwise 
read as lack of initiative, &#8220;natural aptitude,&#8221; or proper style  women&#8217;s inability thus becomes self-confirming
 the same can be said of racial stereotypes &#8212; Nakano Glenn  history of &#8220;servitude&#8221; traded on racist ster eotypes that black women and other women of 
color were &#8220;incapable of governing their ow n lives and thus were dependent on whites&#8212;
making white employment of them an act of benevolence&#8221; (444)   but lot of work
 went into to fabricating appearance of dependency &#8212; such as? 
  calling domestics by first name, or Anglicizing name, or using generic &#8216;Maria&#8217; 
 giving domestic&#8217;s family cast-of clothes, leftover food 
 using back door  Yet, at the same time, women and men also make use of gendered stereotypes in ways 
that can enhance their positions.  Q: To what extent does the strategic use of gendered stereotypes reproduce structural 
inequalities, symbolic basis of women&#8217;s subordination, limits on choice for both women 
and men? To what extent does the strategi c use of gendered stereotypes lead to the 
exercise of individual ch oice, personal agency? 
 this brings us to a key debate in social theory over the relationship between social 
STRUCTURE and individual AGENCY  to what extent are our actions determined by social norms, peer pressure, institutional 
constraints (e.g., even in societies that value achieved status, the status of the family one 
is born into still matters)  Abu-Lughod and Kandiyoti &#8212; rethinking th e relationship between power (male 
dominance) and &#8220;resistance&#8221; (women&#8217;s agency) 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Gender, Work and Professionalization (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_gndrdlabr/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>8</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>gendered labor 
 we&#8217;ve been looking at intersections between the so-called public/private spheres &#8212; social reproduction happens in these intersections &#8212; as does the formation of gender as a mode of social reproduction   working class masculinity/femininity &#8800; professional class masculinity/femininity 
 racial-ethnic gender formations are overlaid, too, by class  structural reasons &#8212; history of discriminatory hiring practices, unequal pay scales, 
uneven quality of public education in communities that differ widely in terms of income  
but also, more subtle means of socialization, ongoing gender acquisition into adulthood 
 
women and men become  gendered &#8212; take on &#8220;masculine&#8221; and &#8220;feminine&#8221; characteristics 
&#8212; in part through segregated labor practices (including mothering and unpaid domestic work)  this, in part, is why what &#8220;femininity&#8221; and &#8220;masculinity&#8221; means will vary for women and men who are structurally divided by class, race, ethnicity.   TODAY we&#8217;re looking at the OTHER side of the equation:  
How might we think differently about paid labor market when we look at it as being 
systemically connected to households? 
 
Kath Weston (147): &#8220;Occupational settings, no less than households and families, are loci for the production and reproduction of gender in the United States.&#8221; &#8212; again, class-specific notions of gender that are deeply connected to notions of race  GOVERNMENT LABOR STATS (overheads)  In 2002, women's labor force participation rate was 59.6 percent. In other words, 59.6 percent of women age 16 and over were working or actively looking for work.  Women comprised 47 percent of the total labor force (male and female) in 2002.  = not too many self-identified &#8220;housewives&#8221; or &#8220;homemakers&#8221; out there  what jobs were they doing?   most in &#8220;pink-collar&#8221; jobs &#8212; #1 is retail service (full-time; not including temps)  NOTE: government recently announced it was going to stop collecting gender-related occupational data  Many of you have a grasp of the history behind this: women&#8217;s employment has tended to 
be looked upon as either &#8220;desperate&#8221; &#8211; immigrant labor &#8212; or &#8220;supplemental&#8221; to a head of 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>women faculty do a disproportionate amount of uncompensated &#8220;service work&#8221; 
&#8212; asked to serve on committees &#8212; either because &#8216;better&#8217; committee members, or as token representatives &#8212; as soon as their hired; doesn&#8217;t count in tenure decisions 
 hard/soft sciences? (heavy/light labor)    
how does occupational gender discriminati on work today, when anti-discrimination 
laws are in place?  
 
not through direct exclusion, but   1) by perpetuating conditions that retain assumption that ideal worker has a wife  
(reproductive labor) &#8212; so women &#8220;choose&#8221; not to accept faculty positions at research universities if they&#8217;re interested in having kids  work/family issues are huge on MIT engineering faculty: 1/2 women faculty have kids; 4/5 men have kids 
 2) being underappreciated &#8212; not having your achievements recognized (as in trades)  3) Susan Hockfield: &#8220;the tyranny of low exp ectations&#8221;  &#8212; letters of evaluation reflecting 
expectations, stereotypes, rather than reality &#8212; always described as a &#8216; woman  scientist&#8217; 
  next time: gender and agency &#8212; important theoretical pieces that may offer tools in revising your papers 
5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>household&#8217;s breadwinner&#8217;s wages &#8212; justifying , not explaining, low wages 
 
this is what calls for &#8220; comparable worth &#8221; &#8211; equal pay for equal work&#8212; meant to redress 
but did you catch Glenn&#8217;s critique  (end of article) of &#8220;comparable worth&#8221;? 
buys into myth of meritocracy: 
  assumes jobs have objective worth based on measurable skills, education,  
productivity 
  
but what about emotional  skills of nurses, caregivers &#8212; not formally &#8220;skilled&#8221;? 
  
racial divide often at skilled/unskilled divide &#8212; comp worth doesn&#8217;t address this 
  comp worth also neglects to consider structural obstacles to entry into skilled  
jobs/professions &#8212; &#8220;pink collar work&#8221; where aren&#8217;t comp men&#8217;s wages 
   
Glenn says if we support comp worth, need to do it alongside support for &#8220;living wage&#8221; &#8212; better pay for ALL less valued jobs &#8212; social security taxes for domestics  
 readings for today go even deeper &#8212; address cultural assumptions that make &#8220;merit based&#8221; pronouncements seem  fair &#8212; that make today&#8217;s wage differentials/gendered 
career paths seem rational &#8212; a matter of personal &#8220;choice&#8221; rather than bias  BUT choice &#8800; desire, what people would want ideally; often settling for something,  
&#8220;choice&#8221; is often a pragmatic compromise 
 just because career paths today tend to be &#8220;chosen&#8221; rather than &#8220;forced,&#8221; doesn&#8217;t mean things are equitable, fair; that we&#8217;ve solved the problems   what Rosalind Williams calls &#8220;gender bias&#8221; in occupational tracking far more subtle than &#8220;gender discrimination&#8221; &#8212; and is more enduring, since can&#8217;t be legislated against  similarly, Kath Weston recognizes that notion of &#8220;discrimination&#8221; glosses rather than explains how committed men in the trades are to the idea that it&#8217;s a man&#8217;s job &#8212; and their genuine surprise to see women be good welders or auto mechanics   Let&#8217;s turn to  Kath Weston &#8212; anthropologist, director of wo men&#8217;s studies at Harvard, author of first 
research-based book on gay families ( Families We Choose, 1991)  
 
she argues that ideologies of gender, and work ability , still do help keep women out of 
the better paying, unionized skilled trades &#8212; even after gender discrimination in hiring 
made federal offence. 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text> 
HOW? What&#8217;s her argument?  &#8220;Our society describes people in general and job applicants in particular as possessors of inherent &#8216;traits&#8217; of character and competence&#8212;traits that incorporate cultural notions of gender, race, class, age, and what it means to be &#8216;able-bodied&#8217;.&#8221;  
what working-class gendered assumptions  are made about job-related traits? (141) 
 
 women have &#8220;manual dexterity&#8221;, &#8220;patience&#8221;  men have &#8220;physical strength,&#8221; &#8220;mechanical aptitude,&#8221; &#8220;aggressiveness&#8221;  JOBS, in turn, are described as having &#8220;requirements&#8221; intrinsic to the work itself   &#8220;heavy&#8221; v. &#8220;light-duty&#8221; work in trades 
microelectronics as delicate, requiring small hands  
 matching of &#8220;the right person for the job&#8221; appears to be objective &#8212; when subjective 
preconceptions are embedded in depictions of both applicant and job  BUT  in &#8220;heavy&#8221; work, do men actually lift engines? 
is welding sheet metal (&#8220;delicate&#8221;) less hazardous than other trade work? and don&#8217;t&#8217; men dominate surgery? (even with electron microscopes?) 
 At the same time, that women/men do particular kinds of work reinforces certain 
stereotypes. Makes the connection between women/being a woman and nursing (care giving), doing piecework sewing or stationary microscope work (to manufacture computer chips and small electronics) seem  self-evident.  
 Weston: &#8220;gender permeates not only the bodies and identities of workers, but production itself&#8221; (139) but this is metaphoric , cultural &#8212; not  essential, inherent to the job itself 
 Weston importantly argues:  
&#8220;Persons do not possess  gender-typed qualities so much as they use symbols to 
fashion presentations of self that incorporate gender.&#8221; 
 i.e., there&#8217;s a lot of work that goes into the appearance of difference b/w heavy/light labor exaggerated acting the part &#8212; carrying tires instead of rolling them; unnecessary safety risk  being extra &#8216;macho&#8217; in ways that make doing the work of a tradesman seem antithetical to &#8220;being&#8221; a woman.  Conceptually, not unlike sense that men &#8220;are taller&#8221; than women b/c straight couples tend to pair up that way.  
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>And women who do make it into the trades? How do they get in? How are they coached? 
 
 &#8220;blue collar dress-for-success program&#8221; (142-43) 
 these are signs  of the ability to do the job, recognition of what job entails; not 
evidence of actual skill (degree, experience) 
 meaningful gender differences aren&#8217;t essential
; they&#8217;re learned, adopted, adapted, elicited 
 &#8220;The conceptual links between gendered traits and job requirements are so powerful that they can influence what men on the job see when they watch a woman work&#8221; (142)  Weston concludes
: &#8220;Fighting occupational sex segregation begins by disentangling 
gendered displays  and notions of gendered capacity  from labor performed&#8221; (148) 
  
what if we apply this to white collar work like banking (London)  (McDowell)? 
 
women blocked from upper end of banking positions not only through infrastructural 
obstacles (&#8220;glass ceiling&#8221;) but because the jobs themselves are gendered masculine  in 
subtle ways that make women&#8217;s presence incongruous, unthinkable, if not destabilizing 
 examples from McDowell?  it&#8217;s also masculinity , too, that&#8217;s a performance 
  compulsory heterosexuality limits masculinity  and while some women &#8220;masquerade&#8221; as men (but only incompletely), others flaunt stereotypical aspects of femininity   p. 198 &#8211; you can &#8220;manipulate things&#8221; by &#8220;being more or less female&#8221;  what do you make of this?     
what if we apply Weston&#8217;s insights to the sciences like physics, professions like 
engineering? 
 
how is gender enacted in MIT culture, pedagogy?  excerpt from Rosalind Williams&#8217;s Retooling  &#8212; prof in STS and former Dean of Students 
 not merely intellectual capacity, but STYLE of thinking, reasoning  
&#8220;one sometimes hears the complaint that women students &#8216;just&#8217; get good grades, without necessarily being creative and entrepreneurial&#8221; (201) 
 
4 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Appetite, Image, Control (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_cntrl_self/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>so, for Maude, extreme weight loss didn&#8217;t reflect distorted body image (didn&#8217;t see 
herself, or fear herself, as  &#8216;fat&#8217;), but an endless form  of body work that displayed 
achievement 
 achievement for women about self-c ontrol, not power; do you agree? 
 &#8220;Bodies are imagined as resources for fitne ss and health, and the fit body is an icon for 
achieving individualism, productivity, and &#8216;sel f-actualization&#8217; within late capitalist 
consumer culture in the contemporary United States&#8221; (385)  Gremillion&#8217;s thesis: anorexia is not so mu ch a pathology, but logical conclusion of 
dominant cultural values &#8212; extreme res ponse to embodying contradictory messages of 
feminine fitness &#8212; meaning both physical fitness and social/moral fitness  understand? what do you think?  relationship b/w consumption and production?   would you agree that this is a particular problem for women? 
 now, Gremillion goes further to argue that psychiatric treatment  of anorexia contributes 
to the anorexic subjectivity &#8212; sense of se lf &#8212; because it operates within the same 
cultural logics that produce anorexia in the first place  HOW? examples&#8230;   
repercussions for emphasis on achieved status : we &#8212; particularly girls/women &#8212; both 
ARE our bodies (objectified as numbers, body parts, sensuality, reproductive capacity) 
and must continually WORK ON our bodies (to demonstrate control, status, demonstrate fitness for masculine workplace)   So, we&#8217;re at the end of the first thema tic section of class &#8212; gender and labor 
 not only have we looked at the importance of gender in the workplace,  in negotiating paid 
and unpaid labor in the domestic sphere &#8212; we&#8217;ve also talked a bout how, in a capitalist 
market-based society where status is imag ined as being based on personal achievement, 
there&#8217;s a lot of work that goes into achieving what I call in my book gender proficiency 
&#8212; to produce gender-appropriate bodi es, cultivate gendered subjectivities 
 NEXT TIME we&#8217;ll begin adding to this discussion the very crucial element of sexuality &#8212; beginning with the history of the very id ea of sexual orientation, or sexuality-based 
identity &#8212; important readings   how does sexuality complicate gender, and vice versa?  
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>control and the self 
 we&#8217;ve been talking about how gender-typed qualities &#8212; reckless courage, multitasking, nurturance, etc. &#8212; are not innate  to women and men, but ne ither are they merely learned 
by women and men (acquired through socialization) &#8212; they ar e also strategically USED 
by women and men.  moreover, people use gender-typed qualities in ways that both conform  to dominant 
expectations (making them appear self-evident) and that challenge  dominant expectations 
 what we see here is a tension between accommodation and resistance 
between internalization of norms and misidentification of norms (seeing norms  and not a counter reality)  
therefore, individual acts of resistance can turn out to reproduce old structures of 
dominance, or even produce new ones &#8212; Bedouin women buying negligees 
  what people themselves think isn&#8217;t the end of the story of social analysis 
 
 1st Q: How is it that ideology works so well?  how do people internalize as &#8220;common sense&#8221; the assumptions, stereotypes, values that 
underwrite social inequality, including gender inequality, racial and class inequality &#8212; 
and, how are some people able to resist or retool &#8220;common sense&#8221; assumptions?  
why is it that women often contribute to thei r own symbolic and material subordination? 
and sometimes even find pleasure and pride in those things &#8212; the fashion magazines, the 
dieting, double day of housework done fo r &#8220;love&#8221; on top of one&#8217;s &#8220;real&#8221; job? 
 initial thoughts at this point?  today&#8217;s readings address these quest ions through the topic of food, eating 
 the aphorism, &#8220;you are wh at you eat&#8221; is really a metaphysical  truism &#8212; not just that our 
bodies are shaped, in part, nutritionall y, but that our eating philosophies embody 
particular notions of selfhood &#8212; a notion of SUBJECTIVITY 
  what do we mean by subjectivity?   how one sees oneself as an indivi dual, within a community of others 
   Collier&#8217;s article traces a shift in subjectivity &#8212; from viewing success as a  
matter of inheritance (ascribed status) to personal achievement 
  it&#8217;s a shift in conceptualizations of selfhood, human potentiality, giving  
meaning to one&#8217;s actions 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text> 
what kind of subjectivity does Counihan see American college students enacting through their food rules?    we embody the principle of achieved status  through our relationship to food 
  thin = self-control, moral superiority  &#8212; higher social status (and economic) 
 fat = lack of self-control, lack of pride,  moral inferiority &#8212; lower socioecon status 
 eating is a way of incorp orating cultural values 
 are these shared values gendered ? do they play out differe ntly to produce gender? 
 
not that all men/wome n eat differently, but styles of eating  are gendered 
 do we see a tension here b/w agency and subordination/power and resistance? 
 
Gremillion: slender, fit body = autonomy and success for women, it also implies 
dependence on others&#8217; approval (p erhaps especially men&#8217;s) 
 
Counihan: practices th at contribute to wome n&#8217;s subordination as a whole 
(emphasis on attractiveness to men rather than, say, strength) can ALSO provide individual  women with measure of power with in status quo &#8212; patriarchal bargain 
 
 it also sorts out a hierarchy among women and girls 
 
the article on anorexia demonstrates the lo gical conclusion of the values, cultural ideas 
embedded in our food rules 
 
Helen Gremillion   
ethnography of food rules in an eating disorder  clinic (attached to  research university; 
patients come from the same demogr aphic pool as Counihans&#8217; students) 
 
let&#8217;s start with the story of 16 year-old Maude &#8212; exaggerated version of the discourse of 
Counihan&#8217;s students:  &#8220;Maude talked to me about the link b/w we ight loss and her creation of a unique and 
independent identity, which she equated with her ability to achiev e (in school and in 
other activities). For Maude, losi ng weight was no effort at a ll. But the effort it took to 
keep up with all her activiti es at increasingly lower weights balanced out the ease of 
losing weight&#8230; Maude implied that she kept lo sing weight so that she could continually 
test her ability to achieve. But, at the same time, she said that this balancing act was &#8216;no 
big deal.&#8217; It was impor tant to Maude that her achievements felt nat ural to her identity , not 
like a test.&#8221; (397)  
2 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Cultural Acquisition of Gender as Learned Behavior (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_learning/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>gender acquisition 
 turning to sociological and an thropological approaches to th e study of gender: think about 
how gender as a source of individual identity in tersects with gender as a social category, set 
of relationships  how do individuals learn gender &#8212; that they ARE gendered (have a gender) and how to live 
up to expectations for what this means? how do ideas about gender get reproduced &#8212; and transformed &#8212; from one generation to the next?  recognition that gender is lear ned behavior beginning from 1950s insight of Simone de 
Beauvoir, &#8220;One is not born, but rather becomes a woman&#8221; (or man)  BUT this can fall back into sex:gender dich otomy &#8212; we are born &#8220;i n nature&#8221; but develop 
&#8220;through culture&#8221;  WE want to keep in mind caveat learned from  biologists, that &#8220;nature&#8221; and &#8220;culture&#8221; are 
NOT entirely separate, independent domains &#8212; i.e., to talk about &#8220;culture&#8221; begs for 
consideration of the physiological or supernatur al/divine (both of which can be aspect of 
&#8220;nature&#8221; &#8212; &#8220;human nature&#8221;) &#8212; as Ruth Hubbard  demonstrated, culture  is not just thought 
and enacted, but embodied  how is gender learned? and how does it come  to be embodied? to shape our bodies? 
 
1) socialization, by  
A) example (mimicking) 
B) elicitation (how children are treated, rewarded/punished) 
 2) ritual &#8212; formalized laying out of cultural principles, norms for behavior, aesthetics, etc. 
baptism, debutante ball  
 
in any culture, these are related to local theo ries of human nature, including scientific and 
religious ones    readings  for today, from A World of Babies  &#8212; posing the question, &#8220;what if Dr. Spock lived 
in Micronesia or Bali?&#8221;   explaining socialization in terms that are cons istent with local, cultural ideas of natural 
processes (material and divine) and of personhood  Q: what did you find interesting in th ese pieces, reading them together? 
 themes:  relationship to spirit world &#8226; Do babies have the devil in  them, or are they divine? 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text> 
&#8226; nature/nurture &#8212; both cultures recognize interplay; indeed, doe sn&#8217;t make sense to try to 
separate them   Bali: reincarnation of ancestor&#8217;s soul, contributing factor   personality and character shaped by day of birth   Ifaluk:  spirit world is ever-present &#8212; in  procreation, in whether infant will survive 
 &#8226; how to teach infants, small children proper behavior?  emphasize managing emotions (without apparent  distinction b/w boys/g irls), although for 
different reasons &#8212; similar practices can have different meanings   Barrie Thorne&#8217;s  social psychology piece on gend er socialization in US 
 Thorne takes up the questions (from Eu ro-American cultural perspective)  
&#8226; &#8220;what&#8217;s in children&#8217;s nature&#8221;? &#8226; how is gender learned, how doe s gender socialization happen? 
 observations in a co-ed pre-school class  found that kids internalize adult expectations and reproduce them amongst themselves 
 
BUT they internalize these only to an extent &#8212; we can see dichotomies in kids&#8217; interactions, 
but we can also  see them bridging the di visions &#8212; sex play, gendered play, is more fluid 
than is often represented by t oy stores, parents, teachers 
 parents&#8217; insistence that they didn&#8217;t make their kid stereotypica lly boy/girl &#8212; if I didn&#8217;t try to 
ideology is never totalizing  &#8212; masks fissures, tensions, contradictions, exceptions 
 much of it has to do with adults seeing wh at we expect to see, not noticing &#8212; or 
according social significance to &#8212; behavior that challenges norms 
 insight : we should look for gendered practices , not gender roles  &#8212; see distinction? 
 how individuals use gender creatively, strate gically v. how gendered individuals act or 
behave (phrasing question that way inev itably leads to overgeneralization) 
  let&#8217;s talk more about RITUAL   
Rites of Passage 
ritualized occasion of transition from one status, social position, age to another 
can be seen to happen at a variety of scales 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text> paradigmatically in &#8220;life crises&#8221; &#8211; such as? pregnancy, childbirth, death, marriage 
 adolescence (Mead)  3 phases of a rite of passage (from Vi ctor Turner, elaborating Van Gennep): 
 1) separation  physical separation of individual from rest of society  symbolic separation from past   2) transition (the lim inal period; margin) 
 &#8220;betwixt &amp; between&#8221;  neither old status nor new one; statusless, identityless 
 &#8220;no longer classified and not  yet classified&#8221; &#8211; nonperson 
 this is the stage he elaborates &#8212; gaining of secret knowledge ; training 
 often symbolic cleansing  / rebirth (bloodletting) 
 3) (re)incorporation  return to society, but in new position, with new status &amp; new obligations &amp; rights   &#8211; new roles  e.g., birth (transition for mother to certai n kind of female adulthood; also for baby) 
 DISCUSSION QUESTIONS:  1) re-narrate Ifaluk birth as  a Rite of Passage &#8212; what elements fit the 3 stages? 
 
2) what &#8220;rites of passage&#8221; are us ed to frame transitions related to gender/sexuality in the US? 
 
 what are defining rituals in &#8220;making&#8221; a boy/girl? or graduating to adult man/woman? 
  
what do these rituals say about &#8220;what&#8217;s in child ren&#8217;s nature&#8221;? 
 
3) what other rituals teach lessons about  appropriately gendered behavior, values? 
  sum up
: learning gender &#8212; as an aspect of child  socialization &#8212; happens not only with 
reference to ideas about biol ogy (sex) &#8212; but ideas about co smology, procreation, what it 
means to be human; basic moral values; notions of personhood  
is individualism or communalism stressed?  
is being nurturing seen  as gendered, or not? 
 infant care practices reflect this set of beliefs &#8212; directed at protecting the life of children, but 
also to guide children toward becoming accepted members of their societies  
eg: co-sleeping  or separate beds/rooms &#8212; reflects moral values &#8212; developing 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>individualism, independence, or reflecting sense that isol ation = loneliness and that 
can lead to illness 
 
ALSO, we can&#8217;t talk about becoming a boy/gi rl, man/woman without specifying becoming 
an Ifaluk man/woman, Balinese man/woman &#8212; a &#8216;high status&#8217; Balinese man/woman. Etc. 
 TUESDAY &#8212; start to put this in a historical frame, and link personal categories of identity 
&#8212; girl/boy &#8212; to politic al categories of social groups &#8212; women/men 
 read first 125 pages of Middlesex, plus articles 
4 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Sexism, Racism and Violence (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_sxl_vio/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>ask: are these characterizations of violence actually the same thing everywhere? 
 
1st, think about the question,  why does violence (in general) occur? 
myriad of reasons &#8212; revenge, fear, hatre d, misunderstanding, marking difference, 
conquest, political ends, material gain  why does sexual  violence  occur? 
it&#8217;s striking how many theories focus on a single  cause, assume universality of 
occurrence and meaning  
ex: it&#8217;s a natural outcome of male sexuality [active, aggressive] (e.g., A Natural 
History of Rape: The Biologica l Basis of Sexual Coersion  = men rape when the 
costs are low and they can get away with  it b/c it&#8217;s a byproduct of evolutionary 
biology and reproductive success)   note: so much of technology, social &#8220;p rogress&#8221; is direct ed at modifying, 
controlling nature, it&#8217;s inte resting that nature seem s suddenly &#8220;uncontrollable&#8221; 
when it comes to socially contentious issues  
 flip side: 
constructivist argument: it&#8217;s a political outcome of so cially constructed male se xuality (men rape because 
they are taught they are naturally aggressive, it bolsters their masculinity)  thus Heise: &#8220;it is partly men&#8217;s insecur ity about their masculinity that promotes 
abusive behavior towards women&#8221;  
 
feminist activist mantra: rape isn&#8217;t about sex, it&#8217;s about power  
 what do you make of this position, Heis e&#8217;s analysis generally? criticisms? 
 
overgeneralizations may undermine political -moral efforts to eradicate violence 
 
a better way to think about the pervasivene ss of sexual violence might be to look at 
 HISTORY and cultural context  
militarized mass rape 
 
 &#8220;gender-based&#8221; violence is also often race/ethnicity-based or religion-based  rape, as di Leonardo points out, is rarely if ever just an act between a man (generically 
speaking) and a woman (generically speaking) &#8212; but b/w white man and black woman, or Serb man and Croat woman &#8212; specificity is important 
 
reducing rape to something boils down to man v. woman has hampered theorizing 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>sexual violence 
 let&#8217;s start with article by Lo ri Heise, who is writing about  the pervasiveness of sexual 
violence against women and child ren, &#8220;gender-based violence&#8221; 
 first, she argues for the importance  of statistical research, ma king visible such incidences 
and it is endemic &#8212; especially wife abuse/pa rtner abuse (also incest, child sexual abuse) 
 b/w 1-5 to 1-7 women in US will be subject to &#8220;complete&#8221; rape in lifetime  &#8212; obviously begging Q of definition &#8212; but still!   repercussions for family pl anning/contraceptive promotion 
 HIV-AIDS prevention  
 when condoms are targeted at women, ofte n assumed their &#8220;choice&#8221; to insist men 
use them, BUT&#8230;  Greece and elsewhere, condoms &#8212; old technology &#8212; associated w/ prostitution and extramarital affairs: to insist on a man using them w/in marriage is read as 
either questioning his fidelity or ackno wledging woman&#8217;s infidelity (why else 
need for safe sex in marriage?) &#8212; often le ads to violence, but even the perception 
of threat  of violence has kept women from raising issue w/husbands. [more later] 
 that said, Heise acknowledges hazards  of exposing the reality of violence, the  
pervasiveness of gender-based sexual violence &#8212; what are these? (p. 423) 
 
1) promoting image of victimization of wome n; all sex bad, no pleasure (esp. for women) 
 woman as passive 
 2) feeds essentializing sterotypes men=aggressive  
if universal, then biologically based = &#8220;natural&#8221; =  &#8220;good&#8221; or, at least,  
&#8220;inevitable&#8221; (more on that later)  
Q: her strategy in response?  
the anthropological veto (Peggy Sanday) 
 but are there flaws with this strategy?   flaw: anthro veto (LIKE universalist claims) assumes that sexual violence is something that could be located in any so ciety &#8212; that is, it&#8217;s not cultur e bound (after all, isn&#8217;t it all 
over the place?)  Q: are there alternative arguments? what mi ght be a better response to the hazards? 
 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>sexual violence (including thinking se xual abuse of males)  
 
rape in/after American slavery 
 
  what did you make of Di Leonardo&#8217;s essay? 
 can&#8217;t analyze away our subjective experience  &#8220;knowledge does not necessarily command emotion&#8221;  fear is shaped by cultural forces &#8212; myths,  stereotypes &#8212; we don&#8217;t always have  
analytical command over &#8212; or at least not until after the fact of initial flood of  adreinaline 
 conversely, &#8220;individual experiences shouldn&#8217;t change well-thought- out-opinions&#8221; &#8212; at 
least not necessarily  &#8212; like Foucault refusing to theorize  from his personal belief about 
the source of homosexual desire in individuals   pitfalls of &#8220;identity politics, &#8221; appropriateness of &#8220;speaking from experience&#8221; 
 how should we move back and forth between  social science analysis and personal 
experience? when is one relevant to  the other?  (pedagogical challenge) 
 importance of attending to  personal experience  
importance of not eliding personal experience and social analysis 
 
3 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>De-essentializing Sex/Gender/Kinship (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_ques/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>19</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>from article: Bronislaw Malinowski, consider ed a &#8220;father&#8221; of British social anthropology, 
did ethnographic research in the Trobriand Islands in the south Pacific during WWI 
 Malinowski argued in 1920s that yes, fa mily = human universal, he was arguing against  
19th C social evolutionists with their progre ss narrative of human cultural evolution  
(Europeans at apex; for them, the family not &#8220;n atural&#8221; but as cornerst one of &#8220;civilization&#8221; 
&#8212; evidence of western moral superiority)   Malinowsi&#8217;s cultural relativism  was well-intentioned 
 BUT undermined by fact that his argument rested on ethnocentric  assumptions: that 
family = nurturnance 
basically, he argued that since we &#8220;need&#8221; nur turance, and families = nurturance, thus we 
have families &#8212; it&#8217;s a functional  definition  
 functionalism theoretical framework characteri stic of early British social anthropology 
 for Malinowski: basic human needs:    are met through social institutions  n u r t u r a n c e      f a m i l y   procreation     kinship system  sustenance     subsistence tech, division of labor  shelter      housing design  organization     law, political systems  difference = cultural variati on in ways humans meet basic needs (hunting/foraging v.  
agriculture? patrilineage v. matrilineage?) 
similar to how gender in 70s was seen as cult ural variation of biological sex difference &#8212;  
cultural elaboration of ge nder difference was a social &#8220;need&#8221; more or less 
functioned same way everywhere 
 for Malinowski,  &#8220;family&#8221; mapped onto:  1) distinct and bounded group distin guishable from other such groups 
 2) group located in physical space &#8212; hearth and &#8220;home&#8221;  3) shared affective bonds, pa rticular set of emotions 
 family = conflation of genealogy /household/emotional intimacy 
Collier et al. point out that this is in formed by Victorian public/private division 
 
it&#8217;s ethnocentric to claim &#8220;they&#8217;re just like us&#8221; when ar gument based on reading our 
institutions and values onto their practices 
 
similarly, as we&#8217;ve seen, sex/gender system its elf to some extent ethnocentric: implies 2-
sex model of binary gender difference   
(other cultures recognize other possib ilities &#8212; perhaps 3rd sex/gender, perhaps 
blending of binaries) 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>bond&#8221;  &#8212; entitled  to immediate love a child (paying for it!?) 
 
ironies of how placements are made?  &#8220;difficult&#8221; children &#8212; older, survivor s of abuse, w/disabilities &#8212; placed  
with single parents, black parents, interracial parents 
 the kids who need the most help placed with people with fewest resources 
WHY? 
stratification of social reproduction &#8212; reproducing class status from one 
generation to the next 
  What do we learn from the juxtaposition  of 3 cases? 
6 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>&#8226; other things you found interesting, challenging &#8212; agreed/disagr eed with analysis 
 
Scheper-Hughes  learning to mother means learning when to let go, but also when it&#8217;s safe to love  motherhood is ascribed, not  achieved, status &#8212; if God wills 
 social production of indifference   mothers&#8217; reactions to infant mo rtality not autonomously authored 
  tempered by indifference of State (barely registers these deaths, or lives)   and Church (which once celebrated child death and now wants to deny it  
&#8212; while also withholding contraception and abortion) 
 motherhood is socially produced &#8212; not ju st &#8220;feelings&#8221; of &#8220;bonding&#8221; but shaped  
by contingencies, ne cessities (poverty) 
like feelings for another woman &#8800; only understood in terms of desire 
  
contrast with the social production of interest in US 
 a woman who chooses not to subordinate own interests to fetus is &#8220;unnatural&#8221; 
 Landsman 
social production of interest  &#8212; if a woman follows pren atal advice, should have 
control of outcome &#8212; motherhood is achie ved status, in our  control&#8230;.but not 
 rites of passage lacking with non-no rmal infant &#8212; not &#8220;real&#8221; mother 
shows social constructio n of motherhood &#8212; rituals do help constitute it 
failing that, these mothers go on to be super-achieving mothers  &#8220;learning&#8221; from child, not just teaching it 
 Gailey (white mother of a black child who had been abused by foster parents) 
&#8220;adoption is the result of two violations of natu ral motherhood [in US]: 
procreation without marriage and nonprocre ation within marriage. So the U.S. 
adoption triad has two failed mothers and a rejected or substitute child as the 
major players&#8221; (22) &#8212; how does th at characterization strike you? 
 
&#8226; often, &#8220;natural motherhood&#8221; script not ex tended to birth mothers in adoption,  
transformed into &#8220;bad mother&#8221; &#8212; sexually active, able to procreate, but unable or unwilling to nurture; irre sponsible; portrayed as victim (raped?) 
  myths of mothers who give up child for adoption  in reality, 2% unmarried births &#8212;&gt; adoption; women who give up babies  
for adoption higher education and class aspirations than women who keep  
 
&#8226; other side: similar to mothers of children  with disabilities (especially &#8220;difficult  
to place kids&#8221;) &#8212; the harder the child rearing, the more they become &#8220;real&#8221;  
parents &#8212; achieved motherhood &#8212; thrilled when they &#8220; earn &#8221; affection of child 
 
contrast to international adopters more likely to &#8220;return&#8221; child for &#8220;failing to 
5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>But as Collier, Rosaldo and Yanagisako  point out, &#8220;most of our talk about families is 
clouded by unexplored notions of wh at families &#8216;really&#8217; are like.&#8221; 
 
&#8220;Confusing ideal with reality, we fail to appreciate th e deep significance of what 
are, cross-culturally, various ideologies of intimate relationship, and at the same 
time we fail to reckon with the complex human bonds and experiences all too comfortably sheltered by a faith in the &#8216;n atural&#8217; source of a &#8216;n urture&#8217; we think is 
found in the home.&#8221; (first page)  in other words, when we hear about families, we often stop thinking! 
 Why?   C, R,Y suggest that b/c family has been on private side of public/pri vate division (itself 
illusion, but with real effects for how people ac t) &#8212; as a society we&#8217;ve failed to grapple 
with the complexity of what goes on in the name of the family, in the name of love 
 not merely a matter of law, but of culture  &#8212; we don&#8217;t want to  see legal officials 
make random checks of domestic settings (which of course they do when families are receiving state support) &#8212; aren&#8217;t a lot of checks on what happens in families  Adrienne Rich wrote in her article on &#8220;compulsory heterosexuality&#8221;: to believe 
that intimacy is part of what a family/marriage is has also meant we often limit our search for intimacy to the family &#8211; can be an inhospitable place in patriarchal 
societies (law of fathers)  for women and children  
 
of course family can also be inhospitable place for gender/sexuality non-
conformists &#8212; boys who like to dress up, girl s who refuse to s it still or who are 
overweight, etc., coming out to parents of ten most difficult hurdle &#8212; stakes are 
high  [then again, our belief in the sanctity of the home as space of privacy has also 
served &#8212; eventually &#8212; as a basis for legitimating homosexuality &#8212; anti-sodomy laws struck down as unconstitutional, infringement on privacy]  In any event, 
 we need to closely examine what we mean by these terms &#8212; not just sexuality, but family, marriage, motherhood, fatherhood &#8212; not  take their meanings for granted &#8212; 
recognize they are not transhisto rical &#8216;things&#8217;, but pr oducts of particular  social, political, 
economic histories &#8212; and therefore subject to ongoing cultural &amp; legal interpretation 
 To see them otherwise, to see them as universal and fixed (as early  anthropologists did), 
is to miss the specificity and maleability of our own definitions and understandings  
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text> de-essentializing sex/gender/ kinship; querying motherhood 
 
moving to final topic: from th inking about sexuality &#8212; as de sire, behavior, identity, and 
various constellations of the 3 &#8212; to re productive politics &#8212; no t unrelated stories 
 helpful transition is to recall the history we traced (Katz) of contrasting sexual ethics: 
 procreative ethic of sex  &#8212; sex is productive of babi es, producing babies is good, 
therefore &#8212; in this way &#8212; sex is good  pleasure ethic of sex  &#8212;  sex is pleasurable, can be t hought of and valued apart from 
procreation  the pendulum swings of sexual ethics (agr arianism to capitalism; post WWII baby boom 
to Playboy&#8482; &amp; 60s sexual liberation)  has been matter of emphasis , not absolute 
difference &#8212; not mutually exclusive; both available for rhet orical appeal &#8212; certainly 
today:  pleasure ethic today bolstered by increasing vi sibility of homosexual lifestyles &#8212; straight 
people don&#8217;t want to miss out on pleasure part &#8212; but increasing &#8220;abstinence-only&#8221; sex ed 
new voice for procreative ethic (more in couple weeks)  sex can  be procreative; sex can be pleasurable &#8212; it&#8217;s often neither 
what we&#8217;re talking about are reigning ideologies  of what sex &#8220;is&#8221; and should be , how 
people expect to experience  it, and why we should value  it &#8212; its significance as a 
component of &#8220;human nature&#8221;  
missing from this distinction (Katz) is how these comp eting ethics have been 
differentiated by &#8211; and used to differen tiate --  not only along an axis of sexuality  (while 
many heterosexuals were committed to procreative ethic, homosexuals carved out 
alternative identity based on a different attitude toward sex, pleasure ethic) but also of 
gender  &#8212; among heterosexuals (once we get that  category), procrea tive ethic has been 
applied more consistently to women  than to men &#8212; women&#8217;s &#8220;natural&#8221; sexual desire said 
to be aimed at procreation mo re consistently than men&#8217;s 
 these sexual ideologies have flip-flopped  frequently enough in recent history &#8212; even 
your lifetimes &#8212; not difficult to realize that sexuality &#8212; how people experience 
themselves and others as sexual beings &#8212; is historically and culturally produced, shaped  
 however
, it may be more difficult to view motherhood  in the same way &#8212; as 
ideologically produced, &#8220;socially constructed&#8221; &#8212; but it&#8217;s true  sexuality, motherhood, marriage, The Family (cap ital letters) &#8212; these are all pieces of the 
same puzzle &#8212; elements that some have de picted as the &#8220;founda tion of society&#8221; or, 
alternatively, as the &#8220;foundati on of civilization&#8221; &#8212; a particul ar, exhaulted, type of society 
 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>  
problem of functionalist  thinking: &#8220;because a social institution is observed to  
perform a necessary function does not mean either that the function would not be 
performed if the institution did not exist or  that the function is responsible for the 
existence of the institution&#8221; (73)  just because we can descri be it, &#8220;see&#8221; it, doesn&#8217;t m ean that&#8217;s what&#8217;s going on 
 SO, instead of asking, is The Family a human universal? Need to ask: What do we mean 
by family? (is there A Family?) 
 Instead of assuming all mothers are by defin ition, or by nature, nurturing and loving, we 
have to ask: What does nurturance look lik e? Does it look differe nt under different 
circumstances? What is mother love? What makes a mother?  Instead of assuming all children better off with biological mothers, or that they &#8220;need&#8221; both a father and a mother, we  need to ask: What do we mean by &#8220;real&#8221; mothers? What 
distinguishes fathering and moth ering? Is what makes a &#8220;good&#8221;  father similar to &#8220;good&#8221; 
mothering, or different? Are both equally nurt uring? If a woman who isn&#8217;t biologically 
related to a child can mother, can a man mother?    remaining readings for today are about 3 qui te different ethnographi c cases that raise 
similar questions, engage similar issues  &#8212; questioning assumptions about &#8220;real&#8221; 
motherhood and &#8220;real&#8221; families  
1) selective maternal neglect  of poor women in Brazilian shanty towns (Nancy Scheper-
Hughes) 
2) mothers of children with disabilities in upstate NY, struggling with status as &#8220;real&#8221; 
mothers (Gail Landsman) 3) transracial and international adoption (Christine Ward Gailey) 
 each of these cases calls in to question common assumptions among Americans about the 
meaning and experience of motherhood &#8212; as definition and lived reality 
 have to understand this in context of wider meanings of personhood, love, agency, 
marriage, family  divide you into 3 GROUPS to collectively analyze  these case studies  
 &#8226; what assumptions that you held (or see as  commonly held) were revealed to be  
assumptions? overgeneralizations? 
&#8226; how do gender, sex (action), sexuality (identity ) come together in this case &#8212; or not? 
&#8226; what do we learn about families, mothering, nurturing &#8212; what these are/aren&#8217;t?&#8212; how  
might case study push us to rethink general understandings about what makes a &#8220;real&#8221; family or counts as &#8220;real&#8221; mother ing? &#8212; implications for current debates? 
4 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Is Sex to Gender as Nature is to Culture? (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_sex_gndr/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>we read gender onto  sex, not from  sex 
 
2) experientially, gender (being a man or woman) isn&#8217;t reducible to sex difference &#8212; not enough to talk categorically about &#8220;women&#8221; on one hand and &#8220;men&#8221; on the other  what it means to be a woman or a man &#8212; even to have a &#8220;male&#8221; or &#8220;female&#8221; body &#8212;  has to do with various historical, cultural and social factors  
corset wearing upper-class woman prohibited from working and her domestic servant &#8212; different bodies, different strength, different health  class, occupation, race, ethnicity, religion (attitudes toward sensuality)  AGE &#8212; physical/cultural/emotional manifestations of masculinity/femininity different when 14 than when 24, 54, 74 
 
be aware of the force of binarisms, but also the work that goes into appearance of 
binarisms 
 
readings for Wed &#8212; if gender isn&#8217;t just rooted in biology, how do we get it? gender acquisition through cultural means  
5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Is sex to gender as nature to culture? 
 ATTENDENCE  last time, introduced gender as an analytical concept  social roles, activities; aesthetic appearances; stereotypical characteristics, cultural  
meanings associated with being men and women 
 even if sex difference seen as given in nature, gender is culturally variable and historically changing  concept of &#8220;gender&#8221; was meant to stress social/cultural origins of gender inequality  This alignment of sex/gender with nature/culture gets us into loops about what counts as nature and what&#8217;s culture, and about what &#8220;nature&#8221; and &#8220;culture&#8221; mean.  
 The so-called &#8220;culture wars&#8221; often have to do with arguments about &#8220;nature&#8221;, what&#8217;s &#8220;natural&#8221; behavior &#8212; and therefore something that should be accepted, not judged (we&#8217;ll discuss arguments about sexual identity, gay marriage). OR, &#8220;natural&#8221; behavior could be subject to medical &#8220;treatment.&#8221;   want to avoid the &#8220;naturalistic fallacy&#8221; &#8212; that what&#8217;s natural is good, or inevitable (this is a cultural belief)  readings for today are both by biologists who challenge our assumptions about the &#8220;nature&#8221; of women and men  Let&#8217;s FIRST go through their arguments SECOND assess the analytic limitations of sex/gender as theoretical framework FINALLY ask where that leaves us, terms of how to think about what gender is, or might be  Ruth HUBBARD (Harvard professor emerita) begins article, &#8220;On Women&#8217;s Biology&#8221; by arguing that women&#8217;s physique, in contrast to men&#8217;s, is a social construct and a political concept, not a scientific one.&#8221; What does she mean?  biology is &#8220;socially constructed&#8221; (doesn&#8217;t exist &#8216;in nature&#8217; as such, in and of itself)  Rather,  1) biology is perceived, interpreted, described through cultural lenses 2) culture also actually shapes biology    
dialectical relationship nature/culture, can&#8217;t cleanly separate them becoming more obvious: GM foods, IVF  
examples: !Kung menstruation patterns 
do not menstruate until 18 yo (high activity levels, diet); get pregnant, breastfeed 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#8212; beyond procreative roles 
 
bottom line : biology is not a stable thing in itself; it doesn&#8217;t ground culture. Therefore sex 
difference cannot really ground gender (if it pr ovides justification, this connection itself 
is not inevitable).  BUT, for now, we DO have ideological i nvestment biological difference -- why? 
&#8220;biological differences b/w women and men are used to rationalize the stratification of 
the labor force by sex; they do not explain it&#8221; (124)  NATURALIZATION   
Anne Fausto-Sterling, biologist at Brown University 
 in &#8220;The Five Sexes&#8221; she argues that humans do not all fall naturally into neat binary categories of male/female   F-S says that there are not simply two sexes. Why? sex is not just one thing; there are many different variables that go into making it: 
GENES: X and Y chromosomes 
 HORMONES: estrogen, androgens  GONADS: ovaries, testes  GENITAL: clitoris, penis  SECONDARY: hair, breasts;  (BEHAVIOR, gendered)  (note that sexual orientation &#8212;orientation of sexual desire&#8212; is yet another matter)  These don&#8217;t always line up in individuals; there is a spectrum.   estimated 1 in 2,000 babies born with ambiguous genetalia, making it difficult for doctors to pronounce automatically &#8220;it&#8217;s a girl&#8221; or &#8220;it&#8217;s a boy&#8221;  So here, Fausto-Sterling suggests &#8220;at least&#8221; a five-sex model, naming three intersexed 
categories:  herms : so-called true hermaphrodites, who possess one testis and one ovary in same 
organ merms : male pseudohermaphrodites, XYs who have testes and vagina and clitoris (do not  
menstruate) 
ferms: female pseudohermaphrodites, XXs who have ovaries and aspects of male genitals &#8212;  
clitoris and penis similar organ 
 (note, however, that even these more complex binary correspondences only work if one &#8216;sex&#8217; is taken as the model for the other; where, for example, is the vagina in this model?)  
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>intensively for 2-3 years; repeat cycle until menopause at late 30s/early 40s 
so: shorter reproductive span, 4-5 kids w/out contraception, few menstruations 
 in US, girls who are athletes delay or stop having period generally speaking onset becoming younger, high fat diet but also, perhaps, due in part to growth hormones in meat, milk  what does it mean to say that women&#8217;s biology is &#8220;socially constructed&#8221;? 
 not that it isn&#8217;t &#8220;real&#8221; &#8212; have real effect, creates real muscles, etc.  indeed, Hubbard wants us to attend to the material effects of cultural ideas of gender   but biology is not destiny (contra Freud, who said &#8220;anatomy is destiny&#8221;) 
 biology and society, nature and culture continuously reshape one another 
 
think about how women&#8217;s bodies have changed through time, varied according to 
other social categories  
a lot of work goes into producing gendered bodies &#8212; effort to tame unruly secondary sex 
characteristics &#8212; plucking, shaving, dying hair; voice training   &#8220;we need have no ideological investment in whether women and men exhibit biological differences, aside from the obvious ones i nvolved with procreation. .. we cannot know 
whether such biological differences exist b ecause biology and society (or environment) 
are interdependent and cannot be sorted out&#8221; (128).   Q: what did you think of her arguments? about men&#8217;s and women&#8217;s relative strength, height differences &#8212; search for &#8220;natural&#8221; limits?  socially sanctioned childhood activities create gendered bodies &#8212; AND the marked categories of the &#8220;tomboy&#8221; (girls who like sports) and the &#8220;bookworm&#8221;(boys who don&#8217;t)    _______________        _______________    we focus on the uneven ends, rather than the overlap 
   
  &#8220;We need to pay attention to the obvious contradictions between stereotypic descriptions of women&#8217;s biology and the realities of women&#8217;s lives&#8221; (127)   examples?  &#8220;Sex differences are interesting in sexist societies that value one group more highly than the other&#8221; (129).   
and it&#8217;s amazing how durable are commitments to biologically based difference 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>in a later article, she says 5 sexes aren&#8217;t enough &#8212; new classifications based also on 
hormones rather than anatomy of gonads and genitalia (problems of classification) HANDOUT 1  
and note that one of these conditions, Progestin-induced androgenization, is iatrogenic , meaning induced by medical treatment of the body 
 Intersex could
 be culturally valued, it HAS been valued historically (and is, elsewhere, 
other cultures, as we&#8217;ll see), but it isn&#8217;t (here). Doctors think they&#8217;re doing a favor to children and parents in modifying intersexed individuals.  medical and legal institutions have worked to preserve appearance of dual system  well intentioned, about &#8220;fitting in&#8221; &#8212; but this is a concern b/c modern &#8220;Western culture 
is deeply committed to the idea that there are only two sexes.&#8221;   
commitment to unambiguous binary gender difference AND HETEROSEXUALITY  these are institutionally  fundamental to western societies 
 
 organizes inheritance, who can marry whom, paternity, hereditary titles, eligibility for  
professions, draft registration (earlier, voting rights), anti-sodomy laws 
 sports: Olympics, between 1968-2000 female athletes had to prove they&#8217;re female;  chromosome tests, DNA &#8211; dozens have failed (excuses made for pulling out)   majority disorders XY but androgen deficiency &#8211; no advantage  &#8220;if the state and the legal system have an interest in maintaining a two-party sexual system, they are in defiance of nature&#8221; (21)  if we didn&#8217;t  suppress these differences, what might that mean for society?  
 we&#8217;ll read later about the Intersex Society of America, against sex reassignment surgery, also Middlesex (protagonist has androgen insensitivity w/ 5-alpha reductase deficiency) 
 SO, what are the analytical limitations of sex/gender formulation?  1) binary sex difference isn&#8217;t natural either &#8212; sex is not a natural, binary, clearly dimorphic category of difference &#8212; rather, we force a range of natural differences into binary categories and take pains to stage dimorphism (tall women not pairing up with short men)   i.e., binary &#8220;sex&#8221; difference is not given in &#8220;nature&#8221; &#8212; so it cannot be a natural underpinning for gender or anything else  
4 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Invention of Sexuality-based Identities (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_sex_iden/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>we read gender onto  sex, not from  sex 
 
2) experientially, gender (being a man or woman) isn&#8217;t reducible to sex difference &#8212; not enough to talk categorically about &#8220;women&#8221; on one hand and &#8220;men&#8221; on the other  what it means to be a woman or a man &#8212; even to have a &#8220;male&#8221; or &#8220;female&#8221; body &#8212;  has to do with various historical, cultural and social factors  
corset wearing upper-class woman prohibited from working and her domestic servant &#8212; different bodies, different strength, different health  class, occupation, race, ethnicity, religion (attitudes toward sensuality)  AGE &#8212; physical/cultural/emotional manifestations of masculinity/femininity different when 14 than when 24, 54, 74 
 
be aware of the force of binarisms, but also the work that goes into appearance of 
binarisms 
 
readings for Wed &#8212; if gender isn&#8217;t just rooted in biology, how do we get it? gender acquisition through cultural means  
5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Is sex to gender as nature to culture? 
 ATTENDENCE  last time, introduced gender as an analytical concept  social roles, activities; aesthetic appearances; stereotypical characteristics, cultural  
meanings associated with being men and women 
 even if sex difference seen as given in nature, gender is culturally variable and historically changing  concept of &#8220;gender&#8221; was meant to stress social/cultural origins of gender inequality  This alignment of sex/gender with nature/culture gets us into loops about what counts as nature and what&#8217;s culture, and about what &#8220;nature&#8221; and &#8220;culture&#8221; mean.  
 The so-called &#8220;culture wars&#8221; often have to do with arguments about &#8220;nature&#8221;, what&#8217;s &#8220;natural&#8221; behavior &#8212; and therefore something that should be accepted, not judged (we&#8217;ll discuss arguments about sexual identity, gay marriage). OR, &#8220;natural&#8221; behavior could be subject to medical &#8220;treatment.&#8221;   want to avoid the &#8220;naturalistic fallacy&#8221; &#8212; that what&#8217;s natural is good, or inevitable (this is a cultural belief)  readings for today are both by biologists who challenge our assumptions about the &#8220;nature&#8221; of women and men  Let&#8217;s FIRST go through their arguments SECOND assess the analytic limitations of sex/gender as theoretical framework FINALLY ask where that leaves us, terms of how to think about what gender is, or might be  Ruth HUBBARD (Harvard professor emerita) begins article, &#8220;On Women&#8217;s Biology&#8221; by arguing that women&#8217;s physique, in contrast to men&#8217;s, is a social construct and a political concept, not a scientific one.&#8221; What does she mean?  biology is &#8220;socially constructed&#8221; (doesn&#8217;t exist &#8216;in nature&#8217; as such, in and of itself)  Rather,  1) biology is perceived, interpreted, described through cultural lenses 2) culture also actually shapes biology    
dialectical relationship nature/culture, can&#8217;t cleanly separate them becoming more obvious: GM foods, IVF  
examples: !Kung menstruation patterns 
do not menstruate until 18 yo (high activity levels, diet); get pregnant, breastfeed 
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#8212; beyond procreative roles 
 
bottom line : biology is not a stable thing in itself; it doesn&#8217;t ground culture. Therefore sex 
difference cannot really ground gender (if it pr ovides justification, this connection itself 
is not inevitable).  BUT, for now, we DO have ideological i nvestment biological difference -- why? 
&#8220;biological differences b/w women and men are used to rationalize the stratification of 
the labor force by sex; they do not explain it&#8221; (124)  NATURALIZATION   
Anne Fausto-Sterling, biologist at Brown University 
 in &#8220;The Five Sexes&#8221; she argues that humans do not all fall naturally into neat binary categories of male/female   F-S says that there are not simply two sexes. Why? sex is not just one thing; there are many different variables that go into making it: 
GENES: X and Y chromosomes 
 HORMONES: estrogen, androgens  GONADS: ovaries, testes  GENITAL: clitoris, penis  SECONDARY: hair, breasts;  (BEHAVIOR, gendered)  (note that sexual orientation &#8212;orientation of sexual desire&#8212; is yet another matter)  These don&#8217;t always line up in individuals; there is a spectrum.   estimated 1 in 2,000 babies born with ambiguous genetalia, making it difficult for doctors to pronounce automatically &#8220;it&#8217;s a girl&#8221; or &#8220;it&#8217;s a boy&#8221;  So here, Fausto-Sterling suggests &#8220;at least&#8221; a five-sex model, naming three intersexed 
categories:  herms : so-called true hermaphrodites, who possess one testis and one ovary in same 
organ merms : male pseudohermaphrodites, XYs who have testes and vagina and clitoris (do not  
menstruate) 
ferms: female pseudohermaphrodites, XXs who have ovaries and aspects of male genitals &#8212;  
clitoris and penis similar organ 
 (note, however, that even these more complex binary correspondences only work if one &#8216;sex&#8217; is taken as the model for the other; where, for example, is the vagina in this model?)  
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>intensively for 2-3 years; repeat cycle until menopause at late 30s/early 40s 
so: shorter reproductive span, 4-5 kids w/out contraception, few menstruations 
 in US, girls who are athletes delay or stop having period generally speaking onset becoming younger, high fat diet but also, perhaps, due in part to growth hormones in meat, milk  what does it mean to say that women&#8217;s biology is &#8220;socially constructed&#8221;? 
 not that it isn&#8217;t &#8220;real&#8221; &#8212; have real effect, creates real muscles, etc.  indeed, Hubbard wants us to attend to the material effects of cultural ideas of gender   but biology is not destiny (contra Freud, who said &#8220;anatomy is destiny&#8221;) 
 biology and society, nature and culture continuously reshape one another 
 
think about how women&#8217;s bodies have changed through time, varied according to 
other social categories  
a lot of work goes into producing gendered bodies &#8212; effort to tame unruly secondary sex 
characteristics &#8212; plucking, shaving, dying hair; voice training   &#8220;we need have no ideological investment in whether women and men exhibit biological differences, aside from the obvious ones i nvolved with procreation. .. we cannot know 
whether such biological differences exist b ecause biology and society (or environment) 
are interdependent and cannot be sorted out&#8221; (128).   Q: what did you think of her arguments? about men&#8217;s and women&#8217;s relative strength, height differences &#8212; search for &#8220;natural&#8221; limits?  socially sanctioned childhood activities create gendered bodies &#8212; AND the marked categories of the &#8220;tomboy&#8221; (girls who like sports) and the &#8220;bookworm&#8221;(boys who don&#8217;t)    _______________        _______________    we focus on the uneven ends, rather than the overlap 
   
  &#8220;We need to pay attention to the obvious contradictions between stereotypic descriptions of women&#8217;s biology and the realities of women&#8217;s lives&#8221; (127)   examples?  &#8220;Sex differences are interesting in sexist societies that value one group more highly than the other&#8221; (129).   
and it&#8217;s amazing how durable are commitments to biologically based difference 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>in a later article, she says 5 sexes aren&#8217;t enough &#8212; new classifications based also on 
hormones rather than anatomy of gonads and genitalia (problems of classification) HANDOUT 1  
and note that one of these conditions, Progestin-induced androgenization, is iatrogenic , meaning induced by medical treatment of the body 
 Intersex could
 be culturally valued, it HAS been valued historically (and is, elsewhere, 
other cultures, as we&#8217;ll see), but it isn&#8217;t (here). Doctors think they&#8217;re doing a favor to children and parents in modifying intersexed individuals.  medical and legal institutions have worked to preserve appearance of dual system  well intentioned, about &#8220;fitting in&#8221; &#8212; but this is a concern b/c modern &#8220;Western culture 
is deeply committed to the idea that there are only two sexes.&#8221;   
commitment to unambiguous binary gender difference AND HETEROSEXUALITY  these are institutionally  fundamental to western societies 
 
 organizes inheritance, who can marry whom, paternity, hereditary titles, eligibility for  
professions, draft registration (earlier, voting rights), anti-sodomy laws 
 sports: Olympics, between 1968-2000 female athletes had to prove they&#8217;re female;  chromosome tests, DNA &#8211; dozens have failed (excuses made for pulling out)   majority disorders XY but androgen deficiency &#8211; no advantage  &#8220;if the state and the legal system have an interest in maintaining a two-party sexual system, they are in defiance of nature&#8221; (21)  if we didn&#8217;t  suppress these differences, what might that mean for society?  
 we&#8217;ll read later about the Intersex Society of America, against sex reassignment surgery, also Middlesex (protagonist has androgen insensitivity w/ 5-alpha reductase deficiency) 
 SO, what are the analytical limitations of sex/gender formulation?  1) binary sex difference isn&#8217;t natural either &#8212; sex is not a natural, binary, clearly dimorphic category of difference &#8212; rather, we force a range of natural differences into binary categories and take pains to stage dimorphism (tall women not pairing up with short men)   i.e., binary &#8220;sex&#8221; difference is not given in &#8220;nature&#8221; &#8212; so it cannot be a natural underpinning for gender or anything else  
4 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Nationalism, Reproductive Politics and Gender (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_gndr_citi/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>21</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Maintaining a fairly consistent RATIO, 20 Arab/80 Jewish is important to the very notion 
of &#8220;Israel&#8221; as a Jewish state &#8212; otherwise, w ould have to be recognized as a &#8220;binational&#8221; 
state 
women have served states in two senses  as symbolic &#8220;bearers&#8221; of the Nation: 
quantitative  bearers o
f the nation&#8217;s children, and qualitative  bearers of tradition 
1) quantitative: birthing citizen s, carry the perpetuity of the nation in their wom bs 
here, women&#8217;s civic duty is about producing numbers through reproducing, 
birthing, new citizens &#8212; new workers, new so ldiers for security (if mandatory 
military service, size of army dir ect reflection of size of population) 
pronatalism v. antenatalism (China&#8217;s one child policy) 
Israel (Greece, Romania): pronatalist 
these states have presented wom
en with aw ards for the patriotic  duty of producing 
very large families &#8212; Mothers of the Na tion&#8212; in Israel, awards to &#8220;Heroine 
Mothers&#8221; (10 kids) was stopped after it became clear that Arab women were 
winning most of the awards  
Clearly, national projects are invested not ju st in sheer num bers of a population, but in 
generating the right SORTS of  numbers, people, citizens 
2) qualitative &#8212; reproducing the cultural trad itio ns and values that bind together the 
nation, keep them unique, which women do by socializing  children &#8212; nurturing specific 
cultural values &#8212; and by  setting the good example 
August Comte (writing in th e early years of the F rench Republic) &#8212; said women 
should serve as the repository of moral valu es, which will be preserved in them  if 
they stay out of politics and business.  The im age of Woman on a pedestal. 
when public/private spheres separated, also  gendered &#8212; had to do with rise of 
nation-state, as well as wage labor and capitalism 
Kanaaneh&#8217;s work: Palestinian citizens of Israel have adopted this dual outlook: 2 
reproductive strategies, both of which ideolo
gically related to wo men&#8217;s reproduction of 
Palestinian nationalism 
1) birth more babies to overwhelm the Jewish Is raelis, just as they fear (quantitative) 
2) have fewer children, educate them well, and present a stronger front in that way  
(qualitative) </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>class # 21: gender and citizenship 
today I want to expand the parameters of our  analysis to think a bout how nationalism  and 
the interests of state governments help to construct gende r, make sexuality meaningful in 
particular ways 
juxtapose two articles by anthropologist R hoda Kanaaneh (who grew up in a Palestinian 
f
amily in Israel) 
1) &#8220;Boys or Men?&#8221; &#8212; discusses how mascu linity  is informed by state citizenship,  
nationalism; there&#8217;s a common analysis of  the militarization of masculinity 
BUT the case of Palestinian Israelis presents interesting complication &#8212;  
here, where there&#8217;s popular opposition  to the state, a critique of state 
collaborators (Arab soldiers volunteering to serve in the Israeli army) is 
carried out in a gendered idiom &#8212; militarism  does not represent a valued 
masculinity 
2) in previous work, culminating in Birthing the Nation  (2002), Kanaaneh presents an 
analysis, again from
 case study of Palestinian Israelis, of how state interests concerning 
population issues have been forwarded through the control of wo men&#8217;s bodies, through 
regulating their sexual ity and reproductive capacity &#8212; a case of population policy being 
played out through reproductive politics (we&#8217; ll see another example next week, Greece) 
let me talk generally, and then get into sp ecifics of case of Arab  citizens of Israel 
first, what do I mean by gendered citizenship? 
citizenship entails the rights and obligations  of a m ember of a nation in return for 
protection by a state 
what those rights/obligations have been  has historically been marked by gender 
example of gendered diffe rence in citizen ship? 
suffrage &#8212; women got vote in US in 1920 military service has been expected of men but not women (exception of 
Jewish citizens of Israel) 
gendered citizenship plays out more subtly, too 
human reproduction &#8212; family size, how desire d f
 amily size is achieved (birth control), 
etc. &#8212; is of great political interest 
It&#8217;s through being born into families that citizens are m ost often made 
case study: Israel, state of majority immigr ant Jewish population (any Jew can apply for 
autom
atic citizenship), plus indigenous Ar ab minority population &#8212; state borders do not 
map neatly onto national ones: meant to be  state for entire Jewish diasporic nation. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Kanaaneh calls this &#8220;the reproductive meas ure&#8221; &#8212; family size used as indicator of 
how &#8220;modern&#8221;/&#8221;traditional&#8221; you are &#8212; not ju st econom ic class, but social outlook 
in global context 
Now let&#8217;s think about additional LEGACIE S and CONSEQUENCES of these ideas 
In particu
lar, real-life reperc ussions of women&#8217;s &#8220;r ole&#8221; as bearers of the nation&#8217;s children 
and traditions. 
Kanaaneh: &#8220;women are considered mark ers of national bound aries, not only 
sym
bolically, but physically as well&#8221; 
If women are charged with guaranteei ng the perpetuation of the hom eland, its 
people and culture, there&#8217;s the problem that  fem ale bodies are permeable &#8212; in the 
same way the national territory in war is vulnerable 
physically : 
fe
male bodies are permeable just as the national territory in war is vulnerable 
this equation makes women particularly vulnerable to sexual violence  during and 
following war 
symbolically : 
women, like the land/nation, mark borders of &#8220;a people&#8221; and also seen as the 
property of men that, like land, must be defended 
military recruitment posters &#8212; nation as female 
problem of gay men in the military? lacking wife/kids? 
clearly, reproduction is politics 
Susan Gal and Gail Kligman ( The Politics o f Gender After Socialism ) argue that &#8220;public 
debates about reproduction make politics&#8221; 
e.g., Kanaaneh&#8217;s &#8220;reproductive measure&#8221; &#8212; how &#8220;traditional&#8221; or &#8220;modern&#8221;? 
abortion debate in the U.S. &#8212; for some, a political &#8220;litmus test&#8221; 
what about MASCULINITY and state citizenship? 
if women&#8217;s  ultim ate service to nation, civic duty, is to give birth to male citizens and 
sacrifice them as soldiers, men&#8217;s ultimate civic duty has been depicted as willingness to die 
for their country 
military service = masculine citizenship 
what&#8217;s the twist in Kanaaneh&#8217;s study of  Palestin ian soldiers in Israeli army? </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>masculinity is crucial to self-identity and la beling by others, but not the standard soldier 
masculinity &#8212; as member of minority populatio n, joining the state army is seen as 
traitorous &#8212; figured as &#8220;immatur e&#8221; masculinity (&#8220;boys&#8221; seduced by guns) 
role of state in framing rhetoric? 
parallels in US history? 
assimilation v. selling out &#8212; civil rights in US 
RACE: African American military servi ce du ring WWII (segregated regiments) 
sparked 1950s civil rights movement (a nd anti-assim ilationist movement of 
Malcolm X)&#8212; grounds for contes ting second-class citizenship 
SO: gender is forged no t only within economic relations, but within conditions set by 
states ; government policies a nd nationalist rhetoric </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Transvestite Lives and Sex Work (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_memas/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>easier for families to accept homosexual tendencies than feminine presentation &#8212; WHY? 
  we&#8217;ve been talking about gender &#8212; what it m eans to be proper man/woman, what&#8217;s read 
as masculinity/femininity &#8212; but what about patriarchy ? male domination (as Prieur 
says)?  by being improper men in displaying passive  femininity, reinfor ces idea that proper 
masculinity is active, aggressive, do minant &#8212; exception proves the rule 
 
in reducing femininity to sexual passivit y, ideology perpetuates male dominant 
view of proper womanhood; but this is reductive, fictional &#8212; women&#8217;s 
subjectivities are not reduced to passive sexuality 
 however much jotas make of their feminine gender identity, Annick Prieur demonstrates 
through ethnographic observation that their gend ering is more complicated than their own 
depictions suggest &#8212; HOW?   they&#8217;re not women (can lead to health pr oblems, violence, disillusionment) 
  they&#8217;re not entirely not masculine &#8212; examples of how they operate in the world  
in ways that are coded masculine?  
physical toughness, fist fights competitiveness (whose breasts bigger, better, etc.) 
 what does femininity boil down to for them? passive role in sex, ability to attract  
manly men &#8212; exaggerated feminine app earance &#8212; not just feminine signs, but 
feminine signs of s exual availability &#8212;  far from a femini st understanding! 
 embrace certain aspects of feminine suffe ring &#8212; for beauty, if not for children 
physical fighting, masculine competitiveness, messiness 
 &#8226; gender is not straightforward matter of personal &#8220;choice&#8221; (class makes a difference) 
&#8226; vestitas, in fetishizing or parodying feminine sexuality, can be seen more to reinforce  
dominant gender stereotypes (dualistic  model) than to challenge them 
 
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Prieur surmises complex combination of biol ogical, cultural and social factors that 
crystalize into self-perceptions and identities depending on cultural context 
 Personal Origin Stories &#8212; the stories they tell about themselves to explain who they are  what is a common narrative among the jotas ? 
  innate tendencies &#8212; dolls, dressing in mother&#8217;s clothes, fascinated by  
penises 
  early sexual abuse (age 6-8), possibl y triggered when adults recognized  
their &#8220;homosexual or feminine tendencies&#8221;; discovery: &#8220;liked&#8221; it 
 how might we unders tand, interpret this? 
   
&#8220;patriarchal bargain&#8221;?  classic patriarchy = law of fath ers (manliness often = abuse) 
 see Marta&#8217;s story  what can we discern about the cultural c ontext in which this story makes sense? 
 ideology that all men are potentially homosexual &#8212; indeed, percentage of Mexican men who have sexual experiences with other men is significant, probably well over 50%&#8212; 
notion that if they try passive  role they might like it, and th en they&#8217;d have to come to 
terms (according to jotas) with this self-re alization &#8212; tortillas who deny taking passive 
role are &#8220;repressed homosexuals&#8221; &#8212; jotas ar e essentializing this identity based on 
pleasure/practice &#8212; not so much a matter of choice or preference, but &#8220;born that way&#8221; 
 do mayates confirm this? 
no &#8212; more constructivist view &#8212; fear that they may learn that they like it (not 
inevitable) 
 what&#8217;s particularly problematic for the mayates  about this? why the apparent denial of 
passive pleasure among the tortillas ?  
  homosexual desire (def ined as passive) = feminine gender characteristics  
 homosexuality is strongly linked with emasculination, not being a man  active bisexuality (penetrating men) not ma rked as &#8216;homosexual&#8217; but also is not  
an open identity &#8212; neither accepted nor stigmatized, but hidden 
 not &#8220;closeted&#8221; because not attached to inner sense of authentic self 
 in Mexico, don&#8217;t have (or only among mi ddle classes) machos who prefer sex  
with men exclusively and claim ho mosexual identity (gay) &#8212; no &#8220;popular 
class&#8221; Macho Men, hypermasculine gay men with built physique and 
cropped hair  
in Mexico, gender is a stricter binary  category than sexuality, whereas the  
opposite is the case in the US 
 what did you make of the jo tas relationships with their families ?  
 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>Annick Prieur&#8217;s Mema&#8217;s House  
 
an ethnography of contemporary Mexico City   first, aside from my book, th is is only full-scale ethnogr aphy we&#8217;re reading; it&#8217;s 
an example of the kind of study that is behind many of the articles we&#8217;re reading  so it&#8217;s worth talking a bit about what it is that anthropologists do &#8212; research 
methodologies what is the sense that you get from Prieur?  
participant-observation &#8212; not quantitative studies, but qualitative sense of how 
people think about what they do  &#8220;thick description&#8221; (from Clifford Geer tz) = observations plus multiple meanings 
held by those observed plus meanings discerned by the anthropologist within theoretical and comparativ e context &#8212; doing a cultural &#8220;reading&#8221; of multiple 
meanings, where those meanings come from, and what implications they have for behavior.  any impact on research the fact that Prieur is a woman?   
 in Mexico City, what is sexual identity based on? what sexualit y-based identities are 
meaningful?  active/passive position  + gender  performativity, the projection of gendered codes 
 how does this case complicate American notion of &#8220;sexual identity&#8221;?  &#8220;preferring men&#8221; has different meaning, different implications for  
identity appearance gender system  
 Prieur addresses the common question: What causes homosexuality ? 
 Q: what do you make of this question itself? useful? what does it assume? 
 is the homosexuality/desire of jo tas same as that of mayates? 
is the homosexuality/desire the same betw een lower and middle class men in Mexico? 
 what&#8217;s interesting anthr opologically is how people themselves, in different cultural 
settings, construe identities based on sexuality, gender, race (which we know 
scientifically is not a valid categor y of biological differentiation), etc. 
 
1 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Do Western Sexual Identities Travel? (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_other_iden/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>do western sexual identities travel? 
 are our categories and assumptions about the meaning of sexuality, developed in the  
US/Western Europe, applicable  to non-western settings?  
or do they obscure our understa nding of sexuality elsewhere? 
 can insights from other cultural settings be brought back to shed light on the possible 
limitations of our own assumptions about sexua lity, gender, identity here in the US? 
 Anick Prieur&#8217;s book offered our first pointer  &#8212; men having sex with men doesn&#8217;t have 
the same meaning in terms of identity, gende r, sexuality in Mexico and in the US 
 Swarr and Nagar&#8217;s article on experiences of women in same-sex relationships in India 
and South Africa &#8212; clearly argue that the voc abulary, assumptions developed in western 
academic contexts do not  necessarily do justice to these women&#8217;s experiences &#8212; speak to 
their concerns  according to Swarr and Nagar, what are limiting assumptions of western feminism, regarding lesbianism?  western feminism tends to view lesbianism first and foremost in terms of desire &#8212;  
in the &#8220;west&#8221; there&#8217;s an increasing emphasis on external expression of inward feeling, as 
captured in &#8220;coming out&#8221; narratives &#8212; but in Third World contexts (or rural, working 
class contexts of US) this can be oversha dowed by NEEDS &#8212; economic survival, social 
survival (including threat of violence)  
western theorizing of sexuality has focused on the INDIVIDUAL &#8212; as unit of analysis 
valuing of autonomous individual aut horing her own destiny (achievement) 
but in many parts of the world, local ideol ogy cannot separate individual from FAMILY, 
CLAN, COMMUNITY &#8212; shared resources, shared  status, shared survival strategies 
 
this contributes to subjective experience of even something as &#8220;private&#8221; as sexuality 
 they write, &#8220;we seek to reconceptualize desire  itself not as innate  or inherent but as 
emerging in conjunction with processes such as development, neocolonialism, apartheid, 
and liberalization&#8221; (495)  from reading, can you explain what they mean  by offering example, illustration of &#8220;how 
the politics of intimacy, sexual ity, and access to resources inte rtwine in everyday lives&#8221;? 
 stories of Geeta and Manju in Chitrakoot, India; Cora and Phakamile in Soweto, SA 
 what &#8220;take home messages&#8221; di d you get from this article? 
 &#8226; even poorest women in most patriarchal setti ngs are not bereft of sexual agency &#8212; they 
too have emotional lives &#8212; not ju st prerogative of the privileged  
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Ogai&#8217;s story 
 
2 of 18 were women whose fathers killed thei r mother or older sister; wanted to make 
themselves unmarriagable so fathers wouldn&#8217;t profit from their bridewealth 
 
HOW does the PNG case help us reali ze the cultural logics behind common 
interpretations of prostitution/sex work in th e US &#8212; make it thinkable, even &#8216;natural&#8217;  
what are assumptions of  our cultural logic? 
 1) women = sexually desirable objects  (men&#8217;s desire is active force) 
2) sex as a commodity &#8212; object of desire me n willing to purchase, and from other side,  
act of sex = compensable labor (&#8220;oldest profession&#8221;) in which men are purchasers 
public/private &#8212; sex for $ &#8800; intimate, emotional 
 why don&#8217;t these cultural logics help make sense of PNG situation? not applicable? 
ideology of desire 
men are the objects of desire &#8212; cultivate beauty to attract women women, not seen as naturally beautiful, mu st often resort to magic to attract men 
 what about the men? what are they paying for? 
 sometimes nontraditional sexual practices would never ask of wives  more, paying for &#8216;modern&#8217; masculinity &#8212; men are resisting sexual taboos,  
based on procreative/kinship ethic 
 passenger women say that when a man offers $ for sex, evidence that he&#8217;s so  
consumed with desire that he&#8217;s overcome his fear of women and their vaginas &#8212; out of gratefulness rather than contempt &#8212; which women read 
as their &#8220;vanquishing&#8221; of men 
  with these cross-cultural comparisons in mind, return to Q:   what&#8217;s problematized around gender/sexuality in contemporary US?  what are the 
questions asked of ourselves and of each other? assumptions within which current 
debates about gender/sexuality &#8212; from sexual identity, to transgender, to commoditized 
sex &#8212; are articulated?  
3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text> 
&#8226; complexity  of identity questions &#8212; not just &#8220;inter sectionality&#8221; (gender / sexuality / race 
/ class), not just carving identity into different slices of pie  
 &#8226; problem w/ identity politics: experien ce isn&#8217;t strictly based on who we are 
 also our personalities, our family rela tionships, our luck in love &#8211; things  
that are never given demographic boxes 
 &#8220;extending intersectionality&#8221; means reconceptualizing &#8220;differen ce&#8221; with reference to 
material and emotional specificitites  &#8212; from struggles over ri ghts (do women have full 
citizenship? is homosexuality  legally recognized?) and re sources (can women have 
exclusive access to money th ey earn?) to intimate rela tionships (family support? 
economic strings attached [jotas]? frie ndships, emotional support?) &#8212; sorts of 
relationships &#8220;people enter in to with or without labels&#8221; 
   &#8220;sex for money&#8221; in Papua New Guinean Huli, Holly Wardlow  terminology: from prostitution  to sex work  to sexual networking  &amp; survival sex  &#8212; 
what different meanings implied in these terms?  sex work emphasizes labor component (safe, legal, fairly paid)  income-generating activity  rather than totalizing identity   
 reducing stigma 
 but still embedded moralization: if &#8220;work&#8221; th en has to be acceptable, even  
perhaps virtuous (especially if supporting kids) 
 of course, even these caveats can&#8217;t be generalized  again: can&#8217;t assume that similar-looking practices (women and men having illicit,  
hidden, one-off sex after which man gives woman some money) mean the same things in different places 
 in Wardlow&#8217;s interpretation of Papua New Guinean Huli &#8220;passenger women&#8221;, economic factors &#8212; scarcity, poverty &#8212; alone cannot ac count for or fully explain commoditized 
sex   these women aren&#8217;t exchanging sex for m oney strictly out of economic necessity 
why, then?   resistance against restrictive feminine  roles tied to  reproduction 
anger and revenge against male kin who do not behave  
 again, use of personal narratives to illustrate how identities
 are produced through 
combination of broader social forces  and idiosyncratic personal factors 
 
2 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Transgender and Transexualism in the U.S. (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_trans/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2 
19. 	 Look at the bottom of p. 126 of the Gould ch apter; what are your explanations for the 
physical insensibility being analyzed? 
20. 	 Have you heard the term &#8220;mongoloid&#8221; used for Down&#8217;s syndrome? Why was the name 
changed, do you think? Can you think of a similar case of name substitution? 
21. 	 In what ways have advances in genetics revived notions that &#8220;anatomy is destiny&#8221;? 
22. 	 Discuss how technosemen is seen as superior to &#8220;natural&#8221; semen. 
23. 	 Provide one other example of the increas ing influence of the &#8220;medical-industrial 
complex.&#8221; 
24. 	 Discuss Schmidt &amp; Moore&#8217;s notion of demate rialized bodies result ing from the virtual 
reality of bodies in internet chat rooms. 
25. 	 Do we continue to believe in Lamarckian evolution in some ways? 
26. 	 What&#8217;s a cyborg?  Give some examples. 
27. 	 According to Kondo, she was an anomaly in Ja pan.  Why?  Have you ever felt this way? 
28. 	 Kondo found living with the Sakamotos difficu lt.  Could she have done it differently and 
felt less uncomfortable? 
29. 	 What are some of the contradictions betw een the roles of dau ghter and researcher 
discussed by Kondo? 
30. 	 Kondo says that a white person who speaks fl awlessly idiomatic and unaccented Japanese 
meets with &#8220;what generously could be de scribed as unpleasant reactions&#8230;treated as 
repulsive and unnatural&#8230;the better their Japane se becomes&#8221; (p. 11).  Discuss. Is there 
anything like this in the U.S.? What lie s behind these displays of &#8220;revulsion&#8221;? 
31. 	 Kondo says that her relationship of depende ncy was &#8220;an extremely advantageous position 
to be in, for people did not feel the need to reflect my views back to me, as they might 
with a more powerful person.&#8221;  Discuss. 
32. 	 Kondo says that her identity &#8220;fragmented.&#8221; What does she mean? Has this happened to 
you? 
33. 	 The decision to leave the Sakamotos was ma de when Kondo caught a glimpse of herself 
being reflected in the metal surface of the but cher&#8217;s display case.  Put yourself in her 
shoes. What would be the most bothersome aspect of this image for you? 
34. 	 Discuss the differences between Japanese c onceptions of the individual and U.S. ones. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>QUESTIONS ON GORDON, GOULD, SCHMIDT &amp; MOORE, 
KONDO, AND P. PASCOE 
1. 	 Describe the social purity movement, as described by Gordon.  What contemporary 
reform movements resemble it? 

2. 	 What did the suffrage, free love, an
d temperance movements advocate? 
3. 	 Describe the &#8220;volunt ary motherhood&#8221; movement. 
4. 	 Discuss the 19th century notion that men had excessive  sex drives. Include the ideas about 
causation, and about correcting such excess. 
5. 	 Discuss the concept of &#8220;the right of childre n not to be born&#8221; (p. 122).  Is this notion still 
with us in 2010? If so, what form(s) does it take?
 6. 	 Describe the goals of the femi nists of the latte r half of the 19th century. 
7. 	 How did &#8220;the cult of true  womanhood&#8221; differ from &#8220;the glory of motherhood&#8221;? (p. 133). 
8. 	 Discuss Lamarckian notions of evolution. 
9. 	 Discuss any notions you are familiar with th at concern the effects of pregnant women&#8217;s 
behavior on the embryo/fetus.  Are any of these psychological? (p. 122) 
10. 	 Discuss the role of eugenics in the evolution of feminism in the latter half of the 19th 
century. 
11. 	 Discuss notions about the superiority of women in the latter half of the 19th century. 
12. 	 What is Social Darwinism?  Does it continue today? 
13. 	 What was the appeal of the trappings of science for the authors Gould discusses? 
14. 	 In what ways do you see men as superior to women?  Women as superior to men? 
15. 	 What does IQ measure?  What is  your definition of  intelligence? 
16. 	 Discuss the notion of primitive peoples and animals as &#8220;criminal.&#8221; 
17. 	 Are humans more &#8220;criminal&#8221; than animals in some respects? 
18. 	 In connection with the a bove question, discuss the reas oning behind the differential 
treatment of sexual offenders following re lease from prison (in this country), as 
compared to the rest of the prison population. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>3 
35. 	 &#8220;You are not an &#8216;I&#8217; untouched by context, rather you are defined by the context.&#8221; (Kondo 
p. 29). What contexts in the U.S. come closest to this notion of the &#8220;I&#8221;? 
36. 	 What did you know about U.S. miscegenation laws before reading the Pascoe essay? 
37. 	 Compare the information Pascoe presents a bout earlier notions of &#8220;race&#8221; and eugenics 
with the information pres ented in Gordon&#8217;s essay. 
38. 	 The essays for today were chosen because th ey illustrate societal  processes of defining 
and drawing boundaries around categories of people&#8212;classifying them according to 
certain socially recognized presumed features  of their bodies.  If you can, provide an 
example of a similar classification scheme. 
39. 	 What were the contradictions in miscegenation laws? 
40. 	 Both the concept &#8220;mixed race&#8221; and &#8220;bisexual&#8221; classify kinds of people seen to belong to 
more than one category in some fashion.  Discuss. What cultural work do these concepts 
do? Are they totally successful? 
41. 	 What are the current major ethno-racial groups recognized by the U.S. government? 
What are these categories used for? 
42. 	 Argue in favor of the U.S. government adopt ing a race-blind approach  to classifying the 
country&#8217;s citizens. Argue against such an approach. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.218J / WGS.170J Identity and Difference
Spring 2010
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Coming Out and Leaving the Closet Behind (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21a-231j-gender-sexuality-and-society-spring-2006/resources/mit21a_213js06_lesbian/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>lesbian experience in the United States 
 
Arlene Stein , Sex and Sensibility 
 
what are the major messages of the book? what big picture views did you take away? 
 &#8226; she argues that sexual or sexuality identitie s based on object of desire (hetero/homo) are 
too restrictive to accommodate the range of subjective experiences that she found in her 
interviews 
 again, we see the tyranny of binary classificatory ideals 
 sexuality binarism rooted in sex/gender binarism  having &#8220;a sex&#8221; and &#8220;having sex&#8221;&#8230; with so meone else &#8212;&gt; &#8220;having&#8221; a sexuality 
(we&#8217;ll start to look at other ways of  imaging these things next time) 
 are you clear on &#8220; sexual essentialism &#8221; v. &#8220;social constructivist &#8221; views of sexuality? (9-) 
  essentialism = naturalization, grounded in some sort of biological basis  
(e.g., medicalization); origin born that way, inherent &#8212; ascribed
 status 
  
&#8220;gender essentialism&#8221; implies that &#8220;bei ng&#8221; a woman or man means that you&#8217;ll 
behave, feel, even think in  particular pre-set ways 
 &#8220;social constructivism&#8221; says that identity based on sexuality = achieved
 status, 
within specific historical and cultural setti ngs; sexuality itself is plastic, malleable 
 as an identity, sexuality, like gender, is performed following recognizable cultural 
scripts &#8212; dress the part, talk the part 
 &#8220;primary
 lesbians&#8221; and &#8220; elective  lesbians&#8221;? 
 what do you think? how is th is playing out in the 2000s? 
 is there a similar distinction (primary /elective) among gay men? why/why not? 
  Q: what are the political implications  of essentialism/constructivism? 
 problems with essentialism?   biological determinism  problems with constructivism?    if &#8220;choice&#8221; then some think coercive meas ures called for to get people to choose  
1 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>differently (not as politically safe as e ssentialism; owing to our views of nature) 
 doesn&#8217;t answer the question of why so me people &#8220;feel&#8221; one way or the other 
 
how to understand people who are convinced  they were &#8220;born gay&#8221;? or for that 
matter, happily heterosexual? 
 
neither  framework necessarily accommodates the variety among, say, lesbians or among 
straight women &#8212; and each overemphasizes di fferences between categorical groupings 
  According to Stein, in the1980s lesbian femi nism started coming apart at the seams &#8212; 
tension b/w &#8220;born lesbians&#8221; and &#8220;women-iden tified&#8221; lesbians who might still fantasize 
about men but were politically committed to  women&#8217;s community, resisting patriarchal 
marriage, etc.  it&#8217;s interesting to note that lesbianism as a self-proclaimed identity emerged from the women&#8217;s movement, as a subset of those challenging restrictive roles for women 
generally (the gay men&#8217;s movement came out of a different politics)  &#8220;coming out of the closet&#8221; &#8212; what is this? 
 ritual of self-definition  classically revealing to others one&#8217;s  deepest, most authentic inner self 
 the confession  
for some, ritual performance that demonstr ated commitment to a cause and to an 
identity (i.e., more about the social  identity than th e personal identity) 
 Katz (22): &#8220;the social construction of homo sexual persons [he means that in a historic 
sense &#8212; including the social construction of essentialism!] has lead to the development of a powerful gay liberation id entity politics based on an ethnic group model. This has 
freed generations of women and men from a deep, painful, socially induced sense of 
shame, and helped to bring about a society- wide liberalization of attitudes and responses 
to homosexuals.&#8221;  but is there also a flip side to the positive?  reinscribed hetero/homo as essential categories &#8212; &#8220; Who am I? Which am I? &#8221; 
 &#8220;identity politics&#8221; &#8212; idea th at what you believe is/should be based on who you are &#8212; it&#8217;s 
essentializing, potentially limiting BUT might be politically strate gic; &#8220;strategic essentialism&#8221;, form of &#8220;necessary fiction&#8221; 
 &#8226; Is &#8220;coming out&#8221; as culturally important today as a rite of passage?  &#8226; How strong do you see the divi de b/w straight and gay as KINDS of sexuality? any 
differences beyond preferred gender? 
2 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
21A.231J / WGS.455J Identity and Difference
Spring 2006
For information about citing these materials or our Terms of Use, visit: http://ocw.mit.edu/terms .</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <videos>
      <video>
        <video_url/>
        <video_title/>
        <transcript>
          <slice>
            <text_slice/>
            <time_slice/>
          </slice>
        </transcript>
      </video>
    </videos>
  </lectures>
</doc>
