<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-224-global-markets-national-politics-and-the-competitive-advantage-of-firms-spring-2003/</course_url>
    <course_title>Global Markets, National Politics and the Competitive Advantage of Firms</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Economics </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
      <list>Public Administration </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Analog Devices Case Notes (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-224-global-markets-national-politics-and-the-competitive-advantage-of-firms-spring-2003/resources/analogdevicecasenot/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>15.224 Governm ents, Markets and International Com petition 
Sources of problems 
1-Nature of US government 
a.	Contrary to general perception of &#8220;l aissez-faire&#8221; governm ent, it actually 
creates a very regulated environm ent through regulatory agencies, courts 
and state governm ents, often with contradictory policies 
2-Financial markets 
a. Capital m arkets create wrong incentives 
3-Industrial relations 
a.	Contrary to general perceptions, un ions create significant problem s for 
businesses. Fragm ented unions prod uce fights with m anagem ent. US 2nd 
to Italy in days lost due to strikes. 
b.	Business Associations: only used to lobby congress rather than to upgrade 
the industry or ag ree on standards. 
4-Education / Training 
a.	Even though  the US has incredib le ed ucation al institutions, the public 
education system  is unequal and highly dependant on incom e levels. 
Five years after &#8220;Made in Am erica&#8221; the US is no w viewed as the &#8220;id eal&#8221; econom y with 
great strengths. W hy? 
1-Wrong analysis:
&#131; Structu ral problem s vs. mom ent in tim e 
&#131; The US had advantage of being fast  &amp; flexible, with opportunities to 
innovate but the disadvantage of li ttle coordination which is probably 
better for more stable periods 
2-Companies actually lea rnt fr om int ernational c ompetition 
&#131; Auto industry integrating suppliers into their plants. 
&#131; Improved training 
&#131; Improved product developm ent 
3-Some minor changes at the institu tional level. 
&#131; Financial sy stem  changed and became less regulated 
&#131; Industrial relations: ch ange in labor m arkets at the state level </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>15.224 Governm ents, Markets and International Com petition 
Analog Devices 
Paradox:  the com pany introduces TQ M and sees an  increase in productivity, quality and a 
decrease in defects and lead-tim e. Howeve r, the com pany goes into econ omic cris is. 
Factors contributing to firm &#8217;s distress: 
&#131;	Did not change accounting: % distributi on of costs now shows an increase in 
indirect co sts that m akes analys ts weary of com pany&#8217;s strategy. Choices m ade by 
the firm  reinforced analy st actions du e to the ince ntives of  the system 
&#131; Fall in sh are price increase s chances of take-over bid 
&#131; Even though the com pany strategy was on t echnological leadership, it focused its 
effort on m anufacturing vs. product developm ent 
&#131; Focused on short term  returns from  manufacturing 
&#131; General ind ustry recess ion 
&#131; TQM falls from  grace du e to vicious circle create d by em ployee lay -off 
&#131; Mism atch between in ternal and ex ternal ob jectiv es </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.224 Governm ents, Markets and International Com petition 
Liberal Market Econom ies &#8211; The United States 
Case: Analo g Devices In c. 
A study on the problem s of the US econom y &#8211; &#8220; Made in America&#8221; - 1989 
In the late 1 980&#8217;s the U S econom y is view ed as weak, with no com petitiveness and 
having los t its edge ove r com petitors. 
&#8220;Made in A merica&#8221;: bottom  up study of problem s in US manufacturing  industry. 
Common problem s found by study 
1-Outdated strategies 
a.	Reliance on m ass production vs. prod uct differentiation strategy. US 
industry trying to be price leader s, mostly commodity industries. 
2-Short term horiz ons 
a.	Capital Mar kets f orce m anagers to p ay attention to short-term earnings 
strategies. 
3-Technological w eakness, specially in Product Development 
a.	Com peting countries speeding up product developm ent cycles by using 
new organizational structures. Cross functional vs. sequential developm ent 
b.	There seem ed to be a lot of  innovation in the US, but no 
commercialization 
c. Weak links between technical know ledge and business realization 
4-Neglect for Human Resources 
a.	Low levels of training. Technological sh ifts complicated due to lack of 
necessa ry sk ill sets 
5-Failure to cooperate in and betw een companies 
a. Cooperation am ong companies or industr ies m any tim es considered illegal 
b. No sharing of standards 
c. Low intra-firm  cooperation 
6-Government &amp; Industry w orking at cross-purposes 
a. Court battles 
b. Regulation blocking from businesses </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Gerber Case Notes (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-224-global-markets-national-politics-and-the-competitive-advantage-of-firms-spring-2003/resources/gerbercasenoteslect/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.224 Governm ents, Markets and International Com petition 
Gerber Case 
Basic Facts 
&#131; 73-year-old firm  from  Freemont, Michigan. 
&#131; Produces and sells baby food &#8211; 165 varieties. 
&#131; Focus on Quality vs. price. Pediatrician recomm ended, etc. 
&#131; Held 72% of US Market, but the US only counts for 3% of world babies. 
&#131; The com pany is looking to grow trad itional business, after failing in o ther areas 
such as day care centers. 
&#131; Decided to f ocus on Eastern European m arket to attack local m arket and as a 
platform  for entry to W estern Europe. 
Poland &#8211; Reasons for closing deal 
&#131; Needs FDI. 
&#131; Needs hard foreign currency. 
&#131; Has to signa l to th e world that it is e mbracing market reforms. Has the g oal of the 
EU in the f uture. 
&#131; Needs to generate exports. This project will create stim ulus to the im portant 
agricu ltural sector. 
Gerber - Reasons for clo sing the d eal 
&#131; Platform  to sell in France and other Eastern Europe countries. 
&#131; First m over advantage: Heinz is  also looking at opportunities. 
&#131; Seem s to be a low price ($ 25 m illion ) vs. $ 100 m illion of investm ent to build 
plant from  scratch. 
&#131; Attrac tive e xisting m arket: bo th Ger ber and Alim a 
&#131; Related industries are deve loped: local farm ers, sim ilar to Freem ont and glass 
producers. 
&#131; Prom ises from governm ent: tax breaks, profit repatriations and duties. 
&#131; Alim a&#8217;s plant is in good shape, re asonable technology and good m anager. 
&#131; Cheap inputs: labour, ag ricultural products, etc. 
&#131; Great opportunities to improve the operation. 
&#131; The deal in creases the sp eed of Ge rber&#8217;s en try to these m arkets. 
Risks 
&#131; Unstable environm ent, doubt about m arket reform s. 
&#131; Property rights: claim  to land from  previous nationalization waves. 
&#131; Sustainability of Financial system . 
&#131; Expectation s of inflation ? Social p ressures &amp; un rest? 
&#131; No interna tional reg ime on FDI to resort to in case of problems. 
&#131; Opposition to deal from  church and workers. 
&#131; Logistical problem s such as re tail channels and distribution. 
&#131; Environm ental hazards. </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Analog Devices Case Notes (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-224-global-markets-national-politics-and-the-competitive-advantage-of-firms-spring-2003/resources/nikeandcsrcasesnote/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.224 Governm ents, Markets and International Com petition 
Nike &amp; Cor porate Social Responsibility 
Basic facts / Problems 
-Outsourcing to LDC&#8217;s 
-Savings from not m anufacturing poure d into marketing / end orsem ents 
-Labor unrest 
-Living W ages? Com pany Responsibility?
-NGO role in creating m edia attention against Nike 
-Child Labor / Health and  safety 
-Corruption in outsourced countries 
-Huge profit m argins can turn against them
-Issue of protectionism  for US Labour 
What should Nike do? 
Nike 
-Get m ore inform ation of situation. Hired external auditor, NGO contested validity 
due to Nike paying auditors. Language issu es / translator underm ines credibility 
-Minim um wages. W hose minimum wages to apply? 
-Industry co mpetitors 
-Reality v s. perceptions 
LDC 
-Econom ic developm ent issues 
-Poverty / productivity 
-Force a rise in living standards 
NGO / Labor 
-Good use of Media 
-Coalition of NGO&#8217;s 
-Are they pushing for protectionism ?
Subcontractors 
-Establish standards for th eir supp liers 
Interactions between MNC and the local econom y 
Why are there differences in different count ries when MNC leave?  Is what is left 
sustain able? I.e.: Taiwan / Korea </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>15.224 Governm ents, Markets and International Com petition 
Competitive analysis 
Five forces 
Buyers 
-Consum ers participation in im proving conditions in LDCs 
-Segm ented buyers 
o high price points surveys show people are willing to pay m ore 
o People do not usually do what they say 
Suppliers 
-Really powerful suppliers. One com pany is producing 40% of worldwide shoes. 
-How can you im pose your standards on them ? What about the other companies? 
-They can forward integrate, they have the technology 
New  entrants 
-Com peting shoes and new com panies com ing in 
Rivalry 
-Com petitors  are doing th e sam e thing. Low production co st / High m arketing 
Substitutes </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Analog Devices Case Notes (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/15-224-global-markets-national-politics-and-the-competitive-advantage-of-firms-spring-2003/resources/daewoocasenoteslect/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>15.224 Governm ents, Markets and International Com petition 
US Review 
Role of gov ernment 
Ideology
Financ ial System 
Industrial relations
Business organization 
Education system 
Who drives the system 
Strengths / weakness es 
Korea US 
Indirect/regulatory 
Laissez-fair e 
Capital Market based 
Fragmented / weak unions 
Weak Business Assoc iations / lobbies 
Bi-polar (to p univ. vs weak public schools) 
Firms 
Flexibility, entrepreneurs / w eak coordination 
(across companies , gov. vs firms) 
-Government role is impressive. St ate led development al model. Similar to 
other Asian countries and also France. 
-After Korean war GDP was below Brazil, Mexic o, India. Incredibly fast 
growth after that targeting certain successful industries. 
-Good social welfare and educational system. 
How did Korea do this? Is this model sustainable? 
Government role 
1- Plans: 
a. 	1960&#8217;s: infrastructure and simple  industries: plywood and cotton 
spinning (light industries). Later on garments and shoes. 
b. 1970&#8217;s: promotion of heavy i ndust ry (steel, chemicals, autos) 
c. 1980&#8217;s: High Tech (ships, electronics) 
d. 1990&#8217;s: continue in high tech. 
-Discipline:  Government played an important  role in discipline of the 
workforce (organized labor) and firms (performance based credit 
assignment , mainly on exports) 
-Subsidized credit:  borrowed from abroad and used control of financial 
system to  promote its plans. 
-Wrong Prices: 
&#8226; Protectionism for it s market (i.e. steel) 
&#8226; Subsid ies 
&#8226; Import restrictions: not IS I, but as a way to develop 
local indust ries. 
-Technology : used market access to extrac t licenses from multinationals. </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>15.224 Governm ents, Markets and International Com petition 
Should the government pull the plug on Daewoo? 
4 I&#8217;s 
-Issue:  bankruptcy or nationalizat ion? 
-Interest : government, suppliers, financ ial communities. Which do we take 
into consideration? 
-Institu tions: not only the firm , but relati onship with other players and 
actors. 
-Inform:  what informati on do we want? Going forward, how does it use the 
information to show it was a good gamble? 
Role of gov ernment 
Ideology
Financ ial System 
Industrial relations
Business organization 
Education system 
Who drives the system 
Strengths / weakness es 
Korea 
Direct / Interventionist 
Developmental 
Credit based 
Docile at first, now Militant 
Strong Chaebols 
Strong 
Firms 
Coordinati on / Transparency, flexibility 
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>15.224 Governm ents, Markets and International Com petition 
-Education : huge investment in primar y / secondary schools. 95% 
enrollment (1994). 20% higher educati on. Vocational training promoted. 
1980&#8217;s huge investment in engineer ing and science. People sent abroad 
and bring back knowledge to Korea. 
Other actors / factors 
-Chaebols:  conglomer ates of firms,  similar to Japanese model. 
Government played role in forming th is groups. Strategy: form powerful 
groups to be able to compete. 
-Cold w ar: US playe d some role in  helping this development. 
Given that this model appeared to wo rk, what happened after July 1997? Was 
there a collapse? If ye s, why did the system collapse? Is it sustainable? 
-Reform pushed by IMF / Government. 
-Bankruptcies in different sectors. 
-Job guarantee no longer exists. 
Daew oo Case &#8211; What happened to this Chaebol? 
-Highly leveraged. D/E of four. 
-Growing and grabbing cheap deals in order to increase size and power. 
Incentive of system is for market share. 
-Decis ion to go into auto industry may have been a problem. 
Industr y 
-New entrants: difficult due to size of conglomerates. 
-Buyers: recession, dev aluation so it is  hard to sell. Principal markets are 
other developing countries also in trouble 
-Substitutes: not a problem 
-Suppliers: captive 
Porter&#8217;s Diamond 
Industry problems exacerbated by nat ional s ystem and set incentives. 
-Demand: suppressed at count ry level. High overcapacit y 
-Factors: skewed cost of capital in  the system. Government intervention. 
-Related industries: no power vs. the Chaeb ols 
-Structure: Chaebol is key to understanding the complicated system. Big 
players loc k up new markets. </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <videos>
      <video>
        <video_url/>
        <video_title/>
        <transcript>
          <slice>
            <text_slice/>
            <time_slice/>
          </slice>
        </transcript>
      </video>
    </videos>
  </lectures>
</doc>
