<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-522-research-seminar-on-urban-information-systems-fall-2005/</course_url>
    <course_title>Research Seminar on Urban Information Systems</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Engineering </list>
      <list>Computer Science </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Information Infrastructure and the Redevelopment of Inner Cities - Mi Diao (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-522-research-seminar-on-urban-information-systems-fall-2005/resources/notes_4/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>4</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.522: UIS Research Seminar (Fall 2005)  - Discussion notes 
Session 4 
Information Infrastructure and the Redevelopment of 
Inner Cities 
Discussant: Mi Diao 
In the last two sessions, Joe and Fabio provided us a genera l framework about planning 
strategies and information infrastructure that might facilitate 'community empowerment' 
and innovative community development strategies . This session can be seen as a special 
case of this framework in the redevelopment of US inner cities. 
The economic distress of American's inner cities  is one of the most pressing issues facing 
the nation. There are substantial researches  and development programs focusing on the 
revitalization of economically  dilapidated inner city ne ighborhoods. Though differing in 
their approaches, many analysts have descri bed the unmet retail demand in inner city 
neighborhoods and the potential of translating this demand into investment. Tapping the 
unmet retail demand has been considered as one import strategy to accelerate the 
economic development in inner cities. Howeve r, there is a &#8216;gloomy vision' among market 
actors towards the inner cities: i n the Unite d States, the term &#8216;inner city' is perhaps most 
widely understood to mean the poorer parts at the center of a major city, which is riddled 
with crime and uneducated labor and is a ghos t town for business. When such &#8216;gloomy 
vision' prevails, the market poten tial of inner cities as business locations either will be not 
perceived at all or will be largely undervalue d. In these circumstances, the inner cities are 
experiencing a shortage of inve stment and market activities. 
Today, a large and growing number of local agencies and community organization are actively engaged in efforts to quantify and evaluate the social economic, and cultural 
health of their neighborhoods, and provide more accurate &#8216;knowledge' to policy makers and market actors . These effort involve th e use of various public and private data, 
accelerated by the improvement in com puting, GIS, RDBMS, information and 
communication technologies. 
This session will concentrate on the role th at information technology can play in the 
understanding of inner city ma rkets and the redevelopment of inner city neighborhoods. 
Please read the articles below and consider the following questions to discuss on Tuesday. 
Discussion questions: 
1.	What are the main differences among the strategies to revitalize inner city 
neighborhoods?
</text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>2.	Why is the &#8216;gloomy vision' towards i nner cities pervasive? Why are the 
comparative advantages of inner citie s not perceived at all or largely 
undervalued ? What is wrong in the &#8220;information cycle&#8221;? 
3.	To draw a true picture of inner c ity markets, w hat kind s of neighborhood 
indicators may be useful ? What are the main obstacles in building up such 
neighborhood indicator systems? 
4.	How can the overall structure, as well as  specific tools, shown in the MIT/MAPC 
UMI project be used in the revitalization of inner city? 
5.	What may be the main obstacles in the implementation of the MIT/MAPC UMI 
approach ? How can we solve these pr oblems with technical and institutional 
renovation? </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>City Knowledge: An Emergent Information Infrastructure for Sustainable Urban Maintenance, Management and Planning - Joe Ferreira and Fabio Carrera (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-522-research-seminar-on-urban-information-systems-fall-2005/resources/notes_2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>2</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.522: PSS Research Seminar (Fall 2005)  - Discussion notes 
Session 2 
City Knowledge: an Emergent Information Infrastructure for 
Sustainable Urban Maintenance, Management and Planning. 
Discussants: Fabio Carrera &amp; Joe Ferreira 
Introduction: 
Recent advances in geo-spatial technologies, t ogether with a steady decline in their cost, 
have inspired many spontaneous  bottom-up municipal initia tives aimed at improving the 
flow and availability of information fo r the purpose of maintaining, managing, and 
planning urban spaces. Simultaneously, spatial da ta sets are more readily available and 
some cities have institutionalized top-down systems that allow planners and other 
professionals to make maps and perform basi c analytical functions . In his dissertation, 
Fabio Carrera argues the need for a middle-out  approach whereby we combine the virtues 
bottom-up specificity with top-down efficien cy. The dissertation is based on Fabio&#8217;s 
experience in designing, maintaining, and us ing municipal-level geographic information 
systems, especially in his hometown of Veni ce, Italy, to propose a nd promote the concept 
of City Knowledge. City Knowledge is a paradigm that aims at instilling in front-line municipal departments an information aware modus operandi  that will emancipate town 
planners, managers and decision-makers from  &#8220;hunter-gatherers&#8221; of  plan-demanded data 
to &#8220;farmers&#8221; of plan-ready information so th at city knowledge can be regarded as an 
infrastructure because it provides an essent ial and ongoing service to  ordinary citizens, 
just like a city&#8217;s transit system  or its water and sewer network. 
Questions: 
In light of the materials you will be reading in  preparation for this class (listed below), we 
suggest that you consider the following ques tions in the context of your own class 
project: 
(a) How could the datasets that you foresee us ing in your project be made to become 
&#8220;plan-ready&#8221;?  Which would be the &#8220;low -hanging fruit&#8221;?  Are there specific 
standard data representations and geometri es that could be used?  Who should be 
in charge (jurisdictionally) of the &#8220;birth certificates&#8221; (and updat es) associated with 
the datasets that you are using? 
(b) What technological infrastruc ture would be best suited  to support a full-fledged 
City Knowledge system?  What 'middlew are' applications may be required to 
make existing (and periodically updated)  datasets re-usa ble in different 
circumstances by a variety of municipal depa rtments?  What could be the role of </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>mobile technologies to be ab le to &#8220;pull&#8221; location-specific urban information in the 
course of day-to-day maintena nce or inspectional activities? 
(c) How could an information infrastructure be &#8220;grown&#8221; through a skillful 
application of a combination of the 5 tools?  How could this &#8220;data farming&#8221; be 
made as inexpensive and systematic as po ssible?  What could be some strategies 
to &#8220;catch up with the backlog&#8221; of inform ation already &#8220;out there&#8221; in the world 
(and in paper archives)?  And what stra tegies and mechanisms could be put in 
place to &#8220;intercept future change&#8221; so that  these datasets could be maintained up-
to-date in perpetuity? 
(d) How could a &#8220;middle-out&#8221; approach be adopted in the institutions that are 
connected to your project to foster the &#8220;emergence&#8221; of City Knowledge?  Are the 
data-producing organizations and the end- user organizations predominantly top-
down or bottom-up?  Do the institutions  related to your project exhibit obvious 
signs of inefficiency and redundancy in the collection and use of urban information that would justify an invest ment in an integrated comprehensive 
municipal information system base d on City Knowledge principles? 
Articles and Other Readings: 
In preparation for this discussion, we sugge st that you read or skim the following: 
(1) For a full explanation of the concept of City Knowledge, you should skim Fabio 
Carrera&#8217;s PhD dissertation especially Part I  and Part V  and you should ready more 
carefully Part IV . 
(2) When it comes to implementing government policies, a school of thought that has 
been put forward by DUSP faculty, suggests that we focus on the so-called &#8220;Five tools of Government Action&#8221;.  A full descri ption of these tools can be found in the 
book &#8220;Preserving the Built Heritage&#8221; edited by our own Mark Schuster and John DeMonchaux. There is a summary of the c oncepts in the introduction chapter.  A 
shorter version is contained in Policy and Planning with Purpose . 
(3) The concept of &#8220;Emergence&#8221; features prominently in the City Knowledge 
approach. If you are interested, we suggest that you r ead the popular book 
Emergence  by Steven Johnson. You may find the book very stimulating. At the very 
least should familiarize yourself with the concept by googling &#8220;emergence&#8221; so you 
can look at shorter explanations such as the Wikipedia entry for the term. 
(4) Prof. Ferreira describes middleware applicati ons in his article entitled "Information 
Technologies that Change Relationships between Low-Income Communities and the 
Public and Non-profit Agenci es that Serve Them" as well as in the MIT/MAPC 
proposal "Intelligent Middleware for Unde rstanding Neighborhood Markets" a pilot 
project of the Brookings Institution Urban Markets Initiative . </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>(5) For recent accounts of the Planning Support Systems that are already in use around 
the world, you can take a look at Kloste rman&#8217;s recent (2005) guest editorial in 
Environment and Planning B, as well as to Maguire and Longley&#8217;s paper on &#8220;The 
emergence of geoportals and their role in sp atial data infrastructures.&#8221; An older, but 
interesting paper predating City Knowle dge is Rubenstein-Montano&#8217;s Survey of 
knowledge-based information systems for urban planning . 
Rubenstein-Montano, B. "A survey of knowledge-based information systems for urban planning: moving towards 
knowledge management." Computers, Environment and Urban Systems  24 (2000): 155-172.</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Role of GIS in Delivering Municipal Public Services - Fazilet Tanrikulu (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-522-research-seminar-on-urban-information-systems-fall-2005/resources/notes_7/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>7</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.522: UIS Research Seminar (Fall 2005) - 
Discussion notes 
Session 7
The Role of GIS in Delivery of Municipal Public Services 
Discussant: Fazilet Tanrikulu
Requirements of the study : Municipalities are recognizing the need to invest in GIS to 
provide better services. The ability to process, manage, and update large amounts of 
information efficiently is an invaluable asset for local governments. Whether for urban 
planning, tax assessment, or in frastructural development, mu nicipalities require fast and 
easy access to map and associated data in an automated system. Further, they need to be 
able to analyze these data to meet increasing service demands.  
Iller Bank is the main organization that gives financial and te chnical support for 
urbanization related services such as crea ting maps, developing urban plans, delivering 
water, wastewater and solid waste services for all municipalities in Turkey. The Bank has 
the biggest spatial data archives because it is  the unique authority to  approve all kinds of 
maps of urban areas in the country.  
But over time, the working system has not  been updated or renewed and it becomes 
insufficient to meet all the need s of municipalities. In other words, its working system is 
behind the latest technological developments . So, it is necessary to update its working 
system according to contemporary progress.  </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>3. What kind of opportunity can GIS bring to the Bank? 
4. Can GIS facilitate the change in Iller Bank? </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>the effectiveness of the system. According to authors&#8217; findings, GIS is very important in 
all land related operations. Mo reover it has a very important  role in delivering public 
services, in management of governmental oper ations and in organizational controls. But 
its success depends on organizational structure.  In order to share in formation with other 
municipalities and other organi zations, attention was drawn to create requirements for 
national guidelines for combining common basi c rules, policies and formats about the 
GIS. In addition, Maguire and Longley (2005) explained the developm ent of spatial data 
infrastructure (SDI) as a common national GIS guideline which was coined in 1993 under 
the coordination of U.S. Federal Geogra phic Data Committee (FGDC). According to 
them &#8220;FGDC defines SDI as the totality of  &#8216;technology, policies, standards, human 
resources, and related activities necessary to acquire, process, distribute, use, maintain, 
and preserve spatial data th roughout all levels of governme nt, the private and non-profit 
sectors, and academia&#8217;&#8221; (p. 5).  Accordi ng to Harvey (2003), the roles of local 
governments are very important in developing na tional spatial data in frastructure (NSDI). 
They are producers and end users of the data . Therefore, NSDI should be based on local 
governments.  
Jacoby, Smith, Ting and Williamson (2002) emphas ized Australian experiences about the 
SDI over the last decade. They underlined the problems of using different data sets and 
the requirements of state SDI. According to them, &#8220;[the] objective of  SDIs is to ensure 
users of spatial data will be ab le to acquire consistent datase ts to meet their requirements&#8221; 
(p. 307). All these studies show that common sp atial data infrastructure is necessary for 
sharing data and information to reduce redundancy. One guideline could be developed for 
all countries. 
Expectations from the class discussion: This topic will be studying during the whole 
academic year. For this reason, in order to guide this research in an efficient way, the followings will be expected from the participants of the discussion: 
1.	Is there any Iller Bank kind of organization in US? 
What are the similarities and differences between them? 
2.	What are the possibilities and obstacles in current situation in Iller Bank for 
the use of GIS? </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>GIS can play a very important role both in  delivering public services and in improving 
the working system of Iller Bank to guide urban and infrastructu ral development more 
efficiently in Turkey. But developing a GIS is a complex process. It requires 
reconciliation of divers e source materials, conversion of paper maps and other hard copy 
data, and the acquisition of new data, hardware and software, and user applications. In the 
process, management structure could be re defined, work flow c ould be redesigned, and 
personnel should be trained. 
The advantages of GIS: GIS has many advantages in the managements of spatial 
problems. According to Nedovic- Budic (1999) the efficiency of an information system 
depends on two dimensions: information quality and system quality (p. 286). In the case 
of information quality first, GIS system n eeds accurate data and it combines different 
data sources. With existing data, advanced an alysis such as modeli ng of a real world, 
environmental impact assessment and suitabil ity analysis can be done and their results 
can be visualized. In this way, system produces informa tion as an output. Because of 
used data and produced information, the syst em becomes more reliant and transparent. 
Moreover, as Nedovic-Budic (1999)  has noted, &#8220;User satisfaction has been used as one of 
the most prominent measures of system su ccess and effectiveness&#8221; (p. 287). In this 
context, GIS supply user friendly environmen t. More complex operations can be handled 
in a simple way. Users of the system are sati sfied with the high qual ity of visual outputs. 
In addition to this, a decision making proce ss becomes more transparent and reliant, 
because of powerful analysis of GIS and everyone can follow everything in that system 
easily. Staff and managers can be more productive in this environment. GIS also has 
many effects on organizations in which it is used. Nedovic-Budic (1999) claimed that 
&#8220;Efficiency and effectiveness are the criteria  used to evaluate how information systems 
affect organizational performance&#8221; (p. 288). First of all, it decreases the inputs and 
increases the outputs in order to supply the same amount of services. For example, while 
operating costs and numbers of staff are re duced, work volumes, product qualities, goal 
achievement and service effectiveness increa se. As a result of all these advantages, 
organizations can return their investments w ith increased revenues. Finally, GIS brings 
equity, participation and transparency to so ciety. Because people, politicians, managers 
and citizens are aware of their situation, they can participate in deciding their priorities, 
needs and quality of services. In this way, GIS plays an important role in community 
development as a whole. 
Examples: In order to establish GIS in the workin g system of Iller Bank, it is useful to 
know other countries&#8217; experiences. For this reason, the United States and Australia, 
which have been using these systems at advanc ed levels for many years were selected as 
examples. Smith, Campbell, Subramanian, Bird and Nelson (2001) analyzed GIS 
experiences in municipalities in United St ates. The municipalities used GIS in the 
establishment of municipal information system s. Their starting point was preparation of 
the strategic plan for the munici pal information systems.  After three years, they evaluate </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Sharing Data and Empowering Communities - Fabio Carrera and Joe Ferreira (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-522-research-seminar-on-urban-information-systems-fall-2005/resources/notes_3/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>3</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>website discussing how Google Earth allows users to publish their own georeferenced 
data that can be view ed using Google Earth. 
Skim through the NICS site to get a sense of the people, organizations, issues, and 
strategies that have been discussed through the various NICS activ ities during the past 
few years. Then read the UMI overview and the two project proposals. You may want to 
skim through the NNIP site to see what cities,  organizations, and pr ojects are involved. 
Finally, read at least the one  chapter of Raj's thesis to  understand the reasoning about 
why and how service-oriented information sy stems architecture would be qualitatively 
different from traditional approaches to ward land use planning and neighborhood 
analysis. 
The Google Earth links are to stimulate your thinking about appropria te user interfaces 
for viewing community data and viable ways  of decomposing the 'information at your 
fingertips' idea can be decomposed into mana geable pieces of 'local knowledge', 'city 
knowledge', 'web-based viewing tools. If  you don't have access to Google Earth and 
haven't seen it before, then *don't* spend time on that - focus on the other readings 
instead. It will be on CRN machines later th is semester and we don't want the whole-
earth data and nice 3D graphics  to distract us from our discussion of city knowledge, 
community empowerment, and data sharing. 
Discussion questions; 
(a) What 'problems' are framed in the UMI overview? Who is supporting the UMI effort? 
What do they want, what do they assume, a nd what do they anticipate doing differently 
as a result? 
(b) What is the 'city knowledge' needed to s upport the kinds of deci sion support tools that 
are envisioned in the UMI proposals? In what  way, if any, are the data, decision support 
tools and methods in the Urban Institute proposal  different from those that a city agency 
might have designed and built? 
(c) How does the MIT/MAPC 'middleware' appr oach differ from the traditional way of 
building the types of decision support tools that UI proposes? What applications are most 
promising to demonstrate the feasibility of the approach? 
(d) What 'middleware' system architecture is practical today? What skill set is needed by 
whom in order for it to deliver useful a ssistance to community groups? What partners 
make sense? What role can/should a regi onal planning organiza tion (such as MAPC) 
play? What institutional and organizational obstacles might we anticipate? 
Notes about readings for the first two classes: 
Fabio's presentation (Discussion Note 1): </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>&#8226;	Better GIS data at parcel scale can have large urban management payoff 
&#8226;	Modern IT allows 'city knowledge' to be  collected and maintained in new ways 
that are affordable, sustai nable, and very useful 
Joe's presentation: 
&#8226;	National Infrastructure for Community Statistics (NICS): frustration with  
o	data gathering difficulties 
o	complexity of indicator development (numerator A / denominator B ) for 
various times and geographies 
o	difficulties integrating of local knowledge 
&#8226;	Urban Markets Initiative (UMI): getting right information to right actors at 
neighborhood level 
&#8226;	Intelligent Middleware for Unde rstanding Neighborhood Markets 
o	can' t empower communities just by broadcasting official city data 
o	'spelling errors' never go away - official data always needs 'tweaking' 
o	codify and accumulate 'local knowledge' separate from official city data 
o	distributed data and knowledge requires  complex infrastructure - worth the 
effort to distinguish basemaps, facad es, rules, reports, thematic maps 
&#8226;	Urban Institute - (NNIP)  - Decision Support Tools To Guide Urban Land Markets 
o	NGOs are developing sustainable (b ut labor intensive) community 
information systems 
o	non-governmental partnerships can  share knowledge effectively 
&#8226;	Singh, Raj. Collaborative Urban Informati on Systems: A Web Services Approach . 
Dissertation. MIT, 2004. 
o	to support planning, urban modeling must be part of a continual planning process among dispersed actors 
o	web services architecture can make  distributed modeling practical for 
planning 
o	need a planning and modeling markup language 
&#8226;	Google Earth - http://www.philb.com/googleearth.htm 
o	3D viewer for map mashups 
o	giant datasets with highly di stributed servers and modern 
streaming/caching technologies 
o	web service protocols for integratin g user-supplied georeferenced data </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.522: UIS Research Seminar (Fall 2005)  - Discussion notes 
Session 3 
Empowering Communities Through Better Data 
Sharing 
Discussants: Joe Ferreira &amp; Fabio Carrera 
We would like to discuss planning strategies and information infrastructure that might 
facilitate 'community empowerment' and i nnovative community development strategies. 
Spatially detailed metropolitan  data about land use, owners hip, jobs, etc. is rapidly 
improving and more and more agencies and NGOs  have, or want, in-house capacity to do 
their own neighborhood analyses. In recent year s, a number of projects and research 
efforts have tried to assist  community groups and local ag encies in acquiring relevant 
planning data and improving their neighbor hood planning and advocacy capacity. These 
trends have led to many 'indicator' efforts and a proliferation of 'data centers' whereby 
each organization tries to acquire and maintain a copy of all relevant data. At the scale of 
cities or even census tracks, it is practical to  archive decennial datasets. However, at the 
scale of parcels, persons, building permits , bus stops, and the like, having a copy of 
everything is not practical. We'd like to disc uss the nature and content of 'city knowledge' 
relevant to neighborhood planning and some of  the strategies and institutional issues 
involved in empowering communities th rough better access to information.  
To facilitate the discussion, I've  identified 6 online readings. They are listed below. Item 
(1) is the website of a 'comm unity of practice' of several hundred professionals at local, 
state, and federal levels w ho are interested in facili tating an improved 'National 
Infrastructure for Community Statistics' (NICS). This site provides background 
information regrading many relevant issues and strategies. Items (2) through (4) involve 
efforts related to the Brooking Institution's Urban Markets Initiativ e (UMI) to improve 
community development methods. Item (2) desc ribes the UMI initiativ e. Item (3) is one 
of the UMI-funded projects that is or ganized by an Urban Institute-organized 
collaboration among community organizations  across a two dozen metropolitan areas. 
Item (4) is another UMI-funded project here  at MIT that is pr ototyping particular 
approaches for codifying and using local know ledge. Item (5) is a chapter of Dr. Raj 
Singh's PhD dissertation on the use of web servic es architectures to support collaborative 
planning. The Urban Institute proposal involv es several community groups in several 
cities that are part of the National Neighborhood Indicato rs Partnership (NNIP)  that Tom 
Kingsley and others at the Urban Institute have organized. They propose to build several 'decision support tools' that can help 'gra ssroots' efforts. The MIT/MAPC proposal 
suggests an architecture for improving the prac ticality of community information systems 
by making it easier to share 'official' data and to inco rporate local knowledge when 
interpreting city data. Raj's thesis suggests a 'web services' approach for the sharing of planning data and models. Item (6) is the URL for the Google Earth 3D viewer and a </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Land Market Monitoring for Growth Management - Weifeng Li (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/11-522-research-seminar-on-urban-information-systems-fall-2005/resources/notes_6/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>6</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>This session will concentrate on the role that  information technology can play in a land 
market monitoring program providing some cases  in different perspectives and how the 
advancements in planning technologies,  such as GIS and RDBMS, can enable 
communities to improve the practice of urban growth management.  
Please read the articles below and consider the following questions to discuss on Tuesday. 
Discussion questions: 
1.	To what extent do different growth mana gement approaches really restrict the 
amount, pace, or location of growth? To what extent are the resulting supply 
restrictions reflected in  land and housing price? 
2.	How do you think of the growth management - land and housing price interaction? 
Whats the main reason? 
3.	Is land market monitoring the only way to balance growth manage ment efforts? What 
else? 
4.	What differences can information knowledge make to better understanding of the 
land markets? 
5.	How can the overall structure, as well as sp ecific tools, shown in the UMI project be 
used in land market monitoring? </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>11.522: UIS Research Seminar (Fall 2005) - Discussion notes 
Session 
Land Market Monitoring for Growth Management 
Discussant: Weifeng Li 
The fundamental debate about urban growth - No growth, slow growth, go growth? will 
never be resolved. However, for urban growth  there is a general agreement that it will 
occur, that it needs some type of management. As a result, the governments of a growing 
number of jurisdictions have imposed some growth management measures to influence 
the pattern of growth. This session will, at first, discuss the management options faced by 
planners, such as Caps on development, re strictive zoning limits on allowable densities, 
urban growth boundaries, and long permit-processing delays, etc. 
New problem arises with growth management efforts. Too little constrain encourages 
sprawl while excessive land restrictions limit the land available for development, forcing 
land and housing prices sharply higher. This  dilemma makes it part icularly difficult for 
communities to plan to meet future housing needs C one of the most important functions 
they must perform. 
So the formulation of growth management policies implementation tools requires timely 
information on the interactions of government policies and land markets. The success of 
the new relationship will depend on commun ities knowing what they already have and 
what they are likely to need in the years and decades to come. The most useful way of 
doing this is by creating a land market monito ring system to estimate and continuously 
monitor development capacity and land demand. 
&#8216;Land Market Monitoring&#8217; is a phrase that describes the processes that can be employed by governments to monitor residential and ot her land uses within a jurisdiction. Done 
properly and updated regularly, land market monitoring approaches can improve 
planning by shedding light on the impacts of urban growth management policies, the current and future availability of developmen t capacity, and assist in  balancing residential 
development near centers of current or future employment. 6</text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <videos>
      <video>
        <video_url/>
        <video_title/>
        <transcript>
          <slice>
            <text_slice/>
            <time_slice/>
          </slice>
        </transcript>
      </video>
    </videos>
  </lectures>
</doc>
