<doc>
  <source>MIT</source>
  <date>28/01/2023</date>
  <course>
    <course_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-221-the-places-of-migration-in-united-states-history-fall-2006/</course_url>
    <course_title>The Places of Migration in United States History</course_title>
    <course_tags>
      <list>Humanities </list>
      <list>History </list>
      <list>Social Science </list>
    </course_tags>
  </course>
  <lectures>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lecture: American Imperialism and Filipino/a Experience (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-221-the-places-of-migration-in-united-states-history-fall-2006/resources/ses18_filipino/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>18</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Marriage 
 
Filipinos who come to California in the 1930s  and what happens to them when they get 
married&#8230;. 
 
March 1930 &#8211; Stella Robinson petitioned cl erk to block daughter&#8217;s marriage to Filipino 
migrant.  She cited an 1880 statue of California &#8211; an anti-miscegenation  statute that 
forbade a Mongolian from marrying any white person.  Did &#8220;Mongolian&#8221; incorporate Filipino 
people or not?  1930: Los Angeles superior co urt granted petition an d Robinson&#8217;s daughter 
never married Tony Romero. 
 
1939 &#8211; Mariang (we only know her first name) we nt before the Philippi ne Supreme Court in 
manila.  She was a Muslim woman from the southern Philippines who&#8217;d fallen in love with David Staples, who had been a soldier but wasn&#8217;t one at the time they fell in love, instead a 
civilian working for the colonial government.  He came to the Philippines from Kentucky in 
1902, and the two were joined in marriage in 1913 by a Mohammadan priest (a Muslim 
cleric) and they lived together since then.  In 1939, Mariang wanted to claim her late 
husband&#8217;s estate but was being challenged by her brother in law who argued that since 
Kentucky law forbade marriage across the colo r line, their marriage was invalid and the 
property should pass to him.  The court was puzzled.  The 14
th amendment, which says the 
most about citizenship, affirms that Staples wa s a citizen of the US and the state in which 
he resides- the court had to de cide was the state Kentucky or the Philippines.  Then there&#8217;s 
the common law principle of domicile &#8211; a wo man&#8217;s legal residence follows that of her 
husband.  As late as the 1970s, as this was th e law.  Did marriage ma ke Mariang a citizen 
and resident of Kentucky even though she&#8217;d ne ver been there?  Citize nship generally follows 
from marriage but it won&#8217;t follow from a marriage if the marriage is invalid &#8211; and cross-
racial marriages are invalid in Kentucky in this period.  The court ultimately ruled in her 
favor and she got half of his estate, $50,000 in 1939.  
 
These two cases demonstrate the uncertainty that you see when you think about citizenship 
and the meanings of citizenship as it comes up against the fact of formal imperialism.  
Certainly, it also highlights the importance of marriage as well as other social institutions, like military service, work, etc. &#8211; public institutions do a lot to shape our 
understanding of citizenship .  The specific experience of Filipinos in this era &#8211; also 
Hawaiians, Puerto Ricans, and Native American s &#8211; they&#8217;re insiders and outsiders at the 
same time.  It sheds a lot of light on the mean ings of citizenship, what it actually means. 
 
The laws of citizenship and marriage in  the Philippines and how it plays out: 
 
Marriage law in the Philippines itself was a subject of contest/controversy after 1899.  
Colonial administrators come and think they&#8217;re engaged in so mething modernizing.  Almost 
all who come from the government are Protestants &#8211; coming to a country whose law is 
Catholic and whose people, many of whom are Catholic, many not &#8211; they could be Muslim, 
animistic, a whole range.  One of the first things the administrators do is take on the civil 
code of marriage &#8211; get rid of Catholic laws , add new ones, like the possibility for divorce 
that didn&#8217;t exist in the Phil ippines before 1849.  Very few Filipinos take advantage of 
marriage or divorce laws &#8211; most marriages ar e conducted in Catholic churches.  In the 
countryside, local village traditions continue outside of any Catholic/Protestant churches. 
 
Usually when people talk about laws of intermarriage and racial restrictions, they put it in 
context of the US color line, particularly white/black and white/Asians/Mexicans.  Part of the 
story has to do with what&#8217;s going on with marriage in the Philippines. 
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 18 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 6 of 8 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>agriculture, banking, progressive era things experimented with in the Philippines sometimes 
with success/resistance/reluctance.  American institutions aren&#8217;t immediately transferred 
but many of them are. 
 
Filipino legal system &#8211; they keep large aspects of th e Spanish system but add more 
things that are more American.  They try to separate church and state (Spain was officially a Catholic country) and start building up legal institutions &#8211; courts, judges.  One of the 
places they stumble is trial by jury &#8211; they decide that Filipinos aren&#8217;t &#8220;ready&#8221; for trial by jury 
yet so Filipino courts don&#8217;t have courts and jury trials &#8211; judges make all the decisions. 
 
Many of these are transf erred in the rhetoric as  preparation for self government.  From 
the Treaty of Paris onward, much of the rhet oric implies/promises/asserts &#8220;at some later 
date&#8221; the Philippines will be independent &#8211; or, when the Filipinos are &#8220;capable&#8221; of self government.  Thus, it&#8217;s imagined as a developmental process .  European colonies didn&#8217;t 
often have such promises/implications in thei r colonies &#8211; but does this make this any 
different in the day to day experience?   
 
As the US is in this process, they run into something they don&#8217;t expect.  They find out many 
Filipinos don&#8217;t want to be colonized &#8211; various Philippine national movements weren&#8217;t trying to get rid of the Spanish to replace with the Americans; they were trying to get rid of 
everyone and establish an independent Philippine republic.  From 1899, Filipino 
nationalists take up armed battle against the US.  An d who leads it?  Agunaldo!  He takes 
his troops trained by the US and turns against th e US.  (This is an old strategy in American 
history.) 
 
The war itself turns out to be a gruesome unde rtaking &#8211; one of the most  violent episodes in 
Filipino history, one of the most violent in Am erican history but almost  completely forgotten.  
From 1899 to 1902, 200,000 Americ ans serve in the Philippines.   The highest during any 
one time is 100,000.  (150,000 in Iraq now.)  It  was a substantial number in the Philippines 
at that time &#8211; 100,000 soldiers in population of 10 million. 
 
When they were fighting in Cuba it was easy with open warfare agains t the Spanish.  In the 
Philippines, they were dealing with guerrilla warfare  &#8211; from hills, villages, drew on local 
community resources, secretly ar med/fed/transported by civilians  in villages.  US had very 
little experience with this &#8211; sometimes the Nati ve American wars were fought this way but 
not often.  US defined this warfare as &#8220;unciv ilized&#8221; because it was unfamiliar to European 
warfare and also because it was undertak en by people they saw as uncivilized. 
 
This became a war of civilizations &#8211; civilized vs. uncivilized .  The rules of civilized warfare 
don&#8217;t apply.  There were massi ve campaigns to destroy the he arts and minds of Filipino 
rebels &#8211; attack villages, burn it and its fields.  Physical torture was also used toward leaders 
of guerilla movement.  In these three years, 4,300 American troops died &#8211; while only a 
couple hundred die in the war with Spain, mostly from disease.  The number of Filipinos 
who died is unclear &#8211; but far greater &#8211; lowest reasonable estimate is 30,000, more serious 
in range of 50,000. 
 
By the time you get to 1902, you have an Amer ican public that launched a war for reasons 
of humanitarian intervention, human liberation, and nation building in the third world which 
has encountered resistance, insurgency, guerilla warfare, bitterness abroad, division at 
home.  The presidential election of 1900 was in  many ways a referend um on the war and by 
the end of the three ye ars, the US was a nation exhauste d and frustrated with a war that 
didn&#8217;t work out the way they planned.  The best solution wo uld be to declare victory and 
leave. 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 18 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 3 of 8 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text> 
So the US declares victory but doesn&#8217;t leave.  They find smarter more intelligent ways to 
work with the local elite &#8211; instead of burning people out of villages, they capture 
intellectually, economically, politically influential people - they capture the  ilustrado  class.  
By doing so, the US takes advantage of ethnic divisions, getting the leading figures of all different ethnic groups and co-opting them, bringing them  into the American empire and 
assuring them that on a day to day basis they&#8217;ll have power in their particular province, that 
their economic situation won&#8217;t change so long as they maintain order.  Agunaldo lays down 
arms by 1902 and pledges allegiance to the US ; he retires to the hills and lives out life 
quietly. Eventually he&#8217;s so attached to the colonial regime, he becomes explicitly pro-
American in the 1910s/20s.   
 
The one part of the country that doesn&#8217;t work is the southern Philippines  &#8211; which is 
predominantly Muslim .  Resistance and violent warfar e continues to 1913 and in some 
ways it never goes away. Muslims resented American presence and that of Christian 
Filipinos in the north &#8211; they don&#8217;t want to be a unified Philippines (they&#8217;d be a minority).  A 
rebellion was put down by the yo ung soldier John J. Pershing (a WWI figure later on).  [This 
would be a good paper topic &#8211; looking at Muslims in the Philippines as incorporated into 
American society and how Americans for the fi rst time encounter Muslim society and how 
they react to it.]  The Bureau of Non-Civilized Tribes was set up to govern the south.   
 
Slavery  and polygamy were still practiced in sout hern Philippines in 1899 &#8211; so old debates 
of the Civil War re-emerge and some say send troops, while others say they&#8217;re uncivilized so 
it doesn&#8217;t matter.  At the same time this is  occurring, the federal government is sending 
troops to Utah to stop polygamy.  There are a ll types of cultural contexts going on here! 
 
In intervening decades from 1902, the US runs the empire on the cheap for the next four decades.  US removes most of its troops, turn ing day to day running of the colony to local 
elites.  There are experiments with public health and educat ion and other reforms, but it 
doesn&#8217;t develop the Philippines as a settler colony like it does Hawaii.  Nor does it look like other European colonies &#8211; the US never developed infrastructure like the British did in India.  
But they do build military bases &#8211; looking at proximity to Japan and China, increasingly 
important as WWII begins to approach. 
 
1920s &#8211; increasing numbers of Filipinos begin to migrate to the US, particularly after 1924 
(the date of the institution of the Immigration Restriction Act &#8211; so far fewer Europeans 
are coming).  The labor needs continue and Filipinos can migrate in ways that other groups 
cannot &#8211; the first exclusion laws are against the Chinese in 1882, and then there are the 
Gentlemen&#8217;s Agreements when Japan agrees to  block emigration, and now Europeans can&#8217;t 
come &#8211; but somebody&#8217;s got to do the labo r.  So the Americans start recruiting Filipino 
labor.  First they go to Hawaii and then to the west coast &#8211; what you see on the west coast 
in the 1930s is a circular seasonal migration pattern.  The first place that a migrant from 
Philippines goes is to Hawaii (sugar industry) then to San Francisco, arriving in spring and 
then heading north to spend summers in Alaska (fishing industry).  Then in winter he/she 
comes down to San Francisco/Seattle and hangs out in neighborhoods, &#8220; Little Manilas ,&#8221; 
next to or part of Chinatown,  thought of and represented in  the same ways by the white 
press.  In the fall, it&#8217;s planting/harvesting season, so you&#8217;d head to central California where big farms were.  During the in-b etween time, you&#8217;d go back to  San Francisco/Seattle.  Many 
of the migrants did return to Manila &#8211; not hu ge numbers, though in large part because the 
wages that these people were earning were pre tty low.  In this phase of migration, the 
gender ratio is 95% men.  Later, post  1965, the vast majority are female.   
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 18 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 4 of 8 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>7</slideno>
          <text>Salvador and Marjorie Rogers want to get ma rried and went to the same clerk and were 
refused.  They hire a lawyer, a prominent LA la wyer that takes their case to the Calfironia 
Supreme Court that hears testimony from an thropologists about th e differences between 
Mongolian and Malay.  The court rules in their favor. They&#8217;re about to get married but a 
couple of weeks later the California legislature rewrites the statute to include persons of the 
Malay race (a racialized term to refer to Filipinos).  The law is a response to this case.   
 
In 1948, California becomes the first state in the union to strike down laws of inter-racial 
marriage.  In 1948, 46 of 48 states have anti-m iscegenation laws (not Vermont and Maine).  
Perez v. Sharp is over the marriage between  an African American woman and a Mexican 
American man.  It was the first case that ov erturned these intermarriage laws.  Filipinos 
active in activism around this &#8211; carrying out their own concer ns from the 1930s court cases. 
 
WWII &#8211; Filipino American men drafted into war wanted to marry their sweethearts, so their 
commanding officer rented a bus and sent them and their girlfriends to New Mexico where 
they could marry.  It was ca lled the Honeymoon Express. 
 
We&#8217;re interested in what this says about citizenship and what it says about our various 
understandings about law and how it operates and how the legal system  can be accessed by 
people who are seen as outsiders but not entirely  as outsiders. They&#8217;re coming to the states 
with some familiarity of the legal system since institutions were being established in the Philippines. 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 18 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 8 of 8 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>6</slideno>
          <text>Citizenship 
 
Complexity and murkiness &#8211; where do citizens fi t as citizens in US government?  There was 
a whole series of court cases in 1899 that re ad the Supreme Court and came to be known 
as the &#8220; insular cases &#8221; (1903 or so) having to do with questions where&#8217;s it&#8217;s unclear 
whether Filipinos are citizens or not.  Courts look to Native American law for precedents &#8211; 
the closest thing that Filipinos are like are Native Americans, &#8220;f oreign in a domestic sense.&#8221;  
The same rulings in insular cases apply to Puerto Ricans as well. 
 
This establishes a three tier system: 
&#8226; Citizens 
&#8226; Nationals (Filipinos and Puerto Ricans) 
&#8226; Aliens 
 
This matters because laws refer to citizens and aliens.  If we think about aliens, go back to 
Asian immigrants &#8211; laws from 1874 say Asian immigrants are ineligible to citizenship 
because they&#8217;re not free white/black persons. 
 
Naturalization  is one thing &#8211; can Filipinos not be na turalized because they&#8217;re Asian?  Or 
can they be naturalized because they&#8217;re not aliens? 
 
Alien land laws  &#8211; persons ineligible for citizenship cannot buy/sell land, and this was 
targeted at Asian immigrants.  Court cases that emerge surround whether Filipinos can be naturalized.  Some say no because they&#8217;re As ian and ineligible, others say the law is 
phrased for aliens and the Filipinos aren&#8217;t alien. 
 
In addition to statutes of anti-miscegenation , you also have marital alienation : A US 
woman who marries a non-American man loses her citizenship, but not vice versa.  When a 
US man marries a foreign woman, she is essent ially naturalized.  This was the case from 
1907 into the 1930s.  You can imagine this ge ts extra complicated when an American 
woman marries a Filipino man and especially if the American woman is of a different race 
than Filipino man she&#8217;s marrying.  For example, a landowning white American woman 
marries a migrant Filipino man.  She can either lose her citizenship and property, or her 
marriage is invalidated and she&#8217; d be subject to prosecution. 
 
Timothy Yatko &#8211; 21 year old Fili pino migrant waiter in Los Angeles (LA).  1925.  Married to 
white American woman, Lola.  Lola is in bed with another man and he kills the other man.  
State charges him with murder and then the state actually invokes the anti-miscegenation 
statute that Lola and Timothy&#8217; s marriage is invalid.  Now she could testify against him 
during the trial.  The state invokes this, gets marriage invalidated, Lola testifies, he&#8217;s found 
guilty in 1925.  1930 and 1940 &#8211; his name is  in the prison roster at San Quentin. 
 
Ruth Salas comes to US from Mexico in 1913 an d in 1931 she goes to the LA county clerk to 
ask for a marriage license to marry a Filipino ma n.  The clerk refused on the grounds of an 
inter-racial marriage.  The Filipino community in LA gets organized &#8211; these marriage cases 
are the first cases Filipinos organize around in  the 1930s and do so with collaboration with 
other immigrant groups. They even tually do succeed &#8211; they go from clerk to court petition, 
and the judge agrees in a backha nded way.  Since neither of th em is white, he doesn&#8217;t care 
if they marry each other.  Anti-miscegenation  statute is about a wh ite person and someone 
of another race, so it doesn&#8217;t apply in their case. The Filipino community isn&#8217;t sure if this a victory or not. 
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 18 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 7 of 8 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola 
Session 18:  American Imperialism and the Filipino/a Experience lecture 
 
 
This week: Focus on post 1965 Filipino immigration. 
 
Today: Background overview about the Span ish American War and the origins of US 
colonialism in the Philippines. 
 
 
Let&#8217;s start with the Spanish Am erican War itself, in 1898.  Part of this we talked about 
before when we were talk ing about Cuban immigrants. 
 
There was a point in 1899 just after the war was over when ambassador John Hay wrote to 
Theodore Roosevelt and described th e war as a &#8220;splendid little war.&#8221; 
 
It&#8217;s pretty clear that  intervention in Cuba  was likely to come &#8211; we talked about how much 
conflict there was in 1898.  In  the spring of 1898 &#8211; there&#8217; s all this unrest in Cuba.  
Significant numbers of US citizens are in Cu ba in the 1890s and they&#8217;re being affected by 
this unrest &#8211; the USS Maine is sent to Havana to  protect US interests.  It serves as sign to 
Cuba that we have our eye on it as well as a sign to Americans that  interests were being 
protected.  On February 15, 1898, the USS Ma ine exploded and 266 people were killed.  
Since then, studies conclude th at it sank because boilers ex ploded, but the explanation at 
the time was that the Spanish had actually blow n it up &#8211; and this prompts the US to declare 
war against Spain, officially on April 25, 1898.  There&#8217;s very little debate in 1898 about 
whether to go to war or not.  After the US S Maine&#8217;s explosion and news reports in press 
about what&#8217;s going in Cuba &#8211; it all led to intervention. 
 
War is declared in April and is over by Augu st &#8211; in large part because Cuban rebels had 
already defeated much of the Spanish army.  Almo st all of it takes place in Cuba &#8211; some in 
Puerto Rico (the US does invade).  When the war is basically over, Admiral George Dewey 
enters Manila Bay in the Philippines and seizes it for US, and the Spanish surrender fairly 
quickly.  The war comes to an end, but the war itself is imagined as a Caribbean war and 
not a Pacific war &#8211; even though the Pacific was an increasing interest to policy makers and 
traders in the 19th century.  There was also a nationalist movement going on in the 
Philippines against Spain.   
 
The US starts looking at various  Philippine nationalist movements  &#8211; they basically 
declared their independence in 1896 and tried to write their own constitution and step up own government.  The US is in the pacific looking for allies against the Spanish.  They turn 
to Emilio Agunaldo who agrees to work with US &#8211; th ey arm and train his troops against 
the Spanish and it works.  What was going in on in Manila now becomes national. 
 
At this point, some of the qu estions emerge about what to do  with what the Americans at 
the time called their &#8220; insular possessions,&#8221; e.g. the Philippines, Puer to Rico, Cuba.  Also in 
1898, the US officially annexes Hawaii and Guam.  In late 1898/early 1899, there&#8217;s a big 
national debate about whether to annex the Philippines .  There&#8217;s the story that 
President McKinley prays for guidance, and God says to take the Philippines.  This story 
seems to show how tortured it was &#8211; but really , that was from a speech he gave to a group 
of visiting Protestant mission aries after the fact when Amer icans were starting to think 
about whether this was this actually the right thin g to do.  At the time of the decision, policy 
makers and most American elites  pushed strongly for annexati on of the Philippines.  There </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Keep in mind for reading for next time: how is it that patterns of US colonialism in the 
Philippines set it up so that large numbers of women will pursue careers in health and use 
that career to immigrate to the US?  What kinds of institutions and practices help make it so 
Filipina women coming as nurses? 
 
Then the Depression hits and exacerbates tensions over work and labor , particularly in 
places like California.  There&#8217;s a lot of tens ion aimed at Filipinos and there&#8217;s a move for 
exclusion, the same kind of rhetoric and tactics as the an ti-Chinese and anti-Japanese 
movements that preceded it.  It takes on a di fferent form though &#8211; sometimes it&#8217;s phrased 
more politely, &#8220;it&#8217;s time  to give Filipinos independence.&#8221;   In the 1930s there&#8217;s a movement 
to give the Philippines independence.  By 1936, the US announces that it will grant the 
Philippines independence &#8211; this would never have happened without the opposition of 
Americans to Filipinos as  immigrants.  Filipino nationalists  don&#8217;t want independence and to 
end up economically weak &#8211; they want rights of migration , which they don&#8217;t get. 
 
By 1937, war has begun in the Pacific as Japan wa s involved in war with  China.  It becomes 
increasingly unclear what&#8217;s going to happen to the Philippines.  Secret  US planning at the 
time called for abandoning the Philippines in ca se of war in Asia.  There were the &#8220;orange 
plans&#8221; put together by Douglas MacArthur and his assistant &#8211; &#8220;we can&#8217;t defend the 
Philippines, we don&#8217;t have enough troops, what we really need to protect is Hawaii and let 
the Philippines go&#8221; &#8211; and this wasn&#8217;t revealed to either Americans or Filipinos.  After Pearl 
Harbor, Japan also attacks US air planes in Manila.  Early 1942: US troops have withdrawn 
from the Philippines, and it&#8217;s under Japanese occupation until the end of war in 1945.  The war comes to an end, and US troops are ther e.  1946: Philippines gain s independence when 
the US officially grants what  it had promised in 1936.  
 
But the story doesn&#8217;t come to an end at all.  The US and the Philippines continue to have 
deeply intertwined relationships  after 1946 &#8211; military, factors of the Cold War (the 
Philippines was a non-communist country in Asia; US supported dictators like Ferdinand 
Marcos because of his opposition to communism), economic and military interests.  The end 
of the story comes in 1998 wh en they&#8217;re celebrating 100 year s since the Spanish American 
War and there&#8217;s some ceremony involving lowering the American flag and raising the Philippine flag.  It was a windy day and both flags get tied together.  This is the Philippine 
condition &#8211; tied up in knots with the US.    
 
US economic relationship with Philippines has been what scholars would call neo-colonial .  
US benefits more from trade with the Philippines than vice versa.  Espe cially in more recent 
decades, a lot of US outsourcing for factory labor has been to the Philippines.  Here the 
legacy of colonialism is clear &#8211; one of the most commonly spoken languages is English.  
Since about 1970s, the main export is Filipino workers.  Filipino labor has contributed 
enormously to the Filipino economy in the form of remittances .  A lot comes from domestic 
work, mostly by women in Japan and Hong Kong, Italy too.  Filipino men in smaller numbers are looking for work, in places like Du bai, as they&#8217;re needed for construction of 
hotels etc.  Another place for male Filipino me n is in Iraq &#8211; reconstruction undertaken by US 
hired out to private corporations with contra ct labor of non-US workers.  Because the 
Philippines is part of the Coalition of the Willing &#8211; supporting US war in Iraq &#8211; US pumped 
enormous amounts of aid into the Philippines to convince them to send large numbers of 
Filipino workers to Iraq. 
 
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 18 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 5 of 8 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>was economic benefit &#8211; new markets for Am erican goods, new raw materials (lumber, 
hemp, other fibers and textiles), and it provided a staging ground for access to China.   
 
Trading with China was on people &#8217;s minds.  How did Americans th ink of China in 1890s?  It&#8217;s 
similar to the way they speak of China today &#8211; a vast, untapped market waiting for 
American industries.  Many argued from the diplomatic perspective  &#8211; although, this is not 
so much in the national press but certainly in  the state dept which says the Spanish empire 
is collapsing and won&#8217;t hold onto the Philippines.  So, if we leave the Philippines to its own 
devices, some other em pire will come in, and they&#8217;re especially worried about Germany and 
Japan.  From a diplomatic perspective , advice for McKinley was we have to take the 
Philippines lest someone else will.  There was the argument to take the Philippines for a civilizing mission  &#8211; bring western civilization, capitalism, schooling, health.  A lot of this 
argument comes from missionaries who are very active in the Philippines.   
 
The one thing that doesn&#8217;t seem to be in the record is any thought of whether to ask the 
Filipinos if they want to be taken.  What fe w voices there are coming  out of the Philippines 
in printed newspapers (mostly in Spanish) are coming from the elite class.  The ilustrados  
are the wealthy elite in the know, educated in western institutions mostly in Spain during 
colonialism, and who&#8217;d amassed power and wealth  in Philippine society.  Some are hoping 
that the Spanish will stay because they&#8217;ve made their peace with the Spanish, some would 
welcome the Americans and would want to work with them clos ely, some become 
nationalists and want independence.  Those are the only voices out of the Philippines reaching Americans, but they&#8217;re not really being heard.  The debate of whether to annex 
the Philippines is among Americans in America rather than an international conversation.  
 
Arguments against annexation: 
 
&#8226; From anti-imperialists.  They saw it as an un-American tradition &#8211; the US doesn&#8217;t have colonies, take over places, keep colonies that  won&#8217;t be states.  They 
distinguished expansion to the west from annexation of the Philippines &#8211; &#8220; we are a 
republic, not an empire &#8221; idea.  These voices were mo st common in the northeast, 
particularly among liberal intellectuals &#8211; the headquarters of Anti -Imperialist Society 
was in Boston.  Their voices were very lo ud &#8211; numerically there just weren&#8217;t that 
many.  You could find them in news papers and magazine s but they were 
outnumbered.  (For most Americans at th e time, there was a more compelling liberal 
argument for empire.  Many saw colonialism through this lens of charity and this 
civilizing process.)  Anti-imp erialists included William Ja mes and Mark Twain but few 
in number. 
 
&#8226; Primarily from the south . The US shouldn&#8217;t take these colonies, particularly the 
Philippines, because the people in these colonies weren&#8217;t Americans and couldn&#8217;t be 
Americanized particularly because they were Asian.  The US should avoid taking 
colonies because it would disrupt racial integrity &#8211; drawing from nativism , 
particularly Anti-Chinese rhetoric.  &#8220;We&#8217;ve already let in too many Chinese, we shouldn&#8217;t make it worse by appropriating F ilipinos into American society.&#8221;  This line 
of anti-imperialism outnumbered. 
 
Treaty of Paris in 1899  &#8211; US purchases Philippines for $20 million (Philippine  population = 
10 million) 
 
Then came efforts by the US government to remake Filipino societ y &#8211; schools, urban city 
planning.  Many of the turn of the century American reformers went to the Philippines &#8211; 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 18 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 2 of 8 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Jazz Singer</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://imdb.com/title/tt0018037/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>13</lectureno>
      <slides/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lecture: Was the Great Migration Great? (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-221-the-places-of-migration-in-united-states-history-fall-2006/resources/ses10_great_mig/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>10</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>whom leave during WWI. If you want to talk about push and pull factors, you can imagine 
what those are: Push factors ar e both economic and political. If this system was in place in 
the late 1800s, why then is it that on ly after 1910 that the blacks leave?  The push and 
pull factors create this migratory moment.  
 
PUSH  
 
Economic &#8211; volatility in cotton markets 
Political &#8211; disenfranchisement and violence 
 
As these numbers go up and down, the situat ion becomes more precarious.  But the pull 
factors are those that really determine what&#8217;s going on: 
 
Here&#8217;s where the story of other immigrant groups intersect with this. 
 
What do we know about the immigrants coming from Europe at this time? 
 
PULL 
  
Economic &#8211; European immigration ends  effectively in 1914 (in law 1921, 1924) 
Suddenly there&#8217;s no new su pply of immigrants.  The wartime economic boom  increases 
demand for labor in factories in urban Northeast (copper for bullets, textiles for uniforms, 
munitions). American economy is in wartime footing in 1915 even if not in the war. The 
labor shortage  is extended to 1917 by conscription &#8211; men were brought into army, out of 
labor force.  These pressures make it possibl e for African Americans to find jobs in the 
north.  (Consider the factories in Lawrence, MA, for example - in practi ce, they were closed 
to African American workers be fore the war.  For factories like that, the war created these 
demands that made them open up.) 
 
Sharecropping is a cash poor economy &#8211; the sy stem develops as it does because no one 
(not even the landowners) has much money. Peop le are paid in shares of the crop.  Real 
basic question: how did people get to places like Chicago in  the 1910s when they didn&#8217;t 
have the money? 
 
Conscription applies to African American men &#8211; who are disproportionately drafted out of 
the rural south. In order to prevent dislocating American families, any soldier with a 
dependent had his pay cut in half &#8211; half went directly to his dependent as cash.  This was 
designed to keep soldiers from abandoning their families and to prevent starvation of 
families or soldiers drinking away their pay. In practice in the poorest parts of America, it 
provides a cash influx  &#8211; even though not great, $8/month.  (A train ticket during WWI 
from rural south to Chicago was about $3.) By taking a train trip several hours away your 
income could quadruple.  (The story in the book: Carter goes to Chicago on vacation, 
someone offers him a job, he stays.) 
 
We don&#8217;t want to underestimate the political and social factors in this, and the extent to which people were fleeing a regime of terror under which they were 
living and headed for a system that was more open, not equal by any means, but 
politically more open for participation that  made possible voting, political voice, 
and where everyday life was less rigidly structured than the south. 
 
But the economic factors, both individual  decisions about family and big economic 
forces people can&#8217;t control, are driving this south to north migration. 
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 10 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 2 of 5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>head scarves, no pajamas outside, don&#8217;t talk too loudly, don&#8217;t spit on the street). In some 
ways people have said these are lot like the columns in immigrant newspapers (e.g. stop 
being greenhorns). Contemporary  example: immihelp.com run by South Asian immigrants 
for South Asian immigrants, a list of should and shouldn&#8217;t in the US, encouraging them to act more middle class, dealing with culture codes, etc. Re ading these advice columns, 
people had differe nt reactions.  
 
&#8226; A line of interpretation from historian Robin Kelley  &#8211; infrapolitics : 
It was a world where African Americans didn &#8217;t have public voice, where their jobs 
weren&#8217;t key to social mobility, where their votes didn&#8217;t really count. You couldn&#8217;t go to 
formal politics to get black polit ics &#8211; you have look to infrapolitics. Everyday interactions 
on the streets and breaking cu ltural codes were deeply poli tical moves not only against 
the white elite but also against the middle class blacks who tried to tell them what to do.  
They took advantage of this leisure in larg e black communities and this was political &#8211; a 
challenge to political order that voting and organizing was never go ing to get for black 
people. 
 
&#8226; Contrary line of interpretation by Evelyn Higginbotham  &#8211; politics of respectability : 
Black churchwomen in the south in the ea rly 1900s &#8211; this group of women might 
culturally seem middle class bu t certainly were not economically; they were some of the 
poorest in the country. They turned to a politics of respectability &#8211; in a world that 
expected black people to be rude, not to obey the work habits of indu strial capitalism or 
the cultural codes of middle class life. This is particularly true of black women who were represented in such stereotypical fashion, often seen as sexually disordered.  They 
reacted to these stereotypes by being pr oper, by being respectable; they were 
undermining expectations in more subversive ways than infrapolitics, which 
Higginbotham thought was a no-win strategy because it confirmed the stereotypes. The 
politics of respectability was more subversive than anyone could imagine. But it plays 
out differently when you move north because meanings of the cultural codes change.  
For example, in the south politeness from  a black man toward a white woman on a 
streetcar could be perceived as flirting &#8211; and this could have consequences. Habitual 
rudeness could be safer. Dressi ng formally could be labeled as uppity. But once you get 
to Chicago, rules change &#8211; politeness and stylish dressing and other cultural codes 
change. 
 
Higginbotham argues that it&#8217;s wrong to call it a middle class sensibility .  Kelley would say 
that this isn&#8217;t consciously political &#8211; everything is political and plays out in a much wider 
realm than we can imagine. 
 
Kelley was looking back at the way historians had looked at Jim Crow at the turn of the 
century &#8211; how they were terrorized and sile nced in a society of mass rural poverty. 
Historians were trying to figure out why is th ere no response &#8211; could blacks have organized 
these political parties?  Why weren&#8217;t they more political?  Why did it take until the civil 
rights movement?  Kelley wants to say those are all the wron g questions; there was politics 
going on &#8211; over things like identity, dignity, ability to control bodily presentation  &#8211; 
and these were the things blacks had power over.  Kelley is insistent that he is not providing a prescription for the present. 
 
 
Why do people move to suburbs? 
 
Student responses: 
- the American dream 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 10 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 4 of 5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>People found out about migration opportunities through information networks of previous 
migrants and return visits to their families.  It &#8217;s more like the people going back and forth in 
the Caribbean than transatlantic migrations. 
 
They&#8217;re also learning about it  as people and news are traveling back and forth on the 
railroad . The Chicago Defender was the biggest newspaper of the African American 
community in the country; it circulated outsid e too, carried on railroads by agents of 
migration.  Railroads segregated, but African Americans can get porter jobs &#8211; distribute 
Chicago Defender  in secret . The federal government sees wh at the white landowners see &#8211; 
the war is disrupting/dislocating our economy, our way of life . All the black people 
are running out of the town in the middle of the night &#8211; German saboteurs must be stirring things up in a secret conspiracy to undermine the production of the cotton crop. 
Conspiracy is an easy way to explain complicated  things, especially if you&#8217;ve been raised to 
discount that blac ks could make rational economic choices in the marketplace.  It doesn&#8217;t 
occur to William Percy (a land owner in Mississippi) &#8211; he feels his workers have betrayed him 
by leaving, he the generous landowner &#8211; it doesn&#8217;t occur to him to do the math that the 
wages are much higher in Chicago. 
 
To replace the labor, what do the white landowners do? 
1. They complain 
2. They raise as much cotton as they can (supplies slightly reduce, prices go up) 
3. They conscript labor ( Work or Fight Laws  &#8211; municipal and state level all around the 
country &#8211; any able bodied man not in the army has to demonstrate he has a job and 
if not he&#8217;ll be given one). The rural south didn&#8217;t have state prisons and so convicts 
were contracted out to landowners as convict labor .  In some areas in Mississippi, 
Alabama, Georgia, and Florida too, work or fight laws were applie d to both male and 
female black residents and so  a black woman who obviousl y wouldn&#8217;t be conscripted 
could nevertheless find herself under th e same terms.  We don&#8217;t have exact 
numbers, but it was not an insignificant number.  Work or fight laws had media expos&#233;s.  They were widely condemned &#8211; even by white labor unions. They were 
pretty quickly dismantled but other forms of coercion still existed. 
 
Look at Jack Temple Kirby article, &#8220;The Southern Exodus: A Primer for Historians.&#8221;  He puts these migrations in a broader perspective &#8211; 7 million people white and black leave the south 
during this time, larger than any other migration of any particular group  we&#8217;re looking 
at it.  He makes the argument that the econ omic and social factors pushing blacks and 
whites out of the south are mo re alike than different &#8211; an interesting addition to the 
argument. Poor white sharecroppers are facing these same questions. 
 
500,000 blacks are leaving, going to  cities &#8211; people moved along migration lines . You&#8217;d 
have small, fragile, largely African American communities that already existed in the cities 
that are now inundated with large numbers of migrants during the ch allenging time of the 
war when there was a lot of economic disl ocation going on.  Also, the neighborhood 
boundaries were being scrutinized by white people so the neighborhood doesn&#8217;t get any 
bigger. 
 
In these black communities, tens ions emerge between middle an d working class blacks over 
community institutions, everyday life, politics, and religion. The way that two different 
historians interpreted this&#8230; 
 
If you read various newspapers, chur ch publications, and even in the Chicago Defender , 
during time of Great Migration, you&#8217;ll find advice columns  written by northern blacks for 
the new arrivals &#8211; trying to get them to give up their rural southern ways (e.g. don&#8217;t wear 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 10 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 3 of 5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola 
Session 10: Was the Great Migration Great? lecture 
 
 
Today : Nicholas Lemann&#8217;s The Promised Land: The Great Black Migration and How It 
Changed America  
 
Related article: Granddaddy of all ghettos faces wrecking ball (CNN) 
http://edition.cnn.com/2006/US/10/08/taylor.hom es.ap/index.html?sec tion=cnn_topstories   
 
Next week : Immigrants and the movies &#8211; immigrants making them, acting in them, 
movies about them. 
 
The paper: Resources such as http://libraries.mit.edu/guides/subjects/history/   
 
 
As you get into Lemann&#8217;s The Promised Land, it&#8217;s a mesmerizing, amazing story that the 
author has put together. He&#8217;s a journalist trai ned as a historian, so he knows what he&#8217;s 
doing as he&#8217;s doing interviews with people. And he&#8217;s found an amazing group of people, 
from very ordinary people to policy makers.  I&#8217; d like to focus on the st ory of Ruby Daniels, 
the first part of the book. 
 
Ruby Daniels is a human being &#8211; a real pers on &#8211; and she does in fact exist and was 
interviewed many times by the author. During hi s first interview with her, towards the end 
of his 12 year research, he thought she wasn&#8217;t  that interesting personally.  She called him 
back asking for another interview, saying he&#8217;d asked all the wron g questions, and she 
proceeded to tell her life story. 
 
To our mass media public debates, people like Ruby are cartoon characters.  She lived what 
for many people are stereotypes for black ur ban poverty &#8211; many husbands, many children, 
unmarried, on welfare, in public housing, lyin g to social services people.  And these are 
images we&#8217;re constantly bombarded with.  Focus on her life story. 
 
The second part of the book is a policy hist ory of Washington and the war of poverty. 
 
Ruby&#8217;s ex and one of her kids sued Lemann fo r misrepresenting them, for slander.  The case 
was thrown out because they had in fact done those things and didn&#8217;t have much of a case. 
 
The book was very controversial when it came out &#8211; this has to do with how to explain 
Ruby&#8217;s situation.  Lemann doesn&#8217;t fit easily into the standard categories of politics, of liberal 
or conservative. He leans more to liberal side but isn&#8217;t an or thodox guy.  He and his book 
were attacked fr om both sides. 
 
Suburbanization is the related flipside of urban poverty. 
 
The south has a cash-crop dependent economy whose laborers are landless &#8211; white tenant farmers or black tenant farmers. African Am ericans are more commonly sharecroppers than 
tenants.  Economic exploitation with political disenfranchisement &#8211; by the 1910s, 
there are almost no meaningful numbers of black voters anywhere in the south. Other 
political rights such as jury service, protection of courts or by police are limited.  
Somewhere around the 1910s, things start to sh ift and the numbers of people leaving the 
south are dramatic.  About 500,000 blacks leave the south between 1910-1920, most of </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>- perceptions of city life not present in subu rbs &#8211; more crime, violence &#8211; want more 
idyllic environment for raising children 
- take what you like about an urban society and take it with you to somewhere you 
like more space, interaction with people 
- their own town, more control over your private space 
- more community in suburbs 
 
The first models of the suburbanization: jobs  and business continued in the center and 
people spread out.  This occurred in the 1940s /50s. From the 1970s onward, jobs also leave 
cities. 
 
The radical separation of work, shopping, living; life is car-dependent - this is the modern 
idea of suburbs. Early suburbs could be ma ss transit oriented, street-car oriented, like 
Watertown, West Roxbury, Chicago, and the bo roughs of New York City.  Definitions have 
changed. Where we are now is probably furthe r from Levittown than Levittown was from the 
cities of before. 
 
Your answers get at questions of push and pull . Some of the  structural issues  that have 
to do with federal policies and expenditures  and other laws have not caused  
suburbanization but made it take on the forms  that it does.  Link that to other 
developments in the same time period of th e 1940s/50s that lead to the construction of 
massive concentrated urban ghettos . 
 
Robert Taylor homes  - the largest housing project, 28 16-story towers in Chicago built 
right after the war.  They were seen as the gr eatest triumph, but when they were destroyed 
they were seen as the worst di sasters.  They&#8217;ve been characte rized by Lemann as one of the 
worst places on earth to live.  See the Chicago Housing Authority&#8217;s we bsite on the redevelopment project: 
http://www.thecha.org/housingdev/robert_taylor.html   
 
For next time, think about: Why do people move to the suburbs? Why do people move into the Robert Taylor homes, the two big urban housing projects? 
 
Another example is Columbia Point in Boston.  These are common in almost every big urban 
city. In the last 10-15 years, almost all major cities have been thinking about what to do with this housing. 
 
There&#8217;s housing like this in New York City, but a lot of what looks like big housing projects are much more mixed use, such as housing fo r elderly people. The co sts of replacing these 
projects are so astronomical in the US that it &#8217;s just not possible &#8211; there&#8217;s a lot more empty 
land than there is in NY. The consensus now is that smaller lower level mixed use housing  
is more effective, but that takes up  more space and houses fewer people. 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 10 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 5 of 5 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lecture and Discussion: What&#8217;s New about &#8220;New Immigration&#8221;? (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-221-the-places-of-migration-in-united-states-history-fall-2006/resources/ses16_new_imm/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>16</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>until you end up with 20,000 people who have either confessed themse lves as illegal or 
brought in other people that they know.  The question is how do we interpret this? 
 
You can get a feel for specifically how complic ated this was for Chinese people in the US 
who are here illegally &#8211; they&#8217;re in this very vulnerable position.  They don&#8217;t belong, they 
don&#8217;t have a right to be here.  But if they pa rticipate, the government offers them amnesty 
&#8211; then everything will be normalized, your citizenship would be legalized.  But this requires talking.  The  murkiness of what it means to be communist  among Chinese people in 
the US in 1950s is totally unclear.  Maybe in  1949 when Mao came to power, making public 
speech saying that China will be world power - saying something like that could come back to haunt you. 
 
On the other hand, there are historians that say it&#8217;s wrong to see this as a witch trial only 
through the lens of McCarthyism.  We can see this as a moment of victory  for Chinese 
Americans. 
 
Students:  
- if they&#8217;re here illegally, they need  to do anything they can to stay 
- you&#8217;ve got a family here, you&#8217;ve establis hed roots here, so it becomes a practical 
matter 
 
We don&#8217;t know how that 20,000 compares to the total number.  It&#8217;s a big number, considering the number of Chinese in the US in 1950 is low.  At least 25% of the population 
in 1950 was illegal.   
 
How can this be a step forward fo r the Chinese-American community? 
 
By achieving amnesty, becomi ng citizens, they become legitimate .  It depends on what 
you think about exclusion.  If you think excl usion is the law and any good Chinese person 
should obey the law and so the people who are here illegally didn&#8217;t really have any right to amnesty in the first place, then you could see it  that way.  But if you think exclusion was a 
racist law, an exclusionary law, then coming  here anyway (through paper son techniques, 
etc.) and amnesty were a way to assert your right , particularly if you think about the way 
the naturalization law had excluded Chinese for so long. 
 
In some ways the government setting up an amnesty program is an admission that their 
policies of exclusion were not working.  The question is does that mean the policies weren&#8217;t working because they were poorly enforced or  because they were incoherent/unworkable in 
the first place.  Think about this as you think about the current debate on amnesty &#8211; 
should it be part of the new system?  If the procedures aren&#8217;t working, is it because the 
Department of Homeland Security isn&#8217;t strong or substantial enough or because the policies 
weren&#8217;t meant to work in the first place? 
 
Think about 4 ways of immigration : 
 
1. Needed workers  &#8211; the immigrant&#8217;s value is based on the American economy. Value 
could be based on skill (like nurses) but it  could also be by need (like seasonal 
agricultural workers).  
 
2. Family reunification  &#8211; puts people&#8217;s relationships first, recognizing that immigrants 
are real people. 
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 16 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 3 of 5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>having completely open borders.  And this crosses all divisions in the US &#8211; Americans 
generally believe that  &#8216;Americanness&#8217; is a pretty valuable commodity . 
 
Student: the None category doesn&#8217;t allo w you to know people&#8217;s purposes here 
 
Could you imagine screening for those things in another way?  Crime?  How are you going 
to do that in this none category?  Now we  use these immigration procedures to screen 
for other things  &#8211; which include crime, terrorism, becoming a public charge.  Recall that 
the very first laws that rest ricted immigration were design ed to prevent Chinese women 
from coming and working as prostitutes.  We haven&#8217;t really gotten away from that sense 
that we use the border to look for all kinds of things. 
 
Is there anyone who would vote for the No ne category, or would see a principle of political 
philosophy  that could underlie None? 
 
Student responses: 
- the idea that we&#8217;re the best 
- we should take care of the people we already have here 
- in addition to closing borders, we should take more active role in global politics 
- globalization argument that we&#8217;d want similarly developed nations 
 
If you read these chapters, it&#8217;s incredibly conf using and a real mess and it&#8217;s not the author&#8217;s 
fault.  Part of what I want you to get out of all this is that behind all of these different 
policies - some of which are totally piecemeal or handovers to some other group (ethnic, or 
a group that employs particular workers), so me of which are compromises, others that 
didn&#8217;t turn out in practice, and yet others that are there for no  real reasons &#8211; behind all of 
these are political theories of justice.  As we talk about the vari ous sort of policy options, 
people turn to explanations  that are in many ways identity based &#8211; how will American 
identity be shaped by a change in this policy?  Sometimes they turn to economic explanations &#8211; would this work in a globaliz ing economy?  Would we be able to pay for 
social security?  The conversati on we haven&#8217;t had as a country is this deep philosophical 
question: on what basic pr inciples should a policy rest?  I don&#8217;t know if we have it in us as a 
country &#8211; I think we do.  Those are some of th e main ways of thinking about immigration. 
 
Breakdown of political philosophy behind immigration policies: 
1. Workers &#8211; what&#8217;s good for the economy? 
2. Family reunification &#8211; linking private and public concerns 
3. Refugees &#8211; political/public concerns above all 
4. Lottery/none &#8211; separating out politics and economics and looking at it abstractly 
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 16 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 5 of 5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>Part of what the book lays out is how these principles work (with lots of details) but it also 
explains why the number of immigrants who come doesn&#8217; t match what people were 
expecting.  Why? 
 
Sources of immigration turn ou t to be different.  Southern and eastern Europeans aren&#8217;t 
rushing to migrate &#8211; but look ing at the poorer corners of  Europe, you see increasing 
numbers of immigrants after 1965. 
 
Also, the numbers turn out to be much higher  than expected.  Family reunification and 
refugees turn out to be much larger.  See page 136 &#8211; look at the preference systems of 
1965 act, you see remarkable ways families can be unified.  It includes children, spouses, 
parents, married children, etc.  You end up with family chains  whereby as families are 
unified, as one person moves he re (maybe as a needed work er or refugee), he/she can 
bring in more family members who can in turn bring in more family members, and these numbers turned out to be more  than people anticipated. 
 
The other part of it was the refugee  portion.  The number of refugees turns out to be far 
larger than anyone anticipated.  As these re fugee policies began, it was as a small-scale 
program for those temporarily displaced.  This was based on Hungary in 1956 - a couple thousand left Hungary and settled in US.  Part of what happens is that under the politics of 
the 20
th century, all kinds of wars and revolutions lead to a general steady stream of people 
who are refugees &#8211; so numbers are far higher.  The conditions of flight, of leaving political crises, turn out to be much greater and more durable than any short-term political crisis. 
 
We&#8217;ve seen the relationship  of these ch anges between domestic politics and foreign 
politics .  In domestic politics, you have the civil rights movement and at the same time you 
have the Cold War context on the foreign front.  How can we see immigration through this 
lens in this time period? 
 
1949 &#8211; mainland China becomes communist.  At th is point, there are still large numbers of 
Chinese people in the US.  There&#8217;s a lot of concern in the federal government about the 
political loyalties  of these immigrants &#8211; this is a forgotten chapter of history.  We know a 
lot about the internment of Japanese a decade before.  But when the stakes of the Cold War 
were awfully high, there was a lot of concern of whether the Chinese in the US could be 
trusted.  And the government sets up this program called the Chinese confession 
program .  See pages 156-157.  The Immigration and Naturalization Service (INS) knows in 
1955 that there are large numbers of Chinese in the US and they know many are here 
illegally.  They actually offer an amnesty program.  If you think about the current debates 
over amnesty, this is in many ways the firs t historical precedent.  The INS would offer 
amnesty to a Chinese immigrant here illegally on  the condition that he/she gave information 
about other illegal Chinese immigrants.  People end up turning in others &#8211; we don&#8217;t have 
exact numbers, but it was between 10,000 to 20 ,000 people.  This was occurring in Chinese 
communities where some were, in fact, communists, some were sympathetic to mainland 
China, or from mainland China, looking at the Chinese revolution not through a lens of 
communist world domination but through a lens of nationalism &#8211; here&#8217;s their country that&#8217;s 
been through a lot, through European exploitation, and now there&#8217;s a nationalist movement under Mao and for many they see it only as nationalist.  Th ey know Mao&#8217;s rhetoric &#8211; not 
interested in it or want to downplay it.  Enthusiasm for Chinese revolution could have been misinterpreted for communism.  The dynamics when you&#8217;re bein g interrogated &#8211; it&#8217;s a good 
chance to get back at people you don&#8217;t like.  The numbers are astonishing &#8211; we know the 1950s and we hear about McCarthyism and yo u think this only affects a few radical 
communists in Hollywood &#8211; this part of the story is usually left out but the numbers show what the naming names policy  could do. It could snowball, people labeling one another 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 16 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 2 of 5 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola 
Session 16:  What&#8217;s New about &#8220;New Immigration&#8221;? lecture and discussion 
 
 
Where we&#8217;re going from here: 
 
Today: 
Immigration policy 
How things have changed in the last few decades 
 
Next class session: 
No library session &#8211; instead we&#8217;ll watch a short film, a &#189; hour documentary looking at San 
Diego and Tijuana to get a joint history but it &#8217;s actually more contemporary, about what 
life&#8217;s like in both places today.  Then we&#8217;ll have a brainstorming session &#8211; we&#8217;ll spend 2 weeks to think about current issues of US-Mexic o border in historical perspective &#8211; what do 
you want to know?  What kinds of sources would you want to look at?  If we were going to 
do this research collectively, what would you want to find?  Resour ces, interviews with 
people across the border, border guards, employ ers of Mexican workers, people who aren&#8217;t 
crossing the borders but are ne vertheless affected by these issues, Mexican-Americans in 
US (multiple generations)?  What kinds of  sources &#8211; newspaper articles, journal, 
photographs, works of art.  We&#8217;ll brainstorm about what might be on this list and then 
parsing out the research.  Eventually, we&#8217;ll have a collaborative project emerge &#8211; website, 
PowerPoint. This is designed to be flexible but substantive too. 
 
Next week: Regular week of class 
 
Thanksgiving week: Border research project 
 
Paper topic: Write up something well in advance of the paper,  definitely before 
Thanksgiving, that gives a sens e of what you&#8217;ll actually writ e your paper about.  What 
sources will your paper be based on?  Everyone will be using both primary and secondary material - primary material from the past to draw out some argument.  Yes, you&#8217;ll rely on 
secondary material from  scholars, but you should have so me core of sources that should 
help you answer some kind of analytical question.  The one thing you should not write is a &#8220;This is what happened&#8230;&#8221; paper.  The paper is due on the last day class. 
 
 
Changes in immigration law and discussion of readings from Guarding the Golden Door.  
 
Think about what is or isn&#8217;t new about this so-called &#8220;new immigration&#8221; &#8211; put it in the 
perspective of other immigrants  at the turn of century. 
 
Let&#8217;s start with the 1965 Immigration Act .  How does it work?  If you were to describe 
the terms of the 1965 act, its cent ral premises, what&#8217;s different? 
 
For a long time, there was a quota system th at eliminated immigration, but the 1965 act 
changed that.  It set a numerical cap &#8211; at the beginning, it was split by eastern and western 
hemispheres.  The 1965 act looks to limit immigration from, in particular, Mexico, Canada, and South America.  There were also the issu es of needed workers,  family reunification, 
refugees.  </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>3. Refugees &#8211; takes policies into account, that the US should base immigration policies in 
part on its politics.  For example, if we&#8217;re fighting the Cold War against communism, we 
should make room for those fleeing it. 
 
4. Lottery &#8211; who cares who comes?  Figure out how much space we&#8217;ve got and have a 
lottery and let people in at random.  
And we could even add two more  categories of restriction&#8230; 
 
5. No limits  on immigration. 
 
6. No immigration  at all. 
 
How should the US decide what citizens of other nations are permitted to enter?  Can you 
think of a set of underlying principles? 
 
If you were going use family as a principle, should it be in US definitions of a family or the migrant&#8217;s own definitions of family? 
 
Student: It&#8217;s based on the idea  that the family is the basic structure of social, economic, 
and political life. 
 
What do you do with someone who comes as a n eeded worker but their spouse is totally not 
needed from the economy&#8217;s perspective?  Let&#8217;s say you just want to work in the US for a 
while &#8211; why disrupt the community and fam ily structure in the home country for x amount 
of time, moving the family to the new countr y where they might not even want to be.  
There could be a reason where you might want to come by yourself.  But shouldn&#8217;t you be 
allowed to change your mind? 
 
Student:  There&#8217;s often a minimum time &#8211; you have to be here a certain number of years 
before you&#8217;re allowed to bring people over. 
 
Most people interpret the time stuff as basically the government stalling to keep numbers 
down.  Could you see it as an ac tual political pr inciple?  Could time be used to measure 
one&#8217;s commitment to the nation? 
 
Lottery is designed to compensate for people from countries that were discriminated against 
in prior decades.   
 
Isn&#8217;t there something denigrating in telling someone who doesn&#8217;t have a good job or didn&#8217;t pick the right spouse that yo u&#8217;re not &#8220;useful&#8221; to us?   
 
Student responses: 
- there&#8217;s going to be a few bad apples 
- they could come over and take  advantage of welfare system 
- these policies are predicated on fear - La tinos are becoming a majority in this 
country &#8211; news reports telling whites to reproduce more, playing on fear of losing power/money 
 
All this goes back to the question of what are immigrants becoming?   They&#8217;re becoming 
American, US citizens, voters, participants in  democracy, workers in capitalist economy, 
consumers in consumer culture, white in a nati on defined largely by it s racial categories &#8211; 
those are all the things that would presumably get lost if Americans were overwhelmed by 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 16 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 4 of 5 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Lecture: Remembering Ethnicity in an Age of Multiculturalism (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-221-the-places-of-migration-in-united-states-history-fall-2006/resources/ses14_multicult/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>14</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola 
Session 14: Remembering Ethnicity in an Age of Multiculturalism lecture  
 
 
We&#8217;ll be learning about the ethnic revival of the 1970s . This will do a couple of things &#8211; 
put the readings in some perspective and g ive some sense of how immigration and ethnic 
identity are changing in 1970s and a feel for what  it is we&#8217;re doing on our trip to New York 
City (NYC). 
 
Optional reading: Eric Liu&#8217;s essay, &#8220;Chinatown&#8221; in The Accidental Asian . A third generation 
Chinese American writing about going from the suburbs to visit his grandmother in NYC. 
 
We&#8217;re aiming for an understanding of what it is that people in the late 20th century got 
interested in &#8211; particularly the descendants of  European immigrants.  They got re-interested 
in roots.  &#8220;What the son wishes to forg et, the grandson wishes to remember.&#8221; 
 
Three reasons why people get interested in their roots, particularly in the 1960s, 1970s, and 
up to today. 
 
Why ethnic revival? 
 
1. What the son wishes to forget, the grandson wishes to remember &#8211; quote by 
Marcus Hansen, one of the first immigration historians. Sense of family history &#8211; personal, autobiographical reasons. 
 
2. General reaction to modernity  &#8211; a lot of the impulse toward ethnic revival was 
often predicated on a search for a more authentic identity &#8211; family, community, home, etc. &#8211; that people who live in (post) modern capitalistic societies feel they&#8217;re 
missing.  
3. Reaction to civil rights movement  &#8211; deliberately vague phrase because it can be 
a product of participation in and backlash agai nst. It placed issues of race, ethnicity, 
identity at the center of American public life.  The world of multiculturalism couldn&#8217;t have happened without people  coming together &#8211; an urge to participate in the 
culture changes implicated by this.  The backlash, on the other hand, an assertion of 
a particular kind of white ethnic identity made distinctions among ethnic groups in 
American life. 
 
The ethnic revival of the 1970s is all thr ee of these things, even until today. 
 
Immigration reform &#8211; after re striction after 1924, there&#8217;s almost no immigration from 
Europe or Asia. But already the tide is shifting on the rhetorical level &#8211; after 1973/4/5, the 
number of immigrants start to rise.  There ar e changes in the rhetor ic as early as the 
1950s. In 1958 Senator John Kennedy (JFK) publishes Nation of Immigrants  where he says 
Americans have been a nation of immigrants and owes its heritage to the reform of immigration laws &#8211; prelude to  election of JFK in 1960. 
 
1963 &#8211; JFK&#8217;s trip to Ireland, back to his family&#8217;s ancestral village.  He&#8217;s using it as a way to 
cement international alliances between the US and Ireland but is also showing that the US 
needs to reform immigration laws. 
 
1965 &#8211; Immigration Reform Act &#8211; seen by Congress as part of a moment of great society, a </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>based on his Haley&#8217;s efforts at reconstructi ng his own family history, his ancestors&#8217; 
passage to America.  It encouraged a national boom in family history and 
genealogy .   
 
It&#8217;s after 1976 that you start to see ethnic revival kitsch  everywhere &#8211; e.g. &#8220;Kiss me I&#8217;m 
Irish!&#8221; or &#8220;Parking for Albanians only&#8221; for personal driveway, cookbooks (like The Joys of 
Yiddish  and Czech Your Cooking ).  Movies starting in 1960 s are increasingly about the 
immigration experience &#8211; Zorba the Greek (1968), Fiddler on the Roof  (1971), The 
Godfather  (1972), Roots  (1977). 
 
The popular cultural texts are coming along wi th new historical texts and approaches; the 
history profession is changing as non-historians have their own interest in history &#8211; 
everyone&#8217;s coming together. As  late as 1962, the president of the American Historical 
Association says &#8220;many of the young practition ers are products of the lower middle class, 
emotions get in the way of historical recons tructions&#8221; &#8211; this was how immigration history 
was received in 1962.  But changes were cl early underway that he was responding to, 
changes that only accelerated as the 1960s went on &#8211; redefining history of 
war/politics/power to changes of work/labor history .  He was also responding to 
cultural changes in literature and film.  They&#8217;re making these things possible.  Kingston 
draws on work of immigration historians. Hale y couldn&#8217;t have written his novel without the 
work of those working in African American history. Howe is writing history.  Philosophers, 
political theorists, cultural studies folk are all exploring theories of  pluralism  - cultural 
relativism, identity politics.  There was am excitement that a lot of people brought to this project, with a wide array of people [and thei r backgrounds] were involved.  A lot of what&#8217;s 
going on is a way of participating in the civil rights movement &#8211; multiculturalism has a place in it for white ethnic identities , white ethnic European identities .  It can also be a backlash 
against the civil rights movement. 
 
The important thing is another 1976 cultural product &#8211; the movie  Rocky.  It&#8217;s a poor Italian 
versus an African American (thinly veiled Mo hammad Ali).  It&#8217;s the standard underdog story 
classic to boxing mo vies &#8211; interesting that he is this white ethnic underdog.  None of this is 
ever explicit &#8211; there&#8217;s a sense in which it is this working class white ethnic guy and it matters that he&#8217;s a man who is suffering under all of these other things &#8211; he&#8217;s living in the 
city at a time when cities are under enormous  strain and decay and other social problems. 
What Rocky taps into even if he doesn&#8217;t directly talk about it is this sense of victimhood  in 
which as assertion of a white ethnic identity like his could actually be a backlash/protest 
against a bunch of things &#8211; class differences against white suburbanites fleeing the cities 
leaving behind the old neighborhood but also against the civil rights movement 
(conceptualized as an African American movement ), or against feminism .  His appeal as the 
underdog is through physicality &#8211; through boxing.  Historically and even up to now, boxing is an immigrant sport.  It&#8217;s not the big popular national sport it once was. Boxing used to be 
deeply divided &#8211; the color line was strictly drawn. 
 
Rocky  appears in theaters at the same time as the Supreme Court ruled on University of 
California Regents v. Bakke  &#8211; the case substantially reins in affirmative action  as a social 
policy in 1976.  People at the time actually talked about Bakke by comparing him to rocky as this white underdog. In 1984 when Reagan makes his journey to Ireland, one of the 
songs they play is the theme song for Rocky . 
 
The ethnic revival of 1960s and 1970s create places of tourism and pilgrimage  &#8211; what 
we&#8217;ll be doing when we visit NYC.  They are part of a very complicated set of cultural 
impulses.  The fact that Roots  and Woman Warrior  and Rocky  and all these other things can 
fit on the same list suggest that there are mu ltiple forces going on in the 1970s causing 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 14 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 3 of 4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>moment of the civil rights movement more ge nerally. The same cong ress passes the voting 
rights act.  Immigration reform acts as a symbolic gesture to show that we are a nation of 
immigrants. Studies done in 1965 suggested th at the number of immigrants wouldn&#8217;t 
change very much, but these laws could get racialization and ethnici ziation of American 
institutions out. 
 
How all of this works&#8230; 
 
Thre&#8217;s a renovation in American thinking between 1965 and 1990.  It&#8217;s in these decades 
that Ellis Island replaces Plymouth Rock as center for American history .  Most 
textbooks or pop culture representations in the mid 20th century place Plymouth Rock as the 
site of national origins.  Ellis Island clos ed in 1954 and very unce remoniously.  From 1954 
into the 1970s, it was empty and decrepit, vand alized, not used at all.  The government had 
some ideas of what they&#8217;d do with it (e.g. luxury condos, public housing, a dump, 
something else). In the 1950s when there were plans to develop an American museum of 
immigration, people turned to the Statue of Liberty not Ellis Island.  A marketing firm did studies in 1955, and found only 20% of Americans could identi fy Ellis Island.  Its mythic 
factor just wasn&#8217;t really there in 1955, not as part of our national co nsciousness.  It was 
made part of the Statue of Li berty national park in 1965 &#8211; the same year Lyndon Johnson 
signs the Immigration Reform Act. No real plans for reno vation until 1976 &#8211; which was a 
turning point for many things, such as the Amer ican bicentennial.  It was a big moment to 
get Americans to think about their own past &#8211; there were localized, community oriented 
celebrations (since the nation didn&#8217;t have mone y for big fair). Local things fostered senses 
of community or ethni c heritage.  Between 1976 and 1986, the renovation of Statue of 
Liberty took place.  1986 was th e centennial celebration and al so renovation celebration &#8211; a 
big 80s celebration.  The main person in charge of fundraising was Lee Iacocca, the CEO of 
Chrysler, himself the son of an  immigrant.  Chrysler was al most bankrupt in the 1970s but 
it came back (with government subsidy) &#8211; it served as a symbol of American being &#8220;back.&#8221; 
Iakoka used money for the reno vated Ellis Island that opened in 1990.  Now more people 
visit daily than ever went through on a given day.  This is testament to the Americans&#8217; 
changing understanding of a place like Ellis Island. 
 
There was  cultural exploration  in literature, pop culture, historical research.  1976 = 
crucial moment. Three influential books were published in 1976 - the best, most respected of the year were: 
 
&#8226; World of our Fathers  by Irving Howe &#8211; giant history of the life of Jewish communities 
of the Lower East Side.  Howe grew up  in neighborhood and writes of the cultural/ 
political life of the neighborhood, questions of assimilation . People responded 
positively, coming at a time when NYC was in tough times, a time of  urban decline , 
so this appealed as a model of NYC in its better days.  It&#8217;s the idea that &#8220;everyone wants a ghetto to look back to.&#8221;  The Lowe r East Side is often referred to as the 
Jewish ghetto. 
 
&#8226; Woman Warrior  by Maxine Hong Kingston &#8211; shows how different strands are coming 
together. Kingston comes out of the culture of ethnic studies and ethnic radicalism 
and feminism , particularly on the west coas t in the 1970s.  The book&#8217;s about 
family, memory, community, and draws a lot on history (Chinese-American history of 
her own family).  
 
&#8226; Roots  by Alex Haley &#8211; the book everyone read  in 1976.  In 1977 it was turned into a 
TV mini-series watched by  100 million people &#8211; a shared national media 
experience  (the country&#8217;s population was just over 200 million then).  The novel is 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 14 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 2 of 4 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>people to look back to their past. And it  had many different impulses &#8211; sometimes 
competing from different people, conflicting from within. 
 
Examples of tension: 
 
The conservative writer Michael Novak in the 1970s had an interchange with Native 
American activist who was criticizing Novak for what his [Novak&#8217;s] ance stors had done to his 
[the Native American ac tivist&#8217;s] ancestors.  
 
The busing crises in South Boston in 1970s was an example of the ethnic revival of Irish 
American identity, class wars, racism against African Americans. One of the common signs 
by white people opposing busing was &#8220;England out of northern Ireland, blacks out of South Boston.&#8221;  The middle and upper class whites of  Boston had already left &#8211; to suburbs where 
busing was not going on &#8211; so that sense of being the underdog is going on as well.   
 
Explorations by historians, writers, particularly in the realm of culture, are very much there in 1970s, but not so much anymore.  The ethnic revival wasn&#8217;t solely a reaction 
against the civil rights movement. 
 
 
Paper topics 
 
How do you know where to do online re search and which resources to choose? 
 
Students: 
- Google scholar 
- JSTOR 
- Wikipedia 
 
A search on Google for &#8220;Lincoln Great Emanci pator&#8221; yields search result by a holocaust 
denial organization.  It doesn&#8217;t seem so at firs t, but there&#8217;s a lesson here to learn.  This is 
also illustrated by how Wikipedia can provide useful knowledge.  But the lesson is you should also  be critical things of works that show themselves as scholarly work . 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 14 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 4 of 4 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Discussion (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-221-the-places-of-migration-in-united-states-history-fall-2006/resources/ses11_great_mig2/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>11</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>this, the people who live there have liked them better, have taken care of them (sense of 
ownership); walking down streets is safer. 
 
Robert Taylor homes replaced smaller buildings , substandard in quality, overcrowded, often 
without modern conveniences like elevators and hot running water. 
 
Why did the Taylor homes decline in quality?  Part of it is how they were maintained, part of 
it is about the resources to maintain it.  The late 1960s/early 1970s was a hard time for 
cities all across America &#8211; economic trouble, losing industries. 
 
Now we&#8217;ll move into the  history of suburbanization and the  history of development of 
concentrated urban ghettos  in the same time period in these two decades around 
WWII&#8230; 
 
1939 &#8211; A federal planner gave test imony before Congress about suburbanization  
(&#8220;decentralization&#8221; ).  His argument was that it was taking inevitably place &#8211; it&#8217;s not a 
policy, but a reality.  It&#8217;s impossible to change this trend, and he likened it to the desire of 
birds to migrate to a more suitab le location.  He emphasized the inevitability  and insisted 
it wasn&#8217;t due to federal government policy . 
 
Today we have the counter argument - that it&#8217;s very specifically about policies, how 
they made suburbs possible and acce lerated their growth. They didn&#8217;t cause  them; in some 
ways suburbs would have happened anyway mo stly because of the ways that American 
cities govern themselves and th e availability of cheap land in the US.  This is compared to 
European cities where there are more expensive,  economic incentives to suburbanization.  
But the policy does map &#8211; it made suburbanization look as if they were inevitable: 
 
1. Automobiles 
 
The development of cars and the ways in which Americans become increasingly car-
dependent right after WWII  is critical.  Car ownership expanded dramatically in the 
1920s with Ford&#8217;s Model T and the Sloan factory.  There was some increase in car ownership 
and use, but it&#8217;s temporary &#8211; the Depression slowed things down.  When people live in 
cities, they tend not to use cars as much/often. Only after WWII, you&#8217;d see people using 
cars everyday for their commute, start to s ee multiple cars in single households.  
 
The invention of station wagon came in the 1940s.  Why &#8220;station&#8221;?  At the time, you only had one car per household, and the wife would drive the husband to the [commuter rail] 
station to take the train; then she&#8217;d take the ki ds around in the wagon.  Over time as work 
patterns changed, it&#8217;s less likely that people take  trains to the city &#8211; so the number of cars 
per household increases.   
 
Some of this is economic : 
- automobiles are getting cheaper as mass production techniques are developing 
particularly after WWII when big 3 manufacturers are reaping enormous gains 
- fuel costs decreasing 
 
But there are also policy  issues: 
 
&#8226; Federal Highway Act (1916) .  This was the first federal effort to build roads .  It 
was mostly in the planning stages in th e 1920s.  What finally resulted was the US 
Highways (e.g. US 1, Route 66). A lot of mo ney was pumped into those roads during the 
1930s, during the Depression, when Roosevel t wanted the economy to get going again 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 11 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 2 of 6 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>but didn&#8217;t want to hand out money - so the government hired lots of people to build 
roads. 
&#8226; Interstate Highway Act (1956)  &#8211; This replaces the older system (e.g. I-90). This 
policy was designed specifically with decentralization in mind ; it made it possible for 
people to live in the suburbs.  (There&#8217;s the popular idea that interstates were built as Cold War defense measures, being wide enough  for B52 bombers to land &#8211; but this isn&#8217;t 
true.)  But one of the ideas was that decentra lization would be a good thing to pursue in 
a nuclear era and suburbanizat ion was thought of as a mean s of finding some sort of 
survivability during nuclear war .  There was increasing demand from all around the 
country for more roads &#8211; the interstate high way system was the largest building project 
ever undertaken in human history, if you take in physical size, number of wokers, 
money spent. If you could count individual construction projects, the largest is the Big Dig (particularly if you count co sts, cost overruns).  So we were pouring lots of money to 
get people to drive away/around highways. Money for roads increased, and money 
for federal efforts for building public transportation systems decreased. 
 
In 1950, what American city had the best street car transportation ?  Los Angeles!  It was 
dismantled over the course of 1950s and replaced by freeways,  which were touted as being 
fast, efficient, more modern, more convenient.  But it&#8217;s hard to think that when you&#8217;re stuck 
in traffic jam at 3:00am for no reason! The system now is not what was imagined in the 
1950s/60s.  Street cars were either folded into  other systems, remain as quaint relics, or 
became commuter rail systems.  But street cars had pretty low fares &#8211; a nickel &#8211; but 
ridership went down.  So the companies increased rates which then, in turn, sent ridership 
down again. The number of forces acting against street cars was too many. It wasn&#8217;t just spending more on roads, but deliber ately spending less on street cars.  
 
2. Mortgages 
 
There was a transformation in mortga ges and mortgage policy . Before 1930 or so, 
down payment was half to two-thirds of the total cost and then you could borrow the rest 
on a 5-10 year mortgage. Houses tended to cost  a little less as a percentage of income as 
they do now. But many people would live their en tire lives as renters.  Part of what turns 
the tide is Great Depression &#8211; 30% own hous es at the beginning of the Depression, and 
very quickly, those who still owe money on their houses go to default. By 1933, half of all 
homes were technically in default and the bank s could have claimed th em if they wanted 
to/had the means to.  
 
The Roosevelt administra tion established the Homeowners Loan Corporation  (HOLC) in 
1933 which was then supplemented a year later with the Federal Housing 
Administration  (FHA), which was designed to protect homeowners from losing houses, 
protect banks from losing loans, protect constr uction industry from going out of business. 
Between 1929 and 1933, the home construction  business virtually di sappears. So they 
create a mortgage insurance procedure  that insures mortgages from banks, allowing 
people to borrow lots of money. 
 
There are changes in the average term of a mo rtgage &#8211; it goes from 5 to 25-30 years.  
- Reduced down payment  (10%) 
- Self-amortizing  &#8211; the opposite of which is on e with a balloon payment (you pay 
interest along the way and at the end, you pay the loan bu t if you don&#8217;t have enough 
money to pay off the loan, then the house is  foreclosed). Rates of foreclosure were 
high, so many didn&#8217;t see reason to buy houses. 
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 11 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 3 of 6 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola 
Session 11: Discussion about the Great Migration  
 
 
In the news today: The U.S. population has now surpas sed 300 million. People are living 
longer. Immigrants have higher  birth rates in the US.  But 300 million is an arbitrary 
number because there are probably more than th at number on any given day, but it does 
elicit a moment of reflection.  
 
Harvard&#8217;s Open Collections Program: Immigration to the United States, 1789-1930 
The Social Museum has many many digitized ph otographs that document social conditions 
in cities and rural areas mostly having to do with immigration and poverty and public health.  By documenting this visual data they attempt to show what was going on.  It&#8217;s 
available here:  
http://ocp.hul.harvard.edu/immigration/   
 
At the turn of the century, in 1911, Congress debated rest ricting immigration. They 
sponsored a study, the Dillingham Commission.  It produced 41 volumes of statistics, 
anecdotes, testimony documentin g the state of immigration of  1910.  Stanford scanned in 
the entire book page by page!  It&#8217;s available here: 
http://library.stanford.edu/depts/ dlp/ebrary/dillingham/body.shtml   
 
Finish up discussion fr om last time: We come back to question of the debate between 
infrapolitics  and the politics of respectability .  I want to emphasize you can have this 
debate with almost any immigrant group. They are often battles between new immigrants 
and the more Americanized ones, battles over cl ass as well.  Many of the debates are about 
tradition  - maintaining cultural tradition, e.g. modernizing/making more American food 
traditions. 
 
immihelp.com &#8211; &#8220;from an immi grant to future immigrants&#8221; 
Resources for immigrants, made by South As ian immigrants mostly used by Indian 
immigrants, topics for newcomers 
 
Debates within communities of immigrants &#8211; when people talk about how to adjust to a 
new culture, they&#8217;re talking about a lot of things, adjusting to class, new work situations 
 
Photographs: Robert Taylor Homes . 
 Chicago Housing Authority&#8217;s redevelopment project:  
http://www.thecha.org/housingdev/robert_taylor.html   
 
Mayor Richard J. Daley&#8217;s speech at the opening of the Robe rt Taylor Homes in 1962: 
http://www.encyclopedia.chica gohistory.org/pages/410107.html   
 
When they were constructed, the Robert Tayl or Homes were the largest housing project in 
the world, with 28 towers, 16 floors each.   
 
Robert Taylor  was the first black housing officer in Ch icago, trained as an architect at MIT. 
 
How much faith do you place in architecture and environment as ways of shaping 
behavior? There&#8217;s an argument for them &#8211; planners will say that, in smaller places like </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>4</slideno>
          <text>Think about the &#8220;ghetto&#8221; as the same way we think about Chinatown &#8211; the word maps a 
place for us, but it also maps the people who live there &#8211; there&#8217;s an  understanding of who 
they are racially but there&#8217;s also a whole othe r set of cultural codes associated with that 
mapping.  
 
The Federal Housing Act of 1949  says we&#8217;ll pump lots of federal money to the 
construction of public housing  to any community in America that asks for it.  Cities are 
struggling with their housing st ock and with providing housin g right after WWII &#8211; a lot of 
the housing is sub par, having not been fixed up since 1929.  Cities ask for money and get it, but suburbs are different  cities and get to decide on thei r own - and they pass on public 
housing. For example, Mayor Daley got money from the federal government that he could 
have given to Chicago &#8211; which would have benefited not only pe ople like those in the Robert 
Taylor homes but also construction unions.  White suburbs of Chicago de clined the option of 
taking federal money, so the housing projects  weren&#8217;t built in the suburbs where land was 
cheaper and there was more of it.  This forces cities to build in more concentrated land &#8211; so 
they end up with solution of a tower (Robert Taylor homes). 
 
This proliferation of localized government  makes big difference in  terms of housing and 
schools &#8211; every individual  municipality govern s its own schools.  1400 Governments: The 
Political Economy of the New York Metropolitan Region by Robert C. Wood and Vladimir V. 
Almendinger talks about the suburbs of New York City. He argues that it&#8217;s a source of this 
variation, making it possible for housing and schools to work out the way they do. It should be governed as one city so there&#8217;s the power to tax and provide social services and 
maintenances .  But with so many different governme nts, some are very rich and some are 
very poor.  You&#8217;re taxing p oor people to come up with services!  We&#8217;re the only 
industrialized country that is this fragmented. 
 
In Chicago, it isn&#8217;t surreptitious after all &#8211; it &#8217;s quite explicit: these housing projects respond 
to the ideas of policy makers and demands of white people in Chicago so segregation 
ends up working out this way.  Some of it was a response to WWII and not having enough 
housing.  Coming out of WWII, there was a giant housing crunch - people really stacked up.  
Politicians hoped they would win votes &#8211; they&#8217;re under pressure from Congress (to bring 
money home to their districts), from the cons truction industry, from highway builders, and 
from ordinary people &#8211; such as a) the urban po or who now have political voice in cities that 
they didn&#8217;t have in the rural south before they moved, and b) those people who want to 
move to suburbs. Luckily, in 1949, the governme nt is flush. They ce rtainly are funding it. 
What happens in the late 1960s is that money starts to run out as the US hits recession, 
and urban areas in the northeast and midw est are hit hard &#8211; jobs disappear, taxes 
disappear, so there&#8217;s less money to maintain the city, public housing, and protect people. 
More and more, people who can are leaving, so  there&#8217;s even less of a tax base.  Take NYC 
subways in 1970s &#8211; what a downward spiral it was.  NYC didn&#8217;t have money to pick up 
garbage for 2 weeks. (Contemporary note: Th ere more rats now than in 1970s because 
there are now more people and hence more garbage.) 
 
 
CLASS DISCUSSION 
 
Decentralization is not a policy claim &#8211; there&#8217;s this idea that it&#8217;s something natural and 
inevitable. 
 
Houston &#8211; not much zoning, incentive to buy, sprawl 
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 11 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 5 of 6 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>3</slideno>
          <text>1944 &#8211; Servicemen&#8217;s Readjustment Act  (&#8220;GI Bill&#8221;) establishes the Veterans&#8217; 
Association .  The government guarantees to banks a form of insurance on the loans; if 
people default, the government will pick up the slack. So banks are more willing to loan 
more, eventually at lower rates. 
 
This combines with the fact that right after WWII there was demand for housing. There 
wasn&#8217;t much construction in the 1930s (nothing to build with).  Right after war, there was a 
big demand for cheap housing . 
 
Policies of how these loans are given force pe ople to suburbs. FHA loans had standards: 
particular size, set back from street, separated from adjacent building. By the late 1940s, it 
was cheaper to buy something than to rent it.  With massive construction in the suburbs, 
new mortgage policies, decreasing  interest rates, there was no incentive to fix up places 
where they were already living. 
 
3. Racial Segregation  
 
The policies of racial segregation: the FHA an d HOLC work together to create a system 
called redlining . As federal agencies figure out where they will/won&#8217;t give loans, they map 
out cities, create rankings for 1st grade to 4th grade according to the condition of the 
housing stock, safety, desire to live in neighborhood, whether it&#8217;s residential or mixed in with other uses (e.g. a factory next door).  Those ratings preferred individual free standing 
houses with lawns, etc. Declining neighborhoods were those that weren&#8217;t ethnically 
homogenous.  They liked &#8220;American business an d professional men&#8221;. Th ey were unwilling to 
loan in 4
th grade areas. It&#8217;s pretty clear that th e FHA and HOLC are actively sharing this 
information with banks; evidence from the arch ives is pretty clear th at the banks are using 
this exact same information with what they&#8217;ll do.  (4th grade neighborhoods were marked 
with red &#8211; hence, redlining.) 
 
Detroit, Michigan  &#8211; big industrial city wi th all different kinds of ethnic groups needed to 
work in factories during the war. One particular neighborhood as it was mapped out was considered declining because it was too ethni cally heterogeneous &#8211; a mix of whites and 
blacks made it seem &#8220;unhealthy. &#8221; One enterprising developer di scovered that on one side of 
a particular road, the majority of  people were white; on the ot her side of the road, black.  
He convinced officials to rota te mapping by 90 degrees and to build a wall to separate one 
side of the neighborhood from the other.  FH A comes in and remaps it; so now, instead of 
denying to loans to everyone, 3
rd grade and 4th grade areas are mapped out, so half of the 
people (those in the 3rd grade area, the white area) get loans.  What road is this?  8 mile 
road &#8211; it divided the city from the suburbs by literally walling off neighborhoods. 
 
Over time, the people who are living in 4th grade neighborhoods can&#8217;t get loans to purchase 
what is there or to fix it up.  The housing stock is declining.  There are specific incentives for 
those leaving these neighborhoods and moving into suburbs (mostly white).  The suburbs 
are governed by restricted covenants  (e.g. &#8220;the person to buy house must be 
white/Christian&#8221;).  In 1948, this was legally overturned but continued in practice as informal 
ways of discrimination. 
 
These are the forces acting towards suburbanization .  There&#8217;s also a series of forces to 
concentrate people in urban ghettos&#8230; 
 
4. Urban &#8220;ghettos&#8221;  
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 11 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 4 of 6 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>5</slideno>
          <text>Houses are now 40% larger than in 1950s. Part  of it is that suburbs now are changing. 
Farmingville is where everybod y moved in 1949.  As even more  suburbs are developing 
and sprawling , Farmingville had sidewalks.  Now it is becoming a place where the 
immigrants are moving.  It&#8217;s not in the intere st of the suburban government to consolidate 
because they give up some autonomy and co ntrol. Municipal services are increasingly 
privatized &#8211; e.g. garbage collection, security. We see this in Atlanta &#8211; the most sprawling 
city in America.   
 
Immigrants commute by bus into the city and then have to get back at 1:30am &#8211; as jobs 
continue to leave cities , it presents challenges.  The patt erns are changing so quickly - at 
the same time that downtowns are gentrifying  (beginning in the 1980s) and getting 
more expensive, patterns are moving back in ways that maintain different kinds of 
communities.  
 
Hollow City: The Siege of San Francisco and the Crisis of American Urbanism  by Rebecca 
Solnit is about how San Francisco was for ye ars the funky place artists and liberals could 
afford to live and now it&#8217;s out of [financial] reach for these people. 
 
&#8220;Californication&#8221;  &#8211; the phenomenon of other states  being overwhelmed by Californian 
migrants who couldn&#8217;t get what  they wanted in California. 
 
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 11 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 6 of 6 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The New Los Angeles</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://www.californiadreamseries.org/nla.htm</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>17</lectureno>
      <slides/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>The Jazz Singer</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/http://imdb.com/title/tt0018037/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>12</lectureno>
      <slides/>
    </lecture>
    <lecture>
      <lecture_title>Discussion (PDF)</lecture_title>
      <lecture_pdf_url>https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/21h-221-the-places-of-migration-in-united-states-history-fall-2006/resources/ses15_lower_east/</lecture_pdf_url>
      <lectureno>15</lectureno>
      <slides>
        <slide>
          <slideno>2</slideno>
          <text>Is this cultural process by which American Je ws have remembered their history a distortion 
of history? A triumph of community? 
 
What&#8217;s the other option other th an mythologizing this?  There&#8217;s forgetting your past &#8211; the 
generation of American Jews wh o moved to the suburbs in the 50s went to great lengths to 
do this.  Furthermore, does the Holocaust have to be the central event of their culture&#8217;s past 
which necessarily creates a cultural history of a culture as victimized?  If you can remember 
the Lower East Side as the center of your cult ural past, isn&#8217;t it more positive, generative, 
creative than the alternative? 
 
Repression and discrimination and violence have actually always created shared collective 
identities for all kinds of groups throughout history &#8211; creating an uneasiness in those 
communities, why do we have to be defined by something else? 
 
The experience of modern life &#8211; a search for some sense of authenticity , solidity.   
 
These are resistant, deliberate misreadings of history &#8211; it&#8217;s not like American Jews don&#8217;t 
understand the history books, it&#8217;s  that they&#8217;re choosing (not ne cessarily consciously) to read 
that history in a different way. 
 
It matters for her argument that this story is also true for non-Jewish Americans, for whom 
LES and Jewish are synonyms in a way.  In that way, the Simpsons are a good example 
instead of just using solely Jewish references. 
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 15 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 3 of 3 </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>0</slideno>
          <text>21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola 
Session 15: Discussion of Lower East Side Memories  
 
 
When we&#8217;re visiting NYC and we get to the El dridge Street Synagogue, what do you think 
the tour guide is going to say? 
 
Student: He&#8217;ll probably leave out how the more real-lived details and instead emphasize the 
grand history.  Why did they make th e synagogue like a typical cathedral? 
 
p. 113 
 
Reference the Temple Emanu-El ca. 1885 &#8211; how do the two compare?  Both have Moorish 
design.   
 
If you look at a lot of synagogues in this time period, a lot of them look increasingly like Christian churches, particularly those built in the US.  In this moment Judaism itself is 
changing dramatically and modernizing and urbanizing and adopting many of the 
architectural and cultural forms of Christianity.  In part, this is because it&#8217;s no longer the 
case that Jews are strictly excluded from the re st of society &#8211; they can do what they want &#8211; 
and other cultural prac tices change in the 19
th century very quickly, e.g. moving away from 
kosher eating regulations, redefining Sa bbath, congregations fragmenting (orthodox, 
reform). 
 
It&#8217;s no accident that it&#8217;s 1986 when the synagogue&#8217;s restorat ion begins &#8211; put that in the 
context of this ethnic revival from last lecture.  It&#8217;s also connected to the rebirth of NYC and cities in general in the 80s and 90s.  One of  the reasons we have a tenement museum is 
that for 50 years, some of the buildings in the Lower East Side were  empty &#8211; people were 
moving out, parts were decaying, it wasn&#8217;t occupied.  Now, with the forces of gentrification 
and urban life, this wouldn&#8217;t have happened.  That &#8217;s one of the forces that actually saves it.  
People who are going on these walking tours are also looking back at the neighborhoods 
their parents/grandparents lived in before they moved to the suburbs. 
 
Diner points out four problems with the mythic Lower East Side: 
- people&#8217;s attachment to this place isn&#8217;t nece ssarily tied to the ex perience of the place 
- Jews have been living in NY for a long time and the standard myth focuses on this 
turn of the century period even though  present as early as 1830s &#8211; it was the 
German neighborhood, Jews coming from Germany 
- People came not only seeking political/r eligious freedom, but economic push/pull 
factors were also at work 
- No real geographical boundary or designatio n of &#8220;Lower East Side&#8221; &#8211; people at the 
time didn&#8217;t use the term, it was constructed later 
 
Questions of memory: Can people actually re member something that didn&#8217;t happen to 
them?  What&#8217;s the appeal for the Lower Ea st Side for contemporary American Jews? 
 
Students: 
- family history - &#8220;we&#8217;ve come a long way&#8221; explanation 
- center for religious/cultural traditions &#8211; freedom to act as they pleased 
 
It&#8217;s a place distinctively Jewish and also tied to religion &#8211; but Diner questions this.  When we go on the tour, will they describe the synago gue as the epicenter/an chor of the community, </text>
        </slide>
        <slide>
          <slideno>1</slideno>
          <text>but Diner suggests that it probably wasn&#8217;t &#8211; othe r institutions were just as important.  It&#8217;s 
become thought of as a very religious place whic h has as much to do wi th secularization of 
20th century life and as people moved away they looked back to this. 
 
Student: It serves as a creation myth &#8211; it&#8217;s huge, intense community 
 
Why did this happen?  One of the crucial thin gs is that the Holocaust and WWII destroys 
other places that could be thought of as the &#8220;Old Country.&#8221;  It&#8217;s also the Cold War.  When 
the Iron Curtain goes down, they can&#8217;t go back  to Poland or Russia (even though they&#8217;re not 
dying to in the first place, but it&#8217;s not really an option anyway).  And so the new places 
become &#8220;home.&#8221;  Diner doesn&#8217;t really talk about how American Jews have that mixed 
relationship with Israel, particularly in the late 20th century, which is yet another option of a 
place to call home.  But it can&#8217;t be necessarily  called the Old Country because it&#8217;s not where 
most Jewish Americans are from.  The Lowe r East Side doesn&#8217;t&#8217; bring the political 
controversy that Israel has.  Israeli Jews are themselves a very diverse group of people 
from many countries. 
 
Zionism emerges in 18th century Europe as a response to the sense of European Jews that 
know they can&#8217;t really be at home in any Euro pean state and so they need a state of their 
own &#8211; first big leader was Aust ria&#8217;s Theodor Herzl in late 19th century who suggested that 
Jewish people settle in Palestine (at that time part of Ottoman Empire, British mandate after WWI).  In the course of these decades, large numbers due migrate, but not as large as 
numbers after 1948.  After WWII, it&#8217;s American Jews who are most  visible, numerous, 
powerful on the international stage &#8211; in this sense the Lower East Side becomes the Old Country. 
 
Where does Diner find the evidence for all of this?  She uses historical artifacts, from 
children&#8217;s books to Simpson&#8217;s episodes.  Now having seen The Jazz Singer &#8230;? 
 
There are still tensions between parents and children, particularly in the immigrant families.  If the remake of the movie was set in 1980 in a suburb, it would have been more accurate 
and less believable. 
 
Collective memory 
 
This is not a book of history &#8211; it&#8217;s not trying to say what happened in the LES, it&#8217;s analyzing what people remember.  Yes, she draws on hi storical documents, bu t she emphasizes that 
people remember something else.  They remember LES as a religious place, uniquely Jewish 
place, cultural place. 
 
By 1980, Ribinowitz was too Amer ican a name.  By changing it back to a less Anglicized 
spelling would be marking this person as not fully Americanized person. 
 
All these people who want to believe something that history books time and time reiterate is not the case.  We&#8217;ve encountered this througho ut the semester &#8211; this is not how people 
remember it, but this is actually what happe ned.  Why is it that people think about 
immigration differently from its actual history?  And what is it about history that&#8217;s not actually getting through? 
 
Students debate whether historical fact/truth is better than cultural/personal memory and 
the validity and purposes of each. 
 
21H.221 (Fall 2006), Places of Migration in U.S. History Session 15 
Prof. Christopher Capozzola  Page 2 of 3 </text>
        </slide>
      </slides>
    </lecture>
    <videos>
      <video>
        <video_url/>
        <video_title/>
        <transcript>
          <slice>
            <text_slice/>
            <time_slice/>
          </slice>
        </transcript>
      </video>
    </videos>
  </lectures>
</doc>
